Well, today I want to return to our discussion of the debate between Karnap and why.
Two people whose views are closely aligned, but who nevertheless disagree about some fundamental
questions about logical truth, about conventionalism, about ontology, and about the nature of philosophy
in general.
So let's begin by going back to what we introduced right at the end of last time.
We were talking about the idea of a framework, and indeed that's something fundamental to
Karnap.
The thought that we introduced frameworks, linguistic frameworks ultimately, but I think
we could also refer to them as conceptual frameworks if that didn't in some sense make
a question that Karnap is interested in avoiding.
But in that case, we talked about some of these last time, and we focused on the distinction
between logic, mathematics, and then natural science, state physics.
We're going to talk about other frameworks today too.
But let's start with that distinction.
Quoting thinks it's tempting with respect to the first two.
When he sees the logical empiricism by Karnap as in general saying about the first two,
these things are true by conventional.
We adopt certain linguistic conventions, and things in logic and mathematics are true.
By virtue of the meanings of the terms, those meanings are determined by those conventions.
Physics is something that isn't a question of convention, that's something that's actually
talking about the real world.
Well, as I see it, Quine is basically saying, with respect to this idea of truth by convention,
that it makes sense only for one of these three.
Which one could we legitimately argue about, whether or not that thing is true by convention?
Logic?
Well, you'd think logic.
That is what, in a sense, quite a card game, Karnap, we're arguing about, except that
actually there, Quine disagrees with Karnap and thinks that the question is ultimately
unintelligible.
It's not so much that he thinks, oh, Karnap thinks it is true by convention.
I think it's not.
And there's a well-defined question we can debate.
He thinks, he says, look, my objection here isn't so much to question the truth of this
point as it's set.
Yeah.
I would say physics.
Physics, there, we might argue, somebody might say there's certain conventions that are established
in physics.
Others might say, oh, it's purely an empirical question.
Actually as we'll see there, too, Quine thinks there's a huge amount of arbitrarians.
And so that it's not clear that there's any real sense to the question of whether anything
in physics is true by convention.
Well, that leaves only one more possibility, right?
Math.
And there he thinks it is actually a legitimate question whether this is true by convention.
Now why is there that difference?
We need to think about this sort of question.
So let's raise this issue of truth by convention.
And here I mean, I'm going to put question mark to indicate, I mean the question of whether
this is true by convention.
I don't really mean to say what I'm about to do is, with respect to the truth, is it
true by convention?
But rather, does the question even make sense?
This answer is with respect to logic.
No.
And with respect to physics?
But with respect to mathematics?
Yes.
Now, why is it different?
What are his arguments in each case?
He thinks with respect to logic, for example, that we can't say anything meaningful in saying
that logic is true by convention or true by the meanings of the terms not or if some
all and other logical symbols or other logical words.
Now why is that true?
What's wrong with this idea of truth by convention there?
Not in the sense that it's false, but in the sense that it's just meanings.
What kind of argument is he given?
I've got to say that when I started out reading Quine as an undergraduate, I thought he was
a breath of fresh air.
He was so clear compared to other philosophers.
But then again, I had studied mostly continental philosophy, so in a certain sense compared
to Hegel and Sartre and Heidegger, he's a breath of fresh air.
On the other hand, I've got to say the older I get, the less I understand Quine.
And so I don't think it's an easy question to say what are his arguments against this
position here and here and what's his argument in favor of its intelligibility with respect
to math.
I used to think I got it, and it was sort of there on the surface.
Now I think it's very hard to tease out what's really going on.
Yeah?
I guess I'm kind of confused because I thought in the two dogmas, or his paper, whatever,
I think it's called just the two dogmas.
He talks about physical objects being the only, I can't remember if it's physical objects
or physics being the only thing so we can, you know, no study, whatever.
Right, right.
Well, we're going to end up thinking about a variety of other frameworks, as you point
out, and one of them is going to be just the framework of things.
We've talked about this issue in relation to Russell and a few other people, whether
we should really think of the ultimate constituents of the world, something like sense data or
sensations or other perceptions, this type of thing, or whether we can really legitimately
talk about objects, like people in tables and chairs or clocks, as the objects that
are in the world.
So there's that question, and we're similarly going to begin with other frameworks like
the framework of propositions and a framework of properties, but you're right that certain
of these client things are matters of, well, there's a sense in which you might say all
of these are really questions of empirical investigation, right?
In the end, his model is that web.
It's not that there's some sort of foundation of given things, either given by virtue of
the means of terms or given directly in experience, and then we construct all these other things
on the basis of it.
Instead, there are certain things we're trying to explain about the appearances of the world
and we're just building these frameworks in an attempt to understand the world, period.
And so it's all sort of mixed together there, whereas in a sense for the earlier logical
empiricists, there's a clear divide.
Certain things go into the foundation, things like logic and mathematics, and maybe some
things directly perceived, and then everything else gets built on top of that.
So if you want to think of it this way, here's the older logical empiricist view, it's this
layer cake view, where down here is sort of logic, math, sensation, and then everything
else gets constructed on top of it.
Whereas in Quine, so that's the logical empiricist picture, then in Quine, we get this picture
of, well, gosh, what?
The web, I'm not too good at drawing webs.
It's like a seal.
It does look like a seal.
Like a tiger striped seal.
By the way, what's going on on campus today?
I walked past camels to get here.
Why are there camels?
Yeah, they're camels.
It's the Israel block party.
Oh, okay.
Right out there in front of the Martin Luther King Center.
I had no idea what was going on.
There's all this stuff near the main building, too.
People handing out t-shirts.
I don't know.
Well, never mind.
Talking about a framework of editing.
There's this framework going on campus today.
But anyway.
Yeah, there's this sort of web of belief that it all hangs together in a certain sense
in trying to explain experience.
There's no one part we can isolate exactly the contribution it's making to the whole.
Now, if we go back to this question about conventionalism,
and we look for Quine's arguments about this,
in a sense, as I said, it's a little hard to uncover
because it goes into so much detail
and there's so much being presupposed.
But I think the core of it is something like this.
What's wrong with the idea in logic
that it is true by convention?
Or for that matter, not.
In the end, he says, look, we could say
we established these conventions about me.
And then logic follows from those conventions.
Or we could say
that, really,
they're just general features of the world.
Like things are self-identical.
Or, you know, gosh.
I'm trying to correspond to the law of non-contradiction.
Reality is not contradictory.
Something like that.
Reality is consistent.
And in the end, he says, there's no real difference
between those two pseudo-doctrines.
Now, why not?
Well, really, to understand this,
I think we have to go back to his paper Truth by Convention.
And there,
there's a lot of complicated stuff going on.
But in the end, it comes down,
I think, to a key move.
How would we establish
conventions in logic?
Here's a really simple convention.
Universal claims
imply their instances.
Right?
So we might say, here's a rule
that the universe will quantify.
In logical notation, we could put it this way.
If for all x,
a holds of x,
then a holds of c.
Let's say, for any constant c,
we substitute for x.
Okay?
Or, to put it in English,
we could just say, okay, everything
is a.
Therefore,
that is a.
And, that would be true for any
that.
Right?
Okay, so now,
there, I've tried to establish a certain convention
that partially establishes
the meaning of all, or everything,
or the universe will quantify.
But now, Klein says,
wait, I can't do that.
What's wrong
with saying, hey, I've just
established a convention, that's part of the meaning
of the universal quantifier
of all, or every, in English.
What's the problem
with that?
Can you rephrase that?
Yeah, sure.
He says, look, here's some card
and other logical empiricists were thinking
about this, and thinking of logic is true by convention.
I established certain conventions,
certain rules for my language,
and maybe I do that by having a
semantics for all,
or for the universal quantifier,
in a kind of formal sense.
Maybe, I don't. Maybe I just
introduce some rules like this. I say, that
establishes the meaning. Or I could do it with
am. I could say, here's what
am means. We have ways of introducing
am, so if I have the truth of a and b,
I can then say a and b.
And if I have the truth of a and
b, then I can deduce
a, or for that matter, b,
whichever I want.
And I might say those introduction
rules establish the meaning of a and.
And I could introduce
an introduction rule for the universal
quantifier and say, there,
I've given you the meaning of the universal
quantifier. I've told you under what
circumstances we can infer from something
else. I've told you under what circumstances
we can infer something else from it.
And that's all there is to establishing the
meaning. Now, Coins' way of saying,
I can't really do it.
There's something wrong with saying,
in doing this, I've just established
a logical
truth.
And why?
Let's take
a very simple example of one of these.
Like,
what's a good universal
claim? True of everything.
Gravity
is
universal.
Yeah, everything
exerts
gravitational force.
Therefore,
you
exert
gravitational force.
I want to say that's true just by
virtue of logic. Okay, and why?
Because of conventions.
Specifically, this convention
is what makes that true.
Now,
that seems plausible enough, right?
But what have I done in going from
this to that?
Here,
I have
a of x.
Here, I have
exerts gravitational force, right?
I
substituted
that to be a
in both cases.
Well,
how, what enabled me to do that?
What justified that?
Yeah.
The word everything?
The word everything, yeah.
And so, you might say,
well, it's just a matter of everything, right?
It appeals to some, well, and the mind says,
ah, yes, right, but wait a minute.
Notice what else I did.
I actually said, aha,
this is saying this is true for every a, right?
And so, I substituted
exerts
gravitational force in for the a,
in both cases.
But now, that was just
a bit of, well,
the very same,
actually, in this case, yeah, the very same
sort of
logical, in other words,
to get from my logical convention
to any actual
logical truth, I have to be willing
to engage in a bit of logical reason.
So, in other words, he says,
I can't actually establish a convention
without presupposing
logic.
In order to establish convention by doing
this, or by doing this for
conjunction, for example,
I have to already presuppose
some logic. I have to presuppose
logic that says, oh, you mean I can
substitute any sentence for a, and any
sentence for b, and have this make sense,
right? In other words, this is true
for all a and b.
And so, I'm presupposing something about
logic. And I'm saying moreover,
think about what I'm saying in the rule. Ah,
if you have both a and
b, you can conclude a and b.
I say, wait a minute.
I already have to understand
and to understand what it means to have both a
and b, right? Similarly
here, I said, if you've got a and b,
then you can conclude a
or b, whichever you choose,
right? And I could also frame it by saying
if you've got a and b, you can conclude a.
If you've got a and b, you can conclude
b. Both of those things are true.
He said, wait, both of those things are true.
To understand your convention, I already have to
understand the meaning of both, and
and all.
And so, you can't give me those things by convention.
I don't understand the conventions
and how to apply them unless I already know
logic.
So the central argument, as I see it,
of his paper truth about convention,
with respect to logic,
is that the conventions
or maybe, well, stating the conventions
I think, but also applying the conventions
presuppose
logic.
And so, they can't give you logic.
They can't give you the logical truth.
They can't specify the meanings
of logical particles.
You don't understand them unless you already
understand the conventions.
And here, I've done it in terms of
syntax.
In terms of, you know, actually
saying what the rules are,
but it wouldn't be any better
if I did it in terms of meanings.
In fact, how do we usually do that?
People will say something like this.
The truth value
of A
and B
is truth
if and only if
the value of A
well, actually, in this case
it's often done
to equal size, but I won't do it that way.
The value of A is true
and the value of B
is truth.
And notice what I've done.
I've given you
by convention the meaning of A.
I'm assuming, of course, you already understand.
And
right?
And it often goes this way.
The truth value of not A
is equal to truth if and only if
well, here's one way to do it.
The truth value of A
is not equal to truth.
You say, hey, I already have to understand not
in order for that to make sense.
Now, this is not a criticism
of these symmetrical rules
or a piece in tactical rules.
It's not any objection to logic.
It's just saying I can't understand
these conventions about meaning or about
use without already knowing
some logic.
You're defining the meaning of A
in a background language that includes A
or not, and well, that includes not.
Or here, the defining universal
quantifier
in a background language where I already have to understand
how to use the universal quantifier.
Now, I can't be getting logical truth
out of these conventions.
I only can state the conventions that apply to them
by already understanding logic.
Do these conventions always follow
things that seem to be logically true?
It's never like a convention's established,
then something follows
from that. It's the other way around, right?
Like, that's what this is saying.
That's what's quite the same. Right, exactly.
It's not like we established the convention
and then these things follow in logic.
It's rather that we have to already
know the logic to even state the convention.
So what does that mean?
Well, what he thinks what it means is that
here would be a simple way of concluding.
Ah, so logic isn't true by convention.
Somehow
stating conventions or applying conventions
and so on would already
presuppose logic. So conclusion,
logic is not true by convention.
Interestingly, he doesn't really say that.
He says, I don't think
it makes any sense to talk about logic
as true by convention. So
it's not so much he thinks the claim is false.
He thinks it's unintelligible and we still
have to ask why that would be true. Yeah.
Can't you define them other ways
like the truth tables that
don't seem to
imply or, you know,
don't seem to presuppose anything
or like that? Let's try that.
Okay, so
we have A, B,
and then A and B
and we're going to set up truth
tables so I say, well, there are four possibilities
here. These might both be true.
A true, B false.
A false, B true, both false.
And now I'm going to say that
A and B is true if and only if
well both are true otherwise false.
So I write a table like that
and that seems to establish a convention
that specifies the meaning of AND.
Now have I in any sense
presupposed the meaning of AND
or other logical
particles? I mean one thing I've
posed right is
universal character. You might say
the schematic letters A and B
already assume that I understand
something about universal quantification.
But have I in any sense
assumed something of the meaning of AND here?
Well, you wouldn't be able to write
the truth values on the right side
if you didn't know AND already meant...
Well, that's true.
Although
yeah, one way of looking at it
is to say, where am I coming up
with these? I must not really understand
if I'm going to do that. Now, of course
I could say, no, no, no, I'm not doing that.
I'm doing that in a purely formal way.
In fact, I could say, given that
there are two terms here
I'm just interested in defining
certain connectives with two
truth values. There are 16
different truth functions. And so
I could really just be specifying all of
those. And then once I've specified
them all, I say, oh look at this one. I'm going to call that
AND. And that's my convention.
That's the convention about AND.
And, you know,
that might be fine. So others
we might have to think a while to realize
what on earth is, if anything,
that corresponds to a natural language.
Yeah. Yeah, I think, but
in this case, it's tempting to say
what Quine does, because AND is part of
our language, and you kind of have
to, you know,
understand what, it seems like
you have to understand what AND is to fill out the table,
but you can do something purely arbitrary
with like a three,
you know, something that takes in three inputs
that has no analogy
in our language, you know,
it's just some arbitrary
truth table that you can define by convention.
Yeah, right.
This is really off topic,
but I can't resist
telling you about one of my favorite connectives.
This is post negation.
Okay. Suppose we have
three truth values, truth,
indeterminacy, and falsehood.
Well, a post negation,
and I don't know
exactly how to write a post negation,
so
I'll just say post A.
Is this? It's true
if this is false.
It's indeterminate if it's true, and it's false
if it's indeterminate.
So what it does is mathematically
very interesting. It just rotates
all the truth values one place, right?
So it rotates it back
like this one place, and so it's super useful.
It turns out that
in a many valued logic, this is
a wonderful way of getting a functionally
and complete set of connectives.
But now,
what does that mean?
I mean, ordinary negation would be
true if this is false, and false
if that's true. Here it's indeterminate if that's true.
And if A
is indeterminate, it's let's say
a borderline case of vagueness, for example,
but this is just false.
I can't think of what that means
in English. I can't come up with any
English equivalent. And as soon as
you get to either three truth values
or more than two
positions here, it's very easy
to come up with connectives where you say,
well, I don't know how to say that in English.
It doesn't seem to correspond to anything.
With one or with two, it's not too hard.
Usually it comes up with some
English expression that captures the meaning.
But a third truth
value or a third term
in the collection
here in that compound
sentence becomes very easy
to generate. So you could say,
look, that's just arbitrary. Don't worry
in other words about this part. That's
something maybe we could just say, we
arbitrarily filled out. Then we arbitrarily
assign the word and to that meaning
and thereby establish a convention.
So I don't think this
is going to be the source
of the objection that the client would have.
But is there another one?
Yeah? So that post-negation
thing, I know it's about topic, but like
so what
are there any institutions in the
world that would apply?
I don't know what use is it.
What use is it? Well,
because in a many-valued logic
the way it's usually done,
we introduce connectives in
a kind of intuitive way and negation would be
just true if this is false, false
if that's true and then indeterminate like that.
So that's a typical negation
in a many-valued logic.
But it turns out that
when you do this in the kind of natural way
introducing this third
truth value of indeterminacy
there are all sorts
of truth functions you cannot express
in that basic language. Because what happens
is you get a fixed point at
indeterminacy, for example.
If all the inputs are indeterminate, the
output is always indeterminate.
And so in standard
many-valued logics
once you sort of hit indeterminacy
you can't get out. And the same thing is
true of determinacy. If all the inputs are
indeterminate, the output is always
indeterminate. So you can't actually
define a truth function that takes
determinacy into indeterminacy or vice-versa.
And that's a real
mathematical limitation of the system.
You might think it's also a real
meaning limitation since it seems
as if we ought to be able to
take indeterminate inputs
and get a determinate output. For example
if somebody says, oh, it's indeterminate that
we ought to be able to actually
then say, oh, that's true because
all the inputs are indeterminate.
And so it means
that illogic has it standardly done. You
can't express things like
it is determinate whether or it is
indeterminate that and so forth.
And so this
is a way of letting you define all of those
things. It's a very mathematically
elegant way of letting you define them.
It's also just a mysterious way
of letting you define them from an English
sort of human point of view. But that's
why it's useful. How do you get to that,
though? How do you just change it?
How does that work?
Well, in math you can do anything you want
to. Just, you know,
instead of saying, you know, you can just say,
well, take a logic with or and
and not define the usual way and then
oh, add the post-connective
and boom, you can now define anything.
You can define, it is determinate whether
or it is indeterminate that.
Or it's definitely true, and I mean true
and not false and not indeterminate that
and so on.
And so it's really useful.
It just requires something that we can't
assign a real meaning to in English.
Yeah.
So just going back to the original question.
We have several different systems of logic
and you've just shown another one and
you can define some logics in terms of
other logics.
So why doesn't that show that
logics can be defined conventionally
so long as the conventions are based on other
logics? Like why can't you just kind of do a
circle? Well, good question.
There are a lot of contemporary logicians
who think, yeah, logic is true by convention
and indeed, you can see it
as soon as you move to some of these other
logics and you think what convention should
we establish? In fact, just the idea
that we could have more than two truth
logics who think, ooh, what should we say
that about and, about or, about not
in such a logic?
And it feels in many cases as if you're being
asked to define certain conventions,
not as if you're being asked to
presuppose what you already
mean or already do.
And it certainly has that feeling
when you are characterizing something like
quantum logic or certain other logics
for highly specific purposes.
So it is a defensible position.
But now, let's get back
to the client's objection. How would he object to it
there or here?
It's not going to be on the basis of this,
although that's very tempting to say
yeah, look,
it's in somehow filling that in
that we're establishing a convention. Here it has
that feeling strongly because this isn't capturing
the meaning of anything we're presupposing. It's not like
oh, come on, we were all using the post-negation
all the way along, right? No, we weren't.
But in this case, let's go back to this
because it's a much simpler case and then we'll
go back. Here,
what is this first row of the table?
How do I explain what's going on in the first row?
I said,
suppose A
is true and B is true.
A is true
and B is true.
A is true and B is false.
A is false and
B is true.
Just in explaining what the table was,
I used and, right?
And I don't know how to avoid that.
So I've already got
and sort of built in here.
That seems very odd because
you could do all of those, do all the tables
just as I said with just and,
but and is not logically complete.
Right.
Which seems very strange, right? You can base it all
on something not logically complete.
All right, good, good, good, good.
Yeah, notice what I, in this example
and really with any of these where I use the schematic
letters, it looks like, what am I presupposing?
I'm presupposing something about universal
quantification.
Whether I stated explicitly
or whether it's really just in the background
by me using letters like A and B.
And then here, do you even explain
the row of the truth table? Before I get to this,
I've got to be using
and.
And we've seen that here.
I've got both A and B so I can do
A and B, etc.
I suppose
you could argue, I've presupposed it then
if both of these are true then
that's true.
So maybe I've presupposed
if in that way. In fact, once I get
to this, here I've
just got A, right? So I'm not presupposing
and, but I am saying if A is
true then this post-connective
applied to A is indeterminate.
And so I seem to be
presupposing if then.
What about not?
When we got to negation
it looked like I had to say something
about not. I had to say
not A is true if and only if
A is not true.
And so maybe I've presupposed not.
But now if I've got all of that
I do have a functionally
complete set. So you're absolutely right
that if I look at individual ones
I'm not using all of those. I might
depending upon the way I'm doing it
be committed to let's say here
all and and maybe if then.
But that's not functionally
complete. Only certain things are going
to actually require negation.
And then
I'm going to end up presupposing the whole thing.
If you did the entire
if you did the truth table for the
Shephard stroke to build an entire logic
counter. Would you need
all a logically complete thing to
define it? That's a good question.
Would you need the not? Let's do it.
Let's do Shephard stroke.
Which is the not A.
Okay. So it means basically
not both A and B.
Well, if you've got both A
and B it's false.
Here
you don't have both A and B. So it's true.
And true and true.
Okay.
Now what did I presuppose in doing that?
Well, I said
if this and that then this.
So I've got and and if
I've got the schematic letter.
So I've got the universal.
I never need the negation.
I ever have to presuppose negation.
Since this means not A
you'd think surely I did.
But how?
You might think it's already implied in the false
but
not necessarily right.
Because we don't have to think of false
as just not true. And the possibility
of many value logics indicates
why we might think that's not right.
But for example here I said
if this is true and that's false
then this is true.
Didn't seem like
I had to use negation there.
Now in thinking about
I did I had to think oh it means
not both A and B. So
here they are both true so
if this is not true it's false.
That went on in my head
but in terms of actually just stating
what the convention is I didn't have to do.
So I think it's kind of interesting
that I don't at least see why this presupposes
not.
Does it also presuppose truth values
or would that not fit under there?
Well yeah it does
presuppose truth and false.
So true and false
get in here too.
And I suppose you might say
there's got to be someone there.
Moreover if I've got false
then actually can't I define not?
Some people have tried
to do that and said yeah
not A for example
is just if
A then
false.
And so if that
would work as a definition of negation then
by having false in there I can actually already
get negation out.
But anyway I think it's a good question
you're raising and something to climb
in both of these papers just glides over quickly.
Just like oh well
the presupposes logic I can't get
I can't state the convention, I can't apply the convention
unless I've already got logic.
But that's really sloppy.
What I need depends on the nature of the convention
right?
And maybe in the end
I need all the first order logic
but maybe I don't.
That's something that really has to be argued for.
It's not just something to vaguely allege.
So thank you for raising these questions
and if it seems like I've gone off on a long logical
regression here. Not really
because the whole idea here is that
in stating these conventions we're presupposing
not just a little tiny fragment
of logic but logic
period and
so it matters what we're actually presupposing
to evaluate quite
the time.
Now
let's move on to math.
It's supposed to be okay
to worry about the conventionalism
of mathematics. Again he's not
committed to claiming that math is true by convention
but just that the question makes sense
with mathematics.
So
before we guess that, maybe we should do physics.
What's wrong with saying that certain
things in law in physics are true by convention?
Now nobody's going to want to say all of physics
is true by convention.
It's obviously an empirical science and there's a lot of
experimental stuff and observation
required but
could there be certain things that are established just by
convention? You might say
for example in classical mechanics
well let's say Newton's laws
of motion. One of them
is force
is, I keep writing things low
in the blank, force is
mass times acceleration.
Now is that
an empirical claim
that requires observational backing
or is it a definition of force?
Is that something that we could say is true by definition?
The definition.
All right,
suppose we say it's true by definition.
Now what does that imply about certain other things?
What's another physical
law that involves force?
Well for example, work is
force times distance.
Is that a definition?
All right, so suppose we say it's
true by definition. Then we've got
work is equal to
well gosh,
distance times mass times acceleration.
And presumably that now follows for our definition.
That's just an analytic truth.
Well what about this relationship?
Kinetic energy
is equal to one half m v square.
Is that a definition of kinetic energy
or is it an empirical claim?
I don't know.
Moreover,
how about this?
Momentum
is mass times velocity.
It's not very clear
what I should take as definition.
I might axiomatize physics
in the way that I might axiomatize geometry.
But the point is that
it's sort of arbitrary which of these
I take as definitions and which I take
as actual
empirical claims.
And his point is, in a certain sense, physics
stands or falls with all of these.
It's not as if,
well for example, I've chosen
this example. Neutronian mechanics.
In part because we now think this theory is wrong.
Okay, we teach it to all our
high school students. We teach it to people in
intro physics classes in college.
But it's false.
Now why is it false? Well because
the speed of light should really be in here.
We need to distinguish between inertial mass
and rest mass.
And so forth.
Now where's the falsehood?
You might think, ah, certain of these things are just
analytic. So the falsehood all has to be in the
empirical claim.
But that seems a screwy way of doing it.
The fact is we have to just figure out
and for example, this is one of the places we
make some adjustments typically.
And so if we
start adjusting that in relativistic mechanics,
you might say, well maybe that
really wasn't a definition.
Or you might say maybe our concept of energy
has changed. Certainly our concept of
mass has changed when we distinguish rest mass
from inertial mass.
So in a way here, Klein's point is just,
it's not that it's unintelligible.
It's just arbitrary.
It's this
great line that says asking
which of these physical claims are really
axioms and are really
definitions is really
kind of like asking which points in Ohio
are starting points.
And presenting the theory, I can introduce
anything as a definition I want
as long as it has the right logical form.
And then other
things will emerge as empirical claims.
But it's really kind of arbitrary how you would do
that. It's not like
some of these are just obviously
definitions and others are obviously empirical
claims. So we adjust that with our
presentation of the theory. Just as we do
in geometry, what should we take as the
axioms of geometry? Well,
you could take all sorts of things as
axioms of geometry and
then derive other things as theorems.
There's nothing about a certain kind of claim that
just says, oh, that's going to be a fundamental
axiom. What we take as basic
is just a matter of how we present
the theory.
But Klein's point on the other hand
is just that, look,
in the end, when we change a physical theory
it's not like certain things are analytically true
and are off the table. We have to figure out
how to adjust things in the theory. And some of the
things in the theory we keep, other things
we throw out, sometimes we take
one notion and replace it with two notions
and in short, draw a distinction we hadn't
drawn before. And there's no way
to predict which of these things are
libel and empirical challenge
and which ones are immune from that because they're
analytic. Yeah.
Do any of them have to be definitions or
can they all be empirical?
Yeah, they can all be empirical. We don't
have to make any of them definitions, right?
And in a sense, Klein's point is that in
the end, yeah, that's really the right way to say it.
I mean, if I'm writing
a physics textbook and I want to present
some as really just defining
the term momentum, let's say, or defining this or
that, then okay, I can do that.
I can do that as a matter of my presentation.
But that's a question of how
I'm presenting the theory. It's not like
something that is fundamentally true
within each of the subjects. So
for example, in thinking
about actually every day in class
how to come in and talk about what I'm going to talk about,
I think, well, where do I start?
But it's not as if
I look at the subject matter.
In this case, the Klein-Karab debate
and just see, aha,
there is the foundational question.
I try to identify what I think
the foundational questions are, but in terms of
my presentation, where do I start?
It's not like I look in and just find starting
points in these debates.
I have to think how am I going to structure
this, how am I going to discuss it
and explain it, and I pick a place to start.
And in short, it would be like that.
So it's not as if
in the physics book we couldn't introduce any definitions.
It's just that
we're doing that as a matter of presentation,
as convenience, not as a way
of reflecting that there really is a distinction
in the underlying physical claims.
So I suppose in that sense
it could be easily misconstrued.
It would be in a way a bad idea
in a physics book to say, ah,
just true by definition of that.
Because that sort of implies that it's
really true about the claim
rather than just by way of talking about it.
And indeed, physics books generally
don't. They're wise enough
not to think, oh, this is a definition
of force or a definition of kinetic energy
or something.
Now, we should
end with mathematics.
What makes this question
intelligible for that?
Well, all math adds to luck,
as we saw last time, was that
and then other things that can be defined
in terms of membership. All we need
really is certainty.
So,
how can we
introduce that? Now, here, Klein says,
actually at this point we are
doing something like
leading by convention.
Does my introduction of that
actually presuppose sense?
He thinks it doesn't.
And so, I don't fall into the trap
of logic falsification.
On the other hand, neither is it purely
arbitrary
because after all, I'm not just
dealing with a bunch of empirical claims
in characterizing the world of sense.
I'm not investigating the sense. It's like,
ooh, there's a set of students in the room
that study the scent.
I don't do set experiments
like that.
Instead, what do I do? Well,
I'm characterizing an idea that I'm
in effect making up.
So, what would I
actually do?
When I characterized that theory, we talked about this
some last time,
but today maybe we should do it a little more
officially.
Here is a principle
that we tend to adopt.
Extensionality
and what it says in logical terms
is that
well, it establishes an identity
criterion for sense.
It says for any sense x and y
x equals y
if and only if for all z
z belongs to x
if and only if
z belongs to y
and so
to put it in English
sets are identical
if and only if
they have the same members.
Now notice
that in doing that
I am certainly presupposing
logic, right? I'm assuming
you understand universal quantification
and if and only if and something about
well, actually identity is being defined here
that's not being presupposed
even though when I say it this way
the same members might think
it sounds like I am, but really
I can characterize that just in terms
of the if and only if and the all.
So this is presupposing
logic.
Is it arbitrary?
Well
no, not really
I mean I can treat it
as a definition of identity with respect to
sets or I can treat it as a claim
a substantive claim about the nature
of sets, but
the fact is it does feel like
I'm establishing a convention that lays down what a
set is. How is a set different
from a property for example where this is not
true? So it does have the
feel of a convention. Now
is it exactly a convention
do I have to be a convention when I'm talking
about it? Well no, I can argue
that there is an underlying truth about sets
and so forth, so he doesn't want to say
this question is decided, but it's not
absurd to say I'm establishing this by convention
it's not really arbitrary
because I
do need
I do need
I do need identity conditions
for sets and moreover
it has the feel
it's a stipulative definition
remember
stipulative definitions
were ones that he thought actually
do a set or something like an analytic
plane. Why? Because
I'm just saying let blah blah blah
I introduce
a term and I just define it in a certain
way and I'm not trying to capture previous
use it, I'm not
introducing this in the context of a broad
theoretical understanding, I'm just saying
let this be that
you know, let a metric space be
blah blah blah blah
and that defines a metric space
I'm just introducing the term in that way, it's not like
I have some previous concept on that, yeah
but isn't the
set
symbol in the definition?
the set symbol is in the definition
oh, I see what you're saying, so wait a minute
why don't I presuppose
sets? This seems like twice as clear
as the logic of why it would presuppose
yeah, right
what I end up doing
is introducing a bunch of different
axioms
all of which are going to involve this symbol
and so
now I end up saying, yeah, really
I can treat it as a definition of this
but what about that?
am I presupposing the sets in all of this
by putting in that symbol?
I think the
claim is meant to be, no, I'm giving
you a bunch of statements about
that symbol and then that symbol
is supposed to be defined as whatever those claims
are true of
but yeah, that's
that's a doctrine
called implicit definition, Russell's
well, other people were fond of it actually
at one point, Russell said it had
all the advantage of theft over honest
toy
and so
in a way, that's why Gwynne thinks
look, it's a meaningful question but
it would be possible to say
can I treat it that way?
his claim is that that isn't presupposed
it's in part characterized by this
you could do the same thing for logic though
right, couldn't you do implicit
definition and just call it
implicit and say it's not presupposed
it's whatever, yeah, yeah, well
that's a good question
unfortunately, we're past
of time
so, next time we'll think about that
question and we'll look at Carnap's
paper, empiricism, mathematics and
ontology and see how he tries
to avoid these problems