My name is Melanie Murphy and I love asking people questions that are difficult to answer.
Something I've been fascinated by recently is how much social media has blown up over
the past 20 years and let's be honest 20 years is a drop in the ocean of the timeline of humanity
and yet it's completely changed our lives. I create online content for a living mostly alone
as well as writing books the loneliest of jobs and while I feel that I spend plenty of time with
real-life human beings my average daily screen time leaves much to be desired.
So how many hours on average do you spend on your screen per day?
Four hours a day Lucy. Over four hours that is like two movies I could be watching a day.
I could be running a whole marathon every day. A lot of time spent with family and friends.
Ever since I graduated I've been partial to that mental nourishment that comes with having
different voices contribute to important conversations and the conversation around
social media and loneliness couldn't be more significant right now. What with study after
study and headline after headline pointing to higher rates of social isolation and depression
in those who replace most of their face-to-face encounters with cliques.
All the while 81% of teenagers feel that social media has a positive effect on their lives
and the credit for helping them to build stronger friendships.
Almost half of the people on this planet use social media every day for hours
and as humans time is our most valuable resource so are all these things like Twitter and Instagram
and Facebook detrimental to our social lives our well-being here is some food for thought.
Face-to-face interaction is like so important I just feel you get a good read of someone
when you're like looking at them looking at their expressions or the way they say something like it's
it's you can't compare that to like a text message or anything like that.
I've met people and I'm friends with people and I've gone on dates with people
I would never have met only for social media. You know it is intense and it is overwhelming
to go online and go on social media and see that 300 of the people that you follow are active
and they are accessible to talk to to interact with but they're not really there.
Social media was created to be social with people and I try to always remember that.
Ironically even though it's supposed to make us feel more connected can actually enhance
feelings of loneliness. I think social media can be really beneficial to people who are
experiencing something that can be really isolating like going through an illness.
The internet has been such a bridge for me such a lifeline.
I think social media makes me less lonely definitely.
I have to put my phone on did not disturb all the time because my brain can't handle it.
If children had phones in schools they wouldn't be locking up from the phone
they would be texting each other through the phone.
I would say that like 80% of my friendship circle has come from social media.
It would not surprise me if a lot of young people growing up nowadays
with who only know social media are terrified of conversation.
But from their point of view they're looking at people like us and going wow
I want to be like them they have loads of friends and meanwhile I'm sitting at home
with my dad with his cancer and no one's there.
Sometimes you'll like chat a lot online and you see that person in person and it's really
awkward and you don't know why and it's just like the chemistry.
Before social media your social life was your immediate friends group your work groups
and arranging to go out with them was you know if you were going to meet someone
say you met a girl in the pub and you were trying to arrange a date
she lived in South Dublin you lived in North Dublin
you'd get if you got her number you would probably ring from a public phone box
to confirm the date and time and then you'd be meeting them the following Saturday under a
clock in old chemistry with the advent of social media you've got your you know your fourth group
everyone I imagine everyone has set up is their family connections
where you can connect with people you would not normally connect with
and a family who've gone abroad historically before the internet you would you would probably
never hear from them again in some on some occasions so you get people past jokes comments
statuses or whatever the children are doing.
I moved home from living in Scotland for five years because social media just couldn't cut
it for me I needed to be around people physically not just see them on social media and see what
they're doing get the snippets of their lives rather than just spending time with these people
I needed to have the actual interaction with people rather than reading a text and they're
always just posting pictures and things like that so at different points when I was over there it
either helped me feel connected to them but also made me feel a bit lonely as well so at different
points I'd be like oh it's so good to see that everyone's having a good time but then other
times I'd be like I know I really just want to be there with them it was really tough.
I follow I think 700 people on Instagram and I know what 300 of them have for breakfast every
morning I know what time they go to sleep at I know how they're feeling I feel connected to
these people because I know these personal things that I would only know if I lived with them or if
I was friends with them but I'm not I've never met this person and it is kind of a lonely feeling
to almost believe that you know someone when you've never even had a personal conversation with
when I'm on Instagram and I'm interacting with people and I I didn't come away from it I feel
less connected to people for example like if if you put up some that's you know like you're quite
upset about and you're kind of looking for support you know do I feel disconnected from people
because it's not it's almost it's not them that's saying it to me but it's it's just a voice
or do I feel connected because I can on hand talk to them so easy it is a big commitment or it can
be a lot of pressure to to be there for someone especially if you're if you're not all there
yourself or you you have stuff going on so to just send the text is a lot easier on you when
shit hits the fan things are tough things are shit that's when you start to realize who your real
friends are I started vine three years of vining made loads of friends vine died and then my dad got
cancer and I spent all of my time taking care of my dad after that and then suddenly every single
person I thought I was friends with just disappeared I think social media is almost like a a poison in
the sense that it can make you feel like you have lots of friends and it makes you feel like you
have a big social life and then when real life happens someone passes away somebody gets ill
you're depressed there really isn't the social media carries on and none of those people are there
for you despite the fact that the numbers are all there the followers are all there the comments
are all rolling in haha this is so funny you're the best creator ever you're just sitting there at
home like flicking through your phone your dad's ill like it's like it's so weird it's it's almost
like an episode of black mirror social media has definitely been a double-edged sword for me
in terms of improving my anxiety and also triggering it again um I think when I first started to talk
about my experience with mental health social media was an incredible tool for me to share and
realize that I wasn't on my own because I think such a characteristic anxiety is that you think
you're the only person going through it so by putting something out there whether it was
Facebook or Instagram instantly I could really I could realize that there was so many people
who were going through the exact same thing I don't know I don't like to talk about my emotions
in person very much I would go to Facebook messenger and message my very close friends
or go to text and text my friends I wouldn't want to be in person with them while discussing that
thing that was bothering me so in a way it kind of aids my ability to talk to them when it's just
text and an image or maybe a couple of emojis you're losing out on the tone of voice the body
language and all of the other elements that go into communication that help you actually
convey a message or receive a message I love face-to-face interaction I'm like I'm
all about it I will talk to someone and give them my undivided attention I love talking to people
face-to-face just sort of quite a gestury kind of person tone and sarcasm and all that kind of
thing is very much the sort of like all my kind of idiosyncrasies um how I get my points across
and there's none of that on social media through text and that it's all very cold
when you're on social media you're behind a screen you're behind several filters or whatever
apps you're using you're curating it you're putting up the best bits if you want to and
you're taking your time to edit your caption and think about what you want to put out there
I've had people say to me that they're annoyed at how long it takes me to respond to messages
I think I'm one of the few people that doesn't get very offended when when I'm left on red because
I feel like I can empathize with why someone would want to leave me on red a lot of the time and
it's not personal it's about their own experience and not about me that gives me anxiety of going
oh are they waiting for me to reply to the message but I'm doing this but should I be
replying to them and it just starts spiraling on my head so instead I just leave it I have a very
different experience of social media I think to a lot of other people because I have a chronic illness
and a disparity that means I can't really leave the house very much and I spend a lot of time
I guess I would feel incredibly alone if I didn't have the internet I didn't have a way
to connect with other people I had a lumber puncture where they accidentally pierced my spinal
fluid sack too many times and my spinal fluid bled out and into my body so for two years while
my spinal fluid grew back essentially I had to be in a dark room by myself I couldn't have
light touch sound I couldn't have anyone near me because it was such an excruciating pain
and for those two years I felt incredibly alone I've thought am I the only person here
who's like this who's in the situation and now I get to make videos that I know touch
the people who are in that place still and that's the most beautiful thing for me
last year I had a really horrific like medical scare I was in hospital for a month with a
flare-up of my ulcerative colitis and I had emergency surgery and now I have a stoma which
basically like a bag poo and I remember being in hospital after my surgery and one of the first
things I did was I was on YouTube I was on Twitter on Instagram trying to find other young women
in the same situation as me and I found these amazing vloggers and bloggers and just like
people on social media who were talking about it who had like been through what I was currently
going through and they were like out the other end like living their life thriving and that was
so comforting to me to just be like right where are my women in their 20s and 30s with stoma bags
I've made so many friends from it I've connected with other influencers or YouTubers whatever it is
even their boyfriends online so it's created like a whole other dimension of socializing
I just don't really see a difference between like online friend and real life friend it's like
the same and like I'm literally here in Ireland because I'm going to the birthday party of a
friend I met online but now we're real life friends face-to-face interaction is incredibly
important for me to feel connected to someone I think because like one of my love languages is
like quality time of physical church so like I do think that social media is very useful but it
doesn't replace for me like you know physical interaction and actually meeting someone maybe
it's like touch them because I'm like a big like squeeze and shoulder hoax kind of person so yeah
you can't replace that I've met so many people and connected with so many people that I wouldn't have
before especially like um creatives of color and like black writers and black performers it's just
pretty amazing to have that community of creatives social media has created something that could make
people very lonely because people are putting so much emphasis into their online life that if that
goes tomorrow what do you have left I think we forget that the impact of how we use social media
can affect other people um in real life I don't even mean about online connections when I go home
my parents aren't going to be around forever and they're there trying to communicate with me trying
to catch up and I'm like yeah yeah answering them and not giving them that attention you're never
going to get that time back so social media has done a lot for me in terms of creating communities
if I look back in 20 years time when social media's gone I'm like that's a really good thing that I left
behind and created a conversation around when I go to meet up my hiking group I promote it all online
I get down I go everyone get off their phones I don't really use it to stay in touch with people
because it forces you to stay in touch with everybody and you don't necessarily need everybody in
your life it's so tempting to vent your feelings or share what you're going through online literally
this morning I was so stressed with various things are going on that I posted a uh Instagram story
saying everything will be fine just carry on everything's fine I'm fine like I was stressed
and I'm like sharing that I'm there and then I got a message from my friend and on reading the
message being like are you okay what's going on I was like ah this isn't the place for that
this world is full of people and sometimes you feel like your interests are yours and
maybe you feel a bit outcast and no one gets it but social media shows you that there are people
around the world who do and that's a wonderful thing there are also those times when I'm sat there
and I've got my phone out and I'm scrolling through Instagram or whatever and I'm seeing people out
at parties living their lives and or people in couples and you'll sit there and you're like oh
I I've noticed a hole that I have in my life yeah so the children I was teaching were quite young
their forms of social media that I found they were using was online gaming and I found that
some of the children who maybe wouldn't have had access to technology at home they got a
little bit left out then because they weren't as involved I have had a parent come to me before
about four times and say my child doesn't use it they don't have it and because of that they're
being left out of conversations it really impacted them it was a really important part of their day
sometimes when I hear heard a conversation why weren't you in the group chat I do see the child
to give a reason but they're trying to go a bit down in themselves then they're not as chatty so
I'd have to go over and chat to them be playing online with somebody who they've never actually
met but they're like oh I have this is my friend and that's my friend it kind of gives a different
definition to what they'd call a friend now I think I think social media can benefit children
that are shy and that they come into themselves online in an online persona they can make connections
with peers in their class online however it might not always translate then into the classroom if
they're not able to express themselves in real life they're not able to respond to that they
want to sit inside and be on a phone or a computer because that's what everyone else is doing which
is really worrying because it can it could give them a sense of really being involved in something
but then they could end up feeling quite isolated if these social media friends or online friends
aren't actively present in their life I do think social media makes you feel lonelier I find the
times where I've gone off it and I go away on holiday and I'm doing loads of stuff I feel great
when I'm hanging out with all my friends I feel amazing you spend a week alone with my laptop
and just my social media I'm not getting that connection I need to hear someone I need to
see them it's I think social media makes you feel lonelier because you're seeing everyone's
highlight reel there are 3.4 billion active social media users and on average people have 7.6
social media accounts it would appear to me that asking if social media makes you lonely is a little
like asking if eating makes you gain weight the answer is it can of course but not necessarily
and not in everyone and not forever it depends on how you use it and why just as it depends on how
much you eat and what social media use can be fine wonderful even in moderation but as with
any lifestyle loaded with processed foods an excessive intake of social media could be bad
for your mental health and for your quality of life and just as people need education around
nutrition we need it badly around technology it seems like social media makes us lonely when we
expect it to replace our real social lives rather than to aid them or when we allow it to take time
away from relationships that make our lives meaningful
you