The first thing many of us do when we wake up in the morning is what?
We grab our phone.
We search through our emails, our social media, all to catch up on the world while we were
sleeping.
Now, this isn't an issue, but it can be if it keeps you from communicating with other
people.
So, if you go to most campuses around here, you might notice students are looking down
at their phones, texting, or looking at social media instead of actually speaking to their
classmates.
Michelle McKenney, the owner of Third Degree Solutions, says all of this liking and commenting
is actually making people somewhat socially awkward.
We have to start back with the social skills to get our students and our kids and our youth
and our college students, especially, to start talking and being social with each other.
Coming up tonight at 5 o'clock, McKenney shares with me how you can make sure your student
at any age can still have a face-to-face conversation with people.
But it's a big problem.
A lot of people, they're just so used to texting or liking everything on social media, then
when they talk face-to-face, one girl says she doesn't like it because of awkward silences.
I'm like, that's so sad.
It's sad because you miss the experience, and you don't always know what's so insane
in text.
If they're really mad or happy or what's going on.