114% this is Anton and today we're going to be discussing some of the new propositions
in regards to the unusual phenomena that could be happening in many different black holes out
there. Phenomena that the scientists are now exploring using quantum physics and something
that can actually help us understand why certain galaxies have certain features and what happens
in certain black holes that spin really really fast. But before we discuss the black holes it's
actually important to understand where a lot of these ideas originally come from. They do come
from quantum physics and specifically from this really unusual state of matter usually referred
to as BEC back or Bose-Einstein condensate. Something that happens to certain particles of gas
as you cool them down and here these particles have to be what's known as bosons. Usually this
is particles of helium. As you start to cool them down each particle starts to acquire bigger and
bigger wave function and eventually each of these wave functions start to sort of interact
and then even joins in creating one single wave function that sort of acts as a single object
and this is what we refer to as BEC. This is essentially how the scientists have been studying
various quantum effects and this particular state of matter has even been created on the
International Space Station and we've discussed this in a video a few years ago. But the most
important part about this state of matter is that it really doesn't act like classical matter
at all anymore. It acts like quantum wave and its behavior and its interaction with other stuff
can actually no longer be predicted by classical physics. For example if you do something to this
matter and you expect certain type of reaction based on what we know about, well I just say
normal helium gas, the results are always going to be very surprising. It almost always acts in a
way that's only explainable through quantum physics and because of this in the last few decades
BEC has been one of the most exciting prospects in order to learn more about quantum physics
and to try to understand how things work in the universe. But while studying these BECs not so long
ago I guess around six years ago back in 2016 the scientists discovered a new feature of these
unusual BECs specifically the ones that tend to spin really fast. So in classical physics for any
kind of a spinning liquid or a spinning gas we can generally predict exactly what's going to
happen to it as it spins faster and faster. As a matter of fact hydrodynamics and aerodynamics
explain a lot of different spinning water and gas particles with extreme precision but for these
quantum particles for these BECs things are very very different. A typical BEC as it starts spinning
around starts exhibiting entirely different structures and entire different properties
something that nobody could predict until the scientists started to do it. They actually start
producing what the scientists today refer to as vortices but even here they're not at all similar
to the ones we find in the water they don't act like this at all. Here's a microscopic image
of what they really look like this right here is a spinning back spinning those Einstein condensate
and each of those tiny dots you see those are tiny vortices that appear inside the condensate.
But here we're talking about a kind of a quantized vortex that's formed with very unusual patterns
or almost resembling a crystal. Here are some other examples from similar experiments but
with the back of different size and so as you can see this phenomenon seems to appear in any kind of
quantum material that starts to spin and when analyzed this particular lattice store looks like this
it has a very specific order and it does seem to have its own physics that it obeys using quantum
mechanics. Today the scientists believe that these vortices can actually help us explain
different phenomena such as superfluidity and superconductivity but even though the scientists
have been studying them for many years they're not there just yet. You can actually see some other
visual examples in one of the links in the description with quite a lot of different
recreations of what happens to these backs as they start spinning but these patterns are not
permanent and they do change with time for example in this case it lasted for about 40
seconds before changing into something a little bit different so these are definitely not permanent
structures. But what does it have to do with black holes? Well when it comes to trying to explain
what black holes are a lot of modern physicists realize that modern physics cannot explain what
happens inside the black holes. For example Einstein's relativity only explains what happens right
until the event horizon with everything after this basically becoming infinity which in physics just
means that we don't really have a good explanation and so the scientists believe that quantum physics
and potentially the idea known as quantum gravity could provide some answers and what happens inside
black holes could be entirely quantum in nature in other words black holes could be basically very
unusual quantum states of matter although naturally at the moment nobody really knows exactly how any
of this works but there is at least one hypothesis and it does involve the hypothetical gravitons.
The particles at some scientists believe could explain how gravity works as well
and in this case because this is also a boson it can also create backs very similar to the ones that
I showed you previously and thus exhibiting very similar effects especially when it starts spinning
and so a few years ago the scientists proposed that well maybe backs with gravitons could explain
certain types of black holes with the most recent paper that was just released going further establishing
that for a spinning black hole assuming that it's made out of quantum gravitons it can actually start
forming these vortices as well with each individual vortex then producing a lot of other additional
effects we observe including very powerful magnetic lines that currently do not have a really good
explanation otherwise or in other words the implication here is really simple some black holes
or maybe even all black holes could be these very unusual boson condensates and might possess
very similar properties to what we actually discover in these experiments as well even showing
that a black hole that's spinning can also be described using similar physics but as a graviton
boson condensate that possesses the vorticity implying that this right here is just a bigger
version of what the scientists were able to take pictures of before and if correct it might provide
certain answers for a lot of different mysteries of black holes first of all it would suggest that a
very fast spinning black hole would be really stable and would not emit any Hawking radiation
in other words it would not evaporate and would actually remain relatively constant at the same
time they show that each individual vortex traps a lot of the magnetic field lines which end up
releasing very specific signatures that will be impossible to produce otherwise and that can
actually be experimentally detected by observing certain black holes which of course implies that
this is not just a hypothesis it's a testable hypothesis that some future studies could maybe
test if very specific observations are made at the same time this could also explain why
certain galaxies and specifically certain galactic nuclei tend to have very powerful magnetic fields
that otherwise are kind of difficult to explain as a matter of fact a lot of the magnetic fields
in various galaxies could maybe stem from these unusual effects from these unusual spinning quantum
black holes but i guess more importantly it also adds a completely new property to a typical black
hole today black holes are generally explained by three different properties we have mass we also
have charge and lastly we have spin so we know that all black holes spin they all have mass
and they all possess at least some charge but now there seems to be a fourth one vorticity
this could also be one of the features if the scientists behind the study are somewhat correct
and if black holes are indeed quantum objects exhibiting quantum features similar to what we
find in both Einstein condensates here on earth so definitely a pretty exciting proposition but
something that we're not going to be able to test until some of the future very powerful
observations from extremely distant black holes that we know most likely spin so definitely not
testable anytime soon but back in general always create so many different surprises as a matter
of fact we'll discuss some of them in videos you can find in the description below and so this
unusual state of matter can definitely help us resolve a lot of different mysteries in the universe
that would be very difficult to explain otherwise because this right here allows us to test and to
observe quantum effects by using actual microscopes and by using larger objects something that normally
only happens on subatomic scales but for now i guess we're not going to know if this is correct
and so until future studies thank you for watching subscribe check out some of the previous videos
in the description below maybe support us channel patreon by joining channel membership
or by buying the wonderful person t-shirt you can find any description as well
and stay wonderful i'll see you tomorrow and as always bye bye
so
You