Hey y'all, today we'll be talking about spinners. These things are really cool. Once you learn
about spinners, your life will never be the same. You'll develop a lingering, justified
suspicion that this world is not as it seems. And you might also develop a lifelong addiction
to physics. So, you've been warned.
To set the tone, I'd like to start off with a quote by the renowned mathematician, fields
metallist and knight, Sir Michael Atia. No one fully understands spinners. Their algebra
is formally understood, but their general significance is mysterious. In some sense,
they describe the square root of geometry, and just as understanding the square root
of negative one took centuries, the same might be true of spinners. Michael was an extraordinary
mathematician, and if he of all people says that no one fully understands spinners, then
it's okay if we're a little confused when we first learn about spinners. Spinners are
confusing, frankly they're disorienting, and not particularly intuitive. You know, if you tell
someone there's a thing that you have to rotate twice to get back to where it started, they might
think you're a little insane. But really, the insane thing is that spinners are not insane.
They're mathematically coherent, they show up in our most fundamental laws of physics,
and they refuse to go away. Spinners are really at the core of fundamental physics. I mean,
look at the way function of an electron, for example, or any fermion for that matter. If not
for spinners, we wouldn't have the poly exclusion principle, and so we wouldn't have chemistry.
Matter would collapse, and the world would be a very boring place. So there's no way of restructuring
physics in a way that you don't have spinners, and therefore these strange weird little mathematical
objects we do actually have to deal with, and we have to work with, and we have to understand,
where does this come from, what does it mean, why do these things exist, and it's really mysterious.
Okay, but what is a spinner? Hmm. Well, in the last few videos, we've been developing some of the
basics of relativistic quantum physics. We've looked at Klein-Gordon, we've looked at the
Dirac equation, we've looked at an example of Dirac equation for the eigenstate of a particle
at rest, and while we've done that, we've seen that spinners have emerged as the sort of two
component complex numbers. But today, I don't just want to define spinners as a pair of complex
numbers, because that's not particularly geometrically insightful. Instead, I want to show you an
argument for why we should expect something like spinners to exist in the first place,
and we'll do that by exploring a very subtle thing about the way objects rotate in three dimensions.
That'll open up a crack in reality that we can use to smuggle spinners into our imagination.
Then after that, we can explore the algebraic properties of spinners, we can see where the
complex numbers come in, we can see how we can draw spinners as flags, we can look at how they
transform under rotations, and finally, we'll tie it all back into the Dirac equation and we'll
talk about how this relates to electrons. This video will hopefully answer many questions,
and it'll surely raise many more. Spinners are one of those things where the more you
learn about them, the more wonderful and magical they become.
Before we talk about rotations, there are a few vocabulary words that we need to borrow from
topology. These are homotopic, simply connected, and homotopy class. So imagine we have a whiteboard,
and we've drawn a squiggly loop. The loop is alive and sentient and is feeling its way around
the whiteboard. As it goes along, in each moment it takes on a different shape, but it doesn't
break apart. It can stretch and shrink, but it can't be cut, and from one moment to the next,
its topology stays the same. The fancy way to say this is that it's evolving into different
loops that are all homotopic. Homo is in same, and topic is in topology, so homotopic means
that they have the same topology. Oh, whoa, little guy's getting nervous. Eh, that's okay.
Stage fright, you know, it's understandable. Oh, there it goes, shrinking down to a point.
It's a defense mechanism. That's fine, you know, I'm a bit shy myself, so who am I to judge?
Anyway, the reason our loop was able to shrink like that is that there wasn't an obstacle,
or a hole, or something weird that got in its way. Instead, it just had a nice, smooth,
simple space, so it was able to shrink on down to a point. And that is our next vocabulary word,
simply connected. A space is simply connected if all the loops that live in the space
can shrink down to a point whenever they want to. But now what if we take our whiteboard
and we drill a hole in the middle? So now as the loop explores its environment,
it goes around and it realizes that it can't go into the hole and it can't escape the board,
but it can still shrink if it wants to, so no problems there. But now consider this little guy,
which was born into quite a predicament. It's wrapped all the way around the hole,
so it can't shrink down to a point. When it's feeling shy, at best it can only become a small
circle, not a point. So that tells us that this space, whiteboard with a hole in it,
is not simply connected. So now think about this, the loop on the left can evolve into a variety
of different shapes that are all homotopic to each other. All the different forms that it can
take on are all a loop that lives between the hole and the edge of the whiteboard. Likewise,
the loop on the right can also evolve into many different homotopic shapes,
but those are all wrapped around the hole. And so you see here we have two different
homotopic classes, class in the sense of like a set of entities that all have something in common.
So we can say that the loops fall into different classes depending on whether or not they wrap
around the hole. And actually it's a bit more complicated than that because in this case you
could also have loops that wrap around the hole multiple times. And so we actually have a different
homotopic class for each number of times it wraps around. And so the winding number matters,
the number of times that the curve is wound around the hole that matters. But those are all
the homotopic classes of loops on the whiteboard. You can organize them just by specifying the so
called winding number. And a curve that has a certain winding number cannot be continuously
deformed into having a different winding number. So you can stretch them and shrink them but you
can't change the winding number unless you cut the loop which is not allowed. This hurts the loop.
Do not hurt the loop. Okay. Oh by the way in this context the loop can pass through itself so we
don't have to worry about the loop getting tangled up in knots and what are the different kinds of
knots and all that. No no it doesn't matter. The purpose of these loops are not to model like
physical rubber bands but just to tell us something about the nature of the space in which they live.
Oh one more thing on this topic. Imagine we repair the whiteboard so there's no more hole.
But now it has the magical property that the left and right edges of the board
are identified with each other such that the loop can appear to teleport from one side to the other.
So there's no longer a hole in the board but there is this weird teleporting situation.
So now is this space simply connected? To address that question we have to think about
what it means for the curve to teleport like this from one side to the other without breaking.
That means that each point on the left side of the board and the opposite point on the right side
of the board must be literally the same point. So we realize that this space is actually the
surface of a cylinder without the top and bottom circles. And so from that point of view no the
space is not simply connected because in addition to loops that can shrink to a point we also have
the possibility of loops that wrap around the cylinder and those cannot shrink to a point.
Now when we look at those loops on the whiteboard they look like weird teleporting lines not loops.
But when we're looking at the three-dimensional view that really shows the nature of the space
without any cuts and teleports but we see the real space the real for real like how it actually is
then we can see that indeed this is a loop and it cannot be shrunk to a point. By the way here
again it's the same exact situation as before where we can also have different winding numbers
and it turns out that all the homotopy classes of loops on a cylinder can be organized simply by
their winding number. It's not a coincidence that the hole in the whiteboard and the cylinder have
the same set of homotopy classes because if you think about it a whiteboard with a hole in it well
that's a cd and a cd is a lamp shade and a lamp shade is a cylinder so therefore whiteboard with
a hole in it is a cylinder. I love topology. You know the difference between geometry and
topology. In geometry you take your ruler and your protractor and you draw lines and angles and shapes.
In topology you take your ruler and your protractor and you throw them out the window.
Okay so now we know about homotopy simply connected and homotopy class. We also know
that if a space seems like it has teleports from one side to the other this might actually be a
totally continuous space with no teleports but embedded in a higher dimension such that you can
actually pull those points together. Now we're going to apply these concepts to the group of
rotations in three dimensions but first we have to specify what even is the group of rotations in
three dimensions. Let's say we have a cube and let's go ahead and stick a flag in it to make
it really easy to see how the cube is oriented. Now let me ask you this if we rotate this cube
what are all the different ways it can be oriented and how can we represent that set
of all possible orientations? Well there's a couple different ways of going about this and
they're all basically the same but probably the easiest way is to notice that every orientation
can be defined with some axis of rotation and some amount of rotation around that axis and this is
known as the axis angle representation. So what this means is that let's say we have some reference
flag that's say pointing up and in a certain direction then we can get to any other flag
orientation just by rotating the reference flag some amount around some axis. This fact is not
obvious but it is true it follows as a direct consequence of Euler's rotation theorem.
Okay now let's introduce the concept of an axis angle rotation vector so what this vector is
it points in the direction of the axis of rotation and its length is the amount of rotation so here
I'm showing a cube rotating around a single axis and you can see that as the vector grows and shrinks
the cube is rotated more or less around that axis and so if you think about it what is the
space of rotations in three dimensions? If you wanted to categorize everything how can we possibly
come up with some kind of space that encodes every which way a thing can be oriented?
Well it's the space of all directions multiplied by the space of all lengths
but it's a little bit tricky because it's not really the space of all lengths you know if you
rotate 180 degrees around some axis that's the same as rotating 180 around the opposite axis
so actually what you want to imagine is like a sphere where if the vector pokes through the
sphere by the way the sphere has radius of 180 degrees or pi if you want but when it goes
through the sphere then it ends up teleporting to the exact opposite side of the sphere
and it ends up coming back in if you keep rotating it see because what happens here and here we'll
just go along a single axis to make it easy to see but as the vector grows and grows the thing
rotates it gets to 180 and at that point we're going to map its rotation vector onto the opposite
axis 180 and then we're going to keep rotating and that's going to keep coming in and coming in
which is like a lesser and lesser rotation around that opposite axis until finally it ends up back
where it started and so in summary the space of all possible rotations in three dimensions
can be represented as a ball a ball meaning a sphere and also the volume contained within it
of radius 180 degrees where every point on the spherical boundary of the ball is identified with
the exact opposite point such that if you go outside of the sphere you seem to get teleported
back through the other side of the sphere but remember this is not actually a teleport there's
not actually anything discontinuous happening here this apparent teleport is just an artifact of the
way we're drawing this space in reality the space of rotations in three dimensions ironically doesn't
really fit in three dimensions and that's not that weird because if you think about it what we
have here is an abstract space that represents every possible kind of rotation so that's a different
kind of thing than the space that we're rotating within so it's actually not that weird that this
space ends up having this kind of topologically interesting character but a lot of weird things
follow as a consequence of that as we're about to see what i want to show you now is that there
are different kinds of ways to rotate an object back to its original orientation and that seems
weird because you'd think any way you rotate an object back to itself it should all be the same
right there shouldn't really be a meaningful distinction between how you go about doing that
but that's not actually the case so first let's recognize that if we rotate an object back to
its original orientation what that means in our axis angle space is that we're starting with the
zero vector at the origin meaning no rotation then the vector is going to go out and grow in
some direction and it can move around and in general it can do whatever it wants to do it can
teleport if it goes more than 180 whatever the case may be but in order to return to the original
orientation it has to come back to the zero vector so the space of all possible ways to orient an
object back to itself is exactly the space of all possible closed loops in this axis angle
representation there is one caveat here which is that when we look at loops in the axis angle
representation we should think of it only as going around the loop once for reasons that we'll see
in a moment and so what we're gonna do actually tell you what we're gonna take a circular cross
section so not the full three-dimensional ball but actually just a two-dimensional disc now this is
just a slice it's just a cross section but it's easier to look at than the full three-dimensional
thing and what i want to show you about there being different ways of rotating things all of that we
can see by examining this cross section and then we'll see that the same exact concepts easily
generalize into the full three-dimensional space now when we look at these loops i'm also going to
use a color map that winds around the rainbow and then comes back to the starting color and what
that's going to do is that's going to highlight for us the continuity of the loop and in a similar
spirit i'm also going to put a little dot on the loop that just goes around and around and so when
we're looking at teleports the ball is going to help us visualize which parts of the curve are
connected to which other parts of the curve but remember each of these loops only corresponds
to rotating an object once around this particular loop okay and that's important because as we'll
see there's a difference between going around once or twice or three times or four times and so
there are some subtleties there so in our diagram whenever we have a loop think about it as that
represents rotating the object one time around this path in the space of rotations
all right well with all that said let's go ahead and start to explore some of the different
kinds of loops we have in this axis angle space the first kind of loop that we'll look at is
maybe the simplest kind it's just a small loop that stays totally within the boundaries of the
diagram and this corresponds to a wiggle where the cube never rotates more than 180 degrees around
any axis it just sort of wiggles around for a bit and then returns to where it started
as you can imagine this loop is homotopic to any other wiggle that stays within the
boundary and passes through the origin because you can always just imagine stretching it and
shrinking it and exploring the entire homotopy class of wiggles and again these loops can pass
through themselves so we don't have to worry about the question of knots and the different
kinds of knots so aside from wiggles what other homotopy classes might there be well consider
a cube that rotates once along some axis so it does a full 360 that means that its loop is going
to start at the origin and then it's going to go out to 180 degrees then it'll come back in
along the opposite axis and finally it'll return to the origin again having completed a full 360
degree rotation now that's a rotation right that's not just a wiggle that's a full rotation and by
the way if you look at the loop it might not look like a loop it looks more like a weird teleporting
line but remember the cylinder and remember that the apparent teleportation here is just an artifact
of the way we're drawing the space but it doesn't represent any real discontinuity in the space you
have to imagine that the space is curvy in a way that doesn't really fit in the dimensionality
of your screen and so the points that the curve appears to teleport through are actually literally
the same point and in this diagram all pairs of opposite points are literally the same point
now this kind of loop is a genuine rotation i mean look it goes all the way around it's way more
than just a wiggle it's a full 360 and you can see that it can't be reduced to a wiggle because
there's no way of continuously deforming this loop into a loop that doesn't cross the circular
boundary without cutting it okay so then now we have at least two different homotopy classes of
loops in the axis angle space wiggles and full rotations so the space of rotations in three
dimensions is not simply connected which is really surprising right you wouldn't necessarily expect
that but here we can very clearly see that there are at least two totally distinct homotopy classes
of loops in the space of rotations in three dimensions and you know that's just a fundamental
fact of reality all right well this feels similar to the cylinder example where you had loops that
didn't teleport and you also had loops that teleported and then you had like multiple winding
numbers of teleportations and so we might expect to find infinitely many homotopy classes here for
the rotations depending on how many times the loop goes through the boundary but surprisingly
that's not the case there are actually only two different homotopy classes consider for example
the fact that a wiggle is homotopic to an octopus that's gotta be a brand new sentence i don't think
anyone's ever said that you're hearing it first here folks freshly minted sentence okay so the
wiggle crosses the boundary zero times but the octopus crosses many times and yet the two are
totally homotopic as you can see as we're going back and forth between these two you see they're
homotopic it's all continuous transformations here there's no cutting so we don't have one
homotopy class for each winding number like we did with the cylinder because now it's a different
kind of teleporting boundary the boundary is round and has a different geometry and so the
loops can slip around and slip through the boundary and what that ends up doing is it means that you
can always add or subtract two boundary crossings by continuously deforming the loop see for another
example let's say we have a rotation that teleports once and by the way each pair of points here
we're counting as one crossing notice they're the same color they're really the same point
it looks like two points on our diagram but that's an artifact of the way we're drawing a diagram
okay so this is one crossing but you can show that this loop is homotopic to a loop that teleports
multiple times but when you do that with this loop because it started off crossing once you can only
ever get to an odd number of crossings and so as it turns out we only have two homotopy classes
and they're based on whether we have an odd number or an even number of teleports
you can see this by noticing that you can always pull part of the loop through the circular boundary
but when you do so you'll always pull two line segments at a time because we're grabbing onto
a closed loop and that's just how it is and by the way you can see that this argument generalizes
not just to the circular cross section but also to the whole spherical situation because it doesn't
matter whether you're pulling a loop through a circular boundary or a spherical boundary
because either way the loop is going to come through two line segments at a time when you
pull on it so this thing about the two homotopy classes even though we've demonstrated that for
this circular cross section it actually does hold true for the entire space of rotations in three
dimensions oh and here let's go ahead and introduce some terminology so we'll say that a loop is
class one if it has an odd number of teleports and we'll say it's class two if it has an even number
this is easy to remember because one is odd and two is even
you know we've now arrived at a checkpoint like in a video game when you get to a certain level
and your progress is saved you'll want to make sure that you're really comfortable with all of
these ideas discussed so far because we're about to get algebraic and it makes all the
difference in the world if you're able to see and to feel in your soul that the rotations in
three dimensions are not simply connected but actually have two different homotopy classes
of loops i really want to emphasize that this is a fundamental insight a pivotal transformation of
your worldview that you have to go through if you want to study spinners you know even though we
haven't used any equations yet there's a lot to think about here and it may take a while to digest
these ideas i know it took me a while so it's worth meditating on these concepts until they become
second nature because seeing that the rotations aren't simply connected but have rather two
homotopy classes is really the difference between your intuition holding you back and pulling you
forward if you get this concept about two homotopy classes if you really feel it then instinctively
you'll suspect that maybe there might be some mathematical object that is sensitive to the
class of rotations and so it would necessarily have to double cover the space of rotations
and it might not exactly return to itself after a single rotation but instead might pick up some
phase factor that alternates depending on whether it's a class one or a class two and so if you
really get this then your imagination is going to pull you in the direction of spinners you'll
yearn for them even before you've seen what they are and you'll be prepared and excited when it
comes time to actually write an equation all right let's get algebraic so we have this idea
of an axis angle representation of a rotation and now the question is how do we actually work
with this what do we do with this let's say we have some rotation vector and we want to say okay
i want to rotate an object in accordance with that axis angle vector what equation do i write
what code do i put in the computer what do i do and i want to tell you about two different
ways of rotating an object the vector way and the spinner way so i want to focus on the vector way
first and this involves rotation matrices and then later i'll talk about the spinner way and this
involves su2 matrices so starting with the vector way of rotating things um actually you know what
here first we're going to go into two dimensions i'll show you how to rotate vectors i'll show
you the implications for this vis-a-vis rotating objects and then we'll expand up into three
dimensions but i'll use the two dimensions as an example to lay out some of the mathematical
framework all right so imagine we're in a two-dimensional space and we have a unit vector
pointing along the x-axis and you know a unit vector along the x-axis is kind of the simplest
thing you can put in a vector space so we're going to use that as our reference object because
you know no need to over complicate it now in order to rotate this vector what we can do is we
can construct something called a rotation matrix in two dimensions the rotation matrix about some
counterclockwise angle theta has the form cosine of theta negative sine theta sine of theta cosine
of theta and if you investigate the properties of this matrix you'll find two things first the
inverse of the matrix is the transpose of the matrix so if you transpose the matrix and if you
take the inverse that's the same thing and another way of writing that is that the matrix times the
transpose equals the identity matrix so that's the first thing and that means that the matrix is
orthogonal so in the inverse of a matrix equals its transpose that is an orthogonal matrix and
another thing we can see by inspection is that this matrix has determinant one because you know
cosine squared plus sine squared is one so our matrix is orthogonal and it has determinant one
and so the fancy word for that is it is a special orthogonal matrix in particular it's a special
orthogonal two by two matrix and so what we say is it is an s o two matrix so a rotation matrix in
two dimensions is also known as an s o two matrix oh by the way even though we're talking about s o
two in terms of matrices the term s o two can also refer to the group of rotations in two dimensions
in a more general sense whether or not we use matrices to represent them for example instead
we could represent 2d rotations with unit complex numbers and complex multiplication
because the group of e to the i theta's under complex multiplication is isomorphic to the group
of s o two matrices under matrix multiplication and that's a neat little connection there between
the complex numbers and the s o two matrices we'll see in a moment that there's a similar
connection between the quaternions and vsu two matrices but more on that later but for now i just
wanted to let you know that there are many equivalent ways to reformulate all of these concepts
but i like the matrix representation because it's very mechanical and transparent now if we
look at this blue thing swinging around we realize that we can use the set of all rotated blue vectors
to visualize the set of all s o two matrices because if we define the unit vector along x
as a reference vector then each s o two rotation matrix corresponds to one and only one rotated
unit vector so if you tell me hey here's a reference vector and now here's a rotated vector
then by looking at how rotated the rotated vector is i can figure out what s o two matrix was
responsible for the rotation likewise if you give me an s o two matrix and a reference vector
then i can draw you the rotated vector so there's a one-to-one correspondence here
and this is true regardless of what reference vector we pick no matter its length or orientation
which you can prove to yourself by skeptically tilting your head and leaning back
so anyway we can see that we can loop through the s o two matrices in a periodic way passing
through each of them in order of increasing angle and then ending up back where we started
and so we can see that the topology of s o two is just a circle and that's why s o two is also
called the circle group so in two dimensions we can represent an s o two matrix in other words
a rotation with just a vector but when we go to three dimensions because of the extra degree of
freedom uh we're gonna have to use a flag and the reason we're using a flag is because if you
just had a vector in three dimensions then that kind of points in a certain direction but then
there's the question of how is the vector rotated along its axis and so with a flag we can see that
flag rotation angle and so we can use that to represent the rotations in three dimensions but
before we get into three dimensions i want to show you how to rotate a flag in two dimensions
and basically the way to do it is just imagine the vector that points from the origin to each
of the interesting points on the flag so the zero vector points to the flagpole base then you
have a vector that points to the top of the flagpole a couple of vectors that point out to the sides
of the flag and then another vector that points along the flagpole to the point where the flag
meets the flagpole so basically we just treat those five points as vectors and you apply a
rotation matrix to those vectors and as it turns out the whole pattern of the flag will rotate
when you do this and that's because rotation matrices preserve the relative lengths and
angles of vectors that they're transforming and so any lines drawn between two vectors which is
also the difference of those two vectors will transform in the same way as all of the other
vectors now here's a view where we offset the flag from the origin so here this really drives
the point home that if you have some shape made out of vectors and you rotate all the vectors
you end up rotating the shape there's a couple of other concepts I wanted to touch on while we're
here for example what would happen if we scaled up our rotation matrix so that its determinant
were greater than one well now it would no longer be a special orthogonal matrix but it would still
be a matrix and it would still transform a vector field and as you can see from this animation if
we take a rotation matrix and scale it up so that its determinant is greater than one then that's
just going to expand all of the vectors likewise if we scale down a rotation matrix so that its
determinant becomes less than one then that's going to shrink the vectors and the reason I
bring this up is so that you can see the connection between a matrix having determinant one and a
matrix doing a rotation transform because with a rotation we don't want to expand or shrink
vectors we want to keep them the same length and by the way when you're transforming a vector space
with a matrix it's not always a uniform expansion or contraction sometimes you can also get a skew
and a matrix that skews a vector space is not an orthogonal matrix because it doesn't preserve the
relative lengths and angles of the vector field you know it squishes them and so anyway that's
another reason why we want to use a special orthogonal matrix for rotations because they
don't skew the vector field oh and also if we go ahead and allow the determinant to go negative
you can see that an inversion of the vector field happens and by the way I know this looks
kind of three-dimensional but it's actually two-dimensional and it's getting squished along
one axis until it flips around and goes out on the other axis while at the same time I'm rotating it
but anyway the main thing I wanted to show you there is that an inversion can happen when the
determinant goes negative so I hope these examples of growing and shrinking and skewing and inverting
vectors gives you some sense of why we want to use special orthogonal matrices to do rotations
okay so now that we're experts on SO2 and rotations in two dimensions we'll go ahead and
pop up into the third dimension a lot of what we just talked about in 2d will transfer directly
over to 3d but of course now we're in an expanded environment so some of the concepts will be adjusted
accordingly but something I want to emphasize is that all of this special orthogonal terminology
gives us a precise way to describe what kinds of matrices we're looking for regardless of the
dimensionality of the space that we're in because all of the same intuitions apply in 3d as in 2d
about not wanting to grow the vectors or shrink or skew or invert anything and so what we're
looking for now are SO3 matrices that is special orthogonal 3x3 matrices where the same constraints
apply about the inverse being the transpose and the determinant being 1 but now there's just an
additional dimension and so the essence of special orthogonality is the essence of rotation and yes
by the way this also applies in higher dimensions but save our tears for another day so anyway
earlier we saw that given some rotation angle theta we can construct the 2d rotation matrix as
cosine negative sine sine cosine but now in three dimensions instead of just an angle for the rotation
we now have an axis angle vector like we talked about earlier and so we're faced with the question
of how do we write the SO3 matrix that goes with any particular axis angle vector this is actually
quite a difficult problem but don't worry it was solved in 1840 by Alinde Rodriguez and the
solution is called the Rodriguez formula the Rodriguez formula is just a recipe for converting
an axis angle vector into the SO3 matrix that does that rotation so you take an axis angle vector
put it into the Rodriguez formula and out pops your SO3 matrix and then you take that SO3 matrix
you just slap it onto a vector and it rotates the vector and that's how that works that's how
you rotate vectors in 3d it's pretty neat so in theory in principle according to everyone's
intuition and imagination that should be good enough if we want to represent rotating any object
you should totally be able to just list out a bunch of position vectors of points on the object
rotate all your position vectors with special orthogonal matrices and then that should be
like all you need to rotate things in math and physics like you should only ever have
special orthogonal matrices for rotations like we have it already it's good enough right this is
fine well not exactly we got to talk about SU2 SU2 I don't even know where to begin with SU2
well here how about this we'll start off by thinking about SU2 as a complex generalization
of SO2 let me clarify what I mean by that so think about an SO2 matrix as we've seen you
can write an SO2 matrix as cosine theta minus sine sine cosine or equivalently we can say that the
general form of an SO2 matrix is a negative b b a with the constraint that a squared plus b squared
equals one and you can see that this is the same thing by the substitution a is cosine of theta
and b is sine theta and when you write it in terms of a and b and a squared plus b squared equals one
you see that we have a unit circle of possible SO2 matrices okay now with that in mind let's
look at the definition of an SU2 matrix so an SU2 matrix involves complex elements we'll
symbolize them as alpha and beta and it has the form alpha negative beta conjugate beta alpha
conjugate where alpha and beta are complex numbers and the magnitude of alpha squared plus the
magnitude of beta squared equals one you can see that in the special case that alpha and beta are
real numbers then this matrix has the form of an SO2 matrix but because alpha and beta can be complex
numbers SU2 is actually a more general kind of matrix than an SO2 matrix it has more degrees of
freedom and whereas an SO2 matrix acts on real valued two component vectors an SU2 matrix being
complex naturally is going to act on complex valued two component vectors those complex valued two
component vectors are called spinners and this is one way of thinking about what a spinner is
it's the vector like thing that an SU2 matrix acts upon by the way there are ways of generalizing
the concept of spinners using other kinds of matrices but i'm not going to worry about that
today today we're just focused on two component complex spinners which are the most common kind
of spinner you'll encounter in physics okay now something you can see by exploring the properties
of these SU2 matrices is that they have determinant one and that the inverse of the matrix is the
complex conjugate transpose of the matrix so this is very very similar to a special orthogonal
matrix but technically the correct word now is special unitary matrix where unitary refers to
the fact that the inverse of the matrix is the complex conjugate transpose of the matrix and
that complex conjugation comes in because the dot product of two complex vectors involves a complex
conjugation and so in order to preserve lengths and angles between complex vectors we have to
preserve the dot product and so there's a complex conjugation that comes in in order to preserve
dot products but anyway i'm not going to go into too much detail on that just know that these are
the constraints on SU2 matrices okay so what we've looked at so far is a very algebraic definition
of SU2 and what we should look at now is the picture of what do these matrices actually do
so the way to do that is to first draw some reference spinner and this will be analogous to
the reference vector we looked at when we looked at SU2 and then we're going to multiply it by an
SU2 matrix and we're going to see how it transforms so first of all how should we even draw a two
component complex vector well there's a lot of different ways of drawing it but today i'm just
going to keep it simple we're going to look at one complex plane and then i'll put two dots in the
plane corresponding to the two components of the complex vector and i'll draw a line between them
just to highlight the point that these two dots are actually two parts of the same object there's
another way of looking at all this math in four dimensions but we're not going to get into that
today anyway so when we multiply our reference spinner by SU2 matrices we can see that it kind
of goes around and it it spins and it transforms in this rotational kind of way and so naturally
we can ask the question of what are the degrees of freedom here as we're transforming our spinner
how does it evolve and how many degrees of freedom does it have well naively it should
have four degrees of freedom right because there is two complex numbers and each complex number
has two degrees of freedom in the complex plane but we're going to take out a degree of freedom
by virtue of the fact that the su2 matrix has determinant one and is unitary and so what that
means is that this spinner is not changing in size and that means that the magnitude squared of the
first component plus the magnitude squared of the second component is always going to equal one
so we actually have three degrees of freedom here and these three degrees of freedom are isomorphic
to the hypersphere which is the locus of points in four dimensions that are all equidistant from
the origin which you can see when you think about it right you start off with four pure
degrees of freedom and then constrain them so that they have to be constant size what you
end up with is a hypersphere interestingly the hypersphere is a simply connected space that'll
be really important later but for now just think of these spinners as rotating around spinning around
in a way that is simply connected okay so here we have three degrees of freedom
and it involves some kind of spinny rotating thing so the question arises does this have any
connection to s03 that is the three-dimensional rotations maybe it will maybe it won't right i
mean if we're just thinking about it from a mathematical perspective that's a legitimate
question to ask and as it turns out shockingly there is a very very close connection between
s02 and s03 and in particular s02 double covers s03 let me explain what that means
so imagine we have s03 which acts on some three-dimensional vector and rotates it
and we also have s02 which is going to act on some two-component complex vector that we call a
spinner and it's going to transform it and kind of spin it around what the double cover means is
that we can draw a connection between any possible rotation in three dimensions and any possible
s02 transformation on these spinners in this two complex dimensional space
but the connection is not one to one it's actually two to one for every rotation in three dimensions
we have precisely two possible s02 transformations and moreover those two s02 transformations
are related to each other in that they only differ by a minus sign so you know at the beginning of
the video i mentioned that quote by michael atia where he was talking about how spinners are in
some sense the square root of geometry and you really see this in the way that s02 double covers
s03 because if you think about it what is the square root of four well it's two but it's also
negative two and what is the square root of nine well it's three but it's also negative three so
when you take the square root of something you get an answer but you actually get two answers
that differ only by a minus sign likewise if you look at any rotation in three dimensions
which corresponds to a single s03 element and you ask what is the corresponding s02 element
you get an answer but you actually get two answers that are related by a minus sign
okay now let's talk about the spinner way of rotating things so because s02
double covers s03 there's an intimate connection between every s02 transformation
and every rotation in three-dimensional space therefore if we wanted to we could mathematically
deal with rotations using the framework of s02 matrices instead of s03 but we would just have
to ignore the redundancy that comes with a double cover but that's not really a problem I mean we
can literally just ignore the redundancy right we can just project it out let me give you an
analogy so suppose that there is a math problem and you have some computer program that calculates
the answer but it's kind of slow and it takes a while to run so you run your program you wait a
moment while it calculates and then let's say you see that the answer is four well okay if you're
not in a rush that method works fine but let's say you're really in a hurry or maybe you have to do
a bunch of these calculations super fast so you look for a way to do it faster and then you discover
a faster method but the catch is that it doesn't give you the answer but instead it gives you the
square root of the answer so if the answer is four then sometimes the fast method gives you two
and sometimes it gives you negative two okay fine that's actually not a problem at all because you
can just square it and the ambiguity washes out and you've got your answer the same reasoning
applies to using su2 to do rotations because it turns out that su2 lends itself to faster
more numerically stable calculations than so3 and even though there are two possible spinners
for each so3 orientation they only differ by a minus sign which can easily be washed away
don't get me wrong so3 is pretty fast too I mean I used like a million so3 matrices while
making this video but then again I also rendered these animations overnight I wasn't in a hurry so
I just took the easier route in terms of thinking about so3 and axis angle vectors and Rodriguez
formula and that worked fine the only time I really had to use su2 for 3d rotations is when
making these colored flag animations those are actually based on su2 because I wanted it to
match the spinners anyway with animations there's not really a time constraint so you might as well
just think in terms of axis angle vectors Rodriguez formula so3 rotation matrices because it's easier
on the brain and usually there's no benefit to rotating a vector like a microsecond faster so
why torture yourself if you don't have to but if you are writing software for video game graphics
or a vision system for a self-driving car or the attitude control system for a rocket then you'll
for sure want to use su2 because in those cases you're going to have to rotate a lot of vectors
very quickly and the only cost of using su2 is that it's harder to think about when you're
writing the code because your imagination has to roll around on a hypersphere and it's kind of dizzying
but at the end of the day you'll end up with a code that's faster uses less ram and is more zen
than a code that uses so3 the numbers flow more gracefully when you use su2 su2 also lets you
avoid the problem of gimbal lock which affects so3 i don't have time to go into it today but google
Apollo 11 gimbal lock for a cautionary tale about the perils of so3 also when using su2 for
rotations in three dimensions people often use the quaternion representation because it's clean
and simple we saw earlier that there's an isomorphism between so2 and the unit complex numbers
and similarly there's an isomorphism between su2 and the unit quaternions and by the way this
isomorphism makes manifest the hyperspherical topology of su2 so anyway whenever you hear people
talking about a rotation algorithm that uses su2 or spinners or quaternions it's all the same
the basic idea is that you're doing your rotational math in this weird simply connected
hyperspherical kind of redundant group that somehow lives like kind of underneath the vector
rotations it's uh it's very bizarre but it works somehow it works and so su2 is actually used
ubiquitously in applications that demand maximum performance and so su2 is more than just some
fanciful abstraction it's actually very practical and you know it'd be one thing if it were just
practical it'd be one thing if su2 was just like a more efficient way to do rotations and you just
ignore the spinner phase fine i mean okay that's cool but that's not particularly profound but
the thing that's really a trip is that in theoretical physics the spinner phase actually
matters so su2 is not just another way of doing rotations but that redundancy that you wash out
if you're just doing like video game graphics that actually is something that's relevant to the
wave function of a relativistic electron for example and as we'll see later in the video
that is a very very deep mystery as to why that's the case okay so let's look at one more double
cover animation and then we'll talk about the physical mystery of spinners so here we have a
very very complicated rotational path and it's all like and it's all like swooping around and doing
all these moves and the point i want to illustrate here is that even when the rotational path is
super complicated there's still this connection between the flag rotating an so3 and the spinner
rotating with an su2 matrix there's still that two to one connection such that if we go around
a class one curve we end up with the phase switched then if we run that class one curve again
bring it full circle we end up doing a class two and we end up back to where we started
so let's take a closer look at this and we can see exactly how that happens okay so first it comes
in it's like shoo shoo and then look it's about to teleport right there do you see that okay cool
let's keep it going now it comes around and look we'll pause here okay now it's come back to where
it started but the phase is reversed as indicated by the fact that the flag is red and also if you
look at the plot you can see that the spinner is the negative of what we started out with
all right and continuing it's going to swoop around and it's going to teleport right now
and it's going to come back through and it'll end up back where it started so we've done two
class ones and that's a class two and that brings us back to the starting point isn't this neat I
think it's neat the thing I really want to impress upon you is that su2 double covers s03 and it's
like a perfect double cover it's like a hand in the glove or like I guess a hand in two gloves you
know so like that's really cool you know like what what does that mean right I mean the algebra I
think as you can see the algebra is formally understood I mean look at all the numbers on the
screen if you pause it at any moment in time you can check for yourself the matrices are right
and you know all the equations we've looked at that's all true it's all good but why like what
does this mean you know the funny thing is when making these videos the equations are the easy
part because an equation is just a recipe and I can put it in the computer and make an animation
and I can just tell you how it is and how it works the hard part is conveying the sense of mystery
I mean aside from the fact that it's just kind of confusing and like whoa what are these things
but how can I share with you that sense of awe and wonder that so many people have when they work
with spinners especially in the context of physics and you know that's much more of a storytelling
problem that's the objective there is to really share a state of mind or an attitude and so I
just want to tell you about it from my point of view so please take everything I'm about to say
with a grain of salt this is just my perspective but I hope it resonates with you as well
okay so you might have heard of the five stages of grief well I like to think that there's a
similar five stages that you go through when learning about spinners uh hear me out so except
it's not as bad instead of anger it's astonishment and instead of depression it's existential shock
now I don't think anyone's ever gotten to the fifth stage but I can tell you about the first four
so starting off with the denial stage if you tell someone that there's something that you have to
rotate it twice to get back to where it started they're just gonna tell you no you're wrong like
that can't be like have you ever rotated an object everyone knows all you need is to do a 360
rotation in any axis and then you get back to where you started this is like a basic fact of
reality and look I get it I mean I understand I've rotated objects too I've actually personally
rotated back in the days when I used to jump out of planes I spent a lot of time rotating
atmospherically so I'm not naive when it comes to rotations I've been around a time or two
sorry I couldn't resist the pun anyway if there's one thing that I know and you know and everyone
knows it's that a rotation of 360 degrees is all you need to get back to where you started
you don't need a 720 rotation so what is this spinner stuff it makes no sense so that's the
denial stage and what breaks you out of the denial stage is when you become really familiar with
the math so when you get to know so3 and su2 and you see that su2 double covers so3 you see that
so3 is not simply connected but su2 is and so now you have two different ways of looking at rotations
and one of them is kind of more elegant but in some sense more redundant than the other and it's
sort of like okay there's something here now when you become familiar with the math it's very
astonishing so I like to call this the astonishment phase and this is when you might be very curious
about the math and you might study it a lot more you might explore it you might write some Python
codes you might investigate every which way you can rotate these different things and you might make
pretty plots and it's very wonderful and beautiful and you find that there's a very rich structure
here that you can spend a lot of time exploring and after having done that there's no way that you
can go back to the denial stage but even still you feel the need to contextualize the math you feel
the need to say okay but what does it all mean and how literally should I take it and what are the
physical implications if any and the part of you in your heart is not going to want there to be any
physical implications I mean you want to think it's just the product of a mathematician's overactive
imagination you don't want to think there's anything in the world that actually does have
to rotate twice to get back to where it started because that's deeply unsettling and so we enter
into the bargaining stage where we say okay fine mathematically sure yeah spinners are a thing but
it's not physics this isn't real this isn't like tangible and so you can sort of argue the math
and physics and say no it's just a useful fiction it's just the structure of the equations but it
doesn't have any physical implications and the problem is that is a losing battle because the
more you learn physics the more prominent and essential spinners become you know for example
look at the Dirac equation look at the wave function of an electron it's a bi-spinner field
and it's this thing that's written in terms of spinners and it's at the heart of quantum physics
so okay but you still want to bargain some more you still want to say well our understanding of
physics is incomplete and so the Dirac equation maybe there's a way of writing it without spinners
so you look into geometric algebra and these different ways of writing the Dirac equation
and you find that nope no matter what you always have spinners or something equivalent to spinners
and so then you say okay but maybe the Dirac equation itself is wrong in some sense and then
so okay it's like what is the Dirac equation well it's three ingredients it's Lorenz invariance
it's the quantum mechanical energy momentum operators and it's the requirement that the
equations be first order in space and time now to the first one of those things no one has ever
observed a violation of Lorenz invariance and in my opinion in my lifetime probably no one ever will
now do i think that Lorenz invariance is literally true at every scale no personally i don't but
i also don't think we're ever gonna be observing any deviations from it anytime soon so if you want
to try to undermine the importance of spinners in physics by arguing against Lorenz invariance
it's not gonna work out likewise with the quantum mechanical energy momentum operators
i mean there's really not much room for flexibility here because they describe so
well pretty much like everything i mean you want to look at the black body spectrum you want to
look at like the hydrogen energy levels so you're not going to be doing away with the quantum
mechanical energy momentum operators but if you look at the third ingredient the fact that the
equations have to be first order in space and time here we do have a little bit of leeway because
with the benefit of historical hindsight we can say that dirac was a little bit misguided
in his original approach you know i think it's fair to say that he was right but perhaps for
the wrong reasons or maybe better for reasons that were not fully appreciated or understood at the
time anyway with the development of quantum field theory we now know that you can have
particles that aren't fermions and so there's no reason for us to think that the electron
must be a fermion it just so happens that they are and it just so happens that the way to write
that wave function is to say that it's a first order equation in space and time take the square
to the mashel spinners pop out you know that whole thing so it's right but it's not obvious that
it's like mathematically necessary for an electron to be a fermion aha so the way we're going to
bargain out of having to deal with spinners is to say that the electron is not actually a fermion
instead we can just choose to model it as a spinless particle right so instead of a bi-spinner
field we could just use a complex scalar field for its wave function sort of like schrodinger or
Klein-Gordon and there are kind of ways to do that if you're dealing with one electron and are okay
making an approximation but the problem is if you take that approach while you're trying to deal
with multi-electron systems like if we're doing quantum chemistry or condensed matter physics
then that approach doesn't work because we get slapped in the face with something called the
spin statistics theorem and it's such a hard slap that we get knocked out of the bargaining phase
and into the existential shock phase the spin statistics theorem deserves its own video and
actually for now i'll just say there's an excellent book written on it called poly and the spin
statistics theorem by ian duck and ecg sudarshan it's a very interesting book and i highly recommend
it if you want a good overview of the history of this theorem and its profound implications
and what is known about it and what is still not known about it but anyway for today we just have
to know what the theorem says in a nutshell it says that particles with half integer spin are
fermions and their wave function will pick up a minus sign when two particles are exchanged
and that leads into fermi dirac statistics
on the other hand particles with integer spin are bosons and their wave function will remain the
same when two particles are exchanged that leads into bows einstein statistics in short the spin
statistics theorem says that there is a direct and mysterious link between the minus sign or lack
thereof picked up by a particle under 360 degree rotation and the minus sign or lack thereof picked
up by a multi particle wave function under the exchange of any two particles this fact is going
to lead to radically different behavior depending on whether you're dealing with an ensemble of
fermions or an ensemble of bosons bosons don't mind being all up in the same quantum state at the
same time it's all good but fermions will never share the same quantum state they do not like to
be together there's a principle that every high school chemistry student learns called the poly
exclusion principle it says that no two electrons can occupy the same quantum state at the same time
this is a profound principle with far-reaching consequences it plays an absolutely fundamental
role in chemistry it's the reason for example that atoms have different orbitals that the electrons
have to stay in you know because you might wonder why isn't it that uh an atom at rest why can't
all the electrons collapse into the ground state together what is it that keeps some of them propped
up into higher energy states well it's the poly exclusion principle you know the lower orbitals
are already filled up so chemistry students take this for granted as sort of one of the axioms of
chemistry but with physics we go a bit deeper and right now we're actually logically one level
underneath the poly exclusion principle because it follows as a consequence of the more fundamental
spin statistics theorem to see this just consider a system of n electrons whose multi particle wave
function can be written as psi is a function of x1 x2 dot dot dot xa dot dot xb dot dot dot xn
where x sub n in this context refers to all the quantum numbers of the nth particle
including spatial coordinates and spin now suppose we switch electrons a and b according to the spin
statistics theorem because electrons are fermions the new wave function is just the minus sign of
the original one so psi of the original quantum numbers is going to equal negative psi of the
same quantum numbers but with the numbers for a and b switched around so all we've done so far is
basically just stated generically what the spin statistics theorem tells us about fermions but
suppose now that we force electrons a and b into the same quantum state with the power of imagination
then by the symmetry of what it means for two things to be the same we conclude that there is no
difference between the original and swapped wave function by definition there can't be if a and
b are the same state then you switch them nothing can change right because they're the same well
now here we have two apparently contradictory things when particles a and b are exchanged
the wave function both does and doesn't pick up a minus sign how can that possibly be because
we're saying that psi has to equal negative psi well that can only be the case if psi is precisely
zero and because psi is a probability amplitude we conclude that it is absolutely impossible
for two fermions to occupy the same quantum state at the same time there is zero probability of that
happening and that is the poly exclusion principle notice that this argument does not apply to bosons
with bosons there's no minus sign picked up under particle exchange and so there's no logical
tension when you put two particles in the same state switch the identical particles around all
you want it's all good and that's why the poly exclusion principle does not apply to photons
for example photons or bosons and they can share the same quantum state no problem and in fact they
often prefer to do so you can see that the spin statistics theorem is quite profound and plays a
major role in shaping the world all around us but why is it true where does this all important
principle come from well we know that the spin statistics theorem is true every moment is bursting
with an abundance of empirical evidence supporting the theorem as electron orbitals continue to exist
and photons continue to be able to occupy the same state additionally the theorem follows logically
from the assumptions of quantum field theory and it's been proven rigorously in that context
but despite all that nobody really understands in a geometric or visual way why there is this
mysterious connection between spin and particle exchange if you think you do understand it because
you've seen Feynman's topological argument or some similar intuitive proof read chapter 20 of the
spin statistics book long story short those so-called proofs are actually analogies without
any explanatory power but they are fun to think about okay fine now there is one last battle
where we try to work our way back into the bargaining phase and that is to say well maybe the spin
statistics theorem is not actually logically underneath the poly exclusion principle maybe
it's just some kind of cosmic coincidence so maybe spin doesn't play a fundamentally
consequential role in the spin statistics theorem but instead maybe it just so happens to be that
the particles in our universe that happen to be fermions happen to obey the poly exclusion principle
whereas bosons do not now this is unlikely but we're really grasping at straws here to try to
retain some semblance of our natural intuition you know we don't want to feel like the world is
much more bizarre than it seems but but it is but anyway the final nail in the coffin is to say okay
look what if we take an electron and we change its spin so that it no longer is a half integer kind
of thing but actually behaves as a boson then if that electron is set free of the poly exclusion
principle we would know that we actually are logically underneath the poly exclusion principle
right now because that experiment would give us a definitive proof that the poly exclusion
principle actually does arise from the spin statistics theorem in a really meaningful way
now it's actually not super easy to convert electrons into bosons but it can be done in
some materials because of the way electrons mutually interact with the crystal lattice
you can occasionally get a spin up electron pairing up with a spin down electron and that pair of
electrons has a net spin of zero and so the pair of electrons is collectively a bosonic entity
so in the material you can have a great many of these and they're able to condense into something
that's spiritually very similar to a boson stein condensate and they genuinely are occupying the
same state at the same time which electrons hardly ever do but when you convert them to bosons all
we're doing is modifying their spin we're not changing their charge we're not taking away any
mass or any of that we're just pairing them up so the spin cancels out and now we set them free
from the poly exclusion principle they condense into a very low energy state and can slip through a
material like a ghost without interacting with the atoms along the way and this is the phenomenon
of superconductivity and so superconductivity gives us an undeniable proof that the spin
statistics theorem is genuinely underneath the poly exclusion principle by the way we'll have a
lot more to say in the future about superconductivity it is an incredible phenomenon and you know i've
personally seen what a superconductor can do my colleagues and i have sent enormous electrical
currents through superconductors many thousands of times the intensity that would melt copper
and i've watched it stay cool as a cucumber it doesn't heat up at all because all that current
is being carried by these superelectrons that are behaving as bosons and so it's not even like
regular physics like we know and love it it's like this weird surreal like crazy version of
reality where the poly exclusion principle only you know doesn't always apply to every electron
i think it's amazing it's a wonderful thing so we'll talk about that a lot in the future we'll
get into uh ginsberg landau and flux quantization and all that good stuff but anyway today i just
bring it up to highlight that this whole spinner thing you know it's real it's mysterious and if
you take away the spinner nature of the electrons wave function you get some pretty bizarre and
surreal effects that actually are real this is not just theory this is not just socrates
philosophies and hypotheses no this is like real like technology like engineering people are building
devices with this stuff so you know so that's something to think about anyway is it possible
to reach the acceptance stage and to really understand spinners in a way that would satisfy
even michael atia maybe but we're not there yet among other things the lack of an intuitive but
rigorous proof of the spin statistics theorem shows that we don't fully understand the significance
of spinners in physical reality we're aware of spinners we're able to work with them we know
how their algebra works but we still do not know why spinner valued wave functions are anti symmetric
under particle exchange now you might be thinking rich come on now you're just dramatizing your
own ignorance this isn't actually a mystery you just don't know the answer well it's true that I
don't know the answer but i'm not the only one who thinks that this is a mystery let me share with
you this quote from the spin statistics book this quote is in a passage about whether or not physics
can explain the spin statistics theorem or is just consistent with spin statistics
we should modify the meaning of understand and at the same time reduce our expectations of any
proof of the spin statistics theorem what is proved whether truly or not whether optimally or not
in an acceptable logical sequence or not is that the existing theory is consistent with the spin
statistics relation what is not demonstrated is a reason for the spin statistics relation
to belabor the point it is difficult to imagine a fundamental mechanism for the
poly exclusion principle upon which all depends which predicates it upon the analyticity properties
of vacuum expectation values of products of quantized field operators did god for lack of a
better word build a series of failed worlds which sputtered and died or exploded and disintegrated
before discovering the stabilizing effect of anti commutation relations for half integral spin fields
was this before or after imposing the requirements of Lorenz invariance
are we the lucky winners of a Monte Carlo simulation in which every choice was tried
and one survived must we reduce our demands on physics to require only consistency
does an understanding of the why of the spin statistics relation have no direct answer in
physics or must physics be formulated to include it the poly result does not explain the spin
statistics relation and cannot the noix wanders and the Feynman's of the world
must remain unsatisfied because the consistency of relativistic quantum mechanics and quantum
field theory with the poly exclusion principle has every reason to be as complicated as these
subjects are not as simple and direct as the poly exclusion principle itself
so in short there there sure is a lot of mystery here and it's confusing but it's kind of cool
to think about right but you know honestly i can only think about spinners for so long
before it starts to hurt it's like diving underwater you try to go as deep as you can but
at some point you have to come back up for air and it's all so disorienting that sometimes
when you stop thinking about spinners it's all so confusing and you feel like you're right back
to square one but my friends if there's one thing that spinners have taught us it's that just
because you returned to where you started doesn't mean you haven't picked something up along the way
so in that spirit i'd like to reiterate part of the quote from the beginning of the video
no one fully understands spinners their algebra is formally understood
but their general significance is mysterious i hope today i've given you some sense of the
algebra but most importantly an appreciation of the mystery
if you enjoyed watching this video as much as i enjoyed making it
then please consider supporting my channel on patreon on there you'll be able to download
these beautiful magnificent pdfs with the equations and diagrams discussed in this video
and other videos too also if you sign up on patreon your input will help determine the
future direction of this channel i know what i'm going to do for the next few videos at least but
beyond that i don't know i need your advice what do you want to see where do you want to go you
want to go into electromagnetism as a gauge theory you want to go into superconductivity do you want
to go into whatever the case may be so anyway your support is not obligatory but it is greatly
and sincerely appreciated all right well hey thanks for watching and i'll see you in the next one