Welcome back from lunch. Now we will hear how quantum machine learning is changing data
and artificial intelligence is presented by Peter Morgan who will join us online and later
we can ask some questions so get ready for that.
Hello everyone, maybe you can see me at this position for the first time on this event,
a little bit virtual but we have a special occasion why we are doing like this. We are
having our distinguished keynote speaker from UK London who unfortunately wasn't being able
to join us this year in live but we are sure that Peter has a good friend of conference
and a member of our advisory board will be with us next year maybe even before the conference
in November hopefully especially if these corona measurements will let us do this much more live
events. Like I said we are going to have a keynote interview with our guest Peter Morgan
and it's going to be a kind of family interview which is going to tell us how quantum machine
learning is changing data and AI in every way, in ecosystem way, in sense of academic way,
in sense of how we are doing business. So without further ado I would like to start with the first
question and I would like maybe to give Peter a chance to present himself to our audience.
Hi thanks for inviting me Alec to speak virtually, yeah it is sad I couldn't make it
with all the restrictions it's better that we do it this way. My background is I started
off in physics, quantum physics and I was doing a PhD actually in theoretical particle physics
in the US at Massachusetts there and I left and went into industry and I basically went into
computer networking and then the last eight years I have my own consulting company in machine
learning and artificial intelligence and about four years ago quantum computing came onto my
radar screen and I realized that I could combine you know my love of physics with my IT background
so you know I haven't really looked back in the last four years in the quantum computing space
although it is very early days so I still earn money from machine learning as well.
Okay I would like to ask you one question before on the beginning of interview and on the end of
interview just to see if your answer was changed so basically that question is
quantum computing the way how we can achieve artificial general intelligence?
Yeah that's a great question it may be a part of the solution I don't think it will be the whole
solution because the reason I say that Alec is because our brains are definitely classical
you know we walk around at room temperature we exist at room temperature. Quantum phenomenon has to
be without sort of interacting with the environment whatsoever like so it needs to be usually that
means it has to be called right down so it actually may be a different type of intelligence
but it won't be like biological intelligence. This sounds very interesting okay I would like
also to go to ask you how would you explain a quantum computing for data and air audience
in terms what's the difference between regular computing and quantum computing
and maybe in what stage of quantum development we are right now?
Yeah a couple of great questions so classical computing is what we're all familiar with it's
kind of hard to explain something that's so ubiquitous right we've all grown up with it and
it's you know it's in our hands with the iPhone the Android we have laptops you know classical
computing is done using classical transistors gates and logic circuits classical logic and it
obeys the laws of classical physics and you know we've got what you know 100 billion processors
on a single sorry transistors on a single processor today so they're extremely the most
complex things that humankind is built okay so they're classical but they're extremely complex
quantum computing on the other hand uses the laws of quantum physics so they have quantum
gates they have quantum logic they have quantum yeah quantum transistors basically so these things
just behave so differently from a classical gate or a classical processor CPU GPU
you know there's no comparison at all between them they just use different laws of physics
now the way that quantum computing the reason that people are interested in quantum computing
and making a qpu for example is that the laws of quantum physics means to say we can do everything
in parallel in something called Hilbert space which is the space that quantum physics occupies it's
just the way the universe is built from the big bang outwards it came endowed with this Hilbert
space which means things can be done in parallel which gives it the incredible power and so we
haven't actually built anything that can do anything commercially useful today Alec but
we can certainly prove that they're doing quantum calculations and we're up to about 100 qubits
IBM announced a few days ago 127 qubit processor and so really we needed like millions of qubits
so we were at the very early beginning days of quantum computing which makes it quite exciting
too it's like the 1950s in classical computing that sounds very interesting so basically what
we are saying right now that quantum whatever we can end engineers researchers computers
like developers basically they are some kind of pioneers you can understand correctly is it right
yeah pioneers definitely it feels like being a pioneer right now which is a great place to be
yeah it really is yeah it must have felt like it did with in the 50s with classical computing for
sure you know you know even pre-intel and Bell Labs making the first transistor the kind of it
that that's point right now yeah it's pretty pretty interesting and exciting but again no commercial
applications just yet so business people are not getting maybe as excited about it as as the
scientists for example okay so with this being said I would like to go to maybe okay we are
talking about the new answer like qubit power that we need to utilize the full power quantum
computing with millions of qubits in what span do you think that it is realistic to have this
million of qubits yeah so we're scaling up it's on its own Moore's law the number of qubit seems
to be doubling every year so we've come from you know two to four to eight or 15 now we're at 127
so IBM and Google have actually and iNQ these quantum computing companies who are building
quantum computers have all produced roadmaps out to 2030 which shows the number of qubits doubling
every year so we are on a Moore's law there so it doesn't take it's exponential so it's not going
to take a hundred years to get to a million probably more like 10 15 years now it's not the
number of qubits isn't the only factor we need them to be not noisy and we need them to be well
connected to each other and so these engineering challenges that need to be overcome it's not
a physics thing it's more of an engineering challenge so a lot of work to do to build a
million qubits for sure but we're on the road okay maybe this being said I would like to ask you
uh we started a little bit with uh we started with the quantum computing as a whole and now
let's move to quantum machine learning what is the difference between a quantum machine learning
and regular machine learning yeah so regular machine learning maybe most of the audience
at this conference data science conference are familiar with machine learning so um basically
what quantum computing okay so that's machine learning done on classical computers CPUs GPUs
for example um ASICs etc now where quantum comes in with machine learning is you can
offload a part of that calculation almost like a co-process co-processor situation where you have
some of the calculation machine learning calculations done on the CPU or GPU and the bits that um
will be sped up using quantum are then passed over to the qpu the quantum processing and then back
again back and forth iteratively and so the whole thing won't be done on a qpu it'll be a
co-processor situation so it will be like a classical quantum hybrid so we'll always need
classical computing for machine learning so basically what you're saying and that will be
the second question but first if I understand correctly and it correct me if I'm wrong uh
when we are talking about quantum machine learning we are not talking about classical
turns only quantum machine learning we are talking about the hybrid between uh machine
learning or AI and quantum machine learning yes absolutely alec yeah maybe one day in the far
far distant future everything will be quantum like you sort of need to load quantum data we
haven't got quantum memory yet that seems like a long long way out so basically for this foreseeable
future next 10 to 20 years it will be a classical quantum hybrid system this is this is this is as
excellent question and this is something that that maybe we can uh can be we can uh maybe it's a
cool thing to say so basically uh what is the role of quantum machine learning engineer and
quantum machine learning researcher is there any kind of difference in these roles or they are still
the same but yeah that this yeah that's a good question because really it's fundamentally comes
back to where we are in the quantum computing development um life cycle and because we're at
very early stage um a lot of it is quantum computing research uh at the moment and engineering
a little bit so kind of like a 90-10 percent split we can see that as we progress and build
more powerful processors say with a thousand qubits and start putting them um well they're on the
cloud now but actually they'll be be able to be used for very small commercial applications
we'll need a lot more engineers at that point Alex so that will be to actually um build the
commercial applications that's the point we'll need more engineering okay this is this is this
sounds very interesting so basically just to to to let's say before we go to the the the next
question is so basically right now we are all researchers some of our are in uh developers
but what we'll need like very very fast is somebody who's going to be engineer if I understand
correctly yeah it will ramp up quite quickly again it's on that exponential curve at the very
beginning yes okay we've been saying that can you give us some examples of where quantum machine
learning is already applied is there any kind of right right yeah that's a great no not yet not in
commercial applications so all of this is kind of test um in in uh you know companies it's not just
in the lab and university labs it's in quantum uh it's in companies who are wanting to become
quantum ready like uh big investment banks uh big pharma companies material science companies
we're talking we're thinking um black so smith Klein Bosch um you know goldman sacks these have
all got quantum computing departments with 20 or so researchers and engineers and developers
working on these algorithms today whether that's machine learning optimization you know pharma
material science simulation so yeah quantum machine learning is a part of the whole picture
but there are other elements too like simulation and optimization as well as machine learning
but so like I say there are companies hiring but I think at this point you know you sort of need
a phd in you know quantum science or quantum information um it's it's a little too early for
them to be employing just just a developer with no quantum knowledge so we have time to skill up
okay and one let's say one personal question for you in which uh industry you would like to
be part of quantum machine learning project yeah so I'm focusing that is most let's say
compelling to you to try quantum machine learning you personally yeah yeah personally I'm
focusing focused on the simulation aspect so that's material science um semiconductors photovoltaic
cells so you know um directly addressing climate change with uh you know also battery physics um
so yeah I mean it's it's it's um a huge very ambitious sort of project and we're just starting
but uh once these quantum computers become bigger we'll be able to simulate battery physics we
able to simulate semiconductors and a lot of photovoltaic cells are made out of semiconductors
for example uh as well as something called perovskite basically it's simulating nature at the um
molecular level um which was Feynman said in 1981 we can simulate physics with a quantum computer
and by golly uh it it looks like a great problem because it doesn't look so easy and 40 years later
where we're just at the very beginning of doing that so it is exciting this sounds very interesting
and basically what is this this important thing to uh to understand not only for data and AI uh
experts and uh leaders but also for software engineers and IT industry as whole because
in the end there you can we can talk about okay we will just add uh unbelievable number of I didn't
know uh computer computational power but in the end computational like hard disks uh processor
they have limitation of physical world without developing further quantum realm and development
in the quantum realm whatever we can we can follow like this we are we are we are we are bounded by
the limitation right now like I don't know if you heard about that this project they are trying to
to to to close a bigger close of the gap between uh between the two two semiconductors but the
basic and the chips because it's very hard not to have like electricity when it's closer to some
kind of nanometers but like I said yeah it can be done but so like I said yeah limited in one part
no that's right so classical computers um we we have to make so many approximations when we try to
model a semiconductor or any kind of battery physics or any physics at the any kind of
molecular dynamics including drugs drug discovery molecular docking um so many approximate because
basically we're solving the Schrodinger equation many body Schrodinger equation for all of these
systems which are quantum systems and we cannot do that directly on a classical computer we we're
using approximations so we're so limited so in that respect if quantum and if and when
quantum computers come along we can simulate these systems directly um it'll be no contest um it'll
be amazing progress will be amazing and fast and swift and meaningful and impactful we're talking
drug discovery solar panels batteries a lot of problems are just waiting a lot of low hanging
fruit we're just waiting on the hardware only that that's the only like yeah the most expensive
parties all the time yeah yeah what we we are like uh we are we are low on okay yeah uh what
i would like to also ask is the one part this is the future with quantum like because uh what
i what i'm like personally and what we are seeing like as a as a society that uh we are witnessing
that ai is basically changed the very fabric of our society on every level and people cannot
realize because it's day to day but when you make comparison like five years ago and now
basically we made a progress that is unmatchable it's not only like because of the covid crisis
we needed to adopt the digitalization etc but because you have adopted analytics
data science and ai so the fair question would be what changes to the society's quantum bringing
yeah though i mean i've worked in the machine learning area you know i haven't i saw my day
job as is a is a machine learning and i've totally agree with you about the exponential increase in
you know processing power and and data and you know just just algorithmic advancement and it's
been astonishing if we see a similar type of um progress in quantum computing we can we can expect
to see um as impactful if not more impactful um advancements to society for sure um i mentioned
you know uh attacking the climate change problem through material science if we can model all
these materials and build more efficient materials that's huge if we get a 10 percent gain even 100
percent gain in efficiency in a solar panel i mean that that's a trillion dollar industry no doubt
about it um yeah maybe more same with batteries with electric cars yeah i mean another trillion
dollar industry um semiconductors you know another trillion dollar industry i mean it's just
basically what you're saying is that that's all i need to develop quantum computers so they can be
yeah yeah we're definitely waiting on the hardware alec but there are there are several
kind of thrusts there's iron traps there's superconducting there's photonics there's um
cold atoms and there's topological so we don't really know who's going to win in the end with
the hardware i mean microsoft is working on topological google are doing an ibm are doing
superconducting um i and q and honeywell are doing iron traps um so again that's quite exciting to
to wonder and you know who nobody knows who the eventual winner will be maybe there'll be a few
winners um different applications for different types of hardware um but it's just going to take
a little bit of time alec we just have to be a little bit patient okay but also i would like to
to come back closer to my question so basically uh once again uh what do you think like for the
like like a regular regular person how much uh dear or her or his uh life will be impacted by
the quantum technology like five or ten years from now what is your expectation basically from the
from the point of one single person yeah i would say in ten years we're going to start to see a lot
five years will still be a little bit r and d phase these things will live in the cloud we won't
have them in our hands like you know the phone so they'll be at a distance so it'll be more
in the background we'll notice solar panels solar cells solar electricity becoming more
prominent and efficient and cheaper so perhaps the average person like you and i will notice
the cost of electricity coming down uh a speed up in process of power um you know better batteries
in our electric cars when everybody's buying them because it is policy now isn't it with the climate
change um conference the other week um you know governments are getting serious about moving to
all electric cars and moving to solar energy so that's i think where the average person will notice
it more possibly in drug discovery but we're looking ten years out i don't want to get anybody's hopes
up this is going to happen next year yeah it's going to be a little way away i know that and we
had a keynote the other day before and it's about uh yeah we are going to find heat the
his talk was basically uh that they already have implemented in modeling like together hybrid model
together with the AI of quantum machine learning some banking so like i said i think that some of
the things will be will be but like you said the full power of it like so the the regular person
uh can can see that that that's like i totally be five or ten years i would like to be five years
but you're the expert in these sizes this matters so i need to to to believe in your word that it's
going to take ten years but still it's going to be uh not only uh people need to have said it's not
going to be ten ten years like just if you not do anything there is a lot of the road ahead of us
so basically my question is our company is ready basically to embrace the quantum machine learning
in day-to-day operation and if yes or not what is needed to get into quantum and have for example
five years from now quantum machine learning departments yeah well i encourage people if
they're interested in moving into this field um maybe they're data scientists today software
developers machine learning engineers to start learning about quantum physics if you're very young
you know going to university doing an undergraduate or even a graduate uh degree um you know physics
isn't isn't a bad option today you know um before it was computer science machine learning today
there's going to be because it's quantum computing there'll still be a computing computer science
element software engineering element but there's going to be a little bit of physics as well
so it's a little bit of a hybrid and it's unclear whether people are going to really be able to
join the two together in a single person um maybe we'll just you know it's it's tough because normally
people love physics or they love computer science and there's a little bit of a there's not a whole
bunch of crossover quantum physics is quantum physics software engineering isn't quantum physics so
you know can a software engineer or do they even want to become a physicist does a physicist
want to become a computer scientist it's it's a little bit you know we're going to have to
wait to see how this plays out but education is key alec okay and being said that uh how do you see
a cooperation between academia and the business sector in the quantum field because it seems that
like uh big tech uh companies uh and there are indeed departments at a bit in front of academic
circles uh this can say to be a true statement and what are your thoughts on this subject do you
think that it's enough or it need to be better if so how it can be better yeah well i've already
seen we're already starting to see companies like google and amazon and microsoft hiring away from
university so it's a little bit uh concerning in a way but we did see the same thing happening with
machine learning um all of the big companies like google just hired everybody from university and and
you know it it saves sort of i've noticed they've sort of gone back to university part time so but
initially there'll be this huge brain drain i think from university because it's very limited
there's a few professors a couple of postdocs um and you know they need it we need a lot more
phds and you know quantum engineering and quantum computing um these these degrees didn't exist five
years ago so you know we're at the very beginning um and so we i am seeing if you go to amazon uh
website and look at quantum computing careers you will see you know they're looking for postdoc
level people today they can't hire enough same as google same as ibm they just simply cannot get
enough people with the right skill set this is interesting what what just for our audience
that can get a bit better of you what what the amount of people we are talking right now
to have like what what the amount of people do you think that one amazon one google need to have
like just to make it with what they would like to have as a progress in the quantum field right
well i think ibm is a little further ahead they probably have the biggest conan uh engineering
team um but i noticed uh google and amazon have about a hundred people now between 100 and 200
they've scaled up in the last two or three years yeah to 100 200 they probably want to double that
over the next two or three years as well and eventually end up with about a thousand plus
so we need it'll ramp up exponentially so the number of people required will probably always
lag the demand um as we go forward because it does take three or four years to train somebody
you know to become a good machine learning engineer a good quantum computing guy
or girl i mean it does take four or five years it doesn't happen overnight so
there's going to be a little bit of a ramp up yeah and basically uh what and this is like
one of the questions i want to ask this because uh i want to just to share with our audience that
basically what we are saying that right now in the world there is just a couple of hundred maybe
a couple of thousand at most like i think it's too much to say a couple of thousand of people who
are doing the for doing machine learning it's not that much yeah but no no no maybe the whole
quantum computing what would be a couple of thousand but quantum machine learning maybe 200 yeah yeah
yeah that's right and uh basically what what can be a good thing like basically if you're thinking
about uh about doing quantum it's not that easy like to switch to quantum because you need to
understand quantum mechanics on the first yeah it is somebody who studied that i can i can tell you
people if you if you saw Brilliant Minds and you didn't or some film about Einstein you didn't
understand the the something that's written on the backboard that's really true what is written
and that's quantum mechanics most probably but what would be your advice to someone who would like
to start the quantum career in terms of like students and in terms of somebody who'd like to
get the pre-qualification or yeah maybe this advice yeah well i think we're seeing physicists
already become computational physicists and in the classical sense so they'll just be able to become
quantum computing at the end of the day quantum computing will be just another type of computer
in the cloud co-located in the data center along with the classical computers maybe there'll be
neuromorphic computing as well it's just another form of computing and it's only for a very specific
type of problem it's not won't solve every problem websites will still run on classical
computers so to train to get there you you sort of there's two ways of getting there one is to
start with the physics background and move into quantum and move into computer science the other
is to start with the computer science background and learn the quantum and you know that might be a
little harder i think than a physicist to learn computer i i'm thinking because it's just a very
specific skill set is you know it's just i mean i did physics and i know it's not for everybody
it's a lot of math okay there's a lot of math yeah that's like that that's a good output that that's
what i'm talking about there's a lot of people in the science field for doing very good because they
understand they are they are mathematical uh basically aperture before this to talk about
math it's very very hard it's very very on some other level but uh okay my last question before
we go to your final remark is what would be uh the first problem you would like to see solve
with quantum machine learning oh man the first problem yeah i was going one computing yeah if
it's kind of computing i'd say i want to simulate materials and you know build better solar cells
and better semiconductor and better batteries if it's quantum machine learning i think like
i said earlier it's always going to be a hybrid classical quantum situation so it can be used
for simulating material science it can be sim it can be used for optimization problems it can be
used for um you know anything that machine learning classical machine learning which is
basically good at you know pattern recognition and it will accelerate that process so i mean it's
it's almost any any field you can think of that machine learning is already used in so you know
you can work in a bank optimization of optimizing portfolios you can work in a transport company
optimizing traffic routes with quantum machine learning you know you can um yeah maybe in medicine
you know alpha fold the deep mind protein folding i would love to see them using quantum
computing to speed that up as well as it as with everybody so any machine learning problem can be
you know given a little boost with these quantum computers from my point of view what i would like
to see is to try uh quantum machine learning and what you'll get in combination with quantum
computing it's in relation of black holes for example yeah that'd be great that'd be amazing
i think that there's something that we can learn a lot of it from from the very fabric of the universe
and maybe get from that question we can move on to to the maybe the the the ultimate question of
them all are we alone in this universe maybe yeah yeah that can be a second thing like
doing after that like i don't know i'm i'm i'm coming back to the roots of my astrophysics
so yeah no a lot of people would like that i mean you might not even we might need even
not even the machine learning there i mean um quantum computers are just um perfectly made to
simulate black holes and the big bang because those are 100 quantum systems yeah so so you
you're you're you're so spot on there that yeah black holes will be a early application when we
make them for sure yeah i was still i think that we need like 10 years but still in 10 yeah we can
simulate black hole people you cannot understand what we can learn from that that's that's something
that that i think it will change not very fabric of our society very fabric of how we are
receiving life like basically and that that's something that it will it will it'll have an
enormous change like on everything but okay that's 10 years from now what i would like to ask you
right now would you like to say anything else to our audience right now as a closing remarks before
we can start with the q and a yeah sure um no not really but if you're interested in quantum
computing don't be put off by the physics just just you know there's a lot of computer science
in there as well a lot of algorithmic theory i mean there's so many different branches uh
in within quantum computing umbrella there's machine learning there's algorithmic complexity
theory there's information theory there's software there's hardware you know there's control systems
so this is a place for everybody so just dive in but i would say to people you know don't be
don't be put off by the quantum physics but there's a lot of work to be done okay Peter thank you so
much for this lovely chat it's all it's always very very pleasant to talk with you and right now
what we are going to do we are going to start with q and a and Peter will join us live to answer
your question hopefully there are going to be a lot of questions okay sure thanks Alec nice to nice
to speak to you again hello everyone hello Peter so you can see me now live okay so basically the
first thing is do we have any question from the audience don't be shy you can raise your hand
there is yes no okay there's two okay let's go here i'll be the one
hi nice to see you again at this conference and shame that you couldn't come to do a live presentation
even so it was great still one of the thing i would like to ask for for somebody who is
devoted to education is how to popularize physics to young generations
yeah that's a good question so i've been doing a little bit of work on this
for various companies it is all about the education at this point because you know there's
this kind of massive ramp up going to be occurring over the next two years a little bit like we saw
with machine learning right so you know a lot of professors leaving academia to be
going to industry we're already seeing that was quantum computing you know physics departments
becoming a little bit depleted already but so but in terms of educating younger folk or people who
want to you know move into this area there are a lot there are actually companies now
creating courses so you don't have to go back to university just like with data science you know
you can do online courses or three month boot camps they're starting to happen IBM have got some
good training material on their website if you just google IBM quiz kit or IBM quantum
and similarly with Microsoft so we're starting to see some of these educational materials appear
online so i would just you know start googling and over the next couple of years we'll see more and
more of this online information and also we'll see universities starting to offer undergraduate
degrees and quantum information science and quantum quantum engineering which are degrees
that don't actually exist at the moment so yeah you know people are addressing it it'll be a little
bit of a slow ramp up over the next few years thank you Peter just another question are you also a
bit afraid that humankind might misuse quantum computing yeah maybe there's always a safety
aspect in any technology right any new technology you know nuclear weapons and you know machine
learning you know AI taking over the world and now rightly so people are considering what could
possibly go wrong with quantum so it's a good question to think about don't stay away too late
at night thinking about it i think you know like any technology it can be used for good or bad right
it does have national strategic importance though so you know governments are probably
doing stuff behind closed doors that will never see the light of day really to be honest
but most of the research has been done at universities and big companies and even startups
nowadays and so you know the hope is you know people will use AI for good good things and
same as similarly with quantum computing we'll be using it to simulate new materials and and
drug discovery you know helping us with quantum machine learning optimization problems and so
those are all good things for humanity but yeah there'll be an arms race you know China Russia
the usual suspects in the west you know it's uh we can't seem to get over that so we can expect
that i mean in some ways it's healthy competition in other ways it's kind of annoying because you
know people start worrying about how you know bad actors are going to use it so you know it's one
of these perennial problems that will never go away we'll never get rid of so we just have to
you know treat it with the respect that it deserves maybe some regulations and legislation
will see happening and but at the end of the day you know there's only so much we can do to limit
bad actors okay do we have any additional question okay i have one question for you it's going to
are you going to put you on the spot here on the light uh so basically Peter who will you
help us to bring at this stage live next year as a quantum keynote speaker i'm sure Alex i'd love
to come back uh to val braid yeah i mean i really enjoyed it last year so sure you and who who
else from which company google or something like that yeah i mean we'll try and get everybody from
the big guys and the startups as well who don't really super interesting stuff so you know the
usual suspects would be google microsoft and ibm and even amazon have a quantum computing
research department now so they're actually making hardware not just putting other companies
can quantum computers on the cloud which you can go and log into now it's called amazon bracket
b r a k e t and you can log into about three different vendors today if you wanted to so we
could get them along so that's four and then we could get maybe four startups okay thanks a lot
okay basically uh if you don't have any additional questions i would like peter once again to thank
you like tatina said i'm looking forward to see you again here in belgium live when the corona
hopefully next year will be it will give us a little bit of slack uh we are moving forward with
the program i think that we are having like a small break or something like that but i will let
zonan he know better than me it's okay people like to watch you uh we have like five minutes
before we uh are joined by simon boyden who is going to follow with his presentation it's going
to be a very interesting one about about wimbledon tennis championship so be sure to be here in five
minutes because we are starting a sharp time because he's joining us virtually thank you