I already told Michael this is a little bit improvised. I was supposed to give this last
week but then I was also I could be paid and in the meantime I have done a bit of hope but
still not as much as I would have liked to do but I think it will be interesting.
So what I'm trying to do here is for the first time to do a research but
I've been busy with one on the origin of goldite, one on the origin of human consciousness.
So what the two projects have in common is that they're both about agency which is a topic I think
that in your lawyer you also have been thinking about. So agency first of all means it's gold
that are moving to the goal in order that they need to be able to mess up the conditions in
which they should be able to make the right actions. That is the main theme but then I want to go to
a higher level of agency the human consciousness where you're not only acting reflexively but
you are able to choose between different different causes of action and that will allow me to put a
first attempt tackling the psychological heart problem of consciousness. So that's briefly what
I want to go out on. So let's start the first part which is about a goal directedness or
actually about a life. So all living systems are there because they have survived natural selection
means they have been selected to be fit and to be fit that means that they should be able to
survive and go. If they are not capable to achieve that goal of surviving and going well they simply
simply are elated. So we can assume all living systems have this imbalal of survival and survival
survival they can maintain their metabolism is of perturbed patients because the world is not
always the same. So this I will summarize as agency living systems have the implicit role of
wanting to survive and to maintain themselves in order to do that they need to that means they need
to be able to support opportunities of surpassing perturbed patients and in order to act they need
to have some kind of implicit cognition namely they need to know what action is appropriate for
what perturbed patients. So that's the basic framework let's now go into more detail about
how that could have evolved. So the best definition of living systems that I know is the
famous one of Maturana eila autopoiesis. Autopoiesis means the existing is self-proloding it forms
it's a network of processes that reconstitutes all and Maturana and Varela automatically
connect this notion of cognition to their notion of autopoiesis because each system should be able
to produce itself it should also be able to withstand any perturbations that may push it to
want the self-maintenance so it needs to have this cognition. The theory of autopoiesis Maturana eila
is I would say very difficult abstract sometimes confusing so I have tried to make a simpler
version of it that is a version where that is based on a network of processes where processes
then can be defined formally. Autopoietic system network of processes is something that some input
transforms that input into some output so it produces new components it consumes other components
or it transforms certain components into other components and then the definition of autopoiesis
is that the components being produced by these processes are such that they never generate the
same processes that started them so they very simply put the processes on the poetic system
system produce components while the components produce the person the whole thing is self-generating
self-producing. So to make that clear I start from what I call a process on poetry that means
I do not at assume that universe is constituted of objects where objects are inert materials
which ultimately people tend to tend to see as particles. I see the universe consisting out of
process and a process is something that we can describe formally as action a reaction meaning
you have some input things some they react with each other and you get an output and then a system
such as an poetic system then becomes appellate network of processes so instead of start on
stable elements of I assume it's stability is the result of process that somehow some are debiliters
so what are reactions a reaction is kind of like the minimal element of my apology
a reaction assumes that there are conditions which are distinguishable states of it's over there
condition can be the presence of particular molecule of part of biological species but also
be something much much more a social condition of worlds or over this anything that can be
distinguished from its absence is a condition and then processes represented by arrows could be
for example that a distinguishable condition appears a is formed and this variable condition
disappears a condition is transformed into a different condition and some some combinations
decisions react react to form a combination of conditions so this is very similar to the world
to the one you think they are in element elementary partition but the ABCDs that are right here they
can be any distinguishable conditions so it wasn't an elementary a poetic system it's a system that
produce itself but of course it must be term thermodynamically open that means it must have
input from outside and there will be some some dissipation with some waste so in this case I
need to have need to have some in a of a some outlay of b and then a and a and being themselves
now that's of course much too simple to have a living system so let's look at it and somewhat
more complicated example complicated example in the sense that I have still an input I still have
still still have an input in between I have a net of reaction that's that's much more complicated
but that but that is such that every everything every every component we condition the the base
the cities there is always always some produces it but in appears in disappears nothing nothing
enough nothing everything is produced by some reaction and the whole reaction thing is keeping
itself going so so uh for those who are interested describe a mathematical model
all the chemical organization is something called chemical chemical organizing theory in which
which you can at the conditions and a network of reactions becomes also auto poetic meaning
meaning self meaning and closed closed that whatever is consumed is produced whatever is produced is
consumed so now uh where does auto is come from that's kind of the assumption of my ontology
that is that process self of organize into more more complicated organizations since
so how I have that that in the simplest I start with a random reaction sections random content
means any any a plus b c plus d's we have we have payments with that we have just generated
random that random network sign then we have seen what's seen what happens is typically
that itself organizes into the kind of auto poetic how does that happen to start with
number of components that are available components of our conditions have the reactions
the reactors form the components into components which come themselves out as something something
the new components are on when you see you start with a number of components components you produce
you add you add the new one up to the point that you point that you can alone do once because
there is no material available to available to add anything there yet on the other hand some of
the some of the kind of consumed but they are not produced or not produced enough to keep the whole
thing going so you remove them in the end what are you left with with components that are being
produced that are being consumed but such that that they are they are being consumed and consumed
at the same time so this is a follow-up that I'm going to schedule quickly for this institute you
can look at look at my papers the chemical organization the apoyosis is what is that a
self-maintenance of reactors is an attractor of the dynamics that means that if you let the dynamics
hold on its own eventually you will get something that resembles an autopoietic system or in most
cases that the apopoietic system will trivial but in principle you can generate an apoyotic system
like that to self-organization now what one thing to get to is that the apopoietic system should
not maintain itself in real circumstances that mean ideal circumstances where all the input
components are not there but in the presence of an environment where things are not always
available sometimes there are conditions that are interfering with your reactions sometimes the
conditions you need for your reactions are not there so I've said that the apoyotic regime is
an attractor but there will be the patients that will be pushing the system out of its
attractor so if we think about the apopoietic system as a kind of a very primitive organism that
organ lacks food so even at the moment there's not enough impotence it will die on the other
hands it it may die because of toxin that means components that interfere with the reactions
that are necessary to the whole thing align so first stage is the system of organisms into
something self-maintaining second age that self-maintaining system being thrown around by
perturbants most most of them are killed by perturbations but eventually we may assume
evolution will lead to another system that's resilient resilient that means that it is able
to bounce back from these perturbations that there are all kinds of changes happening in the
environment it can somehow compensate for these perturbations that means for example
some some components of you that's previously worked as toxins that means they are perturbing
the metabolism your version apopoietic system the more resilient and will have some way to
neutralize these toxins since if for example the food is not available maybe it will have developed
some internal reactions to digest a different type of food so i'm assuming that if the process of
evolution goes on long enough the system will become more and more and more resilient we have
done a number of simulations with these networks and indeed you see that if you give it enough time
the time it tends to become more resilient so so what does it mean resilient in terms of
dynamic systems it means that the auto system is an attracter it's basic basic of attack means
all all the options that lead to the attracter become exciting will become wider it will have
a wider range of viability so let's imagine this the dark green that you see is the attracter that
means that is the autopoietic regime which the system tries to turn the light is the base that
means all of the different regulations from which the autopoietic system can back to its
its regime of sitenance a partition then means means any unregulated change that makes the system
move from one position to another as long as the perturbations remain inside the basin they
will automatically be compensated because as long as the system is in the basin it will on its own
go to the reactor if on the other hand perturbation can push the system outside of the basin then it
will no longer go with the attracter which means that basically the autopoietic system
longer autopoietic that cannot maintain itself what could potentially potentially happen is
also a different attracter attracter potentially could be could be even better let's not discuss that here
so that allows me now to define directness as resilient autopoiesis
autopoiesis is the attracter as autopoiesis this means if you perturb it from the attracter if
you put it out of the attracter it will come back it has a one basin and basin is is a growing
process of self-made so it's not an equilibrium like a thermo system versus thermo thermodynamic
equilibrium that is not a living system a living system is a process that is actively
self-maintaining that is consuming and producing so operation what does that mean a goal-directed
system if it's not in goal it will move towards the goal if it's in the goal it will stay in goal
if it perturbed it means if it's pushed off its goal it will it will perform
action that requires energy so as so as to return to that so that we might kind of a
minimal thing of goldness in living living systems a basic basic form of aid
now we come to the issue of cognition so goal-directed activity we can say requires
a minimal form of cognition because it needs to be able to compensate the deviations from the rule
so if we look from the inside autopoietic system it undergoes a deviation it should it should somehow
do something that there is that there is a deviation that that means it needs some ability
ability of person of something thing and it should also have an ability to perform an action that
means one of its repertoire of reactions should switch on so as to neutralize the deviation
and implicit in this whole dynamic is the notion of knowledge namely action that still gets
by the sun's condition should be appropriate for that to that condition so the sun should
somehow know which action to perform for which condition and that now model model with additional
format is used in AI action rules so function rules you have an agent the agent has a number of
condition action rules that means it recognizes a certain condition for example it
senses that is condition X and it knows if I'm in condition X then I should perform action Y
and we can help with that simply as a process X to Y that process in one of the processes inside
this complex network processes that in a poetic system system
now cognition are lots of definitions of cognition and we need to be
to be careful about what we mean by cognition so one of the more interesting results from
cyber ethics is so-called the law of regulatory models proposed by Conant and Ashby and it says
if you want to have a directed system standard girl direct system must include some mapping
which they call a model namely it should map all the potential deviation perturbations
the right action that means for deviation there should one specific action that mapping exists
then the system is able to control to reach girl and that's model we might say implement the
systems like now model is a common term when thinking about evolution the system has a model
of its environment but that is not the way the way that Maturana Varela interpreted
Ryan and Varela and size it what Conant and Ashby call it is not a representation of the
environment what they say is the is the audit system is autonomous it functions functions
it does not know what is going on in the external world the only thing that we can know is
the deviations its senses it has a metabolism it has a network processes when one of its processes
is functioning the way it should be the whole whole poetic system is perturbances that
there is something wrong but it does not know what lost the deviation so Maturana Varela
emphasized that this kind of knowledge is subjective the auto poetic system knows only
the things that affect its own auto poetic auto poetic it does not represent the environment
in some objective way so now we become to the further evolution so we only have a system that
is almost that is girl like that has some level of cognitive but but he can think this cognition
mission should accept the system be able to adapt adapt these conditions and and lots of
if there is a lot of variation in the environment the conditions will change so that means the
system should be able to sense emotions should be able to interpret the conditions it should be
able to make sense of the conditions that its senses so it requires that it has some elementary
awareness not not really of what objectively going on in the environment but
in what in what way are changing in the environment so that it affects itself so
so we let let evolution its role the system will need to become more aware more and more and more
in so that it can recognize a wider range of of conditions and can interpret them and perform
the right types of actions so so now this is a scheme that you probably seen which I borrow from
Michael he called the cognitive viability I have only the cone of OS so if an agent that is
situated somewhere in the middle of that of that cone agent will to some extent be aware of
what is going on in its environment from this purely specific point of view but still it will
to some degree be aware of conditions in the past in the future in the neighborhood so the cone
kind of kind of represents the range of awareness the kind of kind of range of the system the
potential makes sense the more advanced the system the wider the cone so here is another picture
that I took from Michael here are some examples of cones a very small creature like a pig will have
a very small cone a human can have a very big cone and a dog can have something in between
but now I come I make a very very big jump I started by it by explaining how the boy has
this this which is the organization of a single like a big theorem and now I'm making a jump
in human consciousness so let's forget about all the stages model the cellularity animals
nervous systems etc but what is the essence of the different between the cognition of a
vacuum and the cognition of human or in bacteria the way I use the con the the cognition is
deterministic the the being sense is a part is a particular con performs a part of a particular
always the same condition leads to same action now we're speaking about higher organisms organisms
and we humans are there but probably others probably apes talking sense other mammals and
maybe both are also there but there is an intermediate decision making stage that means
there is a condition that the organism senses and then there is a state here I have called reflection
of considering different of all ways of reacting to that condition condition means that the action
follows so a part of reflection action and actually there is no action I I make some of
the conditionation in women I can decide I need to act in this way or I can decide there is no
action words taking so this is what's called free will we humans have the ability to consider
many different forces and to choose one of them and that is typically what we will
will call conscious ability of considering different possibilities
now define it's easiest to distinguish conscious or subconsciousness so we humans
still have the same level of subconscious reactions like bacteria and like simple organism we have
this kind of automatic involuntary reflex for example if I put my hand on a hot so I will
pull it away immediately I don't need to think about what this is hot if my hand on it on it
then it will burn therefore I should pull it pull away my I will just pull away my way my
and I may not feel the heat of the of the stuff so that process implemented in the brain it's
modeled as what is not a speed forward process it's a process that goes straight from
sense condition to action they stay immediate way there are no details now what's the difference
with with the conscious process a conscious process is a process that we can monitor we can in
our mind minds we know what we are thinking we can I mean our thoughts also redirect our
for example I may distract this and tell myself no you should be busy with that you should be
doing that so conscious processes are processes I define as processes in the mind that can be
monitored that can be examined and that can be redirected of all the different different
many different theories of consciousness though that I like the most the one that I think
explained this is also was was complete is so-called global neural space theory
theory and the most active active research is stony stony slas and what the global
neural workspace analysis is that it is some kind of a special network the workspace which
functions a bit like a kind of a forum or a meeting space where lots of different
process is coming from and part of the building come together and the process in that workspace
they are all what all circulate the other term other people people call it really
or recurrence resonance but the main idea is it's a process a forward process that means
a process that goes in one direction it's a process that that cycles around and what is the
reason for the cycling problem with activation of neurons in the brain is that activation
passed on new neurons do remain activated so you want to keep some keep some new working memory
you need to recreate the activation and you can and you can only by having the active activation
come back to the space and then that's for me now the essence of what creates the consciousness
by keeping this total of this perception active in your memory you can inspect this
and if you can inspect it that means other parts of the brain can look at this other
other part of the brain intervening and is now what will create a free so I will
it's best explained with owing so this is the scheme for the conscious processing the feet forward
propagation so what you have is just a line the sensors some some condition there are a number
of immediate new neural modules that process information for example if I see something
there are different layers in my visual cortex that will first recognize light and dark and then
recognize edges and then they will recognize shapes and then they recognize objects it leads
a particular conclusion in the example I gave the of the hand on a hot stove
here probably it may not even reach the brain it may just go to the spinal cord but
the sensors send a signal that that eventually be pulled away by hands it just a fourth process
so now of course processing that is what I call all circuiting active activation we have the
sensors here on the bottom left left the sun provide input input the effect effectors my muscles
are put on the system but before it reaches the effectors the activation circulates in what
called the global workspace which is some kind of a a suit to be a network of on-range connections
in the cortex and then you have the diff modules which are specialized circuits that for example
recognize sounds or look openings or or make equations or or fractions the the most can be
very diverse very specialist but these models now interact with what's going on in the workspace
that means that what happens in the workspace the activation that's circulating can go to a
to one of the modules which the module doesn't do anything with it on the other hand it can go to
a module module reacts so it's an interaction action or there can be a module that receives
infusion from a different part of the brain and that some some input in our workspace space so
our workspace is seen as a kind of a form a kind of a public or all these specialized
best circuits and they're in a kind of a discussion it's as if they are talking together in this
global workspace space so here here there are some examples of from the of the where they are
doing experiments with all these and you can give them here so-called sub-subliminals that
means something that I think that a visual stimulus and disappears so quickly quickly that
the monkey doesn't have the unconscious of it of it and you see this kind of a field of field
activity that means that for the input the the the the neurons get directly activated and they pass
their output to another of neurons but it moves basically in one direction on the other hand if
you leave the stimulus for a long enough time that the monkey becomes conscious of it now that's
what they call reverberation what I call circulation now you see that the different created neurons
the sensation back and forth everything is keeping itself self-indulgent
that is a standard model of consciousness or what is called access consciousness the
consciousness in the sense that you have access to what's going on in your mind you have the ability
to examine to monitor to read whatever is going on in your mind but now there is another aspect
of consciousness that is subjective experience and associated with this with this whole
problem of consciousness what is a subjective experience it is feeling that that is something
that you are conscious and that subjective experience I personally prefer the term
subjective experience but some other terms you may have heard are qualia acqua is an individual
subjective experience it's also called phenomenal consciousness and a most common phase define what
what a qualia or a subjective subjective experience that what is it like like to for example what what
is it to see see hurt now typically typical example loss of his health healthness is subjective
experiences is something else as an input but you have the subjective experience of healthness
so the heart problem of consciousness is what precisely are these subjective experience
why do we have these subjective experiences and the famous uh thought experiment that kind of
hind the whole heart heart problem of conscious was uh discussed by the philosopher david
charmer it's the zombie thought experiment so so what he does david david charmers he thinks that
there are certain speech he calls zombies that behave just like any normal being but they don't
have subjective experience so he imagines that the zombie would put his hands on a hot stove and the
zombie would he would pull away his hands and ask the zombie what happens the the zombie will tell
i felt hot pain but actually the zombie didn't feel any so the thought experiment is that the zombie
behaves like a normal normal human being but actually he doesn't doesn't have subjective
experience and then the heart problem is since by definition we cannot cannot see between a zombie
and in a human being we cannot do a scientific experiment that we explain what the human being
has subjective experience what the zombie likes yeah to me that is a meaningless thought
experiment because if there is really no way that that i can distinguish only from a human human being
all all of you can be or none of you of you can be zombies any of you can be a zombie to me that is
not not a good way to good way to define it so let's explain something subjective explain
my point the point of view first question a question that philosophers to my surprise
have a lot of difficulties with why is experience subjective why i can't be just objectively see
the way things things are so so for me it appears humans are autoplay systems
autoplay systems as i said in me cannot objectively believe the world they do have access
to opt out in the in the world they only have access to her perterops their self-maintaining
processes whatever interferes with their metabolism if something interferes with my
metabolism that means for for example that it leads to the releases of newer transmitters
if in particle cells then i can feel that perturbation of my metabolism but but i do not access
to think itself though
the thing that follows so much from my theory of poyesis is is that autopoietic processes by
definition they are not neutral they care about what happens to them they distinguish between
good things and bad things whatever helps them to maintain themselves such as food
they see as positive whatever interferes with the autopoietic such as a plate that can burn them
they will see as negative so from an autopoietic point of view all all experiments of course
happen from an internal thousand perspective i can only perceive the world from inside my own body
inside my own brain and what i i perceive as neutral is not objective it is colored by
my goals which is to stay alive and that is why for example have a different perception between
let's say a butterfly and a wasp i butterflies i don't like wasps i know that wasps can be
which will which will interfere with my autopoiesis so and biology might say you should be more you
should be objective objective butterflies wasps are just insects but i'm likely to kill the
the the wasp and not the butterfly
so now
so the subjective experience affects my autopoietic process so what does that mean
effect i'm using using effect now so in the psychology also an effect is something that
acts on all that means it pushes or pulls me pulls me towards it like for example for example it's
if there is food i will be attracted to the food on the other hand it will push me away away from
things are dangerous from disturbances it will push me away from the hot plate or from the wasp
and that is a typical old world directed system there is a classic example of bacteria
taxis bacteria can substance food molecules and toxin models and and they are to follow
a gradient towards the food or away from the toxins so that's what we
define elementary entry agency of the world directedness bacteria are affected by what
happened at one effect there but there is not that conscious effects so now i finally
turn to my solution of the heart problem of business it's what i call local field model
i've also been the local prospect model so effects are equivalent to four these things that push push
or pull on the other hand godness tells me that i don't just just immediately react react take the
time to come to consider our different different process that push and pull in different direction
so there is a range of potential actions now a range is something like a space if i put a force
across a range i get what in mathematics or in physics called a field i could have presented
as a kind of a vector field across a space of potential potentiality that means potential
reactions i i would have but but this i do not do not know what one under all circumstances
there is this cognitive the field the field is flow emanates from the here the here now
and the farther away in space of time the less my my idea will be what what the field is
so how how can we even this local field in the brain i go back to my to my picture of the
workspace there is a circling activation so in the global space there is this this
phase activation but the activation to some the greeks it's a process process spreading
activation in uh in psychomes i think that are are asserts that are related to that are in the
global workspace will receive some leaking activation and that leaking activation in a
sense pairs the way for potentially the next action or the next total or the next interpretation
so the diffusing activation diffusing from the global workspace that's a sense forms
the local the local post which to to be is the subjective experience
uh we'll skip that that one
so this local field it's a conceptual model the reason that nowadays i prefer to call it local
prospect is that that's the first time i started explaining it to people working consciousness
everybody i assumed that i was imagining some some kind of a mechanical field
emanating from my my brain and the field is purely a mathematical concept or a
conceptual model it's not a physical physical field on the other hand on the other hand i'm using
field because because field is something you can explain matter in matter so that means that
potentially i hope that they will eventually be able to make a mathematical model or computer
model of what the subjective experience would be
so in consciousness we speak about about so-called neural correlates of core consciousness
the subjective experience that you feel the neural correlates the activity that is actually
not noticeable in the brain and this neural correlate format for me it's a term that i took
from uh the neural uh uh that was steven goes i call it an adaptive resonance resonance because
it is kind of self-maintaining circulation of activity adaptive because it constantly adapts
to things to inputs and outputs so there's activation that is kind of self-maintaining
within work memory in the global global workspace that activation in and out of out of the resonance
like that it moved one direction action all year and initially the activation again can
do the different actions and then and then it assists it choose the action rather than
the other potential it's a little bit available to the collapse of the wave function in quantum
mechanics if your field of activation is diffusing can be seen as a wave then at a certain moment
when you make a decision to do this or that it's like like the wave of it but then immediately
when it starts spreading again so five free willful uh i see brain as a elective specialized
modules these as modules or circuits we can see them as kind of agents within the society of mind
these agents interact they have a discussion the discussion takes place in these global
workspaces and why is the world free because you can say beforehand what the art of discussion
will be it's as if you different different people with different unions and different different
backgrounds ever to get about whatever whatever political problem you do not know beforehand
what solution they will come out on art because they are they are confronted with perspectives
that have not been confronted before as each speaks in turn that means there is a very strong
effect of who speaks when timing state date etc you cannot predict what discussion will be
it's a non-linear process that means that it's subject to what's called it's called the butterfly
effect meaning meaning that very differences in activation of timing can can lead to these outcomes
in other words whole process isn't predictable why we call it for it free it is not it's not
deterministic so again the same picture the society of mind now now we look at the modules
as if they are agents each agent has certain opinions certain things that are particularly
important certain things you know certain things it's good at and that's agent is is
some of its opinion in the workspace is where all the agents can react to it and their opinion
opinion to it whole thing is is evaluated in interaction different agents agency
so here i go back to the picture i i took from michael where he speaks about compound intelligence
is cells together have a higher level of intelligent cognition than individual cells
be because they interact act because they are in this kind of kind of discussion the same thing
for for organisms like arms same for you or humans at each level each level we can
cognition mission is beauty is collective if
so the the moments are different agents that become coupled that means that they are in some
relationship that's relatively stable i know that they will exchange new information because one
will react what the other one does the orbit of the one becomes becomes the input of the other
and vice versa cells travel from from agent to agent and and that allows a more this or
collective intelligent my first example was a bacterial cell apopoietic network network that
consists of actions each of the action of the action of the molecules is you might say a very
primitive that is in acting with all the others to gather they form apopoietic network
when i look at the human brain i the agents are different models that are helping putting their
discussion in the global workspace and finally in society we might say different people are
discussing in what we call the northern north sphere the worldwide crop crop the
uh gen genitals fee in which communications are
fine finally in russian what i have to do is to do a kind of a natural history of agency starting
from the very simplest agents which are the outcome of reaction networks that self-organize
these reaction networks tend to become but close and self-containing meaning that they are
autopoietic as simple apopoietic systems are uh uh they're going for the innovations they need to
learn to adapt to adapt that means they need to learn to learn to condition action action rules
you know in this in this condition i need to perform perform this action to survive fine
and in human brains we have the additional stage of consciousness that means that the
condition action rules are no longer automatic condition automatically leading to action
thus we will get an intermediate stage of of circulation where activate thoughts feelings
are serrating in what's called the global journal workspace that circulation defines
a local possible possible development months out of these these potential demands
eventually chosen and the one that is one that is is chosen collectively collaboratively
by the different models are discussing so uh i think we still have time for a few questions
great thank you um any questions
sure i'll ask a question this is chris um thanks thanks for your talk
you characterize the environment as a source of perturbations
and you also mentioned that autopoiesis is an attractor in the state space of a complex system
so do you consider the environment to be itself an autopoietic system
uh that's an interesting term uh this is part of a broader perspective which are relational
agency if if you look at an ecosystem you can see the system as a as a whole as a
poetic system in the in the sense that there are flows of uh was it being consumed consumed
and produced so an ecosystem a whole would also be an autopoietic system in that sense
okay great thank you
anyone else
um hi uh i do i do have a question um could you elaborate a little bit about uh your response
to the zombie criticism or are you are you thinking that uh a zombie autopoietic system
cannot exist uh what exactly are your thoughts there this curious okay uh uh it's it's a kind
of a metaphysical assumption uh which which light means the identity of the indistinguishables
so what's given by that is if you cannot distinguish two things if there is no no you can say
i have only here and i have a human here i can distinguish the one from the other some way
then the identity of the distinctions zombies are humans so so for me
isolating a distinction lead to any other the other distinction is meaningless yes another way
to formulate it is it's called the difference that makes it if you start by postulating a
difference between zombies and humans then it should make some other difference just postulating
a difference that does not lead to any any difference to me it's useful that it's making
things complicated that shouldn't be made complicated so the the main question really
for me is is why do we subjective experience experience why do we something for example
if we look at and and we feel because the as the color is a signal that has certain meaning
for us that we have associated for example with the warm or with action and that makes us do certain
things harder than others so the color that will influence me in a different way than the color
blue and that is what the subjective experience is yeah i the way i always understood the zombie
criticism was that subjective experiences is not necessary to do the kind of things that
organisms as complex as humans can do but we do have subjective experience which
is it may have been a product of evolution and maybe it plays a a role