Come here. Stay right there. Stay right there.
No, no, no.
I'm sorry.
Yeah, the lady...
The cage tipped over in here.
Hold her. It's okay. Just hold her.
Yeah, there. Okay.
But the lady inside told me that you're Mr. Bernard.
Bernard, yep. That's me.
My name is Miguel Prado. I'm supposed to be your assistant.
Oh, great. Great.
Yes, I'm from Social Services.
I could get my slip right here from the unemployment department.
Unemployment?
Yes.
Do you have any training? Any experience?
Sure I do. You know, they send me out on all kinds of jobs.
You know, I do everything.
Painting houses, unloading computers, that kind of stuff.
Hold on. I'll be right back.
Carol.
That young man just introduced himself.
Happy New Year, Margaret. Have a good holiday.
Happy New Year. That young man just introduced himself as my new aide from unemployment.
What happened to my full-time experience teaching assistant?
You're lucky to get anybody. There is no money in the budget.
I had to take some money out of maintenance just to pay him.
Figures.
Oh, what happened at the school board meeting?
Did they approve my class heading recess with the rest of the school?
Oh, no. Margaret, that wasn't discussed. We ran out of time.
Why? You were going to bring it up.
But there just wasn't time.
This is not the most pressing issue.
Come on, buddy. It's okay.
It's okay. Come on. Come on.
Come on, buddy. Come on.
Come on.
Hold on a minute.
It's all right. Come on.
I'll take care of you.
There you go.
Carol.
You promised. You said this was the time. You were going to bring it up.
Look, we have had a special ed class in this school for, what, five years?
And it's always been separate from the rest of the school.
It works best that way. Why change it?
The parents are comfortable.
The parents are comfortable?
Yeah.
Harold, I have six very challenged kids in my class.
What about what makes them feel comfortable?
Margaret, I don't even know if we're going to have a special ed class next year.
I don't know if we can afford it.
Now, things are going very well for your class this year, right?
So don't rock the boat.
The Rudds wish me to stress their son has second degree burns on 80% of his body.
I understand, Mrs. Miyako.
My question, however, related to Caitlyn and why she's acting out this kind of violence.
But, Your Honor, what Caitlyn Eldridge did is more than acting out.
It's psychotic and dangerous.
This child must be institutionalized.
Ms. Brown, it's up to you to suggest an alternative.
Social services tried, but that doesn't seem to be one with her history.
Can I say something?
Don't go ahead, Mrs. Rudd.
When this sick child tied Tommy to a tree and set a match to a...
She turned my son into some kind of a freak.
Now, he has to deal with that pain for the rest of his life.
And so do we.
I want you to put her away, Judge.
So she can't never hurt another kid like she done mine.
Don't look at me, Judge. I can't control her. No way.
But you're her father, Mr. Eldridge.
I don't make no difference.
She just turned out bad. That's all.
Caitlyn?
This isn't easy, is it?
Well, maybe you can help me.
Can you tell me why you did what you did?
Caitlyn?
You see? What did I tell you?
Good morning, Lisa Anne. Good morning, sweetheart.
All right, let's try it. Good morning, Maggie.
Good morning, Maggie. Look at my nose. Look at my nose.
Okay, give me some air. Like a big girl. Come on, give me air.
That's a good try. We'll work on it, all right? Let's go sing.
Come on, sweetheart. Let's go sing.
Where do you want me to put this stuff?
Oh, just put it on the plant table and the rest of stuff in the fridge.
I want to be the fish.
I want you to be a big boy now, remember? It's Bradley, the big boy.
Jordan, you can come on and boss it down.
Crap. Crap.
All right, hang it up. Here we go. Everything's fine.
All right.
Come on, Derek, big boy. Take the thumb out of your mouth. That's it.
Stand up. There you go.
Now we're going to have our morning circle.
Jordan, stop. Okay, sit down. Right here.
I don't know. Come on, circle. Come on. Right here, next to Shanice.
There you go. Okay.
Want to chime out?
No. All right. Stand up there.
Get your body in control.
Okay. Good. Let's say morning song.
There you go.
Jorge.
Christmas is over.
That's it. I know Christmas is over, but this is so beautiful.
And we're going to hang it up all year round.
It's good to see you all.
Take off your jacket.
And get ready to sing and do the play.
Miguel, help him with his coat.
Because his mother has to drive.
Come on.
Okay. We're a pretty wild group here after vacation, huh?
Okay. Everybody sitting ready? Bradley, sitting ready?
Okay. Make room for our new guest.
His name. I'm not going to tell you his name.
Do you notice anybody who's new in the group?
Him.
Him and him has a name and his name is what?
Miguel.
And he's going to help us, okay?
Bradley, come here.
See you in just a second.
Sam, could you wait just a minute, please? Thanks.
Bradley, I want you to come sit here.
Come on, Bradley.
Come on. I mean, a child that sets other children on fire.
You've got to be kidding.
Foster care won't touch it.
My father's no help.
What about homebound? Why can't a teacher go to our house?
Nobody will go. Everybody's scared of this little...
Well, I'm scared. And I'm scared for my kids.
Sam, don't do this to me.
Where are you going?
No words.
Listen, I got to get back.
My kids have finally calmed down.
You know, it took four months, but they formed a cohesive group.
They finally feel safe.
You bring a child like this into my class and everything's going to explode.
It's nothing we can do.
The law says the girl deserves to go to school.
She has a right to go to school.
What are you going to do with that?
Keep it, but they don't give them as a quick mention of the garbage glass.
And so the evil queen asked for a magic mirror.
Here's the magic mirror.
Okay, which one is two?
One is two.
This one is two.
What number is this?
One.
Two.
What number is this?
Three.
My turn! No!
Okay, got it.
Which one's two?
One is two.
Bradley?
Which one?
Bradley, go sit down.
Okay, keep going, keep going.
No window.
Okay, which one's two?
Let's go back.
One is two.
Oh, and when you're working with Derek, don't rush to give him the answer.
You know, be patient.
He'll surprise you sometimes.
Is it like this every day?
First days after vacation are pretty tough.
Tomorrow should be better.
See you in the morning.
I don't know if I can be here tomorrow.
I have to go to an appointment tomorrow, you know, and check in.
You'll be here.
You have a knack for this.
Finished.
What time is it?
That was our clue.
Oh, man, four hours to do that closing statement.
I'm not even charging the client.
I get angry they don't make me a partner.
Screwed up priorities, huh?
I like your priorities.
Oh.
This intake information sheet on the new kid, I get...
Ah!
How is it?
It's unbelievable.
You get her tomorrow?
I should have had a lawyer in a baseball cap plead my case.
You would charge her.
I bet you would.
God.
I mean, just read this, attacks other children.
She destroys properties, smears feces on the wall.
And then this underlining red, unteachable child.
No match for you.
It's not funny.
It's frightening.
Take a compliment, huh?
You'll handle her.
You'll connect.
I got it out.
I can't have finished my plan.
You know, we should have a rule.
The first one who finishes their homework,
the other one has to take some time out.
And we just hang together.
Oh, so it's my house and you're making the rules?
I live here most of the time.
This is where I hang my hats.
I should get some jurisdiction.
Good night, teacher.
Everything I know better you have in that file when you're off.
Okay, okay, I'll read it.
Yes.
Now, what do you suppose it might feel like
if you were new to some place and you didn't know anybody?
What would that feel like?
Or hey?
Really bad.
I've had enough.
Yeah, what did that feel like right here?
I don't know. She stinks.
Jordan, I don't want her sitting near me.
She'll spit me out.
She does stink like pee.
She needs help.
You're being very rude. That's dumb.
What do you think it feels like to tell someone that they stink?
It's terrible. It stinks terrible.
It hurt my feelings.
Thank you, Horey.
And what might be a better way that we could teach her?
You can learn her in private.
That she stinks.
And she wouldn't have to change her colors.
That's great. Good talking, too.
What else? What else do we do?
We could pluck up our nose.
Ready?
Backward. All of you.
Okay, Derek, that's it.
I don't want you to go any higher, okay?
All right.
Jordan, Jordan's slow.
Take it easy.
I'm going to the very top.
Nobody else can come up here.
She can come up here.
No!
Stop! Get out of my playroom!
Come on!
Get away from me!
Don't come up here.
Maybe you may be.
Caitlin, if you'd like to play, you can join us.
Come on!
I want to be the only one out here.
Nobody else can come up here.
Get down!
Okay.
Jordan, watch where he's stepping.
All right. Thank you very much.
What's up, Derek?
There you go.
Let's go back there.
Come on.
I got a cheese.
Wow.
Caitlin was deserted by her mother at the age of four
and then left with her father, who was on welfare.
Her father spent time in state prison for theft
and she's currently residing with her father in a trader park.
Wow.
Her options closed pretty early, didn't they?
I don't know.
I didn't give her any work yet.
Well, you know, it's temporary.
You don't have to teach her.
Just let her sit.
And just do nothing?
I think it would be easier on the other kids
not to stir this one up.
Carol, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
Carol, speaking of being kinder to my kids,
will you please talk to the school board
about recess with the rest of the school?
When the time is right, I will.
You think you will?
Yeah.
I found him hard enough.
I think you're pretty good at pounding.
Yeah, I am, aren't I?
Come on.
You have a cuddle.
You didn't say hello to Melissa.
Hello.
Here, everybody.
Discussion time.
Help him out with this mockery.
Thanks, Miguel.
Go ahead.
Good luck, discussion.
Bradley, my push book.
Caitlin.
We need to have a talk.
Now, listen.
We went over the rules in class, right?
And one of the rules is you have to try to talk.
Now, I know it's really hard, but I need you to try.
Shanice didn't talk when she first came here.
Nathan did, Derek.
Okay?
And the next rule is that I want you to participate in discussion.
Or we all get together as a group.
And we talk about our feelings.
All right?
Come on, let's go.
Come on, sweetheart.
Come here.
Push her down the toilet.
She's crap.
Crap.
No.
Push her down the toilet.
She's crap.
Come on.
No.
Are you ready?
When you're ready.
You can come and join us.
Well, it was the first blind date I've been on since high school.
Ooh.
So what was he like?
Well, he wasn't exactly handsome.
It wasn't exactly handsome, I'd call it more like distinguished.
Oh, so it was a dog.
No, he wasn't a dog. He was not a dog.
What are you doing? He was...
He was a dog.
He was barking, baby. Let me tell you, he was barking.
Miss Bernard, some girl's throwing stuff all over the classroom.
Come on, give me the pencil. Give it to me.
Kaelin, give me the pencil. Give me the pencil.
Give me the pencil. Kaelin, give it to me. Give it.
Kaelin, give me the pencil. Kaelin, give me the pencil.
Kaelin, give me the pencil.
Stop. Stop.
Grab your shoe.
Stop.
Help me.
Help me, baby.
What is happening this evening?
Help me.
I'm going to die.
With a child like Kaelin Eldridge,
there is always going to be potential danger.
Look.
The bottom line is
everybody is concerned
what are we going to do about this?
Serve better coffee than seven in the morning starters.
We're better.
What about social services,
putting more pressure on the hospital
and officially force them
to make an opening for her and take her in?
I mean, like next week.
We can try. I don't know that it will do any good,
but we can try.
And until then,
I was wondering, I mean,
are we all going to celebrate when we send this little girl
to the mental hospital,
knowing that she probably will never get out again?
No, I'm confused.
Are you going to class indefinitely
after the goldfish catastrophe yesterday?
I mean...
No.
No, I don't.
Okay, so we're all agreed.
Let's get her in the hospital as soon as possible, right?
Meantime, Maggie,
you should have lunch with your class every day
as long as she's with us, all right?
Great.
Guess what?
I'm supposed to tell you
that Caitlin's early this morning
and from now on.
What are you talking about?
Well, the only bus that connects with her home,
I guess it's very far, is the high school bus.
So she'll be arriving here half an hour early every day.
You're kidding me.
And then the afternoon, the bus will leave
from the high school one hour after your class.
What are you talking about?
She has to wait here.
Here, here.
Look, I was in the office getting my mail.
Carmen says it's only temporary.
She's probably going into the hospital a lot.
Have a good day.
The Marvel's realm is a death ray.
It's not a death ray and she's not going to hurt you.
I want you to go back and do your letters, all right?
You're a good mailman and you're doing a great job.
Okay.
I bet you, uh,
don't know how many Marvel's you've got.
Okay.
How many Marvel's?
Do you have one?
Get up.
It's time to do some math. Come on.
We're going to do math.
No.
Right here.
Get some blocks.
Okay.
All right.
I want you to take your hand.
Okay. And I want you to count three.
Count three.
All right. I'm going to help you.
One.
Two.
Bradley, come back.
Come back here and finish your work.
That is not acceptable.
Now, we're going to do it again.
I'll help you.
Ready?
One.
Two.
It's unacceptable.
Right now.
Miguel, don't have to resist.
Now?
Everybody, it's recess.
We don't have the other kids like we talked about.
But it's not your time.
What the hell with their time?
You take them out now.
No.
Yes.
We're doing math.
No.
It's time for you to learn.
We're going to learn.
No.
Yes.
You know, most of the time, Katelyn still stinks.
Like a toilet.
She'd be on that side from rabbit.
Come on, Jordan. Don't make fun, okay?
If we had a pancake, Katelyn should be on the side with the pancake.
Do you like my picture?
Yeah. Yeah. And I could treat.
You remember what Maggie said about being nice?
About being kind, huh? Hey, hey, you remember?
No.
Come on, go back and do your work.
Come on, finish what you're doing.
All right, Stacy.
Stop laughing now.
Come on, let's go back to work.
Get ready. I want you to find number four.
Good job.
You're number five.
All right, great.
Ready?
We have to go pee.
You can go to the bathroom.
And then we'll do some math, right?
Right?
Okay.
All right.
Count out three.
Good.
Show me ten.
Okay.
How about two plus two?
All right, I'm going to get you on this one.
Fifteen, take away nine.
Pretty smart, aren't you?
Let's try some more.
I mean, do you know how phenomenal that is?
Yeah, I think I do.
Because the hardest part of this job
is that you can't ever really change these kids.
I mean, no matter what.
Because their brain is actually impaired in some way.
Well, that doesn't stop you.
I mean, Lisa Ann and Derek, they're autistic.
I can't exactly set a goal for them.
So it's basically a day-to-day kind of trying
to hold them together.
But then with Caitlyn, you know,
she opened up like that.
It was a dream.
I mean, what's the matter?
I mean, I don't know if she can read yet.
And I don't know if she's ever going to open up again,
but I reached her.
Okay. This is it.
What do you think?
It's okay. Do you know what I'm saying to you?
Okay, I thought it was perfect for over the kitchen table.
You're not listening to me. Do you know what I'm trying to tell you?
Yes, I hear what you're trying to tell me.
So enough of your kids, okay? We're going to interior decorate.
But that's the point. She's not like the other kids.
She's different.
Maggie, look.
Can we just focus on that for one minute?
It's nice.
It's a light.
I'm sorry. I thought it was a porridge.
Do you feel hurt? Guy can tell you fast, please.
What I feel behind on, I've been trying to corner this guy for two days.
Can I just steal him for a minute?
Yeah. Thanks.
We need to figure this out before lunch.
I don't know. I'll try.
Carol, have you heard about Caitlin?
What about her?
An opening in the hospital. I mean, they haven't gotten her in yet.
I can't believe they're taking so long.
I'll call again today, okay?
No. Listen, something phenomenal has happened.
She is reading at a third grade level.
She's doing second grade math.
And then I had Donald test her IQ yesterday.
We are talking 168.
Huh. Read.
Yeah, ask him. He'll tell you 168.
That's genius.
I mean, to put a little girl like that in a mental hospital,
it's just, it's a tragedy.
She's going to revert back to her behavior,
and of course, I'll have to punish her.
Can we appeal the decision?
Can who appeal?
The school board.
Based on her ability.
And her behavior now.
No outbursts, no fighting, nothing destructive.
I mean, she's almost like a new child.
Oh, but that's true.
You really deserve your reputation, don't you?
Crazy kids, crazy teacher.
Yeah.
Oh, one other thing.
The recesses are going great,
and can we have assembly with the rest of the classes?
Maybe.
One thing at a time, okay?
Okay.
But you will try to find out about appealing the court decision.
You want to know what troubles me most
about that little girl's future?
According to her file,
she never cries,
and a child that never cries,
that's inhuman.
You've never seen that before, haven't you?
I've seen a lot of things in my class
that I've never seen before.
Very human.
You know what?
Melissa's going to a party tonight.
She is? Yeah, you going to go with her?
No.
She's going to go by herself?
Yeah, I'm just going to take her.
But you're going to drop her off?
Oh, you figure it out.
Oh, good. Well, you run off,
and I'll see you tomorrow, sweetie. Bye-bye.
Bye-bye.
Caitlin.
Where's we?
I've got a great idea.
Come on.
Okay.
I thought we could
comb your hair out so it looks just like mine.
Now, hmm.
How come you're being nice to me?
Because I like you.
Okay?
Now I'm going to put the other bread in.
I just
like
that.
Maybe tomorrow
we'll give it a wash, okay?
You ready?
You look
beautiful, Caitlin.
My pa,
he'll take him away
and say I stole him.
Nobody ever gave
me nothing.
I'll tell you what.
Why don't you wear them when you're in school?
And then I'll keep them
very safe for you at night.
Okay?
Okay.
It's too big to carry around.
For
almost a year together.
My appreciation.
Open it.
They're beautiful.
I've never had real pearls before.
They are real, aren't they?
There.
I don't know what to say.
I love you, Maggie.
Let's get married, okay?
I...
Well?
Well, why are you changing the rules?
I mean, we've had such a great year.
I want the next one to be even better.
We bought a lamp together.
Two of my bosses came
into my office this afternoon.
That partnership's going to happen.
You're kidding.
Wonderful.
Congratulations. Thank you.
Why didn't you tell me? I am telling you.
I've screwed up so many relationships in my time.
Now that I finally got it right,
I thought, you know...
Thank you.
At the end of the summer,
they owe me three weeks and you've got your summer application.
Damn.
I've applied to go back and get my doctorate.
You know that.
I mean, you said you weren't sure.
Well, I might need that degree if I go back
to college someday.
I just have to
feel that it's right.
I need
to feel a buzz, you know?
Yeah, I've seen it go off
about that kid in your class.
And, uh...
you and me?
There isn't a buzz.
I'm just saying that
I need to get a grip on my own life
before I take on somebody else's, that's all.
You're shutting down, Meg.
I asked you to marry me.
No.
You asked me to change my whole life.
It really scares you, doesn't it?
The idea of trusting someone that much.
I don't want to change you, Meg.
I just want to be with you.
I want to be with you.
They're beautiful.
Morning, Caitlin.
Good morning.
Would you put the clips in my hair now?
You bet.
I think this morning I'm going to give you
the full beauty treatment, head to toe.
A bath.
I found some nice things for you
in our clothes box.
My paw won't let me keep them.
We always see about that.
Anyway,
you know, I
noticed some scars on your back
and on your ankle.
What happened?
I fell.
Caitlin, did your paw ever
leave any marks on you?
You know, like maybe spank you real hard
or something?
It was my mom.
But my paw, he loves me
and never ever run away or dump me.
Why did your mom do that?
What happened?
Well, I'm trying, man,
but it is tough, I'll tell you.
I told you things have changed
since we were stationed down here.
Yeah, well, I sure as hell ain't right.
And this thing all the way back to Portland, I'll tell you that.
Listen, I'll hook something up.
Don't worry.
We'll talk soon.
Traylor's getting a little small for three people.
I heard that.
Um, Ms. Joldridge?
Oh, hi. I'm Keaton's teacher.
Hey, give me a minute.
Listen, I'm out of here, all right?
What's she done now, lady?
She hasn't done anything.
Really, she's a great kid.
So,
are you going to take her away?
Could we step inside?
And there's some clothes at school
that we could give, Caitlin.
I also wanted to tell you
what a great read of your little girl is.
Oh, yeah?
So, what's she done bad?
She hasn't done anything bad.
I came to tell you
that she's really very smart
and I wanted her to have the clothes.
You see him? That's Jimmy.
That's Caitlin's brother.
He was my boy
until that bitch took him away.
He left me with that little bastard
and I can't do anything with her.
What about a foster home?
I mean, that's a solution.
Well, what kind of a bastard
would I be if I gave her up?
You want me to give her up?
No, you're full of crap.
There's no need to talk that way.
Miguel, it's all right. It's all right, Mr. Eldridge.
Mr. Eldridge, listen, listen.
You said...
You said you couldn't control her.
I was just trying to make a suggestion.
No, no, no, no, no.
Thank you so much.
I think you have to leave now.
We don't want your clothes.
Thank you.
We don't need your charity.
Come on.
Thank you.
You should go back to lifting refrigerators, huh?
It's discouraging, isn't it?
But you're going to have to deal
with all kinds of things when you work with these kids.
I don't know if I want to.
Family used to live in a place like this.
Now, that's why I don't like touching the rat.
Seven brothers and sisters.
Me in the middle, all in three rooms.
I understand.
It's sad, too, because you're great with children.
My girlfriend.
She wants me to go back to school to be a teacher.
Smart girlfriend.
You can't do this for me.
Two days, just take two days off.
Next Thursday and Friday.
Yes.
Too soon. I can't leave Caitlyn for two days.
Suddenly like that. She's right on the edge.
I've been working on a defense for this case for two months
because Wally wants to nail that account.
When Wally, the most senior partner,
asks the most junior partner to join him
for a long weekend at the beach house with a client,
the most junior partner goes.
So why do I have to go?
Because Wally specifically asked me to bring it to couples' thing.
I just can't.
I'm the only safe fridge she has.
Give me a break.
I mean it.
You see the way she lives.
I feel for the kid, but you're going overboard on this.
We're talking two days here.
It is tough for a kid to trust
after she has been so badly abused.
And I thought the time away would be good for us.
For a lot of reasons.
You're right.
It's just bad timing, that's all.
Well, everything is these days.
Does it have to be next weekend?
Yes, it has to be next.
Why do you always have to try to control everything?
I am not trying to control everything.
What are you talking about?
Everything. That girl's life, my life, this relationship.
I am not trying to control you.
You are trying to control me.
Control for you means not having to let go of anything, Maggie,
including your feelings.
Down?
Let's go.
For three days.
I'll take Friday off.
We can drive to Santa Barbara on Thursday night.
I want to.
Really.
I'll, um...
I'll try to leave the kids in the classroom.
Okay, everybody.
It's a stop.
Fun now.
I got the platform.
Can we go again in a little while?
Let's wait here.
Is Kate okay?
I don't know.
Did you see that look on her face when I told her
I was going to be in Santa Barbara?
Maybe I shouldn't take Friday off.
No, it should be all right.
I'm really going to put her in that hospital tonight.
She's just so raw right now.
She'll be okay though, you know?
She's not acting out.
Acting out? You're learning fast.
She didn't run.
She didn't make a major explosion, but she's ticking down now, you know?
What, sweetheart?
Can you look through your guts?
Come on.
Show me where, sweetheart.
Where?
Here you go.
Come here.
Come here. I know.
I know, sweetheart.
He's okay.
Feeling a little better, huh?
Caitlin, answer me.
Oh, sweetie.
I wish I could make you understand,
but I can leave for a day and you'll be all right.
Katie, I'm your teacher, you know,
and we won't always be together.
Listen to me. Listen.
This one day that I'll be away,
you can get along without me.
And it's so important that you understand that.
When are you gonna be back?
Monday morning.
Before you know it.
Trust me.
I'll be right back.
Did you fix something with my hair, right?
I think that's a great idea.
I like the way your lady plays the game.
Serious. You too?
You know, I had that backhand volley,
and I missed it.
I'll tell you, Wally, she never thinks she's good enough.
So, Maggie, we're having a charity tournament next month,
and you are such a great player. We'd love to have you.
You know, a lot of the wives are gonna be there.
Well, thanks. I appreciate it.
Great.
Give me a break.
She needs Lisa and wants to order.
Would you like some stew?
Okay.
So would you like anything?
One stew.
Okay.
Two stews coming right up.
Yes. That's a good boy, Derek.
You hung up your coat by yourself.
Didn't you?
You be our customer.
You're ready for this guy.
I wanna be the cook.
I wanna be the cook. I want to.
You have to be the waitress.
I am the cook.
Fine. You can be it for a minute,
and then I'll be the cook.
Brad, you didn't tell her.
She was such a good storyteller.
You know, I thought you were gonna tell us the...
Excuse me.
You know, Doris, I thought you were gonna tell us the one
about the three guys and the rat.
You know, the man of the cloth,
the doctor and the lawyer, okay?
Why are you doing this?
I'm trying to reach McGill.
Something's gotta be wrong.
Maggie, you've left the table three times
in the last 15 minutes. It's making people uncomfortable.
Dan, I'm worried.
Look, I'll tell them about Caitlin,
and then they don't have to feel uncomfortable.
I don't think they're interested. They're trying to enjoy their dinner
and not talk about their work.
I'm sorry if sometimes my job
and my life are a little...
a little.
Just come back to the table, okay?
I will. I'll be right there.
I promise.
Dan, would you come in
or close the door?
No.
It's freezing out there.
No more than that is in here.
You aren't gonna let it go, are you?
Not it, Maggie.
You.
I don't want to let you go.
Dan, I made a mistake.
I never should have
said I was gonna come.
I just don't fit in
as one of the wives.
I don't want you to be
one of the wives.
No.
Why do you have to do this?
What?
Push me off.
I don't know.
Something
happens to me when somebody
gets too close.
Well, I'm sorry.
It makes you a tough woman
to love.
Slumming it?
She's going in.
The school board didn't think it was warranted
to appeal.
Not warranted.
What about a lawsuit?
There has to be something that we can do.
No. They expect an opening soon
before Easter, they think.
But you should feel proud, you know?
You've brought her so far.
Obviously, not far enough.
Why? Why should I continue teaching?
So I can watch another child
be destroyed by the system.
Every child can't be saved, Maggie.
You're a teacher.
That's the equation.
What else would you do?
Teach a muffin.
You know, you're never gonna change
the system the way you want.
You want it all perfect.
Well, that's your terrific teaching
and the energy.
That's what you do.
That's your terrific teaching and the energy.
And sometimes you'll even make a difference.
A little difference.
Let's get real.
There ain't no Camelot.
That's not a reality that I can live with.
Okay, okay.
Solve your own problems.
I can't. Please.
Call him off.
I'll slow it down.
You want some muffin?
No, go ahead.
Oh, Sam, one other thing.
You know, my class doesn't get to go to assembly
but the rest of the school.
I mean, if they did, it would be great.
You never stopped, do you?
First recess, now assembly.
They've already learned the Pledge of Allegiance, Sam.
Give me your mom's leave.
Deal.
Yes, sweetie?
Can you tell me a story?
I'm really busy right now.
Maybe later when you're waiting for the bus, okay?
My favorite story was about a little girl
who lived in a forest far, far away.
It was a beautiful forest.
But the little girl was very lonely
because she had nobody to play with.
And then one day,
she saw a big lion
standing on a rock staring down at her.
Well,
she was so lonely
that she decided to ask for help.
And then one day,
she saw a big lion
standing on a rock staring down at her.
She was so lonely
that she decided to ask the lion
if he would play with her.
But the lion said he couldn't
because he hadn't been tamed.
What's that, tamed?
Well, that is the exact same question
that the little girl asked the lion.
And the lion told her
that being tamed was about becoming friends.
And he said
that he'd been born wild
and fierce.
And that
he wanted to.
She could become his friend
if she would give him all of her love
and trust.
You see, the idea was that
once the lion felt what it was like
to be needed
and to trust,
then he would have to love the little girl back.
And then the lion
would be tamed.
Well,
it had been so long since the little girl
had had anybody to play with
that she agreed
to do what the lion asked.
And you know what?
Very soon
they had learned
together to love
and to need
and to trust.
And then they were
in each other's hearts forever.
And then they both were tamed.
And then
they were
in each other's hearts forever.
And then
they both were tamed.
Hi, Dan here.
Now it's your turn.
Okay.
Rain stop.
Tomorrow I go back to school.
Yeah.
What a lousy day
for you dad to pick up a job, huh?
Wanna play checkers?
No.
You like your dolly, don't you?
Can I have it for me?
You know we could
we could play house.
You could be my dolly.
This one's better.
Which one?
That one.
This one's too hard.
No.
This one's better.
Yeah, that's good.
Okay, I'll try.
This one's better.
Okay, sweetie.
Okay.
Now let's do some math, alright?
I can't.
Come here, I'll help you.
Come on.
You guys finish up over there.
Okay.
Now let's see, where were we?
Okay, we've got two more to do, okay?
So now number nine.
If it's not 12 minus seven
then what number is it?
Sweetheart, what number is it?
If it's not...
Oh, hey look.
Oh my God.
Oh, come here, come here.
Sweetheart, just lay back, just lay back.
Come here.
Alright.
Okay, I'll just stand and be alright.
I'll just stand and be alright.
I'm right here.
I think it's gonna be okay.
Okay, here we go.
Alright, what's that up in the yard?
Alright, let's go.
Alright, make sure they don't weigh that much in, alright?
Alright everybody, let's get ready
to go out for recess.
I don't want to go out until Caitlyn comes back.
I understand, sweetie.
Come on.
My grandpa was to the hospital
and he died there.
Caitlyn's gonna die.
Come here, sweetie.
She's gonna be fine, really.
She's gonna be much better.
Hey, the operation is to stop the bleeding.
And she's getting stronger and stronger every day.
Okay, she's gonna live a long, long time.
My mom said her dad's friend who did that
should be killed dead.
I don't want to talk about this anymore.
Bradley, come here, come here.
Come here.
Alright, everybody.
I know it's a real scary thing.
What happened to Caitlyn?
Alright, I'll tell you what.
Before we go out for recess, let's have a talk.
Alright?
And bring your pictures for Caitlyn.
Come on, kids, let's go.
Doctor, that is the CCU.
Doctor, that is the CCU. Please.
Take it all.
Don't cry, Maggie.
It doesn't hurt too much anymore.
It makes me feel a little bit better
to cry sometimes, kitty.
Here you go.
Do you want to hold my marble like you did yesterday?
No, I think I just want to hold your hand tonight.
Last night, when I woke up,
it was sort of scary.
I wanted my paw,
but I didn't cry none.
Miguel went to get him, sweetheart.
It's for you, from everybody.
Just for me?
Hello, Maggie.
Oh, great, Miguel.
Hello, Caitlyn. How are you?
Good.
Papa.
Mr. Elvish, why don't you go talk to her?
She asked for you.
Well, I can't help her in home.
She wants me to see her like that.
I got this, uh...
today.
I can't believe that this rock...
Hey.
Thanks for meeting me.
No problem.
Just had to cancel three and a half major clients, that's all.
How's Caitlyn?
She's fine. She's up, walking,
mending fast.
Good.
Dan, I called you because I have to know.
I'm sorry.
If I can petition the court.
I mean, can I appeal her case?
Wait a minute. You mean just you?
I know I'm not her guardian or anything official,
but can I appeal?
You want to go over the heads of, what, the school board,
the social services department?
I don't want to. I have to.
Everybody has turned me down.
And believe me, I've made as much noise as I possibly can.
I bet you have.
Maggie the Madwoman.
Come on, there's a decent new place around the corner.
You lose your job, you know that?
I'm giving up teaching at the end of the year anyway.
I decided to get my doctorate.
You're kidding.
No, I'm serious.
Anyway, Caitlyn's the issue now.
Saving Caitlyn.
Yeah, she always had a little more buzz than anyone around for me.
I'll tell you the truth, Maggie.
I was a little jealous.
I was disappointed you called about her instead of us.
I found us.
Why? You're the one who snuck off with his hat
and left a note on the rock.
Dan, a note?
Not only corny, but a little chicken, wasn't it?
I had my reasons.
I don't want to talk about this.
Okay, well, my opinion is you can't appeal the case.
It's risky. Nobody's going to like it.
But you say you don't care.
Will you take it on?
Oh, boy, you've got guts.
Maggie the Madwoman.
And a friend.
A good friend who needs you very much.
I hope you're buying the drinks.
I'm not going to make any money off this one.
It's tough on a child because
basically they have no choice.
Yeah, I worry for Caitlyn.
You know, it's so hard
to stop feeling for them.
Well, maybe that's what makes a good teacher.
Or a bad one.
You think maybe
maybe I make a good teacher?
I think you ought to look in the mirror
and ask yourself that question.
There he is.
Okay, I'll go to the payphone and call Dan.
I let that bastard stay here
for two months and look what he does.
I beat the crap out of them though
before they took him off to jail.
No, thanks.
Well, I appreciate you bringing me
the groceries very much.
Mr. Eldage, we need you to do something
for your little girl.
It's important for her, you know.
You're appealing to the court,
not to send Caitlyn to the state hospital.
And we want you to come to court next Thursday
and just answer a few questions.
Go to court?
This is the date of the court appearance,
the time, and the place.
It's for your daughter, you understand?
I ain't sure I got a daughter.
Now you're full of it. You've got a daughter
and from what I understand she's a great little kid.
Now you'll be there
for her.
Here.
You take this.
What's that for?
Take it.
Oh.
Take your money, Mr.
and you get the hell out of here.
Mr. Eldage.
This is my house!
That guy's crazy.
Damn.
Can we win without him?
Hey!
Okay.
One, two, three, four.
Here, here.
You buy Caitlyn her dress.
Green.
I think she likes green.
Did you remember the tapes?
They're right here in my briefcase.
It's all just...
The parents of the boy she burned.
I didn't know they were going to be here.
I figured they would be. They want to see Caitlyn put away forever.
Where's Pa?
Told him Peter, half hour ago.
Come here sweetheart, sit down.
I don't think your Pa's going to be able to make it.
You should have thrown him in the car and dragged him down here
whether he likes courtrooms or not.
What I brought you?
I want you to draw me a beautiful picture.
Is everything okay?
Do you have any questions? You see that guard right there?
He'll call me.
I want to go and tell him right now.
It's okay.
He wasn't in there either.
Excuse me. Do you see that little girl right there?
You'll be safe here honey.
Maggie and I will be right there.
Appreciate it.
Okay?
Right.
No problem.
Thank you.
Here you go sweetie.
Did I do good enough?
You did great kiddo.
I think the judge was very impressed.
Dan is in the judge's chambers right now
discussing everything that went on in the courtroom.
And then the judge will make his decision.
Is he going to send me away for a long time?
I hope not kiddo.
Okay.
Based on the testimony one could deduce
that she shows some and I underline
some signs of improvement.
But what does that really mean?
That she fits in a class full of misfits?
Oh come on. Look that is just
cheap name calling. This is a child
who had never experienced even the smallest
expression of love.
And then she was put into a healthy,
nurturing environment and incredible things happened.
You saw the videotape her teacher made.
This Caitlyn
is a different child.
I can't think of anything more to get real time for this.
This is Ryan.
What is it?
Could you excuse us just for a minute?
I want you to know that I didn't appeal
to the court on behalf of Caitlyn.
Because I excuse what she did to your son.
It was awful and cruel.
Then why not put her away?
Because I know
that the pain she inflicted came from such
tremendous hurt and fear
that she was having to hold inside.
And now that she's learning to release
those feelings responsibly, there's no
need to act them out. She doesn't have
to keep trying to prove that she is a
bad girl.
You want me to feel sorry for her?
Well, I don't.
Neither do I.
Feeling sorry for kids like Caitlyn.
That doesn't help them survive.
That's exactly what I try to teach each of
my kids how to survive
in a world that
hands them almost nothing besides pain
and rejection.
I can't do anything about the past.
I wish I could, but I can't.
Nobody is going to gain
from trying to destroy that little girl's future.
But how can you be sure?
How can you guarantee that she's not going to
torture some innocent kid as soon as
she gets away from that teacher?
Exactly.
Look,
I can't
guarantee anything,
your honor.
But what's the choice here
to shut a child with Caitlyn's
potential away from society
forever?
She is six and a half
years old.
What's taking so long?
Waiting so hard, isn't it, kiddo?
Maggie?
I want you to tame me
like the little girl did the lion.
No hospitals.
Just therapy.
Yes, yes.
Bottom line, the judge thought
that under the circumstances,
Caitlyn made major progress.
Enough to live at home and attend
regular classes next year.
That's wonderful.
Sweetheart, that's wonderful.
You're wonderful.
Hey, kiddo.
It's Caitlyn's time.
Let's celebrate.
Come on, pizza.
And hot dogs.
French fries.
And hot fudge sundaes for dessert.
Mr. Eldridge, we won.
Listen, we're going to go celebrate.
Would you join us?
No, I can't.
I mean, it's your party anyway.
You did it.
Well, you, uh...
You ought to know that your being here
was very important to the judge.
Thanks for the dress, Pa.
Meat color.
I can keep it, right?
Because you gave it to me.
You look real nice.
Go have some fun.
Huh?
Behave yourself.
Come on, kiddo. Let's go.
Yeah!
All right!
Me, too.
Come on, kiddo. Pizza.
You know, there are a lot of places
you can teach in Seattle.
You don't care that I changed my mind.
Well...
What else is new?
When I saw Caitlyn tonight,
I knew...
I knew you to understand something.
I was able to give that little word
to the judge.
I was able to understand something.
I was able to give that little girl
a love that nobody else
had ever been able to give her before.
A love that...
I didn't even realize
that I had with him to give.
And she was so vulnerable
and so scared.
And she risked it all
by loving me back.
And I was the only person there
who could celebrate
our existence.
That's why I'm gonna
go back and teach again.
It's what I do.
You really get me.
So when do you move?
Next month.
You know, the reason I wrote you that
chicken letter
I left on a half rack
was because I knew I had to leave.
I knew if I
looked into your eyes, I wouldn't be able to.
And you think it'll be
a breeze for me to leave?
Me or Kate?
And sometimes
you are such a butt head.
You didn't answer my question, Maggie.
I need to know.
Then I'm drawing really hard
this time
not to shut down.
Well...
I still have a little more than three weeks.
Good morning, Margaret.
Hello, Harold.
Margaret, what would you say
if Caitlin and
two of your more advanced kids
went to the color guard
at the last assembly of the year?
I'd say terrific, Harold.
But why just Caitlin and two of the others?
I think you'd be even more proud
of your special ed class
if they all were the color guard.
Well, I think that's risking a bit too much.
Come on, Harold. Don't let your good instincts
fail you now.
I ain't gonna go.
This is my class.
Margaret, the school year
will be over in a few weeks.
And everybody's agreed, Mr. Sherman,
the school board, everybody,
that you're ready to go into a regular class
next year.
I wanna stay in this crazy class with you.
Kittle.
Come on, Lisa. Let's go paint.
Listen,
you know, next year
I probably won't be here.
I've been good. You said so.
My pa said so.
He bring home a pizza.
Sometimes
new ideas take a little time, don't they?
Come on.
Let's get ready and practice
for assembly, okay?
Come on.
Good, good, and...
What's in here?
No, and to the public.
Don't we paint this? We're always smoothing
into this bunch.
Good, good.
Other than
invisible
for liberty and justice for all.
Yeah, good job, Derek. Good job.
You go help those guys clean up, okay?
Come on.
I'm so sad to leave them.
I know. The end of the year always hurts.
Okay.
For you, I have
a little thank you.
California University
is pleased to admit Miguel Prado
for the fall semester.
Come here, you.
Congratulations.
Where did you... Oh, he's...
It's wonderful. It's wonderful.
I looked in the mirror and I said,
this guy could be a good teacher.
You know, I think that man was right.
Derek.
Come here.
Come on. It's always going to get hurt.
Okay, everybody, assembly in five minutes.
You have to go to the bathroom now's the time.
You're going to break your class next year.
You and me. No more geeks.
He's a mean incredible broadcaster
and I'm so happy with him.
And he hangs his coat every time.
He knows the pledge. What do you see him in when he's in?
When he's just too fresh?
Maggie, Maggie, excuse me.
Um, Caitlin slipped out of the auditorium.
I don't know where... Okay.
Go back with the others. I'll find her.
Okay. This is Foster. I'm sorry, but...
I'll talk to you if this isn't okay.
Oh, okay. That's all right.
Sorry.
Okay, now.
What's wrong?
Caitlin.
She's not here.
Okay, I'll be right back.
Okay.
I was worried about you, sweetie.
Come on, the assembly's starting.
Let's go.
Gordie and Derek, they're waiting for you to leave them, you know?
Let's go, sweetie. Come on.
No.
I don't want you to ruin the day for everybody.
Don't kick me out.
I'm not going to kick me out.
I'm not taking you out, honey.
You don't need this class anymore.
What do you mean, you don't need them, sweetie?
I'm not taking you out, honey.
You don't need this class anymore.
What do you mean, you don't need them, still crazy?
You are not crazy.
Now stop thinking that.
Fine, then I'll be the craziest girl in the whole world.
Then I'll make you kick me here.
Caitlin, listen to me. Listen to me carefully.
I am going away next year.
I am not going to be here.
Sweetheart, you have grown so much,
and so have I.
And now it's time to see how good that growing up was.
You're ready to try it on your own.
You're strong.
Oh, sweetheart.
No, he's going to pull me again.
Okay, that's all right. Where is she?
Look, Maggie's not here yet, okay?
Yeah, I'm sorry.
But if these kids are not ready in five minutes,
I'm going to have to send some band members out.
I'm doing the best I can.
I'm sorry.
I don't know where they are.
Where's my hair?
You want to know what my mama did when she left me?
You want to know?
Of course I do, sweetheart, but everybody's waiting.
Just listen.
We were in the car.
See?
Jimmy wanted it.
No way. My mama gave it to me.
It's the best that each ever did give me.
Sweetheart, we're ready.
I was screaming in the back.
I was back there trying to make a nice...
Mama said,
Caitlin, come up here.
She gave me a kiss on the cheek
and opened the door
and pushed me onto the highway.
See?
I know, sweetheart.
See? You're just like my mama leaving.
How come you're not going to stay or make me good?
I am not leaving you.
Remember the story that I told you about
the little girl who lived in the forest
and how she tamed the lion
by showing him that she loved him?
Well, that's how it is with us.
We'll always love each other.
And just like that little girl found out,
going away is easier than
because every time you think of that special person,
you can feel
a little bit of their love.
And that love is inside you forever.
Okay?
Come on.
Ow!
Jordan, watch where you walk.
Okay, we're here.
We're here. Let's go.
It's too late, man. It's too late.
Do you want to bet?
Come on, you guys. We can do it.
Come on. Line up.
Come on, let's go.
We can do it. Line up. Here we go.
No, it goes over the right shoulder.
No, wait. It goes over the right shoulder.
Get this. Mr. Sherman.
Maggie, no, no, no.
Can't do it.
You ready?
Let's go.
Come on.
Jordan.
They're late.
Ow!
Let's get in.
Damn it, baby.
Let's go.
Come on.
Let's play.
I pledge allegiance
to the flag of
the United Nations
to the flag
of the United States
of America
and to the Republic
for which it stands
one nation,
one God
indivisible
with liberty and justice
for all.
Thank you.
All right.
It was crazy.
We were wonderful.
We were happy.
You did a great job.
We did a great job.
Goodbye, honey.
Remember, we're going to write letters
and every time we think about each other,
we're going to feel
a whole lot of love.
I'll be bad.
You'll have to come back.
No, I won't, Caitlin.
And I'm counting on you to be good.
I'm betting on you, kiddo.
I'll be good, Mary.
I promise.
Just for you?
No, just for you.
I will.
Bye.
Maggie, I tamed you too.
I did move to Seattle,
and as it turned out,
mine was the last special education class
at Lindbrook Elementary School.
I wondered if I'd ever hear from Caitlin,
because I had decided
to let her make that decision on her own.
Well, a couple of months ago,
in the manor,
I found out that
I had a special education class
at Lindbrook Elementary School.
I wondered if I'd ever hear from Caitlin,
because I had decided
a couple of months ago,
in the mail came a crumpled,
water-stained piece of notebook paper
written on with a green felt-tip marker.
No letter accompanied it.
It was inscribed to Maggie
with much love,
and it said,
You were right to say you'd never leave me,
because I could always feel you there
to dry my tears when I get lonely.
I'm happy I carry your smile in my mind,
so I can remember just how scary
but very kind it was
for you to show me to myself.
And now I need to let you know
that every single day I grow,
and so does the joy that
only you would teach me to share.
Caitlin was right.
She did tame me,
and I will always be a teacher.
Thank you for watching!