Hello YouTube! In this video I'm going to outline hinge epistemology, an approach
to knowledge and justification that has its roots in Wittgenstein's book On
Certainty. Now I want to be clear from the outset that the goal of this video is
not to explain Wittgenstein's own views, which are very much open to
interpretation, rather we're going to look at how hinge epistemology has been
developed in contemporary epistemology. I'm going to focus in particular on the
work of Duncan Pritchard. Okay, so first of all we need to consider
skepticism. Hinge epistemology is often sort of initially developed at least as
a response to skepticism. The skeptic aims to call into question all of our
beliefs, or at least a very large class of our beliefs. So here's a classic
argument for skepticism. If I don't know that not S, I don't know that P, I don't
know that not S, so I don't know that P, where S is a skeptical hypothesis, like
the hypothesis that I'm a brain in a vat, or that I'm dreaming, or that I'm a
Boltzmann brain. You can see my previous video for a discussion of Boltzmann
brains. P is a claim about the external world, like I have hands, right? If I
don't know that I'm not a brain in a vat, I don't know that I have hands. I don't
know I'm not a brain in a vat, so I don't know I have hands. In general I don't
know whether there are any external objects at all. If this argument is
successful it throws doubt on basically all our common-sense beliefs about the
external world. Now it was noticed by philosophers like GE Moore that there is
something a bit odd about this kind of argument. Moore responded that surely a
proposition like I know I have hands is is more certain, more secure than almost
any other proposition. There's nothing that could be more obvious than that I
know I have hands. So Moore argued that no philosophical argument, which you know
I mean a philosophical argument will inevitably appeal to premises less
certain than the premise I know I have hands, no argument like that should lead
me to reject the claim that I have hands. Moore famously responded to this by
simply holding up his hands saying you know here's one hand here's another so
there are two external objects so the external world exists you know you just
sort of flip the argument around right here's one hand here's another so
clearly I'm not a brain in a vat. Again I have a whole video discussing Moore's
argument that I'll link in the comments. So it was this sort of Mauryan kind of
response that prompted Wittgenstein's initial reflections on certainty.
Wittgenstein agreed with Moore that a proposition like I have hands is held
with a kind of certainty even so Wittgenstein felt that there was something
odd about asserting the proposition I know that I have hands and the key the
key problem here is that in ordinary circumstances claims that we have
knowledge or indeed that we fail to have knowledge makes sense only where there
might be genuine doubt about what we claim to know or where we can offer some
sort of justification for what we claim to know like if I say I know that P it's
perfectly legitimate to then ask me well how do you know that P what reasons can
you cite to justify P but in ordinary circumstances these sorts of questions
about you know doubts and reasons and justification they just don't arise when
it comes to a claim like I have hands I mean you know what what sort of possible
justification could be given for the claim that I have hands well I mean when
Moore responded to the skeptic he simply held up his hands and said here are two
hands so you know Moore must be assuming that he can justify the claim
that he has hands by perceiving his hands and I mean you know you might think
okay yeah well surely you know like if you if you ask for a justification for
the claim that I have hands then well I know that I have hands via perception
right I perceive that I have hands maybe that's the justification but
Wittgenstein says there this isn't gonna work because well as he says I quote if a
blind man were to ask me have you got two hands I should not make sure by
looking if I were to have any doubt of it then I don't know why I should trust
my eyes for why shouldn't I test my eyes by looking to find out whether I
whether I see my two hands what is to be tested by what so basically if I were
to have like genuine doubt about whether or not I have two hands then I wouldn't
be able to rely on my visual impressions to test this because you know if I'm
doubting if I'm calling into question the existence of my hands if I'm calling
into question something as obvious as that then I'm also probably you know I
should also be calling into question the testimony of my eyes you know I'm
gonna I'm gonna call into question the testimony of anything else like the
claim that I have hands is sort of I'm just as certain of that as I am of the
claim that my eyes are reliable so you know why why shouldn't I instead doubt
my eyes and then check that my eyes are working by looking to see whether I have
two hands I mean this is actually something that we will sometimes do in
circumstances where you know our vision is impaired like if I'm in a fog or
something I might actually like hold my hands out in front of me and look and
find if I can see them you know like I and then I'm like oh my goodness you
know this is a really thick fog because I don't see my hands there so you know
we the point is is that like the testimony of my if if we're calling
into question the test whether or not I have hands I'm gonna be calling into
question whether or not my eyes are trustworthy so I can't test whether or
not I have hands by by like looking to see whether or not my hands are there
that at least that's not a genuine justification yeah so there's no way to
test this proposition I have hands so questions of doubt can't really arise I
mean there are situations of course where genuine doubt can arise so if for
example I have been in a serious car accident I wake up in a hospital
afterwards I find that my arms are bandaged I can't see my hands in that
situation I might genuinely doubt whether I have hands and since you know I
trust my visual perception I can remove the bandages to confirm whether there
are hands there and this is of course a procedure that I can perform that resolves
my doubt in that situation but for the radical skeptic there is no procedure
that could resolve her doubt there is nothing I can do there's nothing I can
perceive that would resolve the doubt about whether or not I have hands which
for Wittgenstein means that that's not a genuine doubt at all I mean what like
what would it be you know what would it be to genuinely doubt whether I have
hands well maybe it would be that like I wouldn't flinch if I were to see a knife
coming towards my hands of course the this the external world skeptic doesn't
give up these ordinary behaviors if you if you start to try to stab her hands
she's gonna move her hands and if somebody really didn't flinch when they
saw a knife coming towards their hands no doubt their behavior would quickly be
corrected right the knife would hit their hands they'd feel pain and they'd
they'd start behaving accordingly okay so with that in mind then let's say
let's say that in ordinary circumstances I was to claim I know I have hands well
what possible justification could be given for this I mean I mean nothing
right I can't say well I can't justify that claim by saying that I see my hands
because if I'm doubting whether I have hands then I'm not gonna trust my eyes
so you know I can't appeal to the testimony of my eyes in the same goes
for any other perceptual capacity there's no there's no justification available
here so you know there's no there's no justification there's no it seems that
there's no there's no real possibility of doubt like for knowledge to be possible
there must be the there must be the space for for doubt and justification like
when I when I say I know that P this is sort of presupposing the the
possibility that there are like circumstances where I don't know that
P or like maybe I don't know the P right and and what I'm doing is giving a
justification for P knowledge is based on evidential grounds like when I claim
to know something I must be able to cite evidence for it and that evidence you
know might be undermined in which case my claim to knowledge would be undermined
so you know in ordinary circumstances the idea would be that knowledge claims
are appropriate when we have you know arrived at some claim through investigation
when we can when we can ask questions like how do you know but but when it
comes to a claim like I have hands this sort of doubt and sighting of evidence
and investigation this just isn't part of it right I don't investigate whether
or not I have hands I just do things with my hands so the idea is that I have
hands has this sort of special status it's a proposition with a very special
status or claim with a very special status it's a a hinge commitment or a
hinge proposition that Wittgenstein calls these commitments hinges because they
are the presuppositions around which the rest of our language and epistemic
practices turn the the thought is that there are certain commitments that just
have to be assumed in order for various practices to be possible just like the
hinges of a door must stay in place in order for the door to step to stay up
and to open and close like in order for the door to turn the hinges have to stay
in place hinge commitments are required for practices for various practices to
be possible in particular hinge commitments are required in order to
for the practice of rational evaluation to be possible so like rational
evaluation would be like doubt justification giving evidence in order
for that practice to occur there have to be certain commitments that are in place
that make it possible but this means that those commitments cannot themselves be
subject to this rational evaluation they cannot themselves be called into doubt
so so like rational evaluation involves doubt okay I asked myself could this
proposition be false right like I I believe that all you know the all
species share a common ancestor okay but you know why do I believe that could
that be false okay then I then I start to engage in a rational evaluation I
search for reasons to accept or reject the proposition hinges must be exempt
from this sort of doubt because the very act of raising doubts and performing
investigations is itself predicated upon these hinges so since hinge
commitments are outside of rational evaluation they do not themselves have
any rational support so we saw this in the case of I have hands in ordinary
circumstances it wouldn't make sense to try to offer a justification for this
claim so hinge commitments are neither justified nor unjustified they are
neither known nor unknown right so so they're not justified they're not known
so actually when I say something like I know I have hands that would be again
in ordinary circumstances at least that would be kind of you know sort of a
misuse a misuse of language right it would be the mistake is is that no this
just isn't it doesn't have a kind of this sort of epistemic status for the
very same reason they can't be doubted if I was to ask a question like what
reason is there to believe a hinge commitment that would be a mistake
because hinge commitments are what enable the giving of reasons yeah I mean so if
I were to doubt whether I have hands that would just call into question the
whole practice of making claims or doubting claims like even even to doubt
requires a background of assumptions such as I have hands and of course this
accounts for the special kind of certainty that is associated with hinge
commitments hinge commitments cannot be doubted but at the same time we can't
offer a compelling argument for them the certainty of hinge commitments is not
based on our being able to offer a proof for them it's based on the fact that
these are the presuppositions that make inquiry possible or indeed that make our
general form of life possible our general practice as possible okay so let's
sort of see this maybe with another example so consider these two claims so
we have a claim like there is milk in the fridge and then we have a claim like
there are external objects now in the case of there is milk in the fridge there
are very straightforward empirical procedures for establishing this
establishing claim M here I know what to do to test it one way or the other okay
I go to the fridge I open the door I search for a bottle of a particular
size and shape and if I find such a bottle I'm gonna take it that M is true
I'll be like okay I've established that there is milk in the fridge now
obviously further questions could be raised here like how do I know that the
bottle really contains milk how do I know that you know my brother isn't
pulling some sort of prank and he's replaced the milk with something else
but again there are straightforward procedures for answering such questions
if I am really questioning whether or not my brother has pulled this prank I
can you know pour the milk pour the liquid out of the bottle and then I can
taste it and so on so again you know straightforward empirical procedures
for testing this claim M what about claim E that there are external objects
well clearly this cannot be approached in the same kind of way no
observation could establish E it won't help to take you know a microscope and
look through it I'm not gonna I'm not gonna have a microscope and be like
okay I've looked through the microscope and there it is an external object the
difference of course is that in accepting that there are external objects
I'm I'm not accepting a straightforward empirical claim I'm instead I'm
accepting a sort of way of inquiring I'm you know this is the sort of claim that
allows me to gather evidence for and against other propositions and so this
is what the this is a hinge commitment right it's hinge commitments are what
allows to gather evidence for and against other propositions so I might say
something like you know there are three chairs in this room or I might say
that the universe is 13.8 billion years old I can assess evidence for these
claims crucially however this evidence like this this evidence that presupposes
that there are external objects and it it can't the evidence can't provide
support to the hinge commitment because the hinge commitment is what is making
possible the gathering of evidence in the first place so any any justification
given of a hinge commitment would be less firm than the hinge commitment
itself so like I can cite evidence for the claim that the universe has existed
for 13.8 billion years now given that I am significantly younger than 13.8
billion years this is going to entail that there are external objects there
are objects outside my mind objects other than me so you entails E but you
cannot be evidence for E and and evidence for you cannot be evidence for E
because the evidence that bears on you presupposes E all the evidence in
favor of you from physics and chemistry and astronomy and geology would make no
sense without E like we can only bring claims about so if I take the you know
redshifting of starlight or something like that well that's only going to bear
on the evaluation of you if we're assuming E if I'm assuming that you know
there isn't it there are these external objects and I'm not just you know
currently dreaming or whatever so that's the idea of hinge commitments so which
propositions which propositions count as the hinge commitments well different
hinge epistemologists are going to have different answers to this but you know
there are some some some general answers we can give here so that some types of
some hinge commitments are going to include sort of specific propositions
about myself and my own experience propositions that express the sort of
basic pieces of evidence I have from my own experience like I have hands my name
is Kane I am speaking English I have never been to the moon then there are
going to be more general claims bearing on my sort of general worldview and how
I form beliefs so there is an external world sense perception is reliable
reasoning is reliable the universe is older than I am and so on right where
well okay if you like my channel you can support me on patreon where I upload
bonus videos where I offer my own thoughts about the topics I talk about
on the on these on these videos or a one-off donation on PayPal I also offer
private tutoring so email if you're interested in that private tutoring in
philosophy and I have a discord link store this will be in the description
right then so we've seen the role that hinge commitments play in inquiry but
what exactly is the nature of these hinge commitments well a standard
interpretation is that hinge commitments are something like rules they're not
exactly you know they have the form of descriptive propositions but really
they're more like rules so as Wittgenstein says their role is like
that of rules of a game and the game can be learned purely practically without
learning any explicit rules so yeah hinge commitment is going to appear to be a
descriptive claim like if I say I have hands that has the appearance of merely
describing the arrangement of objects in the world it's like okay there is
this thing a hand which is attached to this person so descriptive claim but
really what's happening when we say something like I have hands is we are
we're sort of stating conditions that must be in place in order for certain
practices to occur or we're stating the rules of certain practices so under
normal circumstances I wouldn't explicitly say something like I have
hands in philosophical contexts we use this seemingly descriptive claim to
express certain rules that govern our practices and these rules are manifested
in our actions so when I was writing the script for this video I was typing on my
computer and to do this I I had to have hands I use my hands to type on the
computer and maybe I find that a letter doesn't come up and then I wonder like
does this key still work I try it again I tap it with my hands right I'm using
my hands so my behavior with respect to the computer is governed by certain
rules and I need not be explicitly aware of these rules like I don't have to
consciously think to myself that I have hands in order to use my hands right
often I'll just use my hands I won't I won't sort of have some proposition in
my head that says I have hands I'll just use my hands indeed this rule is not
something that even has to be taught at least not in the way that I was taught
say the theory of evolution by natural selection like I'm not taught the
proposition that I have hands I'm taught how to use my hands to do various
things and in in being taught these practices I adopt these rules these
hinge commitments Danielle Moyle-Sharic put it like this the hinge certainty
verbalized as I have a body is a disposition of a living creature which
manifests itself in her acting in the certainty of having a body so the
certainty is of these rules it's certainly these rules these commitments is
manifested in our actions the fact that I'm acting just shows that I accept these
rules that I'm conforming to these rules and this is why even when I recognize
that there is no rational basis for the truth of the proposition I have hands
like even when I recognize that I have no reasons for this as a belief my
certainty in it is unchanged it will continue to function as a rule that
guides my behavior I can notice that there's no rational basis for the belief
that I have hands and then I sit down and start typing things on my computer
right so this approach gives voice to the worry that skepticism as the
philosopher conceives of it is in some way inert or meaningless so as we noted
earlier there are circumstances where I will experience genuine doubt about
whether or not I have hands as when I wake up in a hospital bed after a car
crash I can resolve such doubts by applying certain standard empirical
procedures that I've learned like you know looking under the bandages and then
I see I see the hands there and I'm like oh I might say in relief oh I know I have
two hands thank God you know this isn't the kind of thing the skeptic is
talking about of course the skeptic tries to ask for a rational justification of
our whole world view and tries to cast doubt on whether I have hands even in
ordinary context but the skeptics doubt it's a doubt that makes no difference
whatsoever the skeptic doesn't change her actions she continues to use her
hands just as the rest of us do and the skeptic doesn't propose any procedure
for resolving the doubt indeed by her lights there can be no procedure for
resolving the doubt because the the skeptical hypotheses are designed to be
consistent with all possible experience so yeah so it's not it's not really a
doubt at all I mean I can ponder these skeptical arguments all I like but at
the end of the day I still know how to use a keyboard and it's this knowing how
to use a keyboard that manifests the hinge commitment that I have hands so
that is the basic idea of hinge epistemology now there are three immediate
challenges to this kind of approach so the first the first challenge is whether
this sort of view actually provides a response to skepticism we've talked about
skepticism a lot and contrasted the hinge the hinge epistemologist with the
skeptic but we might worry whether whether the difference is as great as
it seems to be so notice that the hinge epistemologist identifies certain
commitments as being the hinge commitments and there are two relevant
features of hinge commitments as the hinge epistemologist sees it first they
are the presuppositions on which the rest of our inquiries are built they're
the you know the hinges on which the rest of our practices turn second they are
not justified they are not known no reason can be given in support of them
no justification can be given for them but then you might think well hang on a
minute isn't this exactly what a skeptic would say like all of our beliefs
rest on these presuppositions that cannot be justified so all of our beliefs
are ultimately unsupported now of course a hinge epistemologist will reject this
final inference right all of our beliefs rest on propositions that cannot be
justified sure it does not follow that all of our beliefs are unsupported we
have to pay attention to what it means to give support to a belief this is a
matter of giving reasons of engaging in investigation of assuaging doubts but
this activity presupposes certain hinge commitments the trouble is is that even
a skeptic might be willing to accept what we could call you know conditional
justification or conditional support so the skeptic might accept that look if
you take certain propositions for granted say the proposition that
perception presents a generally reliable picture of the external world if I take
that for granted then I can give support to further propositions on that
basis like if we take P for granted we can get ourselves to Q the issue for
the skeptic is that there's no justification for P but then I mean but
then like where exactly is the line between the hinge epistemology and the
skeptic here is it just that they have like different attitudes to these
presuppositions so like both of them seem to agree that okay there are certain
presuppositions that you can make which like there are certain presuppositions
we make which you know which then allows us to engage in further inquiry you
know which then makes possible all of these other practices or which you know
like if we take these presuppositions for granted then you know this practice of
justification is possible so okay looks like we both agree on that and more
over they both agree that these presuppositions are themselves without
justification is it just that the hinge epistemologist is okay with this
whereas the skeptic is not okay with it like it's just a difference in attitude
so this is one sort of worry that like okay maybe the line is starting to look
quite thin we'll come back to this point later so second challenge is that hinge
epistemology appears to be committed to epistemic relativism basic problem here
is well it looks like people could have could adopt very different hinge
commitments which would lead to different systems of justification suppose
that Verity selects as a hinge commitment that the Bible is the infallible
world of word of God Verity is fervently religious she interprets all other
practices in terms of her literal Christian faith her literalist faith as a
result she endorses young earth creationism as an account of the history
of life now since the Bible is a hinge commitment for Verity it's not open to
doubt or justification in which case it looks like there's no room for debate
with Verity Verity is not making any kind of rational error you know all I can
say is well we have different hinge commitments and our hinge commitments
are immovable so I mean there's a worry that like hinge hinge epistemology
seems to sort of close down rational inquiry and there's also a worry that
it sort of licenses a kind of just dogmatism you know like we just end up
accepting certain things and they're kind of quarantined from from criticism
and justification and of course this this only makes this this specter of
skepticism more vivid because you know we can recognize that Verity's hinge
commitments have led her to a radically mistaken view of the world so we're like
okay these hinge commitments have led somebody massively astray in which case
we might wonder well why shouldn't that be the same for our own hinge
commitments then I mean just insisting that hinge commitments can't be open to
doubt is not a particularly comforting response here you know it's like there
seems to be something defective about the way that Verity the creationist
justifies her worldview if I recognize that the only difference between us is
that we happen to have different hinge commitments I mean maybe my worldview is
defective also you know this is the worry a third problem is that it seems
that hinge commitments can change over time and in response to new evidence so
I have hands is currently a hinge commitment but we've already seen that
there are circumstances where I might genuinely come to doubt this what is it
that makes me doubt this well it looks like it's the changing evidence so you
know or think about a statement like no human being has ever walked on the moon
that was a hinge commitment prior to the 1960s these days we think it's simply
false now the trouble here is that it looks like what's happening is that
these hinge commitments are changing as a result of rational evaluation so when I
wake up in the hospital bed with my arms bandaged and I can't feel my hands in
this situation it's perfectly rational for me to doubt whether I still have
hands but it's like okay so I've received evidence which has now cast out
on whether I have hands but but hinge commitments are supposed to be exempt
from doubt exempt from rational justification so how is it possible
for hinge commitments to change in this manner you know that that like giving
up the belief that I have hands in that situation looks like an almost
paradigmatic example of change due to rational evaluation so how does the hinge
epistemologist account for this sort of case well Duncan Prichard has proposed
an approach to hinge epistemology that he argues solves many of these problems
Prichard suggests that all hinge commitments follow from a commitment to
what he calls the uber hinge commitment the uber hinge commitment is the
proposition I am not radically and fundamentally in error this is the
single basic hinge commitment which all people must share other hinge
commitments are merely expressions of this more general uber hinge commitment
they are how the uber hinge commitment manifests in particular contexts suppose
for example that it would you know suppose it would somehow true that I
don't have hands right now as I'm typing the script for this on the computer in
that case I would have to be radically and fundamentally in error something
would have gone deeply wrong with my belief-forming processes but you know I
take it for granted that I'm not radically and fundamentally in error I
have to take this for granted in order to sensibly investigate anything there
would be no point undertaking an investigation if I could not trust my
capacities to investigate but I can only trust my capacities to investigate if
I take it that I'm not radically and fundamentally in error so this uber
hinge commitment grounds the rest of my inquiries the the uber hinge
commitment is universal but of course different circumstances in conjunction
with the uber hinge commitment will lead us to form more specific hinge
commitments my present circumstances lead to the hinge commitment I have hands
but if I were to wake up in the hospital bed my circumstances would be
different so the uber hinge commitment would require different things of me so
this neatly deals with the problem that hinge commitments seem to change over
time right the the uber hinge commitment remains in place so like right now I
have hands that's not open to genuine doubt because to deny that I have hands
I'd have to take myself to be radically and fundamentally in error contrary to
the uber hinge but this need not be the case in all possible
circumstances right there are circumstances where I have hands could be
genuinely doubted but with the uber hinge still in place what what cannot
like what fundamentally cannot be doubted is the the uber hinge Pritchard
argues that this understanding of the histology hinge epistemology allows us
to address the challenge of relativism so the key point is that not just
anything can count as a hinge commitment you know in particular merely
having the attitude of certainty to a proposition does not make it a hinge
commitment our hinge commitments are only those claims that manifest the uber
hinge commitment so I mean in a sense this will still involve a kind of
relativism because there's the universal uber hinge commitment and then other
hinge commitments will be relative to different circumstances but crucially
this does not entail that you know disagreements are going to be rationally
irresolvable so take a case where two people are debating the same topic so
I'm debating whether creationism ought to be taught in schools as an
alternative to the modern evolutionary synthesis the creationist can say that
she is certain of the Bible even so I mean that's not gonna be a hinge
commitment so both myself and the creationist clearly share various
practices these are going to be everyday behaviors like eating food driving
cars and so on I mean we're both concerned with the education system of
the same country so we share a society we share various practices within that
society so we must have a great deal of common ground and of course we both
share the uber hinge commitment we both take it I am not radically and
fundamentally in error but in that case we should expect substantial overlap in
our beliefs in our beliefs about how the external world works in our common sense
beliefs about what we observe on a day-to-day basis so yeah the creationist
can claim to be certain that the Bible is the infallible world of God word of
God but mere certainty does not make something a hinge commitment because
like even so like suppose the Bible turned out not to be the word of God
would this mean that the creationist is radically and fundamentally in error
well no because the vast majority of her beliefs and practices don't actually
have anything to do with the Bible when the creationist gets into a car and
drives to the grocery store her picture of the world is only tangentially related
to the Bible if related at all so that the real sort of challenge of
relativism is the idea that there can be disagreements that cannot be rationally
resolved if if you accept relativism you have to grant that people with
fundamentally different worldviews might be equally rational and that there's
nothing that we can say to them that would compel them at least rationally
compel them to change their minds but on Pritchard's view everybody shares the
same fundamental hinge commitment and everybody shares a variety of practices
which gives us significant common ground so there's no reason to expect that I
would be unable to present evidence to the creationist that would in fact
connect with the creationist's worldview and that would rationally compel the
creationist to agree with me. Appealing to the Uber hinge commitment can also
so appealing to the Uber hinge commitment can resolve the problem of
changing hinges and the problem of relativism what about skepticism this
this big challenge well here we run into the problem that the Uber hinge
commitment is itself held without justification so the hinge epistemologist
is going to need some other way to you know distinguish her view from the
from the skeptic so as as Pritchard sees it skepticism assumes what he calls the
universality of rational evaluation basically the skeptic assumes that
there are universal rational evaluations where all of one's beliefs are
rationally evaluated all at once what the skeptic tries to do is step outside
of all inquiries suspend all presuppositions and give a general
rational evaluation of all of them bringing them all into doubt when the
skeptic says that a particular claim is not justified this is a kind of
rational evaluation. So the skeptical argument like it rests on the claim
that you know if I don't know that I'm not a brain of that I don't know that P
where you know the argument asks us to consider the basis of any beliefs about
the world whether they be everyday beliefs or scientific beliefs or
religious beliefs or anything else you know can can the basis of our beliefs
exclude skeptical scenarios like the brain in the VAT scenario it thereby
seeks a universal rational evaluation of those beliefs by contrast the hinge
epistemologist proposes that hinge commitments are exempt from rational
evaluation in particular the the Uber hinge that Uber hinge commitment is
non-optional it's non-optional because again as we saw in order for me to
perform a rational evaluation I must trust my rational capacities so I must
assume that I'm not radically in error. So it's perfectly legitimate to doubt
particular beliefs in particular contexts where the skeptic goes wrong is
that she tries to generalize this she tries to doubt beliefs across the board
but why suppose that this is legitimate I mean that's a substantive
theoretical assumption that the hinge epistemologist denies so as Pritchard
puts it I quote the locality of our everyday rational evaluations is not an
incidental feature of these practices as if we were merely lacking in time or
imagination but rather essential to what it is to undertake a rational
evaluation. Okay so the skeptic and the hinge epistemologist agree that hinge
commitments are groundless where they disagree is that the skeptic takes it
that we can genuinely doubt such commitments and we can we can perform
this rational evaluation of them but the hinge epistemologist the groundlessness
of such commitments is precisely what shields them from rational evaluation.
I mean in a sense we can so there are two ways that a belief can fail to have
justification it might have no justification because it is unjustified
where you know that's a negative rational evaluation it might have no
justification because it just has no status as either justified or unjustified
and that's what the hinge epistemologist will say of our hinge
commitments. So is that convincing well here's just one worry although it there
are arguments for radical skepticism that target beliefs across the board like
a gripper's trilemma say not all skeptical arguments are intended to be
global this is the case for the skeptical argument that we encountered
earlier in this video which aims to establish external world skepticism it's
not actually obvious in what sense this argument involves a universal rational
evaluation because this argument is only targeting a specific subset of our
beliefs many beliefs such as beliefs about logic about mathematics about my own
mind beliefs about you know our trust in methods of inductive inference and so
on are not actually threatened by scenarios like the brain in the bat
scenario at least not obviously so so we might object that really this is just
another kind of local evaluation like the the external world skeptic does not
have to doubt the uber hinge commitment so I can think that my rational
capacities are perfectly reliable that you know I have a good understanding of
deductive and inductive inference that I can reliably introspect my own mental
states it's just well turns out that the external world is not as it seems to
be so it's not I don't know it's not obvious that that would involve a
doubt of the uber hinge commitment right like maybe we might think that yeah I
can have I can have sort of better reasons so you know you know perception
is is not perfectly reliable obviously right everybody accepts that on the
other hand there are many many other capacities beyond perception that I use
for forming beliefs and maybe those other capacities can cast greater doubt on
perception right why not that seems to be what's going on in the the argument
for external world skepticism now obviously you know a Wittgensteinian
would object to this solipsistic sort of picture but there's the question is
whether there's anything in hinge epistemology in itself that rules this
out and certainly if the issue with skepticism is universal is that it tries
to perform a universal rational evaluation it's not clear that that's going
to work as an objection to to external world skepticism all right then well
that was hinge epistemology so I'm gonna leave the video there I hope you
found that interesting and I will see you next time right goodbye