Alright, today I'm going to do a quick video on the circle of fifths.
Now first off, a few prerequisites.
This is not an easy topic per se, so I would recommend that if you knew the notes on the guitar,
and one thing you can do, we have a couple of free courses, guitargames.net, there's
one on guitar notes, you can go there and do that, you just need to know basically some
of the names of the notes and how notes work on the instrument, and also I would recommend
knowing what intervals are, and at least half steps and whole steps, which is covered
in our also free, getting started with music theory, so you might check those out if you
don't know what those are.
Alright, now circle of fifths, first of all, I think everyone knows what a circle is, but
you might not know what a fifth is, so let's talk about that.
So a fifth is an interval, and intervals in music work a little funny.
This is how we count.
So first off, you might see, you know, C, D, E, F, G, and that's a fifth, you notice there's
no zero, you might think okay, it goes C to D, that's one, D to E, that's two, but no,
it's the number of letter names really that are in the interval, so the distance from
C to G is called the fifth.
Let's do another one, let's say you take G, and you go G, A, B, C, D, that's going to
be a fifth, one, two, three, four, five.
On the guitar, you probably recognize this, if you see these two notes played together
this is a fifth, you might see this written like F5 or called an F power chord, and if
you can count from most letter names and just count up, so like say D, D, E, F, G, A, gives
you a fifth, there's only one exception to worry about and that's the note B, and the
funny thing about B is that it goes up to F sharp, so remember that has to do with the
fact that there's no B sharp and no E sharp, and both of those are contained within this
space, so B to F sharp.
Alright now, next, the circle itself, so I took the liberty of pre-drawing my circle,
you should do this on a page, I would practice doing this quite often, and then what we're
going to do is basically make a clock, so start here, I kind of divide it up into four
spaces and then I put the little ticks in here, and what we're going to do is we're
going to start with the note C, and then we're going to go by fifths, so a fifth above C,
C, D, E, F, G, and a fifth above G, G, A, B, C, D, and so on and so forth.
Here's our B, so we know we go to F sharp and not to F, now at this point you could call
this F sharp and you could also call it G flat because the note that's one above F is
also one below G, so I'm going to switch over to flats and you'll see why in just a little
bit here, and keep going, so G flat, now a fifth above G flat, I'm going to stick with
flats, so G flat, A flat, B flat, C flat, D flat, we'll call, okay, and then D flat goes
up to A flat, E flat, and we'll keep going here, B flat, F, and then if you've done it
correctly, you should get F and then F a fifth up is C, so that means success, now what's
the point of this?
It's a beautiful circle there, but by itself it doesn't really mean much, now the primary
use of the circle is to find key signatures and scales, so let's talk about those real
quick, now most of you are probably familiar with what a scale is, it's a collection of
notes that fit well together, they're kind of centered around a certain letter, like
C scale, the root of it is C and the notes all kind of gravitate towards C, and scales
are constructed using whole steps and half steps, so if you remember back to our prerequisites
knowing what those are, it would be good, so a whole step basically is two frets on
the guitar, and so we'll see a whole step between these, two whole steps, then a half
step, another whole step, another whole step, so all major scales are constructed from a
pattern of whole steps and half steps, and we get whole, whole, half, whole, whole, half,
now this gives us our scale, we have one of each letter name and no repeated letters,
now for the key of C that means that we have just the regular letter names, now if we do
another key, let's take D, we go whole, whole up, E to F is a half step, because remember
there's no E sharp, so I have to make this an F sharp, and I cleverly left myself a space,
alright, now I need a half step, so F sharp to G sure enough is a half step, one fret,
and I keep going, up, here we go again, so B to C is not a whole step, I have to make
this a sharp, to make it a whole step, and then C sharp to D is a half step, so it matches
the pattern, now this is a D major scale, you'll notice again there's one of each letter
name, there's no F and F sharp, there's no C and C sharp, it's just one of each, but
there's some accidentals, there's some sharps, and some keys have sharps and some keys have
flats, now what is often done is we use key signatures, now what's a key signature, well
this is an abbreviated way of describing this scale, so since I know there's going to be
one of each letter name, and I know that there's two sharps, I can just say that the
key of D has this key signature, right there, and if I say okay the key signature for the
key of D is two sharps, F and C, then I know how to make this scale, put one of every letter
name, and I adjust F and C, alright now how does this apply to our friend the circle of
fifths?