Mark, tell me, why is it that there is something it is like to be me?
Why is it that there is something it is like to be you?
How is this possible?
Well, there are two questions there.
The one is why there is something it is like to be me.
Or to be you, and the other is how is that possible?
The why question, I believe, has everything to do with the fact that the fundamental,
and I say fact, and I'll have to substantiate that later, but it has everything to do with the fact
that the fundamental form of consciousness is feeling, in other words, affect.
And affect arises from a monitoring of our homeostatic imperatives.
We living things have to remain within certain viable bounds, and simpler creatures have reflexive
mechanisms which maintain them within those bounds, but obviously reflexes have a limited
generalizability. There are many situations that living things find themselves in which are
unpredicted by their evolutionary past, and so they can't navigate uncertain or novel
situations, and so most of them expire in those situations, but a lucky few survive,
because they just happen by chance to do the right thing, and then they have progeny,
and so that contributes to the evolution of those reflexes.
There's therefore an enormous advantage, an enormous adaptive advantage for creatures to be
able to experience how they're doing. Is this going well or is this going badly?
When acting voluntarily, in other words, not reflexively, not automatically, they now can,
by trial and error, try different things out, and if it's going well, then they feel it.
This feels like a relief, and if things are going badly, the opposite applies,
and so they avoid what feels bad, and they approach what feels good, and in this way,
as I said a moment ago, they have the enormous advantage of being able to navigate
unknown, unpredicted, novel, uncertain situations, and then to learn from the experience during life
rather than for it to require generations of phylogenetic learning, in other words,
learning by natural selection, or rather adaptation by natural selection.
So, I believe I, with others, it's not my own idea. This is a building on the work,
first of all, of Jagdpanksepp, and secondly of Antonio de Marzio, and others. We believe
that that affects or an extent or feeling is an extended form of homeostasis.
There, you can see in what I've just said, there's an intrinsic value system. The value system of
all living things, the value system which simply underwrites the whole of evolutionary biology,
is that it is good to survive and bad not to. So, good feelings predict your likely survival,
and bad feelings predict your likely demise. So, that's the valence, as we call it,
the valence of affect, the unpleasant pleasure dimension. It is intrinsically valenced,
doing well and doing badly. In order to make choices, and remember that's what I'm speaking
about, the animal having now the capacity to make choices. In other words, to not behave compulsively
according to reflex. That capacity has to be rooted in a value system, because how else do
you make a choice? Something has to be better than something else. So, there has to be some
value system which determines what's good and what's bad, and that's what I've just
explicated. Now, on top of that, we have multiple needs. We complex creatures have multiple needs,
but actually, you don't need to be that complex a creature to have multiple needs,
like for example, to have energy balance needs, and thermoregulation needs,
and hydration needs, and oxygenation needs. There you have four, and each of these has to
be met in their own right. So, you can't reduce them to a common denominator. You can't say,
I have 8 out of 10 need for sleep, and a 2 out of 10 need for nutrition. Therefore, I have a 10
out of 20 total need, so all I need to do is sleep, and I'll reduce the number, and never eat.
You have to do them both. So, why I'm emphasizing that is that this is something in addition to
valence. We also have categories of need. So, valence is a continuous variable.
You can say from minus 50 to plus 50, that's the range of badness to goodness,
but the categorical variables that represent our different needs are by definition because
they're categorical variables. They are qualitatively distinguished from each other.
So, this is why feelings have both a goodness and a badness, and a particular quality, so that
sleepiness feels different from hunger, and from thirst, and from respiratory distress, and so on.
So, when you said why is there something that is like to be me or to be you,
I believe in the most basic form of consciousness, that's why. It enables us to know how we're doing,
to evaluate how we're doing, and it is necessarily qualified. In other words,
qualia arise from the fact that we have multiple such needs. Then there's the second step, which is
if I can, you know, obviously the simple creatures that first evolved, when I say simple, I don't want
to be derogatory, they're not that simple as I've been saying, but the first creatures that evolved
feeling, they weren't verbal, so they wouldn't have been able to say what I'm now going to say,
but it's as if their feelings say, I feel like this, you know, it tells you how you're doing,
and then secondarily, it's a matter of I feel like this about that, and so feeling gets extended onto
perception and cognition, so because you have to develop policies about what you're going to do,
and so affect is the fundamental form of consciousness, which then gets extended onto
cognitive and perceptual consciousness, which gives rise to the forms that dominate our
conscious experience, and because our capacity to plan and think about what we're going to do is so
highly developed. The second part of your question, you know, about how does this happen, well I've
partly described the mechanisms of how it happens, but if you're asking about the hard problem,
in other words, you know, how does physical, physiological processes of the kind that I've
just described, how do they turn into, how do they somehow transform into subjective experiences,
that's another story, so you'll have to tell me if you want me to go into that.
I think, look, okay, there's so much to touch on, I mean, first of all, I just want the listeners,
or for the viewers, we're both in South Africa, this is quite cool because it's the first time
I'm actually chatting to someone in the same time zone, we're both in Cape Town, and just for
everyone who's wondering why the screens are so dark on your side, it's because in South Africa,
we have what's called low chatting, our country just does not give us electricity every now and then,
so Mark's unfortunately on the one side of it right now, just for some context for the viewers,
but okay Mark, let's go to the hard problem, I mean, I've read The Hidden Spring, I mean,
I've read The Neuropsychology of Dreams, your writing is very fascinating, I like the way you're
sort of blending neuropsychology, neuropsychoanalysis into neurobiology and trying to link these
fields together, so you're definitely working at that interface between mind and body, so let's
discuss the hard problem, what are your thoughts on this hard problem of consciousness, is there a
problem, I mean this podcast is called Mind, Body, Problem, Solution, because the aim is to find a
solution to this problem, do you think we're able to find it using what your theory sort of claims?
Well, I don't claim to have solved the hard problem, but I do claim to have given us a
hint as to what direction we need to go in in order to be able to do so, so let me unpack
that story, I could do it in two ways, let me preface it with the first way and then I'll come
to the second way which I'll tell you in more detail, I think that the hard problem arose
because we focused on visual perception as our model example of consciousness, in fact I might
go further and say we focused on human visual perception as our model example of consciousness
and of course conscious vision has everything to do with cortex, so I might sort of you have to
start somewhere, so let's start with Francis Crick's famous book from 1994, it was called
The Astonishing Hypothesis and the subtitle was The Scientific Search for the Soul and there he
explicated a methodological program as to how we might go about sort of saving
the problem of consciousness from philosophy, rescuing it and bringing it into international
science and he proposed this concept of the neural correlate of consciousness, he said all we need to
do, consciousness is nothing special, it's just another biological function, all we need to do
is find the anatomical and physiological substrate of this function, in other words we need to identify
its neural correlate, we need to then once we've isolated that correlate we can start seeing okay
well how does this thing work because this must somehow explain why there's something it's like
to be you and me, it's a sort of reasonable commonsensical reductionist strategy but the
unfortunate choice as I just said is that he focused on human vision and I say it's unfortunate but
it's not difficult to understand why, I mean human consciousness is dominated by visual perception
and also more cortex is given over to visual perception than any other form and we understand
it rather well so it seemed like a reasonable place to start, why I think it was an unfortunate
place to start is first of all you shouldn't start with human beings the most complex form of
consciousness and you know cortex is many, this is more fundamental point, the function of visual
perception does not require consciousness, you can have visual perception without consciousness
so when the very next year after Crick's book was published came David Chalmers's famous paper
in the Journal of Consciousness Studies where he said well you know why doesn't all this information
processing go on in the dark and etc, I don't need to tell you what he said but I think it was a
reasonable question from Chalmers precisely because visual information processing can go on in the
dark so it is mysterious why do we why does it have to feel like anything at all, we know that
not only the superior curriculae can see unconsciously but you know the visual cortex can
see unconsciously and it can discriminate things like pretty elaborate things like color
you know you can you can discriminate color unconsciously so why does it have to be something
it is like to experience red versus blue if you can discriminate them without experience
now that I do not believe applies to feelings you can't have a feeling without feeling it
and I've just explained to you why we feel our feelings it is it is a it is a necessarily
subjective monitoring of my own state with existential consequences for me
and it has to have this goodness and badness has to have value and it has to have a categorical
qualitative differences so you know had we started there had we started with affects
which are not generated cortically and that's another big story they are generated they are
generated in the in the midbrain for the most part but certainly they are generated subcortically
in general had we started with those much more ancient much simpler structures
and I think that the hard problem would never really have arisen I think it's you know to say
why must you feel pain you know why must you feel hunger this is mysterious why don't you have
why don't you unconsciously navigate uncertainty and make choices of existential consequences
within qualitatively distinctive variables and it's just you know just is when you describe
that function you're just describing a feeling and feelings as I said feelings have to feel like
something unlike visual perception which does not have to so that's the the first I said I'm
going to tell the story in two parts that's the that's the the first part but let me now move
from neuroscience to to a more sort of philosophical perspective on this thing
and I said the question the hard problem put in its most basic form you know is as so put it you
know how how does the brain get over the hump from electrochemistry to feeling and how do electrochemical
processes turn into feelings literally turn into them you know what kind of weird metaphysical
transduction occurs there and and and here I think the problem is that the the the physiological
processes do not turn into experiences I think this is remember I'm saying this is a philosophical
perspective yes I think it's a matter of observational perspective on point of view so
um no if you if you look at the processes going on in my brain when I am feeling let us say
excitedly motivated you will see activation of mesocortical mesolambic dopamine circuitry
and you literally will see it if you for example put me in a positron emission scanner you will see
that circuitry lighting up and you can you can use all sorts of methods to you know drill down
into what exactly is going on physiologically there but that's looking at me from the outside
I mean you are now looking at me in the dark from the outside and you're seeing a body
and you can then you know you can start scanning this body and you can see in in more granular
detail what's going on within it but the the crucial issue is you're taking an external
observational perspective on me I on the other hand have another observational perspective on me
that is being me I am me so I have another perspective which is the subjective mark songs
as a subject as opposed to mark songs as an object so I can look at myself in the mirror
and I recognize oh yeah that guy's me it's mark songs but I could also when I first wake up in
the morning before I've even opened my eyes I can have this dawning subjective experience of being
me and that's can only be described as my mind then I stagger over to the bathroom look at myself
in the mirror and that's my body but both of them are me so you know they're not two of them
there's only one of them there's only one mark songs it's just that we're observing
him from two different perspectives so so to say how does how does my subjective experience of being
me produce the physical or I should rather put it the other way around how does the physiological
embodied version of me produce the subjective experience of me is like asking you know how
does something objective produce something subjective objectivity doesn't do subjectivity
they're two different perspectives um now the if we are one and the same thing you know then
it's like actually let me use another analogy lightning and thunder you know with you with
your ears you hear a clap of thunder with your eyes you see a flash of lightning
that they're two different things you know the they're utterly different perceptions
but but they're not they're not actually two different things they're two different manifest
depends what perceptual perspective you take on is it an auditory perspective or is it a visual
perspective we don't ask it would be unreasonable to ask how does lightning turn into thunder
you know we realize these are two different ways of of of perceiving the same underlying process
and then we ask what is that underlying process and then we start going into physics
and we start speaking about you know georelectrical potential differences in the atmosphere
and you know and that's the ultimate description of what's going on the ultimate description
is of the causal mechanisms that we infer from the observational the observable data
and that's how we come up with the basic theory a basic and a fundamental science of lightning
and thunder um you know which is the theory of electricity um and and I think that that's what
we need um in in neuroscience or neuropsychology if we're going to bridge the divide between the
psychological and the neurological between the subjective and the objective perspectives
on the being of a creature then we need to find a more fundamental language which explains
both both sets of phenomena we don't we don't want to ask how does the one set of phenomena
cause the other set of phenomena because they don't so what I'm saying in essence is that
the hard problem is made a lot harder than it has to be uh if we if we conceptualize it
that way if we ask the question how do how does the brain get over the pump from electrochemistry
to feeling it's it's it's a question that can't be answered because it's wrongly framed um
but if we ask you know what is it that produces both the electrochemistry and what explains
the behavior of the electrochemistry and the behavior of the feeling then we then we have a
mechanistic theory and and I I think that um the the prospects of finding such a mechanistic theory
are greatly increased by shifting our focus away from these very complicated visual perceptual
processes which as I've already said uh these cortical processes are way down the evolutionary
line uh they're much later developments they're a secondary application um of what feeling is for
and what feeling does and focus instead on the primary form of feeling in the brain stem which
is as I've also already said an extended form of homeostasis then we say okay so we have a
fairly good clue as to what the mechanism is that we're looking for uh it's it's homeostasis with
some version of homeostasis and I I think from that starting point uh obviously there's a lot
more that could be said about okay so then how do we do it how how does uh homeostasis mechanistically
how does it explain the behavior of the predictive brain and how does it explain
the experience of being an of an intentional being with with with with calls and and aims
and purposes and so on I think that from that starting point it can be done um and my my own
efforts in this area have been have been along those lines trying to trying to begin to um
sketch what what what what this what this uh this monist uh um mechanistic uh um causal
explanatory process might be whereby uh we we have the the particular physiology of consciousness
and the particular phenomenology of it I'm glad you you just mentioned monist and asked because I
was thinking I mean we spoke about some of the history of philosophy we we spoke about David
Chalmers and his 1995 paper I mean do you think Descartes-René Descartes when he started this this
question of this mind-body problem when he started with this dualistic approach do you think that
also had a big impact on the way we perceived this problem in the first place very much so
and and David Chalmers makes little uh secret of his admiration for Descartes
I I think yeah I mean I I I wholly concur with the title of Demasio's famous book Descartes' Error
it was a horrendous error so so the the philosophy that I find myself much more sympathetic with
is is is that of of Spinoza uh that that I think is a great advance over Descartes
um I'm actually going to chat to Demasio about in a couple days so I'm very
looking I'm looking forward to that but Mark seem to be my best wishes I'll definitely like him very
much yeah so I'm looking forward to discussing Descartes' Error in quite a bit of detail well
when you're looking at this brain stem you're looking at this midbrain you're talking about
ancient consciousness I know sometimes because the main goal of this podcast is for me to provide
you someone who has a an excellent new thought process on this problem to explain their view
express themselves openly and to also address any objections people might have or to their theory
but when when you talk about the ancient brain you feel that's giving people a sort of a misconception
on what you mean by ancient consciousness because I feel like I've I've read blogs I've read a
couple things where people think you're taking it too far I've talked to some scientists about it
some some philosophers and they think you're taking it too low but yet you're explaining
exactly why the cortical versions of this are not the same do you think that they're mistaken
consciousness with intelligence I do I do very much so think that uh although um I don't deny
uh that very simple creatures like a bacterium has an intelligence it's obviously in it's nothing
like our intelligence and it's it's a it's a perfectly understandable state of affairs
that we start with human consciousness well we are human for one thing for another thing the
problem of other minds dictates that the only form of consciousness we can ever observe directly
is our own so you know it's it's it's not an unreasonable place to start it's not it's not
hard to understand why we began there but it's quite a different thing to say that therefore
human consciousness is the definitional form you know that anything which doesn't conform
to our type of consciousness isn't really consciousness um you you started this podcast
by asking me the question why is there something it is like to be me that is uh of course charmer's
definition building upon tom nagel's definition from 1974 um it's notoriously difficult to get
a neuroscientist or for that matter anyone to agree on a definition of consciousness
but I think if there's one definition that has more or less uh united us it is that it is something
it is likeness you know it's it is parliad that's what we mean by consciousness and so there's nothing
there's nothing complicated about that it doesn't it doesn't have anything more in common
with Descartes thinking uh cogito ergo sum than it does uh in common with the the the the raw
feel of pain you know there is something it is like to feel pain so when you say I'm going too far
philosophically speaking all I'm saying is I want to stop I want to I want to define consciousness
as as something it is like to be in that there is something it is like to be in that state
and that's not a controversial definition of consciousness and then I'm saying well there
is something it is like to be in pre-verbal non-verbal uh states of raw ethic like pain
I find it very hard to to imagine how anyone could argue against that you know there is
something it is like to be to be hungry there's something it is like to be thirsty this there's
something it is like to be in pain there's something it is like to experience separation
distress with which all mammals experience and display um there's something it is like to feel
fear and you know and you don't need to be able to reflect upon the source of your pain it's a very
very great advantage to be able to but you don't have to have any theory of pain or any
explanation of pain or any knowledge of pain as mechanisms etc or even just know anything about
what caused me to feel this all you just need to know is I feel it that's that is that is I think
a very defendable position that that's what we mean fundamentally by a conscious state
um you know I I grant of course that these higher forms of consciousness add all kinds of
bells and whistles and uh I'm very grateful to be the proud possessor of all of those bells
and whistles and I don't want to forego them you know so therefore I'm well aware that they
add a hell of a lot more but I don't think it's the right place to start if you're wanting to
understand the basic mechanism whereby something it is likeness appeared on this planet you know
how it how and why it evolved that that creatures started to quote Tom Nagel he said
that something like I'm paraphrasing but he said an organism is only conscious if there is
something it is like to be the organism something it is like for the organism you know that's
that's that's a compelling definition for me of what consciousness is and and and it makes
mean in terms of everything else we do in biology you know we take an evolutionary perspective we
we try and understand you know what this thing how this thing evolved why this thing evolved what
does it add what does it do that's why once it once it evolves it gets it gets conserved because
it continues to perform that function and that function bestows such enormous additional
survival potential that that it just hangs around now you've got to look at the arguments
so I've just given you in principle arguments about why I think that's a
fine place to start it's in fact to me the obvious place to start although I can understand
why we started in another place I think that it was a mistake in retrospect and now we can
correct that mistake and start in a better place but it's not just a matter of principles
you know it's a matter it's also an empirical matter when you start looking scientifically
at what is the minimal architecture for for consciousness you you know you
and you know you you you can start with human beings even you know if you if you produce
not deliberately so let me rather say if it so happens that you suffer a lesion
in the reticular activating system that lesion can be as small as two millimeters cubed in other
words the size of a match head if it's in the peri-brachial complex the right part of the
peri-brachial complex that will produce a coma in in any and in every human being you the the
fish's meta fish's analysis of all of the scans of stroke trying to identify what is the small
what is the common denominator what area is always lesion in patients in coma it's the
it's it's a it's a small two cubic two cubic millimeter area of the peri-brachial complex
so that wipes out something it is likeness reliably you know I mean you can at my prediction
is lesion that area the animal will go into a coma bingo it always happens the prediction
is confirmed each and every time now by contrast what about the cerebral cortex the cerebral cortex
in fact since the 1880s where has been removed in experimental animals with gay abandon and
even in the 1880s it was already observed that goats for example did it in dogs the dogs didn't
go into a coma they just they became what goats described as idiotish in other words they became
stupid they they lost their they lost their knowledge their understanding of the world
but they still behaved you know purposeively they they they behave and I'm telling you about
goats but since then for decades you know a decortication has been performed on on innumerable
mammal species and the opposite if it's done neonately you know the the the observation is
always the same that they they play they show fear they get enraged in situationally appropriate
ways they copulate with each other they rear little little pups to maturity I mean not perfectly
but they do they play they hang from bars they swing around you know they they in fact yark
pangsit used to he performed a little sort of an experiment it's not really an experiment but
each of his new cohort of graduate students he would show them two groups of rats in two
different cages the one group had been decorticated and the other group had had a sham decortication
in other words they had the little bandage on their heads but but they they hadn't had the
operation and he asked them which of these two groups has no cortex and and every year he had
the same result you know that the students identified the animals that were were were intact
as being the decorticate ones and he said why and they said because the other ones are more lively
in other words in reality the decorticate rodents are more lively they're more emotionally expressive
that's because they don't have the cortical modulation of the but now we're talking about
rodents and and dogs and what more what about human beings if the cortex was the seat of consciousness
then there's a easy prediction which is that you know just we don't do neonatal decortication
in human beings but sadly they are neonates who are born with no cortex and this is a condition
known as hydrogen and cephalin and the prediction would be if the cortex was the seat of consciousness
that these kids should be in a coma they got no cortex and at the very least
they should be in a in a persistent vegetative state but that's not what you observe they are
not vegetative you know the vegetative state is also called non-responsive wakefulness non-responsive
wakefulness these kids are utterly responsive they and just as I described for the for the
animal studies they are responsive they are emotionally responsive in situationally
appropriate ways in other words you tickle the child she laughs you frustrate the child she
arches her back and complains you give the child a fright and she startles and and they show
behavioral initiative they they approach things that they like and they avoid things that they
don't like you know anybody who has anybody who has studied these children seriously
you know they they come to this conclusion and people philosophers you know who are all
skeptical about this I really invite them to just interact with these kids you know it's it's just
it's it's it's very very difficult to sustain the argument so so I was saying it's it's very
hard to sustain the argument that these kids are not conscious if you actually interact with them
but you know it is ultimately because of the problem of other minds it's ultimately
a matter of of inference and what my colleagues say I mean when I say colleagues here I'm not
only referring to philosophers there are many neuroscientists who who are very skeptical about
the claim the claim by I hasten to add not only me you know a good many of us who actually have
interacted with these kids find it very hard to believe that they're not conscious they are
feeling creatures who behave in every way like feeling creatures the the argument that is made
against this is we cannot know for sure that they are not just reflexes yes well remember
what I said about reflexes at the beginning of our discussion you know in reflexes there's an
entirely predictable response there's no variation there's no trial and error there's no intentionality
you know this is not what you see in these kids it's also not what you see in the deco ticket
animals so it's it's you know anyone who knows anything about how the reflexes of the nervous
system work know that what you see here ain't reflexes or instincts you know they are not
they are not reducible I mean they are dominated by instincts that's true these kids are you know
they are not like you and me but they show they show goal directed intentional
purpose of and voluntary behavior and if you read the the descriptions by the pediatric neurologists
who studied these kids and the neuroscientists who studied these kids you see you know the
detailed evidence for that but you can't be sure say my colleagues so let me just hasten to add
you can't be sure that your pet dog is conscious you can't be sure that your pet cat is conscious
you can't be sure that anyone other than you yourself are conscious and then the argument
is given well reportability gets us out of that problem you know it's true that our dogs and cats
can't report their conscious state so there's room for skepticism there you know but
Tevin Naidu and Mark Solms can say there's something it is like to be me let me tell you
what I'm experiencing right now I'm experiencing x y and z I don't know why that's considered such
wonderful evidence you know because a robot can do that a robot can report its states
you know you can write a very simple program just say you know whenever you're in this that
or the other mode say I'm experiencing it but how do you know it really is experiencing
so I don't think reportability is I mean by the way on the reportability thing we're saying not
only that our dogs and cats aren't conscious we're saying that our preverbal kids aren't conscious
humans you know exactly so we need better we need we need better ways of deciding the question
when you go on the internet and you're trying to access something and it wants to know that you're
not a robot it doesn't say please tell me please declare you're not a robot you know it gives you
an ambiguous situation a problem and you have to navigate some uncertainty there and solve the
problem you know why why why is that the case what if declaring your states you know was was
such a wonderful method for determining that does seem to be the case sorry did you want to add to
that before well sadly I have a lot to add to it so let me rather let you get a word in
eduism then I'll carry on no you can continue I'm enjoying listening so that's why so what I do
what I say to my colleagues is okay well let's take you know you guys don't claim that the
whole of cortex is the seat of consciousness the the the general view is you know that there's
all this information processing going on there which is then accessed by some sort of overarching
global workspace or or something of the kind and where is this thing located well the standard
argument is prefrontal cortex the the other well known or widely held position which is I think
probably a better one is that it's insular cortex I why say better because insular cortex
has to do with feelings which I've already told you is the basic in my view form of consciousness
but if the prefrontal cortex were and many people say this I mean my dear colleague and friend Joe
the dude says that that all of this stuff you know he's an expert on sub cortical
affective circuitry specifically fear circuitry and and specifically the amygdala and he says
all of that stuff going on the amygdala is unconscious until it is until it is read out
by the cortex literally he uses the word label you know in other words until you use until
you can have this concept I am feeling fear you're not feeling fear so so what happens
if you remove again we don't do it experimentally but it happens in nature that they are patients
with no prefrontal cortex in fact I'll tell you it's not unusual to have patients with large
prefrontal cortical lesions on Joe the dude's view they should be less affective they should be
less emotional consciousness but there's more I mean since since Phineas gauge we've learned
frontal patients have too much emotion but I have a patient case W who has no prefrontal cortex
whatsoever and he not only is he like all such patients or frontal patients you know he's a
hyper emotional he's very overwhelmed by his feelings not only that but you know he he answers
questions that I put to him about what is it like to be you I asked him to imagine a scene in his mind
which had to do with I said imagine you have two dogs and one chicken can you picture them he says
yes I said now tell me can you count their legs and tell me what the total number of legs are
and the answer of course is 10 two dogs and one chicken so to my great disappointment because I was
trying to prove is there's somebody home you know he's there with mental imagery and he can
and he can experience it to my great disappointment he said eight the answer was eight I said eight
he said yes the dogs ate the chicken so you know no prefrontal cortex there's a sentient being there
and Domazio reported a case patient B who had absolutely no insular cortex and the same thing
Domazio interviewed him about you know and the patient keeps on referring to me and I and I yes
of course I have a mind and yes I'm experiencing this and and Domazio's patient also had heightened
affective feelings not a reduction in affect which is what but Craig's theory but Craig is the guy who
said you know the insular is the is the is the seat of the fundamental form of consciousness
feeling well Domazio showed that with no insular cortex you still have feeling I showed with no
prefrontal cortex you still have feeling and you have sentient being reportable conscious states
so then my colleagues say well it's due to the remaining cortex so you see I can't win because
they say the case with no cortex they can't declare their states so therefore we don't know
so I say careful let's take this with no prefrontal cortex they say well maybe it's posterior cortex
take one with no posterior cortex well maybe it's anterior cortex so that's now I'm near the end of
my argument which is that so let's look at other methods other than lesion methods so if if the
feelings are actually generated in the subcortical structures I mean literally in in other words
they're not being read out by cortex because everybody knows of course these affective mechanisms
are subcortical but the idea is they're not conscious until they read out by cortex so
if that were the case then if you if you take for example positron emission tomographic images
of human beings who are in intense affective states which they can report so they say I am
feeling really sad you know I am feeling absolutely joyous I am feeling trepidatiously
fearful or I am feeling really angry each of those four states and I'm not just saying I am
feeling I mean people who who really are in the grip of intense affects if you scan them
with pet imaging what is the prediction if it's if it's the if it's the brain stem
and the and this limbic circuitry arising from it that is responsible for those effects
then that's where you should see the highest rate of metabolic activity that's
that's what we that that seems to be an acceptable method for everything else in neuroscience so
you know so yeah we're saying well if the if the greatest if the if the hot spots are in the brain
stem then that's where the state is being generated and that's exactly what you find
if you if you image people in intense affective states you see intense arousal of brain upper
brain stem structures and the circuits the olympic circuitry but not cortex you know now
what about another method so in other words the prediction is confirmed yes now what about another
method deep brain stimulation the the prediction is if the if the affects are generated in the
brain stem you know then if you generate if you stimulate those structures that you are saying
are generating the affects in other words reticular activating system the prediction is
you will stimulate you will generate artificially an intense affect and and conversely you won't
if you stimulate cortex and that's what happens you know you stimulate cortex you get just about
no affects and when you do it's they really thought they're not affects they kind of like
you know i'm remembering this time that i was a bit down you know but you stimulate this when i
speak about a bit down stimulate substantia nigra you produce within five seconds depression
clinical depression like suicidal depression you know and and you switch off the stimulator
90 seconds later the person is out of the depression and i'm talking about reticular
activating system but it's not only reticular activating system it's periaqueductal gray
periaqueductal gray which is which is in the mid-brain there's a greater variety of affects
generated by stimulating the periaqueductal gray than any other brain structure and the
greater intensity of affect and so that's a third method so the lesion method you know
you add it to the functional imaging method you add it to the to the deep brain stimulation
method then there's also pharmacological probes you know if you it's no accident that the major
psychiatric drugs the the the psychopharmacological agents that form the mainstay of of clinical
practice these days they are like like antidepressants SSRIs what are they doing they are
increasing serotonin where is serotonin sourced it's it's it's sourced in the reticular activating
system in the rife nuclei where is where is dopamine you know antipsychotics block dopamine
where's that sourced apart from the substantia nigra which i mentioned earlier the type that's
important for psychosis is sourced in the ventral tegmental area which is part of the
reticular active aging system noradrenaline is sourced in the locus cirrhulius complex you know
you you modulate noradrenaline or you you you block noradrenaline to block anxiety so if these
nuclei you know are are the targets or at least the the the the the source cells of the neurons
that the cell bodies of the neurons that are targeted by all of these psychopharmacological
agents but they they're all in the reticular activating system this tells us something you know
so so i'm saying i'm sorry i'm speaking so much devon let me just come back to my to my main
argument which is that it's not when people say moxons is going too far to say well you know
these brainstem structures and simple effects are the model example of consciousness i told you
in principle why i think effects are the right model example and then i said and empirically
you know the you look at all of the evidence all of the evidence speaks to speaks for the
conclusion that actually effects are generated there where in the part of the brain that we've
known since 1949 is the is the basic prerequisite for all other forms of consciousness the only
problem is in when magoon and maruzzi discovered that and nobody disputes it that it is prerequisite
you can't have a conscious cortex unless it's activated by the reticular activating system
yes but when they discovered that they said yes but the reticular activating system produces
around produces what did they call it the level of consciousness yes a quantitative sort of like
volume of consciousness but it hasn't got any phenomenal content and that's what i've just
shown you isn't true you know it has phenomenal content the content i grant you is not cognitive
but it is effective there's a there's something it is like to be in those states that i've just
described therefore they are they are qualitative states they're not just quantitative states
and they have content the content is you know the the the feeling of pain versus the feeling of
hunger versus the feeling of sleepiness those that's that's the content that's what those states
are about so if if the upper brain stem was was only about some quantitative dimension
the level of consciousness it would only be of interest to an anesthetist yes but
it's the characteristics of tinkering with those with those circuits so yes so there you have it
in essence the youth i mean we've used this clinical differentiation between contents
of consciousness versus a level of consciousness but you're clearly showing that in essence they're
both very much linked i mean they're they're one in the same in a sense with whether you're
whether your level of consciousness is slightly lower in terms of less the gcs scale doesn't
necessarily mean that the person doesn't have effective qualitative experiences
exactly so i find it's a very it's a totally artificial distinction there is no
such thing as i mean how can you how can you have blank consciousness you know it's what is such a
what is a blank consciousness so you know you can't be conscious without being conscious of
something i mean we've known that since Brent Arno you know it's uh so i think that that's
distinction drawn by Maguna and Maruti uh all those decades ago was because they were so
completely flabbergasted by the finding which remember they weren't in any way expecting
that if you disconnect the cat cortex from the cat reticular activating system there is no more
conscious cat you know the the the the the the the the cortical consciousness cannot
just just disappears without without reticular arousal and so it was a way because everybody
knew that the cortex was the seat of consciousness they had to explain this somehow and so they
came up with this totally artificial distinction between um this this waking state which is
contentless um and you know and then the phenomenal qualities and and contents of
that the cortex had i mean but that's what i like about your book as well is that you you do do that
you show different methods of how you can prove this and predict what your theory claims that well
because ideally that's what we want in the scientific theory of of anything you want so
you want different ways of proving the same thing which is what you've basically shown in many ways
what i find very fascinating mark is that others neuroscientists like let's say for example michael
graziano he also pays a lot of attention to the tectum optic tectum which which we call the superior
coliculus but then natural completely different conclusions they regarding i mean he uses this
as the attention schema theory where we're building models of attention but we're not really um aware
in the sense that we have qualia we rather introspectively conclude that we have this
so i still find it quite fascinating that some people are using similar brain regions and
brain structures and drawing different conclusions what are your thoughts on that yeah but but but
let me clarify there um i am not uh i don't i don't disagree with that the the the the optic
tectum or or or superior coliculi they they are they are receiving information from the sensory
end organs sensory motor end organs but that doesn't mean that that information is conscious
i mean the famous example is blindsight with with the cortically blind cases
who nevertheless can navigate an obstacle course they are completely unaware that they're seeing
anything and yet they can avoid things that are in their way and the the the the most widely accepted
explanation for that is it's because the the the optic tectum is is is processing the information
unconsciously i'm fine with that it's unconscious and and and it also receives auditory information
and somatosensory information and so on um and uh the so these kids for example the the the the
hydranin cephalic kids uh i the the reason they're able to respond to their environments is because
they're receiving information about the environment from their sensory epithelium and but it is
unconscious then they it evokes a feeling in them uh all they know all they experience on
the evidence available to me it leads me to the conclusion that they i i don't think i can claim
that they experience anything more than just a feeling they don't have to know what the feeling
is about where it came from what made me feel this what is the thing out there in the world
it it it's not necessary so i'm saying because remember the the the superior
curriculae well well the the the whole of the tectum the superior and inferior curriculae the
whole of the tectum uh is is absolutely adjacent to the periaqueductal gray so all of the well
not smell but all of the other senses of projecting unconscious visual auditory somatosensory
information to the to the tectum uh and that in turn uh is is coupled with uh all of the
homeostatic mechanisms that we've mentioned at the beginning of our discussion all of the
homeostatic mechanisms the affect mechanisms including the emotions because they are bodily
affects and their emotional affects they all send their residual error signals to the periaqueductal
gray immediately adjacent to the tectum so so it's it's something like it's something like
you know where things where things stand now in the outside world which is not consciously
registered uh and where things stand now uh from the from the endogenous perspective of the organism
and and then uh the feeling is about those things but the feeling is all that the that
that the creature experiences you then need higher uh structures and the thalamocortical
structures make it possible for that feeling to be applied to a stabilized grip because the
tectum is just like a sort of salience map it's an attentional I agree with that description of it
but the cortex has the stabilized detailed mappings uh of it's not only that they detailed
mappings of the outside world filtered through a lifetime of experience of it because cortex is
memories memory space but it's also that it can be held in mind in working memories so you can
actually you know okay I feel like this about that so what am I going to do about it you know
that's that's what the cortical consciousness adds and and and and perhaps even more important than
that is that you can then manipulate those representations virtually in other words you
can you don't only have to feel your way through the world here and now by trial and error bearing
in mind that trial and error involves errors which are which are costly so so thinking where you have
virtual representations of if I were to do that what would happen and if I were to do the other
thing what would happen then and feeling you feel your way through these virtuals and all of this
is what cortex adds um and uh I keep on saying I'm very grateful to have that and I recognize that
that is a way more complex form of consciousness than the elementary form but for all the reasons
I've already said I think that the elementary form nevertheless is the right place to start
and the elementary form nevertheless qualifies as consciousness defined as there being something
it is like to have it what what I really like is that at some point I mean when you're talking
about homeostasis you're talking about how we're trying to figure this out and quantify a lot of
these qualitative experiences you that your work then somehow links with a lot of Karl Frister's work
and I mean Karl Frister is definitely one of the like most I mean he's the most cited neuroscientist
on the planet I think um and your work seems to coincide quite well do you want to touch on that
because I find that very intriguing the way you guys have linked up I read the paper that you guys
did together as well and I even used a part of my dissertation that you were very generous to
help me with uh but yeah let's touch on that a bit so I said earlier that uh I'm a dual aspect
monist in other words I think we have two different ways of observing uh the the the mental instrument
um you can look at it from the outside as as an organ uh you can look at it from the inside
as as a as a phenomenal state of mind but these two things are reducible to one causal mechanism
and that is something you infer from the data of of of observation and and I said that if you
if you accept that the elementary form of consciousness is feeling and that feeling
is an extended form of homeostasis then you have a rather simple mechanism you know you have a you
have a good place a tractable place to start because homeostasis is not difficult to understand
and so Karl Friston published a paper in 2013 in one of the journals of the royal society it's
called royal society interface and the paper was titled life as we know it and in which is a
wonderful title and and in that paper he basically explicated uh in in in ordinary you know physical
uh terms how by which I mean by which I mean you know physical mechanics how how does how
does homeostasis work um and so I said to him on upon reading that paper you know the the the
mechanism of of homeostasis which you so beautifully uh you know reduced to equations in in uh in that
paper if if consciousness is an extended form of homeostasis and by the way all those brains
then nuclear are not all of them but I mean the the fundamental homeostasis of the of the human
body are are are you know sort of like hypothalamus and midbrain and I said it should be possible to
extend then these these mechanistic accounts that you provide of homeostasis count of feeling
so that's what the paper that I wrote with him was about um so that's background uh to move a
little bit further forward so as everyone knows so I'm not going to go into this chapter inverse
Friston has has the flag that he's tied to his mast is the free energy principle
which is which is basically a statement of the the that self-organizing systems
systems which persist which continue to exist they have to do something to continue to exist
that this is this is what distinguishes I'm not saying all self-organizing systems are living
systems but what what but all living systems are self-organizing systems and what distinguishes
living systems from non-living ones is that they oppose the second law of thermodynamics in other
words they don't just dissipate they have they have they have preferred states and they work to stay
in those states and that's how they stay alive you know in the end the second law wins we don't
stay alive forever but you know the whole the essential feature of living systems is that they
are acting on their environments in such a way as to increase their chances of carrying on
existing as systems so the free energy principle is just a formalist a formal understanding of
the mechanisms whereby that work how self-organizing systems a resist entropy and by the way when I
said not all self-organizing systems are living systems that's a good thing because living systems
evolve from non-living systems you know so the fact that we can have a physics that explains
the this basic tycov system which then became the living system is a necessary thing you know we
have to be able to explain life in terms of things that were around before life came into existence
and by the way the same applies to consciousness we must be able to be conscious life evolved
long before consciousness evolved so you know there must be something it must have it must
have been constructed out of ingredients that were already there and I'm saying self-organizing
systems provide us with those ingredients so the free energy principle explains that how
self-organizing it formalizes the mechanisms whereby self-organizing systems in order to
continue to exist they have to minimize their free energy which is basically the same thing as to say
they have to have a model of the world because how else can you act in that world to to to
maximize your chances of surviving so it's a predictive model it's a model that if I were to
do that in the world this would be the sensory consequences that's how I maintain homeostasis
say if my sensory state is I'm moving out of my homeostatic bounds I'm getting too hot
I'm getting too thirsty then I must do that I must get out of the kitchen or I must drink some
water you know that will bring me back into my viable bounds so that's the basic and and the
free energy principle says to the extent that what you predicted will happen in consequence of your
actions to the extent that it does not happen that's called surprise all average surprise all
basically is free energy in other words you must be using your energy you must bind your energy into
actions which lead to the outcomes that you require in order to survive free energy in other
words energy that is not being efficiently used must therefore be minimized in other words the
gap between you what you what you expect to flow from your actions and what actually flows from
your actions that gap must be minimized so that's the whole of Friston's work basically just boils
down to that I mean I don't want to diminish it it's absolutely genius you know but that principle
explains homeostasis and it explains the goal directed behavior is the allostatic
imperative you know in order to maintain within my homeostatic remain within my homeostatic
bounds I have to do things in the outside world and I have to have a good understanding of how the
outside world works in order for me to know what things to do and while I'm busy learning that
I make lots of mistakes and I slowly improve my predictive model in order to minimize those
mistakes that's what the whole of cognition is for and what is cognition therefore doing it is it is
serving the the the the free energy principle in other words it's minimizing homeostatic errors it
means that is in other words it is it is reversing negative effects and turning them into positive
effects that's so affect which is the demand for mental work is a demand for predictive work
and the predictive work is what our cognition is all about so I've given you a very broad brush
stroke sketch there but that's what we worked out together in that in that first paper that we wrote
together which I then expanded into my book it's showing that you know I said I don't believe that
we've solved the hard problem but I believe we've given a good clue as to which direction we should
be going in that is a monistic account it's a it's a it's a tractable quantifiable statistical
mechanical account of the the the machinery of the mind and brain which is an information
processing machinery in the service of minimizing free energy in order to maintain the organisms
within their viable bounds so that they can survive that's it so some more I mean like
you're taking a physicalist monist account of this what are your thoughts and then other theories
of consciousness in terms of philosophical theories let's take panpsychism for example
or idealism what are your thoughts on those types of theories I think panpsychism is a little easier
to deal with than idealism so let's start with the problem of other minds which is the big problem
when it comes to consciousness science it really is the because conscious states just
are subjective states you can only ever know your own so we start there this this this might be
considered a really simplistic argument against panpsychism but it's the one that I start with
I can't know whether computers are conscious and tables are conscious and walls are conscious and
rocks are conscious you know I do know I'm conscious so now am I conscious of everything
that's going on inside of me no I'm only conscious of things that are going inside of my brain
my brain the brain states are only the conscious of other bodily states to the extent that those
other bodily organs are represented in the brain so so the brain and this this is not just a
commonsensical argument it's an empirical demonstrable fact you never lose consciousness
by removing any part of the body other than removing the brain if you lose consciousness by
removing the heart it's because the heart is no longer perfusing the brain you know etc so it's
like clearly the case that consciousness is in the brain and so you know all of the other bodily
processes are not conscious I empirically I can tell you that in my own case you know there's the
only way I get to know about and there's a hell of a lot of processes which never become conscious
like blood pressure regulation for example you know it's going on all the time thank god for that
but you know there's no conscious why is there no consciousness involved in that by the way
it's because it's entirely predictable you can't leave that to reflexes you know there's
there's there's no novel situations there that you have to feel your way through
so panpsychism if you take if you take as your starting point well you know the only thing I can
know empirically is what I am conscious of well I know even in my own case there's a hell of a
lot going on within the outer surface of this thing called Mark's arms that Mark's arms is not
conscious of so you could start then saying well of course it is possible that your muscles are
conscious of themselves and they're not reporting it to you and then you know then you should start
getting into into Never Never Land because yeah that's possible I mean anything's possible
it's possible you know that you know that that pigs can fly but I've never seen one you know and
so you know that's my argument against panpsychism now I'll take that's a very simplistic argument
because it's and I start with that one because it's an empirical one it's the only empirical one
because you have to start in your own case even within the brain Tevin there's a hell of a lot
of brain activity brain structures which the activity of which we never become conscious of
you know so so consciousness seems to be something quite special limited to very particular kinds of
structures and so you know then I that's another argument another way of tackling the problem
of panpsychism is you say well let's look at the mechanism what these parts of the brain
that we know are generating conscious states like these homeostatic brain stem mechanisms
let's look at what you know what they're doing there's a very particular kind of functionality
there a very specific mechanism which is not you know you don't find it in everything there are
many things which exist which are not displaying active inference in other words they're not
trying to model their environments in order to in order to persist and you know if that is the
mechanism of the one and only knowable form of consciousness which is ours you know we we know
that the the brain stem mechanisms that generate our consciousness they seem to be doing this kind
of thing we can then look to every other creature that has similar mechanisms which by the way is
all vertebrates and we can make testable predictions we can say I predict if I stimulate dorsal
periaqueductal gray in a zebrafish you know it it won't like it it will avoid the stimulus if I
stimulate the the ventral periaqueductal gray in a zebrafish it will like it and it will approach
the stimulus and the prediction is confirmed so you know that's that's that's and that happens
every time in every creature that has the same architecture as us that we know generates
affective basic feeling states in us all the evidence suggests that they're doing the same
thing in these other creatures and also that they can make choices you know the the behavior of the
animals is consistent with our understanding and then there are other creatures which don't have the
same architecture like cephalopods and insects and so on there I'm less sure that they're conscious
you know I'm not saying they're not I'm just less sure and I I use the criterion of well
can they make choices can they feel their way through a novel situation and survive it and
they can so you know well possibly they're conscious too but there are many creatures
simple simpler creatures like bacteria whose behavior is completely predictable there's you see
no new ideas coming from a bacterium you know the only way that they that they advance is is
through over generations through through natural selection you there's there's no there's no new
problem solving you know so I'm saying that even in living things Tevin starting with myself there
lots of my own bodily processes that I know from my own case are not conscious and then I know which
parts are generative of consciousness I know what those do roughly speaking I know what their
functionality is when I test in other animals the prediction arising from the the the inference
that those structures and that mechanism is what gives rise to two feelings the predictions are
always confirmed where those are not present in living creatures that those structures and those
functions the prediction again is always confirmed that they don't show the functionality that that
seems to underpin consciousness in us then you know that's so so compelling but then you know to go
from that to non-living things I mean to claim that non-living things are conscious it's you just
outside of the not only the bounds of testability you're outside of the bounds of reasonableness
just like why would you say that and you know starting from the observables that's where that's
the conclusion you just have to arrive at if you start from first principles and you say well
it's possible that there's something it is like to be anything then well yeah it's possible
but anything's possible I don't see any reason why one would hold that view
unless one starts from the assumption that consciousness is a fundamental property of the
universe which I have to say is not not not different from the idea of God yeah that at the
time of the Big Bang there was a consciousness maybe but that's outside of science you know to
those kinds of claims that if you think about it that's something that people like Julia Tononi
and Christoph Koch have done fundamentally taking consciousness as phi they can't get as far as
fundamental and doing a lot of but I think they did it in a different way so so like let's take
Tononi's case as you've just said the the the idea that consciousness can be can be can be
objectified as as a quantity of of integrated information processing if you hold that theory
then it leads you down some some rabbit holes that you then have to go down you know because if you
say well okay the amount of integration in the information processing is what determines the
degree of consciousness then you have to say well there's no there's no you know as long as there's
any amount of information processing there must be some degree of consciousness and conversely
you have to say anything that has the requisite you know number must be conscious therefore
any highly integrated information processing system like the internet you know my theory
with me if I'm Tononi my theory requires me to say yep the internet's conscious yes so
fundamentally information at this point which is how a lot of people are seeing it
then in essence everything has a level of fire yes everything has that you know what's what's
what's a curious little historical fact is that charmers you know I'll tell you something
else which is another curious fact many people who bang on about the hard problem of consciousness
have never read charmers' paper you know if you actually read charmers' paper there's this thing
that I'm going to tell you now there's another thing which I'll tell you as an aside at the end
of the paper charmers says the hard problem is hard but there's no reason to believe that it will
forever remain insoluble and he then you know so he's saying it is soluble and and and he even goes
so far as to then present a possible solution and this is the thing I was going to say
his possible solution is that all information has a subjective aspect and that is consciousness
and it has an objective aspect which is this mechanistic thing that we see you know it depends
what kind of substrate you're using but like our computers there they are they're processing
information but the being of the computer says charmers you know because it's an information
processing device that there is some small amount of consciousness associated with it because the
internal aspect of information is consciousness therefore because information processing has
been going on since forever consciousness has been around since forever and it's a fundamental
property of the universe so I don't want to lose sight of the aside I've made there please note
charmers says the hard problem can be solved he said it himself in 1995 so all these people who
revere this problem has been completely insoluble that it's a metaphysical problem which can never
be solved by physical science that's not what charmers said but he then proposes his own theory
which is a panpsychist theory which is when it's something approaching a panpsychist theory he
doesn't say everything is conscious he says all information is conscious which is a which is a
reasonable place to start because what we know about the brain and the mind what they have in
common is that they're processing information you know and not everything in the universe is
processing information so you know that's why it's approaches or heads in the direction of
but now here's the rub for me if you read so information in Shannon's sense
which is the sense in which charmers uses the word he actually says so in that paper
so Shannon's paper which brought information into the concept of information into into physics into
the idea that there's a quantifiable thing called information and that it has causal property
does stuff you know in the physical world that for that realization and conceptualization of it
we have to thank Claude Shannon and you read his paper which was published in if I remember
correctly 1948 it's called the title says it all it says a mathematical theory of communication
it's not a theory of information it's a theory of communication because why information has to
have a source and a receiver it's information doesn't just exist information something is only
informative to a receiver of that information so information and I'm speaking pure Shannon here
information is an answer to a question you know it's is is the coin toss heads or tails you know
is it heads yes or no that's one or zero you know that is the binary digit that is the bit that is
the quantum how we quantify information so how many questions I have to ask determines how much
information I receive from from my interaction with with my environment so this information
exchange is a question asking and answering exercise and the crucial point is that the information is
subjective it's received by me who asked the question the the the system doesn't and a system
doesn't contain an objective amount of information it depends on what question you're asking of the
system so you know so the the very same I mean if for example there's a bag of of balls and we
you and I both know that the yellow red and blue ones in there and we know that they're 30 balls
I know that 10 of them are red you don't know that that that bag contains more information
for you than it does for me you know so it depends on it depends on how so information is a measure
of of uncertainty the more the more unpredictable is the outcome of an event the more information
that carries for the observer of the event and you and I might have more or less prior knowledge
so that will be more or less predictable or unpredictable to us so so the why this is also
important is that when you speak about information whether you're charmers or you to know me you
have to ask yourself the question of well who is the recipient of this information and so you're
back to the question of well where's the subject with like in the internet where's the subject
or the conscious subject of all of this information processing it's integrated you know for what it's
so it's just like a very weird way of thinking about I think to say that information in and of
itself you know is is or the integration of that information in some objective arms length sense
you know is is the mechanism of consciousness I think misses the point so so my way of thinking
about it which I tried in a very brief and rough and ready way a few minutes ago when I
spoke about Carl Friston and my work on this problem our starting point was well an infam
a self-organizing system which has to predict the behavior of the world has to ask questions of the
world you know is if I were to do this what would happen kind if I were to do this what would
happen to my free energy is basically the question that every every biological self-organizing system
has to constantly ask so the information processing that gives rise to feeling in my view is that kind
of information it's not all information it's infam it's it's it's it's it's it's it's the
answering of questions by systems that give a damn about that they need to ask questions and they
give a damn about the answers that is I think the kind of system that is the information processing
within which can can can can can feasibly or plausibly rather be be conceptualized as a as a
sentient system I must like for example mark on when I came into this podcast so when I first
started thinking about consciousness I'm very much on a similar page as you I think I think we're both
very monist physicalist we're trying to reduce it trying to figure out a nice biological approach
to it but I must say someone who came very close to really changing that my mind on that a little bit
was Donald Hoffman I don't know if you're familiar with his work yes I'm not in detail but yes I know
the basic ideas yeah so it's pretty fascinating to see that a lot of physicists nowadays are
starting to show that space time itself is not a concept that we can actually understand or
really even perceive in any real way and and therefore well now when he takes it further
by obviously making the his own conclusion that conscious agents must be fundamental
so that's a separate story but what is a bit strange is the fact that physicists are not
showing us that the reality that we're trying to reduce is not a reality that is possibly
reducible because we see we have absolutely no access to this reality what do you think about that
well um so if you if you you or any of our viewers read my book in in in the penultimate
chapter it's titled back to the cortex and there I speak about so the most of the book is about
effort it's about you know this fundamental form of consciousness and how it is generated and
what that what the implication oh sorry it's not the penultimate chapter it's the third last chapter
the second last chapter is on charmers and the hard problem the last chapter is on artificial
consciousness the third last chapter is on this this this this question of of cognitive and
perceptual consciousness you know the the type of consciousness that that we have for for the most
part focused on and there I make the argument which is again not not a a novel argument it's
it's very similar to Hoffman's although I don't cite him because actually I'm embarrassed to admit
I didn't yet know his work at the time that I was writing that book but I was aware of other
people in the predictive processing tradition you know like like Andy Clark and and and and
Jacob Huey uh speaking about you know perception as controlled hallucination
and that you know the the reality and and Dan Dennett uh you know the this whole thing of the
the use illusion and so on and I find yeah and Neil Seth I mean that whole group of him
and Neil Seth is in that same tradition and Neil Seth extends it from the extra receptive
domain to the inter receptive domain in very interesting ways um actually if we have time
I will come back to that because I think that the that that that affect is not the same as
interception you know I I have a little a little quibble about that but I don't think it's important
for our present purposes so what I'm saying is that in that tradition with although Hoffman
doesn't come up from a predictive processing background I think it's it's it's it's entirely
compatible you know the idea that the reality that we are that we are acting in is a representation
of the of of something in my language beyond the mark of blankets all I can know is my blanket
states and that that is a that is a statistical generative model you know of of of the of reality
minutes you could even say can't it's a cantium view you know I have no problem with that whatsoever
so but you know I don't think it's a and is anything spooky about that and and I don't think
that it requires us I mean all you need to say is the retina the retinal ronson cones
light waves impinge on the retina and the those cells transduced those light waves into nerve
impulses so what we um you know you never actually are you're not that you're not receiving light
waves you are representing them as spike trains you know that that's enough for me it can see
there's nothing spooky there you know and those spike trains all they are are ones and zeros so
from that I then have to infer the the the the causes of these of these sensations in other
words of these signals and I and I model it you know I'm perfectly fine with that
so I but but you know I don't see why that leads to all kinds of spooky conclusions that's
that's there are few steps beyond that that I don't think follow when I spoke to Donald when I
asked him about it because I mean a lot of us in biology in neuroscience we know that we don't
see reality every radical sort of truth we sort of represent something but his physics and his
work with a couple other mathematicians show that spacetime is fundamentally completely different
so we're not even seeing a mild representation or like something similar to reality or close
it's completely different but he does eventually say that however his conclusion that consciousness
must be fundamental is something he's willing to accept might be wrong he's just trying to figure
out a different solution so he actually doesn't take it to that point where he he claims that
consciousness is fundamental he's just trying to find some relative because reality is the problem
in essence we don't we know a lot about mind but we know almost nothing about matter pretty much
yeah I wouldn't but by the way as you can see my lights came on so so hallelujah the the load
shedding has ended for I hope my doesn't see what happens yes let's hope there's not a reciprocal
interaction between where you are and where I am but look there's there's much that I could say
about about quantum physics and that the seriously strange nature of reality and how
utterly different it is from the from the high level average states that we are able to represent
and so on you know that and those things all interest me very much I I will just say about
that that the the the approach that Carl Friston and I take which is the free energy principle
approach it's called variational free energy this is this is you know there's there's
thermodynamic free energy and there's chemical free energy and then there's informational free
energy and and some people no less than chains for example thinks the informational free energy is
is the fundamental explanation of the thing the all of those are probabilistic it's a probabilistic
theory the variational free energy has to do with statistical mechanics it has to do with
probabilities when I was speaking earlier about you know your uncertainty and the palpating of
your uncertainty and all of that we're talking about probabilities and so I think that there's a
very deep link is that there's a I think that the the whole free energy principle inherits from
the traditions that that have replaced Newtonian physics so there's there's that in all of that
interests me very much but I in the time remaining to us I would rather because I'm aware we have
limited time remaining I would rather start with this observation which is which is more concrete
you know I'm a clinician I work with neurological and neurosurgical patients every day and so I
witness you know what happens if a piece of your brain is missing and I've been around for a sufficient
number of years to have seen many many many patients with the same piece of their brain missing
and the curious or the interesting fact is that they all misperceive reality in the same way you
know that that's for example an excellent example is right parietal low patients who
they paralyzed on the left side and they believe they're not and it's patently obvious that they
are you know but they say no I'm not and so you know you see one and another and another and
eventually you realize hang you know if you haven't got a right parietal low you just there's a piece
of reality that you just don't get and never can get why because you've got a piece of your
brain missing that you need in order to be able to get that so you can from that observation
you can you can extrapolate that well all of us have a piece of our brains missing in the sense
that you know we we only have this what if we were to all have an additional lobe or an additional
hemisphere how much more would we be able to to register and compute and comprehend you know
than we currently do so so all I'm saying there is that I again on the basis of my own empirical
clinical experience you know I'm totally ready to believe that we have a horribly limited
conception and perception of reality I'm totally sympathetic with that however you know we are
where we are so you can either say okay I'm going to become a mystic you know because I don't do
anything I'm just going to believe everything or you know it's all you all you say well you know
given given the limited nature of my instrument you know I must do the best I can to to to expand
its bounds to test my hypotheses and you know be ready to find that my predictions were wrong
and I must update my predictive model and so on I didn't see what else we can do I so so so although
I am totally aware of the limits of the of the human brain it's just obvious from what I've just
said and of the limits of science because it's a method it's a it's a method ultimately you have
to have we were talking about idealism and never got back to it but you know ultimately you have
to have faith and I use that word advisedly that there is some reality beyond what I'm perceiving
that I'm probing and that you know I that I that the the the inferences that I draw
and the models that I build each time are less bad you know that that I that they they they
of course they're not reality of course they are a pathetic you know scrap of what we are
capable of grasping of the nature of the universe really but it's but we're making progress each
of us in our own lives and as a species over generations we have less bad models less less
bad understandings and but it is all based on faith you know that that this method is a reasonable
way of of proceeding um it is a matter you know you rarely can say well because it's so limited
because it's so so um unknowable reality in itself and all of that I'm just going to give up
that that's another approach that but I would rather take the scientific approach I just think
we need to have humility as scientists and recognize how how little we know but the very
physics that Hoffman um um sites as evidence for how little we know is the product of that method
you know that it has led us to know that reality is weird and it is very different from from how
we perceive it but but you know Hoffman couldn't have couldn't have come to that view if it wasn't
for the application of the scientific method to arrive at that physics in the first place when
Hoffman when Hoffman so apparently he did the calculations and he and he asked like what are
the probabilities of that our perception of reality would give us an accurate representation
of reality based on natural selection and fitness and actually evolving and surviving
and when you when you when you notice that the probability came to zero apparently had to take
a seat because he's very much a scientist and he loves the scientific method natural selection
all of it so you're here to take a seat because it like messed him up with his fundamental
perception of reality because he was very much materialistic thinker in terms of consciousness
and so it's on that note if what are you you spoke about faith there Mark I mean part of
this podcast also is for the people questioning these big topics often are trying to also find
meaning and purpose while not understanding what's really going on what are what are your
religious or spiritual beliefs and first of all I want to come back one step in our conversation
to this materialist the idea of materialist and mind versus matter and so on you know I to me
mind and matter are the same as what I was saying earlier when I said that there's a there's a
dual aspect to our monistic essence matter for me is an aspect in other words I don't think
matter is a fundamental property I think matter is a way of representing things and and that's
entirely consistent also with the the the the recent physics that we were talking about earlier
matter is not a fundamental property of the universe and the the the the so I'm not a
materialist this segues into your question now you know I I'm not a materialist I'm a dual aspect
monist who says that the material and the ideal that these are two different ways of knowing
of perceiving something which is ultimately unknowable and that's what you and I have just
been talking about the limits of science the humility that scientists have to have in the face
you know of the of the of the massive uncertainties in the universe so so my spiritual position
arises from that in other words it's one of humility I'm sorry maybe you've got the impression of me
as a kind of a pompous or noisy guy I don't know it might be hard for you to to equate
my my personality with humility but it really it is as a scientist and as as a spiritual being
my not only is it my belief that I even find solace in it Tevin I find solace in
what I don't know think I what I know I don't know you know these things are way beyond my can
questions like what happens after I die they're not empirical questions I can't
any prediction I come up with I can't test it until I'm dead you know so so and I accept that
and I say again I take I take comfort in it is there a god you know is there an afterlife
what does it all mean you know I genuinely don't know and and and so it's a kind of an
agnostic position but it is not a materialist and not an atheist position yes but but within that
within those parameters and I'm sorry I'm sort of repeating myself I then have to say okay
given those limitations what is to be done and I say well you've got to do the best you can with
what you've got and so you know so the best I've been able to come up with is science you know I've
read okay which of these things you know which of these things gives me the greatest confidence that
well yeah I might find answers or at least I might find less ignorance that's that's the
approach that that that I take and fully fully aware of the limits of the you know the limits of
the conclusions that I can come to now within that frame of reference and this is probably
be the last thing that we'll talk about I in other words using a scientific
methodology a scientific epistemology to to try to address these questions
I I think that our values you know I was talking much earlier in our conversation about
the fundamental value system of living things is that it's good to survive and bad not to
that that built upon those fundamental values or other also phenotypic values you know like
it's like it's it's bad to be in danger that's fear you know it's it's it's irritating and
frustrating to have an impeding things preventing you from that's that's rage you know that it's
bad to separate a little dependent creature from its caregiver you know that that's got to do with
attachment bonds and so on I think that these evolved endophenotypes is a word that's sometimes
used for them that they are they are basic values that we have just because we're living things and
that they are then more elaborated values that we have just because we are mammals and I think
that these provide and you know it's famously said that you can't derive an orc from an is
but I think that from these is is we can derive some orcs like I've just done bad to separate bad
to bad to injure people or injure living things it's bad to it's bad to for sentient things rather
it's bad to to separate mammals from their caregivers it's it's bad to to to you know
unnecessarily frustrated and be sentient beings and so on I think that our much more elaborated
human value systems which of course have evolved also to to to manage much more artificial
environments for which we were not evolutionarily prepared like like like like you know
agricultural and permanent settlements and and everything that flowed from that
in a private property and all of that there's a lot more that's that the values that we've
built on top of those phenotypic values but I think those phenotypic values and biological
values are the starting point of all of our values all of our values they're not they're not the
values of the universe they are our the values of us living things who have skin in the game
I look I love that mark I mean look you didn't come across as pompous or arrogant in any way
and neither does you I'm relieved I loved reading it I enjoyed it so much I mean
there's something Raymond Tellis once said I like this term he says he's ontologically agnostic
but I mean epistemologically we trust science the most is what what you're basically trying to say
that's right that's right no Mark thank you so much for this conversation I really enjoyed
myself thank you more words from your side well thank you very much and apologies again as you
can see I've lost my this is uh this is how unpredictable and uncertain the world is yeah
but I'm very glad to be speaking to you as a fellow South African and I'm glad that we are both
here these are the problems that belong to me and I'm very happy to be grappling with them
yeah and proud to know that that that that you're a South African your podcast is just great
thanks Stephen for inviting me