Su, I'm so glad we managed to reschedule this. Is the sound working fine? The internet connection
is great this time. Everything works. Good. I think so, yeah. Okay, my side, it's perfect.
How was the retreat, Su? Oh, the retreat was fantastic. I can't remember whether I told you.
I didn't want to go. I'd kind of signed up half-heartedly and the weather being here and
being over 20 degrees is amazing and sunny and I thought, you know, all this meditating all the
time, I wasn't looking forward to it and it was brilliant. The teacher, I really went because
of the teacher, Fiona Nuttall. She's a Zen master and extraordinary teachings and the Zen interviews.
You know, this is part of Zen retreats is the interviews and she just really rings things out
of you that you don't know are there and then sends you back to work. I can just talk merely from
your energy right now. You look in a great place. The other thing was in these particular type of
retreats, there were two work periods of an hour each in the day where you could be sweeping the
floors, cleaning the toilets, chopping vegetables in the kitchen and this lovely sunny weather,
you know, and you don't have any choice and I got gardening so I'm very happy. That's very
unzen, isn't it? Because you just do what you do because you don't do it and, you know, not care
about the outcome but it meant I was outside at each day doing hard physical labor which I'd much
rather do than chopping vegetables or something like that. So yeah, it was very good. As for,
you know, great insights, well a lot happened. It was, you know, struggling with a koan for
a week. I see. Things happened. Do you feel like philosophically any changes fundamentally in your
views? No but I think my way of thinking about things is kind of loosened up
and I spend quite a lot of time as you realise thinking about the mind-body problem, the nature
of mind, the nature of agency and how we wrongly feel we're controlling things and
this koan work tends to hint at those but I can't say I've got some great philosophical
breakthrough now, sorry. Well, I think while we're on that, it's the perfect time. I think
let's take the listeners and the viewers on a journey soon. If you could give me a history
of the mind-body problem from your perspective, I'm curious to know which aspects of this story
you tell me right now. Gosh, you kind of ask the question is though I'm a philosopher and I'm not
or are you doing something much more personal? No, no, I think in general what if you had to
think of the story of the mind-body problem, which names come to mind, what type of philosophies or
even psychology, neuroscience, which icons or figures in history come to mind when you think of
this infamous problem? I'm going to disappoint both you and your listeners because I don't really,
as I said, I'm not a philosopher. I don't remember the names of all the brilliant
philosophers and I kind of, you know, I know this problem goes way, way back into ancient Greeks but
you know, I don't, I'm not going to pull any names out of the non-existent that's on my head.
I don't think in that way about it. I think about it every day in terms of
what's out there and what's in here and is there a difference between inside and outside and so on.
But if I can twist that around to why it's been so important to me, like so many things in my life,
it goes back to the very dramatic outer-the-body experience or mystical experience both that I
had when I was 19, which is a very long time ago, which convinced me completely of a dualist view
as it convinces so many people. I think it's Thomas Metzinger who said, you know, anyone who has that
kind of experience must become a dualist, a substance dualist indeed. And so that becoming
utterly convinced of a dualist view and then actually deciding to devote my life to instead of,
you know, I had a, what I imagine would have been a very good PhD place at Sussex University,
which now has the, you know, the Sussex Consciousness Lab there. Not that it would have in those days but
you know, I turned that down because I wanted to prove dualism. I wanted to prove, you know,
astral planes and all these other worlds and everything and show that scientists were closed
minded as I'm often being accused of being. And so I set about it experimentally, being really
an experimental psychologist, not a philosopher. And all the evidence I got was suggested I was
wrong and so I had to turn to my mind. And since then, which you were talking now,
late 70s, early 80s. Since then, I've been pondering how on earth to make any kind of
monist, any kind of neutral monism actually work. I think, look, so for me, it's very difficult to
actually have a very skeptical interview with you. And it's because you were part of shaping
many of my own views. Yeah, so a big, a big chunk of my dissertation focused on illusionism. So
illusionism as a theory of consciousness, I used psychiatry to defend illusionism as a
theory of consciousness. I quoted you a couple times. And I've obviously
particular, I cited you many times and particularly the delusion aspect of it all. So there's many
aspects where I want to come as a skeptic, but I just cannot because fundamentally, I think
there's so many aspects of this that we agree on. It's going to make this very difficult.
But I think that's exciting anyway, because what I want to know is when you came to the conclusion
of illusionism as a theory of consciousness, I know so many people in your life influenced you,
people like Dawkins. I know Dennett's part of those people who you support in terms of certain
views. I know nowadays you disagree with many aspects. Perhaps Free Will will be one of them.
No, that's the only, that's really the only one. I mean, basically, I'm a Dennettian and, you know,
I love it when I find something I disagree with him about, we can have a great argument, you know.
Your books, Dennett's books, all together on my shelf. So you guys all come together in a nice
So when Frankish published the paper, Illusionism, and he had all you guys together,
Graziano, yourself, there were many of you guys together. Tell me about that journey. How did
that come about? I think Clive Frankish wrote and told me he had been invited to do this special
issue and asked me whether I'd like to write it, write something. And I was then thinking a lot
about the things that I wrote about in there. A lot of my thinking is taking direct experience
and trying to analyze it. So in that paper that I wrote, I wrote about an experience where
I've been on, I can't even remember what island this was, but anyway, I was on some island walking
up quite steep, rough sort of steps going up. And I really wanted to get to the top
in time to be able to go down and catch the boat back to wherever I'd come from.
And I can remember that as I was walking and and being mindful, somehow or another, I realized
that a few moments before I had, I thought, am I going to get there in time? And I thought, oh,
yes, because it's only five past 12. Hang on a minute. I must have just a few moments before
looked at my watch and I looked at it again. And it was five past 12 without in any normal
sense of the word being conscious of it. And this brought up all the sort of Donetti and kind
of thoughts. Well, what's going on? Right this moment now being mindful, I can say, this is what
I'm mindful of. This is what I'm conscious of. This is what I'm doing. If I cast my mind back
to a moment before it doesn't have to be very long. I really don't know what I was conscious of.
Doesn't make any sense. This is one of the things where Dennett says,
there is no fact of the matter. If you ask what was I conscious of a moment ago, there is no
fact of the matter. And yet we assume that there is an answer to that question that at all times
during the day, when whatever we're doing, we're conscious of something or another. Well, that's
simply not true, I think. So I kind of wrote my article for this around that experience and what
it means for why we're deluded. And the reason I say delusionism rather than illusionism is
illusions brings to mind very much sensory illusions, vision and hearing and so on that
where you get things, you know, there's the difference between reality and appearance.
But the delusion I was more interested in the kind of folk theories we make up about consciousness.
And one of those is that at all the times when we're awake and in that sense conscious, there
must be something we're conscious of and other things we're not conscious of. And that's not
true. And then I think because I tend to write not terribly academically, acceptably, I tend to
write rather personally, oh, I think this and I have this experience and this is what it means.
And so then Keith started to say, well, can you change this and can you change that? And then
actually he tried changing things for me. And then I was like, no, you can't do that. I wouldn't
ever say that. And we sorted it all out. And in the end, I was very happy with it. So that's sort
of how it came about and what happened. And then there are all these other interesting papers in
the same issue, which then became a book. I find Frankish's view too difficult for me to really
understand. You say illusionism is a theory of consciousness. It's not really, it's a whole
bunch, it's more like it's an approach to consciousness. It's a way of thinking about
consciousness, which has many variations. Yes, sorry, continue. No, no, go on. I was going to say
because yes, because you define illusionism very differently from what Frankish is talking about.
Yeah, that's right. You see it more as a way to rectify and clarify other views of consciousness,
whereas Frankish is talking about the phenomenal aspect of consciousness. Do you want to clarify
that in your own words? Well, yes, I think he starts by saying that the phenomenal properties
don't exist. Well, I'm immediately thrown into, but I'm not a philosopher and I don't know what you
mean. The other day, Bernardo Castro said to me, if something exists, it has properties. And I'm
going, well, I don't know about, I don't really know how philosophers define existence or properties,
and I don't want to go through the painful, I've got enough to learn that's really interesting
in neuroscience and psychology. And I try and read philosophical things, but I don't think I'm ever
going to get my head around exactly what Frankish means. And whether it's the same as what Dennett
means or not, going back to what you've already elucidated, it's the way Dennett pulls apart
the mistakes we make, the pits we fall into, the errors that just abound all over the place
that appeals to me. And by calling my approach delusionism, I suppose I'm just trying to say,
look, I'm not, I don't agree with all the other people, I'm not saying I'm right or better,
but I'm more interested in the kind of semi-intellectual ways we get things wrong,
and the assumptions we make, than I am in making an actual theory. Because I don't think
I don't think any of these have an actual theory, except possibly with the exception of
Michael Graziano, who refuses to call himself an illusionist. And it's an illusionist theory,
for goodness sake, Michael. I think he's a bit cowardly, really. I understand it, I get it,
you know, if he calls it an illusion, people will misunderstand. I've had that all the,
all the time I've been working on consciousness. You know, people say, you say consciousness
doesn't exist. I don't say that at all. I say it's illusion. How do you define illusion?
Something that's not what it seems to be. And that's really, if I want to say anything I will
say, 100% sure that I believe, it's only that, that consciousness as normally conceived of by
most people, it's not what it seems to be. Graziano was one of the first people I interviewed
for this podcast. And I remember when we spoke about, prior to that, he helped me out with my
dissertation. And we discussed the fact that attention schema theory is most certainly an
illusionist theory of consciousness. It's, it approaches it fundamentally by saying that what
we seem to believe is consciousness is merely an interpretation of what we think is happening around
it. But he calls it a caricature. And in my own work, I also said, I believe that if some,
if you believe something is an illusion, there's no point in changing the words around it. You
might as well just change other people's perceptions about the actual word. Because
an illusion is defined as an emiss interpretation of a sensory stimulus that does exist. So you
cannot say that it doesn't exist. There is a stimulation that's happening that does exist.
And that's fundamentally where I think Keith and you differ because you agree that something's
happening. I am not necessarily agreeing what you just said that it's a, it needs to be a sensory
stimulus. Yes. Well, does it? Um, I don't think so. It's a misinterpretation of a stimulus that
exists. Okay. But can that be an internal stimulus? I mean, because I'm thinking the whole gamma of
experience, including sensory impressions, where we make a, um, a reality appearance distinction,
that's one sort of illusion. But when it comes to, you know, my own, I'm shutting my eyes,
it's dark. I'm, you know, I'm thinking about something that, you know, I'm thinking to myself,
Oh, what I'm conscious of now, if I think that way, is my own thoughts about whatever it is,
what I'm going to do tomorrow or something, you know, that's not a sensory stimulus. In fact,
it's not really stimulus unless you say this bit of brain is stimulating another bit of brain. So
I just quibble slightly there. Yes. So I would say something is happening. And somebody's responding
to something that's happening. Something's responding to something that's happening. Um,
like Dennett, who begins, um, his 1991 consciousness explained with sitting in his rocking chair,
appreciating the way the light is, you know, fully on the dapples on the leaves and all that.
You know, I take as a similar view. I mean, look, there's this, ha, but
the leap that's so easy to make is there's this out there and there's me in here. And that's
already an interpretation. And that's an illusion. So that's where I take off from. And I, I define
illusion is an illusion much more simply having looked it up in various, you know, OED and other
such places as something that is not what it seems to be. That's, that's kind of vaguer. And I'm
happier with that. Yeah. Now, I think what you're doing is basically it's intuition pumps for
thought thinking about consciousness. It's pretty much trying to show people that, okay, look,
there's something happening. We don't know what it is, but assuming that you can find certain
entities or an Ian Vitale or an answer that's going to come out is just the wrong approach.
So searching for a neural correlate of consciousness is not the right way.
And it's amazing how popular that has, you know, good for Francis Crick and Christoph Koch,
starting the whole framework for consciousness and let's, I mean, Crick said, you know, we can't
jump straight in at causal explanations. We have to start with correlations. So what do we do?
Well, here's this problem consciousness, let's look for the neural correlates. Great, as a starting
point. But when you really start thinking through intuition pumps and delusions and what have you,
it doesn't make sense anymore, because it relies on the assumption we were discussing earlier,
that there are some brain processes that are conscious and there are other ones that are
not conscious. And that is such a tempting illusion. But it's not, in my opinion, it's not true.
At what point did you realize, because there's so many different studies that show us that we're
not seeing reality for what it is. Heuristic adaptations, perhaps, shortcuts in our processing,
limited processing, perceptual experiences. So we can't even see outside the optical window,
we can only see ROYGBIV. At what part were you looking at all this information and finally
concluded, okay, you know what, there is no fundamental entity called consciousness that we
are searching for? Well, you ask that question in a way that assumes that there is some sense in
saying the world as it actually is. Yes, I must say, I'm more tempted nowadays to theories that
don't say that. I'm very tempted by various kinds of panpsychism, none of which I can fully endorse,
by information based ideas, that everything fundamentally comes down to information. So
I've been struggling without enough maths with thermodynamics and other ideas about
energy and information and evolution and how these things work. And really struggling with
some kind of straight idealism doesn't work in the sense that, you know, if everything is mental,
how on earth do you explain why we agree about things about the outside world, what you were
saying, you know, how the outside world really is? Well, I'm not going to go that far, but you
can agree that, you know, you can see my picture, I can see your picture, I can see the cupboards
behind you and the whatever, you know, and I'm pretty sure I could predict, this is kind of
important really, that if you went, turned around and pulled a book out, you know, there'd be a space
in the bookshelf. Interestingly, I've got particularly fascinated recently with predictive
processing and Bayesian brain type theories. And when I'm thinking about all this stuff,
what is the world? What is the relationship between this body and this thinking and everything and
that plant you can't see behind the screen? It's always, well, if I did that, if you turned around
and took your book out, if I picked up these glasses, then I would find they felt like this.
It's always if at last something makes sense, of course, because the predictive processing
theories are saying that that that all all of perception and of thinking indeed, and of, well,
I'll leave Pontius for a moment, but all all that is making predictions. That's what system is. So
I try to work from first principles with that sort of idea. So here's a clever brain,
multiply, it must be a kind of tangled hierarchy. It's not hierarchy with, I think,
with me at the top controlling everything, which is kind of how it seems. But it's
hierarchical, nevertheless. And at every level, there are predictions referring to the lower
level and so on. And that begins to make sense of the world, but brings me right back to, well,
then what's it all made of that's doing this? And it also raises the question of, well, does
Bayesian brain approach actually turn into a theory of consciousness and not necessarily?
So I've been playing in fact, when I was on the retreat one evening, I was, we get a little bit
of free time and I went sat under a tree, and was kind of thinking about this with respect to the
tree that that I was looking at, and trying to think about what can underlie this on any kind of
modest view. And again, coming back to kind of fundamental thoughts about information and prediction.
You see, I can't give any answers. I mean, I'm really struggling with all this stuff. I don't
have my own theory beyond, beyond everyone's else is deluded. And so am I. Look, I completely agree
with you because when I came when I started this podcast, I was so I initially came to it with a
very emergentism approach. So I thought at some point, okay, these layers will eventually
culminate into an experience that we call consciousness. Then I went down the very
illusionist path. And I think fundamentally, my view is most likely aligned with that stall.
But as you're saying, after speaking to so many people and reading so many other philosophers
and thinkers, you start to question reality in general, because materialism as it stands
matter, we really just don't understand what matters. And I think that's the fundamental
problem why we cannot ever talk about reality in a way where we think what reality could ever be
is something beyond. So I completely agree with you. So even when I said that, look, when
there's certain things we cannot see in terms of reality, I still honestly do have no idea
what we should be seeing. So I agree on that. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I get quite annoyed. Got,
you know, bored of being annoyed that people just assume I'm a materialist. And I said,
no, I think materialism doesn't work any better than idealism work. And, you know,
that's why I call myself a neutral monist. But then when I look that up as what it actually
means in philosophical terms, it gets a little bit complicated. I think, God, I'm not that all I'm
saying is all I can say for sure is dualism doesn't work. For me, was Raymond Tellis,
he once said he's ontologically agnostic. And I like that. Oh, that's a nice phrase.
I really do. Yeah, because because ever since he said that, I think that's the
term I go to all the time. I'm ontologically agnostic. But when it comes to epistemology and
the stories we've been telling each other, I think I'm pretty much almost atheist towards
those stories or a whatever that theory is. Yeah, it doesn't have to have God, does it? A
theory story, something or another. Yes. Exactly. But I think it's a beautiful term,
ontologically agnostic. Thank you. When you think about your okay, so your journey,
you obviously at some point concluded, okay, these theories and the way we're approaching
this isn't working. It came down to ask yourself these questions. Am I conscious now? That was a
big part of your paper. Am I conscious now? Marvin Minsky once said, if you asked a computer,
if it's conscious now, it doesn't matter because humans can't answer that question. Anyway,
we spend most of our lives in autopilot. So if we ever expect a computer to really think about
the fact that it's conscious, we really do it ourselves. Is there anything you want to add on
that? Yeah, well, the large language models make that very interesting, don't they? Because
given that, I mean, the terrible thing is that they just amplify the idioses of what humans
say and write. So I imagine I've not tried this out, keep thinking I should spend some time playing
around with one of them. But, you know, given that so many people say, well, of course, I'm
conscious, then presumably picking it up from the massive database of everything people have said,
then these so-called AIs have not really, but, you know, we'll just say the same. Yes, of course,
I'm conscious. I mean, if they can say, oh, I love you and I want to be with you and all those
ridiculous things that they do, they're going to say they're conscious and that doesn't tell us
anything at all any more than it tells us when somebody else says they're conscious. But that
question that you say that I wrote in that paper, that was 2016, I think that illusionism thing.
I've been thinking about this question a lot longer than that. And it kind of began, I suppose,
when I was happily a colleague of mine. In fact, he was also a Zen master. He was a
John Crook, a biology lecturer at Bristol University and a Zen master. And I was learning
to meditate with him. And this is going back to the 80s. And he was teaching a course that was
sort of involved quite a lot of consciousness. And he wanted to leave and devote himself more
to running retreats and so on. And so I took over this course. And I began teaching that
in the late 80s at some point, with a lot of, you know, there's so little was was known then.
And then in 1991, sort of early in my first few years of teaching, it's outcame Dennett's book.
And that really changed things and really forced me to think. And I met him, he came to Bristol
and gave a lecture and that really fired me up. And that made me do the first ever experiment on
change blindness, which worked out amazingly. And he predicted that it would work. And I thought,
well, I can do that, you know, and did with a student. So when I was teaching that course,
I was already asking myself, well, I'm talking about consciousness. Well, what is it? Okay,
I'm conscious now. Or am I? What does that mean? And so I began right from the beginning of that
teaching near the beginning anyway, getting the students to do what I did. In other words,
to ask themselves many, many, many times a day, am I conscious now? The first thing I learned is
that they won't do it. Or most of them won't do it. Or the ones who say they're going to do it,
find it really hard to do. And at the end of the week, when they come back, let's say these
in those days were nice small classes, I have like 30 or 40 students and, you know,
and I could ask them all how many people did it, what happened? Most of them forgot to do it or
tried and didn't really get anywhere. Some had really insightful experiences and began to question
they had this shock, which I've written about as you probably know, but this kind of shock when
you go, are you conscious now? Hey, are you? I don't know whether I can get you to have it. But
you know, you suddenly think, Oh, well, of course I am. But a moment ago, I really don't know was
I it's as though I've woken up by asking the question. And in a way, I think this is a really
important point. I can even go so far as to say, you're not conscious unless you're asking yourself,
am I conscious? Exactly. It's that active awareness of the fact that you are asking yourself at least
it's almost that metacognition of it all. It is a metacognition, but it's a delusion,
isn't it? I mean, it's a word based thing. Am I conscious now is saying, and then you start looking
around and going, What am I conscious of? And, you know, that hence the second question in the
big textbook that I have follows. And I've just my daughter and I've just completed the fourth
edition, which will come out in a few months, I hope. And through all of the editions, every chapter
has one of these practices that I wanted students to do. I mean, a lot of them did get in the
hang of it after a while and they and really worked hard on it. But then it becomes, well,
what was I conscious of a moment ago? And lots of other questions of what, you know,
am I conscious of what what I was doing, all sorts of questions that that you can ask,
but they all depend on words. And if you do mindfulness practice without needing any words
by just kind of becoming present, then that gets you away from the wordiness a bit.
And then if you keep doing that a lot, then you're much more alert and open to what's going on.
But you can't really say anything more about it. And what's going on here? This is what's
really interests me. We fall back on these things that there's this thing called consciousness that,
you know, that we might find. And then we're back to the neural correlates of this thing
called consciousness, and it's got to be squirted out of the brain or, or as in the hard problem,
it's got to as Dave Chalmers put it, how does subjective experience arise from
objective activity in the brain. And so you come back to that sort of, to me, deluded idea that
consciousness is something that like toothpaste, it sort of comes out of your head.
You have to give me a definition of delusionism and perhaps compare it to illusionism.
How would you define and differentiate them?
Well, I would say that most versions of illusionism, I would agree with to the extent that they say
that something about our experience is not as it seems to be.
I'm more specifically saying, we are actively deluded about it. Not just that it's an illusion,
but it's a kind of thinking problem, because we jump so quickly to assumptions. And that, and
if you look up delusion and illusion, they're not really that different, but delusion carries more
of a kind of intellectual, wordy thinking thing. And I think that's why I used that word to show
that we make assumptions that we can describe in words. Well, I think consciousness is made in the
anterior of something or whatever. I think consciousness is a product of the brain. I
think consciousness extends beyond the brain into the astral worlds, or I think consciousness
survives death. Whenever we talk about, people talk about these things, they are kind of
reifying with words, this thing. And the word delusionism, I think, gets to that more.
Maybe it doesn't for everyone, but that's what I think is the difference. But it's not a huge
difference. It's just, I think, if people say that illusionism is a theory of consciousness,
you said this, and I think I would disagree in the sense that it's not one theory. It's not
a testable theory, as a whole theory. It's a bunch of approaches that different people have,
and they're all slightly different. And we probably all agree that in some fundamental way,
we've mostly got it wrong about the nature of consciousness, that we probably disagree about
where the origins of the mistakes are. Sorry, that's a bit rambly. I don't know whether that
answers your question. When I took illusion as a theory of consciousness, I was actually
directly quoting Frankish's paper, the headline. I think that's what he called it, illusionism as
a consciousness. So when I approached it, I used psychiatry to try and assist it and defend it.
But at some point, I used a lot of Carl Friston's work. I'm not sure. Are you familiar with Carl
Friston's work with the free energy? Well, I haven't read, I'm just started reading the latest book,
and it's very hard going. As I said, when my daughter and I were doing the fourth edition
of the textbook, I read a lot of the control hallucination sort of stuff, so predictive
processing. I think Carl Friston's work is brilliant, but I do not understand the maths.
I just simply do not have enough of a maths background to understand that. But I mean,
over the years, I've learned something about Bayesian theory, because it pops up in psychology
quite a lot. But I'm very much enamoured of the way that predictive processing is changing the
way we think about all sorts of things in psychology now, or in neuroscience. And I think
that's really going places. I think we're really going to get somewhere with that.
When I spoke to Carl, I actually asked him if he thinks when you apply his view of
Markovian Blankets, the understanding of the free energy principle, Bayesian brains,
does he think this is actually a theory that supports illusionism? And he said it, yes.
He actually said technically, it would, because when you take into account,
in my paper, and when I discuss this with him, if you take into account the prior information
you receive, because that's a fundamental aspect of all of this, you're taking a lot of
prior information, and then you make posterior conclusions regarding your experience. If most
of your prior information tells you things like, I'm a self, I'm a person, I have a conscious entity,
your most likely posterior outcome is going to be, I am a self, I am a person, I have consciousness.
And then at some point, I used your work to say, if you define a delusion, a fixed false belief,
and if already the illusion has promoted a false belief, it becomes fixed at some point because
of all the prior information you've already received regarding this. And at some point,
that's why delusionism is bound to occur. And I think that's how I sort of work.
Great. I must watch this, your discussion with him, which I should, but there are so many things
to watch and listen to. It's a wonderful world, but it's also so difficult to choose, but I will
do that. But you were talking about Markov Blankets and Free Energy Principle and so on.
Again, the maths defeats me when it comes to Markov Blankets, although I do want to pursue
that more. But I have spent quite a lot of time thinking about the Free Energy Principle, because
it relates to what I was saying earlier about my interest in whether we can base an entire world
on some kind of informational theory, and trying to struggle with how that relates to Gibbs Free
Energy. And there are relationships between them. But again, I don't have all the background
skills to do very well with this, but I really think this is important and will help us a lot.
And I agree. I think so as well. I think at this point in your career, which aspects of this problem
or is it free will? Is it consciousness still? What's intriguing you the most at this point?
Well, you say at this point in my career, did you say?
So much. I mean, if you think about it, your work spans on so many different aspects. You
talk about memes, you talk about consciousness, free will, Paris psychology, there's so many
different elements to your career that it makes it quite difficult for one to actually try and do
an interview. Which is why I don't call it a career, because I only had a proper job for a few
years, because I couldn't quite hack it. I prefer to work by myself sitting here, you know. So I,
you know, I always kind of feel a bit surprised. I mean, my initial reaction to that question is
I'm really struggling with, you know, I'm 71, surely. And people are always saying to me,
Oh, you don't need to work anymore. You should be. And I have a big garden on the river. And,
you know, I'm spending a lot of time growing vegetables. And why don't you just do that?
Oh, and I do painting and kayaking and weightlifting and all kinds of things. You know,
why don't you just do those things and forget all that work? When I'm sitting there doing the
email, I'm like, Oh, God, you know. And so you could say at this point, I give it all up. But
that's not true. The more serious answer is it's really we've we've touched on this many times
already. It's really the what is the nature of the world? How does a world sustain what appears
to be dual existence observers and observed experiences and experiences when I believe
and so do you, I think that there is no true observer observing them. And you can have and
importantly, you can have experience without an experiencer with a lot of practice. And that's
really interesting how brains, you know, if you are in the delusion of the self is really in charge,
then it becomes really peculiar to think, Well, I am trying to get rid of myself.
I am trying to not believe anymore in me, you know, those kinds of things you get in all sorts
of tangles. And yet certain processes lead to a brain that is more adept at dropping some kinds
of illusions. So part of the answer to your interesting and difficult question is, that's
why I still go on retreats. This particular one I've just come back from was a co on retreat.
And I had a really, really tricky and interesting co on, which I have not resolved, which is good,
because then I can keep, it can keep working, but has had some quite profound effects on me
with all the struggles going on. So that's one way. And again, that's not a career is it,
but that's one way that I want to engage by doing I meditate every day and have done for
40 years nearly. To practice and train this brain and then thinking sort of memetically and
evolutionarily. It's not me train the brain. It's this person being having picked up
Zen meditation memes over there is somehow thinks it's worth doing and goes on doing,
you know, you when he's tried to dismantle those those prior assumptions about self,
you start thinking in these weird ways. So that's one big streak of it. The other has been
for my daughter and I doing this fourth edition and me getting into the predictive
processing, I'm still really interested in that. And I've got two books at the moment that I want
to read relevant to that. I've also got totally different thread going on, which I started last
year writing a book called, well, it's pretend possible title is God's memes, how and how
religions evolve to exploit us and why we let them. So you can imagine this is, you know,
they are memes out there, horrible meme plexus that get into people's heads and then you can't
get them out. So I'm reading books now about sort of mental immunity and that kind of thing. So I'm
doing that and it's all so I can't give you an answer. Perhaps I should. I think all my friends
and family will say for goodness sake, give an answer just decide what you're going, you know,
but I can't I just get I just keep thinking and being tempted by difficult ideas.
I remember there was a time where I was about, I think I was about nine and and at that point I
became very atheist to a point where I was very anti-theist. And I still remember as the years
went on, where were you living then? What sort of situation were you in? I'm from South Africa,
but I'm from Indian descent. But in South Africa, Indians have been living here for almost I think
about 160 plus years. So we're generations in at this point. And I think I'm like eight.
So did you have religious parents or I'm just I think so they are they couldn't they Hindu
by origin. Some of my family are Islam. I've a Muslim, so they follow Islam. And but I grew up
very much Hindu. But at some point, not really convinced about it. But I think my dad
subliminally just tried to hint me towards non-believing like just not doing it. You know,
he constantly made me watch National Geographic. He made me he wanted me to break away from
it somehow. So it happened very early on. And I remember throughout the years, I was very
anti-theist. And it was when I started coming across a lot of your guys work. So so Dennett,
Dawkins, Hitchens. And I still remember thinking, I mean, this this finally I found this group of
people where they're thinking the same thing. I'm pretty much it's all I've been thinking about.
When you find yourself writing this book at this point, I'm not as anti-theist as I used to be.
I mean, I can understand why we think this and why we get to that point. But I remember you first
break out, it's almost kind of like you want to go all out and and get the best arguments.
Do you feel like that's changed for you over the years where you found yourself constantly wanting
to battle and debate? And now you kind of just like, I might as well just let the person think
what they want until it sort of involves something that's going to directly. Well, this is why I was
interested in where you were coming from, because I was brought up as a Christian. My mother was a
was quite serious Christian. I mean, in the Church of England sort of way,
when she went to church most Sundays, I occasionally went and I had phases. So I didn't
ever have any, you know, really violently. I just remember as a teenager, just I went to the most
horrendous boarding school, and we had to go to chapel every day and twice on Sundays. And I, you
know, it was so boring. And then I began to think, well, it's also rather stupid and doesn't make sense.
And so I became quite quite atheist, but not in an aggressive kind of way. Then at the age of 26,
I fell deeply in love. And both of us became kind of a bit Christian again. And we had to
get married in a Christian church, because that was what you did in those days and where we were.
And that lasted maybe a year or two and kind of gently fizzled out. So I was a very different
kind of experience from you. When I've been trying to write this book, I certainly how I
should admit that I have some times when I'm thinking, and I want to write, this is total crap,
yo, what idiot can believe this, you know, and I think, well, it's not very constructive. And
actually, they're not all idiots who believe these things. Oh, I've had the most twice recently
had time to talk at length with the Archbishop of Canterbury, Justin Welby. And he is such an
interesting man. There is an intelligent kind, as far as I can tell, public spirited, longing to
help people, person who will talk to me as an atheist in a very friendly and open way. And I
try to remember people like that. Now, I think he is completely deluded about the nature of the
universe and how we got here and everything else. But I really like talking to him about it. So I
guess that helps me be a little more flexible in the way I use my atheism.
Yeah, my girlfriend is Christian, and I know she is a believer in it. But I feel like this age,
and at this time in my life, it's no longer a thing, because I know if it was 10 years ago,
it would be something that would be a deal break. Ultimate, it would be done. But at this,
I often think when you're talking about this, I remember the conversation you had with
Jordan Peterson, and you guys discuss this, do you, now while writing this book,
are you looking back at certain conversations like that, and formulating counter arguments to
someone like Jordan, who's very good at arguing and counter points, even though you fundamentally
obviously disagree with? Oh, that was a quite scary encounter. But I saw a little bit of it the
other day, because somebody asked me, I get so confused about all these things, but somebody
asked me to go on their podcast or something. I haven't gone anywhere with this yet. It was
literally yesterday, and that he was putting together some kind of something or other that
included clips for me and Jordan Peterson. And so I watched it, it was very short, you know,
like a minute. I thought, oh, good for me. I actually stood up to him and argued back. I mean,
God, I knew nothing about it. I had not even heard of him. When Premier Christian Radio it was,
the discussion was on. I'd done things for, Justin Briley runs it, and I'd done things for him
before and enjoyed it very much. So I was happy to go along. And I had to look up Jordan Peterson,
but you know, time being what it is. I read his, I read his book most of it on the train going up
to London. It's three and a half hours from here. And it's 12 rules for living, which had quite an
impact on me, because some, you know, ludicrous things in there, and yet it's a bestseller,
and people follow the rules, and one must be nice to cats. And I mean, there's weird things in there.
Like make your bed and small things. Yes, yes, yes, quite good advice. And yet the whole
thing's wrapped up in these weird stuff. And I was sitting there, kind of getting cross with it in
the train. And there was this elderly couple opposite me. Now, I mean, again, I'm interested in,
in where you were when you were growing up, because during my life here in England,
people have got less and less and less religious. So this is typical of me. I don't think first
before I speak. Sorry. But there was this elderly couple opposite me on the table in the train.
And I so went, I sort of looked up at them. I said, Oh, God, this book's doing my head in
or something like that. You know, oh, what is the book? And I said, Oh, that's really interesting.
I said, Oh, he believes in God. And I went to, you know, just that's the sort of thing I would
say. And they said, Yeah, isn't that trouble? And just to completely agree with me. And that is a
kind of assumption I occasionally fall foul of. I was on a group walk up on Dartmoor a couple of
weeks ago. And I happened to say something just assuming that the two people who were listening
to me wouldn't believe in God. And one of them said, Well, I think that something about Jesus
Christ is my, you know, whatever, should be more careful, or should I? And it always raises that
question. I think the fact that I can safely assume almost all the time that other people
around me don't believe in God. They're not thoughtful. I mean, they haven't thought through
their atheism to great deep degree. They just, they just, it's the normal thing around here,
you know, people in my village, we all go and sing Christmas carols at Christmas and thoroughly
enjoy ourselves. And so, and then, you know, those things in the Christmas carols like,
does not abhor the Virgin's womb, you know, I think, Oh, yeah. And so some of us women are
going, Virgin's women, you know, we're just having a laugh. And maybe some people in the
audience in the village, if there's about 100 of us there in the village square, you know,
who are really upset by what we're doing, but that's kind of the atmosphere that I live in.
So it's very easy to be loosely atheist or more strictly atheist and not have to make a big fuss
about it. I still do remember that was quite a long time ago, because at that point, I don't
think Jordan was at this level of, of, of fame and popularity is at this point. It was around
the time I think Sam and him also got into a huge debate and they had that two part series where
they got really into it. In doing your research, I mean, are you rereading books like The God
Delusion or Why God is Not Great by Hitchens? Are you, how's your research process going with this
book? So the specific question, I started reading Hitchens again. And like the first time, I
really disliked it intensely. It's unkind, spiky. Very aggressive, yes. I don't, I don't like it.
The God Delusion, I may well read again. But most of my research has been online finding
things out. I mean, the things I found out like, okay, it seems to me that religions should
make people behave like their religion tells them and therefore be kinder and more altruistic. So
look into all the, you know, research evidence on, on whether it's true and it's not, you know,
and it was, the evidence goes in all sorts of directions, but basically it's not. And then I
got very interested in, in poverty and, you know, it's a very obvious, excuse me, it's a very obvious
fact about the world that the poorest countries are the most religious. Now, why is that? And then
there's Gregory Paul's research showing that if you compare developed countries
on what he calls a dysfunctional society scale against how religious they are, well,
the most religious countries are the most dysfunctional, meaning that the more religious
the country is, the higher rates it has of murder, teenage pregnancy, abortion,
various kinds of serious crime, incarceration rates. I mean, all the things that you would expect
that a religion would improve are actually very much worse. And then there's the question, why? So
we're back to causality and correlation. These are all correlations. Now it looks from the evidence
as though it's not that religions cause depravity, murder, incarceration rates, it's rather the
reverse. It's that living in a dysfunctional society where you are afraid for your health,
for your life, for everything makes you turn to religion. And then the means get hold of you
and you start to believe that you're good because you believe this stuff and you're good because
all of that and you're good because you oppose abortion and you whatever and you think people
should be locked up for whatever it is. And so the United States is particularly interesting
in that respect because it's a very rich country, but it has high rates of religion and it's so
different from the UK speaking sort of the same language, which we have a state religion and
they don't. It's so interesting that. So I mean, I just got myself hooked into, you know,
reading loads of stuff to draw and work out the effects of being captured by religious means.
I haven't read, I know Dawkins wrote a book, I think, it wasn't too long ago for,
was it for young teens, I think, for a book? What is it called? Do you remember? I forgot
the name of the book. No, and I haven't read it either. Maybe I should. There's so much to read
and it's so interesting. The reason why I'm asking about that is, I mean, I know that
Charles Darwin is a big inspiration for you. I mean, I love Charles Darwin. He's one of my
favorite people of all time, possibly. And, and I know Dawkins also up there, these guys,
how have they influenced your way of thinking overall in life? Oh, hugely. I mean, my two greatest,
if you have this lovely sort of dinner party thing, you know, who would you invite from the
Mount Rushmore? Your Mount Rushmore.
Why? I'm sorry, I'm not with you. So, you know, Mount Rushmore, the fourth figures,
the leading figures. It's not all those, yeah, but they're all presidents, weren't they?
But I mean, who would those four people be in terms of the thinkers? You're talking about the
dinner table. It's sort of a similar... Oh, no, yeah, yeah. That's so different, though. They're
not on a pedestal. They are. They are. I would like them, like the Archbishop of Canterbury. I
would like to sit down. I like so, my husband and I went to dinner with him. We sat around a
lovely table in Lambeth Palace and had a lovely chat. So, I'm thinking of that, not
so my top two would be Charles Darwin and William James. Now, we haven't mentioned William James,
but he is such a great hero of mine. Now, his two volumes of 1890, The Principles of Psychology,
has such a profound effect on me. And I keep thinking about him, how way ahead of his time he
was, and the way he thought about things. He clearly was struggling with the kind of problems
we've been talking about here, about dualism, about the nature of the world, the nature of the mind.
Can there be split personalities? And does that mean there's really somebody or not?
And I love one of his thoughts about, and this is all in the textbook, and my son, Julian, did a
lovely cartoon of cows, where he says the owner of the thought, and so the thought with a big T,
is then, in the next moment, passes off the owner of the cow's one, and then the thoughts,
passes them on. It's a new owner, but the same, you know, cows. There isn't a, there isn't a
continuous self. Exactly. I'm sorry about that. James's idea that, I mean, his chat is 100 pages,
his chapter on self, and it's really hard going, and I've read it a few times. I'd love to have
time to read it again, but I don't. But it very much fits with the kind of Buddhist
non-self, or another kind of view that the self isn't what you think it is. And the Buddha was
sometimes saying, there is a self in terms of isn't, which of course fits with the same thing.
There is this illusion, but there isn't the thing that you think the illusion tells you there is.
And William James was really struggling with all of that. So he would be, along with Darwin,
they're my two great historical figures that I so much admire. Of recently, well, I know Richard
Dawkins very well. He's been to stay here a few times. You know, I meet him anyway, so I don't
have to have a mythical dinner table. Then it's same. Yep. We have occasional meme lab meetings
here. We've got one coming up soon, and both of them have been to those, and we've been able to
have long chats about memes and things. And I admire both of them, but they're both still alive
and going strong, which is great. One of the William James quotes that come to my mind, because when
you think about, particularly what you're talking about with religion and how people are influenced
by other people and language, etc. I mean, he talks about how pruning of brains William James
once said, I think he said, for a child, sensory inputs, one great blooming, buzzing confusion.
I think it's something along those lines. Yes, yes, the blooming, buzzing confusion.
Yes. Because at some point, we just take in the information we receive, and then that point,
that becomes your fundamental beliefs. And if everything you, if all the memes you were gathering
over the years were about religion or about a specific view on consciousness, that's what
you're firmly going to believe at some point. But the buzzing, blooming confusion is very
interesting because it led to all these different arguments in psychology about just how much we
have prewired and how much we don't. So he was in the direction of, although not entirely,
in the direction of that it's not prewired, it's all got to be in response to the input,
which was a pretty novel idea then really. And now I think we know that there's quite a lot of
prewiring. But still, that the brain becomes organized by the organization in the, in the
structure of the input. So the visual cortex or auditory cortex get organized in the way the
input comes in. And now this is another thing to think about in terms of predictive processing.
So when you think about a system that is at many levels at once trying to predict what's
coming in the, from the next layer, that fits with it. Your, your baby with buzzing,
blooming, buzzing confusion is, is, you know, struggling. It's got a structure set up that
is capable to do this struggling, that is capable of making predictions, but they're going to be
really simple like to do with, if I put, we're back to, if, you know, if I put my arm here,
ooh, it hit something and then I'll predict and the way babies learn that and the way they blah,
blah, blah, blah, and gradually hone what the noises they make according to the responses and
so on. So yes, I think a lot of William James's ideas, not all, I mean, a lot of things he said
were simply bomb, you know, that he didn't have the physiology. But a lot of those ideas
are still helpful. I think one of my favorite quotes as well has got to be,
then it's illusion. I mean, consciousness is illusion off the brain for the brain,
by the brain. Oh, I've not heard that, but yes, yes.
Off the brain for the brain and by the brain. By the brain. Yeah.
When you hear something like that, what do you think? How do you think then it would approach
a lot of the new idealist theories that are coming out today? Any idea? I've spoken to him by email,
but seems to be relatively unavailable to chat on a podcast lately.
Oh, he's been terribly busy with all this paper on artificial persons and all the
danger of that because he normally replies to my emails very quickly and he didn't this time.
And then when he did replies, I've been totally snowed under with all this stuff.
And you know, so that's probably why I think he would be irritated by it,
but I don't know and I shouldn't speak for him. Now, I must say, I believe that when we fixed
this up a long time ago, I said I could only talk for an hour because you can tell I can't,
this is my problem. I've got chronic fatigue. It's not too bad at the moment,
but I can't not pour out lots of energy. So I've been sitting here really enjoying talking to you,
but it takes a lot of energy and I need to sort of collapse pretty soon.
So I completely understand. I know so much, but thank you. I really appreciate it. I've
been waiting a long time and hopefully in the future we can chat about something in a bit
more detail because there's so many topics I want to discuss with you.
Well, you asked brilliant questions. I do quite a lot of podcasts and they vary so much.
And you know, this is one of the fun ones where some of the questions are fun because I can
answer them easily. Others are fun because I can't answer them and you're really making me think
I'm pushing me and that's that's good. So thank you.
I really appreciate it. I mean, it's great to hear that. I feel much better
leaving this conversation knowing you feel that way. Thank you so much.
It's great. Have a great evening, Sue. And yeah, and we'll chat again.
Oh, let's do that. I would enjoy that. Thanks very much. Cheers.
Bye.