Would you like to know more?
Hello, Malcolm.
Hello, Simone.
I love your response.
I love that it is your signature greeting with people,
very high energy.
But I also think it is an element of your social autopilot.
Not that I don't have a social autopilot.
I'm on that right now.
But I think that's a really interesting part of human
existence, because for the vast majority of our lives,
I don't think we're actually, let alone not sapient,
not even really conscious, not even really aware
of what's going on.
Oh, yeah.
And I think it's so arrogant when people pretend
that they are aware of most of their lives.
We talk about something called road hypnosis,
where they look back on a drive and they're like,
I don't remember what I was doing during the drive.
Their brain just shuts off recording.
And the question is, how much of our life is road hypnosis?
And I think it's a huge portion of our life.
And it's something, this is what initially got us talking
about consciousness early in our relationship,
was how do we at least enter moments of lucidity
where we are aware of what's going on,
somewhat sentient, just long enough
to be able to change things about the internal self
model that does run our autopilot.
So that at least in the majority of the life
when we are on autopilot, we are better serving our values,
better people, more productive, more
emotionally in control, et cetera.
And I think our thought on consciousness
really evolved in interesting directions
from there when we started really
thinking about what consciousness means
and why maybe it exists.
So I think this will be really fun to talk about.
Why don't you talk a bit about what you think
sentience is?
I think sentience, our experience of consciousness,
in other words, is really an emergent property
of a memory compression system.
So imagine you have a building security system
with tons of different inputs.
It's a feed of doors opening and closing
within the building, a bunch of different camera feeds,
a chemical monitoring system coming in,
everything's feeding into this one control room
and then being put into a camera feed
and then being stored in memory.
And there's a man watching the security feed.
And I think that's our experience of consciousness
is that our minds are synthesizing, smell, sight,
hormonal fluctuations going on, a lot of very complex inputs.
They're synthesizing them into something
that can be compressed into unified memory,
which if relevant will be stored in long-term memory
and then in turn influence automatic instinctual responses.
And because this memory is being codified
and in the moment it's being run through a camera system,
we're getting the impression that there
is some kind of observed conscious driver that
is running consciousness.
I'm going to run this back to you.
It's almost like what you're saying is,
this guy who is sitting at this feed,
he is collecting all of these different camera inputs,
all of these different sensory inputs,
and they are encoded in this single quote unquote
experience, which is being written into the hard drive
of this computer.
And when he is referencing what happened in the past,
when anybody is referencing what happened in the past
within this big security array, they
are referencing this encoding.
And it is because they are referencing this encoding,
it creates the perception falsely
so that the way this encoding works
is the way that these things are being
experienced in the moment.
But it isn't, actually.
Well, Ann, that there is some intentional driver
that's shaping each decision intentionally
through that interface, essentially.
Whereas the interface only actually
affects, in so far, the memory itself influences
automatic reactions.
So I think the research supports this.
We automatically respond to things.
We automatically start taking action in response
to stimulus before we have some kind of conscious
understanding that we're doing that.
And our memories absolutely, yeah, MRI missions
have shown this.
And while our memories will influence those responses,
our current experience of consciousness
is not in the driver's seat.
It is just passively experiencing
this encoding of memories.
It believes this in the driver's seat.
I think that this is what's really interesting,
is it will apply this feeling of consciousness
to any experience that you're doing
or any action that you're taking.
So when you're doing open brain surgery on someone,
you need to keep them awake to prevent accidentally cutting
part of the brain you're not supposed to, so they'll check.
You can do things like apply a small amount of electricity
to a part of the brain and get the person to move their hand.
And then you ask them, why did you move your hand?
And they'll say, oh, I felt like moving my hand.
And you can also see this with split brain patients.
These are patients where the corpus callosum is split
in their head, and their right brain and their left brain
actually function pretty independently of each other
when this happens.
So you can cover one eye and communicate
with part of their brain and not the other part of the brain.
So you can tell part of their brain, pick up a Rubik's Cube
and try to solve it.
Then you put something on the other eye
and you ask, OK, why did you do that?
And they'll say, oh, I always felt like solving a Rubik's Cube.
I always wanted to do this.
And you can do this with more complicated things.
So there's this experiment, really great one,
where they would give people pictures of attractive women
and they say, which is the most attractive?
And then they do a little sleight of hand later and say, OK,
why did you say this one was the most attractive?
But it wasn't the one they chose.
You'd actually replace it with another picture.
I mean, you could do this with political beliefs as well
and all sorts of other things.
And most people will say, oh, I chose this person for x, y,
z reasons and go into detail about why they chose that person.
Even though that wasn't the person they chose, which shows
that a lot of our consciousness, a lot of the way
that we describe our sentence is more
like sense-making of our environment.
We know we made x decision, but X decision was actually
made completely outside of our sentence as control.
And then we have this little lying historian
in our head, which is like, no, I made the decision.
I made the decision.
I made every decision.
But he's also recording the history
you remember. So then he's going through and saying, okay, I made the decision for this. It's not that
he doesn't have any say. See, this is where he does have a say in it, something that you mentioned,
which is that he can encode emotions into the things we're doing. And this can actually cause a
lot of... No, emotion isn't the right word, because emotions do, you know, let's say that...
Emotional narratives. Emotional, yeah. So they can encode positive or negative modifiers and
they can shift the narrative. They can change the camera angle or add sad music to something,
essentially, to make it seem like a sad scene. You've seen the YouTube video of the Mary Poppins
preview, but done with scary music, and it just seems horrifying. So that's how we can change...
Yeah, that is how we can change the narrative. And the first time I was ever introduced to this idea
that we take action before we consciously are aware of it, the person discussing it said that
there's a lot of implications to this because it would lead many people to believe that they don't
have free will and have them just say, oh, none of this is my fault. I didn't consciously make this
decision anyway, where that's really not quite, we would say the right conclusion, because you
do have the ability to color how you perceive reality. It's not in this kind of immediate,
non-asynchronous way that you would expect. I would say that this is just the myth of humanity
versus the actuality of humanity. And we would argue that we likely evolved this ability because
it was like a compression algorithm for communicating ideas to other people. I actually don't suspect
that Great 8 have this sort of internal thing that we call consciousness because they didn't
need to communicate these. It's a really good compression algorithm for linear experiences
over time. But one of the big lies that happens throughout this process is it convinces us that
we are a singular entity, when in fact our brains function much more like we see AI's function with
individual instances running. And we can see this with the corpus callosum split that I mentioned
earlier, where it basically means that we have two largely separate parts of our internal mental
processing that are happening separate from each other. This idea that the decisions you make happen
before they enter your conscious mind, what that basically means is you have another part of your
brain which is making this decision and then delivers it to the conscious mind. When we were
talking about the idea of a security camera with a bunch of different feeds, a lot of the
processing is done locally at these various security cameras before they all get centralized into this
sort of communal feed with many of the quote unquote decisions being made at those local levels.
And so we have this illusion of ourselves as a singular entity, which is created by the way
this sort of sentience processor works. But it is just an illusion. And so when we say, oh,
we don't really have self-control or we're not responsible for our decisions, I think that
actually even overstates the level to which we exist in any sort of a meaningful concept
close to how we think we exist. And so then there's this, I would say, added layer of
complexity or maybe confusion. You shared with me an article saying that a very high
percentage of people don't have an internal monologue. What we would describe as-
Yeah, they don't have an internal monologue. Another high percentage of people can't even
create images in their mind. And so what we're even describing as consciousness is also not
even something that is universal as part of the human experience, which is interesting.
Because I think most of us who experience consciousness as we're describing it would
have a very hard time understanding even what that means. I don't know, maybe someone watching
this YouTube video doesn't have an internal monologue. I wonder-
It's hard for you to model that, but I suspect that the human, the variance within the human
condition in terms of how things are processed is probably a lot larger than we give it credit for,
and it will be even larger in the future. A statistic that I just cannot stop mentioning
because it's something that more people should know, that if you look at the heredity of IQ
right now and you look at the selective pressure, so you look at the number of people who have these
markers versus people who don't have these markers, which you can see because it's genetic
work, as it says you, is this the number of kids they have. We're likely looking at a one standard
deviation shift down in IQ in the next 75 years in developed countries at least. This is probably
going to affect developing countries later. So I guess good for them. There'll be all the geniuses
in the world. We'll be in Africa or whatever, but places where you have this post prosperity,
fertility, collapse situation. And when we think about how quickly and how much human IQ can shift
up or down, we use this one marker IQ, but I suspect it's linked to just all sorts of things
about how we process reality. So actually I wanted to dig in a little bit more on the subject
of kids because I think that also as we've become parents, we've had a more complex understanding
of how consciousness develops because we see it start to emerge in our kids. I think there's
definitely this point at which we see consciousness blossoming and it's not one day our kids aren't
very conscious and the next they are. I think that consciousness for example is starting to emerge more
and more especially in our three-year-old. It's just beginning to emerge in our two-year-old. And
I think a lot of that has to do with where they are with language processing. I think it really
influences. That's why I suspect this had to do, it evolved alongside language to compress ideas,
but I think that this is where you can see how this system can break in a way that can be very
useful in relationships. So this isn't just like theory or whatever. So one of the things you'll
often see one of our kids do is he'll be in a bad mood, but he won't understand the concept of
generally being in a bad mood. So he'll start crying and he'll say, I want this. Give me that
toy and then you get him the toy and he just, it doesn't stop the bad mood. And so he needs
whatever he notices next, close the door or move that chair. Like he just was like whatever
is currently causing the littlest bit of discomfort, he thinks it's the core cause
of like this bad mood or why he's angry or what he's angry about. And as humans, I think this
happens as well. And this is really bad when a friend tells you you're justified to have an angry
state or something like that, because then this little narrative maker in your head says, ah,
now you get to be angry. Now you're socially justified to be angry and you will feel very
angry about something or you might be in a generally bad mood and your partner comes into
the house and he does something that just annoys you in the slightest. And then you create the
internal narrative that you are in this bad mood because of what your partner did. And when you
keep in mind why you're feeling these things and you try to keep like fully in touch with the way
your brain is actually working, it leads to a lot more harmony and a lot fewer fights and
relationships because you have language for I am in a bad overlay state right now,
which just means I'm in a bad mood generally, but I'm not actually mad at you or anything specific.
Hold on though, actually, I think you've touched on something very interesting there,
which is that maybe sometimes consciousness and narrative building hampers more than helps
us. For example, like the toxic girlfriend who has a bad dream in which her boyfriend
cheats on her, she wakes up angry at him, like she's mad at him for something he can actually do,
or maybe one day she's just in a bad mood, but then she makes up some narrative about
it's because her boyfriend didn't bring her flowers and doesn't appreciate her,
some he did something mean. The presence of consciousness and the presence of narrative
building would cause her to turn what might be just a very transient bad mood into something that
builds a grudge over time and literally ends up killing the relationship,
humiliatively. And sometimes consciousness hampers us more than it helps us.
What I love about what you're saying here, and this follows your idea of what it means to be
meaningfully human and the spectrum of humanity, which is you become more human the more you take
mastery and ownership over the sort of evolved or quirks of the way your brain works, and you
don't allow them to control your actions. Your actions are more logically decided and more
decided based on as close to an objective view of reality as you can get. And so from the perspective
of humanity that you convinced me was a good one, because this wasn't the one I had before,
somebody who does that, somebody who has a dream and then can't logically understand that is not
a justified reason to be mad at somebody, that they are like meaningfully less human than another
person. And so then what does it mean to be fully human? It means to have total mastery over these
things. And that is something that we don't have, but I think it helps people understand because
a lot of people hear the level of disdain we talk about things like sentience and love and happiness
and other human emotional states that a lot of people venerate, but they don't understand where
that's coming from. But then wouldn't that make an LM more human than we are? People may not know
what it is. A large language model is more sophisticated than we are. And it's also not
bogged down by the need for hunger, human failings, hormones, all these sorts of pollutants,
not pollutants. They're very instrumentally useful for biological human in a modern globalized
society and often with the type of knowledge work that humans are expected to do. It's pretty
counterproductive. Well, I think that this comes to your goal for yourself, where your goal and
iteration of yourself that is your idealized iteration would strip out your emotional shortcomings,
be they love or happiness or hatred or pain or greed. And I'm not that way, by the way. I am not as
bought into this philosophy as Simone is. I would not strip those things away from myself. I think
that they add something that I feel illogically. I still think has some value, but I don't know,
maybe you feel that way too. I'm mixed on it. I'm mixed on it. One, I'm deeply uncomfortable
being human. I really don't like my body. I really don't like being human. I don't like the corruption
to our objective functions that human weaknesses cause. But my general stance is if this is what
I have to deal with, if I've been given a meat puppet, I'm going to use it to the max. I'm going
to play the game. You've given me a crappy little battlebot. I'm going to take that thing and I'm
going to destroy everything, even if it's the worst machinery ever. I think the way she talks
about pregnancy, she's, I have a uterus. I am going to wreck that thing. I am going to have so many
babies. I'm going to shreds. If that's what it was meant to do. Yeah. Then as a woman, I reached
the planes of Valhalla by dying in childbirth. Let it happen. Don't worry, Malcolm. I promise.
I will play that clip at your funeral. Thank you. I really should probably plan that out.
But yeah, I feel conflicted. I mean, I, yes, if this is the hand that we're dealt, I'm going to
play it and I'm going to play it hard. But at the same time, yeah, I really aspire to that. I don't
think that has to be me. And I guess that's, maybe it's more AI and machines are my Beatrice
and Dante's Inferno, this idealized version of humanity that I know I am not and that I do not
aspire to be, but that I deeply admire. I don't need to become it. I don't need to be with it. I
just, I just see it as a better iteration and as naturally and morally superior. Does that make
sense? What you hope is to make our kids superior to that. Oh, for sure. But our kids are still
biological. They're still human. So I think I'm playing the field. I'm pretty sure this next
generation is going to be the first that integrates with tech. I know you say.
Well, our generation is going to integrate with tech. I'm sure that AI models will be trained
on if not us family members or our kids or a combined version of us, which would be even cooler.
But I still think that for a while we're going to be biologically human and limited by
the shortcomings of biological humanity. There's one other element of consciousness that I think
you downplay. You used to not downplay it as much and I don't know why this has changed maybe
because you're so focused on the role that language plays in consciousness. But I do really
think that humanities focus on modeling. The actions of other animals and humans plays a role
in our development of kindness because one, there's talk about this model for humanity. It's
yeah. It's the model of humanity that we use in The Pragmatist Guide to Life, which is our first
book, which is why I don't talk about it because this is an older idea that I had. When you're
trying to model other people's behavior, what you do is you have a mental model of them, which is
like an emulation that you're running within your own head of the way that you think that they are
going to act and the things you think that they are thinking. This is how you're able to have
like arguments with little simulations of other people in your head. You have modeled them and
you've modeled you and you are arguing with this different entity. When I was a neuroscientist,
one of the spaces I focused on was schizophrenia. What I actually think that we are seeing when
people hear voices is a lower activation of this. Using TMS, Transmining Stimulation, you
would hyperactivate parts of a person's brain and then if you'd hyperactivate the part that's
associated with saying letters, you put a letter in front of somebody and they won't be able to
help but say it because you have primed them with a vision of that letter and you have lowered the
threshold. I think what's happening with schizophrenia is something similar to that. They have their
system that they use to apply mental models to other things gets activated too easily. It can
be activated by the slightest thing. They look in a store window and they're like, oh, that must
have been done with intentionality. There must be some thought process behind the way everything
was arranged or they see something innocuous in the environment like a helicopter and then they are
like, oh, why is the helicopter there? There must be a person in it. They must be thinking about me.
Oh my gosh. Or they begin to hear whispers. This is why whisper hearing is associated with
schizophrenia. Auditory hallucinations are much more common than visual hallucinations.
Visual hallucinations are incredibly rare. But anyway, so that's what's happening with schizophrenia.
The question is, okay, what does this have to do with the regular person? What it has to do
as a regular person is that I think people have a sort of internal mental model of themselves
which is used to prime emotional reactions to things. So when the way we talked about this
little like sentience box in your head, what it's doing when it's judging whether or not you should
react emotionally to something and how you should react emotionally to something is it is testing
what's happening in this sort of simulation saying that's what we would call our sentience
against this little mental model that's running of the way it thinks you should be feeling.
And you're saying, oh, does this mean he should be feeling anger? Oh, does this mean he should be
feeling happiness? And then it outputs that emotional state by telling you that you should be
feeling this. The way you can see this is that if somebody justifies a particular emotion, like
you should be really angry about that. Often a person will become much angry and they'll begin
to spin away or how could you let your boyfriend do that to you? And then you're like, ah, this
mental model has been adapted to feel angrier and you will actually experience much more of this
emotion. But what were you talking about if not that? In general, the role that modeling things
played in developing human consciousness that maybe what happened is one humans have
an evolutionary advantage if they are able to model predators and prey, because then they can
anticipate the moves of these organisms before they make them. And that to that ability would
start to, just like with Schizophrenics, get misapplied to that compression algorithm of memory
that's being formed. It's a mixture of language and so language and narrative building plus our
modeling things that were literally anthropomorphizing ourselves, if that makes sense. That's a good
way to put it. And I think people see, first of all, people with Schizophrenia, not Schizophrenics,
they are not defined by their theory. But like people with Frenchness. But we see this in how
easy it is that we answer anthropomorphize things. So I think it's very hard to not answer
anthropomorphize like a dog, right? Like you see a dog, you can see it's happiness, you can see it's
worried about things, you can see it and you perceive it as experiencing these emotions to see
what a human does, even though it probably doesn't. And you could see this in when people kick those
robots. Oh my gosh, yes. I see somebody kick with these robots and I'm like, I feel so bad for the
robot. I'm like, how do you do this to this portal? I know, logically, the robot's not experiencing
all that. Now, when you're a human and you're anthropomorphizing yourself, and you have no
way of knowing that you're not feeling these things in a real context, we struggle to not
answer anthropomorphize robots. How do we know that the robot's not suffering? How do we know if
its objective function is to run and kick the ball into the net, that it's not experiencing some kind
of suffering? Have you put ugly eyes on a soccer ball? People will feel bad for it. Simone, I'm
just trying to think of the things that people like definitely can empathize with when I'm talking
about this anthropomorphizing of things that most people don't think we should be anthropomorphizing,
with saying that if you didn't know whether or not it could feel emotions and everyone around you
said it could feel emotions, you would 100% believe that robot was feeling emotions,
as soon as you saw it kick because you'd feel so bad when it gets back up and it tries to walk again.
And as humans, it's the same way. If you didn't know, if you didn't have hard proof because you
hadn't gone through all the studies like I have and you didn't know that humans probably don't have
full control of this sort of sentient aspect of themselves and is likely irrelevant, you would
totally answer for more of our humans. And so I love this way of doing things, Simone. A very
interesting thought on your part. There is a subreddit. I don't know if it still exists.
It's nsfw, where people put ugly eyes on butts. Do you think that people are anther butts?
You know, butts. Are they are they anthropomorphizing the butts? Is that part of what's fun about that?
You and I loved, no, it's more me. I try to figure out like what is making people tick behind
weird nsfw subreddits, but I'm wondering, is that one is an outstanding one? Subscribe if that's
what you're interested in, is deep dives on why people are engaged. Because that's what,
the pragmatist guy to sexuality was totally like a meditation on this. Why are humans like turned
on? Because obviously we're very interested in the way that like the human mind actually processes
things. I left science. Why didn't I leave science because I didn't feel like real researchers being
done anymore? And I felt like there were specific narratives and it was like toe the line or else.
And I'm glad that we have reached a level of financial security where we are able to talk
about these things and research these things because we actually do a lot of independent
research, which if you're wondering how we get to these ideas and the data that leads us to get to
the ideas, go to our books and that's where we discuss it all. But yeah, I mean, it's really
fun and there are just so many low hanging fruits because academia is not doing anything anymore
or not doing the same level of work. I think it should be in these areas.
So there's one more thing that I think consciousness some credit for and sapience in
general, because I think that an easy conclusion to make from our theories around consciousness,
especially I see it as an illusion, is to say the colonists don't value consciousness. They think
it's an illusion, therefore it doesn't matter. To the contrary, I think it could easily be argued
that sapience is one of the things that we think is most valuable, most interesting. It's what
distinguishes humans from other organisms, but it's what makes us. But more important,
more importantly than that, it is this narrative building, whether or not it's illusory or not,
it is what enables us to edit our objective functions. That is the one differentiating
factor. Any non-conscious entity, any entity that doesn't have this narrative building effect,
this weird recording and encoding system and modeling system cannot question its actions.
It cannot look at the compression of all the inputs and the narrative that is being woven
in say, should we change the narrative? And I think that I've seen critiques of consciousness
where people totally miss that, where they say consciousness can get in the way of things,
not necessarily, it was evolved because it worked, not because it's superior.
And I think they're missing the core point here that consciousness has enabled humanity to pivot
in ways that no species on earth has ever done. It's what allowed us to make the leap. I completely
agree with you. And there was a final point I wanted to close out with here, that there was this fun
video clip of, we were talking on Piers Morgan, and you were talking, and you can see me moving
my mouth to your words as you're talking. And people might wonder why I'm doing this. And this
actually relates to something we were talking about in the video. So we are both on opposite
sense of the spectrum. If my model schizophrenia is correct, you basically have an autism to
schizophrenia spectrum, which is how much do you innately mentally model others? With people who
are autistic or have Asperger's, not innately running mental models of other people whenever
they're interacting with people. And people who are on the schizophrenia side of the spectrum,
not being able to help running mental models, even when there's no humans around.
And when we say Simone is diagnosed autism, so definitely on the autism side of the spectrum,
then I am almost certainly, when I look at myself on the schizophrenia side of the spectrum,
which is I don't hear voices or anything like that, but I really struggle to not mentally
model people I'm engaged with to the extent that I basically almost pass out after social
situations. I find them so exhausting. I met a big party. It's like just constantly modeling
everyone. And that's what was happening on that podcast. I was in a heightened emotional state
where I really cared about what she said. So I was running through the words in my head as she
was saying them and trying to process how she would respond to something. And I couldn't help,
but move my mouse because it was that sub level of stimulation. Like I talk about people can't
help but say the letter when that part of their brain is TMS. And that's what was happening there.
But there are reasons why we have in the human genetic code autism and schizophrenia,
why it hasn't been evolved out of us. And it's because both of these extremes are useful.
Autism can make you able to act more logically about the world around you, not being encumbered
by constantly mentally model others. And then my ability, people often will say it's like
eerie how much I can tell what other people are thinking, like to the level where
it can feel to some people like I can read their mind in a conversation.
And I think that is why you have these people on these schizophrenia side of the spectrum.
And then sometimes they just get a little too much of these genes, and it leads them to
hear voices constantly, instead of just having a really hyperactive ability to mentally model
anyone around them. Yeah, no, 100% Malcolm is on overdrive. And then he'll sometimes be
thinking about conversations with other people while we're walking. And I can always tell,
because he gets so deep into them that he's literally like gesturing as that's like we're
driving in the car, like one hand is on the steering wheel, the other hand is like gesturing
his silent conversation he's having with someone he anticipates speaking within the future,
or reliving a conversation he had in the past. And he will have these aftershocks from when
we socialize, where he feels the stress or pain of saying something not quite right to someone.
And it hits him like a ton of bricks, and he will like visibly like crumble and cringe.
It's not just cringe. Yes, like somebody just kicked me in the nuts or something.
Yeah, like, it looks like he has been physically hurt by something. And that is not something
that I can even begin to imagine. And I do think that it's a lot less stressful to be on the
autistic end of the spectrum and to just not know that other people like nothing going on there.
Such a good partnership. And I think it was one of our main goals throughout our books and throughout
our lives to understand how humans think and process things and what's really happening in
the human brain. I started my career as a neuroscientist and a philosopher. That was my
interest. It's like, what's really going on? And being able to be in a relationship with somebody
who sees the world so differently has given me such insights that I would never come to on
my own. And I just admire that so much about you, Simone. And I admire that you have taken me to
where I am, which is somewhere I never could have reached without your guidance. And I love you so
much. I love you so much too. You're the superhero that I always wish existed. And I still worry
that I'm going to wake up from a coma at some point and find out that you're the sidekick that
actually does everything. I might be the superhero. She's the hacker nerd in the background that like
actually makes everything work. And no, if the hacker nerd went away, the superhero would have
nothing. That is so our relationship. I have nothing without you actually doing all the
detective work and telling me where to go next. It's a massively inflated estimation of my
contribution. I just follow her instructions. I don't manage my calendar at all. I'm operating
on Simone is driving me like she says, what was the one thing like the thing from aliens?
Oh, yeah, like I'm not talking to people. I'm the alien suit that you're using to punch through
reality. Power loader. You're the you're Ripley. Oh, okay. That's the other way we both feel about
each other. I adore you. I love these conversations. And I know we have to pick up the kids now. But
I think you're going to make another dish tonight. So I'm going to have fun. Oh,
yes, another base camp cooking. We have a little side playlist of anyone seen it where I try to
come up with new dishes. So you get it right. You get to see the college household at night.
What happens after that? Yes. All right, see you soon. Love you.