Today on the podcast we have our third conversation with Mike Eleven to
kick off the new year and we talk a lot about the developments that he's been
making in his lab that all centered around the idea of embodied cognition,
intelligence versus consciousness, some of the specifics of the way that the
experiments work because the last time that we talked to him he had just
published his paper on frog skin Xenobots where they had taken frog skin
cells from frog skin, grown them in special conditions and then created these
ambulatory little creatures that could then corral other skin cells to produce
more of themselves and so basically in I think a pretty transparent way made a
new life form out of a cellular format that you wouldn't really expect would be
able to do something new and he kind of teased us with the idea that they were
working on doing the same thing with mammalian cells and this paper was
published over the course of the last year and so a lot of our discussion
centered on what are called antherbots which are tracheal epithelial cells
that grown in a 3d matrix then released from the 3d matrix are now become these
multicellular ciliated structures that astonishingly migrate to the location of
wounds inside of plated neuronal cells and then act to heal the break in the
cellular layer and so it opens all of these questions that are kind of a
perpetual topic with Michael Levin right like what are the parameters that
create the design limitations that we associate with the bodies that we live
in and as always it's a absolutely fascinating discussion because I think
that Levin is thinking about these questions in a way that honestly very
very few people are Levin and collaborators as he mentions towards the end
of the episode and there's extraordinary second third-order effects from the
instrumentalization of these experiments as well right so what does it
world with truly regenerative medicine look like how do we account for the
ability that we can build our bodies back but our minds are perhaps wrestling
with the longevity issue and also how does disembodied consciousness appear at
other scales throughout the cosmos in systems that we might not have access
to how to examine those systems in a way where we can poke at them if they're on
different time scales and different spatial scales that we're used to these
are huge questions so it's a wide-ranging conversation part three and we'll look
forward maybe next year to doing part four we wanted to say a huge thank you
to our patrons for being here all year this is our first podcast for the new
year it's actually New Year's Day today we're really stoked on the next year
we're having our first conference out in Austin Texas we would love to see you
there it's gonna be a really close-knit conversation circle we have some
incredible speakers lined up you can check out all of those things at the
link down in the description and up here and I really hope to meet you guys out
there and check out the total solar eclipse which is happening that weekend
we also have live stream tickets that are gonna be on sale and right now those
are $10 but the price is gonna go up in the next few weeks so get those now on
the early sale and it's still affordable and we're gonna be making a big road
trip out there and playing music shows along the way so if you are on the path
of Oregon to Austin get in touch with us if you want us to play in your town and
we will figure out a way to make it happen and as always a huge thank you to
our patrons we could not do this without you guys because as you probably
well know we live in a society where you you got to make bread to eat bread and
we do eat a lot of peanut butter and jelly but this has been a transformative
experience because we have been able to build this show on the basis of having
an audience that believes in what we're doing and so if you've been listening to
the show for a while and you and you want to support us then come on over to
patreon.com that link is right here and you can join for just a couple dollars a
month and really help us keep the ship going and help us develop it and make
it so that we have more in-person conversations so we can go see you in
the towns where you're at and not have it just be something that is through the
computer screen where everyone is experiencing by themselves all right
let's talk to Michael
it seems like you're spending a lot of time thinking about this idea of
intelligence and the manifestations of intelligence and this the smallest
possible unit of what can be said to be intelligent and studying how it evolves
and organizes and sorts like there was a paper that was just on on the
Reeveson side where you were looking at the way that these different sorting
algorithms clustered during evolutionary experiences and I wonder if we could start
with a conversation about the minimum unit of intelligence and evolution and
behavior because if you can do it with such a simple system then it seems like
those principles are being applied actively in the bio about work sure sure
yeah I mean the thing is and I have some somewhere on my website I have a video
that I made of the word cloud of all our papers from every year and how it's
changed from I think 1992 or something all the way and you can watch them change
and the thing is that it's not that I've spent more time thinking about this now
I always thought about this stuff this was always what I'm interested in but
there was a time when that wasn't the right time to talk about any of it and
progressively over the years it's become more and more fruitful to start to talk
about it because these are topics that go sort of across the grain for a lot of
the way that people think about biology and so on and until we had a body of work
that really was able to say no look this is a useful way to think about things
because it leads to new discoveries right until that had reached a certain
level there was no point in becoming out and talking about basal cognition or
any of that stuff so so now I think I think we're in an interesting point now
where we can actually robustly talk about some of these things yeah and in
particular if you want to start with the with the sorting algorithm so so the
thing about the sorting algorithms is that there is no evolution there this is
purely the standard very few lines of code that a sort of what we're talking
six seven lines of code tops that a standard sorting algorithm has and the
reason I picked it is because understanding the very minimal system
that that exhibits some sort of very kind of basal aspects of intelligence of
cognitive behavior of problem-solving and so on is really important because a
lot of people have and this includes this includes you know professional
neuroscientists and so on they they think that a lot of these kinds of
capacities show up fairly late right and so so you know so so Nick Humphreys
would put it at birds and mammals for example I could mean really late and I
inevitably when I start talking about the symmetries or the invariances that
exist in terms of these different capacities across the tree the tree of
life across all kinds of weird implementations and so on inevitably the
question becomes well what's the smallest piece in other words are you then
saying that every rock has hopes and dreams and things I write that that's
the question that people ask and so so actually I think it's very important to
answer that question to say what do these things look like when they become
really minimal right you know what what are the earliest things that or the
simplest things that have these properties and so what was cool about the
sorting algorithms is that a few things they're well known so people have been
you know computer science students have been studying these things for many
decades they're completely deterministic there there is no even that
there's not even pseudo randomness there they're totally deterministic they're
completely transparent you can see all the code the next thing about that as
opposed to biology is that if I say look here's a biological system that's doing
something new and unexpected someone could say there's a mechanism for you
just haven't found it yet it there's always in biology there's always more
details to be discovered right and you never know that you've got it all and
you probably will never have it all so so but but with these things I can say
no look here are the six lines of code like there's nothing else there literally
is not no other place for anything to hide that this is it and so then if you
have something like that it also has the interesting property that people think
they know how it works and what it can do and this is showing up a lot in the
current AI debates because people it's not everybody of course there are other
people who disagree but but a lot of people are saying well this is just
linear algebra we know we made it we know how it works it does you know and
people have very strong feelings it can't this and it doesn't that and you
know it it there's no there's no way it has whatever interesting thing they
think they have as biological creatures because they made it and I want to say
that even even these incredibly minimal things where we think we know exactly how
they work in these and have very small parts we don't know everything they're
capable of there are major surprises and that and that's what we found in this
paper now I should also be clear this is a preprint so it's not been peer
reviewed so so you know I always like to kind of point out that that's what we're
talking about and so can we go into some of the details about what is the system
that these algorithms are inside of in the behavior that you see yeah so so the
things that we're looking for we're looking for the two two main things
number one we're looking for what I call basal intelligence which which I define
as the ability to solve problems and get to the same outcome by different means
this is William James's definition of intelligence you know same goal by
different means and in particular there's one very particular thing that we
looked for and found which I call delayed gratification and it's the idea and in
fact William James talks about this imagine imagine two magnets and you
know they're trying to get together and you put a piece of wood between them
that's it right what the magnet is never going to do is go around and the wood
and get to where it wants to go because because that would temporarily
actually take it further away from its goal right the energy the free energy
would actually rise as and they can't do that all they do is they go down the
gradient if you have an animal or certain kinds of self-driving vehicles or in
James's example Romeo and Juliet right facing all kinds of physical and
social barriers they have all kinds of tools to do this they understand delayed
gratification they know that temporarily you might have to go away from your goal
in order to reach it later and and so that's a kind of metric of cognitive
sophistication right but but the ability to do it at all is already
something so so one thing one thing that I would that we were looking for is the
ability to to do that kind of problem-solving or delay gratification
the second thing we were looking for is unexpected unexpected goals and when I
say goals I don't mean human level metacognitive goals like I know what my
goal is I don't mean that I mean very simple cybernetic goals which are states
that you spend energy to try to achieve and if somebody sort of pulls you away
from it you'll you know you'll you'll you'll continue to try to get there in
some kind of way so those are those are the those are the two things that we were
looking for and so so let's just go from the beginning what do these sorting
algorithms do all the ideas that you start with a with an array of numbers
these are random random numbers they're there you know let's say from one to a
hundred you have a hundred numbers and they're shuffled they're all randomly
distributed so the sort of the job of the sorting algorithm is we're gonna crank
through this algorithm we're gonna we're gonna look at what the numbers and we're
gonna follow a very simple recipe and by the end of it all of them are gonna be
in order that's all it's gonna do it's gonna arrange the numbers in order it's
a very short algorithm now the main way that it works is there's a there's a
centralized kind of top-down mind that or in this case a computer that knows the
algorithm and is just sitting there rearranging the numbers and there are
many different sorting algorithms is bubble sort selection sort whatever we
made we made two small modifications to allow us to ask all of these
interesting questions and by the way what the the other thing we did is to
visualize that process as a walk in a navigation in a certain space in other
words a walk in sorting space so you start out over here and in many potential
configurations where all the numbers are shuffled but everybody's got to get to
one particular point which is when all the numbers are in place and it's
guaranteed these sorting algorithms are guaranteed to eventually get you there
right it might take a while depending on the length of the stream but they all
get there so they all sort of walk around and they get to this they get to
this one spot okay so and that's that's what we're interested in in terms of
intelligence we're interested in ability to navigate in some kind of problem
space so we so we made two changes number one so we made this a little more
biological instead of having a top-down controller that sees all the numbers and
is following one algorithm and doing its thing we made it distributed and bottom
up meaning that we gave each each each number we call them cells now in each
cell has a has associated with a certain number they all have their own tiny
little agency and all they know how to do is look around and they have preferences
about their neighbors so if you're a five what you would like to have is a four on
your left and a six on your right that that's it so instead of and but you're
going to follow that same algorithm so you've got you've got the algorithm but
now every single cell is following the algorithm it's not top-down you know
omniscient single agent that's sorting them but every cell has its own little
little preferences right so that's very biological because in biology you're
dealing with an agential material where every cell has local local knowledge
local preferences and so on but we don't add anything new so there's no memory we
don't we don't give them all kinds of complex all they have is that same
original algorithm it's just they can't see the whole string all they see is some
some distance away all they see is local so it's we haven't added anything we've
just sort of distributed it out and and by the way the first amazing result of
the paper is that that actually works when you do that you still get sorted
numbers so so if you break the if when nobody nobody knows what all the
numbers are you can still get them sorted that's kind of cool so so that
kind of distributed source so that's that's the first thing then then we
added something else which is very biological and is really the key to
testing this intelligence which is that we stepped away from the notion of a
of an infallible algorithm in other words normally when you do the algorithm you
assume that it works in other words when i say swap the the the five and the seven
you assume that they in fact get swapped we introduce a notion of an unreliable
medium the algorithm might say you want to swap one of the cells could be broken it
could be damaged maybe it can't be moved maybe it can't initiate moves so so we
introduce this notion of a frozen cell now notice that in the traditional
algorithm there is no notion of hey did my did the operation succeed how am i
doing what what am i actually uh you know am i going in the right direction
nothing the algorithm doesn't have any of that all it has is a set of steps and
you sort of blindly take those steps and that's it so so you see this is a
super minimal system uh initially you would look at and you would say well
there is no machinery here for any any of the things you want to find there's no
machinery here for dealing with broken cells there's no machinery here for
delayed gratification there's no sense of how am i doing or what path am i taking
through that space not none of that is there and that's why i i like this
system so much because it shows us that even in scenarios where you you think
you know what's there and what it does you can you can be significantly
surprised so so here's what we found here here are surprised first of all we
found that if if you do introduce these broken cells which can't move
and then you track the progress of the sorting algorithm across the space you
find out that in fact what it does know how to do is delay gratification it
knows how to go backwards which means in this case un-sort the string a little
and in order to have gains later on that that's an amazing thing because that is
not in the algorithm if you look at the actual algorithm there's nothing in
there like that you don't see you don't see that so so that already
starting to tell you that that there are competencies that are not obvious from
looking at the material so that's the first thing and then we were able
to do something else because you know in the traditional way of doing this
there's one single algorithm that's sorting the whole string right you're
you're sort of god looking at it from the top down and you're following
selection sort or insertion sort or whatever it's going to be and you're
moving whatever you need to move around to get them sorted in this case
everything's bottom up every cell has its own uh is following its own algorithm
so we were able to do something something very unusual which in fact we do in
the biology too we made a chimera and that is a mix of cells where some cells
are following one algorithm but other cells are following another algorithm
and for example our our frog allotle is a chimera when you take cells from a
frog embryo and you take cells from an axolotl embryo they have
different local rules that they're going to follow because one's going to make a
frog one's going to make an axolotl but you can put them together in a single
organism you can ask what happens right so we did that here we we um we mixed
two two algorithms in the same string now the way you do it is you when that um
as you assign them randomly so we have a bunch of random numbers and each one
gets a random assignment you're either you're either going to follow selection
sort or you're going to follow a bubble sort something like that right and it's
and it's random it's mixed up you can think about that as the genetic sort of
right it's the thing that determines your policy of action it determines what
you're going to do and there's two different there's two different kinds
um again surprise the first the first kind of interesting thing is that that
works in other words you don't need to both have the same uh journey through
that space in order to get to where it's going and so you can have a chimera
string that still gets sorted even though half of it's following one set of
rules and half of it's following another okay that's cool then we asked that we
asked a really wild question which is if you if you look at the string in the
middle of the process what's the distribution of the of the cells that
are following the two different algorithms like where do they hang out in the
string now now here's what we know we know that at the very beginning it's
going to be random so so let's define a notion of clustering which is just this
I look to my left I look to my right and I ask what are the odds that the that
the guy sitting next to me is using exactly the same algorithm as I am we
call it we defined a new a new term um Adam Goldstein came up with this he
calls it an algotype like you have genotype phenotype so algotype right
and so and so okay so clustering is just I look to my left I look to my right
what's the odds that my neighbor is the same algotype as me
we know that in the beginning it's 50% because they're random we assign them
randomly we also know that at the end it's also going
to be 50% because at the end everybody's got to be sorted according to their
number but the algotypes who are signed randomly they weren't
assigned according to number so that means if we really if we sort you on
the number the other types are gonna be of course just like at the beginning
they'll be all over the place they're gonna be 50 50 what happens in the
middle and this is the amazing part what happens in the middle
is that what the curve so so so 50 it's clamped at 50 50 but in the middle it
kind of goes like this so what happens is that in between the sorting process
cells with the same algotype like to hang out together they spend
a bunch of time in these clusters where we are all the same type of we're all
following the same procedure but then they inevitably get dragged apart
you know I sometimes joke that this is like a it's a minimal model of the
human condition of you know for any living being
like for a period of time in your life you get to do some things that are
against the general trend of the physics of your world but eventually
you all end up in the same place right it's like this really minimal
minimal way you have you have a period of time where you get to do some things
that you want but eventually the inevitable physics of your universe
sort of grinds you down right that's that's like
like a minimal model of our of our existential state
so what's what's amazing about it is that again
nowhere in the algorithm does it say I know what algotype I am
or how you find that out nowhere in the algorithm does it talk about checking
the algotype of your neighbors none of that is there it's completely
emergent and it's not just emergent complexity the way that you know
fractals are an emergent complexity the game of life
cellular automata emergent complexity from very simple rules is not just that
it's what one step beyond that it's actually
in the case of the the the delay gratification it's emergent competencies
and in the case of the the clustering or hanging out together
it's some sort of it's some sort of emergent computational goal that you as
the programmer did not put in there this is a very simple system
that has goals and competencies that you did not put in there
even though you wrote the algorithm the algorithm is deterministic it's small
and transparent and you know this is I this is why I think it's
significant because if if that's the case in these little things
when people say they think they know what you know various AI
architectures do or various you know collective
swarm robotics or swarm you know various things like that
I mean I I think there are so many surprises
in store for us that we really need to develop a science of
guessing guessing these kind of emerging goals and so this
so the last thing I want to say is that this takes us back to your point at the
very beginning that okay so what does this have to do with the various
biobots because much like with with these
with these algorithms when when we make novel biologicals
where the answer to well what what are going to be
its goals all while have a you know long history of of a selection
but determined well they don't have a long history of selection they've never
been here before these biobots there was never a
selection to be a good zanibot or a good anthropobot
so how do you know what the goals are going to be where do they come from
right so that I think is the is the emergence of a new science of
figuring out the novel goals of systems where you cannot
say that evolution is what did it and that's I think that's going to be really
important for us as a species going forward
I love that we have this really straightforward experiment that's so
simplified available to be able to consider the larger implications and
so I want to spend a little bit more time really understanding
the dynamics that emerge from it and so when you say that
these algorithms in the midpoint cluster according to type
do you have a sense for why that is yeah um
why it why is interesting because we have to think about what kind of answer
we're looking for so on the one hand and this is also true in biology
there's no magic here I'm not saying that these things are doing anything that
isn't allowed by the by the algorithm if you were to track
the data flow you would say well this is perfectly consistent with the algorithm
there's nothing to see here which is exactly what some people do for biology
they look at you and your brain and they say
well this is just chemistry this is just just electrons moving around there's
nothing there's nothing special here right if you if you insist on the lowest
level of description that is all that's all you're ever going to see
and that's it's not false it's just a very limiting world view
um on the other hand if you if you if you take a step back and you ask yeah but
knowing what you know about the algorithm why why didn't you predict that that
was going to happen yeah and this is this is kind of my my
my thing about a lot of biology is that after the fact after somebody has done
something interesting and shows you a new phenomenon you've never seen before
it's very easy to go back and look at the micro details and say yep no miracles
here therefore all good like we can explain it you know
yeah you can always track down the the steps that you took
but unless you had a theory that actually told you in advance that this was
going to happen in other words you know not not just explanation looking
backwards but invention looking forwards then then you then you're missing
something and so now so so what we're missing in this case
is a system that would have allowed us to say ahead of time
oh i know that's what your algorithm says but i can see what's going to happen
here these guys are going to want to travel together
right that's that's what we're that's what we're looking for and and
do i have that theory no although um i will um
i'll propose a hypothesis which which we're going to test
soon um the hypothesis is this uh based on uh kind of carl friston's
framework of surprise minimization um chris fields and i had this had this
paper a few years ago now on why it is
basically he calls it an imperial model of multi-cellularity the idea goes
like this why why would cells want to get together
right and and one way to think about this is that well if every cell
doesn't like to be surprised let's face it if you're a living thing and you're
constantly getting surprised you're not going to last very long
so so everything is is trying to minimize uh minimize surprise
well one of the least surprising things out there
is you so what might be nice is to make some copies of yourself and put
them around you to make a sort of like stem cell niche kind of thing where the
cells on the outside are frontline infantry they're facing the uncertainty
of the outside world the cell on the inside is protected and has a very
consistent environment because everything it's dealing with is basically a copy of
itself so um that's our idea so that that was our
idea and so so so uh following this firstonian paradigm
what you really want are neighbors that are predictable
well how will they be predictable well they could be like you if they're like
you they're they're they're pretty predictable so my gut feeling is that
that's what's going on here i suspect that this is a primitive
version a very early version of of surprise minimization
that the reason they're traveling together is uh because they're trying to
minimize joint free energy or some such thing i'm sure carl would
would say it much more much more elegantly but but i think that's probably
what's going on here they're they're traveling together for as long as they
can because it minimizes their uncertainty about
their environment and we again notice that they don't have any explicit
mechanism for this there's nothing in the algorithm that says
uh you know make a prediction to compare it to your
reward model that there's nothing in there it's it's it's emergent
although this is emergent and i think it's consistent with
carl and chris and and other people when they apply this active
inference framework to particles you know they apply it to things that do not
have explicit mechanisms and we knew this from a long time ago
when you do um some kind of a least action model and you say hey look this
beam of light gets to where it picks the path
where it loses the you know the least amount of of effort
right and you say yeah but how does that work it doesn't have any mechanisms
inside to compute all the paths and right it doesn't have explicit
mechanisms for it but i think this is what we're learning is that you don't
need explicit mechanisms to do some of this stuff
that's and i think that's really important well there's an aspect of
with you know the path of least resistance for light
which i imagine has to do with like permissivity
which is that if you're traveling through a field
where there's a bunch of different potential paths
one path will have less resistance than a different path and so you fall and
that that's i've realized that you know physics
doesn't necessarily have a material model for light like it's field
but i think that there is probably a material property of of the substances
that it's traveling through that that affects it like one atom
will transmit light more easily than a different atom
and so when i think about the sorting algorithms
my first thought is algorithms take different amounts of time to run
right and so do you think that there's an aspect of
time that is important here where you have
the information of a of one sorting algorithm
is more quickly accessible than the information
of let's say another and so they're running on different time scales
and so at the beginning when they're sorting they're sorting relative to
which neighbor has a an answer that matches the time scale
of the cell itself does that make sense yeah it does um
yeah it's an interesting it's it's definitely an interesting point i mean
the thing just to go back and and i'm not a physicist so i don't want to get
like too deep into this and say something stupid but my understanding of
the the least what's cool about the least action business is that
you're right of course the different paths of different permissivities but
in order to pick the right path in some sense you have to try them all out
right you don't know that you're on the least path until unless you have some
information about all of them and and so and so that that kind of
non-locality i i think i think in in our case in
the case of the the algorithms there could well be a time component because
in order to know whether your neighbor is like you or not
you need to spend some time with them so so one of the things we're doing now is
tracking their life histories to figure out things like well how much time do
you need to spend next to someone before you decide that hey they're like me or
they're not like me and i think that um uh the active
inference framework is going to make some clear predictions about that you know
in terms of i'm just just in general bayesian you know reasoning is going to
just going to tell you like how many experiences do you need to have
with someone before you know whether their policies are surprising to you or
not right um again underlying the underlining the
idea that none of this is explicit these things don't have the the algorithms
don't have explicit code for doing any of that but we can track it from from
you know from observations so so stay tuned this is this is super super
early still um but i do think it's interesting that
i'm gonna i'm gonna have a discussion with uh with carlin also mark solans
about this because you know it has this it to me anyway maybe
maybe they'll tell me this is nonsense but to me it has this weird um
resonance with uh this idea of of conscious and unconscious drives
right we tell stories about why we did things and you sort of have this like
logical thatcher algorithm those like i well i did it because xyz
but it turns out that actually there may be some underlying pattern that isn't
apparent to you at all and may or may not be apparent to somebody else who's a
different observer may you know maybe an analyst a psychoanalyst or whatever
who's looking and say yeah well you think that's what you did and in that local
you know in that situation that story kind of makes sense but look at the
bigger pattern if you look at the bigger pattern you find out that
actually you tend to xyz right and so i just wonder whether this is also a
really minimal model of how we understand implicit goals which are
there directly in whatever um algorithm you're following uh sorry those would
be explicit goals and then and then there are some implicit goals
that you're following and i have no idea where those come from right and that's
i think that's an exciting area for the futures to figure out where they come
i'm curious about the instrumentalization of this because it seems well is is that
the goal of studying these systems is so that perhaps you can program these
bio bots eventually to towards some end and then if that is the case is it ideal
for the bio bots to be intelligent like would you really want them choosing
their own goals or making decisions um perhaps it is but but it's it's a bit
hazy for me how that would be useful um yeah yeah that's a that's a great point
well well the first let's just let's just start off here uh if they if in fact they
do have their own goals we would love to know about that before we use them in
some particular context right and this is true with bots it's true with bacteria
with CAR T cells with swarm robotics with the internet of things with financial
institutions with social structures if these things are going to have goals
beyond what we think of when we built them we need to know about it right so
whether you whether you want them to have goals or not they may or may not so
you need to know so it seems like the the on the spot developments of goals
right the changing of goals is i guess more what i was concerned about you know
if they decide well we had this goal before but now we're now we've changed
our minds so to speak yeah yeah second order right second order goals you know
choosing your own goals again i don't know that that and by the way i've made no
claims that either the answer or either either the bots or the algorithms do
that all we've done so far is find some goals they have that we don't didn't
know about we i've made no claims that they have the second order ability to
choose their goals but if that's true we need to know right whether that's
whether that's true or not so that's that's the first step now why now let's
answer the other question why do you want them to have goals well
imagine um think of uh the the spectrum of of intelligence all the way from
very simple machines that do very specific things and they're sort of you know
whatever else happens they're just going to do the same thing over again
all the way through various cybernetics creations that have goal directed
abilities and then some animals that can be trained and then some humans that
can set their own goals to some extent and so on um think about think about
medicine you know biomedicine uh where do our interventions fit on that scale
right now almost all of with with only a couple interesting examples all of our
interventions are way on the left side of that spectrum
they're extremely simple mechanical things drugs for example right so
typical drugs they just do what they do they're not context sensitive
if they're binding something they're going to bind it and that's it and
whether that's good for you or bad for you and this is why we're having
massive divergence of efficacy and side effects in people because they just do
what they do imagine if we could get beyond that and we could have
interventions that are higher agency interventions where you could push some
of the complexity onto the reagent such that it would have some and so so now
the obvious thing that people think about here are like smart insulin pumps
right they don't just sort of pump out you know they have a little bit of
sensing and they kind of know what's going on right so smart insulin pumps um
I think our example which I think we talked about last time
of HCN2 which is this ion channel that we use to
repair various birth defects that's a step in this direction because that
that the drugs that open that channel are they act in a context sensitive way
that's what allows them to fix very complex structures like brain face heart
and gut it's not because they do the same thing no
matter what they're actually trying to do a very
particular thing which is to increase voltage depending on what's going on in
the environment increase the difference in voltage the
sharpen the boundaries so that's that's already a step up
and I think that what what the opportunity here is with the for
specifically with the antherobots and we could talk about what they do and why
is we can take advantage of the various competencies of parts of your own body
in this case these are tracheal cells from the same
patient to do complex things that we have no idea how to
how to force in medicine so we could take advantage of the intelligence of
your own cells to heal things and to do sensing in
both directions of the push meaning meaning to to heal and to improve
and then to to read which is the the sensing side you know
these cells probably know more about each other than we even know
to ask questions about nevermind have sensors for and so I think having these
kind of reagents that actually do have a processing they have
you know signal detection amplification memory decision making readouts
all of these things that are part of a a a simple cognitive system
you you want your your medical intervention to have that because
then you can do things that we couldn't possibly micromanage
and the thing that we found the antherobots could do which is just
mind-boggling to me is that if you if you put them on a
on a on a scratch that you've made in the two-dimensional culture of neurons
so you take human pluripotent stem cell derived neurons you grow a
lawn of them on a on a on a petri dish you scratch
you put a scratch through it that's that's you know so when people use that
as a simple model of wound healing it's a scratch
scratch assay you put down these antherobots and what they'll do is over a
few days they'll they'll take the edges of that wound
and they'll knit the they'll knit the neurons together now who knew
who could have said that um the cells of your trachea which
normally sit there quietly for whatever 80 plus years
that if you that if you let them go and let them reboot their life
they can actually run around on their own and find neural
wounds to heal and who knows what else i mean that was just the first thing you
try it who knows what else what else they know how to do
like that's that's a competency of these cells that we had no idea about
and again it's that sort of thing where uh i'm sure somebody reading that paper
could say well uh there must be some pro you know pro neural molecule that
they're putting out and i'm sure we'll find it yeah no
sure of course there's going to be a physical explanation for it's not going
to be magic there's going to be there's going to be some after the fact there's
going to be some explanation for it which we are of course investigating
but how come no theory predicted that ahead of time how come we didn't know to
expect that that's what i think is much more
interesting it's easy to tell stories afterwards the question is
you know uh yeah how you know what what what what models what models in world
used you have to get you to do the experiment in the first place
and so that being the first thing we tried my my i don't think you know we
should be playing the lottery every day it's we're not the luckiest people in
the world i think what this is telling us is that they have tons of unexpected
capacities and we're going to be of course looking for these
is naming them bots ambitious or because it seems like you're you want to have
control over their behavior that's the way i think about robots anyways
i'm not a robotic scientist or anything but
do you is that the ultimate goal is to tell them exactly what part of the
dish to go to or what which of the cuts to heal perhaps
something like that and and what what's the road to that
yeah um well first first let's just talk about the terminology for a moment
yeah um it's it's certainly true that we could have just called them organoids
uh but but the thing with organoids is that organoids are typically
the perp so so here's what i think words are for and and nomenclature is for i
think words are um just protocols for for interacting with something
so so when you name something what you're doing is
facilitating or preventing ways to interact with it so if you call it a if
you call something an organoid what you're really saying is
i'm focused on making this as uh as as best of a model of the of the real
organ as possible i want it to be exact i'm going to screen drugs on it i'm
going to you know study airway biology i want it to be a little
model of a lung that's what i want by calling it bot what i'm saying is
yes all that and there are plenty of people who have made airway organoids
and and and so on but actually there's much more here to do because because
you can we can in fact in the future program them and this this came up
when we were doing the zenobots people said why are you calling them zenobots
i mean developmental biologists who who study amphibian embryos have seen
ciliated epithelium for decades we call them animal caps
these are just animal caps why why do you need a new word for and i couldn't
say it at the time because this stuff was was not published but
the point is yeah and if you call them animal caps you'll never make an
anthrabot because because why would you because if
because that's an amphibian specific embryonic thing why would you take an
adult human trachea that you wouldn't get there
and so words have real power they they they tell you how you're thinking about
something and they facilitate once you once you call them bots you say well
bots can be made out of a lot of things maybe it's not just a frog thing maybe
we could make this out of out of human cells right and so they facilitate so
that's what i'm interested in is terminology that facilitates research
programs and um and so and so yeah so the future
is definitely to program them in in various ways
uh much like with the zenobots you know the first three zenobot papers
were basically just studying the native properties of these things and so i mean
you dug did some super cool stuff about sculpting them and and and so on
but the thing is uh what what what i really want to do
is focus on surprising native capacities because if the first thing we
did was knock in a bunch of synthetic biology circuits
people would say ah well but you've engineered the heck out of them so yes
of course they do whatever you made them do and that's fine
i want to say we've we've in the in the case of the anthrabots we've done
almost nothing to them right we've so so gizem came up with it with a with a
protocol to to get them to to grow from a single cell
and then turn inside out so that the cilia are on the outside surface and all
that but but we didn't do anything to make them heal uh neural
wounds they already do that and and that that i think is really
valuable because yes of course we'll get to programming them and this means
giving them all sorts of stimuli when they're assembling and it means putting
in different cell types perhaps and it means training them maybe so we haven't
we haven't shown that yet but we're working on that both with them and with
the zenobots uh can they be trained can they be you
know what native preferences do they have all that kind of stuff
um that that will all come but but what i think is really critical much like
what the algorithms is to say we thought we knew what tracheal
epithelium does and we thought we knew what organoids are for and look there's
a lot more to it than that
yeah that make that clears it up a lot it's interesting that in some sense that
golf between doing what you want and doing what they want
is both dangerous and exciting and it it seems like there's a lot of crossover
with the ai world because a lot of people are very concerned with that
valley between the two now do you have conversations with ai
engineers about the similarities and what you're finding
yeah yeah um yes and and there's some uh there's some fun that
twitter threads are about it too um uh and and we have you know about
probably a quarter of my group is uh uh computational machine learning
expert so we certainly you know we certainly think about that stuff a lot
um yeah i i think i think the main limiting factor in a lot of these
discussions is that they take place in a vacuum that neglects the wider context
of diverse intelligence i mean people people well first
of all first of all this this this focus on specifically language models and
things like that it that's like a tiny corner of what's
actually coming right diverse intelligence is gonna be so much more
challenging and interesting than than than just what we have now and that's
really important i think a lot of people are not not i'm not getting it and
also you know a lot of people are saying things like
it's it's intelligent like us and therefore it's dangerous there are plenty
things that are incredibly dangerous that are not intelligent like us you don't
need to be super intelligent to be extremely dangerous you don't need to
be like us to be intelligent like there are all kinds of leaps here that
people tend to make that i think are not warranted but just um
just in general like a real uh
understanding of the fact that intelligence can be uh expressed in
unfamiliar guises and some and some humility around like how bad we really
are at recognizing other other forms of it you know besides what we're
used to would be what i would be i think really useful and
essential i think it's an existential need for us going forward if we're
going to survive with the antherbots and the xenobots
both they're derived from organisms that have
immune systems and the action of cells migrating to a place where
there is a wound seems really immune like to me
do you think that there is a significant relationship between
those two functions where there is a certain drive inside
the body to produce cells that will heal that is
encoded somehow in the substrate genetically where it's like once you
liberate a cell from its context there's some sort of other
deeper level programming which is like okay my job now that i'm free
since i'm not a cancer cell is to do the the opposite of proliferate
and is in fact to go into fix yeah um that's a very interesting hypothesis i
mean these are uh epithelial cells are not specifically
immune cells and in the in normally in the body they don't do any of that they
just sit quietly basically but but i like i like where you're going with
this and i think that one advantage that these things
have over other kinds of um robotics that we might make or drugs or various
other things is that they probably share with us the
priors about what it's like to be healthy about about what's good
about being a being because not only are they mammals not only are they human
not only but but they're also your own cells so it's entirely plausible to me
now we haven't proven any of this i want to be super clear we don't know that
they home to wounds we don't know what they can recognize
you know we don't know any of that um but it's very plausible to me that they
share with us this notion of what damages and what repair is
um yeah this this this may be you know this may be
something that that is really uh advantageous about this technology
you know is that you don't have to teach them what's good and bad about
being a multicellular organism and from from what i read of the
antherbot's paper the way that you're generating these cells is that you take
them you grow them in an extracellular matrix that's three-dimensional
from single cells and then you put them into
what you call it a low viscosity medium and in the low viscosity medium you see
these changes occur and
the changes are like you said pretty stark so you have these
these cells that normally would be ciliated
on the interior of the cells you turn them so that they're ciliated on the
outside and so all of a sudden you have this
motile collection of cells and
i wonder if you have looked to see what the actual changes are inside of the
cell that permits this kind of new organization
as a consequence of the different growth conditions
yeah um no we we don't know the details yet it's
the change is a multicellular in other words
it's not an individual cell that does much of anything it's the whole thing
turns itself inside out so you start with a ball where the cili are pointing
into the center of the ball and then then the whole thing just turns inside out
when when we wash it out of the out of the matrix it turns inside out
now what exactly does that we we don't know my gut feeling is that there are
going to be some pathways looking that that probably
would look like embryonic gastrulation and some things like that i'm going to
guess it's probably reusing some of that that's a total guess we don't know
yeah the answer is we don't know but embryonic gastrulation to me
is a almost quasi stem cell property
where it's where stem cells probably the wrong the wrong word to use but
there's early development like early development like they
aren't differentiated to their context yet and so
do you think that it's just a property of cells that once you take them out
of the context of the body where they have grown used to being and now you
put them into this matrix where they have to
recontextualize themselves that this is an opportunity for them to
to kind of redesign their own their own relationship to the environment
suddenly that's that that is a yeah that's a great
point uh what this is all currently under investigation
uh do they think they're recapitulating some kind of embryogenesis we
we don't know so so the xenobots for example the normal xenobot
lives for about a week but we've been able to if
if you feed them and keep them ridiculously clean
they can go longer and they will go uh i think our record is like
84 days or something and during those weeks
it changes shape it changes shape it becomes transparent it
it does some other stuff and uh i don't know is that is that some new
developmental sequence that you know that normally
no no one ever does um yeah we you know we we don't know and the same thing with
the anthrobots like like is this uh is this a developmental
sequence basically for this it does it think it's an embryo we're gonna find
out we're doing all the you know we're we're characterizing all the new
genes that they express both the xenobot and the anthrobot side
uh yeah we're gonna we're gonna find out but we don't know yet
there was a there was a science fiction story i want to say it was
arthur clark but maybe not uh a long time ago where um
they cracked uh aging and so people started living longer
and what they found out was that at around 120 humans undergo all these
changes it's just you've never seen it before because nobody ever lived that
long and so you know they start growing a third like a new set of teeth and all
this stuff and i think i think at the end
what i think they they grew wings and look like angels i forget what it was
but but it was the point where yes actually there was this new
developmental stage it's just you know what you we had didn't access it before
but but so so maybe this is like that maybe these these things have a new
a new developmental sequence that they can do i don't know
it seems like uh when i think about the major health crises
let's say the threats in most people's lives assuming they don't die from an
accident or something it's cancer and heart disease
and those are very different bioengineering projects
one where you're in the case of cancer perhaps trying to
teach cells how to behave themselves again something like that
i mean i suppose the approach right now is to just destroy them
but i i i suppose ultimately you would want your bots to be teachers
in a sense and perhaps it's similar with with
cardiovascular disease as well but that seems like more of a
a repair in the wound healing sense uh perhaps a cleanup job
is there some uh well do you think about this
in terms of the bots in terms of what their ultimate functionality will be
in terms of maybe not simply joining or or obeying some
specific program goal but in terms of teaching and
interacting with their new environments and
re-instructing them and what yeah what is the future of that look like
in your mind yeah i think that uh there's a there's a few there's a few
different uh use cases for the bots the most
the most obvious things are we're going to make
useful synthetic living machines for specific purposes
so maybe they drop off pro regenerative molecules maybe they clean up cancer
cells maybe they scrape the plaque off your artery
walls maybe they they clean up arthritic knee
joints they repair you know retina or spinal cord we like
very specific things so so we'll be some of that
i i think bigger picture what both they and the xenobots
are are a kind of uh platform in which we get to learn to control morphogenesis
so so cracking the code the mapping between
the experiences you received as a cell and the pattern that a group of you are
going to build because if we solve that that's it that's a completely
different path to regenerative medicine that has nothing to do with the bots
per se in other words at some point we're going to know
how to grow a new heart how to grow new limbs how to grow new organs why you
know and and and the stuff what we're working on right now in the lab which
is trying to understand why do they forget why do
tissues forget what the correct pattern is why does everything fall apart after
some number of decades right so so using the bots as a kind of sandbox
platform to understand how do collections of cells make decisions
about what they're going to do so that's kind of that's kind of the second
thing and then there's this is more philosophical stuff but
but but for biomedicine right there are the direct use cases and then
there's the bigger picture of you know what we really want is complete control
over growth and form that's that's what we really do do you imagine that to be
like an in situ process at the end of the day or is it ex vivo are you going to
be growing the do you imagine these medical technicians
i don't know how many years from now are growing these externally and replacing
diseased organs or is it more something that's happening inside of the body
like you're actually you know in the sense reprogramming your body or giving
it the external environment that needs in order to regenerate itself
it seems like two very different approaches yeah i think i think uh long
term it's all going to be in situ and uh
in in the meantime are we going to crack the uh ex vivo morphogenesis and
transplant before we crack the in vivo stuff i'm not sure
i'm not sure uh down the line it's it's it's all going to be
it's all going to be in vivo but maybe maybe maybe the uh
the bioengineered organs will get cracked first i'm not sure
that seems to be the more traditional approach as far as i can tell
you know we are we're already doing organ transplants with varying levels of
success um obviously the huge advantage here is
just that you have ideally your own cells right or
something that matches and you don't have the horrible immune problems with the
transplantation yeah um i mean so you could argue
both ways on the one hand you could say well uh just just growing a specific or
a single specific organ should be easier and then we'll just
pop it in maybe but but look at look at for example the case so
so back in 2010 or so we show that there's a particular um bioelectric
pattern that causes frog embryos to make new eyes
in weird locations when your eyes on the gut on the tail whatever
um we are nowhere near being able to bioengineer
and grow an eye in in vitro right i mean so so so people have shown like if you
explained the eye progenitor cells and you sort of
leave them alone they can make an optic cup and some things like that
but but it's not that it's not that we knew how to how to engineer an eye eyes
are very complex they have lots of different tissue types
what we simply did was to take advantage of the competency of the material
meaning the cells of the in vivo they they they know how to make an eye
they they've already done it twice they they certainly have all that
information what you need to be able to do is convince them to do it again
somewhere else and so if you look at this problem as
can i micromanage the cells to be an organ
you know using traditional bioengineering maybe we make a bladder
maybe we make you know ears are not hard we can make things where we can make a
scaffold we see a bunch of cells on tops
maybe 3d print some things maybe you know you might think that's the way to go
but i actually think the easier way to do it is not to try to control
any of that it's to convince the collective what you want them to build
and just do that in vivo where the surrounding material is
is basically much smarter than we are about how it's done
so i'm not sure i we'll see how we will see how it goes
there's a really interesting aspect of this where if you can
reprogram an embryo to grow eyes in places where you wouldn't expect eyes
okay so there's two places where my mind immediately goes number one
there's a certain permissivity of the embryo
where the entire context of the being is that okay we are in the process we are
we are we are creating the structure we get instructions
we make it and then we get to a place where we cease our differentiation
and the structures are more or less fixed and they get repaired in place
and so one question and you can you can go either way with us
is a do you think that once the structures are fixed you have a completely
different problem where you would then have to inflict some kind of damage
in order to get them to regenerate and number two which is kind of orthogonal
is the eyes that form in places where you don't expect
are they then wired into the brain in the way that you would expect
yeah let me let me do the first one and then remind me of the second one
because i'll forget by the time i'm done
the first thing i want to say which is which is kind of a cool point it has to do with
the permissivity or the competency so and this is something that one of these things that i
couldn't you know say back in 2010 but now now that we're talking about development as a
as a collective intelligence process now we can start to think about it this way
if you look in the developmental biology textbook they will tell you that only in the frog
only the anterior norectoderm so the stuff you know basically from here up is competent to be i
and it's that's the only stuff that can make i and the reason is because if you prompt it with
what they call the master i gene which is this thing called pack six then yeah that those are
the only regions that ever make i but it turns out that actually that limited competency and
developmental biology competency is a narrow definition which is what it's able to make
i use it more broadly but more generically the competency of your material is opaque to you
unless you probe it with the correct prompt we need to and this is you know when people say
aw it can't do this you know this this doesn't do that whenever you're making an assessment
and an assessment of intelligence in some system you are basically taking an IQ test yourself as
an external observer you are saying this is what i have noticed how to make it do that doesn't mean
that's all it knows how to do that's just what you know so so in this is a great case for that
because actually it turns out that if you go to the bioelectric level no i have almost any cell
in as far as we can tell any region in the in the tadpole is it is competent to do this we just
didn't know that because we were using the wrong prompt and so and so this should all of this everything
we've talked about should really fill us with significant humility about about what we know
about the material that we're working with you don't necessarily know if you know i've i don't
know if you've ever seen these things i've got pictures of them on my blog and and a couple of
papers um these these plant galls you know these amazing just about to ask about that because they
create these insane structures prompted by the presence of like wasps and bugs that move inside
the leaves yeah and and if you didn't know that if you didn't have that example you would never
in a million years say that the that the oak genome could make this red spiky brown thing you
would say no it makes a flat green leaf and and it takes a living bioengineer who as dan
then it would say you know competency without comprehension uh is able to to prompt the leaf
to do this crazy to build this crazy thing you would never know it knows how to do that so um
that's uh you know that that's the important thing is that we really need to understand the
competency of our material and what what we're working with and i i actually don't think that
adulthood is when all of that ceases there's a there's a there's a ship a thesis thing going on
here which is that in a standard body right cells and materials are coming and going all the time
and you need to be able to um it's this thing like uh like like in allison wonderland where you uh
you have to work really hard to stay in one place you you in order to maintain a body you
can't just say well okay now i don't need this information i you know i'm just gonna hang out
you will not last very long um and and i think there probably are insects in other organisms
that that you know that live a day or a couple of days where that's where that's true but typically
if you want to persist you have to continuously re repair remodel replace and and and so on and um
so so i think uh the only thing that happens during uh during maturation is that the scale
of those projects gets smaller so instead of re shaping the whole embryo during neuralation and
gastrulation all that you're now saying okay well these few cells are gone how do i maintain the
integrity of my epithelium and things like that right so but but i think i think that process of
of homeostasis anatomical homeostasis which which i am really into is uh continues your your whole
life and and without that process uh i in fact that's what i think aging is is a is a a defect in
that process it's just it's basically a you know i think i think aging is a version of failure to
regenerate it's a which and development is basically just a set of regenerative repairs
from each embryonic stage to the next stage i think all of this boils down to regenerative
remodeling which boils down to homeostasis humans can't really grow gauze though sorry say again i
said humans can't really grow gauze though which is we don't know that we don't know that you know
sure sure i guess i guess the only thing that i'm saying is that if i think about the various human
diseases right because if if there's a parallel between okay oak gall would you say that that's a
disease no no i don't think no i don't think it's a disease i think it's uh now now there are there
are virus induced galls that uh that screw up cells and so on so and those those are basically
featureless lumps they're kind of like a tumor but maybe you can say that's a disease a standard one
of these galls i mean from the perspective of the plant it might be a disease but i i think
it's morphogenetic hacking i think i think all you've done is you've with the what the wasp has
done is to um hack the material to go to undertake a different journey in morpheus space and i don't
think that's i don't think that's it that that that that's a disease do we have any sense of
what's the different morphological purpose is like why does one wasp make one gall another
wasp make another gall um i do not know there are people who study this so so um
uh insect ecologists and uh and such there are a couple of folks that i'm in touch with that study
that kind of stuff i i don't know uh for me the interesting thing is the space of the possible
and how little so so if you think about this giant multi-dimensional uh anatomical morpheus
space which holds all the different shapes that things can be normal standard reliable
development gives you one pointless tiny little keyhole into that space and all you see is the
embryo and the normal thing that it builds and then sometimes you have what they call developmental
plasticity and look this plant can have two different shapes depending on if it's a dry
environment or a wet okay so so instead of a single point you see kind of like a little
little halo or up through your keyhole but through that keyhole is a giant space of possibilities
that we are still very bad at mapping out and what i think these uh all the synthetic stuff
that antherobots the xenobots other other things that people the goo galls other things that people
build are all vehicles for exploring that space they let you they let you take that little keyhole
and like like stick your head in and look around like a like a periscope and and look around and
say here are the other possibilities you know and and what human cells can do uh well we didn't
think they made antherobots until you know we did it a few years ago so i don't know my guess is
i so so so the way to um uh kind of uh uh just just drill down on on that question is uh
are there any limits so people ask is there any limit to what a given cell can build and some
people say yeah they're called developmental constraints there are things that the i'm not
sure i believe in developmental constraints i i think that in a given context there are limits
to what it's going to do does that mean that if you knew what you were doing you couldn't
prompt it to do something completely different no i i think um and and again this is conjecture on
my part but here's here's here's what i think um that basically there are going to be like like for
example if you have planaria if planaria don't have genes to make bone you know the the the hard
minerals and all that okay you're not you're not going to get them to to you know to to make bone
because if the if the hardware isn't there it isn't there but beyond that in terms of shape
i'm not sure there are any limits i i don't i i just i you know i think in the end um except
for materials limits and the laws of physics i don't believe there's going to be any limitations
on what shape you could build i guess this ties back to the question of whether or not the eyes
are tied into the brain right because if you have a crazy body plan and all of a sudden
your like elementary canal is all screwed up and you're just dumping waste into your internal
cavity you're gonna have a bad time yeah so uh yeah um i'm glad you remember that um okay i'm
i'm not gonna say that there aren't ways to screw things up because absolutely there are and uh the
competency of regulative development that fixes all these problems is not infinite and there's
many ways to screw up an embryo for sure for sure but this is some work that um Doug Blackiston in
my group did same same person who did all the zen the zen about biology um but by the way if you
can get him on you'll have a great time uh he's he's amazing but anyway back back in the well yeah
around 2013 2014 something like that we uh we we did some experiments where what we did was we we
we grew ectopic eyes on the backs and the tails of tadpoles and we asked that question can i see
out of these eyes what happens when you have this new architecture is it is it functional
the the answer is super interesting first of all it turns out that yeah they can see we we we actually
built a machine that um trains them on on visual cues and and and and we made tadpoles that did
not have primary eyes but they had this you know this one eye on its tail yeah they can learn in
visual or visual assay so they can absolutely see the next question is you know you said does it
connect to the brain well it doesn't connect to the brain actually it connects to either the
spinal cord or in some cases nothing obvious that we can figure out and they can see anyway
so so not only is it um plastic in terms of um making the right uh the right organs and the right
structure excuse me but actually um even even the wiring is uh is up for uh is is you know is
is up for change and you know just imagine like you you you come into this world and you have this
weird itchy patch of tissue on your back like how do you even know that's visual data you know but
the brain is able to is able to use it and um and and and i'll tell you two two two fun fun things
about that one is that um we we then uh let some of those okay so imagine you got an eye on the tail
you let that animal grow eventually that tadpole is going to turn into a frog well the tail has to
disappear and what happens is normally the tail gets these signals it it degrades it you know
basically um apoptosis uh you know it eats itself and so on and then the tail disappears so we had
a pool going in the lab about well what's going to happen to the eye right and uh because the whole
tail is going to die what what about the eye does the eye think it's part of the tail does it so so
this was this was super cool and we watched this thing and uh i'm not sure if we publish i don't
remember if we published it but i i i got these amazing pictures of um frogs with eyes on their
butts because what happens is the tail gets smaller and smaller the eye gets bigger and bigger and the
eye of it just rides it back and eventually just ends up sitting on the butt of the frog the tail
is long gone that eye is is is perfectly clear that it's not part of the tail and it's not going to
you know degrade the way the tail will and we we don't know if it's functional on the adult frog
because we don't really have a good um behavioral method for adult frogs the way we had for tadpole
so i don't i don't know if the adult frog can see backwards we don't know but um but but yeah the
the eye survived the death of the tail and so just just more broadly you might think about why
i mean why is the frog why is the tadpole ready for this for for eyes to be formed like that
doesn't happen in nature why would ever and why would evolution do that and i think the lesson
that uh i think we not not just from this work but from from a lot of work is this evolution
i don't think makes solutions to specific problems but i think evolution does is make
problem-solving machines and part of that is the um and and i got a paper from a few months ago um
where i beat this uh you know in in significant detail this this idea that because because evolution
is working with an agential material it naturally makes systems that um that that can solve these
problems and and here's one of my favorite examples of of of this kind of thing is um this
was found back in the 40s that if you if you have a salamander and um what you can do is in in for
the very early embryos you can you can do this procedure which causes them to multiply their
genetic material so instead of two n you can have four n five n six n and so on so the first
amazing thing if you do that you still get a normal salamander so that's why it like extra
genetic material doesn't seem to confuse it but that's already kind of cool the next thing that
happens is that the cells get bigger in order to accommodate all that all the copies of the genome
but the salamander sees exactly the same size so that means that as your cells get bigger you need
to know to use fewer of them to build the same the exact same organs and so what what he did was he
took um um this was uh frank hauser and he took cross sections of this tubule that it's a kidney
tubule and he takes cross sections of it and he shows that in a normal uh animal there's like
eight to ten cells that go around and they sort of make this tubule in the middle is a big empty
space and then and then you make these cells big and now there's fewer there's like four or five of
them going around so that's amazing thing number two is that if uh if your cells are the wrong size
you know to adapt their numbers so that you can have the same overall structure here's the real
kicker if you make the cells gigantic and i believe these were maybe like five n or six n
nudes or something like that the cells are so big only one of them fits and so what does the cell
do it bends around itself like this leaving a hole in the middle to make the exact same tubule now
the reason that's super cool is that that's a different molecular mechanism in the former
case you have cell to cell communication tubular genesis blah blah blah in this case you have
cytoskeletal bending so so this is top down causation this is crazy this is calling up different
new more different molecular mechanisms to achieve the same high level anatomical goal
right that that's i mean if that's not intelligence i don't know if we had if we had any kind of a
machine that could do this i mean this would be super amazing intelligence because you're
faced with a problem you've not seen before you can you can call up different resources of yours
to get to get the job the same job done if you're prevented from and and now think of think of the
amazing thing that this that this embryo has to has to deal with i'm going to come into the world
i don't know how many copies of my genetic material i'm going to have i don't know the
size of my cells i don't know the number of my cells i don't know if somebody's going to cut me in
half uh early on i have to be able to make a salamander despite all of this changes in the
environment changes in my own parts for god's sake right like i don't i can't even depend on my own
components i i don't know what what dna i'm gonna have but but i'm gonna make this salamander right
and and so and so i think that is what evolution gives us it gives us in for many species not not
all i'm not sure c elegans does any of that but but for for many species what evolution has given
you is this amazing uh problem-solving machine that does not make too many assumptions about
what the world is going to be like now you now you would think that um that's what evolution is for
is to is to is to progressively over time extract information about the environment and make sure
that whatever you're born in you've got the benefit of all those prior generations but in machine
learning you've got this notion of overfitting you know overtraining on your examples you don't
want to just memorize your training data set you want to uh you want to be smarter than that and i
think um absolutely uh development is smarter than that i don't think development over trains on
on on these priors i think it learns a lesson of how to solve these problems and i think really
every life multicellular but probably all but but certainly the multicellular life
is um is is is born into the world solving problems i don't think it you don't know what
you have until you sort of take stuff and this is why you can take an early embryo and cut it
into pieces and have multiple twins instead of you know half embryos and and so on yeah i know
that shyla has a bunch of stuff uh do you want to do you want to pick up on the on the idea of the
platonic salamander form that remains even with five n i mean i have some more like divergent
philosophical questions about this regenerative medicine that i can hang out if you got if you
want to keep pulling on this thread i mean the let's let's stay here for a little bit because
i think the regenerative medicine is what this all kind of centers around right because we want
to be able to see as as much as i don't like the idea of science being an instrumentalizable process
where there's there's discovery simply for the sake of discovery we we all live within a system where
the discoveries at some point need to be instrumentalized onto something in order to
get people to really see the point of it and to really get people viscerally invested in it and
so i think that that's that might be a good place to end but where do you think the platonic form
of the salamander comes from the idea that you can take this embryo and you can screw with it you
can change the genetic organization you can make the cells enormous so that it goes from
cell cell signaling to create a kidney tubule to just one cell that wraps around it like
what is that yeah boy uh yeah um that that is the uh the hard question isn't it um i mean i should
say from the beginning that uh i don't know but um i think we definitely start with that but um we
we can we can say a few things about it um one one thing is that uh
there there are um there are a lot of what what physicists would call free lunches in this kind
of scenario in the following in the following way imagine imagine that um you're you're running
evolution in a particular world where the most fit um the thing is a particular kind of triangle
yeah it's it's it's a certain kind of triangle so here comes evolution and it does a bunch of
generations and it nails down the first angle and it optimizes the first angle and then
bunch more generations and it optimizes the second angle now it's done it doesn't have to
look for the third angle because we already know that once you know two angles in flat space you
know what the third angle is supposed to be uh isn't that amazing isn't it where did that come
from it's certainly not in the genome uh it's a free gift from the laws of geometry physics i don't
know but but it's it's super practical because whereas one can think you know the old this this
whole idea this this platonic Pythagorean idea of of these um these information structures that hang
out somewhere else not in the physical world then when you make specific physical
embodiments for them then you get to to to to to interface with them you know when you
have a fulcrum you get to have um you know our committees uh so simple machines and things like
that um it it it all sounds initially it all sounds very um philosophical in the bad in the
in the pejorative sense it's like why we need any of that we you know it's it's all you're just adding
you know crazy stuff onto our ontology you don't need it but when you're saving 33 percent of
evolutionary time now this is quite practical now this is this is you you really have to ask
where does this where do these things come from and there are tons of these throughout mathematics
so i you know think of all the truths of number theory uh all of the all you know the distribution
of primes all this other stuff where where where do those things hang out presumably all the all
the physical structures at the beginning of the big bang that set all the you know the the
forces the relative strengths of the forces all that all that stuff could have been completely
different and still the truths of number theory are what they are and so i'm partial to this idea
that there is a platonic realm of some sort um that it does contain a bunch of free lunches that
evolution is really good at searching it that i i don't think that what evolution is doing is
searching the really hard space of microstates on on the on the on the output outcome i think that
what it's really basically searching for is and this is this is a bad analogy but we don't have
better ones yet it's searching the space of pointers into this platonic space it's searching
for ways to capitalize on these free lunches this idea that i mean there's so many of these like
i can imagine if you if you have a uh when you um evolve a voltage gated ion channel what you
really have is a voltage gated current conductance you have a transistor and if you have a couple of
those you can make a logic gate and when you have a logic gate you have a truth table you have the
basis of rational thought you have a truth table and you have the fact that nand gates so not and
gates are actually quite special compared to all the other gates so where is all that stuff all you
did was make a voltage gated ion channel where'd you get all that stuff from you you didn't need to
evolve a truth table you didn't need to nail down all the components uh you you get all of that for
free and so so so i see everything we're doing as a research program in which we develop tools
to map out that space what else is out there because because again you have to ask yourself
what what what is this crazy world you do for you well i think what it does for you is it sensitizes
you to look for things that you didn't expect things that you didn't bake in it helps you think
about making tools to explore that right um and uh i think that the way that you know if you look at
um somebody made this thing called the map of mathematics and it's just like this literally
this map and you get different areas of math and how they relate to each other i i i think i
think platonic space has a structure to it i think there are all kinds of interesting things there
from from from geometry and the things we call geometry and algebra and and you know computation
and so on and evolution is really good at capitalizing on some of that stuff and so so what
else so so to get back to your question does does the form of the salamander hang out there
maybe but also form and function of the antherobots and zenobots and who and galls and who knows
what the heck else is there um and i think i think that structure is um rich i don't think it's
flat and homogenous in the for example when we when we studied the behavior and the shape of these
of the antherobots we didn't just see a continuum of here's every possible thing it came in in in
in morphotypes it came in in in chunks like this there's this kind there's that kind there's this
kind and so yeah i think i think this the the space has structure and i think we need to
and so i'm i'm also working on and this this you know we'll take a little bit and we can
maybe talk about it at some future time because i don't have it all worked out but i think there's
even there's even an interesting uh thing where like under under my understanding of this of the
standard um kind of view of this this platonic space thing is that the contents are supposed to
be eternal and unchanging right it's sort of fixed they're all they just hang out and they are what
they are and like that's it so so i'm not sure that's true i think i think we can start to develop a
kind of chemistry of it that ways in which these things actually are active in some sense
distinct from the way they actually manifest here and i think there are useful i think there
are useful models of that that we can that we can develop to say how do those things combine and
and change and how does that impact which ones and how we are able to implement in in you know
in engineering and biology and so on i wonder to what extent those forms are stored in the
external environment too like when you were talking about the nephron tubule things i was
thinking i wonder how much the hydrostatic pressures and so forth are sculpting the cell
into the form that it takes and how much of the salamander is a product of forcing by the world
the entire i mean i hate to say the entire universe but essentially everything collaborating to make
the salamander yeah yeah yeah it's well for sure for sure the context of those cells matters
right and and it's entirely possible that in order to explain what's going on we need to consider
inputs from the biophysical environment from the energetics and from the from all kinds of stuff
i'm sure i'm sure that's true um the question is is and this isn't this is an open question
is there a more informative meaning a more um a model that leads to better in invention
where what you're talking about is ways in which those parameters index into a pre-existing space
of options versus some other i mean frankly i don't know what the what the what the you know
competing model would be but but some some way of just um you know sort of calculating locally
all the forces and and things like that which i'm sure can be done the question is does it help
you find the next thing you know there's a really interesting limit to the kinds of synthetic
organisms that can be produced and the routes to them like i know that craig vent craig ventner
was working on you know what is the minimal cell that can be produced and the way that they arrived
at it was not from bottom up production it was they took a cell and they continuously deleted
portions of it until they got to some minimum component and the minimum component was some
thing is like 350 protein coding genes and if you look at the papers they're pretty wonky looking
cells like they're not really super functional anymore and there's a there's a there's a limit
there that i think is breachable with a different kind of design right because none of ventner's
work was about this idea of okay environment forcing parameters what can we take to produce
a cell that rises from a different environment and matures into something new and with a salamander
i like you could probably produce a different kind of salamander with a different kind of
body plan with different organs but like do you think that without genetic modification you could
produce something that's like a bird probably not right well i'll tell you what what we have done
in planaria so so so two examples and again on the on the on the bird thing how about those
galls like there's no genetic modification there right like we would have again the
looking backwards somebody's going to say oh yeah i can see how this particular growth factor is
this and that right so you got flat leaf and you got gall great but the bigger issue here you would
have not known that there's a gall you don't know what the next gall is capable of like right so
there's more to it um here's here's what we did in planaria first of all we made two-headed planaria
by altering the bioelectric pattern we talked about this last time there's no genetic modification
there they're permanently two-headed so that's something it's not another species but it's
definitely different than the original species so it's something also we've shown that you can
actually make planaria with heads that belong to other species so about other species about 100 to
150 million years evolutionary distance so again no no genetic modification now can you go can you
go further and you can you know can you make it look like a bird you're not going to get bone
i don't think but could you could you get patterns that look like other animals i bet you could
if you've ever seen um uh there's another thing that's uh that that speaks to this those uh i
forget i forget what the name of the the fly it's it's a little fly and on its wings it has a picture
of ants and it's right you know i'm talking about so so yeah so so there you're what it's doing is
running a stripped down like low resolution two-dimensional morphogenesis program on its on
its wings and so i think the the reprogrammability and the virtualization is massive i think we've
not scratched the surface of it so so you know could i tell you what the limits of that are or
whether there are limits no i don't know but i would i would bet large amounts of money that the
the uh the narrow view that we have now of the mapping between genome and anatomy is way too
narrow for reality so one of the things that comes up a lot when i when i discuss your work
with people who maybe aren't scientists or aren't really thinking deeply about these questions
is okay great we'll be able to regenerate our organs maybe we'll live for a very long time but
the brain or the mind starts to become an issue at some point and there's something about the
mind that's very different from a kidney in that it seems to be that the cells the functionality
of the brain let's say i i know that the mind is sort of delocalized but let's say the central
nervous system or whatever you want to call it the thinking machine of the body those cells
patterning depends on their experience and so if you had a disease of the brain like a
brain tumor or something in terms of treating damage to the brain or regenerating the brain
is it conceivable that we'll be able to in some sense pattern these experiences without
having gone through the entire path of the life in order to have those connections it just seems
like kind of the the expert level regenerative medicine would be this very dynamic architecture
this this web like network which it just depends on on a past almost in a way that perhaps a kidney
doesn't is that something you've given any thought to yeah yeah yeah we yeah i think about this a
lot um a few a few things um first of all uh your brain is different from the kidney but
i don't think it's because the kidney doesn't think i do you know i like right now you my
left hemisphere is having a chat with your left hemisphere and and we're sort of pretty proud
of ourselves for having language and stuff but um there are plenty of other uh systems in the body
that solve problems that navigate physiological and other spaces and and we just don't sense them
anymore than we sense each other's consciousness so i'm actually not sure it's it's special in that
way but um to address your other point about how do we how do we deal with long-term memories i'll
give you i'll give you the kind of bummer idea and then the positive idea after that uh the bummer
idea is is is this i i don't know let's let's imagine and this this goes back to like the
traditional view of of heaven right like this idea of eternal let's say let's say your your you live
unlimited amounts of time it's aside from any issues of regeneration or damage or anything
like that it isn't obvious to me that any cognitive system can stay sane for an
unlimited amount of time like i'm pretty sure i could keep myself busy for 10 000 years probably
but like 10 million years i i don't know you know of a while and would you be able to integrate
your experiences from 10 000 years ago at some point it's like i wonder if we just start pasting
i feel like i paced over my experiences at some point you know i replaced them with new experiences
there's obviously the cognitive psychological modeling where we're constantly rehearsing our
memories as we go and it's not clear that you would even have access to your experience at
some range and that would maybe that's what you mean by going insane is you just lose track of who
you are i'm worried about more than that actually in that in that case um so so so it's entirely
possible and for example i'm i'm pretty sure that uh you know most of my memories past a few years
ago are pasted to a certain degree in the sense that if somebody said oh no you got that all wrong
this is how it really went down and we have video i'd be like all right i suppose that's it
like fine you know like i i don't know that my memories really go like you know that i would
really trust to go back very far at all anyway so so that's fine maybe that would just keep happening
and i think that some creatures like could could a dog stay perfectly sane and happy on a farm with
rabbits to chase and all that good stuff for like a billion years like maybe right maybe every day
would be as joyous as every other day and it would all be super cool like maybe that's fine
could a human do that i'm not sure i'm just not sure i don't know um but uh but let's let's let's
let's talk about the more the more realistic case um i think i think it's actually a lot a lot more
hopeful than than it sounds for the following reason uh the work on planaria and this was uh
first discovered by mcconnell in the 60s and 70s and then we replicated the important parts of it
in 2013 ourselves um they that you can train them and then you can cut off their entire head
brain and all and the tail will sit there doing nothing over the next eight days it regenerates
a new brain and now they remember the original information assuming and when we have to say
it's an assumption i don't know what the alternative is but let's let's assume that it's stored elsewhere
in the body what that shows is that you can actually imprint information onto a new developing
brain because until then they do nothing it's only once the brain is there that you see the
behavior whatever the information was maybe it was neural maybe it wasn't maybe it's holographic
throughout you know there's an amazing book called shuffle brain um about salamanders by this guy paul
peach and uh incredible and and he talks about this holographic theory of memory but maybe it's
all over the body who knows uh it's imprinted on the new brain now i'm not saying we're exactly
like planaria but they're telling us that it's possible they're telling us that it's possible
to uh imprint learned information onto new brain tissue um i actually don't believe that memories
are encoded by the specific micro um the architecture of your synapses that that story there are
increase that story is increasingly sort of cracking at this point and um whatever it is
i i have a feeling that if if we do regeneration correctly uh the memories will regenerate now
that's now now so i think i think that part is optimistic the part we have to keep keep track
of is that in an important way i think we are all like planaria in that we don't have access to our
past what we have access to are the engrams that the past has left in our brains and bodies
at any given moment and i don't know the thickness of that moment for for for each of us
but at any given moment all we're doing is reconstructing a plausible story based on those
engrams about what happened before and we all know it's fallible and it's you know we and every
time we do it we sort of alter the thing you were just talking about we're all doing that anyway
all the time like we are basically like people say oh my god these planaria are amazing yeah we
were pretty much all doing that you know all the time i think so so given that that that the core
self is a process it's a continuous homeodynamic process it's a reconstruction that's not a physical
structure that kind of sits there and you might lose it and then what happens um i think we're
fine i i think we're gonna if when we get to the point of being able to regenerate brain tissue
i think we're gonna be fine and and and i want to um also put in a couple of other
pointers to some stuff first of all and i have a student um carina with whom we are
writing a review of the of of all the mismatches between brain state and um uh and and cognitive
state but you know there are these cases of uh well there are many cases many different kinds
of cases but i'll just talk about one which is these these specific specific cases of of
hydrocephaly where somebody's someone someone is born with um fluid a very high fluid pressure in
there in there in their skull and that prevents the brain from developing and so you know this guy
Lorber in the 80s documented um some guy that had less than a third of the the uh the brain
volume of a chimpanzee and he was doing a master's program in math and he had above normal IQ and
like he wouldn't know he would you know he would introduce himself and meet people who take a
flashlight and shine it in one ear and it would sort of you know like pink light will come up the
other end and uh and he was completely fine and so um so so i think i think our mapping of information
to to um brain uh medium is we we don't understand how it works we have we have no idea and um
and there are many other clinical cases uh that underscore that underscore this idea so so so yeah
so i think uh i i think it's going to be fine i think i think it's much more um robust and you
can think about think about the um the caterpillar butterfly thing right like not only so so so
caterpillars basically destroy their brain they break up most of the connections but
when you do these experiments this is against some of Doug Blackistan's old work when you
check the moth or butterfly they remember the original information that you train the caterpillar
on not only do they remember but they actually generalize across that process because if you
train them to eat a particular kind of leaf on a particular color background the the moth or
butterfly will go feed the same way but they don't eat leaves they drink nectar and so you're not
remembering that leaves you know this particular color means leaves which you're remembering is food
so you're actually smart enough to generalize the category to a complete one when i'm a completely
different kind of being that doesn't care about leaves at all whereas before that's all i wanted
but now i don't care about leaves at all i i'm still going to generalize and i still know what i
want so right so amazing during like there's so much plasticity here i think we're going to be fine
this makes me think of the reports that i've read of people who have organ transplants
and appear to manifest the characteristics of the people that they get a heart transplant
or a lung transplant from yeah yeah we wanted to cover it in that review there's not enough
clinical well documented clinical cases but you're right and i've talked to i've talked to
transplant surgeons about this kind of stuff interestingly enough kidney donors liver donors
they don't talk about that stuff it's heart lung i don't know why but you know again the numbers
are small so not sure what you know the really egregious cases are are you know there's not that
many documented but yeah yeah there's there's something going on here and we have we have a
bunch of unpublished data generated by Johanna Bischoff in our group where we transplanted little
pieces of two-headed planaria into one headed planaria and some percentage of them if you
recut them again they convert to two-headed and so so this idea of transplanting information
be it morphogenetic information or be it behavioral information i don't make that much
distinction between them i think they're the same process it moves it moves with tissue
and it spreads when you put the little implant in it actually spreads across that information
not the cells the information spreads across the host so ultimately you know you know mcconnell
joked at the time it was 67 68 he joked about the concept of professor burgers this idea that
you could actually you know get somebody else's knowledge by eating you know pieces of
flesh made made from their body i don't know right like we know nobody's shown that you know
you can learn calculus and then pass that along in a burger but some kind of information maybe and
if we knew what the proper encoding and decoding was i think there would be all sorts of interesting
new routes for for memories this is i mean a dysfunctional example but prions seem like their
the transfer of information without any kind of organ or genetic relationship yep yep i agree um
yeah i think yeah prions are a kind of non-genetic inheritance um glansman shows uh RNA um so he
trains these aplizia and he and he takes uh you know extracts RNA and injects it into a new animal
and they um and they acquire some of the information yeah i mean it's just really fascinating
because when we were talking about the tadpoles with the eyes some of them are wired into the
brain and some of them can see without being wired into the brain and so you have all of the sudden
this new framework for understanding even something as basic as visual perception where we equate it
from conventional frameworks as being a necessary you know eye brain relationship and so if you
start to release that and all of a sudden it's actually in the body does that radically change
the way that we have to consider of bodies and minds and and consciousness to me it seems like
it must yeah yeah i think so i think that um all of this has a lot to say about what fundamentally
what we are and uh what it is that that persists through time and where things are encoded i mean
in planaria you can chop them into multiple pieces and each of those pieces will become an animal
and that's you know in philosophy of mind 101 you know you go over this example of the
malfunctioning transporter right so it sort of replicates you puts a copy over there but it
forgets to delete the you know the old star trek episode right like it forgets to delete the original
and now which one's the real one well yeah you can do that you can actually do that in planaria
so i think our concept of this this idea that there's a discrete border between me and not me
you know me between yourself and the outside world between different individuals between
the memories that belong to you or the memories that belong to somebody else i i think our uh
conceptions of all that stuff are are pretty primitive and probably um you know wrong
you you mentioned uh the the danger of overfitting with training uh machine learning models and
that links to this kind of tangentially where i think that the way that i've been thinking about
consciousness and awareness and intelligence has to do with the presence of a sensory system
that can then integrate information and then have effects upon the world and when we discuss
the ability of computer scientists to produce consciousness or intelligence to me i always
see there being a limitation in these sensory systems i'm like yeah you can have a brain on a chip
but in order for that to be something that i recognize as conscious it has to be tied into
some kind of body that is able to process multiple modes of sensory information integrate them and
then apply them to goal directed behavior and if there is not a necessity for a brain
the way that i've conventionally thought about it it really changes the way that i think about
machine consciousness because as we start to develop these systems and even if they're not
embodied in the way that i'm used to thinking of embodied systems it seems like we we are opening
the door into what don hoffman calls you know like another conscious portal that we're booting up
yeah yeah um well a couple of things uh first i would be really careful not to lump consciousness
and intelligence in the same bucket i don't think these are synonyms and so we have to i
think talk about them separately um with respect to embodiment i would say that i agree with you
that uh some sort of perception action loop is really important but i don't think three-dimensional
space is the only space in which to do that and so if you're doing that in physiological state space
or you're doing it in transcriptional space or you're doing it in anatomical morpheus space or
metabolic space or linguistic space i think that's good enough i don't think there's anything
i don't think this three-dimensional space is privileged i think we treat it that way because
that's how our sensory motor system developed and we're really used to things that move around well
in the three-dimensional world being the interesting intelligent things like us but uh that's just i
think that's just prejudice on our part i think these other spaces in which other beings strive
and suffer are equally real and so you can have embodiment that is not obvious to us um that
is that is in these other spaces um that was the last thing that was it was a third oh well and so
and so and so another another example of that is uh some is people with locked-in syndrome right so
so you can you can be locked in syndrome where you have basically zero ability to have uh functional
efficacy in terms of anybody noticing you doing anything but you're perfectly conscious and and
you know you've you've got a rich inner life so um i think i think i think we have to be careful and i
think um uh it it used to be that intelligence and consciousness were very closely tied together
i think that evolution kind of makes sure that those things go together and things that are naturally
evolved you can kind of gauge one from the other probably like again we really don't know right so
so the other mind's problem is is serious when you when you start to think about unconventional
things like it's it's pretty easy to say oh come on i know you and i both have minds even though i
don't have access to yours but but i'm giving i'm going to give you the benefit of the doubt well
that's that's that's easy until you get to things that don't actually look like you or are made of
something different right it gets it gets really hard intelligence is easy because because problem
solving abilities is a third person verifiable objective competency um first person consciousness
is is different different and difficult um yeah but uh but but yeah i i think uh i think it's uh
it's much it's much wider than than we normally think and it's and it's not hard to come up with
cases that basically break almost any um i mean this is the one of the main things i work on now
is to try to the one my tame framework is is trying to do is to come up with a
um a framework for understanding uh cognition and agency in extremely diverse across extremely
diverse embodiments because because all of the existing frameworks they they break very easily
with with biological examples most of the things that people um walk around you know kind of talking
about okay here's my criterion you can come up with you know seven examples that will just like
crush it within you know within minutes it's pretty easy it's it's hard to come up with a good
with a good framework yeah i wonder to what extent this mode of re-envisioning intelligence
could be applied to other scale systems like i always thought it was really interesting that the
physicists got uh let's say dominion over astrophysical or cosmic scale processes um it could
i could imagine a different planet with humans on it that the biologists took over that that work
and saw different things different patterns in the sky and different uh let's say behaviors of
galaxies or or systems and and approach them as intelligence and that that wouldn't be treated
as superstitious or rational uh in some sense uh to what extent have you had you do have you
collaborated with astrophys is this about about this possibility um i don't know it just seems like
in some sense very heretical but it but at the same time i can't find a rational cause for why
that's so yeah um i i think uh two two two things to to think about there one is that
i i i think uh the reason that um i i think you need an impedance match a kind of um
kind of uh cohesion between the tools you're using and what you're hoping to find
i think the reason that physicists always see dumb matter and dumb machines and never mind is
because they're using tools that are very low agency tools voltmeters and rulers and you know
telescopes and things like that these are very low agency things all they're ever gonna see is
low agency stuff uh i think you need minds to recognize other minds and um uh so that's that's
one thing another thing is is this uh i feel very strongly that assessments of whether
any people say this to me all the time and say oh uh you know your your team framework is very kind
of panpsychist so what you're just going to say that um that the weather and and and the sun are
conscious to well my point is is this but you can't say that you can't just say anything you can't say
it is or it isn't you have to do experiments and so um but both directions are bad right so so in
the olden days every every rock had a spirit behind it and every you know whatever like that that's
so that's problematic because then you say well what what is that doing for you and your ability
to understand the rock and whatever but the other option when you say oh no the weather definitely
doesn't have any any you know any agency to it i i don't know have you tried training it because we
have tools in in behavior science where you can actually address novel systems and ask does this
thing have habituation sensitization associate of learning predictive predictive coding uh you
know a metacognitive assessment all that these are not things you can have feelings about or
preconceptions about you have to do experiments so so my question is um you know uh yeah you can
you can you can entertain i i think you can entertain the idea that wow what if the you know
the whole galaxy is this like giant intelligence totally possible but you can't say that until
you've done some sort of experiment and they have to be perturbational experiments you can't do it
just by observation that's really key um you know they did these experiments uh in the 70s where
this guy made these um movies where there were different shapes moving around so triangles and
squares and circles and things and he would show them to people and people go oh look it's very obvious
the the the circles in love with the square and then they're trying to run away but the triangle
keeps trying to break them like you can tell these stories all day long but the only way to to develop
them into things that help your research and help you understand nature is to do perturbational
experiments is they find if i put my finger on the triangle and don't let it go what's going
to happen or i put a barrier does the circle really go around and get this way like what's
actually going to happen and so i'm completely open to um potential intelligence is at other
scales of time and space in fact i did i did annoy a bunch of physicists at one point asking them
could redesign a planetary scale synapse so so some kind of a gravitational system where a pulse
comes in and so it's some sort of asteroid comes flying in something changes and then the next time
you know the next three asteroids come flying in it does something different because it's learned
and it's got you know it's it's a synapse right so it has a historicity to it um and yes i think
you can design such things whether they occur in nature i have no idea um well there's some
interesting anecdotes i think there's some flyby anomalies with anomalies it's hard to say there's
some flyby anomalies with uh the jupiter probes you know that that end up leaving their orbit set
you know and and and they're just kind of catalogued and moved on and and again like it's not
such a perturbation it's actually terrifying to think about uh perturbing another galaxy or
something and all of the people in that galaxy are like what's going on um but i suppose you
wouldn't need to do that because there there are these anomaly i mean the galactic rotation problem
is another really interesting one it's like we have a very robust model of gravity quantitatively
we've checked it out locally in our solar system to the best of our ability on earth
and then we look at these large-scale structures and it's like well they're moving by some other
means and uh it really opens the door but i suppose without being able to mess with it
you can't really see if it's responsive or or if it's just some physical process that we are not
aware of yet i mean that's the thing right crossing crossing levels between local physical process
suppose you have a you have a conversation with somebody and uh you convince them to go to grad
school you have this you know four argue four really good arguments why they should go get their
phd and they do and then and then here you know along comes the physics is how did you do that
and and you say well here's and they say okay so let's measure so there was this air vibration and
it went into the eardrum and then there's a okay it's not that that story is false it's just completely
useless that the next time somebody else needs to be talked into whatever it is right it doesn't
capture the essence of what's going on even though even though at the local scale yes it all was
true and it all held together and these are the sets of frequencies and air vibrations that happen
it misses the whole point of the story so um it's almost i i feel it's like um uh and again this is
this is just you know kind of very very hand-wavy stuff but but i'm working on something something
a little better um the the notion of synchronicity right the idea that there are large scale patterns
that show up at specific observational scales when you as the observer know what to look for
but down below they are just chance or they're you know it's it's never magic it's never against
the laws of physics but it but but if you look at a larger scale there's often like yeah wait a
minute though yeah i know each one of these things kind of was was random by itself but all together
there's some there's something going on here and so you have to know how to look for those patterns
and even better you have to know how to read and write those patterns which means perturbational
experiments so you know i i don't have any ideas on how to um do perturbational experiments on on
galaxies but but like the weather kind of a thing should be absolutely uh uh tractable and and we
did something like that with um with gene regulatory networks because they're very simple
dynamical systems and you look at them you say well that's things kind of it's we you know for
sure it's dumb it's never gonna look turns out they're capable of six different kinds of memory
including pavlovian conditioning and all it takes it doesn't you don't need cells you don't need
synapses you don't need any of that it's it's a it's a handful of genes that turn each other on
and off and already you get this amazing free gift which is that some of the biological ones
anyway they can they can learn why do you think that the physicists have such preeminence in our
academic tower you know i feel like people all like if you look at nsf at least last time i looked
it was mostly physicists that were in charge uh it just seems like people expect physicists to answer
these really huge cosmic questions and i've always found that a little bit bizarre but and i've been
trying to trace how that came about and if it's arbitrary or if it's is there something innate
about the way that we perceive the world that demands that kind of explanation even if it's
not capable of it yeah um i would argue that it's because uh they make cd players right like they
i mean they they're the ones and and it's because they pick the low-hanging fruit i mean literally
not to take anything away like physics is amazing and it lots of hard problems and all of that but
but um as as anybody who does computer science or physics when they try to reach bio they get
into biology they want to rip the hair out of their heads because because they're used to systems
that are precise uh basically the low end of the spectrum you can you can we know how to deal with
the low end of the spectrum and now we do anyway after all the hard work and those are the things
where we make reliable technology so so you know if you want a washing machine or you want a cd player
you didn't get there without the physicists now you need some other stuff but but but but the
stuff from the right side of that spectrum so so psychoanalysis and uh but you all that kind of
stuff in and art and everything like it's great but it is notoriously unreliable for doing any
particular thing you know it sort of will enrich some of us and not others and who knows but but
if you really want you know if you if you um if you want to build a house or you want to you want
to you know antibiotics or something like that it's physics and then chemistry and i i i think
that's that's what it is it's just people people can see what works and and it's going to take a
lot of hard work uh to get that degree of um a predictive utility out of these higher higher
agency things if we live in a world of platonic forms that are being biologically manifest and
evolution is you described it as being something that makes problem solving machines
do you have a sense of your own role in that as like what is the what is the platonic form of the
problem that you see yourself as solving yeah so so this is uh just my phenomenology of it i i don't
know because i'm not able to do experiments controlled experiments on the scale of you know
life and science and all of that right so so i i don't know if any of this is has any truth to it
this is just how how i feel um yeah um it certainly feels to me like i'm discovering not inventing
and that the people in my lab uh we are we are uncovering something um i don't know if they
would agree by the way but but uh but me personally everything that that we've done over the decades
i feel like we're unearthing something that already existed and that has a particular
structure to it we don't make it up we find it and we kind of uh we can do better or worse at
figuring out what it is and how to relate to it and how to bring it out into the world
um that's how it feels to me i don't know that any of that is true um but um yeah and i also think
that so so here's another kind of wacky thing uh and i've told this to some of my students um
i i also feel like some of that stuff is under positive pressure in other words it wants to
come out in other words it's there for you to like like when you poke that little hole into
that platonic space by making uh the you know a bot or some kind of new technology stuff comes
rushing through that hole and i really feel like again this is very non-scientific i'm just
telling you how it feels to to to me um that that's what we do we figure out ways to kind of
put a crack in that in that boundary and then stuff starts pouring through the boundary you
don't have to you don't have to pull it out if you if you make the if you if you if you um
make make a make that barrier porous it it comes out i think i think it's under pressure it it it
whatever you whatever you create in this world that's uh uh it will it will um pull patterns
that that are that are there and is that how you approach your own goal orientation in your science
like you know we're starting a new year here and and it's almost like if it's a miracle year for
you what would it look like but i sense that it's almost like you see it as just chasing that that
you know positive pressure that positive pressure yeah you're sort of flowing with it do you set
that that's sort of objective bar for yourself when you when you look out onto the immediate
future as a scientist or are you are you just kind of going with the muse um well i well i
definitely think there's a muse no no doubt about that but um i also think that the space of possible
things to chase after is infinite and so i actually like like on the spectrum you know in some labs
you you know you sort of show up and whatever you do as long as you discover something cool
everybody's you know happy with it but i'm on the other spectrum so i have a very specific
research agenda i would like everybody who joins the higher than my lab we're all working on
very specific things where i know what i want to to come out of this um so and that's that's not
to say that uh that i'm you know uh defining it like designing any of these things it's just that
there are many many different things that different muses that one could tune into
and i have one particular one that you know i'm sort of flowing with and that means being very
thoughtful about um what are the channels through which you write these these findings will hopefully
hopefully flow the center i've got a i've got a mind map that hangs in our um in our in our lab
and it's like this this this this giant poster that we put like nine feet wide that we printed on
silk and the center of the mind map is called embodied mind that's the center so so it's all
the different ways and you know all the different questions and things that we're doing and then
different people's specific projects are sort of peppered around the leaves of the trail of that of
that graph and so that everybody can see where where they kind of plug into this but it's no
it's very specific and it's very curated it's a beautiful world that you're building i really
think that when i i think i've told you this before that when i went to go study biology i
imagined that it would be the the study of what is life and i very quickly realized that it was
much more mechanistic and much more molecular than that in most cases and one of the reasons
that we started this podcast was because i was certain that there were people out there who
were asking the larger questions of the significance and pushing the boundaries of what it meant to
understand bodies and life itself because it does seem to be a very weird center of the universe
and obviously that's like a very you know earth centric or human centric perspective but
there is something that is there's a motive force of life which is the solving of problems
and the universe seems full of problems to solve and so figuring out the process by which
we can do that in novel ways seems to me to be the passage into something that is
greater than the past because at every single juncture where humans have run into problems
the way that we have solved them is by figuring out technological approaches to resolving what
has happened and obviously that creates downstream problems like you look at the you know the green
revolution or something we have solved the problem of mass starvation but now we have
phosphate runoff and pollution of waters and now we have so many people that we don't have regenerative
agriculture that prevents us from just decimating animal life on the planet and i think that the
the passage into the next era is the passage of understanding or biology much better than we ever
have before and i think that your work is really really at the center of this and i just
i'm i'm i'm grateful to have to have met you and to know that that someone is is doing this
it's really it gives me a lot of hope for the future well thank you so much yeah i'm i that's
one of the things i'm happiest about is when people get hope from some of the things i say
and i this is maybe a good time to point out that it obviously isn't just me so in addition
to the people in my lab that do a lot of the hard work it's also i have i have some amazing
collaborators that that have been pulled together some of whom you may want to have on so people
like Richard Watson and you know and chris fields and mark solmes and some other folks
they really make a lot of this possible because these are some of the things i say these ideas
have been around for really long time but they've gotten no traction because there's a huge difference
between saying something and pushing it to the point where it actually generates new discoveries
and until you do that second thing it doesn't move the needle and that that's the really hard part
and so so there have been a lot of people that i've worked with that enable that they have
enabled some of that some of that to happen and i think i think what you're saying is super important
in the sense of understanding life beyond kind of the lowest levels of it meaning the the
mechanistic molecular stuff is is critical it's going to be important for us going into the you
know whatever the future of humanity is the one thing i want to say though is people get
hyper fixated when when they hear life people get hyper fixated on the material and on how it
gets here so so the biological wet the cytoplasm stuff and the product of evolution and i just
want to say that i think life and and that kind of focus on what's important is really critical
but we have to remember the protoplasm isn't magic and it isn't unique and the meandering
course of the evolutionary process is not the only way that mind enters this world and we have to
get broader than than a focus on the easy stuff which is the material it's really easy to say
oh you're made of silicon yeah you're not real you're just you're just faking it and and really
the hard work that we have to do as a as a species is to get beyond those those kind of superficial
criteria and to really say what what do we really mean by um i don't i don't know about life i you
know you can you can keep life what it is but but but cognition um i think goes way beyond the living
world and we we have to understand we have to develop um the rigorous frameworks of of recognizing
in novel guises that we wouldn't necessarily say are alive and i think that this next year is going
to be really interesting to see what happens because i feel like we're approaching that question
in a massive way technologically yeah we we are um i i'm i'm really um disappointed about how
narrow that debate has been and the hyper focus on language models and and uh the kind of
ai's that we have today and the things you know the people people just get so so focused on these
examples and and and the broader lessons of the field of diverse intelligence are haven't even
been scratched yet everybody's just like really focused on this on this one thing i think i think
we get much bigger issues actually coming than than just than just this yeah i mean i think that we
can plan to spend the next year reading up and studying more on the the diverse intelligence
and hopefully we can see you again in at the beginning of the next year yeah absolutely anytime
thank you so much it's always awesome thanks for so eye-opening talking to you and i really
appreciate you giving us your time and giving it to our audience as well that's great i appreciate
thank you always a great discussion be well um yeah stay in touch happy new year
happy new year all right happy new year yeah send me uh send me a link when this comes up
we'll do you got it all right bye everybody bye
you