All right.
Well, this is CS50 Tech Talk.
Thank you all so much for coming.
So about a week ago, we circulated the Google Form,
as you might have seen, at 10.52 AM.
And by, like, 11.52 AM, we had 100 RSVPs,
which I think is sort of testament to just how much interest
there is in this world of AI, and open AI, and GPT, chat
GPT, and the like.
And in fact, if you're sort of generally familiar with what
everyone's talking about, but you haven't tried it yourself,
this is the URL, which you can try out this tool
that you've probably heard about, chat GPT.
You can sign up for a free account there
and start tinkering with what everyone else has been
tinkering with.
And then if you're more of the app-minded type, which you probably
are if you are here with us today, open AI in particular
has its own low-level APIs via which you can integrate AI
into your own software.
But of course, as is the case in computer science,
there's all the more abstractions and services
that have been built on top of these technologies.
And we're so happy today to be joined by our friends
from McGill University and Steamship,
Sill and Ted, from whom you'll hear in just a moment,
to speak to us about how they are making it easier to build,
to deploy, to share applications using some
of these very same technologies.
So our thanks to them for hosting today.
Our friends at Plimpton, Jenny Lee and alumna,
who's here with us today, but without further ado,
allow me to turn things over to Ted and Sill.
And pizza will be served shortly after 1 PM outside.
All right, over to you, Ted.
Thanks a lot.
Hey, everybody, it's great to be here.
I think we've got a really good talk for you today.
Sill's gonna provide some research grounding
into how it all works, what's going inside,
the brain of GPT as well as other language models.
And then I'll show you some examples that we're seeing
on the ground of how people are building apps
and what apps tend to work in the real world.
So our perspective is we're building AWS for AI apps.
So we get to talk to a lot of the makers
who are building and deploying their apps.
And through that, see both the experimental end
of the spectrum and also see what kinds of apps
are getting pushed out there and turned into companies,
turned into side projects.
We did a cool hackathon yesterday.
Many thanks to Neiman, to David Malin and CS50
for helping us put all of this together,
to Harvard for hosting it.
And there were two sessions, lots of folks built things.
If you go to steamship.com slash hackathon,
you'll find a lot of guides,
a lot of projects that people built.
And you can follow along, we have a text guide as well,
just as a quick plug for that,
if you want to do it remotely or on your own.
So to tee up Sill, we're gonna talk about
basically two things today that I hope you'll walk away with
and really know how to then use as you develop
and as you tinker.
One is what is GPT and how is it working?
Get a good sense of what's going on inside of it
other than as just this magical machine that predicts things.
And then two is how are people building with it?
And then importantly, how can I build with it too
if you're a developer?
And if you have CS50 background,
you should be able to pick things up
and start building some great apps.
I've already met some of the CS50 grads yesterday
and the things that they were doing were pretty amazing.
So hope this is useful.
I'm gonna kick it over to Sill
and talk about some of the theoretical background of GPT.
Yeah, so thank you, Ted.
My name is Sill.
I'm a graduate student of Digital Humanities at McGill.
I study literature and computer science
and linguistics in the same breath.
And I've published some research over the last couple of years
exploring what is possible with language models
and culture in particular.
And my half or whatever of the presentation
is to describe to you what is GPT.
That's really difficult to explain in 15 minutes.
And there are even a lot of things that we don't know,
but a good way to approach that
is to first consider all the things
that people call GPT by or descriptors.
So you can call them large language models.
You can call them universal approximators
from computer science.
You can say that it is a generative AI.
We know that they are neural networks.
We know that it is an artificial intelligence.
To some, it's a simulator of culture.
To others, it just predicts text.
It's also a writing assistant.
If you've ever used ChatGPT,
you can plug in a bit of your essay, get some feedback.
It's amazing for that.
It's a content generator.
People use it to do copywriting, Jasper.AI,
pseudo-write, et cetera.
It's an agent.
So the really hot thing right now,
if you might have seen it on Twitter, auto-GPT, baby-AGI,
people are giving these things tools
and letting them run a little bit free in the wild
to interact with the world computers, et cetera.
We use them as chatbots, obviously.
And the actual architecture is a transformer.
So there's lots of ways to describe GPT.
And any of them is a really perfectly adequate way
to begin the conversation.
But for our purposes, we can think of it
as a large language model,
and more specifically, a language model.
And a language model is a model of language,
if you allow me the tautology,
but really what it does is it produces
a probability distribution over some vocabulary.
So let us imagine that we had the task
of predicting the next word of the sequence I am.
So if I give a neural network the words I am,
what of all words in English
is the next most likely word to follow?
That, at its very core, is what GPT is trained to answer.
And how it does it is it has a vocabulary of 50,000 words,
and it knows, roughly, given the entire internet,
which words are likely to follow other words
of those 50,000 in some sequence,
up to 2,000 words, up to 4,000, up to 8,000,
and now up to 32,000 GPT4.
So you give it a sequence, here I am,
and over the vocabulary of 50,000 words,
it gives you the likelihood of every single word that follows.
So here it's I am, perhaps the word happy is fairly frequent,
so we'll get that high probability
if we look at all words, all utterances of English.
It might be I am sad, maybe that's a little bit less probable,
I am school, that really should be at the end
because I don't think anybody would ever say that,
I am Bjork, that's a little bit, it's not very probable,
but it's less probable than happy sad,
but there's still some probability attached to it.
And when we say it's probable, that's literally a percentage,
that's like happy follows I am maybe like 5% of the time,
sad follows I am maybe 2% of the time, or whatever.
So for every word that we give GPT,
it tries to predict what the next word is
across 50,000 words, and it gives every single one
of those 50,000 words a number that reflects how probable it is.
And the really magical thing that happens
is you can generate new text, so if you give GPT I am,
and it predicts happy as being the most probable word
over 50,000, you can then append it to I am,
so now you say I am happy, and you feed it into the model again,
you sample another word, you feed it into the model again,
and again, and again, and again,
and there's lots of different ways that I am happy,
I am sad, can go, and you add a little bit of randomness,
and all of a sudden you have a language model
that can write essays, that can talk,
and a whole lot of things, which is really unexpected,
and something that we didn't predict
even five years ago, so this is all relevant.
And if we move on, as we scale up the model,
and we give it more compute, in 2012 AlexNet came out,
and we figured out we can run the model on GPUs,
so we can speed up the process,
we can give the model lots of information
downloaded from the internet,
and it learns more and more and more,
and the probabilities that it gives you
get better as it sees more examples
of English on the internet,
so we have to train the model to be really large,
really wide, and we have to train it for a really long time,
and as we do that, the model gets more and more better,
and expressive and capable,
and it also gets a little bit intelligent,
and for reasons we don't understand.
So, but the issue is that because it learns
to replicate the internet,
it knows how to speak in a lot of different genres of text,
and a lot of different registers.
If you begin the conversation like, chat GPT,
can you explain the moon landing to a six year old
in a few sentences, GPT three,
this is an example drawn from the Instruct GPT paper
from OpenAI, GPT three would have just been like,
okay, so you're giving me an example,
like explain the moon landing to a six year old,
I'm gonna give you a whole bunch of similar things
because those seem very likely to come in a sequence.
It doesn't necessarily understand that it's being asked
that question has to respond with an answer.
GPT three did not have that apparatus,
that interface for responding to questions,
and the scientist at OpenAI came up with the solution,
and that's, let's give it a whole bunch of examples
of question and answers,
such that we first train it on the internet,
and then we train it with a whole bunch of questions
and answers such that it has the knowledge of the internet,
but really knows that it has to be answering questions,
and that is when chat GPT was born,
and that's when it gained 100 million users in one month,
I think it beat TikTok's record at 20 million in one month,
it was a huge thing, and for a lot of people,
they went, oh, this thing is intelligent,
I can answer, I can ask it questions, it answers back,
we can work together to come to a solution,
and that's because it's still predicting words,
it's still a language model,
but it knows to predict words in the framework
of a question and answer, so that's what a prompt is,
that's what instruction tuning is, that's a key word,
that's what RLHF is, if you've ever seen that acronym,
Reinforcement Alignment with Human Feedback,
and all those combined means that the models
that are coming out today,
the types of language predictors
work to operate in a Q and A form.
GPT-4 exclusively only has the aligned model available,
and this is a really great, solid foundation to build on,
because you can do all sorts of things,
you can ask chat GPT, can you do this for me,
can you do that for me?
You might have seen that OpenAI
has allowed plugin access to chat GPT,
so it can access Wolfram, it can search the web,
it can search, it can do Instacart for you,
it can look up recipes, once the model knows
that not only it has to predict language,
but that it has to solve a problem,
and the problem here being,
give me a good answer to my question,
it's suddenly able to interface with the world
in a really solid way,
and from there on, there's been all sorts of tools
that it build on this Q and A form that chat GPT uses,
you have auto GPT, you have Langchain,
you have React, there was a React paper
where a lot of these come from,
and turning the model into an agent
which to achieve any ambiguous goal
is where the future is going,
and this is all thanks to instruction tuning,
and with that, I think I will hand it off to Ted,
who will be giving a demo,
or something along those lines,
for how to use GPT as an agent, so.
All right, so I'm a super applied guy,
I kinda look at things and think,
okay, how can I add this Lego, add that Lego,
and clip them together and build something with it,
and right now, if you look back in computer science history,
when you look at the kinds of things
that were being done in 1970,
right after computing was invented,
the microprocessors were invented,
people were doing research like,
how do I sort a list of numbers,
and that was meaningful work,
and importantly, it was work that's accessible to everybody,
because nobody knows what we can build
with this new kind of oil, this new kind of electricity,
this new kind of unit of computation we've created,
and anything was game,
and anybody could participate in that game
to figure it out,
and I think one of the really exciting things
about GPT right now is, yes,
in and of itself, it's amazing,
but then, what could we do with it
if we call it over and over again,
if we build it into our algorithms,
and start to build it into broader software,
so the world really is yours
to figure out those fundamental questions
about what could you do if you could script
computation itself over and over again
in the way that computers can do,
not just talk with it, but build things atop it,
so we're a hosting company, we host apps,
and these are just some of the things that we see,
I'm gonna show you demos of this with code
and try to explain some of the thought process,
but I wanted to give you a high level overview of,
you've probably seen these on Twitter,
but when it all sorts out to the top,
these are some of the things that we're seeing
built and deployed with language models today,
companionship, that's everything from I need a friend,
to I need a friend with a purpose,
I want a coach, I want somebody to tell me,
go to the gym and do these exercises,
I want somebody to help me study a foreign language,
question answering, this is a big one,
this is everything from your newsroom,
having a slack bot that helps assist you,
does this article conform to the style guidelines
of our newsroom, all the way through to,
and you need help on my homework,
or hey, I have some questions that I want you to ask,
Wikipedia, combine it with something else,
synthesize the answer and give it to me.
Utility functions, I would describe this as,
there's a large set of things for which
human beings can do them, if only,
or computers could do them, if only they had access
to language computation, language knowledge,
an example of this would be,
read every tweet on Twitter, tell me the ones I should read,
that way I only get to read the ones
that actually make sense to me
and I don't have to skim through the rest,
creativity, image generation, text generation,
storytelling, proposing other ways to do things,
and then these wild experiments and kind of baby AGI,
as people are calling them,
in which the AI itself decides what to do
and is self-directed, so I'll show you examples
of many of these and what the code looks like,
and if I were you, I would think about these
as categories within which to both think about
what you might build and then also seek out starter projects
for how you might go about building them online.
All right, so I'm just gonna dive straight into
demos and code for some of these,
because I know that's what's interesting to see
as fellow builders, with a high level diagram
for some of these as to how it works.
So approximately, you can think of a companionship bot
as a friend that has a purpose to you,
and there are many ways to build all of these things,
but one of the ways you can build this
is simply to wrap GPT or a language model
in an endpoint that additionally injects into the prompt
some particular perspective or some particular goal
that you want to use.
It really is that easy in a way,
but it's also very hard because you need to iterate
and engineer the prompt so that it consistently performs
the way you want it to perform.
So a good example of this is something somebody built
in the hackathon yesterday,
and I just wanted to show you the project that they built.
It was a Mandarin idiom coach,
and I'll show you what the code looked like first.
I'll show you the demo first.
I think I already pulled it up.
Here we go.
So the buddy that this person wanted to create
was a friend that if you gave it a particular problem
you were having, it would pick a Chinese idiom,
a four character Cheng Yu, that described poetically,
like here's a particular way you could say this,
and it would tell it to her so that the person
who built this was studying Chinese
and she wanted to learn more about it.
So I might say something like I'm feeling very sad,
and it would think a little bit,
and if everything's up and running,
it will generate one of these four character phrases,
and it will respond to it with an example.
Now, I don't know if this is correct or not,
so if somebody can call me out,
if this is actually incorrect, please call me out,
and it will then finish up with something encouraging,
saying hey, you can do it, I know this is hard, keep going.
So let me show you how they built this,
and I pulled up the code right here.
So this was the particular starter replete
that folks were using in the hackathon yesterday,
and we pulled things up into basically,
you have a wrapper around GPT,
and there's many things you could do,
but we're gonna make it easy for you to do two things.
One of them is to inject some personality into the prompt,
and I'll explain what that prompt is in a second,
and then the second is add tools
that might go out and do a particular thing,
search the web or generate an image
or add something to a database
or fetch something from a database.
So having done that,
now you have something more than GPT.
Now you have GPT, which we all know what it is
and how we can interact with it,
but you've also added a particular lens
through which it's talking to you
and potentially some tools.
So this particular Chinese tutor,
all it took to build that was four lines.
So here's a question that I think
is frying the minds of everybody in the industry right now.
So is this something that we'll all do casually
and nobody really knows?
Will we just all say in the future to the LLM,
hey, for the next five minutes,
please talk like a teacher, and maybe?
But also, definitely in the meantime,
and maybe in the future,
it makes sense to wrap up these personalized endpoints
so that when I'm talking to GPT,
I'm not just talking to GPT,
I have a whole army of different buddies,
of different companions that I can talk to.
They're kind of human
and kind of talk to me interactively,
but because I preloaded them with,
hey, by the way, you particular,
I want you to be a kind, helpful Chinese teacher
that responds to every situation
by explaining the Chongyu that fits it.
Speak in English and explain the Chongyu in its meaning.
Then provide a note of encouragement about learning language.
And so just adding something like that,
even if you're a non-programmer,
you can just type deploy,
and it'll pop it up to the web,
it'll take it over to a telegram bot
that then you can even interact with,
hey, I'm feeling too busy,
and interact with it over telegram, over the web,
and this is the kind of thing that's now within reach
for everybody from a CS 101 grad,
sorry, I'm using the general purpose framing,
all the way through to professionals in the industry,
that you can do just with a little bit of manipulation
on top of sort of this raw unit
of conversation and intelligence.
So companionship is one of the first
common types of apps that we're seeing.
So a second kind of app that we're seeing,
and for those of you who are on Twitter followers,
this blew up, I think the last few months,
is question-answering,
and I wanna unpack a couple of different ways
this can work, because I know many of you
have probably already tried to build
some of these kinds of apps,
there's a couple of different ways that it works.
The general framework is a user queries GPT,
and maybe it has general purpose knowledge,
maybe it doesn't have general purpose knowledge,
but what you want it to say back to you
is something specific about an article you wrote,
or something specific about your course syllabus,
or something specific about a particular set of documents
from the United Nations on a particular topic.
And so what you're really seeking is
what we all hoped the customer service bot would be,
like we've all interacted with these customer service bots,
and we're kind of smashing our heads
on the keyboard as we do it,
but pretty soon we're gonna start to see
very high fidelity bots that interact with us comfortably,
and this is approximately how to do it as an engineer.
So here's your game plan as an engineer,
step one, take the documents that you want it to respond to.
Step two, cut them up.
Now, if you're an engineer, this is gonna madden you.
You don't cut them up in a way that you would hope.
For example, you could cut them up
into clean sentences or clean paragraphs,
or semantically coherent sections,
and that would be really nice.
Honestly, the way that most folks do it,
and this is a simplification that tends to be just fine,
is you window, you have a sliding window
that goes over the document,
and you just pull out fragments of text.
Having pulled out those fragments of text,
you turn them into something called an embedding vector.
So an embedding vector is a list of numbers
that approximate some point of meaning.
So you've already all dealt
with embedding vectors yourself in regular life,
and the reason you have, and I know you have,
is because everybody's ordered food from Yelp before.
So when you order food from Yelp,
you look at what genre of restaurant is it?
Is it a pizza restaurant?
Is it an Italian restaurant?
Is it a Korean barbecue place?
You look at how many stars does it have?
One, two, three, four, five?
You look at where is it?
So all of these you can think of as points in space,
dimensions in space.
Korean barbecue restaurant, four stars near my house.
That's a three number vector.
That's all this is.
So this is a thousand number vector,
or a 10,000 number vector.
Different models produce different size vectors.
All it is is chunking pieces of text,
turning it into a vector that approximates meaning,
and then you put it in something called a vector database.
And a vector database is just a database
that stores numbers.
But having that database, now when I ask a question,
I can search the database, and I can say, hey, the question
was, what does CS50 teach?
What pieces of text in the database
have vectors similar to the question, what does CS50 teach?
And there's all sorts of tricks and empires
being made on refinements of this general approach.
But at the end, you, the developer, model it simply as thus.
And then when you have your query, you embed it,
you find the document fragments, and then you put them
into a prompt.
And now we're just back to the personality, the companionship
bot.
Now it's just a prompt.
And the prompt is, you're an expert in answering questions.
Please answer user provided question.
Using source documents results from the database.
That's it.
So after all of these decades of engineering
and these customer service bots, it
turns out with a couple of lines of code.
You can build this.
So let me show you, I made one just before the class
with the CS50 syllabus.
So we can pull that up.
And I can say, I added the PDF right here.
So I just, I searched, I don't know if, I apologize.
I don't know if it's an accurate or recent syllabus.
I just searched the web for CS50 syllabus PDF.
I put the URL in here, it loaded it into here.
This is just a 100 line piece of code deployed
that will now let me talk to it.
And I can say, what will CS50 teach me?
So under the hood now, what's happening
is exactly what that slide just showed you.
It takes that question, what will CS50 teach me?
It turns it into a vector.
That vector approximates without exactly representing
the meaning of that question.
It looks into a vector database that
steamship hosts of fragments from that PDF.
And then it pulls out a document and then passes it
to a prompt that says, hey, you're an expert
at answering questions.
Someone has asked you, what does CS50 teach?
Please answer it using only the source documents
and source materials I've provided.
Now those source materials materials
are dynamically loaded into the prompt.
It's just basic prompt engineering.
And I want to keep harping back onto that.
What's amazing about right now as builders
is that so many things just boil down
into very creative, tactical rearrangement of prompts
and then using those over and over again in an algorithm
and putting that into software.
So the result, and again, it could be lying.
It could be making things up.
It could be hallucinating.
Is CS50 will teach students how to think algorithmically
and solve problems efficiently, focusing on topics
such as abstraction, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot.
And then it returns the source document
from which it was found.
So this is another big category of which there
are tons of potential applications
because you can repeat for each context.
You can create arbitrarily many of these once it's software
because once it's software, you can just repeat it
over and over again.
So for your dorm, for your club, for your slack,
for your telegram, you can start to begin putting
pieces of information in and then responding to it.
And it doesn't have to be documents.
You can also load it straight into the prompt.
I think I have it pulled up here.
And if I don't, I'll just skip it.
Oh, here we go.
One other way you can do question answering,
because I think it's healthy to always encourage
the simplest possible approach to something.
You don't need to engineer this giant system.
It's great to have a database.
It's great to use embeddings.
It's great to use this big approach.
It's fancy at scales.
You can do a lot of things.
But you can also get away with a lot
by just pushing it all into a prompt.
And as an engineer, I'm, you know,
that's one of our team who's here always says,
like, engineers should aspire to be lazy.
And I couldn't agree more.
You, as an engineer, should want to set yourself up
so that you can pursue the lazy path to something.
So here's how you might do the equivalent
of a question answering system with a prompt alone.
Let's say you have 30 friends.
And each friend is good at a particular thing,
or you can, you know, this is isomorphic
to many other problems.
You can simply just say, hey, I know certain things.
Here's the things I know.
A user's gonna ask me something, how should we respond?
And then you load that into an agent.
That agent has access to GPT.
You can ship deploy it.
And now you've got a bot that you can connect to Telegram.
You can connect to Slack.
And that bot, now it won't always give you the right answer.
Because at a certain level,
we can't control the variance of the model underneath.
But it will tend to answer with respect to this list.
And the degree to which it tends to is to a certain extent,
something that both industry is working on
to just give everybody as a capacity.
But also you doing prompt engineering
to tighten up the error bars on it.
So I'll show you just a few more examples.
And then in about eight minutes,
I'll turn it over to questions,
because I'm sure you've got a lot about how to build things.
So just to give you a sense of where we are.
This is one, I don't have a demo for you.
But if you were to come to me and you were to say, Ted,
I want a weekend hustle, man, what should I build?
Holy moly.
There are a set of applications
that I would describe as utility functions.
I don't like that name,
because it doesn't sound exciting,
and this is really exciting.
And it's low hanging fruits that automate tasks
that require basic language understanding.
So examples for this are generate a unit test.
I don't know how many of you have ever been writing tests
and you're just like, oh, come on,
I can get through this, I can get through this.
If you're a person who likes writing tests,
you're a lucky individual.
Looking up the documentation for a function,
rewriting a function, making something conform
to your company guidelines, doing a brand check.
All of these things are things
that are kind of relatively context-free operations
or scoped context operations on a piece of information
that requires linguistic understanding.
And really, you can think of them as something
that is now available to you as a software builder,
as a weekend project builder,
as a startup builder.
And you just have to build the interface around it
and present it to other people in a context
in which it's meaningful for them to consume.
And so the space of this is extraordinary.
I mean, it's the space of all human endeavor,
now with this new tool, I think,
is the way to think about it.
People often joke about how when you're building a company,
when you're building a project,
you don't want to start with a hammer,
because you want to start with a problem instead.
And it's generally true, but my God,
we've just got a really cool new hammer.
And to a certain extent, I would encourage you
to at least casually, on the weekends,
run around and hit stuff with it
and see what can happen from a builder's,
from a tinkerers, from an experimentalist's point of view.
And then the final one is creativity.
This is another huge mega app.
Now, I'm primarily living the text world,
and so I'm gonna talk about text-based things.
I think so far, this has mostly been growing
in the imagery world, because we're such visual creatures,
and the images you can generate
are just staggering with AI.
Certainly brings up a lot of questions, too,
around IP and artistic style.
But the template for this, if you're a builder,
that we're seeing in the wild,
is approximately the following.
And the thing I want to point out is domain knowledge here.
This is really the purpose of this slide,
is to touch on the importance of the domain knowledge.
So, many people approximately
find the creative process as follows.
Come up with a big idea.
Over-generate possibilities.
Edit down what you over-generated.
Repeat, right?
Like anybody who's been a writer
knows when you write, you write way too much,
and then you have to delete lots of it.
And then you revise, and you write way too much,
and you have to delete lots of it.
This particular task is fantastic for AI.
One of the reasons it's fantastic for AI
is because it allows the AI to be wrong.
You know, you've pre-agreed,
you're gonna delete lots of it.
And so, if you pre-agreed, hey, I'm just gonna build,
generate five possibilities of the story I might tell.
Five possibilities of the advertising headline.
Five possibilities of what I might write my thesis on.
You pre-agreed, it's okay if it's a little wrong,
because you are going to be the editor that steps in.
And here's the thing that you really
should bring to the table, is don't think about this
as a technical activity.
Think about this as your opportunity
not to put GPT in charge.
Instead, for you to grasp the steering wheel tighter,
I think, at least, in Python,
or the language you're using to program,
because you have the domain knowledge
to wield GPT in the generation of those.
So let me show you an example of what I mean by that.
So, this is a cool app that someone created
for the Writing Atlas project.
So Writing Atlas is a set of short stories,
and you can think of it as good reads for short stories.
So you can go in here, you can browse different stories,
and this was something somebody created
where you can type in a story description that you like,
and this is gonna take about a minute to generate,
so I'm gonna talk while it's generating.
And while it's working, what it's doing,
and I'll show you the code in a second,
is it's searching through the collection of stories
for similar stories, and here's where
the domain knowledge part comes in.
Then it uses GPT to look at what it was that you wanted,
and use knowledge of how an editor,
how a bookseller thinks, to generate
a set of suggestions specifically through the lens
of that perspective with the goal of writing
that beautiful handwritten note
that we sometimes see in a local bookstore
tacked on underneath a book.
And so it doesn't just say, hey, you might like this,
here's a general purpose reason why you might like this,
but specifically, here's why you might like this
with respect to what you gave it.
It's either stalling out, or it's taking a long time.
Oh, there we go.
So here's its suggestions, and in particular, these things,
these are things that only a human could know,
at least for now, two humans specifically,
the human who said they wanted to read a story,
that's the text that came in,
and then the human who added domain knowledge
to script a sequence of interactions
with the language model so that you could provide
very targeted reasoning over something
that was informed by that domain knowledge.
So for these utility apps, bring your domain knowledge.
Let me actually show you how this looks and code,
because I think it's useful to see how simple
and accessible this is.
This is really a set of prompts.
So why might they, like a particular location,
well, here's the prompt that did that,
this is an open source project,
and it has a bunch of examples,
and then it says, well, here's the one that we're interested in.
Here's the audience, here's a couple of examples
of why might people like a particular thing
in terms of audience, it's just another prompt.
Same for topic, same for explanation,
and if you go down here and look at how it was done,
suggesting the story is, what is this,
line 174 to line 203, it really is,
and again, over and over again,
I wanna impress upon you, this really is within reach.
It's really just what, 20 odd lines of step one,
search in the database for similar stories,
step two, given that I have similar stories,
pull out the data, step three,
with my domain knowledge in Python,
now run these prompts, step four,
prepare that into an output.
So the thing we're scripting itself
is some approximation of human cognition.
If you're willing to go there metaphorically,
we're not sure, I'm not gonna weigh in
on where we are on this open AI, a life form argument.
All right, one really far out there thing,
and then I'll tie it up for questions,
because I know there's probably a lot,
and I also wanna make sure you get great pizza
in your bellies, and that is a baby AGI auto GPT
is what you might have heard them called on Twitter.
I think of them as multi-step planning bots.
So everything I showed you so far
was approximately one shot interactions with GPT.
So this is, the user says they want something,
and then either Python mediates interactions with GPT,
or GPT itself does some things with the inflection
of a personality that you've added
from some prompt engineering.
Really useful, pretty easy to control.
If you wanna go to production,
if you wanna build a weekend project,
if you wanna build a company,
that's a great way to do it right now.
This is wild, and if you haven't seen this stuff on Twitter,
I would definitely recommend going to search for it.
This is what happens, the simple way to put it is,
if you put GPT in a for loop,
if you let GPT talk to itself,
and then tell itself what to do.
So it's an emergent behavior,
and like all emergent behaviors,
it starts with a few simple steps,
the Conways game of life, many elements of reality,
turn out to be math equations that fit on a t-shirt,
but then when you play them forward in time,
they generate DNA, they generate human life.
So this is approximately,
step one, take a human objective,
step two, your first task is to write yourself
a list of steps, and here's the critical part, repeat.
Now do the list of steps.
Now you have to embody your agent
with the ability to do things.
So it's really only limited to do what you give it
the tools to do, and what it has the skills to do.
So obviously this is still very much
a set of experiments that are running right now,
and but it's something that we'll see unfold
over the coming years, and this is the scenario
in which Python stops becoming so important
because we've given it the ability
to actually self-direct what it's doing,
and then it finally gives you a result.
And I wanna give you an example still of just, again,
impressing upon you how much of this is prompt engineering,
which is wild, how little code this is.
Let me show you what BabyAGI looks like.
So here is a BabyAGI that you can connect to Telegram,
and this is an agent that has two tools.
So I haven't explained to you what an agent is,
I haven't explained to you what tools are,
I'll give you a quick one sentence description.
An agent is just a word to mean GPT
plus some bigger body in which it's living.
Maybe that body has a personality, maybe it has tools,
maybe it has Python mediating its experience
with other things.
Tools are simply ways in which the agent
can choose to do things.
Like imagine if GPT could say order a pizza,
and instead of you seeing the text order a pizza,
that caused a pizza to be ordered, that's a tool.
So these are two tools it has,
one tool is generated to-do list,
one tool is do a search on the web,
and then down here it has a prompt saying,
hey, your goal is to build a task list
and then do that task list,
and then this is just placed into a harness
that does it over and over again.
So after the next task, kind of unqueue the results
of that task and keep it going.
And so in doing that, you get this kickstarted loop
where essentially you kickstart it,
and then the agent is talking to itself.
So this, unless I'm wrong,
I don't think this has yet reached production
in terms of what we're seeing in the field
of how people are deploying software,
but if you wanna dive into sort of the wildest part
of experimentation, this is definitely one
of the places you can start, and it's really within reach.
All you have to do is download one
of the starter projects for it,
and you can kind of see right in the prompting,
here's how you kickstart that process of iteration.
All right, so I know that was super high level.
I hope it was useful.
It's, I think from the field, from the bottoms up,
what we're seeing and what people are building,
kind of the high level categories of apps
that people are making.
All of these apps are apps that are within reach
to everybody, which is really, really exciting.
And there's, I suggest Twitter is a great place
to hang out and build things.
There's a lot of AI builders on Twitter publishing.
And I think we've got a couple minutes
before pizza is arriving, maybe 10 minutes.
Keep on going.
So if there's any questions, why don't we kick it to that?
Because I'm sure there's some questions that you all have,
I guess I ended it a little early.
Yes?
Yeah, so I have a question around hallucination.
And so, you know, whenever building these sorts
of applications in apps, for example, let's say,
I'm giving it like a physics problem from a PSET
and we want to do that.
Yeah.
And, you know, it's 40% of the time just raw.
Do you have any like actionable recommendations
that these developers should be doing
to make it hallucinate less?
Or maybe even things that like open AI on the back end
should be doing to reduce hallucination.
So it would be something where you use RLHF.
Yeah, I didn't get the answer.
So the question was how, approximately,
how do you manage the hallucination problem?
Like if you give it a physics lecture
and you ask it a question, on the one hand,
it appears to be answering you correctly.
On the other hand, it appears to be wrong
to an expert's eye 40% of the time,
70% of the time, 10% of the time.
It's a huge problem.
And then what are some ways as developers practically
you can use to mitigate that?
I'll give an answer.
So you may have some specific things too.
So one high level answer is,
the same thing that makes these things
capable of synthesizing information
is part of the reason why it hallucinates for you.
So it's hard to have your cake you need it to
to a certain extent.
So this is part of the game.
In fact, humans do it too.
Like people talk about, you know,
just folks who kind of are too aggressive
in their assumptions about knowledge.
I can't remember the name for that phenomenon
where you'll just say stuff, right?
So we do it too.
Some things you can do are kind of a range of activities
depending on how much money you really need to spend,
how much technical expertise you have,
that can range from fine tuning a model to practically,
so I'm in the applied world.
So I'm very much in the world of duct tape
and sort of how developers get stuff done.
So some of the answers I'll give you
are sort of very duct-tapy answers.
Giving it examples tends to work for acute things.
If it's behaving in wild ways,
the more examples you give it, the better.
That's not gonna solve the domain of all of physics.
So for the domain of all of physics,
I'm gonna bail and give it to you
because I think you are far more equipped than me
to speak on that.
Sure, so the model doesn't have a ground truth.
It doesn't know anything.
Any sense of meaning that it's derived
from the training process is purely out of differentiation.
One word is not another word.
Words are not used in the same context.
It understands everything only through examples
given through language.
It's like someone who learned English or how to speak,
but they grew up in a featureless gray room.
They've never seen the outside world.
They have nothing to rest on that tells them
that something is true and something is not true.
So from the model's perspective,
everything that it says it's true.
It's trying its best to give you the best answer possible.
And if it lying a little bit
or conflating two different topics
is the best way to achieve that,
then it will decide to do so.
It's a part of the architecture.
We can't get around it.
There are a number of cheap tricks
that surprisingly get it to confabulate or hallucinate less.
One of them includes recently,
there was a paper that's a little funny.
If you get it to prepend to its answer,
my best guess is that will actually improve
or reduce hallucinations by about 80%.
So clearly it has some sense
that some things are true and other things are not,
but we're not quite sure what that is.
To add on to what Ted was saying,
a few cheap things you can do include
letting it Google or Bing,
as in Bing Chat, what they're doing,
it cites this information,
asking it to make sure its own response is good.
If you've ever had JetGBT generate a program,
there's some kind of problem,
and you ask ChatGBT, I think there's a mistake.
Often it'll locate the mistake itself.
Why didn't produce the right answer at the very beginning?
We're still not sure,
but we're moving in the direction
of reducing hallucinations.
Now with respect to physics,
you're gonna have to give it an external database
to rest on because internally,
for really, really domain specific knowledge,
it's not going to be as deterministic as one would like.
These things work in continuous spaces.
These things, they don't know what is wrong,
what is true, and as a result, we have to give it tools.
So everything that Ted demoed today is really
striving at reducing hallucinations, actually, really,
and giving it more abilities.
I hope that answers your question.
One of the ways to, I mean, I'm a simple guy.
Like I tend to think that all of the world
tends to be just a few things repeated over and over again,
and we have human systems for this.
You know, in a team, like companies work,
or a team playing sport,
and we're not right all the time,
even when we aspire to be,
and so we have systems that we've developed as humans
to deal with things that may be wrong.
So, you know, human number one proposes an answer,
human number two checks their work,
human number three provides the final sign off.
This is really common.
Anybody who's worked in a company
has seen this in practice.
The interesting thing about the state of software right now,
we tend to be in this mode,
in which we're just talking to GPT as one entity.
But once we start thinking in terms of teams,
so to speak, where each team member is its own agent
with its own set of objectives and skills,
I suspect we're going to start seeing a programming model
in which the way to solve this might not necessarily be,
make a single brain smarter,
but instead be draw upon the collective intelligence
of multiple software agents, each playing a role.
And I think that that would certainly follow
the human pattern of how we deal with this.
To give an analogy, space shuttles,
things that go into space, spacecraft,
they have to be good.
If they're not good, people die.
They have no margin for error at all.
And as a result, we over engineer in those systems,
most spacecraft have three computers
and they all have to agree in unison
on a particular step to go forward.
If one does not agree, then they recalculate,
they recalculate, they recalculate
until they arrive at something.
The good thing is that hallucinations
are generally not a systemic problem
in terms of its knowledge.
It's often a one off, the model, something tripped it up
and it just produced a hallucination in that one instance.
So if there's three models working in unison,
just as Ted is saying, that will, generally speaking,
improve your success.
Yes, sir.
A number of the examples you show have assertions
like you are an engineer, you are an AI, you are a teacher.
What's the mechanism by which that influences
this computation of probabilities?
Sure, I'm gonna give you what might be
an unsatisfying answer, which is it tends to work.
But I think we know why it tends to work,
and again, it's because these language models approximate
how we talk to each other.
So if I were to say to you, hey, help me out,
I need you to mock interview me.
That's a direct statement I can make
that kicks you into a certain mode of interaction.
Or if I say to you, help me out,
I'm trying to apologize to my wife,
she's really mad at me, can you role play with me?
That kicks you into another mode of interaction.
And so it's really just a shorthand that people have found
to kick the agent in, to kick the LLM in,
to a certain mode of interaction
that it tends to work in the way
that I, as a software developer, am hoping it would work.
And to really quickly add on to that,
being in the digital humanities that I am,
I like to think of it as a narrative.
A narrative will have a few different characters
talking to each other, their roles are clearly defined,
two people are not the same.
This interaction with GPT, it assumes a personality,
it can simulate personalities.
It itself is not conscious in any way,
but it can certainly predict what a conscious being
would react like in a particular situation.
So when we're going URX, it is drawing up that personality
and talking as though it is that person.
Because it is like completing a transcript
or completing a story in which that character is present
and interacting and is active.
So, yeah.
I think we got about five minutes until the pizza outside.
Eight minutes.
Yes, sir.
So I'm not a CF person, but it's been a fun thing with this.
And I understand the sort of word-by-word generation
and the sort of vibe, the feeling of it in the narrative.
Some of my friends and I have tried giving it logic problems,
like things from the LSAT, for example,
and it doesn't work.
Like, and I'm just wondering why that would be.
So it will generate answers that sound
very plausible rhetorically.
Like, given this condition X, given this Y,
but it'll often, like, even contradict itself
in its answers, but it's almost never correct.
So I was wondering what, why that would be?
Like, it just can't reason, it can't, like, think.
And, like, can you, would we get to a place where it can,
so to speak?
I mean, not, you know what I mean?
I don't mean to think, like, it's conscious.
I mean, like, have thoughts, not-
You want to talk about react?
So GPT-4, when GPT-4 released back in March,
I think it was, it was passing LSAT.
It was.
It was, yeah.
Yes.
Yes, it just passed, as I understand it.
Well, maybe it's because we're not GPT.
That's one of the weird things.
Is that-
At GPT.
Yeah.
If you pay for chat GPT, they give you access
to the better model.
And one of the interesting things with it is prompting.
It's so finicky.
If you, it's very sensitive to the way that you prompt.
There were earlier on when GPT-3 came out,
some people were going,
look, I can pass literacy tests,
or no, it can't pass literacy tests.
And then people who are pro or anti-GPT would be like,
I modified the prompt a little bit,
suddenly it can't, or suddenly it can't.
These things are not conscious.
Their ability to reason is like an alien's.
They're not us.
They don't think like people.
They're not human.
But they certainly are capable of passing some things
empirically, which demonstrates some sort of
rationale or logic within the model.
But we're still slowly figuring out,
like a prompt whisperer,
what exactly the right approach is.
Yeah?
Obviously, having GPT-3 running and prompting it
continuously is very expensive in terms of the user.
Have you seen instances where it directly creates
some sort of business value in for a whisperer,
for a company with a real added value of having
for these real AI apps in terms of
like a review of the drives and the actual digital stuff?
Yeah, I mean, we host companies on top of us,
who that's their primary product.
The value that it adds is like any company.
I mean, it's, you know, what is the Y Combinator motto,
make something people want?
I mean, I wouldn't think of this as GPT inherently
provides value for you as a builder.
Like that's their product.
That's OpenAI's product.
You pay chat GPT for prioritized access.
Where your product might be is how you take that
and combine it with your data, somebody else's data,
some domain knowledge, some interface
that then helps apply it to something.
It is, two things are both true.
There are a lot of experiments going on right now,
both for fun and people trying to figure out
where the economic value is.
But folks are also spinning up companies
that are 100% supported by applying this to data.
Okay, first, a company that wouldn't have,
sort of, wouldn't be AI focused as an input, right?
As it's just using or developing, like,
announcements that use GPT for productivity.
I think that it is likely that today we call this GPT
and today we call these LLMs
and tomorrow it will just slide into the ether.
I mean, imagine what the progression is going to be.
Today there's one of these
that people are primarily playing with.
There's many of them that exist,
but one, people are primarily bidding on top.
Tomorrow we can expect that there will be many of them
and the day after that we can expect
they're going to be on our phones
and they're not even going to be connected to the internet.
And for that reason, I think that,
like today we don't call our software microprocessor tools
or microprocessor apps, like the processor just exists.
I think that one useful model, five years out,
10 years out, is to, even if it's only metaphorically true
and not literally true, I think it's useful
to think of this as a second processor.
We had this before with what floating point co-processors
and graphics co-processors already as recently as the 90s
where it's useful to think of the trajectory of this
as just another thing that computers to do can do
and it will be incorporated into absolutely everything.
Hence the term foundation model, which also crops up.
So, pizza's ready?
One more quick.
Maybe one more and then we'll break for some food.
In the glasses right there, sorry.
Sorry, I was just being told we need to get two more.
So, yeah.
It's hard to get it to do that reliably.
It's incredibly useful to get it to do reliably.
So some tricks you can use are, you can give it examples.
You can just ask it directly.
Those are two common tricks.
And look at the prompts that others have used to work.
I mean, there's a lot of art to finding the right prompt
right now.
A lot of it is magic incantation.
Another thing you can do is post-process it
so that you can do some checking
and you can have a happy path
in which it's a one shot and you get your answer
and then a sad path in which maybe you fall back
on other prompts.
So then you're going for the diversity of approach
where it's fast by default.
It's slow but ultimately converging
upon higher likelihood of success if it fails.
And then something that I'm sure we'll see
and people do later on is fine-tune instruction
tuning style models, which are more likely to respond
with the computer parsable output.
I guess one last question?
Sure.
So one of the, you talked a couple of things.
One is, is you talked about domain expertise here
and you were coding a bunch of domain expertise
in terms of the prompts that you're going for.
What is that, where do those prompts end up?
Do those prompts end up back in the gene chat
and is there a privacy issue associated with that?
That's a great question.
So the question was, and I apologize,
I just realized we haven't been repeating
all the questions for the YouTube listeners.
So I'm sorry for the folks on YouTube
if you weren't able to hear some of the questions.
The question was, what are the privacy implications
of some of these prompts?
If one of the messages is so much depends upon your prompt
and the fine-tuning of this prompt,
what does that mean with respect to my IP?
Maybe the prompt is my business.
I can't offer you the exact answer
but I can paint for you what approximately
the landscape looks like.
So in all of software and so too with AI,
what we see is they're the SaaS companies
where you're using somebody else's API
and you're trusting that their terms of service
will be upheld.
There's the set of companies in which they provide a model
for hosting on one of the big cloud providers
and this is a version of the same thing
but I think with slightly different mechanics.
This tends to be thought of as the enterprise version
of software and by and large,
the industry has moved over the past 20 years
from running my own servers to trusting
that Microsoft or Amazon or Google can run servers for me
and they say it's my private server
even though I know they're running it
and I'm okay with that.
And you've already started to see that Amazon
with Huggingface, Microsoft with OpenAI,
Google too with their own version of Bard
are going to do these where you'll have the SaaS version
and then you'll also have the private VPC version
and then there's a third version
that I think we haven't yet seen practically emerge
but this would be the maximalist.
I wanna make sure my IP is maximally safe version of events
in which you are running your own machines.
You are running your own models
and then the question is,
is the open source and or privately available version
of the model as good as the publicly hosted one
and does that matter to me?
And the answers right now, realistically,
it probably matters a lot.
In the fullness of time,
you can think of any one particular task you need to achieve
as requiring some fixed point of intelligence to achieve.
And so over time, what we'll see is
the privately obtainable versions of these models
will cross that threshold
and with respect to that one task,
yeah, sure, use the open source version,
run it on your own machine,
but we'll also see the SaaS intelligence get smarter.
It'll probably stay ahead.
And then your question is,
well, which one do I care more about?
Do I want like the better aggregate intelligence
or is my task somewhat fixed point
and I can just use the open source available one
for which I know it'll perform well enough
because it's crossed the threshold.
So to answer your question specifically,
yes, you might be glad to know
Chachi PT recently updated their privacy policy
to not use prompts for the training process,
but up until now, everything went back into the bin
to be trained on again, okay.
And that's just a fact.
So I think pizza is now pizza time.
Okay, okay.
Okay.
Yeah.
But we'll have to talk about Q&A's and everything else.
Perfect.