I want to ask Sam some questions myself and then after that we'll open it up to a broader
set of people so everyone can have some time.
You know Sam, just before we start, I want everyone to understand your story because
you have such an interesting background in the tech ecosystem, you know, help us walk
us through from graduating, not graduating, joining Stanford, dropping out, running Y
Combinator, running a different startup before that, and now running OpenAI and a number
of things.
Just help us understand how you came to where you are right now.
Yeah, so I started at Stanford where we met and I was already in love with computer science
but I really fell in love with it once I got there.
I actually went to study AI but at the time AI was really not working at all.
In fact, very memorably one of my professors said the only sure way to have a bad career
in AI is to work on neural networks.
We've decided those don't work.
And so I got kind of discouraged and I started a company.
That was a great experience.
The company didn't work out that well but I kind of like learned about startups and
thought they were a very powerful force and something I was very excited about.
So I then ran YC for a while and while I was doing that, I got newly excited about the
idea of startups that take on hard technical challenges.
And I sort of thought it was curious to me more people weren't doing that.
It seemed like a really valuable opportunity.
With some other people, started OpenAI is one of those examples and many other things
which have gone on to be pretty exciting but really fell in love with OpenAI.
Once it seemed clear that we were really going to have a chance at making true general purpose
AI like a system that could do what a human can do and contribute new knowledge to society,
I got really excited and wanted to go work on that.
And so stop being an investor and now I do that.
So first of all, what is OpenAI?
Is it just chat GPT?
Are they the same thing?
Are they different?
Just help us understand what the company does.
We are a company that is doing research and deployment to try to figure out how to build
AGI and how to responsibly deploy that into the world for maximum benefit.
So this is unlike other technologies.
Other technologies are like this too but this is a strong case of a technology that
on the one hand is the most exciting, most promising, coolest thing.
I think that humanity will have yet built.
We can cure all disease, we can give everybody a great education, better healthcare, massively
increased productivity, huge scientific discovery, all of these wonderful things and we want
to make sure that people get that benefit, that benefit is distributed equitably.
And on the other hand, there are the obvious concerns about the power of this technology
used in a negative direction.
So we want to be a force to help manage those risks so that we all get to enjoy the benefits.
Chat GPT is definitely what we are best known for so I guess there is sort of synonymous
at this point but OpenAI is really about this quest for AGI.
Interesting.
So help us understand, I mean all of us have played with it, right?
We have poems getting written by it, we have all asked it fun trivia questions, teller
and answers but help us understand, you without a doubt have a better understanding of how
it's getting used all around the world and all sorts of different industries, vocations,
reasons.
Talk to us a little bit about some of the most interesting things that you've seen.
For example, what's the most surprising use case of some of the technologies that you
guys have built that you've seen recently?
So the main thing I would say that's interesting about it is its generality.
There's a lot of other systems that can go do this thing well or that thing well or this
thing and in many cases better than Chat GPT.
There's probably not an AI that can write a better poem or whatever but other categories
you could find something that's maybe better but the fact that this one system is truly
general purpose and can do so many things means that people are integrating it into
their workflow as a very powerful tool and so the same thing that can help you write
computer code, one of the areas that we've seen the biggest impact is what coders are
using this for, doubling, tripling their productivity.
There was a paper that just came out that when Italy temporarily banned Chat GPT developer
productivity fell in half on a fairly big study but it can do that, it can also help
you find information, it can help you write a poem, it can help you summarize documents,
it can translate things and people are using this which we hoped would happen as this sort
of super assistant that just makes them more and more productive and it's that generality
that I think is the coolest part.
So with so much ability that maybe even you guys haven't even thought about how people
are using it when you developed it and launched it, I'm sure you've seen a lot of interesting
use cases right here out of India itself.
Can you tell us something or just give us an example of something you've seen that's
really inspired you that you've seen come out of the Indian market?
So India has been a country that has really truly embraced Chat GPT in a way, maybe you
can tell me why, I'm sort of curious, I'm hoping to learn while I'm here, we're very
delighted but there has been a lot of early adoption and real enthusiasm from the users.
One of the very earliest things like in the first weeks of launching Chat GPT, we heard
about a farmer in India who wasn't able to access government services and via like Chat
GPT hooked up to WhatsApp in some sort of complicated way, was then able to.
And that was like one of the early things where we're like, huh, we did not think that
was going to happen.
And just to expand on it, so what I've understood about OpenAI is Chat GPT is one implementation
of the things you've built but you have capabilities to real time translate, to transcribe audio
and detects and are you seeing people use these in combination in ways that are surprising?
Well, we recently launched an iPhone app that has speech recognition in it, which is that's
hooking up two of our models together and people love that.
But the main point that I would like to get across is none of the current systems really
matter.
Like, we're going to look back at GPT4 and you know, I don't know if any of you have
like picked up an iPhone, original iPhone in recent years but it's like, wow, I cannot
believe we're excited about this.
Each pixel is like that big, it just feels like this incredibly antiquated thing.
The curve here is going to be much, much steeper and what the systems are going to be capable
of in the not distant future, we think, is going to be very dramatically different.
So this is like a system that, I don't even know what the right, this is like the old
first like grayscale Nokia phone that looked like a little candy bar and the iPhone 14
is coming.
So what I would say is, it's a mistake to get too focused on the current systems, their
limitations, their capabilities, the impact they're having.
The thing that matters here is we are on an exponential curve, truly, two big miracles
I think in the field.
Number one, we have an algorithm that can genuinely, truly like no tricks learn and number two,
it gets predictably better with scale.
And that, we're going to look back, I think, on those two realizations as a turning point
in human history when you put them together, but what it means is that the rate of progress
in the coming years, the capabilities are going to be significant.
So it's totally cool that chatGVT can write that poem when a future system can like cure
all disease or help us address climate change or radically improve education or make us
all like 10 or 100 times more productive than what we do.
That's quite impactful.
It's amazing.
Now let's flip to the other side of this because there's no doubt there's incredible power
in this technology and with that comes challenges.
I want to play a clip, maybe you guys can put on a clip of something I recently heard
Sam speak somewhere and we can talk about it a bit.
Could you play the clip please?
Hi, my name is Sam and I'm happy to be here today.
Thank you all for joining.
I also wanted to say that the gentleman on stage with me is incredibly good looking and
I also want to say that you should be very careful with videos generated with artificial
intelligence technology.
Okay, so you didn't say that recently, clearly that was just a ploy here and thank you by
the way.
Totally agree with that one.
But nonetheless, I think it raises a real question, right, when this video, if you look
closely you can see the lips aren't perfectly synced, but like you said this stuff is only
going to get better and exponentially better.
Fundamental questions are on authenticity, what's real and what's fake, how do we handle
that?
Yeah, so that was like deeply in the uncanny valley, it's very strange to watch, but we're
not that far away from something that looks perfect and there's a lot of fear right now
about the impact this is going to have on elections and on our society and how we ever
trust media that we see.
I have some fear there, but I think we're actually going to, when it comes to like a
video like that, I think as a society we're going to rise to the occasion.
We're going to learn very quickly that we don't trust videos unless we trust the sort
of provenance.
We'll have techniques like watermarking detectors, more than that I suspect at some point if people
are saying something really important they'll cryptographically sign it and you know web
browsers or phones or whatever will build in some ability to say okay this is authentic.
But that part we can all adapt to, like we did this with Photoshop, there was a period
of time where people thought if you see an image it's got to be real, we learned, we're
like okay you know that thing is Photoshopped, it happened quickly, videos like that, society
will build antibodies quickly, but there's a related thing that I think is getting discussed
less which is not the ability to generate mass media like that, but customized one-on-one
interactive persuasion and I think people are going to be able to create AIs that are
very good at this, so I won't just be like you know I'm watching a video of you, but
it'll be like I'm chatting with you back and forth and it's like the most interesting
compelling conversation that I've ever had that's like affecting me in ways I don't know
about and that's a new thing that's different than just generated media, again I think we'll
find a way to build societal antibodies to it, but I don't think it's discussed as much
and it's going to be a challenge.
I also want to talk about jobs because the natural fears AI is going to make us redundant,
particularly in markets like India where we have so much of a workforce and a lot of
it is often times doing somewhat rote work, should we be worried about this, I mean does
this affect societal disruption on employment and capitalism and all the things in how we've
been running?
I mean to some extent yes, every technological revolution leads to job change and this will
be no exception, I guess three thoughts, number one job change itself is fine, you know if
you kind of look at the history of this, in two generations we can kind of adapt to any
amount of labor market change and there's new jobs and the new jobs are usually better
and that's going to happen here too, some jobs will go away, there will be new better
jobs, they're difficult to imagine as we sit here and dream about the future is going
to look like, the thing that might be different about this is the speed with which it could
happen and I think it will require a change to the socioeconomic contract and the way
governments think about this if it happens at a very fast pace.
The second thing is it's not going the way people predicted so far and I don't think
it will in the future, so the current systems are actually not very good at all at doing
whole jobs, they're very good at doing tasks and so the nature of the job, if you're say
a computer programmer to stick with that example, shifts to you kind of like manage a team of
extremely, extremely junior developers that can only do one minute task at a time and
then they'll do 10 minute tasks and then they'll do an hour task but you'll still have to think
of like how is this all going to fit together, what I want to build and you know maybe eventually
it learns that too but this idea that instead of replacing jobs it's making people dramatically
more efficient and there is such a demand overhang in most places, you know if we can
overnight make the world create 3x more software because we make every software developer three
times more efficient, that is not nearly enough, that does not nearly fulfill the demand the
world has for software and I think we'll see that in many other places.
So another example of this is that the consensus, not the consensus, the like absolute belief
of experts around the world 10 years ago, first AI is going to come replace the physical
labor jobs so truck drivers, farmers, factory workers, real trouble then it will come for
the sort of easier kinds of cognitive labor then maybe eventually like computer programmers
even a mathematician and then you know way in the future or maybe never because maybe
it's like magical and human the creative jobs and of course we can look now and say it appears
like it's going exactly the other direction but that was like really non-obvious certainly
to us we started thinking we were going to build robots and it's still in some deep sense
to me seems like it should be much easier to make robots than it is to make GPT-4 but
here we are. I think with other job impacts it's just going to be surprising but I think
the world will get way wealthier you'll have a productivity boom and we will find a lot
of new things to do.
You talked about robots and you know we've talked about sort of the real practical likely
disruption that we're going to see because of AI but we also have to talk about that
one percent like extinction risk or that robots are going to come and take over our
lives how do you think about that I mean you have actually been probably more so than the
average person cautious about this and for us we kind of think of it as sci-fi kind of
like in the in the realm of not really realistic but interesting to talk about but I think
you would say it's something real that we have to think about how we understand it.
For sure like I want to be super clear I don't think current systems are dangerous I don't
think there's any way that GPT-4 like causes an existential risk to the world but people
are very bad at thinking about exponential curves and GPT-10 may be a extremely different
thing. Given the importance of getting this right even if it's a one percent chance I
think putting a lot of effort into thinking studying like how we align an AGI how we design
safe systems at this kind of scale is super important and starting that early is really
good I think we can totally manage through it I think we're developing techniques to
mitigate it this is really why we started the company this was like our initial focus and
still is our most important focus but yeah we need to address this.
Is there like a power switch in the back of your office that nobody knows about where
you can just pull like that thing in Jurassic Park that giant yeah it has to be big and
dramatic but you pull this big thing and it shuts down all the systems if we need it exactly
like that okay good I'm glad I feel better now okay and it works even if you're traveling
right I mean yeah okay anyways so let's talk about regulation because again I think what's
really unusual is this company is a few years old but really for the for the consumer it's
like less than a year old because of chat GPT and yet here you are traveling the world
meeting leaders globally to talk about the importance of regulation and not only are
you doing that you are probably one of the most vocal people saying we need it and not
one of those you know we'll regulate ourselves leave us alone type of things you are saying
governments need to step up understand this and get involved this is very weird this is
not like how most startups operate what's going on well again we started the company
because we were nervous about AGI risk before you were really before people even talked
about AGI and now I think part of the reason we deploy systems is so that people confront
the technology feel it understand the risks the benefits and now a lot of other people
are also very excited but sharing the concern I think this is a special moment where the
globe can come together and kind of get this right and we certainly would like to try to
do that let's talk a little bit more about AI in India because it's so unique for us
and there are so many interesting use cases that are very India specific you know one of
the obvious questions we think a lot about are languages right India has one of the largest
depths of languages hundreds of languages in the country now AI is by and large trained
on what's publicly available what's available on most of the internet which is you know
inevitably going to be mostly English probably a lot more Western focused in terms of just
the sheer quantity of stuff that goes into trade and that's what we're going to be doing
to training how do you think about biases how do you think about inclusivity how do
you think about multilingual countries like India and making a product that's relevant
that's useful not just for all of us fancy people sitting in Bombay and Delhi but for
you know everyone in the mass of the country yeah it's super important to us we had a big
step forward from GPT 3.5 to 4 at non English languages so GPT 4 is pretty good at say the
top 20 languages and okay it may be the top hundred we will be able to push this much
further you know it's challenging for us for very small languages spoken by you know only
a few tens of thousands or hundreds of thousands of people that that's difficult but the systems
are fundamentally going to be very good at this I think and it's important for us to
do now as you were saying it's not just the language it's also the history the culture
the values and we want the entire world represented in here there will be some areas where the
world's got to agree on like here the sort of global bounds of the system but mostly
if you want to use it in the US or in India that can be under a different legal framework
and then in different parts of the culture in each place it'll be very different and
I think that should all be represented in there we recently launched a new program to
give out grants for people that want to run experiments of the ways we can do this the
way we can collect this but we really really want to you know India has been particularly
unique and successful globally at building a lot of the underlying technology stacks
to support new innovation and digital with India stack UPI other things like this do
you think India should build its own LLM AGI AI engine you know in some sense should we
think of this a little bit like nuclear technology where every country should be building its
own capabilities and you know a little bit more nationalist in the way we think about
this I mean how do you think as a country we should think about AI as something in a
sovereign sense first of all it's super impressive to see what India has done I think in a way
that really no other country has with these sort of saying we're going to do national
technology really well and like make it a really like a national asset in terms of AI
strategy I think there's like a lot of things that can work I think this question of sort
of AI sovereignty none of us have an answer to yet feels like it's going to be at least
somewhat important but the main thing that I think is important is figuring out how to
integrate these technologies into other services and that is an area that I think governments
are behind on and don't have the answers to yet but you know I think like hopefully we
all start to use LLMs to make government services way better both from like how do I enroll
in this program to like how do I get better healthcare but if you're in the Indian government
should you be like we need to set up a team of crack engineers to build our own open AI
I mean is there a concern for us to say are we depending on like for fundamental infrastructure
are we depending on something that's not owned by our country yeah I think it is good to have
certainly some sort of AI research effort what exactly that should do you know should
that be training ground up LLMs should that be pursuing new research directions should
that be focused on fine tuning open source projects I think there's a lot of options
there and there's I don't yet like have conviction on the right answer but some you know nationally
funded AI effort feels like a good idea. One of the things that I think is so interesting
is that open AI straddles this line of being a non-profit and a for-profit and I don't know
how I don't know if I fully understand it I don't know if many people do I know you've
raised money from investors and Microsoft is definitely one of your shareholders when
we think about it is it do we think of open AI as something that's here for society to
do societal good is it here to make money for its shareholders is it both what happens
if those conflict how do we think about that. If they conflict we're definitely here for
the societal good like that's super clear and that's why we put up with all this complication
in our structure. So what is the structure can you help us understand what exactly does
it look like. Yeah so there's like a non-profit that has a board that governs this thing that
we call a cap profit where our investors can make a certain return but if we ever need
to make a decision that is in favor of societal good but not in favor of shareholders we're
set up to do that. And one of the most controversial things I heard was that you don't own equity
in open AI why is that what's going on. I mean it started just as like sort of this
work of our structure where we needed non-conflicted people on the board who didn't have equity
a certain number of them certain percentage. And then I kind of just like never got like
I forget about it until it comes up and something like this but it's I don't think it's like
a particularly noteworthy thing like I made a ton of money early in my career I actively
invest so I expect to make a ton more. I get far more value from even like personally
selfishly speaking I get far more value from like all of the other sort of benefits that
come from running open AI a very interesting life than I would for more money. But most
of all like I just believe that this is going to be the most important project of our time
and I'm super grateful to work on it. If you need me to like send you reminders to
keep up on it I'm happy to do that just let me know. So look a lot of people have flown
in here from all around the country to come hear you and while understanding all this
theory about AI is cool help us do our jobs better. I want to put you in a couple roles
and tell me OK you are now the CEO of a hospital in India. What should you do and not theoretical
go hire a couple people like tell like help me do my job better be my AI for a second.
One of the things that we have heard from a lot of doctors is that they're using chat
GPT with GPT for to help come up with new ideas for tricky cases. So you know input the symptoms
maybe the test results say I can't figure this out. What are some ideas for the differential
diagnosis and in many cases getting great results back. Now let's say you're running
a bank. What do you do. This is like rapid fire. We're all taking notes to do our jobs
better here like a sort of traditional like bank branch on the street that kind of bank
not like an investment. Yeah like a bank like a traditional bank that issues credit cards
and checking accounts and all that stuff. I think I would try to just like on a very brief
little side journey of my career I once like helped build a mobile banking app and on the
side. No no it was like OK yeah whatever. I still think the consumer experience of banking
is terrible and could be a lot of it could be replaced by like chatting with an LLM. It's
interesting. Let's say you're running a university. You're a you're a chancellor. I mean we've all
seen how chat GPT can definitely affect the education experience. Now let's say you're
running a university. Yeah that one I think is pretty clear. I would just like go redesign
the education experience. I would have the equivalent of like personalized tutoring
interactive textbooks. I would like I would integrate it into like all parts of the learning
process. Now just totally theoretically let's say you're running like a large news media
company in like a market like India like just as an example. What would you do. Let me just
get my pen real quick. But what would you do. Just tell me. One of the things that you know
there's been a lot of controversy about whether this is going to be good or bad for the publishing
industry and news in particular. One of the things that we've heard from journalists and
reporters who are actually using the the product is that it helps them do the boring parts
of their jobs better and they get to spend more time reporting talking to sources thinking
of ideas. And so I think I would just like encourage everyone to just start using it.
And now let's say you are the ministry in India responsible for overseeing technology
A.I. etc. You know what what would you do in that situation. Like what would you be doing
today as a regulator. I would say you know we have the G 20 coming up. India can play
like a huge role here in global conversation about what this sort of international regulatory
thing might look like. And we are going to really focus on that between now and September
and make sure we prioritize that. Can you tell us something that you haven't
told other people about what's coming from open A.I. like maybe just some insider information
that we could use in some form. You know we kind of tell people what we're working on
like it's going to get smarter. It's going to get multimodal. We're going to try to like
teach it to generate new ideas come up and help us like discover more new science. We're
going to reduce hallucinations and give users like more control so no one feels like it's
biased or at least it's biased in the way you want us to be biased. We don't have like
a lot of secret plans here. I think always as a company to our strength and weakness we
just sort of say what we think and what we're going to try to do. It's amazing. Now one
of the most amazing things about you Sam is that you are running what is going to be one
of the most impactful companies in history. Whenever people say impactful they leave out
whether it's going to be a good or a bad impact. That is a very purposeful leave out because
we don't know right. But you're going to shape the world with this. We know that. And this
isn't your only job as I understand or maybe it's my only like operating. It's the only
thing that I'm like in the trenches. Can you tell us what else you're doing that's like
exciting you or motivating you outside of open AI. Your side hustles if we put it that way.
I think we're going to get nuclear fusion to work in the next few years at and importantly
not just as a scientific demonstration but as incredibly cheap energy and at global skill.
So I think other than AI if you could do one thing that would like really help the world
get richer increase the quality of life. It's very cheap energy. I think there's like a huge
historical correlation there. And I think we've all like lost sight of the appropriate ambition
level here of how how much of an impact we could make. But if we can get fusion to work and if
we can make enough of it for the world then if it can like cut the energy cost 10 X plus that's
pretty great. I'll pick that one. So your side gig is nuclear fusion. I don't. I am an investor and
sort of like helper of that one. It's amazing. So just so I understand you're you're revolutionizing
artificial intelligence and energy. Not you specifically. I think those are like those are
the two. My basic model of the world is that the cost of intelligence and the cost of energy are
kind of what compounded everything else. And if we want a radically better future those are the
two things we should focus on trying to like make abundant. It's incredible. So my last question for
you is what is the most exciting thing that you are seeing globally in your own company. Like what
is the thing that outside of everything we are all talking about and seeing that excites you about
where open AI or even not just AI in general. What's the most exciting thing ahead.
I mean I think it's this generation of new scientific progress. If these systems can really
contribute additional understanding of the world better technology better science that that is like
the sustainable way that the world actually gets better and that the quality of life increases.
We're not there yet. It might be soon it might take a while but I believe we are going to get there
and that will I think we all underestimate that. It's amazing. Sam thank you so much. Thank you to be
clear. Sam asked me to talk less and to open it up for you all to ask more.