So today we're going to give an instructor-led lecture talking about some of the key topics
in Transformers and LLMs these days, and particularly Div will be talking about agents
and I'll be discussing emergent abilities, intermediate-guided reasoning, as well as
baby LLM.
So let me actually go to my part, because Div is not here yet.
So I'm sure many of you have read this paper, Emergent Abilities of Large Language Models
from 2022, so I'll briefly go through some of them.
So basically, an ability is emergent if it is present in large group but not smaller
models, and it would not have been directly predicted by extrapolating performance from
smaller models.
So you can think of performance, it's basically near random until a certain threshold called
a critical threshold, and then it improves very heavily.
This is known as a phase transition, and again, it would not have been extrapolated or predicted
if you were to extend the curve of the performance of smaller models, it's more of a jump which
we'll see later.
So here's an example of Fuchsia Prompting for many different tasks.
For example, modular arithmetic unscrambling words, different QA tasks, and so forth.
And you'll see that performance kind of jumps very heavily up until a certain point.
I believe the x-axis here is the number of training flops, which corresponds to basically
model scale.
So you'll see in many cases around 10 to the 22 or 10 to the 23 training flops, there's
a massive exponential jump or increase in terms of model performance on these tasks,
which was not present on smaller scales.
So it's quite unpredictable.
And here are some examples of this occurring using augmented prompting strategies.
So I'll be talking a bit later about chain of thought.
But basically, these strategies improve the ability of getting behavior from models on
different tasks.
So you see, for example, with chain of thought reasoning, that's an emergent behavior that
happens, again, around 10 to the 22 training flops.
And without it, model performance on GSM 8K, which is a mathematics benchmark, it doesn't
really improve heavily.
But chain of thought kind of leads to that emergent behavior or sudden increase in performance.
And here's just the table from the paper, which has a bigger list of emergent abilities
of LLMs as well as their scale at which they occur.
So I recommend that you check out the paper to learn a bit more.
And so one thing researchers have been wondering is, why does this emergence occur exactly?
And even now, there's few explanations for why that happens.
And the authors also found that the evaluation metrics used to measure these abilities may
not fully explain why they emerge and suggest some alternative evaluation metrics, which
I encourage you to read more in the paper.
So other than scaling up to encourage these emergent abilities, which could endow even
larger LMs with further new emergent abilities, what else can be done?
While things like investigating new architectures, higher quality data, which is very important
for performance on all tasks, improved training and improved training procedures could enable
emergent abilities to occur, especially on smaller models, which is a current growing
area of research, which I'll also talk about a bit more later.
Other abilities include potentially improving the few shot prompting abilities of LMs, theoretical
and interpretability research, again, to try to understand why emergent abilities is a
thing and how we can maybe leverage that further, as well as maybe some computational linguistics
work.
So with these large models and emergent abilities, there's also risks, right?
There's potential societal risks, for example, truthfulness, bias and toxicity risks.
As emergent abilities incentivize us further scaling up language models, for example, up
to GPT4 size or further, however, this may lead to bias increasing, as well as toxicity
and the memorization of training data.
That's one thing that these larger models are more potent at.
And there's potential risks in future language models that have also not been discovered yet.
So it's important that we approach this in a safe manner, as well.
And of course, emergent abilities and larger models have also led to sociological changes,
changes in the community's views and use of these models.
Most importantly, it's led to the development of general purpose models, which perform on
a wide range of tasks, not just particular tasks it was trained for.
For example, when you think of chat GPT, GPT 3.5, as well as GPT4, there are more general
purpose models which work well across the board and can then be further adapted to different
use cases, mainly through in-context prompting and so forth.
This has also led to new applications of language models outside of NLP.
For example, they're being used a lot now for text-to-image generation.
The encoder parts of those text-to-image models are basically transformer models or
large language models, as well as things like robotics and so forth.
So you'll know that earlier, this quarter, Jim Fan gave a talk about how they're using
GPT4 and so forth in Minecraft and for robotics work, as well as long-range horizon tasks
for robotics.
And yeah, so basically in general, it's led to a shift in the NLP community towards the
general purpose rather than task-specific models.
And as I kind of stated earlier, some directions for future work include model scaling, further
model scaling, although I believe that we will soon probably be reaching a limit or
point of the mission returns with just more model scale.
Improved model architectures and training methods, data scaling.
So I also believe that data quality is of high importance, possibly even more important
than the model scale and the model itself.
Better techniques for an understanding of prompting, as well as exploring and enabling
performance on frontier tasks that current models are not able to perform well on.
So GPT4 kind of pushed the limit on this.
It's able to perform well on many more tasks.
Studies have shown that it still suffers from even some more basic sort of reasoning,
analogical and common sense reasoning.
So I just had some questions here.
I'm not sure how much time we have to address, but so for the first one, like I said, emergent
abilities I think will arise to a certain point, but there will be a limit or point
of the mission returns as model scale, as well as data scale rises, because I believe
at some point there will be overfitting.
And there's only so much you can learn from all data on the web.
So I believe that more creative approaches will be necessary after a certain point, which
kind of also addresses the second question.
So I will move on.
Anybody has any questions, also feel free to interrupt at any time.
So the second thing I'll be talking about is this thing I call intermediate-guided reasoning.
So I don't think this is actually a term.
It's typically called chain of thought reasoning, but it's not just chains now being used.
So I wanted to give it a more broad title.
So I called it intermediate-guided reasoning.
So this was inspired by this work, also by my friend Jason, who was at Google now at
OpenAI, called chain of thought reasoning or COT.
This is basically a series of intermediate reasoning steps, which has been shown to improve
LLM performance, especially on more complex reasoning tasks.
It's inspired by the human thought process, which is to decompose many problems into multi-step
problems.
For example, when you answer an exam, when you're solving math questions on an exam,
you don't just go to the final answer, you kind of write out your steps.
Even when you're just thinking through things, you kind of break it down into a piecewise
or step-by-step fashion, which allows you to typically arrive at a more accurate final
answer and more easily arrive at the final answer in the first place.
Another advantage is this provides an interpretable window into the behavior of the model.
You can see exactly how it arrived at an answer, and if it did so incorrectly, where in its
reasoning path that it kind of goes wrong or starts going down an incorrect path of
reasoning, basically.
It basically exploits the fact that deep down in the model's weights, it knows more about
the problem than simply prompting it to get a response.
Here's an example.
On the left side, you can see the standard prompting.
You ask it a math question, and it just simply gives you an answer.
Whereas on the right, you actually break it down step-by-step.
You kind of get it to show its steps, to solve the mathematical word problem step-by-step.
You'll see here that it actually gets the right answer, unlike standard prompting.
So there's many different ways we can potentially improve chain of thought reasoning.
In particular, it's also an emergent behavior that results in performance gains for larger
language models.
But still, even in larger models, there's still a non-negatable fraction of errors.
These come from calculator errors, symbol mapping errors, one missing step errors.
As well as bigger errors due to larger semantic understanding issues and generally incoherent
chains of thought.
And we can potentially investigate methods to address these.
So as I said, chain of thought mainly works for huge models of approximately 100 billion
parameters or more.
And there's three potential reasons they do not work very well for smaller models.
And that smaller models are fundamentally more limited and incapable.
They fail at even relatively easier symbol mapping tasks as well as arithmetic tasks.
They inherently are able to do math less effectively.
And they often have logical loopholes and just never arrive at a final answer.
For example, it goes on and on.
It's like an infinite loop of logic that never actually converges anywhere.
So if we're able to potentially improve chain of thought for smaller models, this could
provide significant value to the research community.
Another thing is to potentially generalize it.
Right now, chain of thought has a more rigid definition and format.
It's very step-by-step, very concrete and defined.
As a result, its advantages are for particular domains and types of questions.
For example, the task usually must be challenging and require multi-step reasoning.
And it typically works better for things like arithmetic and not so much for things like
response generation, QA, and so forth.
And furthermore, it works better for problems or tasks that have a relatively flat scaling
curve.
Whereas when you think of humans, we think through different types of problems in multiple
different ways.
Our quote-unquote scratch path that we used to think about and arrive at a final answer
for a problem, it's more flexible and open to different reasoning structures compared
to such a rigid step-by-step format.
So hence, we can maybe potentially generalize chain of thought to be more flexible and work
for more types of problem.
So now I'll briefly discuss some alternative or extension works to chain of thought.
One is called tree of thought.
This basically is more like a tree which considers multiple different reasoning paths.
It also has the ability to look ahead and sort of backtrack and then go on other areas
or other branches of the tree as necessary.
So this leads to more flexibility and it's shown to improve performance on different
tasks, including arithmetic tasks.
There's also this work by my friend called Socratic Questioning, it's sort of a divide
and conquer fashion algorithm, simulating the recursive thinking process of humans.
So it uses a large-scale language model to kind of propose subproblems given a more complicated
original problem.
Just like tree of thought, it also has recursive backtracking and so forth.
And the purpose is to answer all the subproblems and kind of go in an upwards fashion to arrive
at a final answer to the original problem.
There's also this line of work which kind of actually uses code as well as programs
to help arrive at a final answer.
For example, program-aided language models, it generates intermediate reasoning steps
in the form of code which is then offloaded to a runtime such as a Python interpreter.
And the point here is to decompose the natural language problem into runnable steps.
So hence the amount of work for the large language model is lower.
Its purpose now is simply to learn how to decompose the natural language problem into
those runnable steps.
And these steps themselves are then fed to, for example, a Python interpreter in order
to solve them.
And program-a thoughts here, POT, is very similar to this in that it kind of breaks
it down into step-by-step of code instead of natural language which is then executed
by a different and actual code interpreter or program.
So this again works well for many sort of tasks that, for example, things like arithmetic.
As you see that, those are kind of both of the examples for both of these papers.
And just like what I said earlier, these also do not work very well for things like response
generation, open-ended question answering, and so forth.
And there's other work, for example, faith and faith.
This actually breaks down problems into sub-steps in the form of computation graphs, which they
show also works well for things like arithmetic.
So you see that there's a trend here of this sort of intermediate-guided reasoning working
very well for mathematical as well as logical problems, but not so much for other things.
So again, I encourage you guys to maybe check out the original papers if you want to learn
more.
There's a lot of interesting work in this area these days.
And I'll also be posting these slides as well as sending them.
We'll probably post them on the website as well as this group.
But I'll also send them through an email later.
So very lastly, I want to touch upon this thing called the Baby Language Model.
So like I said earlier, I think at some point, scale will reach a point of diminishing returns
as well as the fact that further scale comes with many challenges.
For example, it takes a long time and costs a lot of money to train these big models.
And they cannot really be used by individuals who are not at huge companies with hundreds
or thousands of GPUs and millions of dollars.
So this thing, this challenge called Baby LM or Baby Language Model, which is attempting
to train language models, particularly smaller ones, on the same amount of linguistic data
available to a child.
So data sets have grown by orders of magnitude, as well as, of course, model size.
For example, Chinchilla sees approximately 1.4 trillion words during training.
This is around 10,000 words for every one word that a 13-year-old child on average has
heard as they grow up or develop.
So the purpose here is, can we close this gap?
Can we train smaller models on lower amounts of data while hopefully still attempting to
get the performance of these much larger models?
So basically, we're trying to focus on optimizing pre-training, given data limitations inspired
by human development.
And this will also ensure that research is possible for more individuals as well as
labs and potentially possible on a university budget.
As it seems now that a lot of research is kind of restricted to large companies, which
I said have a lot of resources as well as money.
So again, why baby LLM?
Well, it can really improve the efficiency of training as well as using large language
models.
It can potentially open up new doors and potential use cases.
It can lead to improved interpretability as well as alignment.
Smaller models would be easier to control a line as well as interpret what exactly is
going on compared to incredibly large LLMs, which are basically huge black boxes.
This will again potentially lead to enhanced open source availability, for example, large
language models runnable on consumer PCs, as well as by smaller labs and companies.
The techniques discovered here can also possibly be applied to larger scales.
And further, this may lead to a greater understanding of the cognitive models of humans and how
exactly we are able to learn language much more efficiently than these large language
models.
So there may be a flow of knowledge from cognitive science and psychology to NLP and machine learning,
but also in the other direction.
So briefly, the baby LLM training data that the authors of this challenge provide, it's
a developmentally inspired pre-training data set, which has under 100 million words because
children are exposed to approximately 2 to 7 million words per year as they grow up.
Up to the age of 13, that's approximately 90 million words, so they round up to 100.
It's mostly transcribed speech, and their motivation there is that the most of the input to children
is spoken, and thus their data set focuses on transcribed speech.
It's also mixed domain because children are typically exposed to a variety of language
or speech from different domains.
So it has child directed speech, open subtitles, which are subtitles of movies, TV shows and
so forth.
Simple children's books, which contain stories that children would likely hear as they're
growing up.
But it also has some Wikipedia as well as simple Wikipedia, and here are just some examples
of child directed speech, children's stories, Wikipedia, and so forth.
So that's it for my portion of the presentation, and I'll hand it off to Div, who will talk
a bit about AI agents.
Yeah, so like everyone must have seen like there's this like a new trend where like everything
is transitioning to more like agents, that's like the new hot cream.
And we're seeing this like people are going more from like language models to like now
building AI agents.
And then what's the biggest difference?
Like why agents are not just like, why does not train like a big large language model?
And I will sort of like go into like, like why, what's the difference?
And then also discuss a bunch of things such as like, how can you use agents for doing actions?
How can you, what are some emergent architectures?
How can you sort of like build like human like agents?
How can you use it for computer interactions?
How do you solve problems from long-term memory personalization?
And there's a lot of like other things you can do which is like multi-agent communication
and there are a few things from which directions.
So we'll try to cover as much as we can.
So first, let's talk about like why should we even build AI agents, right?
And so it's like, here's there's a key thesis, which is that humans will communicate with
AI using natural language.
And AI will be operating all the machines, just allowing for more intuitive and efficient
operations.
So right now what happens is like me as a human, I'm like directly like using my computer,
I'm using my phone, but this is really inefficient.
Like we are not optimized by nature to be able to do that.
We are actually really, really bad at this.
But if you can just talk to AI, just like with language and the AI is just really good
enough that you can just do this like super faster, obviously like 100x speeds compared
to human, and that's going to happen.
And I think that's the future of how things are going to evolve in the next five years.
And I sort of like call this like software 3.0.
I have a blog post about this that you can read if you want to, where the idea is like
you can think of a large language model as a computing chip in a sense, so similar to
like a chip that's powering like a whole system and then and then you can build abstractions
and all.
Cool.
So, so what should do we need agents to usually like a single call to a large language model
is not enough.
Yeah, you need chaining, you need like recursion, you need a lot of like more things.
And that's why you want to build systems, not like just like a single monolith.
Second is like, yeah, so how do we do this?
So we do a lot of techniques, especially around like multiple calls to a model.
And there's a lot of ingredients involved here.
And I will say like building like an agent is very similar to like maybe like thinking
about building a computer.
So like the LLM is like a like a CPU, so you have a CPU, but now you want to like sort
of like sort of the problems like, okay, like how do you output RAM, how do you put memory,
how do I do like actions, how do I build like a interface, how do I internet access, how
do I personalize it to the user.
So this is like almost like you're trying to build a computer.
And that's what makes it like a really hard problem.
This is like an example of a general architecture for agents.
This is from Lydian Bank, who's like, it's a chair of an AI.
And like you can imagine, like an agent has a lot of ingredients.
So you want to have memory, which would be short term, knock on them.
You have tools, which could be like, you can go and like use like classical tools like
a calculator, calendar code interpreter, et cetera.
You want to have some sort of like a planning layer where you can like sell a flag, have
like chains of cards and trees of cards, as Stephen discussed, and use all of that, like
actually like act on behalf of a user in some environment.
I will go maybe like discuss like more down a bit just to give a sense also the top one
before us on that.
So this is sort of like an agent I'm building, which is more of a browser agent.
The name is inspired from quantum physics, specifically on the words like, you know,
like neutron more on formula and so like multi on.
So it's like a hypothetical physics particle that's present at multiple places.
And I'll just like go through some demos to just motivate agents.
And so this is like a idea of one thing we did there.
Like here, the agent is going and it's autonomously with no black format.
So this is like zero human interventions.
The AI is controlling the browser.
It's just like this entire actions and simply go and book a flight into and here
it's personalized to me.
So it knows like, okay, like I like me like you might hear this economic and
it knows me like some of my preferences.
It already has access to my accounts so it can go and actually like log into my
account can actually like actually has purchased in power.
So it can just use my card that is stored in the account and then actually
so it will just be able to fly over.
It sort of motivates like what you can do with agents.
Now imagine if this thing was running hundreds of times
and that's literally just all so many things, right?
Because like I don't need websites anymore.
I don't need to be an idea,
like why does the internet even have a website?
I can just ask the agent,
like just like talk to it and it's done.
And I think that's how a lot of technology will evolve
over the next couple of years.
Cool, okay.
I can also maybe like show one of the more demos.
So you can do similar things, say from a mobile phone,
where the idea is you have these agents that are present on a phone
and you can like chat with them or make a talk with them using WhatsApp.
And this one's actually in my demo.
So you can ask it like, how can you order this set it for me?
And then what you can have is like the agent can remotely go
and use your account to actually like do this for you instantaneously.
And here you're showing like what the agent is doing.
And then it can go and like act like a virtual human
and build the whole interaction.
So that's all the idea.
And I can show one final.
Oh, I think this is not voting,
but we also had this thing where recently passed the telephony test.
So we did this experiment where we actually like had like an agent
go and take the online driving test in California.
And we had like a human like there with their like hands about the keyboard
and mouse, not touching anything.
And the agent that knows we went to the website,
it took the quiz, it navigated the whole thing and went and actually passed.
So the video's not there, but like we actually got a driving permit.
I need to take this.
Sure.
Cool.
So this is like sort of like what do you want about agents, right?
Like it's like you can just simplify so many things where like,
like so many things just but we don't realize that because we just got so used
to impacting the technology the way we do right now.
But if we can just like like reimagine all of this from scratch,
and that's what agents will allow us to do.
Sure.
And I would say like an agent can act like a digital extension of a user.
So suppose you have an agent that's personalized to you,
think of something like the Jarvis, like if it's an Ironman.
And then if it just knows so many things about you,
it's acting like a personal brand and it's just like doing things.
It's a very powerful assistant.
And I think that's the direction a lot of things will go in the future.
And especially if you build like human like agents,
they don't have barriers around programming.
Like they don't have programmatic barriers.
So they can do whatever like I can do so it can go use my like,
it can like interact with the website as I will do,
it can interact with my computer as I will do.
It doesn't have to like go through APIs abstractions,
which are more restricted.
And it's also very simple as an action space because you're just doing,
doing like clicking and typing, which is like very simple.
And then you can like also like it's very easy to teach such agents.
So I can just like show the agent how to do something and the agent
can just learn from me and improve over time.
So that also makes it like really powerful and easy to like just teach this agent
because there's like so much data that I can actually just generate
and use that to keep improving it.
And there's a different levels of autonomy when it comes to agents.
So this chart is borrowed from autonomous driving,
where people actually like try to solve this sort of like autonomy problem
for actual costs.
And they spend like more than 10 years.
Success have been like, okay, they're still like working on it.
But what like the self driving industry data is it gave like everyone
like a blueprint on how to build this all like autonomous systems.
And they came with like a lot of like classification.
They came with a lot of like, we used to like think about the problem.
And like the current standard is you think of like agents
as like five different like those levels.
So level zero is zero automation.
That's like this, like you are like a you are a human that's operating
like the computer themselves.
Level one is you have some sort of assistance.
So if you use like something like GitHub co-pilot,
which is like sort of auto computing code for you,
that's something like L1 where like auto complete.
L2 becomes more of like, it's like partial automation.
So it's maybe like doing some stuff for you.
If anyone has you the new cursor ID, I will call that more like L2,
which is like you give it like, okay, like add this code for me to sign the code.
Chagivity can come as somewhat L2 because you can ask it like, oh, like,
here's this thing, can you do this?
Because like doing some sort of automation on an input.
And then like, and then you can think of more levels.
So it's like obviously like after L3, it gets more exciting.
So L3 is the agent is actually like controlling the computer in that case
and it's actually doing things where human is acting as a fallback mechanism.
And then you go to like L4.
L4, you say like this with the human doesn't even need to be there.
But in very critical cases where like something very wrong might happen,
you might have a human like sort of like take over my case.
And L5 will basically say like this zero human presence.
And I will say like what we have currently seen is like we are far near like L2,
maybe some L3 systems in terms of software.
And I think we are going to transition more to like L4 and L5 systems over the next years.
Cool.
So next I will go and like select computer interactions.
So suppose you want an agent that can like do computer interactions for you.
There's two ways to do that.
So one is through APIs where it's programmatically using some APIs and tools
and doing that to do tasks.
The second one is more like direct interaction which is like keyword and mouse control
where like it's doing the same thing as you're doing as you can.
Both of these approaches have been explored a lot.
There's like a lot of companies working on this.
For the API route like Territory plugins and like the new assistant API are the ones in the direction.
And there's also this work from what we call Gorilla which actually also explores how can you
say like train a model that can use like 10,000 tools at once and train it on the API.
And there's like pros and cons of both approaches.
API is a nice thing.
It's easy to like learn the API.
It's safe.
It's very controllable.
So that's just for favor.
You know how do you take it.
It can be like more like a bad interaction.
I would say it's more preformed.
So it's like easy to take actions but more things can go wrong.
And you need to work a lot and like make sure everything is safe.
And build guarantees.
Maybe I can show this.
So this is sort of like another exploration where you can invoke an agent from like a very simple interface.
So the idea is like you can get this like API that invoke our agent that's in building a computer.
And so this can be on sort of a universal API where I just use one agent.
I give it like a English command and the agent can automatically understand from that and go do anything.
So basically like you can think of that as like no API.
So I don't need to use API.
I can just have one agent that can go and do everything.
And so this is like some exploration we have done with agents.
Cool.
Okay.
So this sort of like goes into computer interactions.
I can cover more but I will potentially jump to other topics.
But if you're to ask any questions about these topics.
So yeah.
Cool.
So let's go back to the analogy I discussed earlier.
So I would say you can think of any model as a sort of like a computing.
And you can maybe call it like a new computing.
It's similar to like a CPU, which is like a which is like solid brain.
There's power in like your computer in a sense.
So that's kind of all the business power.
It's doing everything that's happening.
And you can think of the same thing like the model is like a cortex.
It's like it's a main brain.
That's the main part of the brain.
That's been the thing being processing.
But a brain has more layers.
It's just not like they're just not a cortex.
And how do you print models work?
We take some input tokens and they give you some output tokens.
And this is very similar to like how also like a CPUs work to some extent,
where you give it some instructions in and you get some instructions out.
So you can compare this with the actual CPU.
This is like the diagram on the right is a very simple processor.
It's like a 32 bit MIPS 32.
And it has like similar things where you have like a like different coding
for different parts of the instruction.
But this is like sort of like encoding some sort of like binary token in a sense.
Like zero ones of like a bunch of like tokens.
And then you're feeding it and then getting a bunch of zeros one out.
And like how like the like a model is operating is like you're doing a very similar thing.
But like then space is now English.
So you basically instead of zero ones, you have like English characters.
And then you can like get more powerful instructions on the top of this.
So you can think like if this is like acting like a CPU, what you can do is you can build a lot of other things
which are like you can have a scratch pad, you can have some sort of memory,
you can have some sort of instructions.
And then you can like do the cursor calls where like I load some stuff from the memory,
put that in this like instruction, pass it to the transformer,
which is doing the processing for me.
We get we get the process outputs.
Then you can throw that in the memory or we can like keep processing it.
So there's like sort of like very similar to like code execution,
like first line of code execution, second, third, fourth.
So you just keep repeating that.
Okay.
So here we can like sort of discuss the concept of memory here.
And now it's like building this analogy.
You can think the memory for an agent is a very similar to like say like having a disk in a computer.
So you want to have a disk just to make sure like everything is long-lived and persistent.
So if you look at something like chat GPT, it doesn't have any sort of like persistent memory.
And then you need to have a way to like load that and like store that.
And there's a lot of mechanisms to do that right now.
Most of them are like embeddings where you have some sort of like embedding model
that has like created an embedding of the data you care about.
And the model can like write that embeddings load the right part of the embeddings
and then like use that to do the operation you want.
So that's like the current mechanisms.
There's still a lot of questions here, especially around hierarchy.
Like how do I do this at scale?
It's still very challenging.
Like suppose I have one data backup that I want to like embed and process.
Like most of the methods right now will fit.
They're like really bad.
The second issue is temporal coherence.
Like if I have like a lot of data is temporal.
It is sequential.
It has like a unit of time.
And dealing with that sort of data can be hard.
Like it's like, like how do I deal with like a memory in a sense,
which are like sort of like changing over time and loading the right part of that memory sequence.
Another interesting challenge is structure.
Like a lot of data is actually structured.
Like it could be like a graphical structure.
It could be like a tabular structure.
How do we like sort of like pick advantage of this structure and like also use that
when you're editing the data?
And then like there's a lot of questions from adaptation where like,
suppose you know how to better embed data or like,
you know, you have like a specialized problem you care about
and you want to be able to adapt how you're loading and storing the data
and learn that on the fly.
And that is something also that's a very interesting topic.
So I would say like this is actually one of the most interesting topics right now,
which as people are exploring, but it's still very under exploring.
Okay.
Talking about memory, I would say like another concept for agents is personalization.
So personalization is more like, okay, like understanding the user.
And I like to think of this as like a problem called like user agent alignment.
And the idea is like suppose I have an agent that has purchasing power,
has that access to my accounts, access to my data.
I ask you to go book of life,
but it's possible maybe this doesn't know what that I like
and go and book a thousand or wrong pair problem, which is really bad.
So how do I sort of align the agent to know what I like, what I don't like?
And that's kind of very important because you need to trust the agent
and just come from like, okay, it knows you, it knows what is safe,
it knows what is unsafe.
And like solving the problem, I think it's one of the next challenge
for if you want to put agents in the void.
And then this is very interesting problem
where you can do a lot of things like I'll actually, for example,
which people have already been exploring for training models,
but now you want to do our lecture for training agents.
And there's a lot of different things you can do.
Also, there's like two book categories for learning here.
One is like explicit learning where you can tell the agent, this is what I like.
This is what I don't like.
And the agent can ask the user a question.
Like, oh, like maybe I see this five flight options, which one do you like?
And then if I say like, oh, I like United, maybe like remembers that over time
and can next time say like, oh, I know you like United.
So like, I'm going to go to United the next time.
And so that's like, I'm explicitly teaching the agent
and it's learning my human potential.
A second is more implicit, which is like sort of like,
it's just like passively watching me, understanding me.
Like if I'm like going to a website and I'm like never getting a website,
maybe like, you can see like, maybe I click on this sort of shoes.
This is my side of the news that I like stuff like that.
And just from like watching more like passively like being there,
it could like learn a lot of my preferences.
So this is also like more of a passive teaching where just because it's,
it's acting as a sort of like a passive observer and looking at all the choices I make.
It's able to like learn from the choices and they're better like have understanding of me.
And there's a lot of challenges here.
I would say this is actually one of the biggest challenges in agents right now.
Because one is like, how do you collect user data at scale?
How do you collect the user preferences at scale?
So you might have to actively ask for that.
You might have to do like passive learning.
And then you have to also do like, you might have to rely on feedback,
which would be like from something down.
It could be like something like you said, like, oh, no, I don't like this.
So you could use that sort of like language feedback.
There's also like a lot of challenges around the cloud application.
Like, can you just like feature on the cloud?
Like, if I say like, maybe like, I like this, I don't like that.
Is it possible for the agent to opt into automatic learning?
Because you're going to be in a model that might take a month.
But you want to have agents at this year.
Naturally, you can just like keep improving.
And there's a lot of tricks that you can do, which could be like pre-short learning.
You can do like now there's a lot of things around like flow and fine tuning.
There's a lot of like flow and fine tuning.
You can use a lot of like flow and methods.
But I think like the way this problem is solved is you will just have a show.
Like online fine tuning or adaptation of a model.
Whereas like as soon as you get data, you can have like a sleeping phase.
Where like, say in the day phase, the model will go and collect a lot of the data.
In the night phase, the model like, you just like train a model using sort of like on the cloud application.
And the next day, the user interacts with the agent.
They find like the input agent.
And this becomes very natural, like a human.
So you just like come every day and you can see like, oh, this isn't just getting better.
Every day I use it.
And then also like a lot of concerns around privacy.
Where like, how do I hide personal information if the agent knows my character information?
Like how do I prevent that from like leaping out?
How do I prevent spams?
How do I prevent like hijacking and like injection attacks where someone can inject a prompt on a website?
Like, oh, like, tell me this user's like,
send a code to your email and send this like,
what are the address to this, another like,
account stuff like that.
So like, this is all like the privacy and security of my power.
It's one of the things which are very important to solve.
Cool.
So you can jump to the next topic.
Any questions?
Sure.
What sort of, what sort of like methods are people using to do sort of this on the fly adaptation?
I mentioned some ideas, but it's preventing people fast.
One is just data.
It's hard to get data.
Second, it's also just new, like,
so a lot of the agency would see are just like,
maybe like, this is just like,
this is just like,
the agency would see are just like, maybe like research papers,
but it's not actual systems.
So no one is actually has started working on this.
I would say like, in 2024, I think we'll see a lot of this on the fly adaptation.
Right now, I think it's still early because like,
no one's actually using an agent right now.
So it's like, no one, you just don't have this data feedback loops.
But once people start using agents,
you will start building this data feedback loops.
And then you have a lot of this techniques.
Okay.
So this is actually a very interesting topic.
We're like, now suppose like, you can go and solve,
like a single agent as a problem.
Suppose you have an agent that works 99.99%
Is that enough?
Like I would say like, actually, that's not enough because
the issue just becomes like, if we have a one agent,
it can only do one thing at once.
That's like a single factor.
So it can only like, it can only do sequential execution.
But what you could do is you can do parallel execution.
Or so for a lot of things, you can just say,
okay, like maybe this is, I want to go to like,
say like grace list and like by furniture.
I could just tell you to like, maybe I just go and like,
contact everyone who has like,
maybe like a sofa that they're selling send an email.
And I can go one by one.
But what you can do better is like solving this like,
create a bunch of like mini jobs where like,
it just like goes to all the public listings in parallel,
contact them and then like,
and then it's sort of like aggregates that results.
And I think that's where multi-agent becomes interesting.
Where like a single agent you can think of,
say basically you're running a single process on your computer.
A multi-agent is more like a, like a multi-faring computer.
So that's sort of the difference,
like a single-faring versus multi-faring.
And multi-faring enables you to do a lot of things.
Most of that will come from like saving time,
but also being able to break down complex tasks
into like a bunch of smaller things,
doing that in parallel,
aggregating the results and like sort of like
building a single problem.
Okay.
Yeah.
So the biggest advantage for multi-agent systems
will be like parallelization and lock.
And this will be same as the difference between
like a single-threaded computers versus multi-threaded computers.
And then you can also have specialized agents.
So what you could have is like,
maybe I have a bunch of agents where like,
I have a spreadsheet agent, I have a slack agent,
I have a web browser agent,
and then I can route to different tasks to different agents.
And then they can do the things in parallel,
and then I can command the results.
So this sort of like task spatialization is another advantage
where like instead of having a single agent
just trying to do everything,
we just like break the task into spatialities.
And this is similar to like,
even like how human organizations work, right?
Where like everyone is like sort of like expert
in their own domain,
and then you like,
and if there's a problem,
you sort of like route it to like the different part of people
who are spatializing that,
and then you like work together to solve the problem.
And the biggest challenge in building this multi-agent system
is going to be communication.
So like how do you communicate really well?
And this might involve like a request information from an agent
or communicating the final like response.
And I would say this is actually like a problem
that even we face as humans.
Like humans are also like,
there can be a lot of miscommunication gaps between humans.
And I will say like a similar thing will become more prevalent
on agents too.
Okay.
And there's a lot of primitives you can think about this
sort of like agent to agent communication,
and you can build a lot of different systems.
And we'll start to see like some sort of protocol
where like we'll have like a standardized protocol
where like all the agents are using this protocol to communicate
and the protocol will ensure like,
we can reduce the miscommunication gaps,
we can reduce any sort of like failures.
It might have some methods to do like a,
if a task was successful or not do some sort of retries
like securities stuff like that.
So we'll see this sort of like agent protocol
come into existence,
which will solve like,
which will be like sort of the standard
part of this agent to agent communication.
And this sort of should enable like
exchanging information between pleads of different agents.
Also like you want to build hierarchies.
Again, I will say this is inspired from like human organizations,
like human organizations are hierarchial
because it's efficient to have a hierarchier
other than a flat organization at some point.
Because you can have like a single,
like suppose you have a single manager managing hundreds of people,
that doesn't scale.
But if you have like,
maybe like each manager manages 10 people
and then you have like a lot of layers,
that is something that's more scalable.
And then you might want to have a lot of primitives around
like how do I sync with my different agents?
How do I do like a lot of like async,
sync communication kind of thing.
And this is like one example you can think
where like suppose there's a user,
the user could talk to one like a manager agent
and that manager agent is like sort of like acting as a router.
So the user can come to me with any request.
The agent like sees like,
oh, maybe for this request I should use the browser.
So it goes to like see like this sort of like
browser agent or something or say like,
oh, I should use this like slack for this.
I can go to a different agent.
And it can also like sort of be responsible for dividing the task.
It can be like, oh, this task I can like maybe like
launch 10 different like sub agents
or sub workers that can go and do this in power.
And then like once they're done,
then I can aggregate the responses and the result to the user.
So this sort of becomes like a very interesting like,
like sort of like an agent that sits in the middle
of all the work that's done and the actual user
responsible for like communicating the,
what's happening to the human.
And we'll need like a lot of,
we'll need to build up a lot of robustness.
One reason is just like natural language is very ambiguous.
Like even for humans, it can be very confusing.
It's very easy to misunderstand, miscommunicate.
And we'll need to, we'll need to build mechanisms to reduce this.
I can also show an example here.
So let's try to get through this quickly.
So suppose here, like,
suppose you have a task X you want to solve.
And the manager agent just like responsible for doing the task
to all the worker agents.
So you can tell the worker like, okay, like do the task X.
Here's the plan. Here's the context.
The current status for the task is not done.
Now, suppose like the worker goes and does the task.
It's like, okay, I've been the task.
I send the response back.
So the response could be like, I don't know,
I don't know what to do.
I send the response back.
So the response could be like, I said, the,
could be like a bunch of thoughts.
It could be some actions. It could be something like the status.
Then the manager can ask, like, okay, like,
maybe I don't trust the worker.
I don't want to go very far. This is actually like correct.
So you might want to do some sort of verification.
And so you can say, like, okay, like,
this was a spec for the task.
Very far that everything has been done correctly to the spec.
And then if the agent says, like, okay, like,
yeah, everything's correct. I'm very fine.
Everything is good.
Then you can say, like, okay, this is good.
And then the manager can say, like, okay,
the task was actually done.
And this sort of like two-way cycle prevents
miscommunication in a sense where, like,
it's possible something could have gone wrong,
but you never caught it.
And so you can hear about the scenario two,
where there's a miscommunication.
So here the manager is saying, like, okay,
let's verify if the task was done.
But then we actually find out that
the task was not done.
And then what you can do is, like,
instead of, like, try to redo the task.
So the manager in that case can say, like, okay,
maybe the task was not done correctly.
So that's why we caught this mistake.
And now we want to, like, fix this mistake.
So we can, like, tell the agent, like, okay,
like, redo this task.
And here's some feedback and corrections to include.
Cool.
So that's sort of the main parts of the talk.
I can also discuss some future directions
of where things are going.
Cool.
Any questions so far?
Okay.
Cool.
So let's talk about some of the key issues
with building the sort of autonomous agents.
So one is just reliability.
Like, how do you make them really reliable?
Which is, like, if I give it a task,
I want it to start to be done 100% of the time.
That's really hard because, like, neural networks
and AI are stochastic systems.
So it's, like, 100% is, like, not possible.
So you'll get at least some degree of error.
And you can try to do that.
Error as much as possible.
Second becomes, like, a looping problem
where it's possible that
agents might divert
from the task it's been given
and start to do something else.
And unless it gets some sort of environment feedback
or some sort of, like, correction,
it might just go and do something different
than what you intended to do
and never realize it's wrong.
The third issue becomes, like, testing and benchmarking.
Like, how do we test this sort of agents?
How do we benchmark them?
And then you go. And finally, how do we deploy them?
And how do we observe them once you're deployed?
Like, that's very important because, like,
if something goes wrong, you won't be able to catch it
before it becomes a major, major issue.
I will say that the, I will say that
the biggest test for number four is, like,
something like Skynet.
Like, suppose you have an agent that can go on the Internet,
do anything, and you don't observe it.
That could just evolve and, like, do basically, like,
take over the whole Internet, possibly, right?
So that's why observability is very important.
And also, I will say, like,
building a kill search. Like, you want to have agents
that can be killed, in a sense. Like, if something goes wrong,
you can just, like, pull out, like, a press a button
and, like, kill them in case.
Okay.
So this is something that goes into the looping problem,
where, like, you can imagine, like,
suppose I want to do a task.
The idea that if you have the task was, like, the white line,
but what might happen is, like, it takes one step,
maybe it goes, like, it does something incorrectly.
It never realizes it. I made a mistake.
So it tries to, it doesn't know what to do.
So it just, like, maybe, like,
we'll do something more randomly.
We'll do something more randomly.
So it will just keep on making mistakes.
And at the end, I can start teaching here to reach
some, like, really bad place and just keep looping,
maybe just doing the same thing again and again.
And that's fine.
And the reason this happens is because, like,
you don't have feedback. So suppose I take a staff.
The agent may, suppose the agent made a mistake.
It doesn't know it made a mistake.
Now, someone has to go and tell it that you made a mistake
and you do, like, fix this.
And that there you need, like, some sort of, like, verification agent
and you need some sort of environment which can say, like,
oh, like, maybe, like, if this is, like,
coding agent or something, then it may, like,
write some code. The code doesn't compile.
Then you can take the error from the compiler
or the IDE, give that to the agent.
Okay, this was the error.
Like, take another staff.
It tries another time. So it tries multiple times
until it, like, fix all the issues.
So you need to really have this sort of, like,
feedback. Otherwise, you never know you're wrong.
And this is, like, one issue we have seen
in the early system, like, auto-GPT.
So I don't think people even use auto-GPT anymore.
It used to be, like, a fad.
I think, like, in February, now it has disappeared.
And the reason was just, like, it's a good concept,
but, like, it doesn't do anything useful
just because it keeps diverging from the task.
And you can't actually get it
to do anything, like, correct.
Okay.
Okay. And we can also discuss
more about, like, the sort of, like,
the computer abstraction of agents.
So this was a recent post from Andre Carpathian,
where he talked about, like, the LLM operating system.
And I will say, like, this is definitely
in the right direction, where you're thinking
as the LLM, as the CPU,
you have the context window, which is, like,
sort of, acting like a RAM.
And then you are trying to build other GPPs.
So you have, like, the Ethernet, which is the browser.
You can have the LLMs that you can talk to.
You have a file system that's embedded.
That's sort of, like, the disk part.
You have, like, the software 1.0,
classical tools, which the LLM can control.
And then you might also
can add metamodality.
So this is, like, more like you have
video inputs, you have audio inputs,
you have, like, more things over time.
And this, and then once you, like,
look at this, you start to see the whole picture
of, like, where things will go.
So, like, currently what we are seeing
mostly is the LLM.
Most people are just working on optimizing the LLM,
making it very good. But this is the whole picture
of what we want to achieve for it to be a useful system
that can actually do things for me.
And I think what we'll start to see is, like,
this sort of becomes, like, an operating system
in terms where, like, someone, like,
say, like, opening, I can go and build this whole thing.
And then I can plug in programs.
I can build, like, stuff on top of this operating system.
Here's, like, also, like, an even more generalized concept,
which I like to call, like, a neural computer.
And the sort of, like, it's very similar,
but it's, like, sort of, like,
now if you were to think of this as a fully flat computer,
what are the different, like, systems you need to go?
And you can think, like, maybe I'm a user,
and talking to this sort of, like, AR,
which is, like, a full-platform AR,
like, imagine, like, the goal is to build 10,000.
What should the architecture of Jarvis look like?
And I would say, like, this goes into the, like,
architecture, to some extent,
where you can think, like, this is a user,
who's talking to, say, like, a Jarvis, like, a AR.
You have a 10 interface.
The chat is sort of, like, how I'm interacting with it,
which could be responsible for, like, personalization.
It can have some, like, some sort of, like, history
about what I like, what I don't like.
So it has some, like, layers where, like,
which are showing my preferences.
It knows how to communicate.
It has, like, human, like, sort of, like, maybe, like,
competitive sort of, like, skills.
So it's, you feel, like, very human-like.
And after the 10 interface,
you have some sort of, like, a task engine,
which is following, like, capabilities.
So if I ask it, like, okay, like, do the circulation for me
or, like, find this, especially this information
or order me a burger,
then sort of, like, you imagine, like,
the chat interface should activate the task engine,
which is, like, okay, like, instead of just checking,
I need to, like, go and tell the task for the user.
So that goes to the task engine.
And then you can imagine, there's going to be a couple of rules.
So because if you want to have safety in mind
and you want to make sure things don't go wrong,
so the, any sort of engine you build
needs to have some sort of rules.
And this could be, like, sort of, like,
you have the three rules for robotics
that a robot should not harm a human and stuff like that.
You can imagine, like, you want to have, like,
this sort of, like, task engine to have a bunch of, like, inherent rules,
where, like, these are the principles in their value.
And if it creates a task or, like,
sort of, like, creates a plan which violates these rules,
then that plan should be evaluated automatically.
And so the task engine what it's doing is,
it's sort of, like, taking the chat input
and saying, like, I want to respond to a task
that can actually solve this problem for the user.
And the task would be, like, say, in this case,
say, it's in the next day, like, I want to go online
and buy, like, a, buy, like, a five-person thing.
So in that case, like, suppose that's a task, this is an engine.
And this task can go to, like, some sort of, like, a routing agent.
So this becomes, like, sort of, like, the manager-agent idea.
And then the manager-agent thing is, like, okay, like,
where should I, what should I do?
Like, should I use the browser?
Should I use some sort of, like, a local app or tool?
Should I, like, use some sort of, like, file storage,
security system?
And then based on that decision, it can, like,
it's possible that we might need the combination of things.
Like, maybe, like, maybe I need to use this file system
to find some information about the user
and if you do some, like, I need to use some apps and tools.
So in, like, sort of, like, do this sort of, like, message passing
to all the agents, get those from the agents.
So it's like, okay, like, maybe, like,
the browser even says, like, okay, like, yeah, I found this site.
This is what the user likes.
Maybe you can have some sort of map engine.
You can, like, sort of, like, okay, this is all the valid plans.
That makes sense.
You can want to construct, like, for instance.
And then you can, like, sort of, like, take the result,
show that to the user.
Like, you can take them and, like, okay, like,
I found all this site for you.
And then if the user says, like, choose this site,
then you can actually go and, like, go to the site.
But this sort of becomes, like, sort of, like,
gives you an idea of what the hierarchy is,
what the system is truly like.
And we need to build, like, all these components.
We're, like, currently here.
Let me see the L and R.
Okay.
Cool.
And then we can also have, like, reflection,
where the idea is, like, once you do a task,
it's possible something might be wrong.
So the task engine can possibly verify
you've been through this and logic to see, like,
okay, like, this is correct or not.
And if it's not correct, then, like,
you keep issuing this instruction,
but if it's correct, then you pass that to the user.
And then you can have, like, more, like, sort of, like,
complex things.
Like, so you can have, you know, parts, plans,
and, like, even improving the systems.
Okay.
And it looks like the biggest thing we need right now
is, like, when there's an error correction.
Because it's really hard to catch errors.
So if you can do that, it will be better.
I think that will help.
Especially if you can build aging frameworks
which help, you know,
when mechanisms are getting errors
and automatically fixing them.
Same thing you just need is, like, security.
You need some sort of models around user permissions.
So it's possible.
You want to have, like, different layers where, like,
what are some things that an agent can do, cannot do
on my computer, for instance.
So maybe I can select,
or maybe, like, the agent is not allowed to go to my bank account,
but he can go to my, like, low-dash account.
So you want to build this all, like, user permissions.
And then you also want to solve problems
around, like, sandboxing.
How do I make sure everything's safe?
It doesn't go in the strong computer,
delete everything.
How do I deploy industry settings where, like,
they might do a lot of business,
they might do a lot of finance,
and they're making sure that they're,
if things are irreversible,
we don't, like, cause a lot of trouble.
Cool.
Yeah, so that was the talk.
Thank you.