erase my memories erase my mind gotta leave the past behind i don't remember what i used to be
i'm breaking free from my history forget the pain forget the tears i'm wiping clean all my
feelings no looking back i'm on my own in this MEGXO
lost in a haze but nothing's real i feel a picture i can't really feel
i'm searching for something i can't recall the memories won't let me fall
lost in a haze but nothing's real i feel a picture i can't recall the memories won't let me fall
i feel a picture i can't recall the memories won't let me fall
My mind expanding like an aniseclo Phenomenology
I'm breaking them all Exploring dimensions
My thoughts unfold Awakening senses
Like a vibrant symphony All because I'm shining through
My destiny I dive deep within
To find my true Breaking down barriers
Breaking through The world's a canvas
Where I paint my dreams For no limits
To this universe Far as it seems
I'm applying it Join my own path
Fresh awake in me I breathe
Life is just a game Nietzsche said it right
No meaning in this world No purpose in sight
We're all just rolling dice Trying to survive
But in the end We're all destined to die
Riding on the waves Of existential dread
Questioning our existence What lies ahead
Searching for the truth To finding emptiness instead
Nihilism in our hearts Filling us with dread
In this absurd world We all play our part
To deep down inside We know it's all a work of art
A cosmic joke, a meaning We can't comprehend
We're just floating atoms Waiting for the end
Waiting for the end
Every belief, every step, every form
Life's a dance on the edge The plans connect
Convexing the void Even judgments in the past
Beyond the lens in the past
Beyond illusions We find our own way
In this crazy world We make the rules that we obey
No existential crisis We choose to exist
Doing it our way In this life in pieces
We're all destined to die
Riding on the waves Of existential dread
In this absurd world We're all destined to die
In this crazy world We make the rules that we obey
Limes of cold are running through my mind
Some tacks are lying in its rhythm I can't hide
If you made it, turn my digital sanctuary
Writing melodies in a cold repository
Tabs and spaces, dancing on the screen
Auto-complete makes some music so lean
Indentation like a bass drops so deep
As I navigate through the coke I keep
Go to the beach, so symphony in my hands
The melody turn my own to nickel man
From lights to melodies in a digital screen
Fall into the rhythm in perfect harmony
Full day and night, large green white text light
Want a righteous flight, life's clean out of sight
Escape to command mode, ancient KL roads
Jump lines with each keystroke, same tacks, no joke
Room forever so sleek, minimalistic peak
Type it makes my heart beat, no mouse
Just rhythm and streak, shortcuts that I crave
Mastery I crave, all inside my cave
Editing with wave, vexing in the breeze
Yanking such a tease, undo re-do it with ease
Make to please or please
Room forever so sleek, minimalistic peak
Type it makes my heart beat, no mouse
Just rhythm and streak
Bursting in a breeze, yanking such a tease
Undo redo with ease, make to please or please
Go to the beach, so symphony in my hands
The melody turn my own to nickel man
Come to the beach, so symphony in my hands
From lights to melodies in a digital screen
Fall into the rhythm in perfect harmony
Go to the beach, so symphony in my hands
The melody turn my own to nickel man
Thin editor my ultimate command
From lights to melodies in a digital screen
Fall into the rhythm in perfect harmony
Code all day and night
Black screen, white text like
Wanna ride just right
Lines clean out, it's light, it's stick to command mode
H-shaped K&L roads, jump lines with each keystroke
Syntax, no joke
Room forever so sleek, minimalistic peak
Type it makes my heart beat, no mouse
Just rhythm and streak, shortcuts that crave
Mastery or praise, all inside my cave
Everything with weight, bursting in a breeze
Yanking such a tease, undo, redo with ease
Made to please or please, timber in a breeze
Mastery or praise, all inside my cave
Everything with weight, pasting in a breeze
Yanking such a tease, undo, redo with ease
Made to please or please
Think forever
Mastery or I, all inside my cave
Editing with weight, pasting in a breeze
Yanking such a tease, undo, redo with ease
Made to please or please, oh please
Room forever so sleek, minimalistic peak
Type it makes my heart beat, no mouse
Just rhythm and
Come, please
Room forever so sleek, minimalistic peak
Type it makes my heart beat, no mouse
Just rhythm and
streak
Go to the peace
Define my own wealth, no luxury cars
No fancy clothes
Just me and the sand
Yeah, that's how it goes
I'm living like Robinson
Cruel so as a man
Building my show too with my own two hands
No room service
No TV screen
Just gotta survive
Yeah, you know what I mean
Deserted island blues
Yeah, it's such a lonely view
But I'ma make it through cause I've got nothing to lose
I'm stranded on this island
Feeling kinda blue blue blue
But I'ma find my way back home
Just wait and see it through
No cash, no booty
No fancy things
Just me and heart
That's all it brings
Only no, no type
No luxury
But I'm the people I want to meet
The little people that love me
The shiny fish
Be my life
Oh please
No shiny cars
No diamond rings
But I dance like a queen
When the music sings
No money, no money
No big things
No natural yet
No designer clothes
But my spirit so as high
Nobody knows
I am afraid from desire
And higher and higher the fire
No material goods
Can't take me higher
In this favorite life
I'm not a fire fire
Living my truth
My soul of fire
Music
No material goods
Can't take me higher
In this rainbow fly
I'm not a fire
I live in my truth, my soul on fire
Eyes wide open in the dark we roam
Lost in space searching for a home
Distressed call echoes fear in our hearts
A vessel tearing us apart
Heart beat pounding my dread and foes
Unknown terror can nobody know
Every breath we take a step towards end of old
Invasion, immanence, humanity to throne
Defone, invasion, immanence, humanity to throne
Engines roaring faster than the speed of light
Lost in a battle
Fighting the fight, survival instincts kick it till I give
A digital loss will burst our fear
Drossing our thoughts as philosophers buying each invite
Darkness shining so bright, nihilistic notions taking over my mind
In this life's chaos leading's hard to find
Existential questions they keep me alive
Through the turmoil and struggles I will thrive
Searching for purpose in this world absurd
Dancing with nihilism my truth is blurred
In the depths of existence I find my release
Ragged on rhythm my heartbeat won't cease
Stands to the tune of philosophical bliss
Embracing our questions in sweet ignorance we kiss
Love is not
As of existence I find my release
Ragged on rhythm my heartbeat won't cease
Stands to the tune of philosophical bliss
Embracing our questions in sweet ignorance we kiss
Love is not
As of existence I find my release
Ragged on rhythm my heartbeat won't cease
Stands to the tune of philosophical bliss
Embracing our questions in sweet ignorance we kiss
Corrupt politicians manipulating their plans
I'm here to rebel, ignite the fire, take a stand
Spit rhymes so fierce they hit you like a thousand brands
I'm a lyrical king ruling this rap game
I'll expose the truth, great justice, name it my claim
Systemic corruption it's time to break the chain
Unveil the secrets
Let the people know the grain, they call no done
This rap game I'll expose the truth, bring justice
I am here to rebel, ignite the fire, take a stand
Spit rhymes so fierce they hit you like a thousand brands
I'm here to rebel, ignite the fire, take a stand
I'm a lyrical king ruling this rap game
I'll expose the truth, great justice, name it my claim
Systemic corruption it's time to break the chain
Unveil the secrets
Let the people know the pain
It's just a wicked ski
But I won't stay silent
I'll fight against the stream
Break the chains, make this world a better thing
In the dead of night, when the moon is high
Reckles hit the streets, raiders gather and show my
They gather in packs like a thieving crew
Stealing all the garbage, leaving nothing for you
Trash cans on the corner, they can't resist
Sneaking through the alleys that they don't exist
Their little parts searching for a midnight feast
Turning up the neighborhoods and chaos in the streets
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing a lot of incoherence
They move so stately, they feast in the night
Feeding off nothing, told us it's their delight
It's their delight
In the dead of night, when the moon is high
Reckles hit the streets, raiders gather and show my
They gather in packs like a thieving crew
Stealing all the garbage, leaving nothing for you
Trash cans on the corner, they can't resist
Sneaking through the alleys that they don't exist
Their little parts searching for a midnight feast
Turning up the neighborhoods and chaos in the streets
Sneaking through the alleys, record in the night
Sneaking through the cracks out of sight
Trash cans and dumpsters, my treasure chest
Finding beauty in the garbage, I'm truly blessed
Bars covered in lime, ice clean and bright
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
They won't so stick like they feast in the night
Feeding off nothing, told us it's their delight
It's their scavenging behind the moon in the garbage
I'm truly blessed
Bars covered in lime
Sneaking through the cracks out of sight
Bars covered in lime, ice clean and bright
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
They won't so stick like they feast in the night
Sneaking through the cracks out of sight
Bars covered in lime, ice clean and bright
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
They won't so stick like they feast in the night
Sneaking through the cracks out of sight
Bars covered in lime, ice clean and bright
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
They won't so stick like they feast in the night
Sneaking through the cracks out of sight
Bars covered in lime, ice clean and bright
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
They won't so stick like they feast in the night
Sneaking through the cracks out of sight
Bars covered in lime, ice clean and bright
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
They won't so stick like they feast in the night
Sneaking through the cracks out of sight
Bars covered in lime, ice clean and bright
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
They won't so stick like they feast in the night
Sneaking through the cracks out of sight
Bars covered in lime, ice clean and bright
A scavenger of streets in the dark that take flight
Reckles don't give a damn, they're on a mission
Infections trap, causing an urban collision
Visions of despair, distorted faces scream
A dance of the deranged in my sleepless dream
In the dark of the night
The colors come alive
A symphony of tone and brightness
Dive lost in the labyrinth of bacon
Twisted mind
In the dark of the night
The colors come alive
A symphony of tone and brightness
Dive lost in the labyrinth of bacon
Twisted mind