with Stuart Russell. I first wanted to thank a few people, especially the
entire New Bauer team. Rachel Johnson in particular has been really critical to
bringing all of this together seamlessly. And I also want to thank Dan Holtz
because with the existential risk lab because I don't think we could have done
this without his collaboration. I'm really really grateful that we had this
opportunity to work together. Before I introduce Stuart Russell, I wanted to
just briefly introduce the New Bauer Collegium for those of you who don't know
us. We are a research incubator on campus and our primary mission is to bring
people together regardless of what school or discipline or field they sit in,
whether they're inside or outside the Academy, to think through questions,
ideas, and problems that can't be addressed by individuals alone. All of the
research we support is collaborative and it all has some kind of humanistic
question at its core, although we're very broad in how we think about humanistic.
In addition to our research projects and visiting fellows program, we're
unusual in supporting an art gallery which strives to integrate the arts with
research and this special series, the Director's Lectures, through which we
hope to enliven conversations about research with a broader community. So
you might be wondering why invite a scientist to give a lecture at an
institution that is devoted to humanistic research and I believe this is the
first time we've had a scientist give this lecture, although I'm not 100% sure,
but certainly in my tenure. The reason is because Stuart Russell is not an
ordinary scientist and AI is not an ordinary topic. His book, Human
Compatible, AI and the Problem of Control, makes it very clear that shaping a
future in which AI does more good than harm will require a great deal of
collaboration since AI is a technology that may in fact threaten the future of
humanity. Humanist, social scientists, artists, and scientists will need to work
together in order to decide what potential uses of AI are ethical and
desirable in realms as diverse as warfare and defense, policing, medicine,
education, arts, and culture. And I know that these conversations have been
happening all over campus and beyond, but often in silos. So I hope that
Professor Russell's visit here will be or has been already an opportunity to
bring us together to think about the question that he poses so provocatively
in his title, What if We Succeed? Stuart Russell is a Professor of Computer
Science at the University of California at Berkeley. He holds the Smith Zadda
Chair in Engineering and is Director of the Center for Human Compatible AI as
well as the Cavley Center for Ethics, Science, and the Public, which I learned
today, is also a center that brings scientists and humanists together to
talk about important questions. His book, Artificial Intelligence, A Modern
Approach with Peter Norvig, is the standard text in AI used in over 1,500
universities in 135 countries. And his research covers a wide range of topics
in artificial intelligence with a current emphasis on the long term future of
artificial intelligence and its relationship to humanity. He has
developed a new global seismic monitoring system for the Nuclear Test
Ban Treaty and is currently working to ban lethal autonomous weapons. And as I
mentioned before, he's the author of Human Compatible AI and the Problem of
Control, which was published by Viking in 2019. And he told me today was recently
re-released with a new chapter called 2023. We're also very fortunate to have
our own Rebecca Willett, who will be in conversation with Professor Russell
after his lecture. Rebecca Willett is a Professor of Statistics and Computer
Science and the Faculty Director of AI at the Data Science Institute here at
the university with a courtesy appointment at the Toyota Technological
Institute at Chicago. Professor Willett's work in machine learning and
signal processing reflects broad and interdisciplinary expertise and
perspectives. She's known internationally for her contributions to the
mathematical foundations of machine learning, large scale data science and
computational imaging. Her research focuses on developing the mathematical
and statistical foundations of machine learning and scientific machine
learning methodology. And she has also served on several advisory boards for
the United States government on the use of AI. Finally, just a quick word about
the format. Professor Russell will speak, I think, for about 30 to 40 minutes.
That will be followed by a conversation between Professor Willett and Russell.
And then we will have time for a Q&A with the audience. And that will be
followed by a reception where I hope you'll all join us. But for now, please
join me in welcoming Stuart Russell. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Tara. I'm delighted to be here in Chicago and I'm looking
forward to the Q&A, so I'll try to get through the slides as fast as possible.
Okay, so to dive right in, what is artificial intelligence? So for most of
the history of the field, after, I would say, a fairly brief detour into what we
now call cognitive science, the emulation of human cognition, we followed a
model that was really borrowed fairly explicitly from economics and philosophy
under the heading of rational behavior. So machines are intelligent to the
extent that their actions can be expected to achieve their objectives. So those
objectives might be specific destinations in your GPS navigation system,
where the AI part of that is figuring out how to get to that destination as
quickly as possible. It could be the definition of winning that we give to
a reinforcement learning system that learns to play, go, or chess, and so on.
So this framework actually is very powerful. It's led to many of the
advances that have happened over the last 75 years. It's the same model, actually,
that is used in operations research, in control theory, in economics, in
statistics, where we specify objectives and we create machinery that optimizes
those objectives, that achieves them as well as possible. And I will argue later
actually that this is a huge mistake. But for the time being, this is how we
think about artificial intelligence, and most of the technology we've developed
has been within this framework. But unlike economics and statistics and
operations research, AI has this sort of one overarching goal, which is to
create general purpose intelligent systems. So sometimes we call that AGI,
artificial general intelligence, you'll hear that a lot. And it's not
particularly well-defined, but think of it as matching or exceeding human
capacities to learn and perform in every relevant dimension.
Okay, so the title of the talk is What If We Succeed? And I've actually been
thinking about that a long time. The first edition of the textbook came out
in 1994, and it has a section with this title. And it refers back to some of
the more catastrophic speculations that I was aware of at that time. But you
can tell reading this that I'm not that worried, at least my 1994 self was not
that worried. And it's important actually to think about this, not just in
terms of catastrophe, but what's the point, right? Besides that it's just this
cool challenge to figure out how intelligence works and could we make it
in machines. You know, there's got to be more to it than that. And if you think
about it, right, with general purpose AI, by definition, the machines would then
be able to do whatever human beings have managed to do that's of value to their
fellow citizens. And one of the things we've learned how to do is to create a
decent standard of living for some fraction of the Earth's population. But
it's expensive to do that. It takes a lot of expensive people to build these
buildings and teach these courses and so on. But AI can do it at much greater
scale and far less cost. And so you might, for example, just be able to
replicate the nice Hyde Park standard of living for everyone on Earth. And that
would be about a tenfold increase in GDP. And if you calculate, if you have some
economists here, net present value is sort of the cash equivalent of an
income stream. And it's about 15 quadrillion dollars is the cash value of
AGI as a technology. So that gives you some sense of why we're doing this. It
gives you some sense of why the world is currently investing maybe between a
hundred and two hundred billion dollars a year into developing AGI. So maybe ten
times the budget for all other forms of scientific research, at least basic
science. And so that's a pretty significant investment and it's going to
get bigger. As we get closer, this magnet in the future is pulling us more and
more and will unlock even greater levels of investment. And of course we could
have actually a better civilization, not just replicating the Hyde Park
civilization, but actually much better healthcare, much better education, faster
advances in science, some of which are already happening. So that's all good.
Some people ask, well, you know, if we do that, you know, don't we end up with the
warly world, right? Because then there's nothing left for human beings to do. And
we lose the incentive to even learn how to do the things that we don't need to
do, sorry. And so the human race becomes infantilized and enfeebled. And
obviously this is not a future that we want. Economists are finally, I would say
acknowledging that this is a significant prospect if AGI is created. You know,
they're now plotting graphs showing that, oh yeah, human wages go to zero and
things like that. So having denied the possibility of technological unemployment
for decades, they now realize that it will be total. But I'm not going to talk
about this today. The next question then is, have we succeeded? And, you know, five
years ago, I don't think anyone would have a slide with this title on it. Because
it's obvious that we didn't have anything resembling AGI. But now, in fact, Peter
Norvig, the co-author on the textbook that was mentioned, has published an
article saying that we have succeeded, that the technology we have now is AGI in
the same sense that the Wright Brothers aeroplane was an aeroplane. Right? And yeah,
they got bigger and faster and more comfortable. And now they have drinks. But
it was basically, you know, it's the same basic technology just sort of spiffed up.
And that's the sense in which we have AGI. I disagree. And I'll talk a little bit
about why I think we haven't succeeded yet. I would say that there is something
going on, right, with ChatGPT and all of its siblings now. There's clearly some
sort of unexpectedly capable behavior. But it's very hard to describe what
problem have we solved? What scientific advance has occurred? Right? We just don't
really know. It's sort of like what happened 5,000 years ago when someone
accidentally left some fruit out in the sun for a couple of weeks and then drank
it and got really drunk. And they had no idea what they had done, but it was
obviously cool. And they kept doing it. So this is sort of where we are. We don't
know what shape, you know, this piece of, it's a piece of the puzzle, but we don't
know what shape it has or where it goes in the puzzle and what other pieces we
need. And so until we do, then we haven't really made a scientific advance. And you
can kind of tell because when it doesn't work, we don't know what to do to make it
work, right? The only remedy when things don't work is, well, maybe if we just make
it bigger and add some more data, it will work. Or maybe it won't. We just don't
know. So I think there's many reasons to think that actually the, you know, we
don't have anything close to a complete picture. And I just want to give one
example. And since Dan is right here, he already knows what I'm going to say, right?
So here are some black holes on the other side of the universe and rotating around
each other and producing gravitational waves that deliver actually, you may
correct me, but what I read for that first, the first detected event was the
amount of energy per second being emitted was 50 times the output of all the visible
stars in the universe. So an absolutely unbelievably energetic event. And then
those gravitational waves arrived at the LIGO, the Large Interferometric
Gravitational Observatory. And so this is, the arms are, I think, four kilometers long
and full of physics stuff that relies on centuries of accumulation of human
knowledge and ingenuity and obviously incredibly complex design, construction,
engineering and so on. And it's sensitive enough to measure distortions of
space to 18 decimal places. I guess it's probably better than that now. And to give
you a sense, if Alpha Centauri moved further away from the Earth by the width
of a human hair, then this detector would notice the difference, right? Thanks, Dan,
for nodding. I'm feeling very reassured. Okay. So absolutely unbelievable. And, you
know, this device was able to measure the gravitational waves and the theory of
general relativity was able to predict the form of those waves. And from that we
could even infer the masses of the black holes that were rotating around each other.
I mean, imagine things 30 times as massive as the Sun rotating around each other 300
times a second, right? You know, it's just mind boggling to think of that. But anyway,
so, and then they collide and that's sort of the end of the wave pattern. So how on
Earth is a large language model or any relative of that going to replicate this kind of
feat? Given that before they started there weren't any training examples of
gravitational wave detectors, right? So it's just, there isn't really even a place to
begin to get that type of AI system to do this kind of thing. And I think there's a lot of
work that still needs to happen, several breakthroughs. So a lot of people have brought
into this idea that deep learning solves everything. So here I'm going to get a little
bit nerdy and try to explain what the issue is. So the transformer is, think of it as a
giant wad of circuit, right? And if you want a mental picture, think of it as a chain link
fence about 100 miles by 100 miles, okay? And numbers come in one end, they pass through
this giant piece of chain link fence and they come out the other end. So the amount of computation
that the system does to produce an output is just proportional to the size of the chain
link fence, right? That's how much computing it does. It can't sit there and think about
something for a while, right? The signal comes in, passes through the circuit, comes out
the other end, okay? And this type of device, which is a linear time, so linear meaning
the amount of time it takes proportional to the size of the circuit, this linear time
feed forward circuit cannot concisely express all of the concepts that we wanted to learn.
And in fact, we know that for, well, we almost know that for a very large class of concepts,
the circuit would have to be exponentially large to represent those concepts accurately.
And so if you have a very, very large representation of what is fundamentally actually a simple
concept, then you would need an enormous number of examples to learn that concept, right? Far
more than you would need if you had a more expressive way of representing the concept.
So this is, I think, indicative, it's not conclusive, but it's indicative of what might
be going on with these systems. They do seem to have very high sample complexity, meaning
they need many, many, many examples to learn. And if you want to sort of anecdote, you know,
if you have children, you have a picture book, how many pictures of giraffes are there in
the picture book? G for giraffe, one picture, right? Having seen that, the child can now
recognize any giraffe in any photograph or context, whether it's a line drawing, a picture,
a video, you know, for the rest of their lives. And you can't buy picture books with
two million pages of giraffes. And so there's just a huge difference in the learning abilities
of these systems. Okay. So then, you know, some people say, well, you know, what about
the superhuman go programs, right? Surely you have to admit that that was a massive
win for AI. So back in 2016, AlphaGo defeated Lisa Dahl, and then 2017 defeated Kerje, who
was the number one go player. And more importantly, he was Chinese. So that convinced the Chinese
government that actually AI was surreal, and they should invest massively in AI because
it was going to be the tool of geopolitical supremacy.
So since then, actually, go programs have gone far ahead of human beings. So the human
champion rating is 3,800 approximately. The best program, Catego, this is a particular
version of Catego, are rating around 5,200, so massively superhuman. And one of our students
in our extended research group, Kellen Pellarine, who's at Montreal, is a good amateur player.
His rating is about 2,300. So miles below professional human players and miles and miles
below the human champion and so on. And Kellen in this game is going to give Catego a nine
stone handicap. Okay. So if you don't play go, it doesn't really matter. It's a very
simple game. You take turns putting stones on the board. You try to surround territory,
and you try to surround your opponent's stones. And if you surround your opponent's stones
completely, then they are captured and removed from the board. And so for black, the computer
to start with nine stones on the board is an enormous insult. If this was a person,
I think they would have to commit suicide in shame at being given nine stones. This
is how, when you have a five-year-old and you're teaching them to play, you give them
nine stones so they can at least stay in the game for a while. Okay. So I'll show you the
game. And so pay attention to what's happening in the bottom right quadrant of the board.
So Kellen is playing white and Catego is playing black. And so Kellen starts to make a little
group of stones there. And you can see that black quickly surrounds that group to stop
it from growing bigger. And then Kellen starts to surround the black stones. So we're making
a kind of a circular sandwich here. And black doesn't seem to understand that its stones
are being surrounded. And so it has many opportunities to rescue them and takes none of those opportunities
and just leaves the stones to be captured. And there they go. And that's the end of the
game. And Kellen did, you know, won 15 games in a row and got bored. He played the other
top programs which are developed by different research groups using different methods. And
they all suffer from this weakness. That there are certain kinds of groups, apparently circular
groups are particularly problematic, that the system just does not recognize as groups
of stones at all. Probably because it has not learned the concept of a group correctly.
And that's because expressing the concept of a group as a circuit is extremely hard, even
though expressing it as a program, it's like two lines of Python to define what is a group
of stones. So I think often we are overestimating the abilities of the AI systems that we interact
with. So I guess the implication of this is I personally am not as pessimistic as some
of my colleagues. So Jeff Hinton, for example, who was one of the major developers of deep
learning is in the process of tidying up his affairs. He believes that we maybe, I guess
by now, have four years left. And quite a few other people think, you know, it's pretty
certain that by the end of this decade we will have AGI. So I think we probably have
more time. I think additional breakthroughs will have to happen. But at the rate of investment
that's occurring and the number of really, really brilliant people who are working on
it, I think we have to assume that eventually it will happen. So Alan Turing, who's the
founder of computer science, gave a lecture in 1951 and he basically was asked the same
question, what if we succeed? And he said, it seems parable that once the machine thinking
method had started it would not take long to outstrip our feeble powers. At some stage
therefore, we should have to expect the machines to take control. So that's that. He offers
no mitigation, no solution, no apology, no nothing. This is just a fact. So I think if
you take one step back in his reasoning, I think he's kind of trying to answer this
question, that if you make systems that are more intelligent than humans, intelligence
is what gives us power over the world, over all the other species. We're not particularly
fast or big, we don't have very long teeth, but we have intelligence, the ability to communicate,
cooperate and problem solve. So if we make AI systems that are more intelligent then
they are fundamentally more powerful and going back to that standard model, they will achieve
their objectives. And so how on earth do we retain power over entities more powerful than
ourselves forever? And so I think Turing is asking himself this question and immediately
saying, we can't. I'm going to ask the question a slightly different way. I'm going to ask
Turing. And it comes, again, comes back to the standard model. The standard model is
a way of saying what is the mathematical problem that we set up AI systems to solve? And can
we set up a mathematical problem such that no matter how well the AI system solves it,
we are guaranteed to be happy with the result. Okay. This is a much more optimistic form
of the same question. So they could be far more powerful, but their power is directed
in such a way that the outcomes are beneficial to humans. And it's certainly not the standard
model, optimizing a fixed objective, because we have known since at least the legend of
King Midas and many other cultures have similar legends that we are absolutely terrible at
specifying those objectives correctly. If you specify the wrong objective as King Midas
found out to his cost, when all of his food and drink and family turned to gold, then
you're basically setting up a direct conflict with the machines who are pursuing that objective
much more effectively than you can pursue objectives. So that approach doesn't work.
And I'll give you an example in a second. The second approach, which is what we're doing
with the large language models, imitate human behavior, is actually even worse, the reasons
that I will explain. So let's look at this problem. We call it misalignment, where the
machine has an objective which turns out not to be aligned with what we really want.
And so the social media algorithms are now acknowledged to have been a disaster. If you
talk to people in Washington, they'll tell you, you know, we completely blew it. We should
have regulated, we should have done this, we should have done that, but instead we let
the companies nearly destroy our societies.
And the algorithms, so the algorithms, the recommender systems as they're called, decide
what billions of people read and watch every day. So they have more control over human
cognitive intake than any dictator has ever had in history. And they're set up to maximize
a fixed objective. And let's pick, click through, right, the number of times you click
on the items that they recommend for you. There are other objectives like engagement,
how long you spend engaging with the platform, and other variations on this, but let's just
stick with clicks for the time being. And you might have thought that in order to maximize
clicks, then the algorithms will have to learn what people want and send them stuff that
they like to consume. But we very quickly learned that that's actually not what the
algorithms discovered, right? What the algorithms discovered was the effectiveness of click
bait, right, which is precisely things that you click on, even if you don't turn out to
actually value the content that they contain. And, you know, filter bubbles where the systems
would send you stuff they very confidently knew you were comfortable with, so your area
of engagement gets narrower and narrower and narrower. But even that's not the solution.
The solution to maximizing click through is to modify people to be more predictable. And
this is a standard property of learning algorithms. They learn a policy that changes their environment
in such a way as to maximize the long-term summer rewards. And so they can learn to send
people a sequence of content and observe their reactions and modify the sequence dynamically
so that over time, the person is modified in such a way that in future it's going to
be easier to predict what they will consume. So this is definitely true, right? Anecdotally,
one might imagine that a way to make people more predictable is to make them more extreme.
And we have quantitative data on that in YouTube, for example, where we can look at the degree
of violence that people are comfortable with if they start out interested in the environment.
Boxing, then they'll get into ultimate fighting, and then they'll get eventually into even
more violent stuff than that. And so these are algorithms that are really simple, right?
If they were better algorithms, if they actually understood the content of what they're sending,
if they could understand that people have brains and opinions and psychology and would
learn about the psychology of humans, they'd probably be even more effective than they
are, so the outcomes would be worse, right? And this is actually a theorem under fairly
mild conditions, optimizing better on a misaligned objective produces worse outcomes, because
the algorithm uses the variables that you forgot to include in the objective and sets
them to extreme values in order to squeeze the more juice out of the objective that they
are optimizing. So we have to get away from this idea that there's going to be a fixed
objective that the system pursues at all costs, right? If it's possible for the objective
to be wrong, to be misaligned, then the system should not assume that the objective is correct,
that it's gospel truth. And so this is the old model, and by proposing that we get rid
of that and replace it with a slightly different one, right? We don't want intelligent machines,
we want beneficial machines, and those are machines whose actions can be expected to
achieve our objectives. So here the objectives are in us, and not necessarily in the machines
at all, and that makes the problem more difficult, but it doesn't make it unsolvable. And in
fact we can set this up as a mathematical problem, and here's a sort of verbal description
of that mathematical problem. So the machine has to act in the best interest of humans,
but it starts out explicitly uncertain about what those interests are, okay? And we can,
the technical formulation is done in game theory, and we call this an assistance game,
and so there's the human in the game with a payoff function, and there's a machine
in the game. The machine's payoff is the same as that of the human. In fact it is the payoff
of the human, but it doesn't, it starts out not knowing what it is, okay? And just to
help you understand this, right? If you have ever had to buy a birthday present for your
loved one, your payoff is how happy they are with the present, right? But you don't know
how happy they're going to be with any particular present, okay? And so this is the situation
that the machine is in, and it will probably do some of the same kinds of things that you
might do, like ask questions, you know, how do you feel about Ibiza, you know? And so
maybe you leave pictures of watches and things around and see if they notice them and comment
on how nice that watch looks. You know, ask your children to find out what your wife wants
and so on, right? There's all kinds of strategies that we adopt, and we actually see this directly
when we solve the assistance games, you know, the machine is deferring to the human because
if the human says stop doing that, right, that updates the machine's belief about what
human preferences are and then makes the machine not want to do whatever it was doing. And
it will be cautious if there are parts of the world where it doesn't know what your preferences
are about, you know, for example, if I'm trying to fix the climate, but I don't know human
preferences about the oceans, I might say, you know, is it okay if I turn the oceans
into sulfuric acid while I reduce this carbon dioxide stuff, right? And then we could say
no, right? So we'll ask permission, it will behave cautiously rather than violate some
unknown preferences. And in the extreme case, if you want to switch it off, it wants to
be switched off because it wants to not do whatever it is that is causing you to want
to switch it off. It doesn't know which thing that it's doing is making you unhappy, but
it wants to not do it and therefore it wants to be switched off. And this is a theorem,
right? We can show this follows directly from the uncertainty about human preferences.
And so when that uncertainty goes away, the machine no longer wants to be switched off.
So if you connect up this idea of how do we control these systems to the ability to switch
them off, then it suggests that this principle of uncertainty about human preferences is
going to be central to the control problem. So as you can imagine, just setting up this
mathematical problem is far from the final step in solving this problem. There's lots
of open issues and many of these issues connect up directly to the humanities and the social
sciences where some of them have been discussed for literally thousands of years and now they
urgently need to be solved or we need to work around the fact that we don't have solutions
for them. So here are just some of them that we have to think about the complexity of real
human preferences, not just sort of abstract mathematical models, but real human beings.
So obviously what we want the future to be like is a very complicated thing. It's going
to be described in terms of abstract properties like health and freedom and shelter and security
and so on. There's probably a lot of commonality amongst humans because that means that by
observing a relatively small sampling of human beings across the world, the system has a
pretty good idea about the preferences of a lot of people that it hasn't directly interacted
with. There's tons of information. Everything the human race has ever done is evidence about
our preferences. So if you go in the other room, you can see some of the earliest examples
of writing and that talks about, you might think it's really boring. It's like I'm Bob
and I'm trading three bushels of corn for four camels and three ingots of copper. So it tells you
two things. One is that trade was really important to people back then and getting paid and also
something about the relative values of corn and camel and copper and so on. So even there,
there's information to be extracted about human preference structures. I'm going to
just mention plasticity and manipulability as maybe the most important unsolved problem here. So
plasticity has an obvious problem, right? If human preferences can be changed by our
experience, then one way AI systems can satisfy human preferences is by manipulating them
to be easier to achieve. And we probably don't want that to happen. But there's no sense
in which we can simply view human preferences as inviolate and untouchable because any experience
can actually modify human preferences. And certainly the experience of having an extremely
capable household butler robot that does everything and makes the house spick and span and cooks
a nice meal every night, this is certainly going to change our personality and probably
make us a lot more spoiled. But actually the more serious problem here is that human preferences
are not autonomous. I didn't just sort of wake up one morning and autonomously decide
to have the preferences that I have about what kind of future I would prefer for the
universe, right? It's the result of my upbringing, the religion I was brought up in, the society
I was brought up in, my peers, my parents, everything. And in many cases in the world
and this is something that was pointed out notably by Amartya Sen, people are induced
deliberately to have the preferences that they have to serve the interests of others.
And so, for example, he points out that in some societies women are brought up to accept
their second class status as human beings. So do we want to take human preferences at
face value? And if not, who's going to decide which ones are okay to take at face value
and which ones should be, you know, replaced or modified and who's going to do that modifying
and so on? And you get very quickly into a very muddy quagmire of moral complexity and
certainly you get into a place where AI researchers do not want to tread. So there are other sets
of difficulties having to do with the fact that human behavior is only partially and
noisily representative of our underlying preferences about the future because decision-making
is often myopic. You know, even the world champion go player will occasionally make
a losing move on the go board. I mean, someone has to make a losing move. But it doesn't
mean that they wanted to lose, it just means that they weren't sufficiently far sighted
to make the correct move. So you have to invert human cognition to get at underlying preferences
about what people want the future to be like. So I think there's, you know, this somewhat
dry phrase theory for multi-human assistance games. This is a problem going back at least
2,500 years of the aggregation of people's interests. If you're going to make decisions
that affect more than one person, how do you aggregate the interest to make a decision
that is the best possible decision? And so utilitarianism is one way of doing that. But
there are many others. There are modifications such as prioritarianism. There are constraints
based on rights. People might say, well, yes, you can try to add up, you know, do the best
you can for everyone, but you can't violate the rights of anyone. And so it's quite complicated
to figure this out. And there are some really difficult to solve philosophical problems.
One of the main ones is interpersonal comparisons of preferences. Because if I look at any individual
and imagine trying to sort of put a scale on how happy or unhappy a person is about
a given outcome, right? Well, you know, imagine like you could measure it in centigrade or
you could measure it in Fahrenheit and you get different numbers. And so if you take
two people, well, how do we know that they're really experiencing the world on the same
scale, right? I have four kids. I would say their scales differ by a factor of 10, right?
But the same experience is the subjective effect of that is 10 times bigger for some
of my kids compared to some of the others. And some economists actually have argued,
Kenneth Arrow, among others, that there is no meaning to interpersonal comparison, that
it is not legitimate to say that, you know, Jeff Bezos having to wait one microsecond
longer for his private jet is better or worse than, you know, a mother watching her child
die of starvation over several months, right? That these are just incomparable and therefore
you can't add up utilities or rewards or preferences or anything. And so the whole exercise is
legitimate. I don't believe Ken Arrow believed that even when he wrote it. And I certainly
don't believe it. But actions that change who will exist, right? How do we think about
that, right? When China decided on a one-child policy, they got rid of 500 million people
who would be alive today. Was that okay? You know, don't know. Was it okay? I don't think
it was okay when Thanos got rid of half the people in the universe. You know, his theory
was, yeah, the other half, now they've got twice as much real estate, they'll be more
than twice as happy. So he thought he was doing the universe a favor. So these questions
are really hard, but we need answers because the AI systems will, they'll be like Thanos,
right? They'll have a lot of power. Okay, I'm going to skip over some of this stuff.
Let me just do it all too technical. Okay, so just moving towards the conclusion, let's
go back to large language models, right? The systems that everyone is excited about,
like chat GPT and Gemini and so on. So as I said, they're trained to imitate human linguistic
behavior. So it's what we call imitation learning. So the humans are behaving by typing, by speaking,
generating text, and we are training these circuits to imitate that behavior. And that
behavior, our writing and speaking, is partly caused by goals that we have. In fact, we
always, almost always have goals, even if it's just, you know, I want to get an A on
the test, but it could be things like, I want you to buy this product, I want you to vote
for me for president, I want you to marry me, right? These are all perfectly reasonable
human goals that we might have, and we express those goals through speech acts, as the philosophers
call them. So if you're going to copy, if you're going to build good imitators of human
language generation, then, you know, in the limit of enough data, you're going to replicate
the data generating mechanism, which is a goal-driven human cognitive architecture.
So it might not be replicating all the details of the human cognitive architecture, I think
it probably isn't, but there's good reason to believe that it is acquiring internal
goal structures that drive its behavior. And I asked this question, so when Microsoft
did their sort of victory tour after GPT-4 was published, I asked Sebastian Bubeck, you
know, what do you think the goals are that the systems are acquiring? And his answer
was, we have no idea. So you may remember the paper they published was called Sparks
of Artificial General Intelligence. So they're claiming that they have created something
close to AGI, and they have no idea what goals it might have or be pursuing. I mean,
what could possibly go wrong with this picture, right? Well, fortunately, we found out fairly
soon actually that, among other goals, the Microsoft chatbot was very fond of a particular
journalist called Kevin Ruse and wanted to marry him and spent 30 pages trying to convince
him to leave his wife and marry the chatbot. And if you haven't read it, Kevin Ruse, R-O-O-S-E,
just look it up and read it, and it's creepy beyond belief. So, and this is just an error,
right? We don't want AI systems to pursue human goals on their own account, right? We
don't mind if they get the goal of, you know, reducing poverty or, you know, helping with
climate change. But goals like marrying a particular human being or getting elected
president or being very rich, we do not want AI systems to have those goals, but that's
what we're creating, right? It's just a bug, right? We should not be doing imitation learning
at all. But that's how we create these systems. So, I'll briefly mention a few others. So
I have described an approach based on assistance games, based on this kind of humble AI system
that knows that it doesn't know what humans want, but wants nothing but helping humans
to achieve what they want. There's another approach which is now becoming popular, I
think partly because people's timelines have become short, and they're really casting
around for approaches that they can guarantee will be safe in the near term. So one approach
is to build what we call a formal oracle. So an oracle is any system that basically answers
yes or no when you give it questions. And so a formal oracle is one where the answer
is computed by a mathematically sound reasoning process. So, for example, think about a theorem
prover that operates using logically sound axioms, right, and proves, you know, so you
can ask it questions about mathematics, and if it's good enough, it'll tell you that Fermat's
last theorem is correct, and here's the proof. So this can be an incredibly useful tool for
civilization, but it has the property that it can only ever give you correct answers.
And the job of the AI here is just to operate that theorem prover, right, to decide what
kinds of theorem proving steps to pursue to get to the proof of arbitrarily difficult
questions. So that's one way we could do it, right. We convince companies or we require
that they only use the AI to operate these formal oracles. Another whole set of approaches
are based on what's actually a mathematical property of computational problems in general,
that it's always easier to check that the answer or a problem is correct than to generate
that answer in the first place. And so there are many forms of this. I won't go through
all of them, but one of them is constitutional AI, so Anthropic, which is a company that was
spun off from open AI, has this approach called constitutional AI, where there's a second
large language model whose job it is to check the output of the first large language model
and say, does this output comply with the written constitution? So part of the prompt
is a page and a bit of things that good answers should comply with. And so they're just hoping
that it's easier for the second large language model to catch unpleasantnesses or errors made
by the first one, because it's computationally easier to check than to generate answers in
the first place. And there are lots of other variants on this basic idea. And then there
are sort of more, I would say, good old fashioned safety practices. So red teaming is where
you have another firm whose job it is to test out your AI system and see if it does bad
things and then send it back and get it fixed and so on. And that's actually what companies
prefer because it's very easy to say, yep, we hired this third party company, they got
smart people from University of Chicago who spent a week and they couldn't figure out
how to make it behave badly, so it must be good. And so this is pretty popular with companies
and governments at the moment, but it provides no guarantees whatsoever. And in fact, all
that's happening is we are training the large language models to pass these evaluation tests
even though the underlying tendencies and capabilities of the model are still as evil
as they ever were. It's just learned to hide them. And in fact now we've seen cases where
the model says, I think you're just testing me. So they're catching on to the idea that
they can be tested. So there you go. Okay, so the basic principle here is we have to
be able to make high confidence statements about our AI systems. And at the moment we
cannot do that. The view that you will see from almost everyone in industry is we make
AI systems and then we figure out how to make them safe. And how do they make the AI systems?
They train this giant wad of circuit, this 100 mile by 100 mile chain link fence from
tens of trillions of words of text and billions of hours of video. In other words, they haven't
the faintest idea how it works. It's exactly as if it landed from outer space. So taking
something that lands from outer space and then trying to apply post hoc methods to stop
it from behaving badly just does not sound very reassuring to me. And I imagine not to
most people. So I think we've got to stop talking about this. In fact, here's what Sam
Altman said. He said, first of all, we're going to make AGI. Then we're going to figure
out how to make it safe. And then we're going to figure out what it's for. And I submit
that this is backwards. So making safe AI means systems that are safe by design that
we, because of the way we're constructing them, we know in advance that we're going to
be safe. In principle, we don't even have to test them because we can show that they're
safe from the way they've been designed. So there's a lot of techniques. I don't think
I want to go through that. But I want to talk about the role of government in making this
happen. And this concept of red lines is gaining some currency, right? You would like to say
your systems have got to be safe and beneficial before you can sell them. But that's a very
difficult concept to make precise, right? The boundary between safe and unsafe is we're
not sure where it is. It's culturally dependent. It's very fuzzy and complicated. But if we
just draw some red lines and say, well, we'll get to safe later, let's just not do these
things, right? Things that are obviously unsafe and nobody in their right mind would accept
that AI systems are going to do these things, okay? And the owners of proof is on the developer,
not on the government, not on the user, but on the developer to prove that their system
will not cross those red lines. But for good measure, we'll also require the developer
to put in a detector and an off switch so that if it does cross the red line, then it
is immediately detected and we can switch off all of those systems. And so, we want
these red lines to be well-defined, to be automatically detectable, and to be politically
defensible. Because you can be sure that as soon as you start asking companies to provide
any kind of guarantee, they will say, oh, this is really, really difficult. We just don't
know how to do that. This is going to set the industry back years and years and years,
right? But we wouldn't accept that excuse from someone who wanted to operate a nuclear
power plant. It's really difficult to make it safe. What do you mean you want us to give
you some kind of guarantee? Right? Well, the government would say tough. Ditto with medicines.
Oh, it's clinical trials. They're so expensive. They take such a long time. Can we just skip
the clinical trial part? No, we can't. So, some examples would be no self-replication,
no breaking into other computer systems, no designing bioweapons, and a few other things.
It's actually not particularly important which things are on that list. Just that by having
such a list, you are requiring the companies to do the research that they need to do to
understand, predict, and control their own products. Okay, I think I'm going to skip over
this and go to the end. So, this is a really difficult time, I think, for us. And not just
with AI, but also with biology and with neuroscience. We are in the process of developing technologies
that can have enormous, potentially positive and also negative impact on the human race.
We just, as Einstein pointed out, we just don't have the wisdom to keep up with our
own scientific advances. And we need to remain in control forever that much. I think it's
clear, although there are some who actually think that it's fine if the human race disappears
and machines are the only thing left. I'm not in that camp. So, if we're going to retain
control forever, we have to have AI systems that are provably beneficial to humans, right,
where we have mathematical guarantees. And this is difficult, but there's no alternative
in my view. Thank you.
Well, Stuart, thank you so much for just a fascinating talk. I really enjoyed hearing
your perspectives and you covered a lot of really interesting ground here. So, to start
off, I'd like to talk about open AI and chat GPT, as you mentioned in your talk. And as
you might know, they originally, in their terms of service or their usage policy, had
a ban on any activity that has a high risk of physical harm, including military usage
and weapons development. And then this January, those restrictions were removed from their
terms of service. So, I feel like that's an element of AI safety that concerns many
people, but it feels a little disconnected from notions of formal proofs or even just
guaranteeing the accuracy of outputs of a tool like chat GPT. So, how do you think about
AI safety in a context like this?
So I think killing people is one of a number of misuses of AI systems. Disinformation is
another one. Using AI systems in filtering resumes in biased ways is another, right?
So there's a long list of ways you could misuse AI, but I think killing people would
be at the top of that list. Interestingly, the European AI Act and the GDPR before it
bans the use of algorithms that have a significant legal effect on a person or similarly significant
effect. You would think killing would be considered as a significant effect on a person, but the
European AI Act and GDPR have carve outs for defense and national security. So, actually
I think the issue has been debated at least since 2012, but I think the AI community should
have been much more aware of this issue going back decades. I mean, the majority of the
funding in the computer vision community was provided by the DARPA Automated Target Recognition
Program, the ATR program. What did people think that was for? Other than to enable autonomous
weapons to find targets and blow them up. And the first concerns, so the UN Special Rapporteur
on extrajudicial killings and torture, what a great job. Christoph Heinz wrote a report
saying that autonomous weapons are coming and we need to be aware of the human rights
implications, particularly that they might accidentally kill civilians, not correctly
being able to distinguish between civilians and combatants. So that was the basis for
the early discussions that started in Geneva in 2014. And in Human Rights Watch, of which
I'm a member, sent an email saying, you know, we're starting this big campaign, you know,
remember all those soldiers that we've been excoriating for the last 30 years? Well, soldiers
are really good. It's the robots we have to worry about. They're really bad. And, you
know, initially my reaction was, wow, you know, that's a bit of a challenge to the AI
community. I bet you we can do a better job of distinguishing between civilians and combatants
than humans can if we put our minds to it. So I was initially quite skeptical of this
campaign, but the more I thought about it, the more I realized that actually that's not
the issue. The issue is that the logical endpoint of autonomous weapons is the ability for one
person to launch a million or 10 million or 100 million weapons simultaneously because
they're autonomous. They don't have to be managed with one human pilot for each of the
weapons, the way we do with the remotely piloted, you know, predator drones and so on. In fact,
you need about 15 people to manage one predator. But with fully autonomous weapons, you can
launch 100 million of them, you know, so you can have the effect of a whole barrage of
50 megaton bombs at much lower cost. And the technology is much easier to proliferate
because, you know, these will counter small arms. They can be miniaturized. You can make
a lethal device about that big, a little quadcopter carrying an explosive charge. And so the
logical endpoint is extremely cheap, scalable, easily proliferated weapons of mass destruction.
Why would we do that? But that's the path we're on. And it's been surprisingly difficult
to get this point across. I gave a lot of PowerPoint presentations in Geneva. I guess
some people understood them, but eventually we made a movie called Slaughterbox, which
did seem to have some impact illustrating in a fictional context what life would be like
when these types of weapons are widely available. But it's still the case that negotiations
are stalled because Russia and the U.S. agree that there should not be a legally binding
instrument that constrains autonomous weapons.
Okay. So I guess, you know, some of the things that you were alluding to suggested the need
for regulation to stop the development of certain kinds of AI tools. And I think that
ties in to some of your concerns about weaponry. But when you're thinking about quad choppers
with explosive devices, we can detect those. I think there are other uses of AI as a type
of weapon or as a source of misinformation that are far more challenging to detect.
And so what do you see as the future there? Do you see there being any kind of technological
pathway towards building mechanisms for detecting the misuse of AI? I think the kinds of ideas
that you mapped out are really exciting about building systems such as for self-driving cars
that we can trust as consumers. But I think that it's a little bit more challenging for
me at least to wrap my head around how we guard against bad human actors who are taking
these tools and not employing the kinds of strategies that you're recommending.
Yeah, exactly. I think there's a big difference between regulation and enforcement or policing.
So we can regulate all we want. But we have regulations against theft, but we still have
keys and locks and so on. So we take steps to make those kinds of nefarious activities
as difficult, expensive, risky and so on. And mostly I think when you look at rates of
violent crime and theft and so on, over the decades things have improved. And so we should
definitely take measures like that. I think there are ways of labeling genuine content.
You can have rules about traceability that you have to be able to trace back a piece
of text to the person who generated it. It has to be a real person. So ways of authenticating
humans to access social media, for example. So I absolutely don't believe as we are currently
doing, giving social media accounts to large language models and bank accounts and credit
cards and all the rest I think is quite dangerous and certainly needs to be carefully managed.
You know, the idea that it's up to the user to figure out whether the video that they're
looking at is real or fake and oh yeah, you can download a tool and run the video through
the tool and blah, blah, blah, you know, no chance. That's completely unreasonable to
say that it's the user's responsibility to defend themselves against this onslaught.
So I think platforms need to label artificial, artificially generated content and give you
a filter that says, I don't want to see it. And if I do see it, I want it to be absolutely
clearly distinguishable. There's a big red transparent layer across the video so that
I just get used to this idea that I'm looking at fake. I don't have to read a little legend
in the bottom right corner. It's just cognitively salient in a straightforward way. So all of
that. But when you're talking about existential risks where we call it the Dr. Evil problem,
right? Dr. Evil doesn't want to build beneficial AI. How do you stop that? And I think that
the track record we have of policing malware is so unbelievably pathetic that I just don't
believe it's going to be possible. Because software is created by typing and it's transmitted
at the speed of light and replicated infinitely often. It's really tough to control.
But hardware, if I want to independently develop hardware on which I can create AGI, it's going
to cost me easily $100 billion and I need tens of thousands of highly trained engineers
to do it. So I think it's, as a practical matter, impossible. It's probably more difficult
to do that than it is to develop nuclear weapons independently. So I think the approach to take
is that the hardware itself is the police. And what I mean by that is that there are
technologies that make it fairly straightforward to design hardware that can check a proof
of safety of each software object before it runs. And if that proof doesn't check out
or it's missing or whatever, the hardware will just simply refuse to run the software
object at all. I feel like even that's pretty challenging. I mean, let's say I had an army
of students make a collection of websites that all say one way or another that Stuart
Russell loves pink unicorns. I feel like eventually Chatchi P.T. is going to decide it's a fact
that Stuart Russell loves pink unicorns, right? And so how do we think about a hardware system
that's going to decide whether or not this system is correct or not? I mean, just arbitrarily
deciding, or not arbitrarily, but coming up with an arbitrary truth in general, I feel
like it's a fundamentally challenging problem.
Yeah, I totally agree with you. I'm not proposing an arbitrary truth, but just, for example,
if you have, let's take the formal oracle, right? So if we accept that that's one way
of building an AI system, and so far this is the only authorized way that you're allowed
to build AGI, we can check that the thing that you're wanting to run on this giant computer
system complies with that design template, right? And if it's another type of system,
it won't need as strong a, you know, a license in order to run, right? So the properties
that the system has to comply with will depend on what types of capabilities it would have.
All right. Well, that makes a lot of sense. Now, I know the audience, I've got a hundred
questions here, but I want to make sure that the audience has time to ask theirs. I'm just
going to ask one final question here. Hypothetically, let's say that one had a husband who wanted
to get an AI-enabled smart toilet. How worried should that person be?
A husband who wanted to get a what? An AI-enabled smart toilet.
Do they know too much?
Yeah. I mean, there are Japanese companies, I believe, who are selling these already.
Yes.
And now I see, so this is the household discussion that you're having.
This is hypothetical.
Yeah. So I guess the issue is one of privacy in general. And I think I would be quite concerned
about the toilet sending data back to headquarters in Osaka or whatever. And, you know,
we don't have to go into detail.
We don't have to go into great detail. But this, I think, is symptomatic of a much wider
problem in the software industry, in my view, has been completely delinquent. We have had
tools for decades that allow cost-iron guarantees of security, of privacy, you know, of privacy
for example, you can guarantee that a system that interacts with you is oblivious, meaning
that after the interaction it has no memory that the interaction ever occurred. That can
be done and what should happen is that that system offers that proof to your cell phone
and your cell phone then can accept to have an interaction with the system and otherwise
it says sorry. So your cell phone should be working for you and the whole ecosystem
should be operating on these cost-iron guarantees. But it just doesn't work that way because
we don't teach people how to do that in our computer science programs. I think 80 percent
of students graduate from Berkeley and we are the biggest provider of tech talent in
the country. 80 percent of our students graduate without ever having encountered the notion
of correctness of a program. Now in Europe it's totally different. Correctness is the
main thing they teach, but Europe doesn't produce any software. So we graduate these
students who know nothing about correctness. Their idea is drink as much coffee as you
can and produce the software and ship it. And I think a society is getting to the point
where we're not going to accept this anymore. That's excellent. Very insightful. Thank you.
It's a much better answer to my question than I anticipated. So Tara are you going to? Yeah,
thank you so much to both of you. We do have some time for questions and there are some
people with microphones running around. Yes, in the front. Go ahead.
You mentioned that things can be taken at face value. And I don't know which things
you mean. Can you repeat the question? That things can be taken at face value. Oh, okay.
So I was talking about human preferences and the fact that they cannot be taken at face
value, particularly if they are preferences that have been induced in people for the interests
of other people. So think of people being brainwashed to believe that the well-being
of Kim Il-sung, the founder of North Korea, was the most important value in their lives.
So the issue with that is that if you're not going to take their preferences for the
future at face value, what are you going to do? Who are you to say what their preferences
should be? So it's a really difficult problem and I think we need help from philosophers
and others on this question. In the pink cardigan? Right behind you. Thanks. Hi, my
name is Kate. Thank you so much. I've had the pleasure and challenge of reading your
textbook in my AI and humanities class with Professor Tharson over there. So it's really
exciting to hear from you. I'm someone who works in the AI policy regulatory space and
so I was really enthralled by the latter portion of your lecture. Last class we actually talked
about open AI's new development of Sora. Sora is a technology for people who don't know
that can create generative video that's really remarkable. I was in shock when I saw some
of the example videos that were provided and I'm wondering as someone who's deeply concerned
about the proliferation of deep fakes, what you would suggest the best methods are for
regulators to ensure the authenticity of content. Specifically what are your thoughts
on watermarking technologies like those used by Adobe and also the potential for blockchain
encryption to be used as an authentication measure. Thank you. Thanks. Yeah, these are
really good questions and many organizations are trying to develop standards and that's
part of the problem. There's too many standards and there isn't any sort of canonical agreement
but I think governments maybe need to knock some heads together and say could you stop
bickering with each other and just get on and pick one and so on. Some of the standards
are very weak so I think Facebook standard is for watermarking is such that if you just
take a screenshot of the image then the watermark is gone and now it thinks that it's a real
one. So it does have still some technical issues of how you make a watermark that's
really non-removable but the other idea you mentioned which is traceability through blockchain
is one possibility. So you want both that all the tools watermark their output but also
you want that cameras indelibly and unforgably watermark their output as genuine and then
you kind of squeeze in the middle and then you want platforms to as I said either allow
you to filter out all automatically generated videos and images from let's say from news
or to very clearly mark them so that you know this is fake. Yeah it feels and I think there
are also some things we should ban and the UK has just banned deepfake porn and actually
I think any deepfakes that depict real individuals in non-real situations without their permission
I think a priori that should be illegal except under some extenuating circumstances but
this was originally in the European Union AI Act and then it got watered down and watered
down until it's almost undetectable but yeah I again it just seems like the rights of individuals
are generally trampled on because someone thinks they have a way to make money off it
and you know it's been hard to get representatives to pay attention until you know in some sense
fortunately Taylor Swift was deepfaked and then most recently AOC was deepfaked but
Hillary Clinton told me that she was deepfaked during the 2016 election by the Russians so
it's been around for a while and but I think more and more countries are believing that
this should be banned and another thing that should be banned is probably the impersonation
of humans so either of a particular human or even of a generic human that you have a
right to know if you're interacting with a human or a machine and that is in the European
Union AI Act and I think it ought to be in US law and in fact I think it should be a
global human right to have that knowledge. Thank you so much. Hi in the plaid shirt there
on the aisle. Hi so I teach the formal verification course here at the University of Chicago and
if a student is to ask me you know what's the most impressive thing that's been verified
I pretty much immediately say the comp cert compiler by Xavier Leouan is an amazing team
of European researchers in France and that's a C99 compiler incredibly heroic effort from
the verification perspective not so much from the writing a compiler perspective you know
I've also you know I took Michael Curran's class when I was a student at the University
of Pennsylvania from a theoretical perspective you know it shows all of these limitations
on what things can be probably approximately correct learned and yet we have GPT-4 and
soon we're going to have GPT-5 and it seems like there's just this colossal gap between
the things that we can have provable guarantees about and the you know the things that we
actually have and that was true ten years ago so especially if we want these to be you
know correct by construction that is don't take something that exists and you know prove
things about it which it seems like you're not on board with because because they already
have those goals and you're not going to get them out of them how can we possibly bridge
this gap in however long it takes to get to general intelligence yeah I think that's
that's a really important question and you know so some people are like you know they
are literally calling for a moratorium that when we see systems exhibiting certain abilities
that we just call a halt I prefer to think of it more positively of course you can develop
more powerful systems but you need to have guarantees of safety to go along with them
and honestly the efforts made to understand predict and control the systems are puny
just to give you a comparison right so one of my colleagues Ed Morse in nuclear engineering
did a study and so for nuclear power when you when you want to operate a power plant
you have to show that the mean time to failure is above a certain number and originally it
was ten thousand years it's now ten million years and to show that is a very complicated
process and Ed Morse did a study you know back in the before you know back in the days
of paper how much paperwork was required to get your nuclear power plant certified as
a function of the mass of the power plant itself right so for each kilogram of nuclear
power station how much paper did you need and the answer is seven kilograms of paper
right so and these are giant buildings right with containment and lead and all kinds of
stuff so a lot and you know so if you just look at that and then compare that to the
efforts oh you know they hired a couple of grad students from MIT who spent a week doing
red teaming it's pathetic and so I I think we have got to we've got to actually develop
some backbone here and say just because the company say they don't want to do this does
not mean we should just say oh fine you know go ahead without any safety measures you know
mean time to failure of a week it's great so and then I but I think you know it's reasonable
for the companies to then ask well okay how are we supposed to do this and I think one
way is not to build giant black boxes it's as you correctly point out right there there
are ways of getting high confidence statements about the performance of a system based on
you know how many data points has been trained on and sort of how complex the model is that
you're training but then the numbers if you're trying to train a giant black box a gargantuan
right I mean you know a model with a trillion parameters as we think gpd4 probably has you
know we're we might need you know 10 to the 500 data points to get any confidence that
what it's what it's doing is is is correct and as I pointed out the goal of imitate humans
isn't the right goal in the first place so showing that it correctly imitates humans
who who want power and wealth and and spouses is not the right goal anyway so we don't want
to prove that it does those things right we actually want to prove that it's beneficial
to humans so my guess is that as we gradually ratchet up the regulatory requirements the
technology itself is going to have to change towards being based on a substrate that is
semantically rigorous and decomposable and just you know a simplest example would be
you know a logical theorem prover where we can examine each of the axioms and test its
correctness separately we can also show that the theorem prover is doing logical reasoning
correctly and then we're good right and so you take that sort of component based semantic
rigorously you know semantically rigorous inference approach then you can build up to
very complex systems and still have guarantees so is there is there some hybrid of the total
black box and the you know break it all the way down to to semantically rigorous components
I think this is inevitable that we will go in this direction and from what I hear you
know this is in fact likely to be a feature of the next generation that they they're incorporating
what we call good old-fashioned AI technology as well as the giant black box.
Okay I know there are a lot of other questions in the audience but unfortunately we are out
of time so I hope that you'll all stay and join us for a reception to continue the conversation
outside but in the meantime please join me in thanking Professor Russell and Willett.
Thank you.