So, this is the philosophy of Max Scheller, introduction to the life of Max Scheller.
He was a German social and ethical philosopher.
He was born in Munich on August 22, 1874.
His mother was Jewish and his father a Lutheran.
However, he joined the Roman Catholic Church maybe because of its concept of love,
one of the concepts that Max Scheller developed in his philosophy.
He studied medicine and philosophy in Munich and in Berlin
and he received his doctorate at Vienna University in 1897.
Or he taught from 900, the year 900 up to 1906.
In 1901, Scheller became a lecturer at the University of Vienna
and stayed there until that particular year 1906.
So, from 1907 to 1910, he was professor at Munich
and met some of the disciples of Kusser.
And with their influence, his thinking turned to phenomenology.
He became acquainted with expanding phenomenological movement
but he kept a notably independent position from phenomenology.
In 1910, he retired from teaching and retired to Berlin
and wrote his major works.
In 1917, he joined the German Foreign Office
as a diplomat in Geneva and at the Hague.
And in 1919, he became professor and chair of philosophy
and sociology at the University of Cologne.
During this period of productivity, which ended around 1921,
he became renowned in Germany and elsewhere
for an unusual amount of publications.
Perhaps one of the most prolific writers
of the phenomenological movement is Max Scheller,
second to Edmund Musser.
After that, his favorite worldwide proportion
documented by the many invitations extended to him
to lecture in Paris, in Japan, in Russia,
and in the United States.
In 1920, he became a pacifist
and repudiated the horrors of war
and was converted to Roman Catholicism.
But about 1924,
he turned to a more pantheistic view of man in the world
and left Catholicism.
In early 1928, he went to the University of Frankfurt
where he also lectured there.
And he died on May 1928.
His widow was the devoted curator
of thousands of post-humans manuscripts
until she passed away in 1969.
As a phenomenologist, Scheller sought to discover
the essence of mental attitudes
and the relation to their objects,
ating that he will develop
in his major work, therefore, Malismus.
He differed from Musser in his readiness to assign
an independently real status to the objects.
Remember that Musser
took objects to be
the intentional objects
of our consciousness.
At the development of his thought,
the first period of Scheller's thought
centered on the incontrovertible value
of the individual person and value ethics
centered on the non-formal or material ethics
which is opposed to the formal ethics proposed
by Immanuel Kant.
This position of Max Scheller
is founded in his major work
on formalism
or formalism in ethics
and non-formal ethics of values
a new attempt toward the foundation
of ethical personalism.
That's the entire title of his work.
In the first part of his value ethics
he established the values,
he established that values are correlates
of three types of feelings.
Feelings in the body, feelings of life
and personal feelings.
Moral experience cannot be divorced
from feeling values as such.
And in the second part
he showed that each person was a unique
self-value.
Personal self-value must be accounted for
in all variable moral situations.
So here in the first part of his
ethics and his formalismos
established the notion of values.
Values as objects of our emotions
of our feelings.
But in doing that
he also criticized the formal ethics
of Immanuel Kant.
And we're going to discuss that later.
So in the second part
of this value ethics
was on the nature of the person.
The exemplary persons.
The nature or the theory
of the nature of the person
is a new and most interesting analysis.
The series was also developing
a kind of ethical personalism.
He showed that our being a person
is the form of our mind
and our consciousness.
No matter whether the mind
or the consciousness
are understood to be human,
divine, or just fictional.
We developed his idea
of the ideal moral person.
However, in the second period
of his career
after writing the formalismos
Sheller developed a more comprehensive
anthropology
that works on the vitalism
and pantheism.
So he figured out
to determine what he called
the meta-anthropological status
of humanity.
And this he developed
in his work,
Man's Place in the Cosmos
or Man's Place in the Universe
which was published
in 1928
after his death.
So it was published
mostly. Remember that he died
of that year.
Sheller in that book
which is actually a very,
just a very thin book
offered a graduate
view of being.
In his view, man, God,
and the world
are one self-becoming cosmic process
in absolute time.
And this process of self-becoming
has two poles.
The guys and the drunk.
Guys meaning spirit
and the drunk meaning the life-hearts.
The guys according to Sheller
is powerless
unless it can,
its ideas can functionalize
with life factors
meaning with material conditions
that realize their actual,
their actualities.
And the one that
can provide the guys
with power,
with vitality
is the drunk.
So the drunk is
the source of life,
the source of vitality.
But the drunk does not have any direction.
So it is the guys
that provides direction.
So the guys is the
source of direction,
source of
the ideas,
source of reason,
but it is powerless.
Does not have any vitality at all.
The drunk on the other hand
is the source of vitality
but it does not have any direction at all.
So when you combine it to
then you have both vitality
and direction.
So,
now Sheller for a particular
kinship to
introspective and intuitive philosophers
like Blaise Pascal.
And it was also
was actually from Blaise Pascal
that he borrowed the notion
of reason of the heart
or logic decor
which would
be very prominent
in his articulation of
our understanding
or feeling of the values.
So he preferred
these introspective and intuitive philosophers
more than the abstract theories
about morality and God.
These tendencies
become the basis of criticisms
against Sheller's emotive philosophy
that his ethics
is emotive.
It's based on
the emotions
on the feelings.
And no less than Karol Vitiva
was critical of
the philosophy of Max Sheller
although Max Sheller influenced a lot
the phenomenology
or the way Vitiva understands
phenomenology.
Of course, there are other
philosophers who also influence
its view about this
about the intuitive
about
introspective power.
Philosophers like
Nietzsche, Briggson and
Delphi.
So these philosophers also influence
this orientation
Max Sheller.
Of course, the other philosopher
who influenced Max Sheller
was Edmund Pusser
and Immanuel Kant
because she studied Immanuel Kant
although he was critical
of the ethics of Immanuel Kant.
The other philosophers
or thinkers who have Sheller's
thinking includes
those thinkers in the history of philosophy
who demonstrated their
phenomenological orientation like
philosophy and other oriental
philosophers.
His other works also
showed the result of Kantian
and post Kantian influence.
As I mentioned here, their
formalismos, although it was
a critique of Kant's formal ethics
he nevertheless agreed
with Kant on certain points
and we are going to discuss
that later. The influence
of phenomenology
especially
Brusser account for Sheller's
interest on empirical research
and in metaphysics.
So those are
the important
influences in the philosophy
of Max Sheller. Now let's
go to his methodology.
Of course
he strongly emphasized
the phenomenological method
which at a time
was being formally developed
by Brusser
and he also actually
acclaimed this in his door formalismos.
He first came
in contact with the movement
when he moved to the University of
Beauty in 1907 as we have already mentioned
and there he met
some of the students of
Brusser.
So he was
attracted to this
movement or to this approach
of philosophy. Although
he
applied the phenomenological method
not on
epistemology the way
Brusser applied
phenomenology
but applied it to
actualogy, to ethics
or to values
and to his notion of
the human person.
Sheller is firmly convinced
that phenomenology would bring about
basic transformation
in our way of conceiving the world
and ourselves.
Although some consider it
thought to be quite unsystematic
Sheller was one of the most
insightful and acutely
intuitive and brilliant thinkers
and writers of the early 20th century.
And his works
abound with
detailed description of the
sample states of consciousness
like sympathy which he has a
book on
resentment
love
and joy.
So here are some of the
important works of
Max Sheller
on resentment and moral
value judgment
published in 1912.
And then contributions
to the phenomenology and theory
of sympathy and of love in 8
the following year 1913.
And then he's there formalismus
and non-formal ethics of values.
and then man's place in nature
or man's place in the cosmos
posumously published in 1928
and man in the age of
equalization
published in 1929.
So these last two are
posumously published.
Now let's go to his theory
of values.
And here we are going to
zero in on the
formalismus.
And it would be nice
it would help if you're going
to read at least the first
chapter of the
formalismus for you to better understand
his theory
of values.
Now in that book the formalismus
Sheller explained that one
ought to do
what one ought to do
presupposes a feeling
of the value of what ought
to be done.
Now this ought
is actually
the concept of duty
of Immanuel Kant.
So he's referring to
the concept of duty
the categorical imperative
of Immanuel Kant.
And according to Sheller
what we ought to do
our understanding of what
of duty
presupposes a feeling
of the value of what ought
to be done. In other words
the feeling is more primordial
than the understanding
of
the duty.
Because for Sheller
even if you know
that we ought to do
our duties
we have the feeling of the value
of that duty
we will never do it.
So it presupposes
that we already have
a feeling of the duty.
That feeling of
the duty is based on our
values.
Now he divided the values
into five ranks which are given
a priori.
So for him the values
must be a priori meaning
they don't pass to experience
that fulfill
the requirement of Kant
that for something to be universal
it must be a priori.
So if you apply
the idea of
a priori
that the universal must be a priori
by saying
that values are given a priori
then that means
the values are universal.
And these values
are anchored
in our
ordo amoris
or the order or logic of the heart
logic decor.
And this
logic of the heart
is not congruent to the logic
based on reason.
So aside from
the logic of reason
Sheller adds
another thing the logic
of the heart.
And the reason
of the heart cannot be
understood by reason
by pure reason
by the intellect.
And in this
view Sheller follow the idea of
the French philosopher
Blaise Pascal and of course
oppose himself to the ideas
or to the position of
Immanuel Kant.
According to this view
moral acts and deeds
are individual
and they originate
in an individual's
pre-rational
preferring of values.
Meaning before
we can rationalize
about values
we already prefer
the values before we can even
understand before we can
even reason out about
values. We already have
preference
tendency
for values.
So we will
explain that in details
in the later part.
So moral experience lies in the
what he calls the call of the hour
of the moment
in which the a priori ranking
among
values become individually
transparent.
In a particular moment
we're going
how we value things will become
transparent it will manifest
itself.
No matter how much the order
may be distorted by the
feelings of the sentiment
of hate and other passions
we will go back to this later.
Now let's go to the
first part of the therefore
balismos.
Because in the first part of the
it is where
Scheller presented
this criticism of Kant's
formal ethics.
By the way when you say
non-formal ethics
it means material ethics.
Material here
pertains to
the non-rational.
The non-rational.
So the formal is rational
that's the
position of
reason
pure reason practical reason
so it's formal.
And
the non-formal
the non-rational
is
regarded by Kant as
empirical
or material.
So
Scheller
develops his theory of values
in the realm of the material
in the realm of the
non-formal.
What is that material
non-formal in the realm of the emotions.
So Scheller's theory of values
and ethics would be in fact
incomprehensible
without taking into consideration
his criticisms of Kant's
view of ethics.
Because in the first part of the
therefore balismos
he was commenting
and criticking
the formalism of Immanuel Kant
although he agreed with Kant
on certain points.
And therefore the non-formalismos
in the non-formalismos
Scheller
preoccupied himself with a lengthy criticism
of Kant's formal ethics
and built much of his
own ideas on these
or from these criticisms.
He said
in the early pages of the non-formalismos
in this work
I can accomplish my task
only through revealing Kant's
erroneous presuppositions
and by replacing
them with correct
ones. That's how
ambitious the project
of Scheller is
in this
work that are formalismos.
Scheller though agreed
with Kant on certain points.
First he agreed with Kant
when Kant rejected
all ethics of goods and purposes.
What is an ethic
of goods and purposes?
Well, it's a kind of ethics
that bases the morality
of action or morality itself
on purposes.
Remember
the teleological theories on ethics.
So
Kant rejected all teleological
theories
of ethics.
Because these ethics base morality
on purposes
on uncertain goods.
For example, you want to be happy
if what you're doing
will make you happy, happiness
is something good, then
your action
is ethical.
But Kant rejected
that kind of ethics.
He rejected that kind of ethics.
And Scheller agreed with Kant
in his rejection
of this kind of ethics
of goods and purposes.
So according to Scheller
Kant was correct
when he refuted all ethics
starting with a question
what is the highest good
or what is the final purpose
of all our
volitional connection.
So he agreed with
Kant on that point.
Kant he said was correct
in dismissing them
as having false basis.
So Scheller wrote
in the Der Formalismus
and I'm quoting him here
I quote
Kant maintained
that whenever
we make the goodness
or moral depravity
of a person
and act will
indeed, etc.
Dependent on their relation to
the realm of existing goods
or evils,
posited as real
we make the goodness or the
privacy of the will
dependent on the particular
contingent existence
of the realm of goods
as well as on its experiential
noability.
So he agreed with Kant
that we cannot base our
the moral goodness
or the moral
depravity of a particular
act on the basis
of a realm of goods
because this realm
of goods
is based on experience
and
anything that is based on experience
or empirical cannot
be permanent it will be changing
and therefore you cannot base
your morality on that. So he agreed
with Kant on that point.
Kant further added
that the moral value of the will
would always depend
on the way in which
it intervened in the
maintenance or promotion of this
realm of goods.
However,
since this realm of goods
is continually changing in
history
because this realm of goods
is contingent
it's
empirical
the moral value of the will
would also be changing
so like for example
let us say
God yet
belong to this realm of good
so if we are going to base our
or fame for example
or power for example
but this realm of goods
they keeps on changing
in history.
So that means that the value
of the will would also be changing
the destruction of this
realm of goods would also
mean the dissolution of the idea
of the moral
value.
So with these presuppositions
ethics would be based on sensible
experience and therefore
it would only be empirical
and it will only have
inductive validity
and remember that for
Kant
morality should be universal
a knowledge
should be universal
that's why he said
that morality should be
based on the moral law
the moral law is something
that is universal the moral law
is law is a priori
so the
a priori is that which is
universal
so if we base our morality
on a realm of goods
that will be changing
continuously
in history then
morality will also be changing
the same holds true if ethics will be
based on purposes
on the end, the loss
any ethics which measures
the moral value of the will
against the final purpose
like you want to be happy
or you want to be
say
useful
that would necessarily
degrade the values of the goods and evil
to mere technical values
subordinated to that purpose
so Scheller echoes Kant
when he wrote and again echoed
ethics must reject
all talk of good and bad purposes
for purposes
as such are never
good nor bad
when considered apart from the value
that are to be realized
in positing them
and apart from the values of the act
that posits them
remember that for Kant
there is only one thing that is good
without any qualification
and that is the good will
so therefore we cannot base ethics
on any purpose
because these purposes
may change
it may be good
under certain condition
but remember
for Kant
the good must be good
without any condition
and the only thing that is good
is the good will
so on this point Scheller agreed
with Immanuel Kant
purposes are justifiable
only when they will posit
when the will posits
or has posited them is good
and the only way that can posit
it to be good
is the good will
what makes a purpose good or bad
is not the particular realization of that purpose
but the very positing
or the manner
or phases in which the purpose
has come about
so he agreed
with Kant on those points
however
he refuted Kant
when Kant assume
that the material
or non formal ethics
which is also an ethic
of goods and purposes
when Kant assume
that
non formal ethics
is also an ethic
of goods and purposes
because Kant
distinguish only
formal
or non formal
and
he included
the non formal ethics
to ethics of goods and purposes
so for Kant
the only thing
the only ethics
that is
viable and acceptable
is a formal ethics
he dismissed
the material
non formal ethics
Kant believe
that an ethic preceded by correct methods
must exclude
improsipositions
of the concept of good and bad
and the constitution
not only goods and purposes
but also all
values of non formal
nature
so
Jose
in general
can't reject
all kinds of
values
of non formal nature
meaning the values
that are not
rational
and again he called
all practical principles
which presuppose an object
meaning a material
of the faculty of desire
the desire is emotion
at the determining ground
of the will are without exception
empirical
and can furnace as no practical
loss
and by practical
by material of the
faculty of desire I mean
an object whose reality is
desired
that's from practical reason
so it's
in practical reason
so here
according to Scheller
Kant eroniously
assume that any material
or non formal ethics
must necessarily be an
ethics of goods and purposes
in that such ethics
is empirically inductive
and aposteriori
an ethics of
success
it's an ethics that is hedonistic
it's eronus and it is an ethics
that is incapable of determining
the moral foundation
of action and is
incapable of furnishing insight
into the dignity
of the person
so
that's the position of Kant
and that is the position
that Scheller rejected
so on the contrary
according to Scheller
the rejection
of an ethics of goods or purposes
does not imply
a rejection of concrete values
Kant thought that we can
or he can exclude
from consideration the value
which represent themselves in goods
but this would be correct
if instead of finding
their fulfillment
in autonomous phenomena
the value concepts
were to be obstructed
from the goods
or if one could derive them
only from actual effects
an ethics
of material values
does not necessarily
presuppose
empirical knowledge
because as
Scheller would show
how the material values
are not
known
through empirical knowledge
they are also a priori
meaning they are also universal
so
Scheller elevated material values
in the same level
as ideas
as formal concepts
because for Kant
you have the concepts, you have the laws
the formal laws, the moral law
universal
and the material values
they are empirical
but according to Scheller
no, the material values
are also a priori
they are not empirical
so Scheller also rejected
Kant's identification
of the a prioristic
with the rational
in the material or non formal
with the sensual or
a posteriori
because for Kant
is the rational, this is the formal
and it is a priori
the material
or non formal is
a posteriori
empirical
okay, that's the position
of Kant and Scheller
rejected that position
so why can't believe
that a material ethic must
refer to the organization
of the egotistic
crimes of human nature
in all ethical
valuation
Scheller believed
otherwise
so he refuted the claim
of Kant that only formal
ethics
avoids the fallacies
committed by non formal
or material ethics
so Scheller believed
that
this fallacies
can also be avoided
this egotistic
this egotistic valuation
can also be
avoided by
non formal
or material ethics
so now the main purpose now
of Scheller
is to show that an ethic
of material values
which Kant rejected
by no means
leads to the conclusion
rich rich rich
by Kant
he developed an ethical
theory based on the inside
that material values
and their hierarchical
order
form a realm
of material
aprioristic data
which is disclosed to us
by emotional intuition
so if the formal
if the concepts
ideas
are revealed to us by reason
the values
are revealed to us
by way of emotional intuition
and Scheller also wanted
to show
that the dichotomy between the sensible
and the intelligible
or between the intelligible
and the emotional
when it comes to knowledge
is not exhaustive
because
there is a separate realm
between the senses and the intellect
there is something
between what is perceived
by the senses
and what is taught by reason
and this separate realm
is the realm of feelings
that which is
felt
the realm of the emotion
so senses
thought
or intellect
thinks
the emotions
feel
so
he develop his ethics based on the
emotions
based on what is felt
and what is felt is the value
so the value
is
the intentional object of our
emotion
or of our feelings
and this is where phenomenology
would come in
because just like Pusser
who develop the idea
that the intentional
objects
are the intentional
the ados
are the essential
or the intentional objects of our consciousness
for Scheller
the values are the intentional objects
of our emotions
so now let's discuss
the nature of values
so through the phenomenological
approach to ethics into values in general
Scheller
hope to make the theory of values
impervious
in the criticisms
of relativism
in of the behavioral sciences
he wanted this theory
this
theory of values
immune
from the criticisms
of Kant
so according to him
many emotions have objective
referents
meaning intentional objects
he stressed that the belief
that emotions are purely subjective
states of consciousness
is based on an
erroneous description
or misanalysis
or misunderstanding
of their structure
people believe that emotion
is just a subjective
emotional state
or states of consciousness
now according to Scheller
although some moods
do not go beyond themselves
the experience of a value
is usually an intentional
act
which is parallel to perception
and conception of ideas
so in perception
we have the material object
in conception we have the ideas
in the emotion
we have the values
so the object
like for example
the feeling of joy
about a good news
is an experience which have
subjective and objective points
so joy is not just a subjective
state of consciousness
because there is an objective point
to this emotion
the object
of that experience is seen
as a good thing
which insensates a value
so for example
we have the feeling of joy
because
of the good news
what is the good news
why is it a good news
so the news is something good
because it insensates
a value
and the value
is the objective point
of your emotional or subjective state
so
the emotion
or the feeling of joy insensates
a value
so it's not only the good news
that will
insensate that particular value
so therefore according to Scheller
there is no such a thing as
a cognitive emotions
in that point to certain real objects
cognitive emotions
and of course
this cognitive emotion
is not something that is congruent
to the cognitive reason
going back to
the order amoris or logic of the heart
that he borrowed from Blaise Pascal
so again in the Darformalismos
he disagreed with Kant's
identification of the
a priori with reason
for Scheller
the a priori
extends far beyond
the uses of reason
and therefore included
feeling
the feeling nature of mind
within the constitution
of the mind
and posited what he called
emotional a priori
so the mind
is not only
formal or rational
the mind
emotional component
so that's where he said
it's connected to what
we have already mentioned
that what one ought to do
which is
the a priori
of reason
presupposes the feeling
of the value of one ought to be
done that's the emotional
a priori
so there is the formal a priori
of duty
and there is the emotional
a priori of the value
of that duty
alright now let's move
on to the order amoris
because this is one
very important concept
of Mark Scheller
and this is where he
described how we
recognize
the value
as a priori
so values are a priori
and these are
anchored on our
our order amoris
or the order
or logic of the heart
and again as we've said
this is not something that is
congruent to the order
of reason to the formal
part
of our mind
and again as we've said
this is what he
borrowed from
according to this view
moral acts
or deeds
are individual
and they originate
in our own pre-rational
prefering of values
now what is this
pre-rational prefering of values
in the ordinary sense
when we say prefering
or preference
using something
over something else
but in Scheller's
terminology
when you say prefering
it pertains to
a pre-rational act
it's an act
that happens
prior to making a rational
or deliberate
choice
between one
between two or more
different things
so
when we make a decision
or a rational decision
we analyze
which one will I choose
we deliberate
we enumerate
we think of several reasons
why choose this
but in pre-rational
prefering before you can
even think of
these things
before you can even deliberate
you already have certain tendency
you already
lean towards something
before you can even make a choice
so this leaning towards
something
has already taken place
in us even before
we make a choice
so we may
for example lean towards
contemporary music
over classical music
before we can even think of
why do we like
contemporary music
over classical music
or we may prefer
a particular color
we prefer say
color blue
over some other colors
why is that
well
you can think later on
we deliberate
choice
I want blue because
because of this and that
or I want red because of this and that
but even before you do that
you already have some leaning towards something
so in such cases
we inadvertently
experience a drift
or propensity towards something
rather than something else
so there is
pre-rational preferring of
contemporary music over
classical music
or pre-rational preferring
of certain colors
over other colors
now
this leaning towards something
may accompany us for a long time
or even for our entire life
or it may take
different directions during
our middle age
when we grow old
now another parallelism
in our
visual perception
we do not choose to see it alive
that makes
things visible to us
rather our sense of sight
possesses a pre-visual
tendency
or trend towards life
towards
what is lit up or bright
there is
a pre-visual preference
to light
rather than darkness
that's pre-visual
and there is also
pre-rational
so love is in the sense
analogous to light
love has an intrinsic
bent towards
other higher values
than those that were merely given to us
no matter whether
or not love will realize them
so we prefer
certain values over other values
now
the more experience lies
in the call of the hour
in which the a priori ranking
of values becomes
individually apparent
no matter how much the order of more
may be distorted by feelings
or other passions
in other words
there is already a
pre or an a priori ranking
of values
meaning
it is not the person
who ranks these values
but values themselves are already
ranked
there is an objective ranking
of values
and these values
are as follows
value of the senses
meaning the value of
what is pleasant or unpleasant
or maybe
what is enjoyable or not enjoyable
in the physical
or bodily sense
the value of life
whether something is noble
or common
the value of the spirit
which is divided into two
the aesthetic values of ugly and beautiful
or the value of knowledge
and then
the value of
religion or the religious values
the value of the holy and unholy
so if you are going to rank them
in ascending order
it will follow this
the lowest would be the value
of bodily comfort
or the pleasure values
and then higher
than the bodily comfort
the value of the senses
would be the pragmatic values of usefulness
these two lower ranks of values
are either manageable
or calculable and divisible
it's as if cultivation of them
as happens in modern society
this unites people
so this is the lower value
the higher value is
the value
that contains life values
they belong to what is noble
and life values
but
life values pertain at the power
only with persons
and then the highest
values
the two highest value ranks
are experienced exclusively
in human personal feelings
the value of
the spirit and the religious
values
so here the rank of
mental values of
justice, beauty
and the cognition of truth
so ranking of values
and then the highest of the value
would be
the value of
the religious feelings
the holy or the unholy
so fourth seller
the values are already
ranked
there is an objective
ranking of values
no matter how
our feelings
or our resentment
or hate
may distort them
some people who are resentful
may think
of the value of beauty
as lower
as lower than
for example the value of
say
usefulness
or
pleasurable
we may say
justice
is one of the highest
values but some people will say
well the value of justice is
lower than the value
for example of
pleasure or comfort
now i will stop there
if you have some questions
yes Alexis go ahead
Doc may randin po ba siyang concept
ng
parang kai-kant na logiver
kasi po di ba sabi po ninyo
nakarank na po yung
mga values
si na po yung nag rank po ng mga values
noyan doc
if you think of the logiver
in the context or same
as Kant
there is this logiver
it's simply that
in reality there is this
values
so even Kant does not say
that the values are rank accordingly
based on the logiver
Kant only say that there is the moral law
and this moral law
is the highest of the laws
but as to the lower values
does not say where it came from
it's part of reality
the values
values are
we just not say that
values are created
values are there
they are part of our human experience
you can only stress that as far as well
because humans
are created
and part of his existence are the values
then the values must also be created
by a higher being
but cellar would not say that
it's part of our experience
it's part of the human reality
okay, any questions?
oh, let me pull out it
since there is already a pre-establish
of values and values
as already rank
because it means values are not
no
it's not about
immoral or being moral
this is not
this is not an ethics
this is not an ethics that talks about
what is moral or immoral
okay
na
you are mixing things
please up
it's not talking of
moral or immoral here
of course
it talks about evil
when later on you're going to see
that if you
evil would be the preference
for a lower value
okay
but it's not talking of the
of immoral
in the
in the Christian sense of being immoral
that it's a sin
it's evil
meaning if there is
no congruence
if our
if our ranking of values
is not congruent, is not in conformity
with
with the ranking of values
then there's something evil in it
there's something negative in it
but not in the
in the Christian sense of being a sin
okay, other questions?
okay
okay, no more
na you have one minute to answer
if you are listening to my lecture
okay
you have one minute to reply
if you don't reply, you have one minute
that means you are not following my discussion
okay
may
may kindly take note
take note of those who replied
okay, thank you
alright, so
that's my way of checking
if you are listening to my discussion
if you are still here or you just
plug in
we know some people are dais
okay
but 37
alright, let's continue
values as intentional objects
of feelings
so again, we recall
the notion
of intentional objects of consciousness
of who's heart
okay
consciousness is always consciousness of something
and
the consciousness
has intentional objects
now, Sheller adopted this thesis
of
who's heart
okay, that the ideal objects
of knowledge
are independent of the knowing subject
so the ideal objects
of knowledge, these are the intentional
objects of our consciousness
so
Sheller adopted this idea
and he applied this
to his
disclosure of the realm of values
just as there are
intentional objects of knowledge
the ideal objects of knowledge
he contended
that there are also intentional objects
of feelings
and what are these intentional objects of feelings
the values
right
so the
ideal objects of knowledge are a priori
and the values are also
a priori
so what are values
these are particular class of ideal
objects
which are objective, eternal
and immutable
so values are
given to us as intentional
objects of our feelings
just as colors
are
the objects of our
visual perception
so concepts
are objects of our thoughts
colors and the other
material qualities
are the objects of our senses
values
are the objects of our feelings
and just like
the concepts
they are objective
eternal
and immutable
so
the modes in which
values are knowable to us
are beyond the grasp
of the intellect
so the intellect grasp
our grasp
as the
the essence
for example
the ideas
the values
are grasped by our feelings
how our feelings are grasped
by our emotion
is beyond
the understanding
of the intellect or reason
it has its own reason
that reason cannot understand
so according to Scheller
just as
the ear
is blind
to color
so the intellect
is blind to
the values
so the emotional aspects of the mind
feelings
preferring
loving, hating, willing
because these are
the emotional acts
the mind has its own acts
the intellect rather
the intellect has its own acts
apprehension, judgment
analyzing, critiquing
disputing, et cetera
the emotional aspects of our minds
have also its own acts
feeling, preparing, loving
hating, willing
and so on
and they are not founded upon cognition
but are of an
apprehensive character
in our emotional feeling
we feel something
for example
this or that particular value quality
why do we prefer this
why do we feel for this
for Scheller
we prefer
our emotion has its own reason
but
reason, the intellect
cannot explain why we prefer this
of course later on you can have
your own rational
deliberation why you prefer
contemporary music
over classical music
so according to Scheller
there is a very rational preferring of this
that cannot be explained by reason
so intentional objects
intentional
feeling functions
do not need the intermediary
of the objectifying acts of the intellect
like representing
and judging or analysis
in order to come into immediate contact
with their objects
values for example as agreeable
charming
lovely, friendly, et cetera
in principle
are accessible to me
without my having
to represent them
as properties belonging to
things or men
values are not conceptual terms
which find their fulfillment
in the common properties
of things which are the
bearers of these values
for example when you say
what is
a house
what is your idea of
an institution
what is your idea
of beauty
now when you think of
your idea of beauty then you are going to
come up with certain common characteristics
but why do you
find this thing beautiful
can you give
an enumerable common properties
of things according to Scheller when you do that
sometimes you end up
empty-handed
because when you say
I find this charming
and then I also find this thing charming
and then I also find this charming
but when you look at these things
they have nothing in common
why do you consider this
to be agreeable
and this is agreeable also
why do you have that feeling
you cannot
give a reason because
it is beyond
reason
beyond reason
meaning it is not
within the realm of
reason
so according to Scheller
this is shown by the simple
fact that it's time we attempt
to determine such common
properties
of what is charming to us
or lovely or friendly to us
we always end up empty
and dead
even the habitual
or even the ethical values
or aesthetic values like normal, courageous
and as beautiful
becomes accessible
not through a number of defined characteristics
I find this
I find this beautiful
I find this accessible
this is normal
so that's the point of Scheller
of course other philosophers
are critical of this position
but
here's a point here also
so values are independent
of our subjective emotional states
what is our subjective emotional states
like for example when you are sad
sadness
is an emotional state
but the sadness I feel may involve
in me various emotional sentiments
so being brokenhearted, being defiant
being composed, jatra
these are our subjective emotional states
now the feeling of sadness remains
while my subjective emotional state
may change
at one point I'm sad so I become brokenhearted
or I am defiant
or yeah I may be sad
but I'm sad composed
moreover the causes
must not be confused with emotional
with intentional object
the question for example
why am I angry
is entirely different
from what do I feel
so what do I feel
is your subjective states
why am I angry
my anger
anger is the emotion
and what is the object of this anger
it may be something else
that represents
a particular value
so I am angry because
I was defiant
okay
my instructions were not followed
so not following instruction causes me to be angry
but what is it in
this not following
following my order that made me angry
so not obeying instruction
not following represents a particular value
that makes me angry
that becomes the object of my anger
okay
because
I am going to be angry
not only because somebody
defied me
or somebody did not follow
my instruction
I may also be angry because somebody betrayed me
so betrayal
this obedience
they represent a particular value
which is the object of my anger
so a value phenomena
as a value phenomena
values are true objects
and they are different from all states
of feelings
there is a difference between
feeling of sadness
feeling of anger
and the values
that are the objects of my
anger or of my sadness
now
values are independent
of their bearers or carriers
what is this bearer or carriers
these are things or relations
that shell are collectively called the goods
the goods are units
of value qualities
which instantiates
objectifies
the value in the real world
the value qualities do not change
when these goods
when these bearers
change
so for example
let's use an analogy
let's talk about the color
this is the color blue
now thus the color blue
turns red
when
an object that is blue
becomes red
like for example
a dress
so dress
bears
or carries
the value bears the color
so
if this dress
which instantiates
the color blue
becomes red
so it's now a red dress
thus the color blue
change into red
no
the color blue
remains blue
the color red
remains red
but the dress which instantiates
which is the carrier
or the bearer
of the colors
have changed
it now carries a different color
so it's not true
that values are affected
by their order
when their bearers
change in value
food is still food
poison is still poison
the value of friendship does not change
even when your friend
changes
so this person
who carries the value of friendship
becomes your enemy
he now instantiates
not the value of friendship
he now instantiates the value of an enemy
friendship
did not turn into
being unfriendly
so goods are value
things
they are bearers of value
for example
when you go
go inside the church
see the altar
the altar may carry
or may bear certain values
may have
aesthetic value
because it's very beautiful
or it may also bear
the value of the holy
so the altar is just a bearer of value
it can instantiate
the value of
beautiful
for the value of the holy
so it's like saying
the absence of light
is not
saying darkness
para pang ganun
what do you mean?
parang
mayapuban, ayusin kumunayin tanong
ok
other questions?
ok, let's read
the a prioristic structure of values
so
sheller made a distinction between
the realm of values
and the realm of goods
and his assertion that values are independent
of the bearers of values
affirmed the correctness of Kant's view
that a philosophical theory of values
or ethics or even aesthetics
must not presuppose things
or goods
they agree on this
they agree on this sense
on this point
that there is a distinction
between the realm of values
and the realm of goods
that instantiate them
so for example a particular person
may instantiate several values
the values of friendship
the values of courage
the values of health
the values of holy
the values of intelligence
so there is some
independence between the realm of values
and the realm of goods that instantiate them
so it does not mean that for example
the value of the holy
turns to be unholy when
a holy person becomes unholy
it's just that
that person no longer instantates
the value of the holy
so that's the a priori
thing about
this realm of values
now
the a prioristic relation
of values
all values are
either positive or negative
okay
there's no such thing as
a neutral
value
okay
there's always a value
there's always a quality
of worth
positive or negative
the existence
of a positive value
is in itself
positive
the existence of holiness is positive
the nonexistence
of a negative value
is also positive
so if
for example chaos
chaos is a negative value
there's no chaos
that's something positive
the nonexistence of positive value
and the existence of a negative value
is a negative value
so
nobody's holy
there's no holiness
that's a negative value
it's impossible to evaluate
the same value simultaneously
as both negative and positive
a barrier of value
at object
may instantiate two values
okay
like for example a person
may instantiate both
friendship
okay
or love or instantiate hate
but love and hate
cannot be
simultaneous
as a value
good is the value attached
to the realization of a positive or a higher value
evil
the value attached to the realization
of a negative or a lower value
now we're not saying that
that is immoral in the Christian sense
so this is in the actual logical
sense
now
we've already mentioned about the hierarchical
order of values
values constitute
a special domain
with their own distinct relation
and correlation
and among these
there is an order or rank
independent of the realm
of values
so we have already talked about
the hierarchy of these values
all values are
non-formal qualities of contents
possessing a determined order
of ranks
with respect to higher or lower
in this order
independent
of the form of being into its values
and terminating
the carriers of their
the carriers or bearers of these values
or the goods that instantiate this value
so again
this value model
those values reveal by
sensory feeling, by vital feeling
by the spirit
and by the holy
or holy order religious
so this is the ranking
of values of shallow
well, some people may criticize
these ranking of values
but that's how shallow
ordered
rank
these values
the next topic will be the exemplar persons
as shallow said
we need to
attain
a higher moral status
and the vehicle
for attaining a higher moral status
is an exemplar
meaning a model
so an exemplar
is an ideal
but a non-existent
model of one of the value ranks
so every value
there is
an exemplar
an ideal model
that manifest
this value
these ideal
exemplars manifest themselves
in historical role models
like for example
in Buddha, Christ
Muhammad, Hannibal
Ronaldo, Joan of Arc
et cetera
they are our
they are the historical
role models
they manifest the exemplars
the nature of an exemplary person
is authentic
in being exemplary
the moral effectiveness
of exemplary persons
reaches all people directly
regardless
of occupation, vocation
or interest or even culture
so the origin
of becoming good
in concrete practice
lies in the genuine exemplarity
that a particular person
exercises
on others
without deliberately wanting to do so
so for example
consider Christ
we consider
him to be exemplary
and he exercises
or he exercises a particular
influence on us
without really wanting to
be exemplary
such exemplarity occurs
in living persons
so the living persons are the
concrete manifestations
of the ideal
nonexistent exemplars
meaning nonexistent
well
in the same way that values are out there
a priori
they belong to a different realm
the exemplars also belong to a different realm
but they are manifested
in historic
in history so there are also
living persons
who manifest them
okay
but of course
only outlines of ideal persons
which are embedded in our
value feelings so in the words
for example you have your own
ideal
boyfriend or ideal
girlfriend
we exist in that
in that ideal world of yours
but that will be
some living
concrete people who would
somehow manifest
this ideal boyfriend or girlfriend
okay
so
there are empirical model persons
meaning
these are concrete living persons
so manifest our ideal
and the first concrete
empirical model persons
are our parents
so they become
the models for us
and then of course
our models
they grow meaning
okay so parents
okay
and some other people can also have
a strong exemplary effect
on us
a teacher
a president
a prince, sex man, artist
performer
an actor perhaps
depending on the particular
culture
it could be the chief of a tribe
or our ancestors
or our wise men
masters
in different cultures
but according to him
it is the exemplary holy man
who exercises
the strongest moral influence
in history
like for example Jesus
Muhammad
Buddha and only other
holy men in history
and what is common
among them is that they did not
choose
or explicitly willed
to be exemplary
nor were they chosen
by those who freely follow them
genuine role models
or model persons
almost automatically set up
moral standards for other people to follow
so people are drawn
towards them
and are motivated by their exemplaryity
no matter how deeply
or silently
they follow
these role models
or the holy
or moral persons
in contrast to the empirical model persons
an ideal model person
is only an exemplary
outline in our mind
so like your
ideal boyfriend or girlfriend
it's just there in our mind
in the same way
as values do exist
at least they are realized
in materials
or by persons
so all these absolute value types
do not exist
unless their ideal value
is realized
with concrete persons
okay
so your ideal boyfriend or girlfriend
is just there
but it will functionalize
if they are
you have some concrete person
to embody them
so according to Scheller
these ideal outlines should functionalize themselves
with concrete person
now
based on the
values there are five
ideal moral person types
the ideal personifications
of the aforementioned
value ranks
so they are the highest
would be the ideal saint
then the ideal genius
then lower the ideal hero
then the ideal
leader of a society
or of a civilization
and then the absolute master
of enjoying sensible
pleasures
so these are the ideal
moral person types
and you can think of
of course of
empirical
concrete persons
who may functionalize
these ideal
moral
person types
now in the same sense
as values are experienced relative
to the individual's natures
historical manifestations
of ideal person types may vary
so for example
the ideal hero
would have different appearances
like for example in Joan of Arc
or in Alexander the Great
the ideal artist
may vary
in a bit hoven
or in a Michael Angelo
and even the ideal saints
may vary
subject to the choices
between
them since one can make choices
only among the lower
sorry
but it vary
depending on the religion
but in the latter
the founders of religion
are not subject to choices
between them because
one can make choices
only among the lower types of
exemplars
so if a person converts to
or otherwise begins to abandon
the original fate
now there may be some defection
or even betrayal
something that does not occur when one
makes a choice among the lower
exemplars
okay so there are many
different
personifications
of these
ideal types
okay
now let's go to the last
topic here
the moral person
what is the moral person
Sheller
retains Kant's understanding of person
as having an absolute
value and end in
itself remember
the
second articulation of the
categorical imperative
treat the person whether
in you or in others to be
not only as a means
but as an end in itself
so Sheller
as we have said it was influence
by Kant retain that
idea of a person
as having
an absolute value
however he is critical of Kant
as Kant grounds the absolute value of the person
in the universal category
of reason that's understandable
after discussing his criticism
of the
formalism of Kant
now Sheller describes the person
as the concrete unity of acts
of
different types of nature
concrete unity of acts
so the person is present in each
and every act
my person
is present in its
in every act that I perform
but the person
is not reducible to any
of one act
okay so I am present
in all my action but my person
cannot be reduced in one particular
act that I perform
unity here means
a particular style
particular style of acting
style of
executing my action
or of being
so every individual
will have his or her unique
style of loving
of assigning meaning
of
willing
of choosing
and necessarily has his own
or her own access to the world
and when a person dies
not only
is that the style of loving
of assigning or choosing
thinking is lost
but so is that
world
is own access to that world
it is also lost
now
for Sheller
our being a person
is the form of our mind
and of our consciousness
no matter whether
mind and consciousness are understood
to be human, divine
or just fictional
Sheller rejected the notion
of a pure consciousness
or mind
similar like
what Husserl
stressed or affirmed
so the person is just
the form of our mind
okay
so
the form of a person
is indifferent
to gender, culture
race and social station
so the person manifests itself
without reference
among men and women
culture, race, social station
et cetera
among Asian or European
ancient people's culture
American or Asian
et cetera et cetera
whether it's or poor it doesn't matter
okay
the person is different to all this
the existence of the form
of our mind the person
is not also comparable
to the existence of a thing
when we ask the existence
of a thing
is it's being an object to us
personal existence
consists only in the
execution of mental
volitional
and emotive acts
so as persons we execute
mental acts, volitional acts
emotive acts
so we cannot be reduced
to a thing or an object
because objects and
things do not act
mentally, volitionally
or emotionally
so such acts are for example
that the person is capable
of loving, of feeling
thinking, willing
remembering, expecting, hoping
despairing, choosing
et cetera et cetera
now also
share other content that
the word person cannot be applied to
to a being
where we assume animation
eagleness
consciousness of existence
or value of the ego
it cannot be applied to man
in general
the phenomenological essence
of person reveals that although
there are scenes of personhood
in still and developed
levels of human beingness
like for example in the case
of children, in the case of
it cannot be applied
or it can only be applied
to a specific level of human existence
or a certain kind of man
where certain characteristics
are already there
so for example babies
or share other babies
who are not be
they already have
the scenes of personhood
but they cannot be considered
to be person yet because
they are not capable of
this unity
of acts
of course there are persons
because they are already
they have the scenes of personhood
but they cannot be considered person
in the full sense of
moral personhood
okay?
it's like
it's like our notion of the age of
maturity
or age of, for example
at this particular age
18 years old then you are
already a full citizen
because you already have
attained a certain degree of maturity
so something similar to that
now
the imperative that is given
in the value a priori
in the objective ranks of values
is only felt by person
so consequently persons
are the only beings
who are ethically responsible
and because every experience
is evaluated
a person
is responsible
to love the object
or a being of that experience
most fully
so for example in relation to other persons
it's the responsibility
and ethical responsibility
of the person to love
so in loving another person
one is called
ethically to love
even more
fully and deeply because
the object of that love
is a person
who has the highest
or the absolute value
now finally
let's talk about what are the characteristics
of a person
for shellar
the person possesses
a holy sound mind
so the person
is somebody
who executes intentional acts
that are bound
by a unity of sense
not the unity that we talked about
a while ago
person is subscribed only to a certain level
of development
so eagerness
possession of a soul
consciousness of self
do not make a man
a person in the moral
sense
because you have to perform
actions
the emotive
the volitional and the mental acts
a child
or a person coming
of age
has the ability to experience
inside difference
between one act and other acts
so if a child can already
experience this
then he can consider to be
a moral person
so he is able to
in a different shape
and conscious of his ability
conscious of his ability
defines a person
so the question is
what about the embassy
for the embassy
the men retarded
while they have the seeds of personhood
they cannot be considered to be
moral persons
so person is restricted
to those in whom
domination over the live
body appears immediately
he is a master
a mastery of his live body
and
lastly the concrete subject
of all acts of the essence
of inner intuition
and therefore for Scheller
the person is
only
as the concrete unity of acts
executed by the person
and only
in the execution of these
acts
can a person be considered to be
a moral
person
but just to clarify
man
all men whether it's
a baby or an embassy
they contain the seeds
of personhood
only that because
they have not attained a certain degree
of moral maturity
then they cannot be considered to be
a moral person
ok so that concludes
my presentation on this topic
this is not the whole of Scheller
we have only discussed
what is
what he discussed in the
their formalism was not even whole of it
not even whole of it
and I already mentioned
many of some of the
important works of Max Scheller
but I hope that this presentation
will give you
you know
you may introduce
give you an overview
of the
philosophy or at least the philosophy
of values of Max Scheller