Welcome to BrainVR podcast. We are sitting here with Professor Michael Levin, a distinguished
professor in the biology department at Tufts and Serfs as a director of the Allen Discovery Center
at Tufts as well and the Tufts Center for Regenerative and Developmental Biology.
Your group focuses on understanding the biophysics, biophysical mechanism that implement decision
making during complex pattern regulation and harnessing the endogenous bioelectric dynamics
towards rational control of growth and form. And you also did your postdoctoral training
at Harvard Medical School where you began to uncover a new bioelectrical language by which
cells coordinate their activity during embryogenesis. And you also had independent laboratory
at Forsythe Institute and now you are at Tufts University and you are developing a new molecular
genetic and conceptual tools to probe large-scale information processing in regeneration,
embryogenesis and cancer suppression. Does that sound right? Did I miss something which is
important or is that okay? Oh yeah, it sounds right. I also have an appointment at the VISA
Institute at Harvard but other than that I think we got everything. All right, cool. So we do our
interviews maybe a little bit differently because we are really interested in people that we talk
to so we love your work, we love what you do and what you've discovered. It's just so fascinating
but we would like to kind of dig a little bit into your kind of a story. Like what were the
you know the moments that decided, the most important moments in your life that decided
the path that you're gonna take, the path that got you right where you are right now,
studying what you studied because I think you were also doing before some computational,
basically like helping science with computational stuff and stuff like that. So could you maybe
you know add a little bit of a story behind what you do and behind your path? Sure, yeah. Well I
suppose we could go to the kind of to the beginning when I was a little kid and I was born in Moscow
Russia so I lived there when I was little and I had asthma and what happens with asthma of course
is that your airway closes up and so you get nervous which makes your airway close up more
which makes you more nervous and so it's this kind of like feedback loop. So at the time we didn't
have access to really medication right proper medication for asthma and so as a solution what
my father used to do is you would take the um this TV set which was this giant like wooden thing
with a tiny little screen in the front right I don't know if you can even imagine such a such a
thing but um but you know and inside of so he would turn it around and he would take off the back
yeah take off the back panel and you could see all the vacuum tubes it had these glowing you know
vacuum tubes and all the electronics and all the parts and and and the you know the goal was to
was to of course distract it right so to distract me so that I would forget about the you know the
breathing and so on and so so that worked but you know kind of amazing that that was for me that
was really a very formative moment because I remember staring at this stuff and thinking
it's kind of incredible that somebody knew how to put all that stuff in exactly the right way to
make the cartoons you know come out the front of the of the set right so somebody is who clearly
it wasn't random clearly somebody knew how to do it uh apparently you can teach people to do it
because you know I said well where does this come from right so in the factory they they sort of do
it okay so so that was amazing and and I right from the beginning I kind of decided that okay
that's that's what I want to be I want to be the guy that knows how to put these things together to
make a particular thing come up so so for years after that I was interested in in in engineering
and and and technology and and things like this but uh at the you know when I when I got a little
bit older I had a I had a friend who uh was really into bugs and insects uh and so we would go
outside and we would he was a little bit older but we would go and play and he would show me all
the different you know caterpillars and beetles and all the stuff and I remember thinking that
well this is very interesting because clearly they are made of parts too they're different parts
than what the tv is made of and they do way more stuff and they appear they're pretty different
they they have preferences and they you know they have behaviors and it's clear they like some
things and don't like some things and so on and I said well how does that work and and where
do those parts come from and who put those parts together right so so it's a really kind of a
you know it's kind of a constant and I spend a lot of time and and and you know what's inside
of us like we probably have parts too and um and uh things like that and so when I was uh
when I went to college well prior to that I was uh when when computers first first showed up and
this was like uh when we came to america in 78 so early 80s you know the computer started to show
up I got I was able to I was able to get access to some very simple you know simple computer
stuff and so I was really interested in programming and and really AI right the idea that that could
we could we develop could we develop new minds that we built ourselves right and so so I went to
I went to college for for I majored in computer science was interested in artificial intelligence
and things like that but basically I'm kind of pretty soon it became really clear that
we would have that that it wasn't going to be good enough just to try to do computer science and
and to do on its own because because we really didn't know what we were doing it was really
very unclear where our minds come from except that in biology you see this every day so
we all start life as a single cell you start life as an egg cell and then eventually this
little piece of chemistry and physics becomes a mind and some bastion right during development
so so so that was it I thought I thought okay I have to I have to also do developmental biology
and so so I gotta um right around the same time I got a second uh bachelor's degree in in in biology
and that's you know that's kind of and then I went to grad school and so that that's kind of my
my story well uh yeah this is how minds emerge from chemistry and physics and even just the whole
organism how does it even happen like it's just one of the most fascinating questions that as humans
we can have I think so um I just I would like to go into this basically into this process
and go maybe step by step into how our minds maybe let's go there maybe how our minds emerge from
physics and and chemistry but we have to start at the level maybe of genes at the of the single
cells of the developmental biology that you that you do so could you kind of explain to us and our
listeners how does it even happen that we have some information maybe you know genetic information
how does it happen that from genes there comes this whole thing that's us that's any organism
basically and maybe we have some you know ideas that you know they're encoded I don't know like
plants basically for our limbs and where the head is should be and stuff like that but maybe there's
a little bit different story there because uh that's fairly simplistic I think and we are
both biologists as well so we know it's like this kind of weird you know mechanism that's not really
easily graspable but I think you have some really nice metaphors and uh and you explain it in a
really nice way so could you maybe uh explain to us how how does that even how does it even
happen how is that possible sure um I'll give you my thoughts on it obviously this is very much an
open you know an open area of investigation and and I should point out that uh my view on it is
probably let's say not not in every way the mainstream view so I'm going to tell you what I
think and then you can get the kind of different perspectives from from from others and it's a
pretty different perspective than you would get from a standard let's say developmental biology
course or something like that um the first thing the first thing I would point out is that in placing
the emphasis on genes is already quite a commitment and we need to back up be firm in it because
especially now I mean it was always problematic but especially now we can read genomes right and we
know what's in the genome and when you read the genome of course you don't see anything like what is
your symmetry type how what's the size of this organism how many eyes it has does it have eyes
how many limbs you don't see any of that in in the genome um what you see is uh you see protein
sequences and so so what's in the genome is the is the description of the micro level hardware
that every cell is going to have so genomes are very much a description of the hardware now we've
known for uh for decades now that uh certain kinds of devices and I'm going to argue that
biology is exactly for for many reasons is exactly such a such a device uh yes there's a
hardware layer and you can can manipulate it or try to understand it at the hardware level
layer but there's a much much um more interesting and possibly a more important
software layer to go along with it and we know this right away you know right away that uh we
have something something missing here today because despite all of the amazing progress in
molecular biology and genetics and all of these things they're very basic questions like for
example in my lab we make something called a frog a lotel what's a frog a lotel well it's a
half a frog embryo cells half axolotl cells okay now uh baby axolotls have legs frog larvae or
tadpoles don't have legs so if I make a frog a lotel and I say to you um well here's your here's a
frog genome okay here's a zenithus genome here's a axolotl genome so you have both genomes now I
want you to tell me are frog a lotel is going to have legs or not and now we have a big problem
we have no idea of frog a lotels ahead of time are going to have legs we don't have any way of
making that making that prediction because what what is what because the outcome here
is uh the process of uh of decision making by cells that are going to determine some kind of
morphology and we get so used to we get so comfortable with with reliable development
the idea that okay frog eggs make frogs and acorns make oak trees that we think well of
course that's how it has to be but actually uh there's an i'm sure we'll talk about it today
there's incredible plasticity in that process so something really important is the idea that
the genome encodes for the hardware of the cells right selection meaning meaning that part of
evolution that selects for specific traits that acts on the phenotype that acts on the final
outcome so on the anatomy and on the behavior but the genome but the mapping between the
genotype and the phenotype is really complicated it's not directly straightforward right except
for very you know there's this pair of enzymes and some things like that that are directly sort of
encoded by by the genes but mostly it's not like that and that internal process that software that
developmental physiology that's actually the software that runs the whole thing is to my mind
one of the most important aspects of all of this because it has some incredibly interesting
properties it has some degree of intelligence in the sense of novel problem solving ability in
new circumstances and that has huge implications for biomedicine for for understanding evolution
for basic basic developmental biology that that that layer that that that that the interactions
there are really profound there's a lot of work that's being done by that layer and in addition
to that i want to pretty early in the discussion pull out something else when when we when we try
to explain things so we see something let's say this is here's a creature and it has a particular
style of of hand or it has some eyes or whatever it is and we want to explain this so you can ask
yourself well well where where does that come from right well how do we explain it and i want to
start off by thinking early on about what it means to explain certain kinds of features like what
does that mean how what does it mean to explain where something comes from imagine that i'll give
you i'll give you two simple examples and then you'll see why it matters to developmental biology
um you may have seen this thing it's called a gallatin board so it's a piece of wood like this
you bang a bunch of nails into it just sort of space regular and you take a bag of marbles
and you dump it into the top of the board what happens boom boom boom boom boom that you know
they sort of go around and in the end if you have enough marbles what did they do they land in this
beautiful bell curve at the bottom right you get then it's a tip but you can buy this toy on amazon
whatever so you get this you get this toy so you could ask yourself okay uh where does this beautiful
bell curve shape come from is it in the wood no is it in the description of the nails no is it in
the positioning of the nails no is it in the marbles no where does it come from right so so
that's so that's one simple example another example is if you if you discover a transistor let's say
you discover how to make a transistor and for example biological ion channels are a kind of
transistor because they can be voltage gated right so they're voltage gated current conductances so
they're basically transistors if you figure out how to make a transistor you could connect a few of
those transistors into a logic gate so it could be and or those kinds of logic gates right those
logic gates come with a truth table that tells you how it works yeah for example the and yeah and
with those truth tables especially if you have a knot and an and gate you can make all kinds of
all kinds of things now you can ask yourself where did that truth table come from i didn't
and i didn't have to evolve a truth table what i evolved is a transistor it's a piece of it's a
piece of physics but the truth table came for free once once you have certain things so where do
those things come from so so sometimes they come from specific selection forces other times there
are kind of free lunch in a certain sense and there are many types of these you know in geometry
in in basic i mean mathematicians have been talking about this for a long time right the
truths of of number theory of prime number distributions all these kinds of things they
you don't have to evolve them they're just sort of given to you for free if you have the right kind of
physical machine that to to to take advantage of them so there are laws of biomechanics about
bioelectrics or computation and many things and so what evolution might do so is is is is find a
simple machine that can harness all this stuff and so so i so i think it's important to understand
that when we ask where does it come from there's the part that is genetic but there's also that's
the part that's generic and people like Stuart Stuart Newman or Stu Kaufman have been talking
about this for for many years it's sort of there are generic laws of the universe that that biology
can harness that are not specifically in the genes anymore than that nice bell curve is in the
description of the wood and the nails speaking of intelligence and these these generic laws
how do the cells and cell groups decide what to make and when the process is finished yeah that's
that's that's very important so so there's two ways to to think about that question one way is
how does the decision making work in general so so so how do we scale up so so the the amazing
thing about biology is that evolution unlike unlike a lot of our engineering you know up until
recently when we were engineering we were working with passive materials so you know wood
metal that kind of stuff and the thing about passive materials is that you as the engineer
are responsible for all the outcomes the material basically doesn't do anything except keep its shape
usually and then you are responsible for placing it however it goes evolution can't do that because
evolution is working with an agential material the cells themselves have abilities they have
preferences they have behavioral repertoires so from that perspective evolution evolution is
working with a material that already has all these activities and so what you're really looking at
is behavior shaping it's a lot more like behavior shaping where where what you want is for cells to
give other cells signals so that they do specific things and I can give you some some cool examples
of that but anyway so so what we have to understand is how this process of competent subunits works
together to to to pursue bigger goals right now individual cells are very good at pursuing cell
level goals what's a cell level goal pH hunger level right so some sort of metabolic states all
kinds of like local little little things but multicellular collectives let's say limbs you
know cells of limbs and those kind of things they can work towards much larger goals so for example
in a salamander and they work together to build a limb if you cut off some of the fingers or the
whole wrist or the hand they will rebuild exactly what goes there right they will rebuild the exact
limb and then they stop when they're done so you can see this kind of goal-directed activity
where the system will exert energy to minimize the error between whatever is happening now versus
what it wants to have happened so so of course there's many things not understood about this we
are very actively studying this process but one thing that we can now see is that the process of
connecting the connecting cells into specifically electrical networks okay allows them to do a
very interesting kind of scaling and it's it's a little bit like the the notion of artificial
networks in computer science where you can you can connect these little subunits the subunits by
themselves don't do terribly much although cells of course do but you can connect them in a particular
way that enables the whole thing to have bigger computational properties and i can give you i
can i'll i'll give you just a very very simple example of how it works imagine imagine two cells
that are signaling to each other in the conventional way which means one cell secretes some kind of
signaling molecule that floats around and and it binds the next cell and okay that's a signal
so the thing with that kind of signaling is that the receiver is very clear that this signal came
from outside and once you get a signal from outside you can ignore it you can do something
about it whatever you have many options now imagine evolution invented this amazing thing
called a gap junction a gap junction is this these these proteins that allow cells to stick
together and pass small molecules directly between the intercellular milieu from one
into the other the amazing thing about the gap junction is and i'm simplifying this greatly
but but the interesting piece of this is that when something happens to cell a let's say let's say
it got injured it got poked or something in it and and there's a calcium spike that that went on
that calcium spike or whatever memory molecule will propagate through the gap junction into the other
cell and what i what i what i say about the gap junctions is that they have this property of
wiping identity meaning that when that signal propagates this cell cannot tell that that signal
came from outside because you because because it's calcium spike looks exactly like this other
calcium spike once there is a signal a physiological signal of something now you don't know that it
came from from the outside right so what this means is that there's a kind of mind meld almost a
mental connection between these two cells where memories lose identity they lose ownership so
from the perspective of this single cell that's a fault that that molecule is a false memory
because it this cell never got poked but from the perspective of the collective
that's absolutely a true memory because the collective did get poked and so what happens is
when cells get merged into these tight electrical networks they start to the the the identity the
separated identity starts to fuzz meaning that it's it's they're they're having a hard time keeping
their their knowledge separate and when when when you can't if you and i can't keep our memories
separate then in an important sense we become one larger unit right because that that distinction
starts to break down so when that distinction breaks down and cells connect into larger electrical
networks the three things happen those three things let's go back to the homeostasis right
if you're a single cell and you're trying to keep homeostasis you have to do three things
you have to be able to measure what's going on now what is my ph now then you have to remember
what the correct one is what's my correct ph range and then third you have to take action
to bring the current ph to closer to the correct ph right maybe a dump asset or something like that
imagine what happens to those three things when cells connect connect into large electrical
networks so tissues when you take a measurement because you're gap junctionally connected you
don't you no longer just measure your own local environment because you're all connected you
measure something very large so you're taking non-local measurements right every cell knows
what's going on everywhere else because your measurement is now a function of a much larger
area when you try to remember what is the right set point your computational capacity is now huge
whereas before you might only be able to remember a few very small things well now you're a big
network now you might be able to remember all kinds of things right and your action whereas
before you were a single cell able to take local actions as a collective you might do all kinds
of interesting things you might bend you might deform like a sheet you could do all sorts of
things but they're large things so everything scales up right the other interesting thing that
happens here is that you scale you scale stress and what i mean by that let's just think about this
for a second why when you're when you take a measurement and it's not correct why do you
take any action to fix it the way biology tends to handle it is by stress so stress is proportional
to that delta between the current state and the preferred state and and what it does is try to
minimize stress as long as that stress is high i'm going to take action and when the stress goes
low enough then i can relax everything's cool right that's something like that so what you can
do is so just imagine if you're a single cell by proper by by by releasing your stress molecules
and propagating them out to your neighbors you make your problem becomes their problem whereas
before if you were stressed out let's say you're a cell that is sitting in some other cells and
you're in the wrong location you need to be up here but you're down here and you have some
amount of stress over that if you just keep your stress you will stay there and no one will get out
of your way and you cannot move if you start to propagate your stress outwards remember it's
will be the same stress molecule as all the other cells have so they're stressed too everything gets
a little more plastic everybody everybody's sort of willing to change and it doesn't have to be in
physical space right it could be in physiological states it could be in transcriptional states
whatever but that stresses it makes everything a little more plastic and then you can go where
you need to go and then the stress will drop again so it doesn't make anybody more altruistic
what it does is everybody acts because they want to reduce their stress not because they care about
you but it's a very cool mechanism to take to to to to scale up goals because it because your
local goal becomes everybody's goal because everybody wants you to stop stressing so you
can stop stressing them out so so so that that kind of process and i mean i'm only telling you the
part that we i think we have a little bit of insight to there are many things here that we
don't understand that kind of process enables cells that care about little tiny things okay to
start to have bigger goals the scaling of goals whereas before your goals were physically in
terms of space and time very small now they're starting to get bigger and this is how you have
goal and a talk goals in the anatomical space so let's make you know let's make a limb or whatever
that that could be a story of scaling okay so like right now it just seems like you know it's
for you it's like daily work basically and it's you deal with this on daily basis but basically
what you just said is some really important insight starting by okay there is some bio
electrically imprinted information and not you know neuronally binded so it's just by you know
any cell and it makes sense because you know neurons are also you know a cell so it makes
sense that other cells they have ion channels they have different kind of channels and they can
make gradients as well so why not make bioelectric gradients so this is like the first huge huge
insight and i think you know a lot of your work kind of stands on that as well i think and it's
so important and what is then i was i was listening to your other some other interviews and work as
well and the the thought of agent of agency of individual of self by forgetting who i am and
you know kind of mind melting together that's just that's really brilliant and i wanted to you know
there is this thing where the bio bio electrically imprinted information could could also get
decoupled as well and it just came to my mind because the decoupled did that decoupled bio
electrically imprinted information uh is also um is also similar to what happens with cancer am i
right or yeah yes no yeah i just wanted to i had to thought where if there is like maybe that's just
you know i'm thinking out loud but you were talking about the stress and the amplifying of
stress basically a little bit so what if there is like too much stress and some of the cells kind
of decided oh my god this is like too much out of this whole agent like it's too much i'm gonna you
know head out and leave this entity there and i'm gonna you know play by myself maybe is that
something that we might think about i think that's a very reasonable idea we are testing exactly that
hypothesis uh i don't have the answer for you yet but uh i think by the end of the year we
should know something about this i think i think yeah i think that's completely reasonable i mean
these electrical networks let's just take a take a step back here um if we think about all the cool
things that brains do right so they have memory they can pursue goals they have preferences all
these things where did all these things come from so of course they didn't just sort of evolve out of
the arise out of nowhere they they evolved from much more simple versions of the same thing and
as far as we can tell what basically evolution did was pivot some very early biophysical tricks
into different problem spaces so cells were first solving problems in metabolic space and then
physiological space and then transcriptional space uh and then morpheus space and later
three-dimensional space when muscles and neurons came aboard right so we have to think about about
about this kind of intelligence long before three-dimensional space and in fact evolution
discovered that electrical networks are really great for this kind of thing very long time ago
so for example there's some beautiful work on bacterial biofilms where even even bacterial
biofilms can do some of these brain-like things so ion channels were were at the beginning you
know there's some great neuroscience koshland did some great neuroscience and bacteria should
looking at how ion channels work and now the the modern uh work uh is is is really showing that
this is this stuff is ancient so what it was used for before was to navigate something called morpheus
space which is the space of anatomical configurations right what shape should we be navigating that
space is exactly the same problem as navigating three-dimensional space there are good regions
there are bad regions there are barriers sometimes you find yourself not where you expected you have
to figure out how to get to where you're going you have limited uh energy you have limited ability
to see where what's what's around you exactly the same problems and so and so biology um uh
you know it was was using these electrical networks very early and so and so what happens
in uh in multicellularity is that cells join together into these electrical networks
to more intelligently navigate that space but as you just pointed out that uh that process
can break down it has failure modes and one failure mode is and of course we know that
that all kinds of stresses can lead to cancerous transformation one failure mode is when the
cell is electrically disconnect and it doesn't have to be caused genetically although it can be
the first thing that oncogenes tend to do is to is to electrically uncouple cells
shutting down gap junctions is one of the first things that that oncogenes tend to do
once the cells uh electrically disconnect then as far as they're concerned the rest of the body
is just external environment so that boundary between me and the outside world can grow and shrink
it can grow during evolution uh or and it can shrink during cancer where the cancer cells are
not any more selfish than the other cells they're just have smaller cells right like everybody's
equally selfish in biology just sometimes your self is huge and sometimes your self is sometimes
your self is tiny and and exactly as you said those cells might say okay i'm out of this network
and as soon as you unplug you no longer see the bigger the bigger goal which is to build a nice
limb or a kidney or a liver or something like that what you see is your your ancient unicellular
goals which is what for to become two cells for every cell to become two cells and then to go
wherever life is good and that's metastasis basically so do i understand it well in my mind
just appeared some uh hierarchy of identities uh from the little cell to the multicellular
organism of or a multicellular group and uh i would like to ask you if i understand it well that
what binds these cells together what binds their intention together so they're able to make a limb
is uh these uh electric by bioelectrical networks and in these bioelectrical networks
there is a working some kind of uh memory like can i uh can i can i imagine like that oh yes yes
yes it is literally and it is it is literally a kind of memory and i say that because i mean think
about um so in all of these things all all agency claims okay this is my perspective of course all
agency claims meaning how intelligent is something what kind of agency it has are really engineering
claims they're not philosophical claims they're engineering claims that need to be tested by
experiment so if i tell you if i show you a new device and i say to you this is a homeostatic
device it's a it's i say it's it's it's it's it has the cognitive level of a thermostat it's able to
it's able to pursue local goals and and that's that's what it has right what i'm telling you
really is it's not it's not a you know kind of a philosophical claim it's it's engineering it means
that if you in order to test this idea you should say okay if you are correct then three things have
to be true we have to find how the set point is encoded because because the because the because
any homeostatic system has to encode a set point we have to be able to decode that information meaning
read what is the set point i have to be able to read it and then we have to be able to change it
rewrite it in a way that does not require physically rewiring the rest of the machine
in order to change it if you have to rewire the whole machine then you didn't give me a thermostat
you gave me a mechanical clock or something like this right that does not rise to the level of a
thermostat with the magic about a thermostat is that i don't need to know how the rest of it works
and i don't need to rewire the whole thing all i need to know is where is the set point how do i
read the set point and how do i write the set point and then something beautiful happens i
read i reset the goal and the machine takes care of the rest right that's an engineering dependency
it means that if i if i use this in my you know in my bigger device i don't have to micromanage
the temperature i let this thing take care of it right that's those are that's what an agency
claim is it's how much um how much can you trust something to do in your own absence basically
right that's that's my view of agency so so uh so why do we so so let's let's test this out how do
we call it a memory if if um let's say uh so so here's good to talk about this model system of
flatworms so flatworm is a little free living thing called a planarian it has a head and a tail
and uh you know they're very cute they have a true brain lots of internal tissues and things like that
um they have many interesting properties one of the interesting properties is that you can cut
them into pieces and every piece regrows exactly what's missing not only does it regrow what's
missing but the piece actually shrinks so that by the time the new head and tail come up of course
they're small the whole thing will be proportional right so it's very cool everything is scaled down
and and you get a perfect little worm so you might ask the question okay so you might say okay uh we
here we have two hypotheses hypothesis number one is that this is a a purely emergent mechanical
process so all the cells locally do whatever they do based on local rules and uh that's it
whatever happens happens that's that's the standard null hypothesis uh some years ago i made a different
hypothesis and i said okay i think there's more intelligence here than that i think it's a homeostatic
system which means that i think this thing actually remembers what a correct planarian is supposed to
look like now that's a very that's a very weird kind of claim because uh you know first of all
people like to reserve these kind of terms for complex you know they say what do you mean it
remembers right well i remember things i'm like well you know memory there's all kinds of memories
and you're not the only thing that can remember things um and so and so i said that's okay let's
see let's see if the memory paradigm helps us here at all so so so we started looking and we found
out we found out three things we found out that a if you actually look at the bioelectrical pattern
and the way you do that is using these voltage sense that a fluorescent dye so it's a chemical
you throw it on and it basically glows depending on the local voltage concentration
it's a it's the whole the whole thing by the way is a version of we we i i we steal all kinds of
ideas from neuroscience because it's all the same stuff so so this is basically the notion of neural
decoding right this idea that they have a neuroscience that if we just scan the brain and we if we
understood how to decode it we would see your memories and your plans and your you know all the
mental content that you have so i said okay let's see if we can do this for the rest of the body
let's see i'm going to take seriously the idea that the body is a collective intelligence of cells
the same way that we are a collective intelligence of neurons right we're bags of walking neurons
basically so i said okay let's take seriously this idea that that that there's a collective
intelligence that navigates morpho space now in morpho space there are two headed worms and one
headed worms and triangular heads and flat heads is all this stuff in morpho space these animals
are amazing at navigating that space right the way that rats can navigate mazes these guys navigate
morpho space it's okay well let's take seriously the idea that this is a collective intelligence
it's navigating morpho space that means that somewhere there's going to be a memory of where
it's going let's see if we can see this memory so we found out that yes in fact we can see a
bioelectric pattern that tells you how many heads a piece is supposed to have we then we said well
now let's rewrite it and so the way we can rewrite it is you can make a computational model that will
say this is what the pattern of the tissue looks like now which what what channels do I need to open
or close to make the pattern be different okay and this is of course is what we're working now for
biomedicine this is this is the big you know kind of the big idea is that if you can predict what
what channel opening and closing would get you to the right state maybe you can address all kinds
of defects and things like that so so so we found some some drugs that open and close ion channels
and we converted that one head uh kind of pattern to a two head pattern no genetic change meaning we
don't do no CRISPR no genomic editing no trans genes we don't do anything genetically but what we found
is is two amazing things once you do that if you injure the animal it then will consult the pattern
see that oh two heads okay and it and it builds a two-headed worm right no problem the cells don't
care because that is their reference the cells have no idea that anything is wrong because that is
what tells them what they're supposed to be in the first place so that's the first thing the second
thing we found is that that electric circuit is amazing because it has it it's it's it's really
is a memory because once you convert them to two-headed it stays two-headed so you can cut them
again and again and again and they will continue to wait that that circuit once you've switched it
so so you can think about it like that okay so so so then you ask so where was the number of heads
encoded really right was it encoded in the genome you might want to say that because
all standard worms look the same so maybe the so it has to be somewhere it's right on the other
hand clearly it's not completely determined by the genome because we just made a line of of of
two-headed worms that that has nothing genetically wrong with them so here's the here's the I mean
so here's the kind of analogy that I that I like what the genome gives you is a piece of hardware
meaning that genome sets all the channels and all the other stuff it it it encodes a piece of
hardware that very reliably when the power is first turned on when the thing is first alive
and the physiology is going it very reliably settles into a particular state when you buy a
calculator you imagine you you get it you get a parts list that has a bunch of electronic parts
you assemble them according to the to the schematic you turn on the power and the little lcd it says
zero every single time you do it a thousand times every single time it starts at zero okay great so
it's reliable it says zero but then you realize that hey wait a minute this thing is actually a
programmable calculator which means that if I give it some inputs not to rewire it I can put away my
soldering iron right I don't need to rewire it but I can give it some input some brief you know
taps on the buttons that change the electrical signal just for a brief amount of time then I can
make the thing instead of zero I can make it say something else and in fact it has a memory and tomorrow
it will say something else again it will you know still have the same thing so so this is what I
think happens I think evolution builds hardware that is reprogrammable that has a default a very
reliable default state but that's not the only state and we have many many other interesting
experiments with xenobots and other things that can tell that that tell you that the default
behavior of this thing is not the only behavior that's just the kind of you know the default
behavior so is this feature what you call anatomical homeostasis that like every cell has its
local position in some some group or some or some body and it has some kind of a latent memory
that gets activated in times of need for example in some in some damage or when it needs to
again regenerate something yes except that I don't think it's a single cell level memory
I don't think the single I mean single cells also have memory of course but I think but the
thing that we're talking about now is a property of the network not of individual cells and we've
shown the we have many examples where you can mix things around and it doesn't matter where they go
the whole the the collective it's the collective is what stores and and we're pretty used to this
right with holographic theories of memory with neural networks where it's not the individual
neurons that know anything it's the network that knows something so I think I think that's
the you know bi-electricity is not a single cell the exciting the exciting part of bi-electricity
is not the single cell property it's the network property yes yes I meant it this way like the
the cell perceives the information that flows from the cells around and just this this flow of
information that these cells can perceive their position in the body and their role and what they
are supposed to make as a position and function I mean think about think about you know in the
the more familiar version in the brain your brain is an electrical network that makes decisions
and then issues commands to muscle cells right to implement to implement to move you through
three-dimensional space electrical circuits in the body are exactly the same thing but they
issue commands to other cell types not just muscle to move you through anatomical space
they don't move you through three-dimensional space although there are systems where that's the
sit you know that that merges kind of tightly but but they they're moving you through morpher space
and it's the exact same thing it's the it's the the decision-making in the electrical network and
then signals are passed down to let's activate some genes let's act let's activate some some cell
migration differentiation proliferation cell death all of this stuff is downstream of that
can you tell us more about your experiments for example that one that when you created
an eye a third eye on the frog so okay so so there's two there are two different types of
experiments there the first one has to do with bioelectricity and it's this idea that we we we
we looked at the the early frog embryo and in the early frog embryo you can see that an
electrical pre pattern that tells you where all the organs of the face are going to be right you
can already see them it's it's cool because it's it's a it's an easy pattern to start with because
some of them are incredibly complicated and you don't know what the encoding is the face one is
really nice because you can see it i mean it basically looks like a face so there's not much
decoding that needs to happen it looks like a face some of them are really complicated so so you
can ask the question and we actually did the eye experiments before we even knew about the face but
but you know this i'm telling you in a way that makes the logic clear you might ask the question
if this bioelectrical state tells the system where to put the eye what happens if we if we
copy that state somewhere else because that's how you want to test it because otherwise you might
say well that pattern doesn't do anything it's just kind of a epi phenomenon it's a byproduct right
so so now we got to do the functional experiment so long ago and this is uh this is you know kind
of part of the story storytelling but when when we when we first started my lab i had a i had a
graduate student named Ivy Chen she was actually a dental student she became a dentist afterwards
she's not a scientist but but she but she was doing research in the lab and i had asked her to
inject some ion channels they happen to be curse 6.1 ion channels i asked her to inject some RNA
for curse 6.1 in weird places in the early frog embryo okay uh now at the time this is this was
considered ridiculous because i remember as a postdoc i i um i wrote away to all sorts i wrote
letters to all sorts of people working on uh neuroscience and gut physiology and kidney and
everything and i said look if you've cloned any ion channel genes send them to me and and i'm going
to try to to to you know to reproduce them somewhere else and i said look this is you're
crazy because because voltage is a housekeeping parameter and if you perturb the voltage everything
will just die and you will have uninterpretable phenotypes okay that was the standard assumption
and i was pretty sure that that that was that was wrong so i wanted to test that
so i asked her to to inject these these things and then and so so we inject them then we come back
six days later and uh and she says to me and something funny because she says um you know
they're full of these black dots and they said black dots um what is that let me look so i get
that i sit in front of the microscope together and i said oh my god look carefully at these black
dots these are eyes and so these tadpoles had eyes all over the place because what you what we were
doing is reproducing the electrical uh map that says build an eye here we were reproducing that on
the tail and the gut i mean anywhere and so we found out several important things that day one
is that in fact about voltage is not just a housekeeping parameter it is uh it is
instructive for a very subtle thing for first shape number two it's extremely modular the
architecture of the animal is modular because we didn't have to provide all the information on
how to make an eye i mean can you imagine how many different cell types and the or you know the
positioning this goes back to your first question of where does the shape come from right we didn't
have to say well here's how you make an eye first you need a lens and then a retina then we have to
do any of that we we provide a very simple piece of bioelectric information this is your voltage
pattern so that looks like a very much like a subroutine call right when you program you have
a subroutine call which is a simple trigger that kick starts a very complex set of a set of actions
third uh the eyes formed and then they stopped so again that that that module that subroutine
is self-contained we'd make an eye and then that's it we didn't have to tell it when to stop it didn't
you know sort of make a gigantic eye that took over the whole embryo we've made a
paranormal eye and then it stopped and then so so so so i what that's i guess four things
so the fifth thing is that if you look at the developmental biology textbook it will tell you
that only the anterior norectoderm is competent to make eye right it will tell you that all the
other tissues cannot make eye why does they say that because the pack six master eye gene in frog
anyway only works in front of you know basically in front of the brain the anterior norectoderm
that's wrong many tissues are competent to make eye including gut and tail and all kinds of other
stuff but pack six doesn't do it because pack six is not the top of the hierarchy the top of the
hierarchy is the voltage and the voltage will of course turn on pack six in these other organs
we so we can see it but that's not enough that's not by itself that's not sufficient but but but
what it means is that our our view of the of the competency of these other cells is limited by the
way the way we ask the question how you probe it and that's actually really important not until
fairly recently did it what did i appreciate the irony irony that nowadays we're i'm studying you
know weird unconventional intelligence and telling people that well you can't guess correctly the
intelligence if you don't ask it in the right way but we were already seeing this in 2001 we
were already seeing that really that right that that that's that that's the fact and the other
thing we learned which was also super cool is this imagine that when you inject the RNA into the
embryo you put in a lineage tracer so you can see every cell that gets your RNA becomes blue
with beta gal beta galactosidus so you can tell which cells got your RNA so what we saw was this
was this very interesting thing where if you have a for example a lens sitting in the tail of a
tappel somewhere you take a section through it and you look only half of it is blue so what that
means is that if we don't get if we don't convert enough cells to do this the cells that are making
a lens they will recruit their neighbors they know there's not enough of them to make a good lens
they will recruit a bunch of neighbors that themselves did were not affected by us at all
and say hey you're part of this project now you need to make this lens so there's two levels of
instruction right we instruct the cells hey make a lens right here but i'm not going to tell you how
to do that in fact i'm not even going to affect enough cells and those cells say okay well i'm
going to instruct my neighbors and then we're going to build this thing right so several several
layers of instruction so this was so so that's so that's one story of the eye there's another
eye story which is not bioelectric that story is that Doug Blackiston who was at the time of
postdoc in my group now he's a staff scientist he um he took eye primordia cells so the cells that
are going to later become eye and he stuck them on the back of a tappel they of a frog embryo
they these cells not first of all so here's the amazing things about that first they still make
a great eye even though they're in a completely bizarre environment so instead of being near
the brain they're sitting in the middle of muscle no problem they make they make an eye number two
they have an optic nerve that comes out where does this optic nerve go it doesn't go to the
brain it's it sometimes it goes nowhere sometimes it goes to the spinal cord okay so it synapses
onto the spinal cord number three those animals can see perfectly well out of those eyes because
we tested them this is the craziest part we tested them in this visual learning assay so we
had this like moving blue light and we wanted them to move away from the from the blue light right
and and they do they can see perfectly well if they don't have any other eyes but an eye on
their backs they can see and so and so think about this right this this brain that evolved
for millions of years to expect visual input from specific location now you suddenly you have this
weird patch of itchy tissue on your back that's providing some sort of electrical tingling
up your spinal cord your brain could say oh yeah that's visual data no problem I can work with that
and uh and it's fine right this has this is massive implications for evolution remember at the
beginning I said that that middle layer has competent has intelligence that helps evolution
and think think about this imagine you have a mutation like all like all mutations it has
multiple consequences one mutation is that your eye ends up on your back okay the second the way
but it has other effects that might be good if a right if a creature was hardwired this eye on
your back you wouldn't be able to see your fitness is zero you're dead that's it and so evolution
never experiences the benefits of this other again never explores the benefits of the mutation
whereas here for in this example in other examples if your eye is on the back well I can still see
it's fine so now your fitness is not zero now you get to explore well what else did we what
else do we have that might be good so it turns that competency turns negative mutations which
are most of them right deleterious mutations it turns many of them into neutral mutations because
man we can live with that the the developmental process can can still they can still get their
job done you see this is the the goal directiveness of the eye even though even though its environment
has changed and the genes you know may have changed it it it can still get its job done
and that means that evolution now has a much nicer space to search because because those
competencies help smooth the evolutionary landscape so those are those are our two eye stories
before we get to another experiment I just wanted to kind of reflect and maybe sum up for me for
the listeners for us in this conversation there are many levels to this and we've kind of now
went through in our mind emergent properties that weren't encoded before as you said with the
with the marbles you know coming down and stuff like that this happens in our biology in our
organism and stuff like that and different kind of levels of emergence kind of happen and so right
now it if I understand it correctly right now we can think of these different levels and kind of
choose the level where it's the best for us like where is the best to act on our intention
basically if I if I want to have an eye on the back do I as you said do I you know do the molecule
or things or do I imprint the bioelectric pattern so we found out you found out that okay
that's a better way to imprint the bio bioelectric pattern so right now it's such an interesting
field because there are some I was wondering about a question if if you can basically learn
those goals throughout evolution so in evolution we have this random process that ends up in some
form of organism does it learn to have a goal basically is like it's like some intentionality
or like theological side of things because you've said in interview with chonkerl that the biologist
and biologist like kind of theophobic but there we can see that there are some goal and goal
directedness and it's on many levels not only on the basic level of genes but okay there is this
goal directedness developed on the level that emerged out of you know so that's like so interesting
for me how do you think about that yeah yeah yeah you said many interesting things here um
let's let's uh kind of for a bigger context um the the reason for the teleophobia is that
at the beginning of of science basically there were only two options you you were either uh
very smart like a human or you were very stupid like a rock those were your two options right
there was there was true intelligence and then there was mechanics clocks and you know things
like that when you have those two options and you want to do science of course you know it
forces a binaryization where you start to look at everything as a clock because because no one
knew how to analyze things that were smart like humans so you said fine everything we're going to
pretend everything is a clock and we're going to just find out how the hardware works i i but but
the thing is now now it's time to to realize that since the 40s the 1940s we've had a science of
machines with goals cybernetics control theory okay so it's no longer magic we don't need we there's
nothing theological here there's nothing magical here we don't need any of that what we have now
is a good science that tells us it's a continuum it's not just dumb like rocks and smart like humans
there are uh it's a it's a it's a whole continuum along the way and that means that when you analyze
your system you don't have to pick one or the other you can make engineering claims about
where you think it is and then we will test those theories and either we will find out that oh you
overestimated and it's not really that smart or you underestimated and it's much smarter than you
thought but these are all now uh experimental questions the thing that drives me crazy is that
people will often vocalize their their feelings about oh uh this can't be this and this can't be
that these are not philosophical questions these are these should be empirical questions and so
and so you asked the most um you you you got right on on to the most important thing which is
what is the best level of control because because someone might say and people have said to me is
oh i see uh because you are showing how the bioelectrical decision propagates down to the
gene expression level right so i mean of course it does they say oh well it's just chemistry and
physics i said well what did you think it was going to be of course it's chemistry and physics but
but right underneath everything is chemistry and physics obviously but you are making a very specific
claim if you if you try to manipulate down at the lowest level let's find out let's find out who
has the better control you can try to control 10 000 genes every couple of minutes so but you know
and control it that way or you can go upstream and try to change the the the decision making of the
system okay we've now shown many examples where where the latter is is much much better because
and we already know right we already know that uh when i have the slide that i always show in
talks of what computer programming looked like in the 50s right what do you do you sit there
plugging you know plugging wires back and forth okay that work does does anybody want to program
that way nowadays right for most things i mean it's it's so difficult to program at the hardware
level it's just really hard so neuroscience is kind of on board with these multiple levels because
you know that if you have a problem with maybe it's a molecular problem so maybe somebody's missing
a neurotransmitter fine or maybe it's a it's a sort of behavioral problem so somebody might
need the behavioral modification therapy or something then or maybe it's a psychological
issue or maybe someone has read too much existentialism and now is depressed you know
that's not really a solvable by by neurotransmitter manipulation right that's a that's a that's a
completely different thing so so we kind of know that there are these different levels and and things
are handled at the should be handled at the appropriate level so we've made this so we made
this argument that that a lot of interesting regenerative medicine is only going to be achievable
when we are when we are no longer afraid to deal with the system at higher levels maybe we can
train tissues maybe we can talk about risk assessment by tissues a lot of the things that
are happening you know active inference perceptual control theory a lot of the things that are
happening in neuroscience are directly applicable to to other cells that are not brains and they
require us to understand many levels not just the molecular level maybe not even the bioelectric
level at some point you know we can train right imagine humans have been training animals for
thousands of years knowing zero neuroscience right you don't need to know what's what's inside
the brain as long as you understand that hey the system can learn and i know what the currency of
motivation is meaning rewards and punishments then that's it it doesn't matter what's really in there
so so maybe at some point for some things we can even go beyond and say i don't know what the
correct bio electrical state is but i'm going to train the cells for a specific outcome can you
train a genetic genetic pathway or something like that because i think you've talked about that a
little bit yeah yeah and we're not we're not the first lab to show that Richard Watson's group
and a couple of others shown something similar this is this is a good example of my point that you
can't just have feelings about these things you have to do experiments so for example if i show
you a gene regulatory network right you know so it's a bunch of transcription it's a bunch of
genes and they all transcriptionally regulate each other up or down you look at this thing and you
say wow this is the paradigm of genetic determinism there's no magic here there's no indeterminism
here uh it's i can see exactly how this works it's just it's just it's just physics right it's just a
piece of physics okay but nevertheless the question might become well what cognitive level does it have
if you if you assume from the beginning that it has zero meaning that the only way i can control
this is i can change the trans the promoters so that the i can delete nodes i can add nodes physical
rewiring you can do certain things so we and others as i say have done something like this we took the
made the assumption that actually let's find out right let's find out and so we took this the with
this the models of these of gene regulatory networks and we pretended they were neural
networks and we tried to train them what that means is that you pick some nodes you pick one
gene as your condition stimulus one gene as your unconditioned stimulus one other gene as a
as a response and you simply ask does the history of tweaking meaning up or down regulating these
inputs change the way it reacts to those inputs later on i mean that's learning right that's the
we found so in our work i'll just talk about they'll talk about ours um and this is uh sarama
biz was was the postdoc who did this uh she found six different types of memory including
pavlovian conditioning so like uh you know pavlov's dog right with the so so so she found that
biological networks can have many types of memory like this control random networks right so you just
just you know designed random networks they don't tend to have this property which suggests that
evolution actually likes this for whatever reason evolution actually favors uh this property of
being able to being able to learn and it has it has amazing implications for uh for biomedicine
because it means imagine right imagine the thing about the pavlovian conditioning imagine you have
a drug that is very powerful it works very well in the petri dish but you can't use it in humans
it's too strong so now if your disease circuit has this associative learning property it means that
maybe you can give that drug together with a completely neutral drug which we call we call
that in the in the in the review we call that a um a molecular placebo you take another drug that
doesn't do anything and you pair them together and you just give them together if the system learns
to associate them then maybe after a few presentations now you can just use the the neutral one and you
don't need the you know you don't need the really strong one right so and then maybe at some point
it will give up the way the dog you know if you keep ringing the bell the dog will give up eventually
eventually so maybe then you have to retrain you know I don't know but but but you get the idea so
so so this this is this is just a good example that you can't assume about these things you have to
you have to make hypotheses about cognitive level and then you have to test them I really like this
concept of both ways of control that the first way is bottom up it's from genes that there emerges
proteins and our other emergent structures and the other way around is from top down that these
electrical patterns can influence the genetical level and I would like to ask you like from your
experiment with the eye is it possible to get this eye passed to another generation that it's
like incorporated in the genome uh yeah uh we don't have any evidence that this feeds back into
the genome so it's fine now we haven't done the experiment but but I don't have any reason to
believe that the next generation of frogs would have this eye however um in the case of the planarian
it's a little more subtle because planaria normally reproduced by tearing themselves in half
and then regenerating and now you have two worms when that happens a two-headed planaria does give
rise to another two-headed planarian so it's not the same as sperm and egg reproduction it's not
classic uh lomarchism because you're not uh changing the hereditary material
but let's be careful you're not changing the DNA but DNA is not the only hereditary material and in
planaria the bioelectric circuit is also a hereditary material in fact there's others so so with
Chris Fields we wrote a something that show that talked about the fact that when you look at you
you know look at you look at any organism and look at the history all of its parents what molecules
are directly conserved through that whole lineage well certainly the DNA that's the whole point right
that the genome is passed on but there's two other things that are passed on one is the cytoskeleton
every cell's cytoskeleton is directly templated off of the previous cytoskeleton right and it's
also the cell membrane because the cell membrane also is so so and and also there are bioelectric
circuits who knows what else right there may be nine other you know media that are that we just don't
know about yet I don't know but but but at least in planaria you can take advantage of this additional
hereditary medium that's not genetic do do vertebrates have that I don't know there's some
nice work from Oded Rachavi in C. elegans where he studies transgenerational inheritance and so
there certainly are mechanisms for passing things back into the genome whether the bioelectrics does
this or not I I don't know we were talking about different levels of emergence basically but and
also the phenomenal work of six types of learning of these genetic networks basically and pathways
and stuff like that so I wanted to explore a bit more of these you know higher levels of
maybe cognition and get to minds because that's also another emergent level and we can think of
okay so right now I could tweak your brain and you would get in very very complicated way
the same information maybe as I'm speaking to right now but it's much more simple for
simpler for me to speak these words and move in this level of cognition basically and I was wondering
you know this gets us to there are many many weird kind of ideas how to get into with your
intention how it affects your body basically and it's also possible as well we've talked about it but
this is so interesting because right now we can kind of test it test it scientifically and test
how how could placebo work and what how strong the intention of this level where we kind of move
together how strong it is and how it actually affects the body and and the whole organism and
it does right because like you have these like you can think about something I don't know stressful
and suddenly you know your your body is secreting stress hormones and wow it affects things
affects the cells and the cells are connected and it affects the whole organism so how do you think
about our intention let's say power of our intention and how it affects the body and and yeah well a
couple things first you know if I were to tell you that you can voluntarily change the voltage
potential of cells in your body 30% of the cells in your body you could voluntarily change the
voltage potential you might say wow that you're crazy how am I going to change voltage potential
in my cells but in what but when you're lying down in the morning and you decide to stand up
guess what you're doing right you're changing the bioelectric state of your muscles so so we already
know that your intention can absolutely change the electrical state of your cells and and of
course the chemical and many others as you point out so so lots of people study the the
interface the immune the immune system interface to to the body many many other things people have
found effects on on stem cells from from meditation and certain kinds of practices so of course the
the link the link is is is strong um the thing that the thing that I would say is that I I
because because of this continuum right the fact that we were all one cell at one point in your
life you were one cell nine months and some years later you can say I am you know people
you get up a human who will say things like I am not a machine I am more than physics well
you used to be a you used to be a quiescent oocyte is what you used to be and and slowly
with right and the key the key is developmental biology does not offer any particular point
where some kind of lightning flash comes in ah now you have a mind before that you were just
chemistry right okay that doesn't happen so so so this thing is completely slow very you know
sort of step by step gradual so for me this means that if if I like to think backwards a lot of
people say paramecium has a mind come on single cells don't have mine I like to work it backwards
if we can agree that we have minds then you owe a story about where they came from and that story
cannot be well on day 59 you know this happened there's that's that's ridiculous and so so then
the story has to go all the way back and so once you have that you can you can say that I think
I think we can conclude a couple of things one is that minds change obviously the mind of a cell
is not the mind that we have now and there are many things in between and there are many alien
kinds of minds that we make with AI and with various other things and who knows what in the
universe who knows what else is out there they change that's a and b we are I think we are
very bad at recognizing unconventional intelligence I'll just give you a simple example we are born
with our sense organs looking out into the three-dimensional world where medium size objects
move around at medium speeds and that is our training set for look for for a for a recognizing
intelligence so when you see your cat or your neighbor or a bird or something else doing
something interesting you say oh look at this that's that's intelligence I see that that you know I
hid the you know I hid the reward from here to there and he still figured out how to get it or
you know you made the little you know the crows make the little tools to open the locks and do
all this stuff I recognize that as intelligence imagine if you were born with a an internal sense
of your body chemistry so a multi-dimensional sense of all the different chemicals in your blood
and you knew exactly what your liver and your pancreas were doing every moment of the day to
to adjust all of that stuff in that case you would understand that there is such a thing as
physiological space you would understand what intelligence looks like in physiological space
you would say oh my liver is really intelligent because it's able to do all these amazing things
despite different perturbations you would recognize that implants right like like smart
insulin pumps and pacemakers and things like that are robots that work in physiological space
right now when I say robot you imagine you know the the the Mars rover that drives around in the
or a self-driving car yeah that's great that's a robot in three-dimensional space we have robots in
physiological space right your your insulin pump that measures a bunch of stuff and gives you little
puffs of of insulin at just the right time it's navigating physiological space right but we don't
think about it that way right because because we are just you know sort of blind to all that stuff
because of our training set so I think I think that we need to understand that minds are incredibly
diverse minds come with all kinds of different bodies that we're not used to and and many more
will come I mean in your lifetime you're going to see creatures that just you know are completely
alien to us and synthetic and chimeric and cyborg and all that and and mind solve problems in in
novel spaces it's not all about movement and it's not all about three-dimensional space there are
there's intelligences all around us that are very hard to to see this brings a lot of ethical
questions about how we are moving through through the world what's what's your point what's your view
at the concept of the self identity because we are talking about intelligence at many layers
so what's your point on identity uh yeah there many things can be said it's a complex area of
course um I I one one thing that I have done is to try to come up with a framework where highly
diverse intelligences could all be um compared and recognized on the same in the same space so so
what I wanted to do and this was um this was a challenge put to us a few years ago at a meeting
in them of the Templeton Foundation they had asked us to come up with a framework to be able
to compare directly all kinds of unconventional intelligences you know and so and so some people
think you know octopus uh you know something or insects or something like that I want to go really
broad I want to be able to think about uh swarms I want to think about alien life forms I want to
think about AI I want to think about synthetic and chimeric intelligences other spaces like
really broad and so so what is a self right what what is how do you uh how how can you compare
all these different different things I think that uh cybernetics got it right with a focus on goals
so so so here's here's what I think a self is I think a self is a collection of parts that
are able to work together towards system level goals the goals that belong to that that collection
not to the individual pieces now one thing we can do is we can map out the size of your goals
so we can add in whatever whatever whatever those goals might be how about the size of them so if
you are so let's let's think of some examples if you tell me that my biggest goal the biggest thing
I can work and remember what a goal is a goal is some state that you can exert energy to reach
that state that's a goal so if you tell me that the biggest goal you can possibly think about
is the local sucrose concentration then I'm going to guess you're a bacterium of some sort and that
is your level okay if you tell me that uh you can have goals that reach forward a few hours and in
terms of space you can handle things that go on a few you know a few hundred feet in diameter
but that's about it I'm going to say well maybe maybe you're about the level of a dog meaning
that your dog has certainly some memory going backwards certainly some predictive capacity
going forwards it understands some amount of space but you can never get your your goal your dog to
work towards a goal that's three months from now in the next city over impossible right they just
can't handle that size of that's now now why do I say this right somebody if somebody somebody
could prove me wrong and then train their dog to you know to work towards things that are months
away I mean that's probably you know that's great then I'll change my example but but you understand
these are empirical claims there are minds that okay that have those kind of limitations then you
might tell me that well I have I have a goal that has to do with the the financial markets of the
next hundred years or you might tell me that while I'm really I'm really sad that the sun is going to
burn out you know billions of years from now okay then I'm going to say you're at least a human
because because your goal your goal and so I call this the cognitive light cone it's sort of the
boundary it's the size of the kinds of things you can have as goals not not not the distance you
can sense right because for example the tell it you know the James Webb telescope has a massive
distance of sensing that's not the point the point isn't about sensing the point is about
goal directedness so so you could be a human but then you might say to me you know uh I I I really
I I really I feel um I feel a certain way when something happens to to a thousand people
and when the same thing happens to a million people I'm not able to be a thousand times more
more upset I've just not I don't have that linear range I just can't do it and then we can start to
think about okay humans are probably not the top of the food chain at some point there will be a
massive intelligence that can literally in the linear range care about an enormous amount of
stuff that we can't even wrap our heads around right in terms of being a goal right so for somebody
like now now now there are of course traditions that talk about this right there are traditions
that talk about you know some sort of Buddha nature that where some where where something is
evolved to the point where they can literally care about all the sentient this sentient creatures
on on earth right maybe that's possible I have no idea if it's possible but you can think about
you know that humans are not the top of this this food chain so so for me in terms of um what a
self is a self is a temporary uh a temporary bundle of activities that works towards specific goals
so selves have goals they have preferences they have some
degree of competency in navigating various spaces maybe very high maybe low so so those are those
are selves and and of course selves are nested so in our body so we are a self we have many
selves inside of us most of which are nonverbal right not all of them but but most of them are
nonverbal and we are also part of probably larger selves that are you know social structures or who
knows what who knows what what's about us um and so yeah that anyway that's that's that's my talk on
the selves that's uh yeah that's um so interesting are you familiar with uh philosopher and Henry
Bergson uh he's yeah so his idea basically of of levels of consciousness was to do something with
indeterminism and it's so interesting and now you know you have uh you you just said okay my goal
is to get this so close okay it's probably a bacterium but you can create a space between the stimuli
or the goal and the many ways that can achieve that goal and that's basically the inter inter
indeterminism and that's basically the level of the self and maybe level of consciousness that
contains that self as well and i was just interested in the scaling of the goals i was
thinking one day okay what does how am i like how are humans motivated maybe a different
perspective on that and i was thinking okay so let's stretch out those homo static goals that we
have you know and the goals of you know the evolution has and if you stretch them out you you you can
maybe like okay why am i sitting in this room right now why was this building built and stuff
like that and this is basically this just stretched out basic homo static loop of my organism or of
you know this swarm of humans to get to a certain temperature and this is for me is so interesting
like scaling of goals and right now we are you know in the times of internet and we are connecting
right here right now and it's just um we think maybe this sci-fi that we're gonna get connected and
have you know or connected there there is going to be some higher level intelligence or self or
something like that but i think that as you've said we don't have insight into different level of
minds or different you know different minds all together so maybe there is already something
like that you know this like kind of this kind of hive mind but you know not really this like
like woo perspective but more like realistic perspective what's happening right now it's it
feels like it's actually here already a little bit so yeah there was just some thoughts on that
yeah i i think i know i think that's very important because we we're we're very bad at
recognizing ourselves at lower levels we're even worse at recognizing them at higher levels
we don't have really any tools so so so one can ask this question if if you were part of a larger
mind could you tell first of all could you tell could you gather evidence that you were part of
a larger cognitive system and b could you if if you could could you gain some understanding of
what the goals of that system were right which is very important because as humans if we're building
some kind of massive uh political economic structure whatever uh what are the goals of
that structure right well we this happens all the time we do internet of things we do swarm
robotics and then you say can okay we have any idea what this thing's gonna want to do when when
well you know when it when it boots up right so so the thing is that i have a feeling and i don't
know this for a fact but my feeling is that probably with some version of girdle's theorem
tells you that you are never going to really understand what the higher level is doing
very much like you know when you go to work and you you know you step or don't step on
some ant on your way to a meeting the ant has absolutely no no capacity to understand the
context of what it just participated in you know why this is happening right so so it's
entirely possible that we are the same right and if and people have said that to you know
why the universe works in mysterious you know ways the bigger patterns right um but maybe it's
possible and i don't know but but maybe it's possible with some kind of math or you know causal
information theory or something to start to gain evidence or or against the idea that we are part
of something larger and just to give you an example i spent a lot of time in the last few months
thinking about what it would be like to be a neuron or a subset of neurons inside a large
neural network that's being trained and you could imagine two ways imagine this conversation between
like two two neighboring subnets one says oh look uh we live in a cold mechanical universe
doesn't care what we do uh i can learn you know i can learn about things and uh and we live in a
we are an insignificant spec in this in this giant universe that doesn't care about anything
there are no larger minds we are the only thing you recognize like this is you recognize this this
the story this is the this is the standard scientific story of today right we live in this
you know um mechanical cosmos that doesn't care what we have the other the other the neighbor says
you know i'm not so sure i i've been i've been tracking things here and i can tell you that
every time i do certain things life is good but when i do other things this this this massive
wave of punishment right this back propagation wave comes and smacks me and and forcibly changes
my voltage and does all this other stuff and i'm starting to think that the universe but at my
you that our universe actually does care what we do and in particular for some reason right you
know this have you seen um google deep dream have you seen these things it's like it makes it makes
it and then all these pictures have dogs in them because they're always running around well and so
i can imagine right so this is total fantasy of course but you get you get you get the idea
i can imagine that this one says look i i don't know i i cannot comprehend the the the thought of
our universe but i think it likes dogs because every because because every time i find an i like
every time i output this dog i life is good and otherwise i get you know corrected or something
like this right and and so you could easily imagine right the in in that universe the the
the one that thinks that it lives in a mindless world is wrong it's it's factually wrong the
quite right the question so now the question is for us the question is what is the right
view i mean there are certainly people who feel that there are patterns to life and that they
can know i mean i who knows right i don't nobody knows but but but i don't think it's crazy to
ask the following question this this is the distinction that i think is really important
are you learning or are you being trained what's the difference the difference is
in both in in both cases right in both cases you are engaging in something that is designed
to change your own mind when you are learning you pick up a book and learn stuff with the with
the inherent purpose of changing your own psychology and and by the way we are complex enough
that we are even subject to this idea of the thought that breaks the thinker right you can
imagine that if you're like really a kind of a deep thinker you might come across a piece of
literature or something that just screws you up completely and spirals you into some sort of
depression and whatever right but but we are we we know that we can learn and we can change our
mind but when we do that we assume that we are the only agent in that interaction so there's me
the agent and then there's the outside world and the outside world has zero agency and i'm the boss
i do what i want i can learn or i can not learn whatever the or i am provided with inputs and i
am changed the way that i would look but i don't know that the outside world has zero agency you
know that's that's an assumption we don't actually know that and under certain circumstances you
would be wrong to assume that if you're a neuron in a neural network you'd be wrong to assume that
so i don't know i'm not claiming i'm making no claims whatsoever about anything like that but
i'm just saying that i think i don't think it's a crazy question at all to try to develop some
sort of mathematical formalism to try to gain evidence for being part of a larger system even
knowing that you will never understand the whole goal you don't know what space it works in
but maybe you can see your option space being deformed in some way that is that is consistent
with with a not a zero agency on the other end so you just put a framework to a lot of you know
kind of these i don't know it feels like you are part of the universe you are not separated
from it and there is something maybe something maybe mysterious and you you know you have
subjective experience and whenever someone asks me if i believe in something you know i usually
say i believe literally i believe in something i can't really i believe there is like something
else that i can actually perceive because i know i can perceive only you know just these little
things and i think this is such a nice logical logical framework to ask ourselves whatever this
mysterious thing might be and only you know only the thoughts that you put out there is so important
because many many people are on in in one camp on one extreme and they say ah definitely there's
i don't know from panpsychism from eastern philosophical perspective you know we are this one
hive mind one consciousness consciousness and or like transmit we are you know transmitters
or something like that and now you are putting frame to it and kind of asking real question
and asking real possibility of kind of you know testing it maybe mathematically some
sometime in the future or something and you are kind of okay so you're not on this extreme
not on this other extreme but you are in the middle and it feels like you are trying to not
to have an agency in in this or or something because yes that's the how it's supposed to be
done and not wish something is like that or like that because that's like actually going to affect
the the stuff that you do and that you are going to you know explore and stuff or discover so this
for me is really interesting way to putting to to put these things together and and think about it
and kind of the extreme the the extremize the world that we live in because there is a lot of
extremes and when we can have even as you know scientists and and researchers and everyone
when they can have this kind of um uh you know uh talk or something i or discussion i think it's so
important because otherwise we can't you know we can't move forward so i really am great grateful
for what you do and that you put the job that you are putting these frameworks out here out there
so yeah thank you for that well thank you yeah thank you i i do think it's important to two things
one is to as treat as many things as possible as empirical questions right once you say i believe
whatever it uh it it closes off the ability to test it first of all so we should always be working
to come up with some some way of making this practical and testable and that's a and b we
should realize that whatever your framework is it can it limits and enables different next steps
so it constrains you know if you if you never if you can never believe philosophically that
gene regulatory networks could have non-zero agency you will never do the experiment that we did
right planar you know planaria have been um uh have been studied since uh 1903 i believe uh right
you know and and two-headed animals have been produced right at the beginning of the last century
no one ever thought to cut to recut them to my knowledge no one ever recut them why because it
was perfectly obvious that that well genetically they're unchanged and when you cut off that second
head well of course they're going to go back to normal what else could it be and so so there are
so many experiments like this that we've done because uh each lens has things that it enables
and other things that it does not let you do and and as much of this as possible and the and the
biggest one of all is look there's a as scientists there's one thing that we all take on faith the
all science begins with an act of faith which is basically this idea that the world is understandable
right that there's a pattern behind it and then what we are doing is discovering a pattern nobody
no scientist can go to work saying i'm going to find a bunch of stuff today but tomorrow it'll
probably all be different that's great and like nobody believes that but you wouldn't do you couldn't
do science if you were some kind of you know if if hum was right and we were living in a
random uh you know just collection of randomness that has pockets of of of just by accident things
look like they make sense kind kind of in pockets if you had that view you would never be able to
do science science is predicated on on a complete leap of faith that has no no empirical justification
that that behind all of this stuff there is some kind of truth that we are getting to so so i think
you know i think we need to be honest with ourselves that that we all start in this in this field
anyway we all start with a bit of faith and then and then you move as much as you can to experiment
thank you for that michael what is your focus right now oh boy uh that's that's well uh and i
apologize i have about a minute and then then i have to run but uh you know we do a lot of things
in our lab i would say the focus of the whole group is to understand different kinds of minds
in various embodiments but that means regenerative medicine it means uh applications and birth
effects it means uh what cancer we do some uh synthetic biology synthetic morphology to make
artificial new proto organisms we do some artificial intelligence we do a lot of different
things all of them are around this this kind of question yeah uh michael i i'm so grateful for
your time thank you so much i think there is like questions of consciousness and regenerate
regeneration of limbs and stuff like that uh where do people find you uh you know leave us
some links or i think you're part of some company as well that is trying to research i think
regenerating limbs as well so could you could you link that everything is going to be in the
description and michael thank you so much for your time thank you so much i appreciate the
conversation i will i will email you a bunch of links yeah there's a couple of spinoff companies
all our stuff is on my website that you can see all that so yeah thank you so much and i'm happy
to talk to you guys anytime we can always do it again cool nice thank you very much bye have a
nice day bye