Now, instead of having to know all this, all the scales, the dominant, the subdominant,
one, four, five, blah, blah, blah, and all this diatonic harmony, it's impressive.
And now you can explain it if somebody asks you, but wouldn't it be nice to just get rid
of this and just have a circle?
Yeah.
Because watch what happens.
This is step number one, right?
This is four.
This is five.
This is two.
This is six.
And this is three.
All right?
Have you ever heard the term relative minor?
Every major key has a relative minor key.
All right.
Back to the husband and wife story.
Home, wife, husband.
All right?
If the husband leaves home, if the C chord goes to a G chord, almost always with the
GPS in my family, the Cecil's like, look, he loves that woman inside that GPS, okay?
She talks the whole time we're on a trip, but just get, get, get, get, turn left, turn
right.
You went too far.
Go back.
You just want to smack her.
Her name is Jill.
Yeah.
One goes to five.
The husband almost always knows how to get back home.
So if a C chord goes to a G chord, one to five, see, it always goes back to one.
If the wife leaves home, goes shopping, generally she can find her way back home too.
See, four goes to one.
But once in a while, I don't have a GPS.
So I have a tendency to get lost.
So I have to call the husband or go get him and then both go home.
See, use his GPS, then go home.
All right.
So C chord, if the wife leaves most of the time, she goes right back home.
Occasionally, one goes to four, goes to five.
One goes to four, goes to five, goes to one.
On the circle, I just go, okay, C goes to G, 99% odds that the third chord is going to
be G.
All right.
If a C chord goes to F, 85% odds, well, no, 90% odds that she's going to go back home too.
But if she doesn't go back home, she usually goes, gets the husband and then they go home.
All right.
That's how it works.
So if I'm not in the key of C, I'm in the key of F.
Look, what are the three major chords in the key of F?
F, B flat and C.
If F goes to C, what's the next chord?
F.
If F goes to B flat, what's the next chord?
Right.
All right.
How about the key of E?
E, B and A.
See how easy?
Yeah.
Now comes these other little guys, those minor, the relatives.
Okay.
I've got husband and wife all set with the home.
Then I've got these relatives out here.
All right.
The relative, the main relative is Uncle Albert.
We'll call him.
The relative's house is always at nine o'clock, right around the corner.
If the major chord is at 12 o'clock, the name of the key, the tonic, then the relative
minor is at nine o'clock, always.
And the one to the right of it and the one to the left of it are the other two minors.
So check it out.
In the key of C, this holds true, right?
See, look.
C, there's D minor right there, E minor and A minor and G and F.
So I have every step of the scale from eight o'clock to one o'clock.
And that is, and if I go all the way down, if I just cut the pie in half, there's that
B diminished chord.
That's the last note in that C scale.
So it's the pie, one o'clock, all the way to seven o'clock.
Those are all the chords that get used in the key of C.
Cool, huh?
If I put F at 12 o'clock, let's pretend that that's 12 o'clock, it would be F to E.
The major chords would be F, B flat and C and the minors would be D, A and G.
And G, I can't jump back there.
I have to take the road to get back there.
Thus comes my chord progression.
And I don't even need to think.
It's C, A minor, D minor, G, C.
If it jumps down here to E minor, look.
Say it.
C, E minor, A minor, D minor, G, C.
And there it is.
Everybody.
Aren't you glad you have a circle?
Okay, I'm in the key of B flat.
First chord is B flat.
Second chord is D minor.
What's the next chord?
G minor.
Next chord?
C minor.
F major, B flat.
Remember, one to the left, one to the right, or major.
The next three back are minor.
But there's always a flat.
Not always.
Depending on the melody and how the composer wrote the song,
sometimes these minor chords, which are supposed to be minor,
they just decide to make them major just because they can.
For example, this song.
Now, the first chord is C.
The problem is the composer probably wrote the melody
before he figured out the chords.
And he went 5-2.
There's a G sharp in the second major.
Big problem.
He tried every single one of those other chords in the key of C.
He tried F.
That didn't work.
He tried G.
He tried D minor.
That didn't work.
He tried D major.
See, none of them worked because the G sharp was in the melody.
From C all the way down to B,
what's the only chord in that segment that has a G sharp in it?
That's a quiet answer.
Spell the chords.
G B D, D F sharp A, A C sharp E, E G sharp B.
The E chord.
The E major chord has a G sharp in it.
So, I'll use that E chord.
Now, the rest is a no-brainer
because remember, I told you, you've got to take the road home.
What comes after E?
Now, he said it now is in major, so it's going to probably,
let's try A minor.
Oh, that's too depressing.
He left it major.
A, then what? A, then what?
D, then G, C.
And because most songs are divided into eight bar sections,
the next section did the same thing.
E, A, B, G, C.
Boring.
Yeah, but it's fun.
It's fun.
And you know what?
When you start using the circle, everything changes.
You start to go, wow, this song used to be hardened now.
I get it.
Okay, what if I want to play 5-2 in the key of G?
Oh, I can either sit down with my little pencil
and do what we did earlier,
or I can use my transposer on the organ,
or I can use logic here.
Now, in the key of C, my first note was E.
All right, I'm not going to use the circle to figure this out.
In the key of C, what step of the scale is E?
Use your fingers.
Three.
So in the key of G, G, A, B,
I'm going to start on B.
And I'm going to play all the ethnotes chart.
Okay?
So I'm going to start with a G chord.
All right, now, from the key of C,
I went all the way back to E.
The key of G, I'm going to go all the way back to what?
B.
What's my next chord?
G.
B.
Next.
A.
B.
Next.
G.
First time I did that, I'm so excited you thought I just wrote a symphony.
Something that small, that little accomplishment,
you stood there to go.
Wow, I changed the key.