All right. Welcome to this week's Non-Pictive Geometry and Topology Seminar. It's our pleasure
today to have Petr Zeeman from the Technical University of Denmark, who will tell us about
quantum automorphism groups of graphs.
Thank you for inviting me. So in this talk, I will talk about, as you said, quantum automorphism
groups of graphs, and this work is based on those two quite recent papers with those
people that are listed here.
And so I'm currently a postdoc with David Robertson, and the project we are working
on is in the intersection of graph theory and quantum information theory.
So somehow, graph theory is used to study some concepts in quantum information theory.
In particular, the area of graph theory is graphomorphisms, which I will talk about a
little bit. And at some point in some works, quantum groups of graphs occur, and these
two works are sort of like a bridge between those two areas in some sense, since probably
from the quantum group side, there are two groups of people that work on quantum groups
and that work on graph theory, and those groups usually don't know much about the things
that the other ones work on.
And basically, what I would like to a lot focus on in this talk is to show you some
techniques from combinatorics that we used to obtain some, like in combinatorics, the
combinatorial analog would be some simple results about automorphism groups of graphs,
but for some reason, these results did not at all exist in the relatively recent but
not that recent field of quantum automorphism groups of graphs.
So let's start with just the notion of the graph isomorphism. So two graphs are isomorphic.
Basically, if we can find a permutation or a bijective mapping between the vertices of
one graph to the other graph, such that this mapping preserves adjacencies and non-agencies.
So in other words, the graphs are exactly the same up to some relabeling of the vertices.
We denote it like this. And so alternatively, this alternative two points of view will play
a role here. So alternatively, one could view it if you take the adjacency matrices of the
corresponding graphs and you would have a permutation matrix that has to commute with
those adjacency matrices. So that's an equivalent definition of isomorphism of graphs.
And another very impressive theorem was given by Lova's in a previous century in 1967, which
basically characterizes this relation of being isomorphic by the following counting of homomorphism.
So homomorphism of between two graphs is like isomorphism, but you relax the condition a
little bit. It's a mapping that only has to preserve adjacencies. So for example, you
can have a homomorphism from a bipartite graph to an edge. So and this notation means that we
count the number of possible homomorphisms from some graph F to the graph G. So the isomorphism
relation between two graphs is characterized by homomorphism counting. So the homomorphism counts
the number of homomorphism from each possible graphs to those two graphs. If it's the same,
then the graphs are isomorphic and also the other way. Now it's not necessary to just restrict
ourselves to all graphs. We can use various families of graphs. So there is a similar
notion of homomorphism indistinguishability, where we take some family of graphs and do these
homomorphism counts within that family of graphs. And then we get a notion of homomorphism
indistinguishability, which depends on that particular cross of graphs. So here we have
a table of some results. And this is the Lovaas theorem, where we take the family of graphs
to be all graphs. And when you take various other, let's say, natural families of graphs,
you get other similarity relation between those classes of graphs, like for cycles. If you just
take cycles, then this corresponds to the cospectrality of adjacency matrices, which means
that the multisets of eigenvalues of the adjacency matrices of graphs is the same.
Cycles and paths would be cospectral components. Trees, this is actually fractional isomorphism.
So fractional isomorphism, you get by relaxing this equation here. So instead of a permutation
matrix, you would use something called doubly stochastic matrix, which is basically that the
rows have to sum to one. And then there is a class of bounded trivids, trivided most k.
And this corresponds to indistinguishability by something called k-dimensional Weisfer-Lehmann
algorithm, which I will talk about later. But it's just some procedure on graphs, but I will
talk about it. But trivid k is some parameter of graphs, which tells you how much the graph is
close to a tree. And then tree depth is something similar. So for various classes, we have notions,
and then this is the important one here, that if you take planar graphs, this is a quite recent
result that actually corresponds to a notion of quantum isomorphism. So homomorphism indistinguishability,
homomorphism indistinguishability when you restrict yourself to planar graphs. So in other words,
what we will see being quantum isomorphic, the result is that it's like having the same
homomorphism counts from planar graphs. So, okay, so just a little bit about what is this
quantum isomorphism. So this
that this small home, this is just numbers, numbers, yeah, yeah.
Number of homomorphism, yes. So this notion of quantum isomorphism comes from the notion of
a non-local game, which is an important concept in quantum information theory. I will just briefly
introduce it. So in the game, you have two players, Alice and Bob, and a verifier. And
both of the players have some finite input sets, X, A, X, B corresponding to those players,
and some finite output sets, Y, A, Y, B. And then you have a Boolean predicate, which is basically
a function, zero one function from this Cartesian product. And so basically the players are asked
a question from the input, and they have to answer, and the players win if this is evaluated to one.
They cannot communicate after receiving questions, but they can decide on a strategy,
what they will do. And there is only one round of the game, and one is concerned with perfect
strategies in which players win the probability one. And now what kind of strategies can you have?
You can have deterministic strategies, where you have just some functions, which deterministically
say what will be the answers for Alice and Bob. Then you can have randomized strategies, which
are not that much better, but where you can use some randomness potentially. And then you can
have quantum strategies, where this Alice and Bob will share some entangled quantum state and
use it to get answers. So let's immediately look at this GH isomorphism game. So we have two graphs,
G and H. And the intuition is that Alice and Bob want to convince the referee that the graphs
are isomorphic. So here is the setup basically similar that the Alice and Bob are asked some
questions. Well, now the questions are the input sets are the vertices of the graph,
also the output set. And what must be satisfied is that the relation between H and H prime is the
same as a relation between G and G prime. So relation in the sense adjacency, not adjacency.
So again, the players cannot communicate, there is only one round, and they must win with the
probability one. And the theorem is that basically these classical players can win classical in the
sense that they have like a deterministic strategy, if and only if the graphs are isomorphic. And now
to define the quantum isomorphism is to basically turn this definition around and say that the graphs
are quantum isomorphic if quantum players can win this game. So that's basically a definition that
the graphs are quantum isomorphic if quantum players can win this GH isomorphism game.
What does it mean just briefly is that here we have a shared entangled state between those
players. And basically, so Alice and Bob share this quantum system in some states psi,
which is basically a unit vector in some Hilbert space. And upon receiving this vertex G, Alice
performs some measurement e g and this e g is basically some set of operators satisfying
these conditions, which is based on the quantum formalism. And the same same is done by Bob,
that he he does the same, these operators can commute. And there is some probability
probability that the players respond H H prime, given G G prime.
So one can reformulate this in using the notion of quantum permutation matrix. So here we have this
that a matrix whose entries are p i j. And these are elements of some sister algebra is a quantum
permutation matrix also called magic unitary. If we have this that each p i j is a projection,
so it must satisfy these relations. And these these matrices in the sort of in the row and
column must sum up to one. And the theorem by Lupini-Manchi-Sky-Robertson is that this
graph quantum graph isomorphism is equivalent with commuting with a quantum permutation
permutation matrix. So so it's it's can be expressed in a similar framework as the other
similarity notions like isomorphism is just commuting or fractional isomorphism with
with doubly stochastic matrix. And here we have commuting with this quantum permutation matrix.
So formally formally this this is just written out what does it mean formally that these things
commute. Yes, and it's important to say that quantum isomorphism is actually undecidable problem
compared to the graph isomorphism problem which is clearly decidable where you just can
can try all bijections between two graphs. And there I'm not stating not showing it here but
there is an example of graphs that are not isomorphic but are quantum isomorphic.
Right now I want to get to the somehow into the quantum isomorphism groups of graphs
and let's just recall that the isomorphism groups of graphs basically express the symmetries of
graphs and so so basically an isomorphism is just an isomorphism from a graph to itself.
So it's a bijective mapping with which again preserves adjacencies and similarly
automorphisms form a group under composition and it can be equivalently expressed using such equation
that the adjacency matrix has to commute with a permutation matrix.
Yeah so this in particular graph has a dihedral group d5 as an automorphism group we can do just
reflections and rotations here. Okay so you probably know much more about these things but
I'm just mentioning here that we have the notion of compact groups there is a correspondence between
compact groups and commutative sister algebras then when we take the sister algebras to be
non commutative then from there we go to compact quantum groups. So we now immediately
say what is a quantum automorphism group of a graph. So this is definition according to
Banica and basically so we say what is this sister algebra in this case so the
c of qg that's how we'll denote the quantum automorphism group of graph is the universal
sister algebra generated by the elements pij and satisfying basically these following
relations which we had similar relations before and these first two relations correspond
to the fact that sort of the p made up of this entries pij is a quantum permutation matrix
and this last one corresponds sort of to this commuting equation.
So if we require those pij to commute then then we get that the c of algae the algebra of functions
on the automorphism group of graph and the pij would be a function taking an automorphism
to the ij entry of the matrix representation and this matrix p is then called a fundamental
representation of qg. Now let's connect it to quantum isomorphisms and so let p be the fundamental
representation of qg and we can define the following relation that ij corresponding to some
vertices let's say of the graph i is in relation with j if pij is not a zero.
Now the theorem or lemma is that this is actually an equivalent relation
and the orbits of the or quantum orbits are defined to be these equivalence classes
of this of this relation and so the how we connected with the isomorphism quantum isomorphism is that
if g and h are connected graphs then they are quantum isomorphic if and only if there exists g
one vertex in the first graph and one vertex in the second graph which are in the same orbit
of the union of the graphs which is sort of mimicking what is expected in classical
automorphism groups of graphs i will mention it also later. It is a very important theorem
which will actually provide us with the combinatorial tools that can be used to study
quantum automorphism groups of graphs and this is exactly the following so let g be a graph and
now i will define this two-dimensional Weissfer-Lehmann algorithm shortly
but it's some kind of algorithm that creates a partition on the graph which is
automorphism invariant in the classical automorphism group so we have this partition
of the vertices and which is constructed let's say by this two-dimensional Weissfer-Lehmann algorithm
and if two vertices belong in two different colors or partitions
then this pij is equal to zero so in other words they are in different quantum orbits
so so this is very important very very useful tool in general and it's actually
this result is due to also these people and this is very powerful tool powerful combinatorial tool
to use and it appears in many many different areas so it's actually i think quite fascinating result
and there is also and i will talk about this there is also a better version of this two-dimensional
Weissfer-Lehmann algorithm but it is no longer useful for quantum groups because as far as i
understand it's not really possible to define quantum quantum orbitals
like analogs of orbitals which are basically the orbits of the action of the group induced
on the Cartesian product of the set on which is acting so
yeah so if you remember in the beginning we had this slide where this notion of
k-dimensional Weissfer-Lehmann indistinguishability is equivalent to
homomorphism counts into graphs of this bounded trivite so then there was the result by
robertson manjiska which says that quantum isomorphism is equivalent to counting homomorphisms
from planar graphs so this is another reason why higher dimensional Weissfer-Lehmann doesn't work
here is this because all planar like all trivite graphs at most two are planar but trivite graphs
at most three are not all planar so that's another let's say reason why this Weissfer-Lehmann
doesn't work anymore in higher dimension now let's finally talk about this okay Weissfer-Lehmann
in a bit so now i want to a little bit talk about the graph isomorphism problem because that's
actually the motivation for this Weissfer-Lehmann algorithm so the graph isomorphism problem is
just the computational variant of this graph isomorphism so basically we'd get two graphs and
we want to answer yes if and only if the the graphs are isomorphic and there is actually
a polynomial time equivalent problem which is computing the generating set of the
automorphism group of the graph so actually this is very similar to what we said before about
quantum groups and quantum isomorphism that to to see this why why this is equivalent or at least
one direction is to just consider two connected graphs and then take the disjoint union and
basically if there is an automorphism taking one to the other then then we know that they
must be isomorphic when there is a generator in the generating set of the automorphism group
so the currently best known algorithm for graph isomorphism runs in this time which is called
quasi polynomial and it is actually heavily based on group theory and just why this problem is
actually interesting is that from the complexity theory point of view actually you can have basically
things that can happen and each of them would be very interesting like if so the goal is usually
to solve some problem in polynomial time and if you could solve it in polynomial time then it means
that you probably have to invent some new mathematics if it was mp complete which is like the notion of
algorithmic hardness then then something called polynomial time hierarchy collapses which is
basically part of complexity theory and if this collapses then many people believe that this doesn't
collapse so they believe there is evidence so that it should not be mp complete and when it's
intermediate somewhere in between then it would resolve the famous p versus mp question so so this
problem originated from some practical applications but actually for practical applications it's
pretty much solved actually by these vise or lemma that I will mention it works very well
in most of the practical cases but yeah so why is this problem actually difficult is that
these algorithms are actually heavily based on group theory and
one of the one of the main parts is to do some recursive algorithm and
the problem the problem are are different complication complicated actions of some large group
like if we have this simple graph then it has the automorphism group Sn and it has the so-called
natural action on the set one to five which basically doing what you expect to just permeate
the vertices but if you care to guess okay I'm missing an edge here oh no what is the
automorphism group of this graph which is the well-known peterson graph
yeah it's also s5 sorry s5 yes it was s5 yeah it's s5 but now it's acting like on 10 points
and actually you cannot find like partition into into non-trivial blocks
so like partition that is preserved by the action you can only partition it trivially
and this means that action is primitive and you cannot do recursion so the problem is in
this isomorphism testing with large large groups which have not quasi-polynomial order
but it is a large order and complicated action that you cannot decompose okay so let's get to this
vise-for-lemon so first the simpler version of the vise-for-lemon is just a color refinement
algorithm which is something that probably if you were given as a homework to solve the
isomorphism problem then probably this would be the first thing that would occur to you is that you
just take two graphs and you first color all the vertices uniformly and now you look at each vertex
and see how many what is the degree of that vertex and if you know that the degree is different then
you surely cannot map it to some other vertex with a different degree so then you can recall
the graph based on this you see that the blue vertices have the same degrees
and the red vertices have the same degrees now you iterate this process until you get something
stable that no longer can be refined and then basically if you end up with a different colorings
then you can say that these these things are definitely not isomorphic but if you end up
with somehow the same colorings then you really do not know now the vise-for-lemon algorithm
does something better so instead of just coloring the vertices it's coloring the pairs of vertices
right so how does it how does it work so here we have just this very simple
graph and if you want to depict the pairs of vertices we can just depict them by some arrows
so here is the the pairs of vertices that occur in this graph and we give it some
initial coloring or initial partition so this green color corresponds that there to the fact
that there is no edge here and this red color corresponds to the to the pairs of the form
uu let's say and this blue corresponds to the edges now we count we construct a new partition in the
next step yes in the initial coloring we and actually it will be recolored as you will see
so the in the initial coloring all pairs that correspond to the edges to the actual edges
will be colored the same and all pairs that correspond to the non-edges and the diagonal of the
yeah and in the next iteration we do the following counting so for each pair uv of some color k
and every ij we count the number of vertices such that there is such a triangle in the graph
so the base of the triangle is the uv with color k and we count the number of vertices w such that
there is the first step in color i and the second step in color j of course this k ij can be possibly
the same they don't have to be all distinct and then for each pair we do this count and then in the
next step we recolor the pairs based on these counts so the next step here would look something
like this so actually you will get some some new colors on on here and the color and the new colors
here and this actually makes sense because it should be approximating the orbits of the automorphism
group and this that this vertex got orange these two vertices got orange color and this
remained red actually makes sense because these two vertices here should be in a different orbit
and these vertex and of course it doesn't work perfectly but it works very well and of course
you can construct some examples where it doesn't work but it's a very as i said the connection
with the quantum groups is actually also approximates the quantum orbit so basically whatever
is distinguished by the vise for lemma you can also use it when studying the quantum group
okay so what we actually did we colored the aj-sense matrix and now the idea of this vise
for lemma you can think of it as basically constructing invariants in mathematics we
distinguished objects by constructing invariants like the dimension of a vector space of or more
complicated like in algebraic topology some homology groups so this is something similar
basically because we colored the aj-sense matrix and we actually constructed some coherent algebra
which is generated by the following matrices so to each color you can actually assign a zero
zero one matrix so like this uh so here you have uh some these these are basically zero one matrices
where the ones are exactly at those places which are of the same color and so in this case this
coordinate algebra would be generated by these five matrices and it is like a matrix algebra
satisfying the following condition so the first condition is that all of the matrices so this
generating matrices might sum up to all ones matrix so which is here clear that if you sum it all up
you get the all ones matrix so then there has to be has to be some some subset of the matrices
that sum up to identity so in this case it would be this orange matrix and this red matrix they
sum up to the identity so this basically tells you that is actually also approximating not only the
two orbits of the graph but also the orbits so it should be more powerful than just the degree
refinement and then if you take any pair of matrices if you use the bad student product the
component wise product or true product then then you get the zero matrix and then you have the
transpose matrix there it's like for example here we have a pair of transpose matrices and
then the last condition is that the product of the matrix can be expressed in such a in such a sum
and this number c i j actually are some constants that corresponds to this counting of triangles
when it's finally stable so we have this kind of matrix algebra on top of the graph and if these
algebras are isomorphic then or non-isomorphic then we can distinguish the graphs by this
Weisfer Lehmann and if they are the same then we cannot make a conclusion now you can go even
yes yes it's like basically it's the Weisfer Lehmann actually doesn't only have to be applied
for graphs you can start with any because each each each of these matrices zero matrices can be
also interpreted as just some binary relation right so you are basically starting with a bunch of
relations and the Weisfer Lehmann algorithm will find what is called a coherent closure
so the smallest coordinate algebra satisfying these conditions that contains those relations so
but when you want to apply it for graphs you start with the specific three relations that
I depicted but it's not necessary to do that
yeah yes in this case it's just the adjacency matrix but in general you can get you can start
with any bunch of relations yeah and you can go further you can do k-dimensional Weisfer Lehmann
so here instead of coloring k tuples sorry two tuples you will be coloring k tuples but I don't
want to get too much in today's because as I said it's not anymore relevant for quantum groups but
but there are some very interesting connections like for example the k-dimensional Weisfer Lehmann
distinguishes two graphs if and only if these graphs are distinguishable by k plus one
variable sentence with counting quantifiers so for example here you have two graphs that
this cycle and these two triangles so these are all regular graphs so one-dimensional Weisfer
which was the color refinement is actually also called one-dimensional Weisfer Lehmann algorithm
this doesn't distinguish these two graphs because all the vertices are the same degree
so it doesn't do anything basically but you can distinguish them with two-dimensional Weisfer Lehmann
and this would correspond to some formula in three variables
you can implement this distance formula between the two vertices with one extra variable so this
would be like a three variable formula that also distinguishes those two graphs so that's a
connection to logic and then there are many more very interesting connections like integer linear
programming as I said in the beginning the homomorphism counting that this homomorphism
in distinguishability for bounded three-width graphs is equivalent to to being distinguishable
by k-dimensional Weisfer Lehmann okay let's go somehow back to the quantum groups and
um so I uh what what we did in our work we basically
did a quantum group quantum underwater group of graph version of two classical results
and I will mention them now so first of all like uh Frux theorem is quite old and it says that for
every graph there or sorry for every group there you can construct a graph with the isomorphic
automorphism group and actually the quantum analog of this Frux theorem does not hold
even for quantum permutation groups and so but we are still interested in some quantum
automorphism groups of restricted classes of graphs because a lot of the results about quantum
automorphism groups of graphs were were in the spirit of analyzing whether a given graph has
or does not have quantum symmetry or maybe some calculations for for some for some specific
graphs let's say but uh it's it's kind of interesting that uh the the quantum
automorphism groups of trees which we looked at uh was was not so much now and so to do that I want
to recall a first product of groups so first product of groups and we will need the quantum
analog of that first product of groups uh is like when we want to determine the automorphism
group of two graphs if they are not isomorphic we can just use a direct product to construct the
automorphism group but if they are isomorphic no longer works with uh the uh direct product
because if you look at the structure of the automorphism group uh it's actually uh not a
direct product if it was a direct product then this uh front square and the back square is the
Cayley graph would be different so sorry the same if it was a direct product so it's just a
depiction nice depiction of the structure of the group uh but this uh is described by the
rest product and by that I just mean the following so uh if I have two groups and uh a set omega on
on which q is acting then I can take the direct product like for each for each element of the
set omega I take a group a copy of the group D and take the direct product of this and um
and then the rest product is actually naturally defined as a semi-direct product uh and the
the semi-direct product is defined by this action of of of q on the coordinates of this
let's say vectors or uh omega tuples in in in this direct product in a natural way
so just by action on the coordinates so that's the rest product and what we can do with this
red product is for example to determine the automorphism group of a disconnected graph
by the following formula so if we have like a bunch of copies of some graph then this
automorphism group will be just the automorphism group of the component uh rest producted with
the symmetric group and so in general if we have a bunch of connected components xi then we can use
the following formula to compute the whole automorphism group uh based on the automorphism
groups of the individual graphs and this actually can already give us a proof of a very neat theorem
and this is one of the result that we will have a quantum analog for so this maybe is a very
interesting theorem that could probably be even in some undergraduate course which basically gives
a description of all the automorphism groups of trees and it's and it's quite quite simple so
it's basically just an inductive description so there is a trivial group in the class and if
there are two groups then there is a direct product and if there is a group then there is
it's worth product with a symmetric group no so how to see this so if if we have uh if we have a
group g and h then we can construct a tree with the direct product just by putting those trees
onto a common root and maybe if g and h is the same so g equals h we can just add one vertex to
prevent swapping so that we have the direct product and if you want to construct the rest
product it's also easy we just take a copy of one tree uh or n copies of the tree then attach it to
the common root and we get the rest product with the symmetric group on the other hand if you want
to prove that these are all the groups then we can just take any tree delete delete the root
it's okay enough to consider root trees delete the root apply the formula from the previous
slides for disconnected graphs and notice that only only rest products and direct products
occur there so so so the group must be in this in this class
so now we have um let so the class qt is the class of all quantum automorphism groups of trees
that can be described as follows so here instead of the direct product we will have a free product
of the of the quantum groups and instead of the rest product we'll just have uh the so-called
free rest product with a quantum symmetry group s and plus there is which which contains the
contains the classical symmetry group and here um yeah it's just mentioned what I already said
and there was a result by Fulton in 2006 who actually showed that the automorphism that the
trees which have classical automorphism group s2 to the k have quantum symmetry but uh yeah this is
of course contained in our result as well and um only recently only recently uh there has been
almost at the same time publish a paper by some other person who I forgot the name
but he actually also arrived to this result that we have and also for maybe some other classes of
graphs uh by using completely different methods so doesn't use vice for lemma or so on so here I
have again the definition of the quantum automorphism group of a graph but I can just go quickly
because here um we have um just what we need something more is to add some condition so
because we want to work with colored graphs right so we want to have uh some colors on the
vertices and we want to preserve these colors so we just there is just some extra condition for that
here is mentioned again quantum isomorphism let's just go further and uh so with quantum
automorphism groups something that is uh very easy in the classical automorphism groups has to be
checked very carefully so we have some bunch of operations that we use and for each we have to
prove that this actually preserves the quantum automorphism group uh but this may be very obvious
in the classical way but still we need it so one of the operation is for example that if you have
just an independent set which is a union of colors then we can add edges between all the pairs of
vertices in s so just something like this right so you have two color classes and you just add
all the edges between that uh I mean it's a very simple thing but it has to be checked carefully
with quantum groups um or adding a complete bipartite graph between two disjoint sets that
are also union of color classes so something like this you have some color classes and you add like
a complete bipartite graph between these so this also preserves quantum automorphism group
or changing this is like very very seems very trivial that changing the color of some monochromatic
vertex set to a different color or adding an isolated vertex of a color that no longer existed
so because what do what we want to do we want to with quantum groups we also want to use some
similar kind of induction as is used for regular trees but um we need to transfer from regular
trees um sorry regular automorphism groups of trees we need to transfer from under unrooted
trees to rooted trees so that we have some option for an induction and we we basically use this
simple operation that we proved that preserve quantum automorphism groups to to replace undirected
trees with rooted trees so how is it done like using this operation is very simple so you just
color the vertices then you remove an edge so you can also reverse the operation then you add a
vertex of a different color then you add like the complete bipartite graph between two color
classes and then you uncolor and so it seems very trivial but somehow with quantum groups one has
to check everything carefully that it works so it's like the process of rotification you can just
basically introduce a root to to an unrooted tree oh i forgot to mention that every tree has a center
which is either a vertex and edge which is like a vertex and edge which is like a subset of vertices
that is equally distant from the leaves of the tree and we do this this process that was depicted
here with the center and that is also de-rotification so so really that the class of rooted trees is
exactly the same as an unrooted tree so rooted trees are basically just like trees with one
distinguished vertex with one colored vertex which has to be preserved so here we if we have a rooted
tree what we can do is basically attach a very long path to it and then basically we force
force the center to be somewhere on the path because it will be very very long
longer than any path in the tree and then we then then we can
unrooted and basically we we will get that the automorphism or quantum automorphism group is the same
so then i will maybe not define everything just go over this probably you're familiar with
free products of quantum groups and then there is a free breast product of a quantum group so
it's basically this analog of the the direct product and and
breast product of groups and we have two important lemmas that are also analog of what is what we
proved for this or what is known for these classical automorphism groups that if we if we
basically have a bunch of color color graphs that are all connected we have some components
and these components are not quantum isomorphic in this case then actually the quantum automorphism
group of this de-joint union of graphs can be just expressed as a free pre-product of this
quantum automorphism groups and similarly if we have like a connected vertex color graph and if
we take n copies of this graph then the quantum automorphism group of this digital union is
expressed as a free breast product with the quantum symmetry group and i didn't actually
mentioned how we are actually using the vice for lemma here but the vice for lemma here is used
in such a way that basically vice for lemma can distinguish all trees so since it can distinguish
all trees then it's enough to decide isomorphism for them so it's also enough to decide quantum
automorphisms for them so in other words thanks to these trees are isomorphic if and only if there
are quantum isomorph so that's why we can apply these things for trees and putting these things
together we get this equivalent or equivalent the quantum version characterization of the
quantum automorphism groups of trees another result that i will mention is the sabidusis theorem
so this theorem says about lexicographic products of graphs so here is like some
technical definition but it's very easy what is a lexicographic product of
product of graphs so basically this is a lexicographic product of a cycle with k2 which is an edge
so basically we take for each vertex of the outer graph we take a copy of the inner graph so
like here we have four red edges and put all possible edges between the copies if there was
an edge in the c4 so basically we just take a bunch of for each vertex of the outer graph
we take a copy of the inner graph and and put complete bipartite graphs between those copies
if there was an edge in the outer graph x and the sabidusis theorem says that the automorphism group
of of this lexicographic product of two graphs is described as a breath product of the corresponding
automorphism groups if and only if some condition holds what is the condition so this is actually
two conditions written in one so if this inner graph is disconnected then the outer graphs should
have no twins twins are vertices that have see exactly the same neighborhoods so you can imagine
if this inner graph was disconnected and there were twins in the outer graph you can think of
how you could create extra automorphisms that are actually not in this breath product so this
breath product will be a subgroup always but the equality happens if this kind of condition is
satisfied for for the graphs right so in this case this is like s2 breath product with d4
the dihedral group and the quantum version is just that we replace we replace automorphism groups
with quantum automorphism groups and we get a free breath product in there and just in all proved
the result by completely different methods some years ago just for regular graphs so just for
graphs which have the same degree at every vertex so we obtained basically probably a much more
elementary proof for this and we prove it for all graphs so we we make a quantum version of the
sabidu CTRM and here we actually use the Weisner-Lehmann algorithm more deeply
so I'm not going to now go into these counts let's just ignore that for now
so but basically what we have to do we have to just follow the Weisner-Lehmann algorithm
and see that the inner and outer edges so what we want to basically prove
because what are these what are these automorphisms in a classical case what what should they do
you should have if this is just an equality you should have just two types of automorphisms those
that follow the structure of the outer graph and those that act inside the inner graphs
this is just two types of automorphisms that should be there in case there is an equality
and what we use the Weisner-Lehmann to do is that we prove that the Weisner-Lehmann actually
distinguishes all the inner edges and all the outer edges so this is just a purely
combinatorial result but thanks to the connection of Weisner-Lehmann and the quantum groups we can
it actually helps to also analyze the quantum groups so it's not clear how actually Sabidouci
proved it in his original paper because this is something from the 50s and it was there were
several iterations for the papers there were several mistakes in it like it was at least
three times corrected or two times and but he must have done something similar he must
somehow distinguish the inner edges and outer edges but
but the Weisner-Lehmann algorithm is much more elegant way to do it and we also
not only update the quantum version of Sabidouci but I think we prove the Sabidouci theorem in an
elegant way and maybe I'm coming to it to the end and
okay let's just quickly go over this thing here so we could we could then actually also prove this
yeah so we actually do the then do the same we could prove it by ourselves but it's easier to
use this existing result by Banika and Bishon where they actually define yet another kind of
product of graphs which is the free they call it free product of graphs but and they I'm not going
to define it because it's not that important now and they prove that this quantum automorphism group
of this free product of graphs is also the rest product so and for us to use the free product
is actually exactly what we need from the Weisner-Lehmann is this partition of this inner
and outer edges and non-edges and then we can just very simplifying it now then we can plug in
to this Banika and Bishon and this is exactly what is doing just in all who proved this only
for regular graphs he's also using this result by Banika and Bishon and yeah and just just
yeah so we prove that under the sabidusi condition the quantum automorphism group
of this lexicographic product of graphs what we what we want is exactly equal to the quantum
automorphism group of this free product of these graphs where they are colored based on these colors
that we obtained from Weisner-Lehmann and with this color because this free product of graphs by
Banika and Bishon is by is using some colors and we use exactly these colors from Weisner-Lehmann
to plug into their product basically and yeah so maybe I almost ran out of time here is just
a very small cherry on top is that you can also you you can prove a version of this sabidusi
TORM for vertex transitive graphs this means that the two the graphs have just one orbit
in their automorphism group and yeah let's just not go over this anymore but the theorem is basically
that if it's not the case that the equality occurs in the sabidusi theorem then for vertex
transitive graphs you can still find a formula for the automorphism group and the quantum version
happens to be exactly the same okay so let's just mention some problems at the end so something
that we already have in progress is to and there we have to do much more quantum groups
is to define inhomogeneous free rest product so you have this rest product of groups
where you have a group acting on some set and now to each element of this set you assign a group
now you can consider the orbits in this action and for each orbit you could pick a different group
so in this way you get an inhomogeneous rest product of groups which somehow generalizes
the rest product and it would be interesting to have a quantum group analog of that and see
what it what can be done with it so maybe apply it for some further graph classes
like planar graphs for example and planar graphs this there are some problems even in planar
graphs that are not clear and it might be very interesting for people working in geometry because
if you wanted to determine the automorphism groups of planar graphs there is a key case
of so-called three connected planar graphs if you don't want to so three connected planar graphs
basically corresponds to the graphs of polytopes and Mani's theorem says that they can be uniquely
embedded into the sphere in such a way that the automorphisms of the three connected planar
graphs exactly correspond to isometries of the sphere so the automorphism groups of three
connected planar graphs are exactly the finite subgroups of O3 and so these are some infinite
families of groups and the symmetric groups of platonic solids and so quantum Mani's theorem or
or yeah or and maybe because there is a quantum group O plus three so there might be something
there so look at maybe quantum automorphism groups of three connected planar graphs even that would
be very interesting I think so that's it
answer very much for that very interesting talk do we have any questions either in person or perhaps
we have something
yes
How do they respond to this?
Quantum on the resume group of a complete graph should be the SM plus, the quantum permutation group.
Actually, I don't know much about the result, I just heard a talk which claimed this, but yeah, I think it should be definitely true that there is no quantum analog for proof theorem, but I don't know exactly the statement from the top of my head, what is exactly the statement that they proved in that.
It was proven by, I think, Bishop McCarthy.
And when you mentioned the flux sum and the failure in the quantum sense, what I was wondering is there, so if it fails for graphs, I mean, is there some other structure for which there is a version, a quantum version of.
Yeah, I don't know, but yeah, it's an interesting question, but I don't know.
Well, classically, the point is that every group is a permutation group.
So every group acts on itself, but if you have a quantum group, then one group is not a classical space, and quantum permutation groups in this sense are symmetries of classical spaces.
So if you want it, a quantum proof theorem, you actually should not consider classical graphs, but quantum graphs, some graph structure on quantum, on some algebra, non-quimitorial algebra.
I wanted to ask, again, for the difference between the Weisfeller-Lehmann and the quantum isomorphism, so is the difference quantified somehow more precisely, how much is different?
So in terms of computability, there's a huge difference, but for how many graphs, the orbits are different by Weisfeller-Lehmann or quantum automorphism, or do we know some examples of pairs of graphs that cannot be distinguished by Weisfeller-Lehmann,
but they are not quantum isomorphic or something in this sense.
Like, if I understand it correctly, like if you, so if they are not distinguished by two-dimensional Weisfeller-Lehmann, or because...
I don't think it tries strongly regular graphs.
Yeah, I...
Because Weisfeller-Lehmann says classically, it tries strongly regular graphs, it stops in the beginning.
That's like, yeah, maybe.
Then maybe you want the other extreme where Weisfeller-Lehmann works fine, but the quantum algorithm or whatever...
Isomorphism.
It is basically the same, but classically, more complex than these, but far from strongly regular graphs.
Yeah, yeah, right.
That would also be interesting to have some larger class of graphs where we know that Weisfeller-Lehmann would answer the question.
Well, power graphs.
Well, power graphs is not clear.
For power graphs, it's not clear whether two-dimensional Weisfeller-Lehmann will answer the question.
So power graphs is actually the open problem, whether two-dimensional Weisfeller-Lehmann will distinguish them, but currently it's known that three-dimensional Weisfeller-Lehmann distinguishes power graphs.
And the open question is whether also two-dimensional distinguish them.
And yeah, maybe.
But people believe it's going to be true.
Like you mean it's conjectured that it works even for the classical automobiles.
Yes.
Yeah, right.
But for the classical, it is not clear whether two-dimensional, two-dimensional, three-dimensional, five-dimensional, about one-thousand.
Yeah, well, if the classical conjecture was true, then it's not that interesting for the quantum place.
But if it was not true, then maybe it is.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a good question.
Not any other.
So can you explain where this undiscibility comes from?
Why it is not decidable?
Because in the classical case, you just check all the bijections.
But why here there is problem that there is no algorithm?
Yeah, I don't know the problem.
But you must check, I mean, it should be the problem that you have to check infinitely many possibilities.
Otherwise stupid algorithms would exist.
Yep.
What?
So if there's nothing further, then maybe let's thank our speaker again.
And next week, we will have somebody.
I hope you will join us.