OpenAI, a company that we all know now, but only a year ago, was 100 people, is changing
the world.
Their research is leading the charge to AGI.
Since ChatGPT captured consumer attention last November, they show no signs of slowing
down.
This week, a lot of nice sit down with Ilya Sutskover, co-founder and chief scientist
at OpenAI to discuss the state of AI research, where will hit limits, the future of AGI,
and what it's going to take to reach super alignment.
Ilya, welcome to NoPriors.
Thank you.
It's good to be here.
Let's start at the beginning.
Pre-AlexNet, nothing in deep learning was really working, and then given that environment,
you guys took a very unique bet.
What motivated you to go in this direction?
In those dark ages, AI was not an area where people had hope, and people were not accustomed
to any kind of success at all.
Because there hasn't been any success, there was a lot of debate, and there were different
schools of thoughts that had different arguments about how machine learning and AI should be.
You had people who were into knowledge representation from a good old fashioned AI.
You had people who were Bayesian, and they liked Bayesian non-parametric methods.
You had people who like graphical models, and you had the people who like neural networks.
Those people were marginalized because neural networks did not have the property that you
can't prove math theorems about them.
If you can't prove theorems about something, it means that your research isn't good.
That's how it has been.
The reason why I gravitated to neural networks from the beginning is because it felt like
those are small little brains.
Who cares if you can't prove any theorems about them?
Because we are training small little brains, and maybe they'll do something one day.
The reason that we were able to do AlexNet when we did it is because of a combination
of two factors, three factors.
The first factor is that this was shortly after GPUs started to be used in machine learning.
People had an intuition that that's a good thing to do, but it wasn't like today where
people exactly knew what an NGPU is for.
It was like, let's play with those cool fast computers and see what we can do with them.
It was an especially good fit for neural networks, so that definitely helped us.
I was very fortunate in that I was able to realize that the reason neural networks of
the time weren't good is because they were too small.
If you try to solve a vision task with a neural network which has like a thousand neurons,
what can it do?
It can't do anything.
It doesn't matter how good your learning is and everything else, but if you have a much
larger neural network, it will do something unprecedented.
I'll give you the intuition to think that that was the case, because I think at the
time it was reasonably contrarian to think that despite the human brain in some sense
works that way or different biological neural circuits.
I'm just curious what gave you that intuition early on to think that this was a good direction.
I think looking at the brain and specifically, if all those things follow very easily, if
you allow yourself to accept the idea, right now this idea is reasonably well accepted.
Back then, people still talked about it, but they haven't really accepted it or internalized.
The idea that maybe an artificial neuron in some sense is not that different from a biological
neuron.
Now whatever you imagine animals do with their brains, you could perhaps assemble some artificial
neural network of similar size.
Maybe if you train it, it will do something similar.
That leads you to start to imagine.
Almost imagine the computation being done by the neural network.
You can almost think like if you have a high resolution image and you have like one neuron
for like a large group of pixels, what can the neuron do?
It's just not much it can do, but if you have a lot of neurons, then they can actually do
something and compute something.
So I think it was like, all right, like it was considerations like this, plus a technical
realization.
The technical realization is that if you have a large training set that specifies the behavior
of the neural network, and the training set is large enough such that it can constrain
the large neural network sufficiently.
And furthermore, if you have the algorithm to find that neural network, because what
we do is that we turn the training set into a neural network which satisfies the training
set.
Neural network training can almost be seen as solving a neural equation.
Solving a neural equation where every data point is an equation, and every parameter
is a variable.
And so it was multiple things.
The realization that the bigger neural network could do something unprecedented.
The realization that if you have a large data set together with the compute to solve the
neural equation, that's what gradient descent comes in, but it's not gradient descent.
Gradient descent was around for a long time.
It was certain technical insights about how to make it work.
Because back then the prevailing belief was, well, you can't train those neural nets anything.
It's all hopeless.
So it wasn't just about the site.
It was about, even if someone did think, gosh, it would be cool to train a big neural net,
they didn't have the technical ability to turn this idea into reality.
You needed not only to code the neural net, you need to do a bunch of things right, and
only then it will work.
And then another fortunate thing is that the person whom I work with, Alex Krzyzewski,
he just discovered that he really loves GPUs, and he was perhaps one of the first person
who really mastered writing really, like, really performant code for the GPUs.
And that's why we were able to squeeze a lot of performance out of two GPUs and produce
something unprecedented.
So to sum up, it was multiple things.
The idea that a big neural network, in this case a vision neural network, a convolutional
neural network with many layers, one that's much, much bigger than anything that's ever
been done before, could do something very unprecedented because the brain can see and
the brain is a large neural network.
And we can see quickly, so our neurons don't have a lot of time, then the compute needed,
the technical know-how that, in fact, we can't train such neural networks.
And it was not at all widely distributed.
People in machine learning would not have been able to train such a neural network even
if they wanted to.
Did you guys have any, like, particular goal from a size perspective?
Or was it just as, you know, and if that's biologically inspired or where that number
comes from or just as large as we can go?
Definitely as large as we can go.
Just keep in mind, I mean, we had a certain amount of compute which we could usefully
consume, and then what can it do?
Maybe if we think about just like the origin of open AI and the goals of the organization,
like what was the original goal and how's that evolved over time?
The goal did not evolve over time, the tactic evolved over time.
So the goal of open AI from the very beginning has been to make sure that artificial general
intelligence, by which we mean autonomous systems, AI, that can actually do most of
the jobs and the activities and tasks that people do, benefits all of humanity.
That was the goal from the beginning.
The initial thinking has been that maybe the best way to do it is by just open sourcing
a lot of technology.
We later, and we also attempted to do it as a nonprofit, seemed very sensible.
This is the goal, nonprofit is the way to do it, what changed.
Some point at open AI, we realized and we were perhaps among the earliest to realize
that to make progress in AI for real, you need a lot of compute.
Now, what does a lot mean?
The appetite for compute is truly endless, as now clearly seen, but we realized that
we will need a lot and a nonprofit wouldn't be the way to get there, wouldn't be able
to build a large cluster with a nonprofit.
That's where we became, we converted into this unusual structure called CAP Profit,
and to my knowledge, we are the only CAP Profit company in the world.
The idea is that investors put in some money, but even if the company does incredibly well,
they don't get more than some multiplier on top of their original investment.
The reason to do this, the reason why that makes sense, there are arguments, one could
make arguments against it as well, but the argument for it is that if you believe that
the technology that we are building, AGI, could potentially be so capable as to do every
single task that people do, does it mean that it might un-employ everyone?
Well, I don't know, but it's not impossible, and if that's the case, it makes sense, it
will make a lot of sense if the company that builds such a technology would not be able
to make infinite, would not be incentivized, rather, to make infinite profits.
I don't know if it will literally play out this way because of competition in AI, so
there will be multiple companies, and I think that will have some unforeseen implications
on the argument which I'm making, but that was the thinking.
I remember visiting the offices back when you were, I think, housed at YC or something,
or cohabited some space there, and at the time, there was a suite of different efforts.
There was robotic arms that were being manipulated, and then there was some video game related
work, which was really cutting edge.
How did you think about how the research agenda evolved, and what really drove it down this
path of transformer-based models and other forms of learning?
So I think it has been evolving over the years from when we started OpenAI.
In the first year, we indeed did some of the more conventional machine learning work.
The conventional machine learning work, I mean, because the world has changed so much,
a lot of things which were known to everyone in 2016 or 2017 are completely and utterly
forgotten.
It's like the Stone Age almost.
So in that Stone Age, the world of machine learning looked very different.
It was dramatically more academic.
The goals, values, and objectives were much more academic.
They were about discovering small bits of knowledge and sharing them with the other researchers
and getting scientific recognition as a result.
And it's a very valid goal, and it's very understandable.
I've been doing AI for 20 years now.
More than half of my time that I spent in AI was in that framework.
And so what do you do?
You write papers, you share your small discoveries.
Two realizations.
The first realization is just at a high level, it doesn't seem like it's the way to go for
a dramatic impact.
And why is that?
Because if you imagine how an AGI should look like, it has to be some kind of a big engineering
project that's using a lot of compute, right?
Even if you don't know how to build it, what that should look like.
You know that this is the ideal you want to strive towards.
So you want to somehow move towards larger projects as opposed to small projects.
So while we attempted a first large project where we trained a neural network to play
a real-time strategy game, as well as the best humans.
It's the Dota 2 project, and it was driven by two people, Jakob Pachotsky and Greg Brokman.
They really drove this project and made it a success.
And this was our first attempt at a large project.
But it wasn't quite the right formula for us, because the neural networks were a little
bit too small.
It was just a narrow domain, just a game.
I mean, it's cool to play a game, and it kept looking.
At some point, we realized that, hey, if you train a large neural network, a very, very
large transformer to predict text better and better, something very surprising will happen.
This realization also arrived a little bit gradually.
We were exploring generative models.
We were exploring ideas around next-word prediction.
Those are ideas also related to compression.
We were exploring them.
The transformer came out.
We got really excited.
We were like, this is the greatest thing.
We're going to do transformers now.
It's clearly superior than anything else before it.
We started doing transformers with the GPT-1.
GPT-1 started to show very interesting signs of life.
And that led us to doing GPT-2.
And then ultimately, GPT-3.
GPT-3 really opened everyone else's eyes as well to, hey, this thing has a lot of traction.
There is one specific formula right now that everyone is doing.
And this formula is train a larger and larger transformer on more and more data.
I mean, for me, the big wake-up moment to your point was GPT-2 to GPT-3 transition, where
you saw such a big step function and capabilities.
And then obviously, with four open eyes, published some really interesting research around some
of the different domains of knowledge or domains of expertise or chain of thought or other
things that the models can suddenly do in an emergent form.
What was the most surprising thing for you in terms of emergent behavior in these models
over time?
You know, it's very hard to answer that question.
It's very hard to answer because I'm too close and I've seen it progress every step of the
way.
So as much as I'd like, I find it very hard to answer that question.
I think if I had to pick one, I think maybe the most surprising thing for me is the whole
thing works at all.
It's hard.
I'm not sure I know how to convey this, what I have in mind here, because if you see a
lot of neural networks do amazing things, well, obviously neural networks is the thing
that works.
But I have witnessed personally what it's like to be in a world for many years where
the neural networks don't work at all.
And then to contrast that to where we are today, just the fact that they work and they
do these amazing things.
I think maybe the most surprising, the most surprising, if I had to pick one, it would
be the fact that when I speak to it, I feel understood.
Yeah, there's a really good saying from, I'm trying to remember, maybe it's Arthur Clark
or one of the sci-fi authors, which is effectively it says advanced technology is sometimes indistinguishable
for magic.
Yeah, I'm fully in this camp.
Yeah, it definitely feels like there's some magical moments with some of these models
now.
A way that you guys decide internally, given all of the different capabilities you could
pursue, how to continually choose the set of big projects, you've sort of described
that centralization and committing to certain research directions at scale is really important
to open AI success.
Given the breadth of opportunity now, what's the process for deciding what's worth working
on?
I mean, I think there is some combination of bottom up and top down, where we have some
top down ideas that we believe should work, but we're not 100% sure.
So we still, we need to have good top down ideas, and there is a lot of bottom up exploration
guided by those top down ideas as well.
And their combination is what informs us as to what to do next.
And if you think about those bottom, I mean, either direction, top down or bottom up ideas,
you like clearly we have this dominant continue to scale transformers direction.
Do you explore additional like architectural directions or is that just not relevant?
Certainly possible that various improvements can be found.
I think I think improvements can be found in all kinds of places, both small improvements
and large improvements.
I think the way to think about it is that while the current thing that's being done keeps
getting better as you keep on increasing the amount of compute and data that you put into
it.
So we have that property, the bigger you make it, the better it gets.
It is also the property that different things get better by different amounts as you keep
on improving, as you keep on scaling them up.
So not only you want to, of course, scale up what we are doing, we also want to keep
scaling up the best thing possible.
What is a, I mean, you probably don't need to predict because you can see internally,
what do you think is improving most from a capability perspective in the current generation
of scale?
The best way for me to answer this question would be to point out the, to point to the
models that are publicly available.
And you can see how they compare from this year to last year.
And the difference is quite significant.
I'm not talking about the difference between, not only the difference between, let's say
you can look at the difference between GPT-3 and GPT-3.5 and then chat GPT, chat GPT-4,
chat GPT-4 with vision, and you can just see for yourself.
It's easy to forget where things used to be, but certainly the big way in which things
are changing is that these models become more and more reliable before they were very, they
were only very partly there.
Right now they are mostly there, but there are still gaps.
And in the future, perhaps these models will be there even more.
You could trust their answers, they'll be more reliable, they'll be able to do more
tasks in general across the board.
And then another thing that they will do is that they'll have deeper insight.
As we train them, they gain more and more insight into the true nature of the human
world and their insight will continue to deepen.
I was just going to ask about how that relates to sort of model scale over time, because
a lot of people are really stricken by the capabilities of the very large-scale models
and the emergent behavior in terms of understanding of the world.
And then in parallel, as people incorporate some of these things into products, which is
a very different type of path, they often start worrying about inference costs going
up with the scale of the model, and therefore they're looking for smaller models that are
fine-tuned.
But then, of course, you may lose some of the capabilities around some of the insights
and ability to reason.
And so I was curious in your thinking in terms of how all this evolves over the coming years.
I would actually point out that the main thing that's lost when you switch to the smaller
models is reliability.
I would argue that at this point, it is reliability that's the biggest bottleneck to these models
being truly useful.
How are you defining reliability?
So it's like when you ask a question that's not much harder than other questions that
the model succeeds at, then you have a very high degree of confidence that it will continue
to succeed.
So I'll give you an example.
Let's suppose that I want to learn about some historical thing, and I can ask, but tell
me what is the prevailing opinion about this and about that, and I can keep asking questions.
And let's suppose I answered 20 of my questions correctly.
I really don't want the 21st question to have a gross mistake.
That's what I mean by reliability.
Or let's suppose I upload some documents, some financial documents.
Suppose they say something.
I want you to do some analysis and to make some conclusion, and I want to take action
on this basis and this conclusion.
And it's not a super hard task, and these models clearly succeed on this task most of
the time.
But because they don't succeed all the time, and if it's a consequential decision, I actually
can't trust the model any of those times, and I have to verify the answer somehow.
So that's how I define reliability.
It's very similar to the cell driving situation.
If you have a cell driving car and it's like, does things mostly well, that's not good enough.
The situation is not as extreme as with a cell driving car, but that's what I mean by reliability.
My perception of reliability is that, to your point, it goes up with model scale, but also
it goes up if you fine tune for specific use cases or instances or data sets.
And so there is that trade-off in terms of size versus specialized fine tuning versus
reliability.
So certainly, people who care about some specific application have every incentive to get the
smallest model working well enough.
I think that's true.
It's undeniable.
I think anyone who cares about a specific application will want the smallest model for
it.
That's self-evident.
I do think, though, that as models continue to get larger and better, then they will unlock
new and unprecedentedly valuable applications.
So yeah, the small models will have their niche for the less interesting applications,
which are still very useful.
And then the bigger models will be delivering on applications.
Okay, let's pick an example.
Consider the task of producing good legal advice.
It's really valuable if you can really trust the answer.
Maybe you need a much bigger model for it, but it justifies the cost.
There's been a lot of investment this year at the 7B in particular, about 7B, 13B, 34B
sizes.
Do you think continued research at those scales is wasted?
No, of course not.
I mean, I think that in the kind of medium term by a high time scale anyway, there will
be an ecosystem, there will be different uses for different model sizes, there will be plenty
of people who are very excited for whom the best 7B model is good enough, they'll be very
happy with it.
And then there'll be plenty of very, very exciting and amazing applications for which
it won't be enough.
I think that's all.
I mean, I think the big models will be better than the small models, but not all applications
will justify the cost of a large model.
What do you think the role of open sources in this ecosystem?
Well, open source is complicated.
I'll describe to you my mental picture.
I think that in the near term, open source is just helping companies produce useful.
Like, let's see, why would one want to have an open source, but use an open source model
instead of a closed source model that's hosted by some other company?
I mean, I think it's very valid to want to be the final decider on the exact way in which
you want your model to be used.
And for you to make the decision of exactly how you want the model to be used and which
use case you wish to support.
And I think there's going to be a lot of demand for open source models.
And I think there will be quite a few companies that will use them.
And I'd imagine that will be the case in the near term.
I would say in the long run, I think the situation with open source models will become more complicated
and I'm not sure what the right answer is there.
Right now it's a little bit difficult to imagine.
So we need to put our future hat, maybe futurist hat, it's not too hard to get into a sci-fi
mood when you remember that we are talking to computers and they understand us.
But so far, these computers, these models actually not very competent.
They can't do tasks at all.
I do think that the will come a day where the level of capability of models will be
very high.
Like in the end of the day, intelligence is power, right?
Right now, these models, their main impact, I would say at least popular impact is primarily
around entertainment and like simple question and answer.
So you talk to a model, wow, this is so cool.
You produce some images, you had a conversation, maybe you had some questions, good answer.
But it's very different from completing some large and complicated task like, what about
if you had a model which could autonomously start and build a large tech company?
I think if these models were open source, they would have a difficult to predict consequence.
Like we are quite far from these models right now.
And by quite far, I mean by itime scale, but still like, this is not what you're talking
about, but the day will come when you have models which can do science autonomously,
like be delivered on big science projects.
And it becomes more complicated as to whether it is desirable that models of such power
should be open sourced.
I think the argument there is a lot less clear cut, a lot less straightforward compared
to the current level models, which are very useful and I think it's fantastic that the
current level models have been built.
So like that is maybe, maybe I answered a slightly bigger question rather than what
is the role of open source models, what's the deal with open source?
And the deal is up to a certain capability, it's great, but not difficult to imagine models
that are sufficiently powerful, which will be built where it becomes a lot less obvious
as to the benefits of their open source.
Is there a signal for you that we've reached that level or that we're approaching it?
Like what's the boundary?
So I think figuring out this boundary very well is an urgent research project.
I think one of the things that help is that the closed source models are more capable
than open source models.
So the closed source models could be studied and so on.
And so you'd have some experience with a generation of closed source model and then you know
like, oh, these models capabilities, it's fine, there's no big deal there.
Then in a couple years, the open source models catch up and maybe a day will come when we
going to say, well, like these closed source models, they're getting a little too drastic
and then some other approaches needed.
If we have our future hat on, maybe it looks like think about like a several year timeline.
What are the limits you see if any in the near term in scaling?
Is it like data, token scarcity, cost of compute, architectural issues?
So the most near term limit to scaling is obviously data.
This is well known and some research is required to address it.
Without going into the details, I'll just say that the data limit can be overcome and
progress will continue.
One question I've heard people debate a little bit is a degree to which the transformer based
models can be applied to sort of the full set of areas that you'd need for AGI.
And if you look at the human brain, for example, you do have reasonably specialized systems
or all neural networks, be it specialized systems for the visual cortex versus areas
of higher thought, areas for empathy or other sort of aspects of everything from personality
to processing.
Do you think that the transformer architectures are the main thing that will just keep going
and get us there?
Do you think we'll need other architectures over time?
So I understand precisely what you're saying and I have two answers to this question.
The first is that, in my opinion, the best way to think about the question of architecture
is not in terms of a binary, is it enough?
But how much effort, what will be the cost of using this particular architecture?
At this point, I don't think anyone doubts that the transformer architecture can do amazing
things, but maybe something else, maybe some modification could have some compute efficiency
benefits.
So it's better to think about it in terms of compute efficiency rather than in terms
of can it get there at all?
I think at this point, the answer is obviously yes.
To the question about, well, what about the human brain and its brain regions?
I actually think that the situation there is subtle and deceptive for the following reasons.
So what I believe you alluded to is the fact that the human brain has known regions.
It has a speech perception region, it has a speech production region, it has an image
region, it has a face region, it has all these regions, and it looks like it's specialized.
But you know what's interesting?
Sometimes there are cases where very young children have severe cases of epilepsy at
a young age, and the only way they figured out how to treat such children is by removing
half of their brain.
Because it happens at such a young age, these children grow up to be pretty functional adults,
and they have all the same brain regions, but they are somehow compressed onto one hemisphere.
So maybe some information processing efficiency is lost.
It's a very traumatic thing to experience, but somehow all these brain regions rearrange
themselves.
There is another experiment which was done maybe 30 or 40 years ago on ferrets.
So the ferret is a small animal.
It's a pretty mean experiment.
They took the optic nerve of the ferret, which comes from its eye, and attached it to its
auditory cortex.
So now the inputs from the eye starts to map to the speech processing area of the brain.
And then they recorded different neurons after it had a few days of learning to see, and
they found neurons in the auditory cortex, which were very similar to the visual cortex.
Or vice versa, it was either they mapped their eye to the ear, to the auditory cortex, or
the ear to the visual cortex.
But something like this has happened.
These are fairly well-known ideas in AI that the cortex of humans and animals are extremely
uniform.
And so that further supports the AI, like you just need one big, uniform architecture.
So all you need.
Yeah.
In general, it seems like every biological system is reasonably lazy in terms of taking
one system and then reproducing it and then reusing it in different ways.
And that's true of everything from DNA encoding, you know, there's 20 amino acids and protein
sequences.
Everything is made out of the same 20 amino acids on through to your point, sort of how
you think about tissue architecture.
So it's remarkable that that carries over into the digital world as well, depending
on the architecture you use.
I mean, the way I see it is that this is an indication from a technological point of
view.
We are very much on the right track because you have all these interesting analogies
between human intelligence and biological intelligence and artificial intelligence.
We've got artificial neurons, biological neurons, unified brain architecture for biological
intelligence, unified neural network architecture for artificial intelligence.
At what point do you think we should start thinking about these systems in digital life?
I can answer that question.
I think that will happen when those systems become reliable in such a way as to be very
autonomous.
Right now, those systems are clearly not autonomous.
They're inching there, but they're not.
And that makes them a lot less useful too, because you can't ask it, hey, like, do my
homework or do my taxes or you see what I mean.
So the usefulness is greatly limited.
As the usefulness increases, they will indeed become more like artificial life, which also
makes it more, I would argue, trepidations, right?
Like if you imagine actual artificial life with brains that are smarter than humans,
gosh, that seems pretty monumental.
Why is your definition based on autonomy?
Because if you often look at the definition of biological life, it has to do with reproductive
capability.
Plus, I guess some form of autonomy, right?
Like a virus isn't really necessarily considered alive much of the time, right?
But a bacteria is.
And you could imagine situations where you have symbiotic relationships or other things
where something can't really quite function autonomously, but it's still considered a
life form.
So I'm a little bit curious about autonomy being the definition versus some of these other
aspects.
Well, I mean, definitions are chosen for our convenience and it's a matter of debate.
In my opinion, technology already has the reproduction, the reproductive function, right?
And if you look at for example, I don't know if you've seen those images of the evolution
of cell phones and then smartphones over the past 25 years, you got this like, what almost
looks like an evolutionary tree or the evolution of cars over the past century.
So technology is already reproducing using the minds of people who copy ideas from previous
generation of technology.
So I claim that the reproduction is already there.
The autonomy piece I claim is not.
And indeed, I also agree that there is no autonomous reproduction.
But that would be like, can you imagine if you have like autonomously reproducing AIs?
I actually think that that is a pretty traumatic and I would say quite a scary thing if you
have an autonomously reproducing AI, if it's also very capable.
Should we talk about super alignment?
Yeah, very much so.
Can you just sort of define it?
And then we were talking about what the boundary is for when you feel we need to begin to worry
about these capabilities being in open source.
What is super alignment and why invest in it now?
The answer to your question really depends to where you think AI is headed.
If you just try to imagine and look into the future, which is of course a very difficult
thing to do, but let's try to do it anyway.
Where do we think things will be in five years or in 10 years?
I mean, progress has been really stunning over the past few years.
Maybe it will be a little bit slower.
But still, if you extrapolate this kind of progress, you'll be in a very, very different
place in five years, let alone 10 years.
It doesn't seem implausible.
It doesn't seem at all implausible that we will have computers, data centers that are
much smarter than people.
And by smarter, I don't mean just have more memory or have more knowledge, but I also
mean have deeper insight into the same subjects that we people are studying and looking into.
It means learn even faster than people.
What would such AIs do?
I don't know.
If such an AI were the basis of some artificial life, it would be, well, how do you even think
about it?
If you have some very powerful data center that's also alive in a sense, that's what
you're talking about.
And when I imagine this world, my reaction is, gosh, this is very unpredictable what's
going to happen.
Very unpredictable.
But the bare minimum, but there is a bare minimum which we can articulate.
But if such super, if such very, very intelligent, super intelligent data centers are being built
at all, we want those data centers to hold warm and positive feelings towards people,
towards humanity.
Because this is going to be non-human life in a sense.
Potentially.
It could potentially be that.
So I would want that any instance of such super intelligence, the warm feelings towards
humanity.
And so this is what we are doing with the super alignment project.
You're saying, hey, if you just allow yourself, if you just accept that progress that we've
seen, maybe it will be slower, but it will continue.
If you allow yourself that, then can you start doing productive work today to build the science
so that we will be able to handle the problem of controlling such future super intelligence.
Of imprinting onto them a strong desire to be nice and kind to people.
Because those data centers, right, they'll be, they'll be really quite powerful.
You know, there'll probably be many of them that will be, the world will be very complicated.
But somehow to the extent that they are autonomous, to the extent that they are agents, to the
extent they are beings, I want them to be pro-social, pro-human social.
That's the goal.
What do you think is the likelihood of that goal?
I mean, some of it, it feels like a outcome you can hopefully affect, right?
But are we, are we likely to have pro-social AIs that we are friends with individually
or, you know, as a species?
Well, I mean, friends be, I think that that part is not necessary.
The friendship piece, I think, is optional, but I do think that we want to have very pro-social
AI.
I think it's, I think it's possible.
I don't think it's guaranteed, but I think it's possible.
I think it's going to be possible and the possibility of that will increase insofar
as more and more people allow themselves to look into the future, into the five to ten
year future and just ask yourself, what, what do you expect AI to be able to do then?
How capable do you expect it to be then?
And I think that with each passing year, if indeed AI continues to improve and as people
get to experience, because right now we are talking, making arguments, but if you actually
get to experience, oh gosh, the AI from last year, which was really helpful this year puts
the previous one to shame and you go, OK, and then one year later and when it's starting
to do science, the AI software engineer is starting to get really quite good, let's say.
I think that will create a lot more desire in people for what you just described, for
the future superintelligence to indeed be very pro-social.
I think there's going to be a lot of disagreement, there's going to be a lot of political questions,
but I think that as people see AI actually getting better, as people experience it, the
desire for the pro-social superintelligence, the humanity loving superintelligence, as
much as it can be done, will increase.
And on the scientific problem, I think right now it's still being an area where not that
many people are working on.
Our AI is getting powerful enough, you can really start studying it productively, you'll
have some very exciting research to share soon.
But I would say that's the big picture situation here.
Just really, it really boils down to look at what you've experienced with AI up until
now, ask yourself, like, is it slowing down, will it slow down next year, like, we will
see, and we will experience it again and again, and I think it will keep, and what needs to
be done, it will keep becoming clearer.
Do you think we're just on an accelerated path?
Because I think fundamentally, if you look at certain technology waves, they tend to
inflect and then accelerate versus decelerate.
And so it really feels like we're in an acceleration phase right now versus the deceleration phase.
Yeah.
I mean, VR, right now it is indeed the case that VR in an acceleration phase.
You know, it's hard to say, you know, multiple forces will come into play.
Some forces are accelerating forces and some forces are decelerating.
So for example, the cost and scale are a decelerating force.
The fact that our data is finite is a decelerating force to some degree at least, I don't want
to overstate it.
Yeah, it's kind of within an asymptote, right?
Like at some point you hit it, but it's the standard S curve, right, or sigmoidal.
With the data in particular, I just think it won't be, it just won't be an issue because
we'll figure out something else.
But then you might argue that the size of the engineering project is a decelerating force,
just the complexity of management.
On the other hand, the amount of investment is an accelerating force, the amount of interest
from people, from engineers, scientists is an accelerating force.
And I think there is one other accelerating force.
And that is the fact that biological evolution has been able to figure it out and the fact
that up until now, progress in AI has had up until this point, this weird property that
it's kind of been, you know, it's been very hard to execute on, but in some sense it's
also been more straightforward than one would have expected perhaps.
Like in some sense, I don't know much physics, but my understanding is that if you want to
make progress in quantum physics or something, you need to be really intelligent and spend
many years in grad school studying how these things work.
Whereas with AI, if people come in, get up to speed quickly, start making contributions
quickly, it has the flavor is somehow different.
Somehow it's very, there is some kind of, there's a lot of give to this particular area
of research.
And I think this is also an accelerating force.
How will it all play out remains to be seen.
Like it may be that somehow the scale required of engineering complexity will start to make
it so that the rate of progress will start to slow down.
It will still continue, but maybe not as quick as we had before.
Or maybe the forces which are coming together to push it will be such that it will be as
fast for maybe a few more years before it will start to slow down.
If at all that's, that would be my articulation here.
Ilya, this has been a great conversation.
Thanks for joining us.
Thank you so much for the conversation.
I really enjoyed it.
Join us on Twitter at NoPriorsPod.
Subscribe to our YouTube channel if you want to see our faces.
Follow the show on Apple podcasts, Spotify, or wherever you listen.
That way you get a new episode every week.
And sign up for emails or find transcripts for every episode at no-priors.com.