He wasn't established a long time, his long career career back then is five.
He works on a whole bunch of physical principles related to origins of life,
pro-cells, after biology. It was his pleasure to have him here today, PhD.
Thank you. Yeah, it's certainly also, it's always wonderful to be back here and
nice to see a number of known faces and some new ones too.
Some of you know that I've been a bit obsessed with,
we're trying to create life in the lab for many years.
When I was younger, I thought I'd be long done by now, but it's not so easy.
So what I'll present here today is our latest work on computational work, theoretical work,
on the missing link to actually implement a living system in the lab.
And I want to emphasize my collaborators here, and we have Christopher Thompson
and Marco Toccio. They are two recent graduate students I've had, and you guys
of course know Artemis. He's been here for a long time at SFI.
Hansiak is an old friend from Los Alamos and Didliu.
Bornebush is also one of my previous graduate students.
So, I'll focus on the question of how to get information into a self-replicating
molecular machine. This has been an issue we haven't been able to solve experimentally yet.
So, if I can figure out, and it doesn't work this year,
I can also use this one here. So, I think that most of us would agree that
if we want to have a transition from non-living to living matter,
then it has to be characterized by the origin of some functional information that can
tell how to build this living matter. So, the goal is to demonstrate how particular
molecular reaction networks they can generate and store this kind of information.
I guess it looks smart, but it isn't.
So, my answer is to start with a metabolism. I think this is really the key, and I'll try to
argue for that, because there's still some discussion in the community about
what came first, the chicken on the egg here. It's clear that energy is needed and information
is needed. There has to be some kind of containment also, but I really think that
one should focus on the energetics in the beginning. So, imagine we have an energy gradient,
some free energy available. We can then use this free energy to turn resources into building blocks,
and the key is to have a catalyst that can be in more than one state. So, there can be a selection
of catalysts if these building blocks, they will actually also be, or one or more of them,
will be catalysts. So, we are in a situation where we provide energy from the environment,
so we start with resources, and then we end up with building blocks. Of course, the desired
situation is that we lift our building blocks up, so we get more complex building blocks that are
energetically higher up, but it's also okay if we can just make new materials by this process.
And of course, this is not clear why this is true, at least some people say it is not clear.
So, therefore, I've tried to state two questions here. Why focus on metabolism? Is metabolism
really primary to information since our topic is mainly information? And how is a good metabolic
catalyst selected and up-concentrated if you have a system like this here? Free energy available,
you use this energy to turn resources into building blocks, where one of the building blocks is
actually a catalyst that can catalyze its own formation. So, we have an order catalysis. And
for some of you, this is, you already know that, but I want to emphasize that if we look at a molecular
system that has different states, let's see that it has w different states, then we know from Boltzmann
that it can encode information to the amount of the equation of PIS, which is information is equal
to Boltzmann's constant and the natural logarithm of the possible states. And there is information
represented many places in living systems, the most well-known sequential equation, DNA, RNA,
proteins and so forth. But I want to emphasize that information can also be present as conformational
information where an aggregate can be composed of different components and then the how many
components and in high concentrations will also represent the information. This is the one Lancet
that has introduced that and sequential information like we have in DNA and RNA and proteins, etc.
That's a particular kind of compositional information. Compositional information is more
general. So if we take Boltzmann's equation and the fundamental first law or sorry second law
where we have that information or entropy here is equal to energy divided by t and then we insert
this fundamental equation from thermodynamics into Boltzmann's equation. We get an equation we see
here where we can eliminate or we can isolate e and then we get in a system where there are two
states, we get an energy that is this big. And this was Landau that I think was first in pointing
out that if you want to delete or create or store a bit of information there has to be
it costs you something and the cost is about if you put in the room temperature and the value
for the Boltzmann constant you get a small amount of energy. And I think this is a physics argument
for why one has to look at free energy before one can think about information. And this is of
course in line with all of our experiences whenever we have to write something we have to use energy
computers use energy transmission of information on cables and you know
satellites and what all of this is something we already know very well.
Oh biological systems they also require energy to the replication machinery is energetically
it needs energy. Can I ask you a question? Yeah yeah absolutely. So
it's interesting that you're using Landau's principle as this you know the argument for why
we need a metabolism. I mean I agree with all this but I just as far as I know I agree real
metabolism is many orders of magnitude above that in the amount of heat it releases per bit.
And so is that an indication that actually some other mechanism is making the metabolism
necessary than Landau's principle? No no this is just this is just to state I mean you guys most
of you are it's sort of you know preaching to the choir but for many people in the community
that are interested in these things it's not obvious and it'll be contested but I
know I think I know that I mean you need to use about two electron volts to split water
so you need much more energy to do to run chemical reactions and how exactly how the
relationship is between how much energy you have to to process or to run a chemical process
compared to how much information there is I I'll not get into that here. I'll sort of try to
put these two things together at the end. Yeah the ribosome which is running all these strings
is about four times off the Landauer bound so it's real and then that machine is about half
of cellular metabolism in bacteria so that's where one of these costs actually does get
scaled all the way up to sort of cellular scale. It's only about four times that? It's four times
that. Oh no I thought it was yeah hundreds or thousands of times. No no no it's not no
but it but it is I mean we have I don't think anybody has actually reached the this limit
has that been done I don't think so anyways so let's believe that we need to have free energy
before we can have information and so then if that's true then we can go to the next question
how is a metabolic catalyst selected and up concentrated because now we we agree that we
actually need free energy to generate this catalyst and I will I'll claim that a catalyst
is a sufficient condition for having a catalyst is that you have an energy transducer and a
combinatorial cofactor in chemistry you have you have catalyst that speed up chemical processes
and and if you have an energy transducer that's a that's a molecular machine that can turn
one kind of energy into another kind of energy we're going to focus on how we can turn light
energy into chemical energy and this can be modulated with a so-called cofactor and I'll get
into that later so we so that's number one we actually require or assume that this catalyst
is composed of an energy transducer and a combinatorial cofactor that can modulate it
and a cofactor can be it does need to but it can be an an electron donor or an electron receptor
depending on how the system is made up so that depending on how how well it donates electrons
to to this energy transduction machinery the process will run faster or slower
and if we also want this catalytic cofactor to be replicated then the question is how how is
that possible I mean how what what kind of systems can both satisfy the first one that we have
the catalyst being in a energy transducer and a combinatorial cofactor and it can also be
replicated and and now as we go on I have to emphasize that I'm not trying to solve the
origins of life I mean the historical origins of life here on earth we're just trying to create
life in the lab from from non-living materials so so um so how do we think about this I mean we
we've tried a number of different things and this is sort of the workhorse that we are currently
believing in where we have a um you can see over here we have we have a
vesicle fatty acid vesicle and on on this exterior of this vesicle we have anchored
an energy transducer this is a ruthenium complex with a with a tail a hydrophobic tail
and then we have a DNA duplex which is a cofactor so so here we have we have a sort of a blow-up
up here we have the energy transducer and and it it's composed of both this molecular system that
can capture light and and and then a a energy transducer that can deliver an electron and
we have a little blue indication up here because it turns out that depending on what kind of
bases we have in a DNA or an RNA or a pna strand uh we will have a good or a bad
cofactor so so we have the we have this as a ruthenium complex and up here we have an oxygoinine
because oxygoinine is a very good or reasonably good uh electron donor um so how how so how can
this work i mean what what what does it do and and also how is how is this cofactor actually
able to replicate because we know that replication without enzymes is is very very difficult can
ask a question absolutely yeah i'm curious why you chose DNA instead of RNA since
on auto catalysis has been RNA yeah that's more likely to auto-catalyze than DNA well it's simply
because we uh DNA is much easier to work with it's much cheaper and and and if you look at
charge transfer which we will focus on here it it's it's more difficult to do charge transfer
in RNA than it is in DNA DNA literally thousands of papers out on charge transfer of DNA and all
all kinds of different so so we and the reason why we're using ruthenium is also because it's the most
studied uh uh energy transducer photo photocatalysis there is so so that's why the chemists they've
chosen they've chosen that so just to indicate what we mean by this protocell and to to be
interesting it has to go through a life cycle so remember before this was a protocell that
is composed of in principle three different components the membrane i mean the vesicle
uh this energy transducer and the cofactor then we feed the system with an oily substance
that will then go into the membrane this is pigolinium ester and we can then by
illuminating the system turn pigolinium ester into fatty acid and then that means that we get more
membrane and as the membrane expands then the protocell gets gets bigger eventually if you
run the process long enough then it will get unstable and it will divide and not in a controlled
way but you'll get spotting events so as we do that or as this metabolic process runs we also
provide a small oligomers which are pieces of DNA and they will then template if we make sure that
this DNA has some certain properties which we'll get into a little later it has to have
it has to have deletions and imperfections so it doesn't glue too strongly together so it's not
hybridized too strongly then we can actually get a replication of these of these cofactors
and then over time you'll eventually end up with with two or more sometimes not it doesn't divide
but on average you actually do get more of these aggregates
so
how I promise to talk a little bit about how we can actually modulate a metabolism with the with
the DNA yeah we've done a number of we've done experimental and theoretical work on this for
many years this was our first life cycle of a of a protocell it was Mauer's PhD thesis
where she demonstrated it where we actually have yeah anyways we we yeah it goes I don't want to
get into details but we can actually show that that that you can that these that these vesicles
they can grow and divide and by keep feeding this the guillenium ester we can actually get the system
to generate more and more of these of these vesicles but here we don't have a replicating
DNA strand we only have oxo guanine as a as an electron donor there isn't any so there isn't any
inheritance so we have to provide new oxo guanine all the time
so how how does it actually work if we want to have and have this process to to to act or have
have this cofactor to act as a as a as a modulator and so here is the surface of the membrane the
fatty acids are the green ones and the blue ones these are these oily the guillenium esters and as
you illuminate the ruthenium complex which actually intercalates the self-assembles into the into
the DNA then what happens is that you will steal this once once it gets activated it will steal a
an electron from a guanine that is sitting in in the vicinity because once it gets activated then
an electron jumps from the ruthenium metal out to one of these bipyridine antennas here
and and then it'll steal an electron from the strand so now there is a hole there's a missing
electron and it'll diffuse up and down the strand until it eventually will be absorbed by the oxo
guanine and as we have an energy rich electron here it's been banged out there by the light
then this electron can actually be used to to deprotect a picolinium ester and turn it into a
fatty acid it needs to have a we need to have a sacrificial proton donor and then this process
will go and then we don't we don't like to have a damage the oxo guanine so we need to have a the
same what's it called or a proton donor here but at the end of the day we actually convert
this oily substance into membrane so the system grows and this is modulated by the
strand here because if if we can't if we can't get get rid of the hole then this this ruthenium
complex is sort of say on it's not usable for one for one for the next for the next time
it has to be you know it has to be it has it needs to have this electron back
so what we've done here is looked at this process and tried to calculate
how the strands they how well the strands they
conduct these holes depending on the sequence and unfortunately that if you go to the literature
I mean we don't have the measurements for that it's not all transition states that's
actually published we don't know what the rate constants are from all these different
combinations this is what we were able to to find and we had to we had to guesstimate some of them
ourselves and these are either direct measurements or they are of an issue calculations I mean where
you have quantum calculations of of of this system so we have the rates from for instance going from
from an a to an a or from an from a g to an a etc and you can then you if you want to simulate
such a system you can set up the matrix like this and you will then have the these rate constants
they will determine how likely it is for you to go from one state to the other and mostly
you see off diagonal you have diffusion and then every once in a while they are actually what we
call super exchange where if you have a gc pair and then you have a gc pair a little I mean a
couple of of three sides four sides further down you can actually have the hole to to tunnel
the quantum tunnel for one from one to the next so what we've done we've first we looked at all
these rates and when we realized we couldn't just we couldn't make all the rates on one hand they
are all the sequences in the world on the one hand that was good because we didn't have simulation
time to to simulate strands I think we we go on now I know we go up to about 18 strands of 18
that's what's been we've also done experiments and other has done experiments with and if you
take what what we know here and you then do the actually do the counting you can only construct
or you can at most construct 160 strands so what we've done we have constructed these 160
strands and then we've done the simulations we've then found these medium first passage
time for the hole to to get up to the to the octagon and and and also we actually also
calculated the the the mean there's a little bit of difference but how experimented what's it
you said that you found mean first medium first passage time how did you find it
no this was this was this is calculations these are calculations all of these transition
this transition constants they are found either experimentally or they are found with first or
I mean with with the quantum mechanical calculations or a couple of them we had to
guesstimate because we couldn't find them in the literature but they probably are known I
don't know it best to like 10 percent but for instance here you've said you know times like
this 10 digits not 10 but five digits so is it just for fun what is for fun for instance this
tau you've you said you know something with like four significant digits so five significant digits
and this numbers you know rates you probably know with I don't know five percent ten percent
oh yeah oh yeah I know don't know this don't worry about that yeah yeah no no no we don't know
this should yeah no no no yeah so so so that that's just what that's what what the computer cranked
out no no don't worry about all the all the digits there we are we just know what the order of magnitude
is and that's it we cannot count on more any other questions yeah I don't understand right
the idea here is to understand the timing it takes to saturate the electrons being trapped in the
eight oxo yeah and then but yeah but then what limits you're assuming 18 base pairs of length
these could grow I assume and no no no no no you have you have just think about think about uh
don't think about any changes just think about a DNA yeah a duplex that has a certain length
you can then place the oxygorne in different different different locations and you can you
can then also have different ATs or GCs but then I'm thinking in your system you need the DNA to
self replicate yeah okay that comes later they come longer than 18 base pairs no we don't we
don't allow it to get longer because we we feed it with with with the pieces so we can make sure
that it doesn't get any longer but that's that's sort of the that's that's actually the next step
here you're too fast so so just to to show here what we got out of that so this is the histogram
of all the of all the simulations this is where we have the slow ones is when we have the oxygorne
above the ligation side and and this is the fast ones when we have the oxygorne below the ligation
side that means it's close to the to the ruthenium complex which makes sense and then there's a
bunch in the middle where it's more complicated what's happening so so that's the result of our
our simulations now obviously there's much more going on than just charged charged transferred
in the DNA if you look at this this is a I think we've gotten pretty much all of the reactions
in here for our metabolism this is the ruthenium complex in ground state it's activated by light
and then it can either jump back again or you can actually deliver this energized electron to
to the to the DNA and you can then have the charge run up to the to the oxygorne you then
destroy or you modify the what's it called the the oxygorne it actually loses a hydrogen
atom and you then have to repair it and then you go around in this in this cycle here and
then downstream as you as you go down to the ground state here with with the ruthenium
then you can use this energy to convert picolinium ester into a into into a lipid into a fatty acid
the canoic acid and and I don't want to get into all the details but we've started that both
experimentally and and computationally theoretically and I so we know this system fairly well although
all of the constants reaction constants are not known we they're not verified experimentally but
you can when you simulate the system you can have some bounce on them in any way if you look at how
look at the what determines the time for recharging the ruthenium complex
this circular reaction is determined by the charge transfer reaction constant so
if you want to to ensure that the charge transfer is is not too slow then we can figure out I mean
there is we have this this rate that that is the excitation and then we have the
a number of things that's going on up here but the time it takes is one over the rate
plus the time it takes going around here and then we have a rate sort of a composed rate for the whole
thing and if we say that we only allow the the charge transfer to slow the system with
50 percent or with 10 percent or 1 percent we can we can actually get a bound on on this rate and
we say that we only allow it to reduce the recharge with 1 percent and that means that we have a
a rate constant in this charge transport to be that it has to be larger than
five per sorry 50 per second and we'll require that for the as we go forwards
any question yeah and it this this is this is complicated so now we go to what you asked with
the replication how does that work and and the main sort of break that that the community got was
with juliane gibbs she and her groups they figured out a way to to actually replicate
DNA without enzymes by doing a a ligation reaction and and making sure that we don't have
product inhibition and and the community has sort of been has been struggling i mean i had
to pay several phd students we weren't able to solve it and i mean many many many people have
tried to do DNA or RNA amplification with without luck and and it turns out that if you make if you
make mismatches or bulges or air bases add that to the DNA strand you can actually get
it exponential amplification by by by by having having these errors in in the DNA and and she
calls it the lesion induced DNA amplification and and if you just look at it here then
then we have some mismatches or some a basis that means it could be where there's no
actually there's no base at all it's just a backbone and if you have have this destabilized
enough then there is enough breathing in this short system so that when you feed it with with
these resource strands here and provide an extra ruthenium complex you will actually be able to get
and replication so that's how the replication happens and this has been demonstrated in the
in the lab many many times many groups nobody so far has done it while the DNA has been anchored so
that's something that has to be done yeah you start with mismatched yeah that's how this works but
do you end up with a product that's mismatched yes interest because else you can't you can you can
dehybridize interest so else you and that's that then you get a product inhibition so this is the
main the main that that's the main i mean this is the the ingenious thing that that uh uh julie
gives she did anyway so at the end of the the day we have a cofactor replication
so now we can write down the reaction diagram you can see that here and then you end up with
15 coupled ordinary differential equations i've written the first two ones there are 13 more
and what's interesting here is if you look at the all the reactions almost all of them are of this
form where you have two two reactions that turns into a third one or you have and all of it is
reversible except the ligation part where you actually glue these at the backbone together
and then we know from the ratio relationship between Gibbs free energy and the equilibrium
constant here this is something you've learned in in college chemistry if you then know
one of these either the forward or the backwards rate then you can actually and you know the the
free energy associated with the hybridization then you can find the off rate and turns out the on
rate is much faster than the off rate i mean much much faster and it doesn't depend much about it
doesn't depend that much on the sequence details so if we for the sake of simplicity assume that
it's constant then we can find the off rate by by sorry if we know this one and if we know the
delta g and delta g is we've taken from santa lucía and hicks there they made this monumental
work where they actually figured out how to calculate this free energy but also use there's a
lot of online tools like a new pack that gives you gives you the the free energy and actually
turns out that depending on what you're using you always get differences it's still there's still
a little bit of of what's it called art and i don't think they've really nailed it down but
anyways that's how we can we can figure out what the rate constants are by when we have the sequence
then we can calculate the off rates so the results here are given to the left so we get
replication rates and they're sort of all over the place in in this range here again this is the
logarithm we are using and and what we have to compare here is when we do these experiments
to do the ligation we need to have one of the ends energize with imidazole and that actually
decays in water it falls apart in water so if you can't wait forever because else the system will
simply die and the rate is i think the the place where they found the highest rate was about 10 to
the minus 5 10 to the minus 5 per second so it's a relatively slow rate and we just we decide that
we want to have a replication rate that it's at least one order of magnitude faster so we say
that replication rate has to be higher than 10 to the minus 4 and that's here so we these guys are
okay so there's a few of them that will be they'll be disqualified now to make simple to make things
simple we've actually assumed that this happened and bought and not on a surface at an interface
now we did do interface calculation then you have to adjust some of the rates and it turns out that
it's at least an order of magnitude the collision rate is at least an order of magnitude faster
if you do it on the surface but since there are many other reactions involved it's not
that that big of a difference and this is assuming there's no crowding if you have too many molecules
i actually don't know what happens if there's a crowding but we've also that's a whole other
story we we've made we actually made a model we this is a sipping graph model where we can
where we can take into account how it went when they collide on the surface how they actually
also involved how depending on on this on what sequence details you have then sometimes you'll
sliding and mismatches it takes a while for it to find the the the final situation so you can
actually do the ligation but that's a different story but i think that it is true i believe
that it is faster on the surface than it is in bulk so now we've done a study of charge transfer
or charge transport on the dna we found out how fast or how slow we will allow the system to be
and we've also done replication studies figure out you know of these 160 strands that we
we have started which ones are fast enough etc so another question is of course how
what does that mean for the for a protocell how do we combine these findings and that's the
the last question namely try to figure out i mean how can the combined charge transport and
replication process support a protocell life cycle so the first thing the easiest thing to do
is to look at simply map these two our findings out on two different in a coordinate system
where we have the the sorry the charge transfer rate on the the logarithm to the charge transfer
rate on the x-axis and this is the logarithm of the of the replication rate constant on the y-axis
and then we we had these as we had these requirements that we need to have the the this
this charge transfer to be faster than than than 50 per second and the replication rate has to be
faster than 10 to the minus 5 10 to the minus 4 per second so so we are good with replication in
the blue area and we are good with with charge transfer in the reddish or light right red area
and this area out here is then the sweet area this is where both things are are satisfied
one thing i didn't discuss earlier is that for to have a good coupling between i mean for for
selection and replication we we it's you you want to have your dna to replicate
and not just be the resource pieces that can actually run the metabolism so if you think
about if you have a an oxygrenine right next to the right next to the surface of the vesicle
in one of the pieces one of the resource pieces you give the system then you don't need to have any
replication to actually run the metabolism because the the the oxygrenine can communicate
directly with the ruthenium complex you want to have the oxygrenine higher up so you need to have
have a charge transfer in in in the duplex in in this pipe stacking that you have inside the
dna what these what this charge transfer can happen so so all the the the round one the circles
they have they have the um they have the oxygrenine above the ligation site i mean higher up on the
dna away from from from the surface and all the triangles they have it very close to the surface
so so in a way we we uh these are the fastest ones but we don't like them because it doesn't
connect the two things very well but anyways it's it was kind of surprising to us that 63 out of these
160 test the strands they actually satisfy these conditions so that's uh that means that we if we
just make strands we should we should be possible for us to uh to actually make it work so the next
i'm going to tell you is is i'm not sure how much um how relevant it is for for the experiments but
i couldn't help doing it um and because you have you have the uh the these two mechanisms you have
the replication and you have the charge transfer and is there a sort of a mathematical way to connect
these two and it turns out that we a long time ago while i was still here still living here in in
Santa Fe um we actually did a study it was a grad no it's actually a grad undergraduate his name
is Tristan uh he did this here where we looked at a system where uh we have a single stranded
a dna or a template and we have an we have oligomers you can then make duplexes um
because they they uh they hybridize they are ligated and then they can uh separate against
you have two single stranded uh dna and then you have precursor lipids i mean oily substance
that that together with the duplex here um is able to to to make lipids so that's a these are sort of
the much simplified much more simplified system um where we have separated we earlier you know
previous work here earlier today we looked at this separately and this separately here we can
solve these two things uh together and and it's not so simple because we have to look at uh you
have to distinguish between the global concentration and the concentration of substances in these small
protocells on the surfaces so you have the local concentration of the template um and then what is
the volume of of the of the protocell container of the the surface and this is a number of of
protocells you have in the system that gives you the global the global concentration of of your
of your templates to give an example so it takes a little bit of of manipulation but you can get
get these equations out one for the uh for the production of of templates and one for the production
of the aggregates and in this you have a a replication rate and you have this metabolic rate
which i mean the metabolic rate is includes this charge transfer and it turns out that these two
equations if you if you divide this one with this one you get a Bernoulli equation that can
actually be solved analytically and um you can then if you do that uh you can then get a doubling
time expressed with all these things here and that means that you you actually if you look at it here
you have a a doubling time then you have to switch it around the to the reciprocal uh expression
so you get you get this k t squared and you have the uh the k sorry where is it and k l that's in
in uh that's in the first order and then this will be uh uh to one-third so so this if you want to
to uh to make a combined um fitness function or whatever you want to call it a gross rate function
then it will the best guess that we could come up with is using what we know from from this system
which is very similar although a simplification we will then have to multiply these two guys
with different with broken with broken exponents so if we do that and then we order our
uh our sequences again um where we we rank them from the worst to the best we get uh
yeah well it's yeah some kind of theoretical fitness uh coefficient for for for the system here
and you can see that it has it has the same shape as you can see here here they're sort of
they're they're civil they're these three uh plateaus of three different regimes uh if you
just go back here that's yeah so since i'm i can't follow some of the chemical details
is is the is this your design process for coming up with these sequences or is this a fitness
landscape that you're hoping these protocells cells mutate and and improve on so so so
this is more this particular thing i was i was debating whether i wanted to
you know include it or not because this is just for for i think this is more an intellectual
exercise because we we believe that this is the shape of a fitness function but since we
we've just taken these two constants there was many more constants or there are many more
parameters involved in the other system but i think that that will be sort of the functional form
um but you cannot make any quantitative uh assessments from from this uh to to the to the
real system but but ultimately is this is this sort of consideration what you're using to design
the best sequence or or are you hoping that the protocells will mutate and that the sequence of
the highest metabolic rate will take the population so so so here from we already know
which is uh which is a good uh uh charge transfer i mean you want to be up here because then you're
both good at charge charge transfer and you're good at replication so so you want to uh experimentally
want to you want to pick uh some of these sequences here and then uh once you've picked a sequence i
mean just there'll be a big party if we get it to work i mean if the system can just replicate
and and not die um then we can feed the system with the pieces of sequences that are better we
our calculations predict are better and if that's indeed true then we'll see a takeover of this of
the new co-factor and then there'll be another party so does that make sense
let's say the the the evolution isn't taking place through mutation exactly no no no i did
you you're feeding it like different oligomers yeah so so it can pick from different oligomers
and the i mean these oligomers they'll form uh they'll form these duplexes that are then
cofactors and the ones with a good co co-factor will uh i'll compete the other one yeah on the
same topic you design the oligomers so that they have the imperfections yes you need to do that
else we can't else we can't unless you so you play god you have to oh yeah with the imperfections
yes because otherwise you don't get that that's right that's right yeah no no we we have to i mean
in these are new imperfections because you break the molecule at the first imperfection right and
then it's gonna anneal again at the same imperfection so you have to you have to create a new
imperfection in what you're feeding with or no we just we just make sure that there are mismatches
or there is a basis in the right places matches what's that that there's some mismatch yeah there
has to be and and they can't well depending on where you put the mismatches it works well it
doesn't work very well so so there is a number of details that that i i don't think well i can
say one thing for sure that right at the ligation side that's where you have need to have a bulge
or a an airbase because without doing that you you won't you you will not prevent
what's it called product inhibition but but where you put the other mismatches depends on the rest
of this of the sequence for instance if you have lots of AT's they're weak compared to GC's so then
you if you have if you have sort of a GC heavy sequence you need to have more mismatches than
if you have an AT heavy sequence and and the ultimate goal here is that so that you ensure
growth of the lipid and the DNA and the little energy molecule at the first order rate kind of
over time you you ensure that that's the goal yeah the goal is to just have the have all the pieces
to play together no nobody has done that so far and that would be that'll be fantastic and then
i think that if we can make that play in the lab then i think to actually see a see an evolutionary
takeover will not be so hard i mean the difficult thing is to see whether this can actually work
just want to show one more fun thing here so yeah i think this is theoretically interesting
i don't think it helped us much too in the lab but here's another thing that this was
Artemis he pointed out that it's actually interesting to to look at the functional
information it's not easy to calculate the functional information in in real molecular
systems but in this system it is easy because we we can we can this is a hasten hasten's paper
we used or his idea i guess it's from a show stack originally but anyways we can we can calculate
the probability that we have a strand if you pick a strand at random from these
what is it hundred and and 60 strands i get yeah you know it's 160 strand so what is the chance that
it satisfies this condition divided by the total number of strands that gives you the
probability that you pick a strand that's good enough for a charge transfer you can do the same
for replication and you can ask for both of them to be fulfilled and then you have the probability
for that and then we can calculate the computation the compositional functional information by
taking the the logarithm minus the logarithm and then simply calculates these and then
we'll get these results out and if you look at it here
we have calculated the oh yeah so this is a functional information from for the charge transfer
process where we have again ranked them so we've said the bad ones first and they get better and
better and better and better and they will then level out up here at about 2.32 bits because
we have 32 strands that have identical charge transfer rates so that's why it stops there
it's a little bit different over here for the replication but if you do the calculation you get
just one point 34 bits for for of information is necessary to ensure
growths about self-sustaining so it's not very much information but again there were 63 strands
out of these 160 that satisfied our our goal so i'm sorry yeah experimental what this plots
they will stay cases you got this howl from experimental no no no this is this is from
by taking by ranking um uh by by simply calculating the this is the the functional
information here by by calculating the functional information uh then then you you'll have as you
go through the strands then as you get better and better strands uh there'll be fewer you have
to be more and more lucky to pick the right strands and if then rank order them you get a staircase
like that does that make sense what do you what do you say yes going back to chris's question
if you did this as a full population explicit evolutionary situation you'd say the strands
that survived only gained 1.34 bits over the strands that didn't survive everything
sort of like the information dealt yes yes yes yes but but there will be but there will be a
even though you just make it over the threshold then there'll be some that are better than just
doing the threshold so so you can then calculate what that is i mean this is the threshold for
for for these 50 per second for the for the charge transfer and and this is the one for the
replication over here so are you maybe we can talk about it afterwards how we how we do this
but it is it's it's really not it's very simple you just you just take the you just rank order
um how much information there is as you improve as you improve the strands
and and so this is the best ones they are the ones that are fastest here okay so
so hypothetically what we want is to set up a chemostat where we put in resources and then
we have a certain outflow rate and so this is the inflow rate this is the outflow rate
and we have to know the hydrolysis of all these processes or all the the products or the the
i'm sorry the the input and and and these are then the fitness rank cofactors and and this is
where we've used we can think about it from from what we calculated earlier and these are the
resources these are the different types of oligomers in the system as well as as a picolinium
ester and we have to have this proton donor etc etc and we then get i mean you are probably
familiar with these with these chemostat equations and you then get if you look at the biomass we
then get a transition for life where these where this is fulfilled and and i think what's interesting
is that it's extremely important it's not just the um the the what's it called the gross factors
or the fitness function you you have to look at what the degradation rates and then as you can
see the rest of it is actually environmental parameters which are really important and then
to end up here we have a so that's i guess our perspective on on what what's going on
where we have a if this is again lined up where we take the strands the cofactor with higher and
higher fitness so so once you are below this self-maintaining threshold you will be flushed out by
the chemostat but if once you're above it then you'll actually have a biomass existing in terms of
protocells and if you just pick these strands at random and provide them then it'll probably be
you know a discontinuous there'll be discontinuous jumps if you if you put them in sort of one
after the other with the one is a little bit better then it'll be approached or it'll be
approximated with that with a continuous curve so you know i know that the literature people talk
about whether you can view the transition to life as a first or a second order phase transition in
biomass and i think you can you can you can do both here and also the the same will be true this is
our it's just a symbolic representation of the functional information here and yeah this is where
once once you actually have a cofactor that's able to support this protocell life cycle then
you have the possibility of starting to to select information or store and select information
once the co cofactor doesn't provide you fast enough metabolism and fast enough replication
then the system will just be flushed out
so so what did we get out of this study i mean i i was you know you go in there and you don't know
what well i didn't know anything about charge transfer my my graduate student denied us so we
had to we had to take a crash course and that and and many people are real specialists they all said
oh we have to do quantum calculations of initial calculation but if we did that you know we'd have
to occupy one of the big machines for for weeks for for making a calculation of a single duplex
and we wanted to have an ensemble to figure out you know what what what the differences were so
that was why we we did this this differential equation approach instead but the most important
thing is that we can't really reject that this will work i mean along the way when we've
tried to implement this a living system in the lab from time to time we've
has either been impossible experimentally or we've figured out that we hadn't thought about
enough and theoretically we we made a boo boo but here it seems like 30 or 63 of them are actually
okay and then there are some assumptions that i think is important we have assumed that we have
super exchange uh across the bulge across this uh ligation site we couldn't figure out whether
this is indeed true or not uh we couldn't find any literature on it we did assume that it is possible
if it is not possible then we need to use uh we need to put our oxygen in just below the
ligation side so that you need to still have a hybridization you need to have a duplex
for for having the charge transferred to to actually work and another important
approximation is that we don't have any interactions between the charge transport and the
replication dynamics or the environment so we are sort of using a super a simple superposition
of the two and of course a more comprehensive simulation that's much more complicated would
take all these things into consideration but we didn't dare to venture into that
so so i think these are the two most important uh sort of simplifications and and then of course
the main issue here is to hopefully convince a sponsor that we can we can test this in the lab
thank you
questions
else i'll be around until uh May 8th so we can talk if you have questions