Hello and welcome, everyone. It's July 22nd, 2024. This is Active Inference guest stream
82.3. The Projective Wave Theory of Consciousness. Robert Warden will give a presentation and
we have several others to join and comment and give their insights. So thank you everyone
for joining and Robert, please begin the presentation. And also, Robert, close the YouTube on your
side. All good.
It's Active Inference guest stream 82.3.
Right.
I've objectively, it's coming through on my loud speaker, which is a problem.
Yeah, it's all good. Like, all good.
Okay. So this is a talk about the Projective Wave Theory of Consciousness. And there's
already a paper about it on Archive this month. So you can look at the paper if you like.
But let me start by describing roughly the roadmap for the talk. The Projective Wave
Theory is very closely related to the Projective Consciousness Model, PCM. And we're fortunate
to have three of the authors of that model on the call today. But I'm going to give this talk
in four different parts. The first part is talking about data. And the idea is that any theory of
consciousness has to fit the data, has to fit some data in order for us to believe it. And so the
question is, what kinds of data is there about consciousness that the theory has to fit? And I
should be arguing that the main kind of data we have is spatial consciousness. So that's part one
of the talk. Part two, I shall talk about the Projective Consciousness Model, PCM. And to my
mind, the big virtue of the PCM is that it does predict account for just that, the spatial nature
of consciousness. And in that, it's a great deal. It does a great deal better than many neural theories
of consciousness. And I shall probably pause at that point after parts one and two and have
discussion about the first two points there. But before that, I think the PCM has great
strengths. But I think in common with all neural theories of consciousness, it has three problems.
And I shall talk about what those problems are. But I shall emphasize that those problems are not
specific to the PCM. If you buy into the classical neural model of the brain that neurons do everything,
then whatever your theory of consciousness, I think you're going to have these problems.
And so in order to get out of those problems, we have to do something that's not in the classical
neural model that assumes that neurons in the brain do everything. So we have to add something
to the PCM. And the something we have to add is there in three. The assumption we're going to add
to it is quite a big one. It's an assumption that there is a wave in the brain which stores
3D spatial information. In other words, neurons don't do everything. And then part four of the
talk, I shall bring those two and three together to a projective wave theory of consciousness.
And talk a little bit about firstly, how it solves the neural problems, but secondly,
how it fits the data and some more general considerations about it. So that is the root
map of the talk. So we start off with what are the reasons to believe some theory, whether
there's theory of consciousness or anything else. Why do we believe it? Basically, we believe a
theory because it fits data. And it there's a complexity measure here that needs to fit more
data, which you can measure in bits, if you like, than the complexity of the assumptions you put
into it. If you just put in a huge number of assumptions and fit a small amount of data,
that's no use. So there's a kind of Bayesian balance between the assumptions you put into a
theory and the data it fits. And I've illustrated the Bayesian balance, a pair of scales here. And
I've measured the complexity of the theory and the amount of data it tests by a so-called zip
test, which simply says you describe these things in text files, you zip them up and you see how big
they are. So established theories in science like a theory of physics or chemistry have a hugely
positive Bayesian balance. They have quite few assumptions and they account for huge amounts
of data. So how can we get to that point with the theory of consciousness? How can a theory of
consciousness produce a positive Bayesian balance between its assumption and the data it accounts
for? So the question arises, what is the data we have to test theories of consciousness? And there's
a big problem, which is well known, that consciousness is a private experience. So there's not much
public data about it. But there are several kinds of data we can use, such as data about levels of
consciousness, alertness and being asleep and so on, data about quality. And they are problematic
because they're private phenomena. But nevertheless, two people can agree something about similarity
scales of their quality, like different colors being similar or different. And the form C is the
shapes of things in spatial consciousness. And I shall argue that the main manifestation of
consciousness, which we have, what we're experiencing right now, is a 3D spatial model of the world
around us. And that 3D model is very detailed and quite faithful to the real world around us.
And so that has a large information content. Going down the list, there's conscious imagination,
there is consciousness of the self, there are anomalies and illusions of consciousness,
and there is the hard problem, if you like, the existence of consciousness itself. Now I shall
argue that point C, the shape of spatial consciousness gives us much more data to test any theory
than any other type of data. So what's the testable data in spatial consciousness?
Spatial consciousness is like a 3D model of the real world around you. That's what you're
experiencing right now. And it has a lot of the geometry of the real world, and particularly
straight lines in consciousness correspond to straight lines in the real world. And you can
test this. I won't go into the years of how. So this agreement between our conscious experience,
which is quite information rich, and the real world around us, which is obviously information
risk, gives a lot of data to test any theory of consciousness. And I suggest roughly it gives
us thousands of bits, even in a few seconds. And I shall suggest that no other form of data
about consciousness comes anywhere close to this in terms of testable information content.
So if you really want to prove your theories right, then it's got to account for the spatial
form of consciousness if you're going to believe it. And down at the right here, I put my conclusion
that spatial consciousness is, if you like, the element in the room, consciousness theory.
So we have to consider how the brain does spatial cognition. And all animal brains pretty much do
that. They have to understand 3D's local space for a very fundamental reason, just to control
their every movement, to move every movement of their limbs, they have to understand 3D space
around them. And there's been huge selection pressure to do this well. And we believe that
animals do it very well, even insects do it quite well. And also it appears that most of the animal
brain is devoted to that. Now, if we assume a Bayesian hypothesis about cognition, then the way
animals do that is to build a maximum likelihood 3D model of local space in their brains from their
sense data. So it becomes fairly natural to expect that spatial consciousness is going to be linked
to this spatial model. And the question is, is it a purely neural model as a classical neural
models of the brain? And if it is, how does neuron firing represent 3D space? And this is quite a
difficult problem. And really, there are very few viable solutions to it. But I shall switch now,
I shall put that problem on one side and switch to the Projective Consciousness Model, PCM,
which has been developed by David and has collaborated since about 2017, and it's built on the
free energy principle. So it's based on a Bayesian model of local space in the brain.
And for its neural process model, it assumes the process model of the free energy principle.
And so the PCM assumes that the brain holds a 3D projective transform model of local Euclidean
space. And the key thing is that PCM then predicts that spatial consciousness is like
that model. And this is a very good prediction. It agrees very well with data. For instance,
the trivial fact that straight lines in your consciousness are straight lines in the real
world. So the PCM has a good Bayesian balance. I should say this is very distinctive amongst
many theories of consciousness. Very few of them talk about the spatial nature of consciousness.
And if they do, they probably treat it as a bit of an afterthought. But the PCM puts it
out in the front. And I think that's a very positive feature of it. And it has a good Bayesian
balance. And it does make various other predictions which people have talked about in the papers,
makes predictions about illusions of consciousness, and makes predictions about
predictive imagination and planning actions. Now, I don't think those are quite as significant
in the Bayesian balance in the agreement with the data as the basic agreement with the
form of consciousness right now. Consciousness from sense data. But I shall say the PCM has
three difficulties. I shall emphasize they're not difficulties of the PCM alone. I believe
they are difficulties of any neural theory of consciousness. And I'll just list them briefly
here because there's going to be a slide describing them. The first difficulty is neural
selection. How do we pick out just those neurons which cause consciousness from all the others that
don't? And the second one is neural precision and speed. We know that our conscious model of space
is a very detailed and precise one. Can you do that with neuron firing? I would suggest you can't.
And the third one is a complex decoding problem that, anyway, I'll come onto that.
So I'll describe these three in a minute. But the emphasis is that they are not just problems
of the PCM. They are difficulties for any neural theory of consciousness, for instance, IIT or
global neural workspace theory and so on. So what are the three difficulties? The neural
selection problem. Most neurons in the brain are not linked to consciousness. We know that from
cortical lesions, we don't interrupt consciousness, or the cerebellum, or Bjorn Merkur has written
quite extensively about this. But neuron theories of consciousness say that the activity of some
neurons causes consciousness and not others. So the question is how are those special neurons
selected? And as far as I know, there's no sound physical basis to pick out some neurons from
all the others. So you build in some selection assumptions into your hypothesis, but those
form a debit in your Bayesian balance. So they're a debit for any neural theory of consciousness.
The second difficulty is how do neurons represent space? Now, there are several possible ways of
having neurons representing 3D space. You can represent 2D space, all right? Can you return to
sharing the screen? Oh, sorry, I've lost sharing, have I? All good.
So how do neurons represent 3D space? There are several ways they might do it, but they all have
problems of precision and speed. For instance, there is a Bayesian computational model of how
animals build 3D internal model of space from their sense data. And this is already on one of the
AI live streams that this YouTube address. But that model shows that in order to build a 3D model
of space, even for a small animal like a bee, you need memory storage errors to be roughly the order
1% as small as that. Whereas if you model neurons accurately, properly, they don't give you this
precision because in a neuron, most theoretical models of neurons are ideal abstract neurons whose
outputs are real variables of high precision. And that's shown in the top of this picture here.
Whereas actually, neurons' outputs are spike trains, which in a short time scale gives very
limited precision. For instance, in a fifth of the second possible time scale for consciousness,
you may get about 10 pulses. And that gives you a precision of only 30% in that time scale.
So the precision you get from neural representations is very different from what you need to build
a decent 3D model or what we experience in consciousness. And this, I think, hasn't been
really spotted very much because most of the neural models that you see in the literature,
they don't model spike trains. It's different enough to model networks of neurons. And so
they use abstract, precise neurons. So that's the second difficulty. How can neurons store
precise and responsive, fast model of 3D space like the one we experience?
Finally, can you see that change? Third difficulty? The third difficulty is what I call the hard
triangle because conscious experience, which is C in this picture here, is a faithful, hardly
distorted model of the real world. There's the real world, A, and there's consciousness
awareness, C. But what the models we have found in the brain are two-dimensional models and very
distorted models. And so they're many different models, and they're highly complex encoding to
get from A to B. So if you want to get back from B to C, you have to do very complex decoding to
undo all the complex coding that most species brains do. And so ABC is the hard triangle.
You have to have complex decoding assumptions in any neural theory of consciousness. And the
worst thing of that maybe is that the decoding has to be species specific. It can't be universal
decoding. So those are the three difficulties for any neural theory of consciousness, including the
PCM, I believe. So that's where we've got to. I've covered topics one and two of this talk,
and now I think we'll break for any discussion or contributions.
Thank you very much, Robert, for your presentation up to now. I can follow it very well. I think
you point out very important issues. I should say, and perhaps we scan,
that from the standpoint of the PCM, even though indeed we have framed it in the context of active
influence and more specifically the free energy principle, we do not necessarily
entail, it does not necessarily entail that we buy or we endorse or we believe in
the current neural network models that are used in this context. Personally, I've been a neuroscientist
for many years. I've done a lot of electrophysiology, lesion work with human patients. Also, I worked
with rodent. I've done a lot of functionally maging and modeling. At some point in my career,
I thought that I did not understand the brain well enough, and I stopped doing neuroscience. I stopped
carrying quote-unquote about the brain. For us, what is the most important in the PCM at this point
is all you said, is that we can capture some aspect of this phenomenology that seems essential,
et cetera, et cetera. Personally, I have given up at this point trying to
devise or figure out any realistic neural network models. When you take just one neuron,
as you said, Robert, it's a universe. You just think about how receptors are
or downregulated through fast gene expression or dendritic trees and their complexities
and their geometry plays a role in computation. I don't believe that the spiking of the neurons,
which we often call the output of the neuron, are necessarily where we should be looking at.
I don't know where we should be looking at. I committed an odd paper a long time ago in 2015,
in which I kind of said, well, I explained why I had given up hope at this point about brain
science to account for that, because I think we don't understand the brain. I think they are
principle we haven't figured out yet by far. My guess was that a bit like by analogy with
computer science, there are layers of abstraction, mechanism of virtualization that hide the detail
of the hardware, which we don't understand at all. And so far, it's a very open-ended thing.
So to me, what matters the most about the PCM at this point is with respect to the brain,
it is neutral. We don't know. At this point, I have absolutely no hypothesis, except very
gross anatomy of hypothesis, but also possible details about, but you're right,
that's the hard problem. And personally, I have given up on trying to account for it.
Thanks, David. I find so much to agree with there. And so, yeah, we don't understand what's going on
in the brain. Maybe neurons are doing something much more complicated than simple spike trains,
but maybe there's also this wave, and we'll talk about that. Carl, Ken, do you have any comments
on this thing? Carl, you want to go ahead? Or I can, if you don't mind, I'll just follow up with,
I completely agree with what David said. And I will say my own sort of approach to the problem has
always been sort of agnostic about the underlying realization. So I've kind of started from,
in my own thinking anyway, always from the point of view of phenomenology with some kind of,
you might say, general acceptance of some sort of physicalism, but agnostic about the details of
that physicalism. So agnostic about whether it's exactly what goes on in the brain or what level
and so on. I guess I've tended to, even though I agree you can't exclude it a priori, I've tended
to kind of think, well, quantum mechanical theories are probably barking up the wrong tree,
but that's just like my gut on that. And then I'm sorry, personally, Ken, at this point,
I'm so confused about the brain and about the physical nature of the universe that
I'm even totally open that the whole thing is quantum. I have no idea.
Okay. Yeah, as I said, it's just sort of like my gut on that, but not, I can't really defend it
in detail for a number of reasons, going to my own ignorance. But and I would just add that,
and I agree, I think the way you presented the PCM, generally was exactly right. You did mention
that we do have something to say about imagination, like action planning, and about anomalies and
illusions. And we, you know, we agree with you, I think that the main set of data we aim to capture
are the spatial component of consciousness and the perspectival spatial component, like,
you know, the project, what we use, projective geometry to capture. But then we do try to,
as you know, try to derive certain other bits of parts of the relevant data from that basis. So
accounting for illusions, like the moon illusion and the aims room illusion, and accounting for
imaginative action planning. And also, I should add some data about self awareness. So we have
paper on self awareness in this context as well. So, yeah, I think that's all I got so far. But
this is this has been very interesting so far. Thanks again. Come on.
How can I make any comments? No, I'm just enjoying this as a spectator,
batting for both sides. One comment, it seems to me that we're focusing on the distinction between
principles on about how the brain makes sense of its world and the process theories that attend
those principles in terms of instantiation. And there's an agnostic approach I think you can take
in relation to process theories. So I'm interested to see how much Robert's focus will be on the
process theory and the actual substrates, which I think is interesting from the point of view of
actually simulating this kind of inference and also being able to reproduce it in silico in
terms of creating a kind of artificial intelligence that has this kind of competence. So there may
be a more pragmatic focus. I was intrigued by the previous slide, this hard triangle.
Yeah, just go to it there. Yeah, I didn't quite resonate with this. I think for a start the
notions of encoding and decoding for people like me should be usefully unpacked. So everything in
terms of belief updating is some kind of mapping or morphism or relationship. So I'm assuming...
Mapping is a good word for it. Yeah. Okay, so the world generates sensory inputs and then the brain
represents those inputs. I mean, for B, you just imagine the visual cortex with a highly distorted
version of space in it, all around the fovea and so on, and all the other cortical maps,
a highly distorted representation of space. Somehow you have to tram all those back into
an undistorted representation. So you've got to decode the encoding that's gone on.
I see. Right, so the conscious awareness is still part of the brain somewhere.
But it must come from the brain somewhere, I think. Yes, we all. I see. So you're using encoding and
decoding in a sort of... Distorting, undistorting. It's like a distorting mirror, you've got to
undistort it. But I guess it relates to Karl's distinction between neural substrate and process
theory. Because indeed, if you look at the classical sort of quote-unquote 2D maps in the
cerebral cortex, for instance, the visual cortex with your retinotopy, where you see a lot of
deformation, but also somatosensory cortices, you think about the classical map of the body.
And you are saying, well, if that's the way it is kind of represented quote-unquote at the level of
that substrate, then since it is deformed and we don't experience it that way, we should somehow
have a process on top of that that use some morphism to transform this deformation.
I'm saying our theory of consciousness has to tell us how that unscrambling distortion happens.
Yeah, but I believe that the level of observation that we are considering here,
for instance, those 2D quote-unquote 2D, because they are not really 2D, but
cortical maps, retinotopic or somatotopic or topic maps are a very quote-unquote low level
of processing, which might be very far away from what is going on at the level of the process.
There might be some other super representation somewhere, but we've not found it yet.
Yeah, it might not be visible at the level of the anatomy.
Well, yeah, those are alternatives, I agree.
Okay, so sorry Carl, I interrupted, but I wanted to make this precision too.
Yeah, no, that clarifies it, thank you.
But Carl, I think we can all be agnostic about certain things in the process model.
I think you and I at least are not agnostic about basing into them.
Yeah, I would put the notion of
sentience of the kind we're talking about as a process of basing belief updating.
I put that at the sort of principle level, at the mechanics that doesn't commit to
an infrastructure or a realization or a process that realizes that kind of principle,
that kind of mechanics. So I think the spatial wave theory is really a commitment to a process
theory that could happily accommodate basing belief updating and its particular application,
the context of spatial perception and the projected consciousness model.
You're muted.
Oh, yes.
Okay, so moving on.
So we've done one and two, and what we're going to do in three is add something to the PCM.
And the thing we're going to add is not a little thing.
It's the assumption, the hypothesis that neurons don't do everything, but there is a wave in the
brain which stores 3D spatial information. So that's what I'm going to talk about next.
So here's the hypothesis. There is a wave in the brain that represents 3D space.
So it assumes there is some nearly spherical region of the brain with a diameter D and it
holds waves, which couples the neurons. And there the sphere is illustrated and a couple of waves,
wavelength lambda two, the green wave, and wavelength lambda one, a shorter wavelength,
that red wave. And those waves represent things in space. And they represent the red
thing R1 and the green thing R2. So there's an inverse relationship there. The shorter the
wavelength, the longer the distance to the thing that's being represented. But obviously,
if it's a spherical region, you can have waves in any direction. So you can represent any direction
and any distance up to a maximum, which is defined by the minimum wavelength.
So that wave can represent lots of different things. And the hypothesis is that that wave
acts as a working memory for space. It's really like a hologram. Now, one issue with that is
that if you want to represent objects at very large distances away, then you get into wavelengths
that's too short. So that's why you may need a projective transform of space to pull in those
long distances to be able to represent them on the wave. By the way, the evidence for this wave
is going to be described in another YouTube livestream, which we're making next week,
is going to get that address. So, well, there's a wave based spatial memory form.
It can represent approximately d of a lambda cubed independent positions, which is quite a lot.
And it can give you spatial precision for the order of lambda over d. And the point is that this
can easily be 1% or better, which is the precision you need. So there are significant benefits to
wave storage. It has high capacity. You can put many objects in it. It has a high precision.
It can be fast. And it has low spatial distortion. It is just like a hologram.
And it's a very simple and direct representation of space. So a spoiler looking at part four of
the talk is that this is very much like spatial consciousness. Question is there any evidence
for such a wave? I think there is evidence and there's three kinds of evidence. First two come
from brain anatomy, because there are spherical regions in the brain, which are very well suited
to hold this wave. In the mammals, there is a thalamus, and that's shown in green on the
left of the picture. And you see it's approximately spherical. And that is very suitably connected
for holding spatial information. It's connected to all the sense data, and it's connected to all
the bits of cortex that work out what to do with the sense data. And similarly, in the insect brain,
there is a central body in the very center of it. That is approximately spherical, and it's very
well preserved shape in all insect species. So those are both pieces of evidence for a wave in
the brain. There is a place for it. So I believe there are three lines of evidence for a wave.
One is the computational neuroscience, which I mentioned before, that spatial cognition is a
very important thing, but neural memory for it is too imprecise and too slow. Whereas a wave
storage model can possibly overcome these problems. So that's the yellow evidence, the evidence from
the insect central body that is nearly round, very central, very well connected. And there's evidence
from the mammalian thalamus. It's also round and well connected. But there's also what I call a
smoking gun for a wave in the thalamus that if you don't assume a wave, the anatomy of the
thalamus doesn't make sense. But I won't go into that in this talk. So together, I believe these
give quite strong support for the wave hypothesis. In fact, they give it a probability of 0.5
approximately, even if you try and weight the odds against it. As I say, you can see the
discussion of this in another YouTube live stream we're about to make. So
then that's on from part three to part four of talk.
Assume there is a wave in the brain, which holds the near-projective transform of 3D space. And
this wave is serving a very essential role to understand space to control all movements for
any animal. And the hypothesis simply is the wave is the origin of consciousness.
That neurons have nothing to do with consciousness at all. It comes entirely from the wave.
This solves three problems, the three problems that I outlined before. Firstly, the neural selection
problem, no selection problem, because neurons have nothing to do with consciousness. The precision
and speed problem, the wave has sufficient precision and speed to do it. And the decoding
problem, the coding in the wave is just a Fourier transform. So it's a very simple coding,
encoding, and it's a very simple decoding to give you back conscious experience.
So it has solved those three problems of neural theories. But the main thing is that spatial
like the PCM, preserving the merit of the PCM, the spatial form of consciousness
agrees very well with our conscious experience. It has to be projected because we need the
projection transform to pull in objects from very large distances to represent them by a minimum
wavelength. So in summary, the projective wave theory has a positive Bayesian balance,
doesn't have any Nazis about it, and it agrees very well with the main source of data about consciousness.
So just some aspects of this theory. What is the physical nature of the wave? A big objection
might be we've never seen the wave because I believe it's probably not an electromagnetic
wave or an electromagnetic field. And the main reason I believe that is that electromagnetic
fields on their own don't store information. For the time periods, we need to store information.
And now electromagnetic fields might be part of the answer, but I think they're not the whole
answer. And the big question then is why have we not detected this wave in the brain? It's been
there all these years. I think the reason for that is if there is a wave representing space,
we will expect it to evolve to have very low intensity. So its energy consumption is very
small. And having that low intensity, we simply haven't known how to look for it.
Now, coming to quantum possibilities, the wave might be a coherent quantum
excitation. And there's increasing evidence that quantum effects do have a role in biology.
And it might even be a Bose-Einstein condensate, a BEC. Now those examples of those are superconductors
and superfluids, they're very rash state in nature. But the key thing about a BEC is
a superconductor can hold information for unlimited time. So it would be good for memory.
And they're a very rare and distinctive state of matter. And so if you assume that consciousness
comes from them, you don't get to a trough of panpsychism. Or it might not be a quantum effect,
because I think that this question is entirely open. So we'll set that on one side and that's
future exploration. There is an issue about the evolution of consciousness. We know that
consciousness is, our consciousness is like the real world. It's very like the real world.
And the question is why is this? And you think, well, it must have evolved that way because
some need for it to be like the real world. But in neural theories, there's a problem.
Because neural computation in the brain, the classical neural model, is classical dynamics,
not quantum physics, and is local. And so consciousness is a non physical, non local
effect, and they don't have any effect on neurons firing. So the result is that consciousness in
a neural theory has no causal effect on fitness. That means there's no selection pressure on it
to make it the way it is. So in a neural theory of consciousness, we're driven to this slightly
awkward conclusion that the special form of consciousness that we have is just a bit of
an accident. That seems very unlikely. Whereas in the projective wave theory,
there is a good evolutionary reason for consciousness being like it is. That is that
3D spatial cognition is very important. Wave is an essential part of it. So the wave has been
shaped by evolution. And it's been shaped to be just like the real world, because that's the best
way of controlling. So consciousness then is determined by the wave. And that means consciousness
has evolved to be like that. So the wave theory solves another problem there.
Finally, the unity of consciousness. You may ask this question occasionally, why do I only have
one consciousness and not several parallel consciousnesses? And this also is something
with difficulty neural theories, because we have plenty of neurons in the brain to have many
parallel consciousnesses. And brains can do some things in massive parallelism. And if we had
multiple parallel consciousness, it might be useful, for instance, for parallel planning of
action to see which one works. That's a difficulty for neural theories. The wave theory doesn't
have this difficulty because it accounts for the unity of consciousness. There's only one wave in
the brain. That is the source of consciousness. So there can only be one consciousness.
I think I'm on to the last slide now, pretty much the last slide. If this theory is taken
serious, it makes consciousness into a scientific problem rather than a philosophical problem.
Because a wave in the brain, if a wave in the brain is the key to understanding consciousness,
well, if there's no wave, then this theory is wrong. Get about it. If there is a wave,
I think there are very strong reasons to link it to consciousness, because it has such a good fit
to consciousness. So whether or not the wave exists, that's a scientific question. It's not a
question for philosophy. And I think there's a good prospect of answering it in the next 10 years.
So in 10 years time, either this theory will be the only theory of consciousness,
or it will be wrong and forgotten. I think that's a virtue and a theory.
So finally, last slide on the hard problem, David Chalmers' hard problem. The
predicted wave theory doesn't solve that problem. What I'd say about that is all
science has hard problems. There is the hard problem of consciousness. Why is consciousness
and link to matter? There are hard problems in physics, like what is space-time, or what is the
most fundamental particle? Or the hard problem of cosmology, why is there a universe? So hard
problems just don't have an answer. Scientists will like children keeping asking why, say why this,
why that. And we can go on asking why for as long as we like. So for instance, for fundamental
particles, we thought there was matter, we thought there were atoms, we got to protons,
we got to quarks, and we keep going on and we'll never get the final answer. But we still do science.
So I'm not too worried about the hard problem, consciousness. So that is all, and I've just
laid out a few questions or might want to discuss in the remaining time.
Maybe you could share your slide again so we can see the question if you have them on the slide.
Sorry, is it not sharing now? I see the slide still. Yeah, so you can leave it, maybe check
your view, David. And then you can leave that up and we can have a panel discussion.
Well, thanks a lot. Those who are here can, and Carl and David, please feel free to comment.
And also people will write some questions in the chat and I'll read one in if you pause. But
anyone here who'd like to give a reflection or any comments, that would be awesome.
Could I go ahead? Can you hear me? So if I may, I basically agree with what you say about the
hard problem, just to take the very last thing that you mentioned about the hard problem. And
this is why earlier on when you said that you had kind of a list of sort of, you know,
the idea of the Bayesian balance for theories of consciousness, and you mentioned the existence
of consciousness as itself, something that might be a problem for all neuronal theories of consciousness.
I think you did that on the slide too. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, so I agree. I think it's a problem for any
theory of consciousness, even the kind of more metaphysical theories that people who reflect
like Chalmers and others, panpsychists who reflect on the hard problem a certain way
end up with, you can actually raise the same set of questions for them. So there's really no progress
there, in my opinion. So in other words, if you take the hard problem as a kind of indication
that, well, consciousness couldn't be physical, or, or either that, or the physical world itself
must just be consciousness, which is kind of the two directions they go there. I think that's kind
of misguided. I mean, we, we have to sort of accept that our ability to penetrate, you know,
cognitively, a priori into the nature of the cosmos is, is limited. So our, the best we can do is
make models and, you know, based on the phenomenology and try to arrive at a model that would give us
some kind of neural or physical, to speak more broadly, physical, testable, you know,
hypothesis, hypotheses we can test about the physical world, what we think realizes consciousness.
And it seems to me like that's exactly what you're doing. And that's what I would think is, is right
too. But I did want to ask you, when you say that no neurons are linked to consciousness in your own
model, do you mean, maybe I just don't understand exactly, but they're not linked directly to
consciousness. Okay. But there's some involved in the realization of the wave. Is that Oh,
they are absolutely, they're controlling the wave, they're setting up the wave. They're all
on the cortex, they're using sense data to, to fix the wave. And it's the wave that makes consciousness.
Okay. And on the issue of unity, well, so suppose we identify this type of wave. I mean, it's at
least, you know, conceivable that we would find multiple such waves. Would you can see
well, I think the evidence in the thalamus and the central body is one way.
Okay. And I think one way is what you need to understand one space around you.
Okay. So, but if you found multiple such waves, would you be an issue? Yeah, okay. Well, I mean,
would you conclude that there must be multiple consciousnesses, then in a single brain? Or
would you, would you think that the theory is wrong? No, I would have a selection problem,
just like neuron theories have a selection problem, selecting neurons. I'd have a problem
selecting which wave is conscious. I see. Rather than conclude that there are multiple.
You want to avoid that. My experience is I don't have multiple consciousnesses. Yes.
Right. But that might just be because only one of them gets to report.
Yeah, absolutely. No, like, like the way they, you know, I know it's debatable, but the way they
often interpreted the split brain cases coming out of. Yeah, good question. Good question. I mean,
I say one wave, but we have two thalamus. So the assumption there is that those waves are linked
and perhaps in split brain, they don't get linked. Okay. I think two thalamus have one wave in them,
that's a detail. I see. And then when it comes to the kind of wave, like,
so you don't think it's an electromagnetic wave, you think it might be a Bose-Einstein
condensate. That's a hypothesis, I think, that Karen Smith once flowed. It's been around for some
years. Yeah. Alexander Karen Smith in the book. That's the, yeah, not the book on the origin,
the famous book on the origin of life, but he wrote a book on consciousness back in the 90s,
I think. Yeah, there was Michael Lockwood as well in the 80s, I think. It's a long history.
Okay. So how, when you say that you think we'll be able to probe this within the next 10 years,
I mean, could you sort of sketch how that might go, how we might be able to. Yeah. I mean, just,
this is not, this is probing the idea of the wave. Right. As I say, I think there are those three
pieces of, there's neural models that you can't build decent neural models. There is the thalamus
and there is the insect central body. I think we can go further on each one of those. We can test
them. We can test the thalamus ideas much better using connectome data. We can test the central
body using connectome data. And we can test the computational models by just trying to build them
and see if we get in. So there is science to be done to falsify this hypothesis and it may
succeed in falsifying it. Okay. But how would you measure such condensate? I mean, if you want to
be able to demonstrate the existence of the problem. Ideally, you'd like to actually directly
detect it. I think it's a bit like when Pauli in the 1930s predicted the neutrino. He thought it's
absolutely impossible to detect neutrinos. And it took 25 years to find it. And I think it'll take
a long time to really find this wave in the brain, because it's very low intensity, probably,
and because we just don't know how to look for it. And I think we have to do the biophysics
until we have a convincing case for eyes, this kind of wave, and then we can build a detector.
But until then, I think we won't detect it like neutrino or like dark matter.
Similar thing predicted theoretically years ago, but still not detected.
I'll read a question from the live chat.
Okay. Andrea Val wrote, thanks for sharing such interesting ideas. I wonder how the
PCM or 3D model can explain or deal with the un slash consciousness of emotions.
So where is affectant such in this kind of spatialized model?
Yeah. So maybe you want to join the PCM first, David?
If it's okay, Robert, maybe you have read some recent work on that, but I have a specific
answer to that question. Yeah, you go first.
Yeah, sorry about that. Well, one of the things that we realized working with that
particular geometry is it transform information in the sense of information in space. You can
think about distribution in space, for instance, that are going to be changed by projective
transformation in a manner that affect directly entropy. So if something is very far,
you know, and you have some uncertainty about the localization of these things,
so there is a probability function that represent that uncertainty about the localization
of that thing. And there is only one thing in your field of consciousness to simplify the problem.
Then the entropy of the whole space, if you consider the whole 3D space and some
scalar on it that would represent probabilities is very small. Whereas when you get closer,
for instance, by imagination, the projective transformation that anticipates action,
you get the object closer and you transform also the information, the variance, if you wish,
of your distribution, so it becomes broader. So the entropy increase, actually,
as an effect of projective transformation on the distribution of information.
So how does that relate to emotion? What we realized is that it can account for some
drives that are related to exploration or exploratory behavior or search behavior
to reduce uncertainty or maximize information. And that just does that. So basically,
the projective transformation by in virtue of making probabilities function in space
change their shape as a function of perspective taking, if you wish, until or induce a drive
to approach or avoid things or in this context to approach behavior either through imagination
or through actual behavior because that will maximize information by increasing entropy
of the object and you have more details. So that's something that we wrote a paper that is
currently under review in biological cybernetics about that with Gregor Sergent-Pertu as first
author with a bright mathematician and we can do a demonstration and actually direct theorems about
that and also simulations that show interesting behaviors that depend on projective parameters
that will show that the behavior of the agent, depending on the parameter, will be more focused.
So they will tend to always approach one object because they are driven by this anticipation
of increasing information through projective transformation. But with other parameters or
values of the parameters on the contrary, they start now oscillating between objects.
They start losing focus as if they were kind of ADHD. So there is a deep link between let's say
the evaluation of space, the appraisal of space, the drives that are that unfold from this information
and the behaviors that you have, for instance, approaching and that geometry, that very geometry
we are talking about yield, that type of thing. So here we are talking about what is typically
described as epistemic emotion, basically curiosity. So we have natural curiosity and part of it
that drives behaviors is a result of the very geometry that represents information and appraisal
according to that theory. I cannot enter into the detail on that, but you can also look on
papers that we wrote in what was that 2022 in the Journal of Theoretical Biology in which we use
little robots to demonstrate adaptive and maladaptive behaviors with principles also derived
from the geometry and the free energy principle or something equivalent to get a wealth of
affective behavior of approach avoidance, but also social cognition. We can kind of
simulate social anxiety. We obtain joint attention behavior as a result of mutual perspective taking
and there are a lot of things we could account that we can use in this model and in this framework
to account for emotion. There is a lot of work ahead, but we believe that there is and we have
good reason to believe there is a deep link between space and emotion that's actually called
aesthetics that consciousness is a form of aesthetics where space and emotion are untangled
and that we can fairly well account for many phenomena that relate to emotion and behavior
through this model, but that's sorry for the long talk.
That's great. Shall I give my final answer? It's very much along the same lines that
emotion and space are deeply linked. In the wave model, I mean the model of space contains all
of space, the external space and the internal space of the body and an important part of emotions is
feelings in the body and they are part of your conscious awareness, part of the
wave model or projection model just like the others. Basically, the PW theory and I think the
PCM says all consciousness is spatial. We have qualia, but they exist in space. You hear words,
you experience colors, you experience all of those and you experience feelings,
all of them in space. If you look at all the components of emotion, human emotion for instance,
the words we say to ourselves and the feelings we have in our bodies, they are all represented in
that conscious space. Human emotion is a complex story which perhaps we don't want to go into,
but basically it comes down to the way we experience it is in that model of space.
And if I may, I would have that if you take the standpoint of pure phenomenology and you ask yourself
when I experience an emotion, for instance deep anxiety or fear, something very intense that is
very salient, you can ask yourself how much of that phenomenology of that experience is actually
quote-unquote reducible to some spatial experience. For instance, the experience of the body with the
heart that starts pounding in your chest and you feel it stronger, your lungs that change,
you breathe faster for instance and you can feel that movement in your body and all of that is
spatial. What you feel in your gut or your intestine gets kind of stretched or whatever,
we have metaphors, but actually a lot of the details of the phenomenology of emotion or feelings,
let's say, I believe is actually spatial, but it's overlooked. People don't think about it.
But in particular, about body awareness, there is a lot of spatial stuff going on here.
Yeah, I agree. Mindful meditation, talk a lot about space and talk a lot about the body.
I think they put emotion in the right place.
Carl or Ken, want to add anything or I can look for another question in the live chat.
Well, I have one question. So I mean, your current hypothesis is that this wave is
realized in the thalamus. Is that right? That's right. Yeah. Okay. So that's sort of
would, you know, there's this kind of debate about whether or not consciousness is cortical
or subcortical. So this would definitely be on the subcortical side. I think there's a lot of
sense in the global workspace theory and they were talking originally about a workspace involving
the thalamus and the cortex. I think it's the consciousness really comes from the thalamus
integrating all that spatial information. So it is down. So the follow up, but yeah, that's fine
with me, frankly. But the follow up question is, well, it's not exactly a follow up to that. It's
more a general question about your way of thinking about it. How, I mean, I know maybe you can't
really answer this until we have a more specific hypothesis about exactly what kind of wave it is,
but could you say something generally about how the wave integrates with or what's the right way
to put it, use it, recruits and, you know, the kind of computational apparatus of the brain
so that, you know, you end up, you decide to, oh, I'm going to reach out, you know,
yay far and grab this bottle. How does the, how does, you know, computationally speaking,
how does the wave integrate? Yeah, I think that's a very good question and could have a very long
answer. But basically, the wave integrates information from all the sense data. So from
your hands, from your ears, from your eyes, all that information goes through the cortex and cortex
decides where it's coming from and broadcast signals back to the thalamus and the thalamus wave
integrates all those signals together to produce the Bayesian best model of what's happening at
this moment based on touch, proprioception, hearing, sound, hearing, vision and so on. So the
computation, it's an integration of many sorts of information, possibly in a cycle between the
thalamus and the cortex. Okay, but if you need to, you know, for example, program and action,
so you've, that's kind of the, you got your sensory, the integration of all your sensory
information, now you need to program and action. How do, and maybe this is just my ignorance,
how do waves, how can waves be used in a way to generate programming of an action and then give
it back to your neurons? I mean, I've only got beginnings of answers to that. But basically,
wave is very good for representing 3D geometry and for calculating displacements. I know where
my hand is, I know where my coffee cup is, so the wave helps me calculate the displacement,
which way I have to move my hand to pick up the coffee cup. So it's that kind of spatial
calculation that the wave is always helping us do, just to move our limbs.
I have a follow-up question on that, if I may. Ken, do you mind?
Yeah, no, go ahead, go ahead.
You invoked earlier Fourier transform and inverse Fourier transform, so at least 3D Fourier transform
and inverse Fourier transform, in order to do the encoding and decoding to, you know,
go move from the wave to the neural substrates back and forth. Of course, as you know,
there is a limit in resolution. When you do a Fourier transform, you have the uncertainty
principle that rules the initial resolution that we can have. Of course, it depends on the
number of samples. I mean, there are a lot of arithmetics behind it. It can be more and more
precise as you have more and more bits of encoding, if you wish. So you said that classical
neural theories like build upon substrates that lack enough precision in spatial resolution,
for instance, to account for our experience. Would you think that in the context of a wave theory,
the type of uncertainty principle that are attached to it, could cause a problem of resolution too,
or that it's the granularity? There is a problem, yeah. There is a problem of resolution.
I alluded to it in the slides. That is that if you've got a minimum wavelength lambda
and a diameter of the sphere D, the maximum precision is lambda over D, and that can't
be infinite precision. So that's the uncertainty principle. But the idea of the Fourier transform
is not that something in the brain does a Fourier transform. It is the fundamental bridging law for
consciousness does the Fourier transform. It says that consciousness is a Fourier transform of the
wave, full stop. Fourier transform is there in fundamental laws of nature, like quantum mechanics,
for instance. So it's saying this is a fundamental law of nature, just like quantum mechanics says
momentum is a Fourier transform position. So the bridging law for consciousness says
the form of consciousness is a Fourier transform of the wave.
I'll make a short comment, or Carl, do you want to?
After you. Okay. So thank you for the presentation, and it's really interesting on many levels.
First, you and the paper goes into more detail on this. You lay out what your priors are,
and kind of the dependency structure to actually reach at least an estimate of probabilities,
which is it's really interesting. It gives a lot of opportunities for people to dig in
and say, yeah, I think that's 10% likely or no, it's a zero. This is not possible and kind of
close off a branch of inquiry. And also this discussion here about the algorithmic and the
substrate realization interaction with the substrate, and even this poly computation idea of
the observer's model of what's happening in a process, and kind of like the dark matter there,
like the observer might suggest that there's a cryptographic process, though they couldn't
decode it. And then that would have an entropy distribution that wouldn't be distinguishable
in the absence of the decryption from a noise, but it would be like still a hypothesis kept alive.
And you could say, I think it's a 1% chance of this being the case. One thought is how
high precision really is the spatial generative model in that there could be visual upscaling?
We know there's attention play to make the periphery look sharp and have color vision.
And so it's possible that especially for like distant objects, small objects that they could be
bundled and just seen as a assembly, as a larger object, if they're touching like the car body
and the wheel, and then the same way that in the periphery, color and visual attention seem to give
this extreme like, wow, that's like exactly this angle. If you were to go over there with a protractor,
but that could be as we're sort of seeing with diffusion and generative AI models,
that could be quite a low resolution structural inference followed by a just compatible visual
realization. And then just last comment, really interesting to explore, how does evolution
and intergenerational change shape the substrate that the sense data wash over so that non-stationary
stable states, whether they're rate encoding of neuron, whether glial, electro,
and all these other even potentially more exotic options, how are those stabilized?
Wow. I mean, those are real questions to investigate, particularly the precision of our
conscious experience and how much is quotes and illusion. But I personally think that if you look
at something which is a straight line, you experience it as a straight line with some kind
of precision that's of the order of 1%, a deviation of 1% from a straight line would show. And so
that's a lower bound on the precision of your model. But again, there can be lots of discussion
about this. Yeah, interesting. Karl, any thoughts?
Well, just a few sort of practical and specific questions. So the nature of this wave, if I wanted
to model it, I mean, are we talking about a standing wave? Are we talking about a soliton?
Are we talking about spherical harmonics on the surface of the thalamus? Are we talking about
what kind of basis might I use for this kind of wave, even before asking questions about what
the wave amplitude actually means? So what's the functional mathematical form of this way?
Very good questions, whether it's a standing wave or a moving wave. I don't know. The nice
thing about a Bose-Einstein condensate is that it acts like a long-lived quantum mechanical
wave function. In other words, it has phase which can be detected, and it preserves phase for long
times. And the wave might have to preserve phase in order to represent positions. If you have a
standing wave like cos theta in some direction in this sphere, then there's an ambiguity. It
represents plus a direction and the minus direction and what happens to the minus direction. So
I would rather have phase in the wave like a Bose-Einstein condensate, but they're very
deep questions and I don't do the answers. I mean, we could start modelling and see what happens.
Just propose some answers. Basically, you just need a spherical volume that holds a wave
excitation with a certain maximum wave vector, and we could try out standing waves, moving waves,
and so on. What would differentiate a condensate from a formulation in terms of a time-dependent
floating wave equation? Well, I think your time-dependent floating wave, as everybody knows,
the problem with quantum in the brain is that decoherence smashes it in 10 to the minus 20 seconds,
but that doesn't happen to a Bose-Einstein condensate. A Bose-Einstein condensate is a long-lived quantum
state, and so that's an ordinary floating equation. Decoherence is going to smash you in no time at
all unless you have some incredibly clever insulation like in a quantum computer.
Right. I mean, lifting from the microscopic to the macroscopic, I mean, that would suggest
that you need very, very low temperatures thermodynamically speaking. No one has observed
a BC at room temperature yet, but we've got close, and the idea is that nature might be cleverer than
we are. One angle, perhaps from the quantum FEP from Carl and Chris Fields and others is,
and what I heard in the basis set question, Carl, was this brain region that hosts the
functionality or the core aspect of the functionality, like one option is it is like the wave is
represented inside of that sphere. Like just, there's probably multiple ways even that could
happen, but it's like a little reconstruction wave, but symbolized. Another option would be,
like a holograph, the representation space is encoded on the interface of that region with
other regions, and so that kind of surface is maintained and stabilized and has information
flowing through it. And then there wouldn't necessarily be something in the middle, but it'd
be more like a ripple on a surface, which was the basis set question. Daniel, that is very
interesting because in the thalamus, there is the thalamic reticular nucleus, TRN, which is a thin
skin around the surface of the thalamus. And you could just say that is holding the surface wave.
And the wave is projected inside from the surface.
It would be useful to engage Chris Fields here. There are two very distinct uses of the word
holographic here. You could be referring to the holographic principle, whereby all the information
on the bulk, on the inside, say, of the thalamus was on the surface, on the reticular nucleus
of the thalamus, for example, or just on the surface in one sense. And that is what the rest
of the brain sees and possibly consciousness sees. But that's a very different use of the notion of
a holographic projection using constructive and destructive interference to encode things.
So Daniel, you're absolutely right. My question was really searching to distinguish,
are we talking about a wave function in the thalamus? Are we talking about
application of the holographic principle to the classical information on the surface
of some bulk that was the thalamus? And you could then argue, if you wanted to, that the bulk,
which can never be observed from the outside, unless you are the thalamus, you never know what's
happening on the inside. You could only observe what's on the surface. That would be a different
notion of a wave theory that would certainly be consistent with quantum information theory
and also consistent with Chris Fields in a screen hypothesis that could be
spatialized and endowed with, in virtue of the fact that on the holographic screen itself,
on the surface, there can only be classical information and that information can now be
cast in terms of classical Bayesian inference. But it also relates to, I repeat to Chris Fields,
in a screen hypothesis, which is, if you like, taking quantum information,
theoretic principles and trying to apply them to consciousness, that eludes the problem of
applying quantum mechanics that is only relevant at the very small scale, for very precise or
low temperature systems. If you want to apply that kind of maths to macroscopic phenomena,
then you have to apply it in a scale invariant context and I think quantum information theory
would certainly do that. So, Daniel, yes, I was exactly trying to probe.
Is PW red? The Bose-Einstein condensate variant or alternative version of the projective wave
is that committed to quantum mechanics or is it really an expression of condensate-like dynamics
in the context of quantum information theory? And if it is, does it live on a holographic screen
or does it live in the bulk? And if it lives in the bulk, what are these wave functions over?
So, these are the practical questions I was trying to get out.
Very interesting questions and it's all to play for. I have an open mind about them, but
my feeling is that the BEC is a way of getting past this decoherence argument from
Tickmark others that neurons have to be classical. And the BEC, it does work very well as a memory.
That's the practical point of it. Working memory, I think, is what you need for space.
Awesome. Perhaps each can give a last round of thought. Where do they feel this takes them
or what are they looking forward to and can then David and then Carl and then Robert?
Yeah, I don't have anything new to add. I find this really interesting and I remember
reading Karen Smith's book kind of arguing that Bose-Einstein condensates might be
important for understanding consciousness and thinking that among the quantum mechanical
hypotheses, I like that one the best. I said earlier, I just sort of have this kind of bias,
but I'm totally willing to be talked out of it. I don't want to go into the details, but
I think Karen Smith's concern was about the unity of consciousness primarily and also kind of made
the case that as you were suggesting that maybe as you put it, nature is cleverer than we are
and there's some way to realize that Bose-Einstein condenses it in the brain without the decoherence
issue. But anyway, just to say this is all very, very fascinating to me and I am happy to continue
the discussion next week, right? Isn't it next week? Thank you, Ken. And from my part, yes,
I'm also looking forward to continuations of the discussion. My direction of questioning
will be something on the lines that I think both Karen and David alluded to which is the
the link between spatial waves in the brain and the projective geometry that they speak to
and the information geometry that underwrites belief updating and the Bayesian mechanics that
inherit from the free energy principle, being it classical mechanics, the classical information
processing or looking at using quantum information theory to read belief updating.
I'm not sure I'm going to get any answers, but that's what I'm interested in hearing more about
and the process. If you haven't talked about mortal computation yet, so we need to talk about
mortal computation. Oh, yes. David, any last thoughts? Well, the thought of a
of a man who is 15 now and feels that the more he learns, the less he knows. So it was predicted
in all the books I had read in my years. And so I'm whole opened to that complex universe. I certainly
believe that nature is clever than I am for sure. And I find that fascinating. I like the rationale.
It's not like, you know, there is a lot of stuff about quantum mechanics and the brain
and consciousness that to me has always sounded wishy-washy, if not completely wacko.
But I came back a bit from that. I had a lot of like Ken priors, negative priors about it.
I remember once in Tucson, Arizona, at the famous conference about the science of consciousness,
there were this bunch of guys who called themselves, they were German, the quantum
consciousness Academy, and they were all dressed in black and they are all, you know, headset and
microphone like that. And they were like speaking nonsense as like a cult. But I found that very
fascinated because I used to like very fascinating. So I used to like this conference back in the day
when it was very psychedelic. But that was kind of, you know, and I come back to that because
my ignorance, I'm becoming aware more and more of my own ignorance. I say, well, why not? And
definitely I think that maybe Carl can try to do that. If we could get Chris Field in the next
core role, he would certainly be among us, the most competent. I tried to get Grgoire Sergent
to the core, but he was not available. He's a very bright mathematician and he master quantum
mechanics like, like if it was, you know, I don't know, it's nothing for him. Or Daniel Benka would
be the best also is Grgoire. But I'm afraid I won't be able to have them here. But I think it
would be very useful to have some people like that who definitely know more than me about those
things. And Chris might be interested to join. I don't know, Carl. But looking forward to the next
to the next discussion, one correction, they were Swiss, David, they weren't, they weren't, they
weren't, they were Swiss, they were Swiss black, I think. Yes, they kind of look like people from
the matrix. They were Swiss. They were not German. They were Swiss. And they had, they had a leader
they were always in contact with. Super hot.
Wow. Okay. Yeah, please, Robert, and, and, and we'll contact Chris.
That's been really fascinating. I think the virtue of this theory is that it is falsifiable.
In other words, if there's no way in the brain, forget it, this theory is wrong. And that's exactly
the question we're going to be looking at next week. I look forward to having your contributions.
Awesome. Thank you all. See you at 16 UTC on July 29th. Okay. Thank you. Thank you. Bye.