Hello and welcome. It is September 12, 2023. We're here in the Active Inference for the
Social Sciences course at the Active Inference Institute and having a discussion section
on semiotics and semantics here with Lorena Saganzula. We're going to be having a fun discussion,
I hope. If you're watching live, please feel free to write any questions in the live chat.
If you thought about joining and you weren't sure, it's not too late. Otherwise, we're going to
pick up on some key points from the lecture and on the topic and see where we go. So, Lorena,
welcome back and however you want to begin, let's go from there.
Okay. Hello. Thank you, Daniel. So, let's try to recap a little bit where we left off during the
lecture just to remind us where we were. My point, what I was trying to articulate was the idea of
what does it mean to talk about formal semantics in a way that is not really
loaded because it's an interesting thought to have a semantics that is actually only formal.
In principle, it would be relative to meaning. In the notion that
active inference is trying to cash it out. It's more like an idea or a way of modeling how
how we deal with meaningful situations. And she understands that in a more interesting,
more embodied and more concrete way, I was suggesting that we could use bio-semiotics as
as a model and as a theory for leaving creatures like language users to navigate the realm of symbols.
And gave one example which came from James Koch, which is the European forest
trade that comes with a practice. Understanding this scientific understanding of forests as a
practice that allows us to refer to meaningful things in the environment in terms of what is
valuable, what's interesting and what is not. And interestingly, what is more important also
from what becomes valuable, it is what is cropped out from the meaningful perspective. So things
nature, parts of nature becomes left out or understood as something that is not desirable.
And you just understand what you don't want in your articulating principle as weeds or
something that you should get rid of in respect to what is more desirable in terms of crops and
how you understand nature in a more commoditized way.
And I find like this example from Scott kind of very, very elucidating.
In the book he creates this, in the book he's talking about states, how we articulate
life around one specific notion of state. But in this specific example he has
the idea of one official observer and this official observer establishes a principle of
meaning in a way you have to have a handle of nature and that also articulates how
villages and how practices around agriculture and how people relate to each other within these
practices gets organized. Specifically for one interesting point that he makes that is to appreciate
to appreciate the constriction of that is like a vision that notices not
what within the meaningful crops but which is left outside the field of vision.
And I bring that specifically to understand how
the free-knit principle can or could be connected to a generalized synchronization
over time in relation to those symbols and those practices in terms of niche construction and
how those, how this niche construction brings along with the symbolic
use of our language, our predictive value.
Thank you. Bryn, do you want to bring up any thoughts on that or any other
pieces or I'm happy to add a comment.
Okay, guess not. A lot to say there. There was a little bit of a double play with what is cropped.
On one hand what is cropped is the industrial crop that is being prepared and then the other
side of that coin is what is cropped out and what we crop in is the part that we're paying
attention to and we can't pay attention to everything so it's like two sides of the same coin
what we pay attention to what we include in attention in our cognitive awareness
leaves the shadow which is what we exclude and that could be like the weeds or the other ecosystem
services so by highlighting the meaning or one dimension of meaning or one stance on meaning
that only it's like a seesaw that becomes salient to the extent that something else
must be deprioritized so that's how we accentuate these distributions of meaning
and what do we get from active inference and and free energy principle beyond for example
what's provided and seeing like a state. I think there's a lot we could say on that but
one piece is we get a process theory a real procedural approach to how different systems
come to do sense making and cognition and action so just describing the lay of the land
or the history of forestry in Europe or any other state of affairs in the world
merely describing it may not even help us determine what's going to happen
a short time later let alone a long time later or what might happen in a very different ecology
whereas if we understand the processes of sense making and decision making that different kinds
of cognitive agents do certainly humans also those states as cognitive entities which is
what seeing like a state or thinking like a state entails we get a process-based view
on what otherwise might be merely descriptive and along with that process-based view we gain
an increased ability to make unique explanations predictions accounts and so on.
Yeah we can we can also understand it in a different perspective in terms of
realizing what becomes sensitized and what becomes desensitized
along the process so you can you can possibly model that using this kind of tools and understanding
how that happens over time right I don't know how how much in terms of prediction
of things that we're not foreseeing in these descriptions we can we can achieve in fact
you can achieve some some level for sure but like that system should be this side how
how that delivers a very all-encompassing prediction in this kind in these cases they
don't believe it can right I don't think that's the purpose as well but we can at least have
which is might not be as positive as we want but I think we can understand how
we can gain some understanding in this process of being more sensitive or less sensitive to specific
primes and how this organizational principles how powerful they become over time
yeah I'll read some comments in the chat and then Lorena or Brent feel free to just give
any thoughts just upcycle club wrote hello biomimicry can enhance biosemiotics by showing
us how nature solves problems and creates beauty through signs and codes and by encouraging us
to apply these principles to our own creations yeah the idea of coding is an interesting idea
but to talk about codes I don't think we can that's my take right I don't understand
like you have we haven't coded any type of principles within our cognitive ability but
biologically speaking however you can understand these encodings in terms of becoming more or less
sensitive over time to environmental cues as the example in terms of I use the example of
forestry right so in that specific case this what becomes more what you become more sensitive and
the more you organize your life or the social life is organized around specific principles
then you can make sense of these relational stories instead of just leveraging one full
difficult to explain notion of encoding in terms of social cognition because it will be hard to
explain how the brain will be encoding these specific symbols but they can be cashed out
in the environment relationally in terms of those organizational principles
and then you have this idea of biomimicry like this reiterations and how that comes along with
to explain what this mimic or this mean will be then
of it's not so so straightforward they think
well certainly decompiling the source code of nature is somewhere between challenging and
misguided or impossible but that notion of a code script for biology has animated discussions of
life going back to for example Schrodinger's what is life he basically says there's two
aspects of living systems there's their organizational capacity their negentropic capacity
and then there's their code script their aperiodic crystalline informational repository
and then another place that coding comes up a little bit less in the source code space is
predictive coding and that's in a way highly compatible with active inference and gives a
deflationary account on how the semiotics are encoded rather than saying well this is what this
variable in the source code means or this is what this codes for or here's a code switch
predictive coding is like saying we're not even going to touch the semantics of what the sign is
itself we're just going to hypothesize that the way that information about the sign is transferred
is through this maximum information signaling approach called predictive coding because predictive
coding arose out of video compression algorithms and only at the end of the 90s was found to be
increasingly relevant for neural circuitry and so on so it's another example of where like a process
based approach ends up deflating or reframing the otherwise semantically loaded question
it's like switching out the question of like where we're going to be with how we're going to get there
and instead of only focusing on the meaning of the signs first off as if the meaning of the
signs could be discussed outside of their implementation and then even if we could figure
out what the signs were we would then just turn around and want to know how they were transmitted
and so predictive coding or predictive processing in a way short circuits that or
inverse it by first looking to explain how information is transmitted that could support
semiotics and then in the context of biological systems we naturally have biosemiotics
yeah i would ask the question when you talk about information being transmitted right what that
actually means and i think that's a very very big topic and a very large discussion in terms of
uh information information theory when specifically applying that into biological systems i think
there are some interesting people working on information that makes the case that Shannon has
a point and he's really interested not in the semantics or in the meaning or anything else it's
kind of interested in the problem of transmission and when you talk about transmission
it's worth to ask what is being transmitted exactly in the terms of of signals even if you're
capturing specific patterns and you think that the pattern is this thing that will be transmitted
in that sense but that would be a worth
a worth asking question to understand like the this notion of what is actually being
transmitted in that sense like the information probably this information theory is focusing
on this notion of the problem of transmission and then all the the concepts that come along to
explain that in terms of uncertainty or noise and everything that uh impacts this transmission
of processes and if you're saying like we're transmitting information in these things that
is breaking this semantic code apart yes it is because like the problem is not focused on that
it's that focusing on the specific correlations that we have that we call it we're mentioning
as information and how these correlations are an issue from from the cat go from what is being
picked up in one side being correlated to what comes into the other side right how that how do
you lose or gain more information in that but the deeper question here is
how can you say that you are actually gaining or losing that information because you are defining
this correlation that could be transmitted or not from the cat go if you don't have that
you don't have anything being actually actually communicated
so with that in mind you can explain these concepts in terms of function and then there's
a bunch of theories that navigate this sense of uh signaling that is specifically only functional
and then predictive coding tries to
try tries to push that a little further maybe but then you have to explain in
in a deep sense how this information is being actually transmitted and processed and I don't
think that is really really as obvious and as clear as we think it is
specifically when we're talking about this biological
way of nature navigating this process this this signaling
we have to talk about because the correlation if it's defined are being issued like from the
beginning you can only have this kind of transmission for someone specific that can
be able to understand that in the other side right
well certainly whether we're talking about a chemical pheromone that requires some type
of receptor or something more ephemeral like language that requires more of a semantic reference
frame there's no receiving the message without the sender it's like they're kind of the two
sides of the phone call um I'll ask a question from the chat love evolve how about cultural
encoding and principles in contrast to organizational so how do we think about
cultural meaning and is and is that similar or different than organizational
yeah that's that's a good point right I think if you take very seriously the example from
the forestry is a practice then I think it has to be organizational in that sense the meaning
navigates this organizational practice this organizational story that
that impacts not only communication between agents but also how
how the environment will be interpreted so and in this sense it will be transmitted
and repeated over time because it has a history you cannot ignore like the history of this
practices being pushed further and replicated through generations right so
the way like the villages will be
organized in terms of that specific practice for instance can be understood in a meaningful
and cultural way that organizes life in virtue of
some specific principles that sensitizes our agents towards specific directions
and I think
I don't I don't forget my point for instance you can talk about
if you think about archaeological findings and how archaeological
so descriptions of specific villages and how they navigate this mapping out this
this archaeological sites they usually know exactly if you have some kind of history already
from this this communities how this how that city will be likely to be organized
first off like where is the water and if the water is in certain directions probably
there will be certain kinds of relationships with housing and communal housings and where
are they going to place their dead in relation to this kind of specific organization principle
the water is here so plantations will be not so far away from that and this city organizes
like the village organized a little bit in this sense and that builds up cultural practices
at least archaeologically can be explained as such
I thought of something similar organization being the logistical or the operational structural
aspects so those would be the roads that connect the forestry outposts or the circulatory system
that connects the different organs of organization and then the culture is a cause and a consequence
of organization organization is the enabling conditions for culture to arise okay so given
this road network what cultures arise how similar or different are they convergently what are their
practices or their narratives that are shared amongst these different outposts
or in the bodily example okay given the organization of the organs literally the organizing
process or principle then what biosemiotics can arise with glucose and insulin and glucagon
and what culturally can arise maybe even in terms of the generative model of encultured
agents as a function of organization and then what are those encultured agents do
to the extent that they can modify organization and so these kinds of
um unrolling cause and consequence relationships can be hard to disentangle
because there's not like a clean single starting point that can be separated out or because it
unfolds historically it's not exactly a reaction in a test tube
so how does active inference give us an entry point into thinking about this
yeah that's one interesting thing about active inference that you
you don't really need one uh you don't really need an origin point right you can
start start modeling you start understanding that at any any given point and build up from
from that story and see how it unfolds over time i think that's the most beautiful idea that you
you define your parameters and then you see from that parameter that can be arbitrarily defined and
you can navigate how things change within those parameters in the generative model right when
you when you have your like dynamical systems for instance you have your state space they have
some specific range of defining parameters that set the limits of the possible states that you're
going to navigate and if you use this notion that this two densities brings about in terms of
Bayesian modeling you can use these these kinds of tools to understand how from that specific
parameters update why what we narrate in active inference as if belief updating can change over
time in these terms that's a very nice point it reminds me of Bruno Latour's actor network theory
or ants which kind of advocates a similar approach to what you describe which is like enter anywhere
open-mindedly because in an iterated modeling or iterated analysis setting the first proposal
or the first trace detected we know that's not the whole picture there may not be a whole or only
picture so we need to enter and iterate and then with active inference specifically because of the
compositionality that we get within a layer collective behavior and then also the kind of
nesting smaller things inside of bigger things we can always build something and then we can go oh
wow it's like there's a lot of top-down influence maybe there's a higher order factor or slower
factor or a contextual factor we should consider or oh we were abstracting across these smaller
things inside but for a later day or if relevance we can dive in and so then it allows a light hold
or a grasp on the proposed generative model obviously it's map not territory but even
beyond that we always know that we can expand laterally and across scales starting from anywhere
in an iterated modeling process without our first or even 11th model being proposed as like
the accounts of some complex cultural phenomena which we're always going to only ever have our
own perspectives on yeah I think you don't really find that you being so oh all in copas
saying like you have one model that will model them all you can you you can navigate those models
in these more more instrumental terms it raises different questions when you put things like that
in terms of the ontology of models and models and theories and sciences but you they can be also
described as tools for describe tools for yeah tools for for grasping and describing
phenomena in a more non-committal way
how much that how much that smuggles in philosophical or more ontological problems
it's still I think under like debate but it is still
it's still uh it is still a tool to bring insights to think about specific cultural
collective uh phenomena which is not it's it's complicated to because I think what I'm getting
at I'm kind of like going back and forth but when you talk about social sciences and modeling
usually you have like ways of modeling agents or ways of modeling collectives and active inference
is trying to to come up with a a modeling in which you can understand agency and collectives
within the same modeling uh schema and I think the specific specifically for these
cases if you're interested in understanding uh types of cultural phenomena among language users
in uh in specific contexts you can at least partially understand or have or gain some insight
in this agent-collective relationship that that is a little bit more interesting than
we have found so far in the social sciences because you can have like or specific understandings of
means but then how the agent where is the agency in that you you lose a little bit of agency
well when you're trying to understand uh only agents then you don't know how that
kind of scales up because active inference tries and offers this scale free uh modeling tools
that facilitates this this um conversion into agents agents and uh collectives
I would be interested in asking you actually how how do you navigate that when you talk about
social phenomena in ants or termites or
because then yeah you have very specific coding demarcations I guess for for this uh
social environments
yeah it's a great question it's also whether it's a uh open wounds or a dirty closet that's just
shut there's actually a lot of ambiguity and unresolved tension around well is the ant colony
social are they social insects that reifies the nest mate as the individual and then what
they're doing is like when we hang out and talk so reifying the nest mate as individual makes
the colony social but if the colony is individual then what nest mates are doing with each other
is not social anymore than we would describe the liver and the kidney as having like a social
single cellular interaction but we know that would be missing the point and so there definitely is
attention with some of these evolutionary lineages like ants being monophiletically
obligate you social all and only ants are you social they all live in the colonies there's no
free living nest mate whereas other parts of the evolutionary tree there are
life histories that do look a little bit more like social collaboration that can then
dissolve and so knowing what level of lock in makes something social
when are we socializing and what level of lock in goes beyond social and it kind of like makes
when the blanket is so strong around the social that like for multi-cellularity that it it's kind
of losing the social feature again because if we just use social to mean the connective tissue
or the kind of lubricant or the spaces between everything then it means nothing so a real attention
is what space does the social account for and is this going to be a concept with a lot of creep
looking well it's a social relationship between the roots of the tree and the fungus and it's a
social relationship amongst the molecules in the test tube is that too broad of a social conception
are there downsides or are there trade-offs associated with a broader social concept
social concept do we dilute what the social means and then on the other side
might we exclude phenomena that could importantly be considered social
well that's not social they're just talking on a train it's like well that's the other side
if we were to have carving out encounters that we do want to include as social and
and is there a true social does active inference help us sidestep or at least negotiate this territory
because we could develop a generative model or an ecosystem of shared intelligence with
one person and two internet of things devices and a bird and a metronome and just say we made
what we made and then leave it as a second-order interpretation whether that is a social setting
I mean I think you you are pointing at like how I think granularity of those scales right
if you have a model that I want you want to everything that you already have it's probably
not interesting and not informative because you cannot like define those limits of what you're
trying to understand and in the other hand when you do that when you define those limits if you're
too narrow or you're gonna leave out you're gonna idealize also in a way right and leave out many
other parts of the system that you're interested in but if you don't do that if you don't
if you don't make this if you don't make this decision when modeling you think then how
how you can have any access to the phenomena right and and to connect this to the forestry
so in the forestry example the disirata was lumber now that may have been a very narrowly scoped
desire but it's it's a relevant thing to to want this resource and then industrialization
science as a process professionalization those allow the description and and the handling and
ultimately the kind of top-down legibility and control thinking like a forestry company now
with respect to the social sciences by analogy to forestry science so now we're entering an
era of increased legibility and control of social systems and human natural capital and
attention as a resource trust as a resource in a way is being cropped analogous to produce the
content of lumber but now there are social content so as the social goes from being just
only simply the water we swim in not something that's even compared counterfactually to alternative
cultural possibilities per se but falls under the scope of the professional management like
forestry then that's when this discussion of well what's the lumber and what is the weeds that are
being pruned and what ecosystem services when we pay attention to certain parts of human social
culture and when we seek to make more of this kind of lumber what else does that come along with
and what decisions come into play and that comes along when you see
you
or instagram i don't know twitter after what happened to twitter but
but yeah the in terms of attention pruning you do have that very effectively already happening
already you can see how that happens if efficiently in the world in elections for instance it can be
very very easily manipulated and we saw what happened in elections for instance in brazil or in
the u.s and well all over you navigate a system of attention organization that
selects in only what he thinks that you're interested in
in the effects of that in terms of decision making and in terms of trust in terms of
diversity of discourse we have seen that it can be devastating
so the and the question would be like how can you make this a little bit how can you use active
inference and these tools that we have to make this kind of technology a little bit more inclusive
without being super also disruptive is it even like
a possibility i really don't know i think it's an ethical problem that we have when we talk about
social systems and these principles of attention exclusion leaving things out
lot to say on that um with modeling and interpolating and models whether it's large
language model type or linear regression type it is able to interpolate to put data points within
an enclosure of what has already been described and Bayesian statistics and other types of
prediction algorithms are not immune to that either if we have some prior distribution belief
um we believe it's possible for it to be between 20 and 30 degrees outside
then when we get data inside of our bounds we can converge and that actually
tightens our beliefs not always a bad thing of course and then outside of the scope of the
possible those data are just seen as noise and they may not even be integrated so then that
can lead to a reinforcing process not necessarily an adaptive one either where information that's
confirmatory is used to ratchet and increase precision and then information that is not
confirmatory is discarded as not useful
it doesn't yeah in this case is yeah it doesn't even enter the uh the landscape
of attention of the user in
what i what i'm what i was thinking in relation to this no this idea of
uh a forestry is because we have now organizational principles that are faster and
more populated with uh information and attention grabbing kinds of prompts
we transformed the same
we just from the same principle into
a harder to grasp process it's it's hard it becomes more complex it becomes harder to
describe this the process of understanding that in terms of forestry is kind of way more grounded
when you apply that socially to this kind of environment that we're talking like internet or
is highly uh volatile
and virtual in principle in environment it becomes much harder to assess what is being
pruned out or not you just don't know it makes it more clear that
there is a process of pruning you need to have no control of what is being taken out
you have no idea what's being like left away from your perspective of attention
so to this topic of intended or unintended semantic pruning i think um this has helped me
identify attention if we want to talk about the semantics or semiotics biosemionics whatever we
want to call it of the letter e in relationship to letter a we're looking for an account that might
convey letterness but we're generalized above enus or anus so in some ways we've erased or
abstracted generalized away from the particulars of the sign's meaning by taking a semiotic
perspective and so it's like we got into the game to have a semantic account of biological
phenomena or of any phenomena for biological entity yet this process in a sense distances us
from the particulars that actually do grant it that meaning in the actuality like if we
walk into a sacred space and it's like oh well that is just doing that over there and this
architecture is doing this and because of the layout people must use the room this way
that's removed from the actual meaning which is the cause and consequence with the organization and
culture that we discussed but that prima facia account doesn't generalize get any generalization
that we make so that we can talk about multiple places or multiple letters on a common
accounting framework is going to remove those particularities
so it's a very challenging catch 22 whether we want to really
account for the n equals one and maybe even live and act and play and work in the n equals one
versus develop something that might be satisfying and cut and dry but it's always going to be on
the sidelines with respect to what it actually means but what do you mean like is i don't understand
what you what you're getting at like is it you mean like it's generalized or not generalized
i didn't get that like when we have a general when we generalize when we
ask what words mean what what words mean beyond any given word we've lost touch with
what any given word means but words are what they actually mean in a situation
so it's just in this scientific approach to meaning semiotics and semantics
we have these two tensions or a tension to reconcile between actually giving an account
of the meaningfulness of the specific thing
versus taking a more scientific approach which would be
gathering a group of similar things and finding their shared attributes
which out of necessity must abstract must crop out
features that are are empirically or anecdotally taken to not matter like we abstract whether it
was a monday or tuesday that we did the experiments we just combine all of our replicates together
when we do the scientific analysis
you mean you mean if you generalize the practice you lose
what you're being if you generalize it too much you lose everything that's meaningful to it in
terms of like for you formalize it and then you have no yeah you have an empty semantics you
have a semantics with no meaning that can only be meaningful in terms of how you apply that in
terms of specific practices yeah it's like i i have a framework for you know the formal meaning
of letters within words within sentences within paragraphs and then it's like well but now what's
your next n equals one word that you're actually going to bring it's not just about building some
abstract scaffold yeah for bigger and bigger boulders of meaning
at some point through our embodied thought and action
in our experience it is going to come down into the particulars
and it doesn't immediately seem clear that simply generalizing further
brings us there
yeah yeah particularly i don't really believe you can have that kind of generalization i think
we attempt to build whatever what i see that's the interesting aspect of the formal semantics
you try to build this more general
understanding that's just formalizes to model but for that to be meaningful it has to be embedded
in a way of practicing it like in a forestry practice you have to be embedded in a cultural
environment in which that can be actually uh observed in terms of what happens when
a generative model is being updated or not
is that what you mean because otherwise i don't really understand how it becomes too
yeah it becomes too formal it becomes too abstract in terms of some i would not understand
what that is
i'll i'll think of a little more um brand or tj do you want to add any thoughts or questions
yeah sorry i i think like i don't have a lot of context i've been like following some of the
discussion but not attended a lot of these calls i'm like it's all yeah yeah um yeah i didn't know
i think um yeah i'm in general just sort of interested in trying to understand the relationship
between um yeah like sorts of like constructionist epistemologies and um yeah like generative models
and active inference style stuff and um how active inference style like yeah what are the
philosophical commitments that active inference involves with respect to knowledge and epistemology
and there's a sense in which like rational choice models often assume a certain sort of like
objectivity to beliefs and then desires are where most of the degrees of freedom lie or something
um whereas there's a lot of like issue like there's a lot of things that come up once you
start talking about reflexivities where concepts themselves become self-fulfilling prophecies
what you believe about what your beliefs about society and shaping the society itself so there's
the sense in which there's a score dependence between the object of knowledge and knowledge about
that object itself and i think yeah like i'm sort of interested in like how the active
entrance ways of thinking about this offers what perspectives on those questions and stuff like
that um yeah thank you great questions yeah so when you talk about the uh object of knowledge
and knowledge itself and active inference uh
i think you you you can think of in terms of this
well there's a few ways to think about that i guess
uh the knowledge itself it has to come epistemically from where your agent
is actually embedded and situated in specifically an active inference it's embodied
it kind of needs to have a model the model is modeling a body is modeling a body that is in
the world and it's all the time uh situated is never disconnected to its environment and it's
history and how the history of that environment right yeah uh but if you think if you push that
to the object of that knowledge uh i don't know how how different
that will
how different how can you differ differentiate that so sharply when you talk about active inference
because
if you think of uh in terms of a generative model then what will be updated comes is updated from
a prior that is always directed in this body in this situated realm so they sort of conflated
as i see maybe a maybe a mistaken but they sort of correlate in how you're gonna update your
generative model which it will be at the same time in at the same time what you know and what you
the object of this knowledge still i sorry if i can just like uh raise a question to that
yeah so i think like i think that there is a sense in which like with respect to
something that in epistemology we call self knowledge there is there is a question here
that the the active inference agent has this model of that is like situated in the body or like in
in its like um like structure and is also modeling that structure itself and there is like this issue
of like where where yeah like the belief is not unidirectionally dependent on the object
sort of a thing but has this feedback loop thing comes up there but there's another way in which
i think like uh where this sort of thing comes where even if the object is outside of the body
of the knowledge i think that that could still come up so for instance if i live in it if an
active inference agent lives in a society of other active inference agents where currently all of them
defect on prisoner's dilemma but maybe like on further reflection they would want to like again
like i don't know what further reflection would mean in the active inference sense but i'm like just
saying in the intuitive sense like that what would it mean for them to like go from one fixed point
to another fixed point where they're all cooperating or or or something like that and
that that i think is not clear to me like how that shift can happen in active inference where
it's not just purely using the empirical information to keep running the the the middle of the of your
like free energy equation but also recognizing the contingencies and then identifying those
contingencies to make something like shifts from one state to another like if if i model that the
society is a cruel space and if everyone models the society is a cruel space then we will end up
creating a society that is a cruel space but if only we could recognize that our belief or our
model that society is a cool space is a contingent belief and we could all somehow negotiate or
communicate and shift to a different belief about what society is and society is a kind
place then we will end up creating that kinder society or something and that sort of like a
belief about the thing that society is it's not entirely within the agent like it's sort of
it it has a weird intersubjective character so it's not entirely outside of the agent either
but it's not entirely like internal to the agent either or something yeah yeah you can think of
that like you're talking about active inference action comes first right you have to you don't
have the knowledge like inside your head waiting for you to to push that out of the way action has
to come first so if you if you take that as a principle an organizing principle it depends on
the contingency of your actions the possibilities might be limited by your situated um condition
but they are limited it doesn't mean that you don't have like a range of options from that state
space in which you can go you can navigate so you can navigate it for the good or for the bad
but it starts with the the action perception loop it starts with the action
a lot of few other pieces on that teach a very good point like when we see the pragmatic component
of action as self-fulfilling epistemic component of action having to do with gaining knowledge and
the salience of information but the pragmatic component is about bringing our observations
into alignment with our preferences and then you identified two related settings one of them is like
pure intra subjectivity like I expect myself or I find myself or I habitually think about x well
that's kind of a trivial self-fulfillment because thinking about something is its own
fulfillment and then when we're in this second person or social space we can agree on little
performance art or on a game and games give evidence to that that when people are able to
perform communication or message passing such that new expectations or preferences are set
whether more top down like more seeing like a state or more laterally more like collective
behavior then those regimes can be embodied and then you brought up a very important point about
the awareness of the contingencies or where awareness is of adjacent possibles or of counter
factuals so the body might be we could model its morphology as doing some computation but that
doesn't mean that the the morphology has an awareness or can explore a counterfactual
like bodies are not always exploring every counterfactual because skin is in the game
but again mentally it's very cheap and easy to consider counterfactuals and situational awareness
of social settings especially if it can be not understood but communicated opens up a space
where we're all playing prisoner's dilemma now there's parameterizations of prisoners multi-agent
prisoner's dilemma where tragically we just all defect all day and never learn there's also
parameterizations where you just start all cooperating and never defect and then the interesting
settings are where there might be like phase transitions or where perturbation moves the
system from one attractor into another attractor so there's just a lot of richness and that's the
work of building generative models in that iterated modeling process to unpack and refine
and active inference isn't going to have a stance on the prisoner's dilemma we can use
active inference to to describe the prisoner's dilemma but active inference isn't going to come
down on on literally even a little two by two game theory matrix so we can then extrapolate that
active inference is not going to come down with an opinion on something significantly
more rich and real than a two by two game theory matrix and so that work is what people enact in
applying active inference right and i think like my question is something like but insofar as like
humans try to constantly improve their social games how can we model that sort of a prior
or your actions or policies that enables that sort of like progressive
improvements or something well
you can we are assuming that we're trying to improve right we we don't know that but you
can model them as improving but like following Daniel's lead we're talking about these specific
games and contingencies they they did these these transitions from one state to another
specifically if you're talking about this modeling of social actors and talking about
several actors if you're modeling several of them will not be really linear right you don't
have like a easy smooth transition of improvement you can capture over time as modeling how they
might tend to go towards a direction and understand that as improvement but that takes
specific iterations that will not be fully linear i guess specifically if you want to
understand error and improvement instead of try an error but try and adding up into this
error like error improvement but when you're modeling specifically with dynamical systems
for instance you you you're not going to see a full linear story and i don't think you're
going to see that uh if you're modeling using active inference and multiple agents agents
i'll add one piece there so how can we go about modeling multi-scale social goals so
we could think about you know different citizens in a region and they the modeler is going to
choose what knowledge to realize in the generative model like what you put into the calculator it's
going to calculate upon now this happens to be a elaborate stochastic method but if we only tell
people yeah there's just your personal income optimized for that your preference is to have
that be higher well then the simulation is going to unfold a certain way if we say well there's
your personal financial income and then there's your city and then there's your region then that
opens up through through different mechanisms you know maybe an individual goes flat or neutral
on the personal in service of a larger win at a higher level well now what if the modeler says
it's not just about the financial income now we're also going to have this secondary criterion
well now different agents could attend differently to those two different outcome variables
and maybe there's one simulation where 50 only care about this and 50 care about that and it
works perfect or it doesn't work it's like a broad surveying you know or lego set or or grammar
or or active inference ontology for scoping very broadly and very inclusively but all the work is
in the real simulation developments and sweeping because very little could be said about a game
theory game if you didn't know what the parameters were in the matrix you wouldn't know whether this
prisoner's dilemma was going to be like an always cooperate or which agents with which strategies
would or wouldn't cooperate if you don't know what the matrix looks like so before the values have
kind of been filled in it's just like actually describing the adjacencies and the counterfactuals
and the contingencies of our scientific model but that's still prior to having the model in hand
and the model you know so now we're looking at that tree in the european forest
and it's like well if i had this tool then i could cut it down this way if i had this tool
i could cut it down this way or i could wait it's like that's alternative actions about that tree
now in the social science setting discussion of different scientific methodologies are like
counterfactuals about that social tree
yeah and specifically if you're navigating these kinds of game theoretical models if that's what
you're interested in you can even define in terms of prisoner's dilemma for instance
specific values just see what happens when everybody deflects and in how frequent
modulate those frequencies in terms of specific in multiple iterations how
how how are you gonna build up the weight or the tendency of deflecting again if your neighbor
deflected once and deflected twice or three times or and see how that will accommodate
over time how many times this agent will change its behavior until it stops changing the behavior
but that you don't really
that's that that again you use you might use a bayesian understanding a bayesian model for that
but it not necessarily explain
me
he does not necessarily explain the action fully i mean social you just you're modeling only the
interest of that specific actor i have a slightly meta question if i can ask both of you i'm not
sure how these calls usually go i'm curious what are your interests in active inference what do you
think like what brings you to active inference and like what do you think what do you think active
inference adds to our theoretical understanding and in what ways or something the right now go for it
well
i think i was trying to touch upon that before and how we can if you're navigating for instance
behavior in terms of game theory this kind of modeling if you're talking about like
trust games for instance you're gonna understand how this do addict interactions evolve over time
specifically over interactions but you don't have an account of change because i have very
limited options of actions and you don't have an account also on scales and i think active
inference tries to add a little bit an account on how you can scale that and how
how
how can add more parameters into the game and see how they evolve with a more clear
understanding a richer understanding that for instance when you talk about specific
interactions in game theory so when that's one one aspect that active inference kind of
contributes another point is because we have this parameterization that is
specifically in terms of belief updating and also in terms of dynamics
we are always talking about agents that will be situated and embodied and have a very specific
uh
synchronization with the environment all the time because when you talk about active inference
the action comes always first so you have a less you try to have a less reductive model
specific and when you want to model cultural agents and collective action i think that's
kind of desirable that's what you're looking for is it also your area of interest sorry is it also
your area of interest mine or is that laryna's area of interest laryna's what do you mean oh sorry
like my question was also like what brings you to active inference and i think you answered a lot
of ways in which active inference adds theoretical value but i wasn't sure like if that was also
your subjective interest or motivation it's my subjective interest yeah i'm curious to see how
that pans out right i'm interested in how that helps us to to think of this type of
uh
phenomena and i'm very interested in how this relationship for agents to collectives and back
again work like
and i think it might give us some well it gives us some very insightful way of modeling
these relationships
in navigating is as you want because this this uh feature of being scale free is kind of helpful
to looking things you can you can define your uh mark of blanket in terms of what you're interested
right and see what happens
i don't know yeah i'll i'll i'll just give a few thoughts even though also surely some of these
thoughts are are scattered um you asked tj what does active inference add to our theoretical
accounts of the social it does many things in in my view and that's what makes it so valuable
epistemically and pragmatically it gives us the expressivity within a scale to describe
collective behavior and across scales to describe nested systems so that brings continuity to
discussions of the social with broader discussions of the biological ecological
computational physical and so on so that's a multi-scale transdisciplinary element
active inference provides us with legible first principles which can either be taken
instrumentally as just heretics and also in certain situations can be viewed empirically
as justifiable first principles and then from those legible first principles which are not
english specific they're already in a space that has a lot more
possibility and promise then for example a mere enumeration of important adjectives or nouns
we can develop lists of important adjectives and nouns
when we have a broader cognitive modeling framework and so this methodological turn
then supports just a tremendous diversity of thought and work instead of asking us to kind of
go through the eye of the needle and you know get on board with this one ranking of features
and then try to apply it more broadly that's like an overfit before the cart situation
with active we can expand the methodological discussion connect it to theoretical physics
and mathematics in ways that really haven't been seen before and then that opens up more
than it closes down it brings up more questions than it resolves in and of itself but it opens
the questions that can be resolved like what generative model can I make that will keep the
temperature in this building livable but active inference isn't going to have a stance on what
you should do for that building so we need to in a way take a step in the methodological direction
which I see as moving towards active inference to enable a million steps in different directions
I have a bunch of questions here I think one is probably just a reference question
the three topics that I'll say if you guys have any papers or articles on those things I would love
to like get a reference one is in what ways can we model a collection or an aggregation of active
inference asians as a like super agent or like super like active inference super agent or something
and like how does this like decomposition and aggregation like flexibility work in different
contexts like if there's like work that tries to either make informal commentary or formal
modeling either ways I would love to see that secondly just quick on the first just on the first
check out the previous section of this course on collective behavior where I reviewed many
such works great thanks okay is it on the same notion is it linked from the same notion things
all in the same places and in the same playlist with this course same syllabus yes good okay
the second is is there an active inference account of say markets or economic interaction
where like your prices act as some sorts of like information signals and like like can use active
inference to then talk about aggregation in of market entities or something I'm guessing this
would also be covered in the same list indeed people have explored cognitive economics and
people are working on it but that doesn't mean it's a done deal theoretically or especially in
practice so keep going it's quite experimental still but there are a bunch of people working on
that I guess I don't remember any specific paper right now but I can I can look it up and forward
to you but yeah yeah it would be great I can drop my email address here yeah sure the third is
probably more trickier than both of these which is is there an active inference account of natural
language um yes thankfully colleagues like Elliot Murphy and others have explored specifically
the linguistic aspects of natural speech I think Lorena's lecture and area of focus generalizes
a bit beyond specific natural language because we're talking about semiotics and semantics
in a more intermodal sense however yes there's been limited work from a computational
linguistics and neurobiology perspective on speech okay so then
okay so you said something like first principles stuff when you're making a commentary on what
active inference brings I have still I have I'm still often like struggling what is active
inference offering and I like try to encounter different things I think I enjoy a lot of
philosophical questions at the conversation opens up but like I'm still like very ambivalent about
the theory um and when I read like this new book uh which Friston has not written uh but like is
and quarter I don't remember was the name of the book um uh yeah I don't exactly remember there's
a book right which is like supposedly like supposed to be the canon and like Friston as a
co-author but in the preface he says so so that's the 2022 par Friston Pazulo textbook right par yeah
yeah I wouldn't quite say it's the canon since it's a short book but certainly it is a landmark
moment for the fields right and when I read that the one thing that bothered me was
it brings up the Helmholtz free energy thing but it sort of argues that by fiat like okay this is a
simple principle it can model a lot of things but that doesn't tell me why I should why I should
trust it like what what is the reason to act why why does this principle lead to cognition like
what like sure you're positive a very simple principle and then said hey look this simple
principle can explain so many things but well it can it also explain things that don't look like
cognition and like I like I'm not sure like there's an I got an account of why that principle is like
uh works or something the rain I go for it I'll think of some other ways to say it yeah you can
think of like modeling by construction and modeling by first principles and if modeling by first
principles you have you have some limitations in which you cannot fully explain some things but
the virtue of the model and how the first principle organizes everything that comes along with the
model usually might be sufficient or might be a useful a useful tool to help you explain that
phenomena that based on the first principle that you were bringing along and that's one way of
one part of answering this question is I think it might be a big question for the for the field
for the field yeah here here's some short little threads on that
yeah we can describe maladaptive cognitive systems or adaptive cognitive systems whether
something's adaptive or not is always in relationship to its niche like the foraging algorithm that
works in the desert doesn't necessarily work in the rainforest so these systems are like intrinsically
adaptive or not we want to have natural language that allows sentences that are valid and invalid
and have different kinds of semantics so again this is just an expressivity framework
that enables people to build cognitive models of high reliability or important settings or you
could make something that looks just like a beautiful circuit board and not even worry about
what the outcome is so yeah for sure you can describe all kinds of systems that would be like
having a less than functional methodological system if we said well we're doing the linear
regression framework but we only want positive regressions it's like well no at the methodological
level we want it to be able to do any slope so here in the cognitive modeling setting we want
more expressivity so that we can actually construct the ones that we're interested in
and then how does this really do cognition how is it that a first principles like surprise
minimization or the bounding of surprise through free energy how can that really cover
so many cognitive phenomena that's the question and the play but how is it that
Newton's laws of motion can describe so many objects being dropped off a tower
how is it that Bayesian mechanics can describe so many different priors being updated
and so by understanding cognitive paths as paths of least action which is the free energy principle
a wide variety of models become of a of a similar kind now yeah whether that's useful to a given
person in a given setting like if you make an active inference model of your business it doesn't
mean you're gonna succeed if you make a self-driving car with active inference it doesn't mean it's
gonna work this isn't a guarantee of success but it's a method that can be utilized and we know
that the method reaches different kinds of modeling outcomes and supports subsequent
perspectives and models from where it reaches but we can't a priori limit where the method reaches
to like only the successful ones or only biological systems then we wouldn't even have
the expressivity to talk about cognitive ecosystems with synthetic intelligences
um and when you're talking about cognition also we can use this kind of first principles
to model aspects of cognition but you might not necessarily think that cognition is all encompassing
like that everywhere all the same but you can ease that to model specific things that you're
interested in in cognitive behavior like adaptivity does it give me any insight to understand what is
adaptive adaptive behavior for instance and which kind of insights do i get are they interesting
are they useful so that's what the availability that this kind of model bring along so you can
you don't have to believe in in the whole story but it gives you a lot of leverage
to ask ask questions and what kind of questions you'll be asking
okay so let's say that like free like active inference and free energy allows me to talk about
systems but does it give also give me vocabulary to then classify those systems
in terms of let's say adaptivity would be one property but like there could be other properties
in terms of like how much how rich the world model is or stuff like that or yeah um if you have
a portfolio of generative models you could summarize them according to the tj statistic
you could summarize them according to the number of nodes you could put them into a common environment
or different environments and summarize their activity in any number of ways but we can't
talk about a ranking or summarization of a portfolio of generative models that's not in hand
this is a framework that lets us build those diverse generative models
and then in a very open-ended way do model comparison model selection model adequacy
all the kinds of complex systems engineering methods that we want
and also I would ask you where do you see a peer or a comparison first principle
you know active inference has legible first principles which are reflected in the active
inference ontology and expressions using it which can be represented in natural language so that's
the talking about it but it's not only represented in natural language other frameworks have other
first principles that may or may not be legible and people may choose different paths to go down
for whichever number of reasons well right models like they have the virtue you can compare them
and see which one gives you the best insight that you're looking for
well so yeah I think like something that I could compare to active inference is like say the
Bayesian utility maximization thing and which has a different ontology I'm not a fan of that either
like that also I'll just note that Bayesian utility maximization is a special case of free energy
where there's no epistemic value all you have is pragmatic value and so a special diminished case
not necessarily you have value of information and you have explore exploit trade-offs
in Bayesian utility maximization as well like you like like if you load into your utility function
if you can beg the question and load episteme into pragma you're right then all you need is
pragma but in expected free energy we have epistemic and pragmatic value which is what enables
us this expressivity but I think we're aligned on that right I think like I'm somewhat like also
slightly confused because in the Bayesian utility like between the languages comparing the languages
as such like in the Bayesian utility maximization the exploration parts that are prioritized based on
your X and the estimation on the value of information whereas I'm not sure that holds true
for the active inference model as well that the epistemic exploration is prioritized or valued
in terms of some of the same pragmatic thing as well. You'll have a lot to explore and learn
you can make a model that is 80-20 or 20-80 or 100-0 between epistemic and pragmatic
there's nothing we can say across generative models about whether active inference prioritizes
episteme or not because you can make a model that's 100% or 0. Sorry I meant more like does active
inference allow us to talk about systems that the Bayesian utility maximization doesn't allow us to
talk about. I'm talking particularly about expressive power of the language. Are there
things that the Bayesian utility maximization can talk about that active inference cannot
other things that active inference can talk about that Bayesian utility maximization cannot.
Two short answers one short answer utility maximization must cram epistemic value into
pragmatic value we gain more expressivity when we can articulate out pragmatic value which is the
alignment of preferences with observations from epistemic value which is information gain so
that's a huge articulation and the second thing is when you're in a anything maximization framework
when you're in a utility function now again bagging the question how you constructed this
function that you're trying to maximize. When you're in a maximization framework we have a well
known set of approaches for finding local and global maxima using optimization or maximization
frameworks. What active inference uniquely provides is it describes the path that that
cognitive thing takes as a path of least action that minimizes surprise so instead of climbing
to the top of the hill up are we on a foothill or are we on the biggest hill we're like a ball rolling
to the bottom of the hill finding the least surprising path now that least surprising path
can still include novelty and information gain but it turns out to be a lot more tractable
and connected with statistical physics and quantum mechanics when we talk about the path of
least action ball rolling down the hill rather than this sort of question bag on top of a mountain
climbing adventure Bayesian utility approach. But it's up to each person to feel how they want to
feel. Yeah it's a little bit what's in the book as well when you take the low and high road for
energy principle right because how much you want to have your utility maximization function being
disconnected to the pragma to do to the action.
Because when you're modeling behavior it will be hard to do that independently like you have a
lot of you have way more assumptions you're committing too much to a greater level of assumptions
for your utility function if you don't do that.
Because with the pragma with the action first that pragmatizes you have reasons to describe
have reasons to believe why that information gain works the way that it does. You can leverage
explanations on that without it you have a model that has more assumptions and I think if you have
a model with less assumptions it's always healthier let's say so.
Yeah so I think like that that that does talk about the compare compare the analysis of the
expressivity but I would also say as a meta point that like I'm not happy with either of those languages
I'm like I suspect that both of those languages claim certain ontological assumptions and I'm
like always suspicious but wait but like where are these ontological assumptions coming from.
A few other points we tap into an absolutely meaningful nexus of statistical methods and
message passing schemes with active inference if you can state something in the active inference
ontology and construct a generative model then message passing algorithms can be deployed that
contractively compute that model so that's absolutely non-trivial otherwise it's possible
just to get wrapped up in some analytical formalism but then once you want to do that on a 4k video
now you're on square zero with the computer engineering this is not that way and then I
will respond to your meta point with a meta point which is when we've enumerated the alternatives
the one that we like best personally I feel happy with I'm also open to new alternatives arising but
being unhappy when all things considered is in play why. What bothers you specifically on the ontology
of the active inference. Yeah like I think like I'm still looking for I don't know what exactly
I'm looking for but I'm I feel dissatisfied with the account given for why Helmholtz free energy
least action thing like is the central thing here or something like why does it work like why
does this principle yeah. There's a lot of funny answers I could give there that that delta that
discrepancy that's curiosity and that's the space of the open and that's learning and that's your
unique contribution to make and that's everything so that's not just a thorn in your shoe that's like
our experience of action amidst uncertainty which is the water we're in and so whether we
take a higher order narrative perspective on that discrepancy being dissatisfying
or that discrepancy being satisfying I think it's pretty. I just need to minimize my surprise there
yeah and you can choose to minimize your surprise through your attention
you can choose to minimize surprise at a higher narrative order like I'm satisfied and complacent
that I don't understand number theory but I use numbers to count objects around me
so that discrepancy and understanding knowing that there's a thousand years of research
that could be done on numbers it doesn't unsettle me but for someone else that might be unsettling
and that might lead them to ruminate it also might lead them to do a phd and number theory
so just different paths for different individuals and contexts but there's always so many technical
and meta levels with active huh. Okay so I don't want to like keep you guys over time but I would
ask one last reference based thing which is are there active inference accounts of seeing
like a state phenomena uh in any literature I think I heard you mention it once so I was like
yeah like this yeah check out live stream 33 series but also this course that we're literally
actually enacting in with Avel is where these accounts come to roost and where we're creating
a space to develop it and it's not a cathedral for us just to spectate at today but if you
want to make an active inference generative model of whatever social setting when you have the model
in hand a lot of your questions will be sidestepped okay where is the 33 thing that you mentioned
if you go to the page with all of our institute live streams and look in the live stream
series like the paper discussions in the 33 series there's a dot zero video with background and
context and then we have a dot one and a dot two conversation with the authors but Avel who's also
the course coordinator for this course and kairos research like Avel's and and colleagues work has
heavily built on the seeing like a state thinking like a state optimal grasp all these different
topics yeah I'm yeah I'm on your youtube channel I'm slightly finding it hard to find the thing
if you look up live stream 033.0 or if you go to in the video description of any video where it says
all live streams here go there and search for but you'll find it and you can always email us
or get in contact but yeah and I think Avel's paper like thinking like a state also can help
you a lot to understand how how active inference modeling is useful for the social sciences in
comparison to other types of modeling he makes an comprehensive description interesting
great thanks and this is this is our first iteration on this course we are going to continue
bringing new information to the table and supporting individuals who want to build
generative models you know around this area whether it's part of an internship program
or part of a course credit or different kinds of programs that we'll be able to develop but
this is the real thing and we're able to work with people who want to think and do
make sense indeed any closing thoughts on tj then I will go and then Lorena with last word
um no that this was great thanks thanks for the conversation
thank you well thank you for bringing tj for joining Lorena for the lecture this was a fun
discussion we never really know where how it's gonna go but I'm glad that we could cover
so many of these topics and probably raise more questions and footholds than door slams so thank
you again Lorena yeah thank you for inviting me and I think active inference like holds a lot of
space for experimenting as well some things you try to see if they make sense and they're gonna hold
up and open new questions and that might be an interesting aspect of uh of the framework itself
thank you everybody thank you everybody for the great live chat comments there's a lot
there I couldn't read at all so till next time
you