Hello and welcome, everyone. This is Physics as Information Processing, Session 4 on Communicating
Observers. It's the 10th of August 2023. Chris, looking forward to this lecture off to you.
Thank you, Daniel, and welcome to this session.
As Daniel said, this is about communicating observers and fastening your seatbelts,
because we have a lot to cover in the next hour.
So just to do a quick review, we've been talking about quantum information theory,
and we've been talking about it in the simplest possible setting of two systems, Alice and Bob,
that exchange information through their mutual boundary.
And we've assumed that everything is finite dimensional, so we don't need to worry about
infinite energy transfer across this boundary. And of course, we assume conservation of energy,
so there are no sources or sinks in either of the systems Alice and Bob.
And we emphasize that this way of depicting things as topological, we're not assuming any
background geometry, no sort of spatial embedding, which is going to become very important in this
session. In the last session, we talked about how the boundary, which I'll always call B,
it can be thought of as a channel that comprises in qubits that are independent,
and Alice and Bob each can prepare and measure those qubits. And they can always choose
independently their reference frames for doing so, so how they define up and down when they're
measuring a spin with effectively a Z-spin operator to interact with these qubits.
We talked a little bit about the free energy principle and its quantum formulation.
And the principle basically says that interacting systems will behave in a way that aligns their
reference frames and that they therefore asymptotically approach entanglement.
So the FEP is a classical limit of the principle of uniterity. And that's one reason for studying
quantum information to learn more about the FEP and so to learn more about active inference
and what the theory of active inference says about agents.
And last time we talked a lot about the constraints that are imposed by a limited free energy supply
on any agent. Recall that we talked about the fact that in the absence of sources of free energy
within an agent, so as long as you conserve energy globally, that the free energy that each
agent uses has to come from its environment. That's clearly true for us. We have to consume oxygen
and eat food and things like that to keep running as systems. And we discussed a little bit this
theorem that if two reference frames or quantum processes Q1 and Q2 don't commute,
they have to be implemented by compartments that communicate classically. And we'll use this
extensively today. But the bottom line last time was that physics alone gives us compartmentalization
in systems whenever the systems are complex enough to have multiple kinds of measurements that they
can't deploy simultaneously. So where we're going, today we're going to start from this
place we left off last time of the possibility of agents that are compartmentalized
and into compartments that have to communicate classically. So we're going to talk about agents
that can be compartmentalized into multiple subagents that share an environment, the environment
consisting of Bob, and how those agents talk about that shared environment.
So the motivation for this is simple. It's that what we do all the time is a group activity.
And what we're doing right now is a group activity that involves sharing an environment,
what's shown on this screen, and talking about it. And the whole post-session discussion process
will be another example of just that sort of thing. So to talk about science at all, or to talk
about any kind of social relations, or to talk about anything other than solipsism, we have to
be able to talk about how multiple agents communicate about some shared environment.
And so that's what we're going to develop a formal way of talking about.
And there are two things to notice right off the top about this. One is that the way we've defined
interactions of boundaries, they're effectively instantaneous. So each agent, remember,
interacts with its boundary with some set of operators. And what those operators do is
effectively measure, each operator effectively measures the spin of a cubic. So this is a very
fast process. The other thing that we then need to notice is that if we have two agents,
and they're communicating with each other classically, then they're going to be using degrees
of freedom of their shared environment in order to communicate. And that's exactly what we're
doing right now. For example, we're using degrees of freedom of the internet to communicate. I'm
using degrees of freedom of the local atmosphere to talk to my microphone. And I'm using degrees of
freedom of the local photon field to see my screen. So all communication between agents,
and certainly all classical communication between agents,
uses degrees of freedom of the environment. And the environment, remember, is the other system,
Bob, that's on the other side of that shared boundary. So we're going to be interested in
how components of Alice use Bob as a communication channel, and in fact, as multiple communication
channels. And I just wanted to quote my colleague and friend, Mike Levin, in his statement that
all intelligence is composite. All of us, all organisms, even single cells, are composite
systems that comprise many, many different agents that are able to make different kinds of measurements
and execute different kinds of actions, and so have to communicate classically.
So we're talking about all of life here, as well as all of social systems and ecosystems,
and such things as that. So the first thing I want to do today is simplify the notation
so that we don't have to draw quite such complicated diagrams. So the picture on the left
here is a picture from the last session. It shows the structure of a very simple agent that
makes some measurements using a reference frame called E, and then writes some results of those
measurements to memory using a reference frame called Y. And those two processes are connected
by an internal clock that ticks between the input process and the output process. And the clock
tick corresponds to the expenditure of free energy to write information irreversibly on the
boundary. So the memories are actually written on the boundary because that's where classical
information lives in this theory. So you can think of this whole process from E through the clock and
back to Y as a single quantum process or as a quantum computation that maps some sector E of
the boundary to some sector Y of the boundary. And so we can represent it in this much simpler way
that's over on the right side as some process Q that maps some sector on the boundary to some
other sector on the boundary. And formally, that process can be thought of as a topological quantum
field theory. Topological here is important. It's not geometric. It doesn't assume an embedding
in space. And this will become critically important later on. And the operation of that
TQFT requires a clock tick, or it incorporates a tick of this internal clock.
And we can do this because we were able to prove, Jim Glaceburg and Tonino Marchiano and I were
able to prove last year, that we can always represent a quantum reference frame as a topological
quantum field theory. And this just illustrates the two kinds of transformations between
quantum reference frames that are important. We can take one and divide it into two pieces
that commute, or we can take a two-part reference frame, and we can swap in
another part that doesn't commute with the part that we've swapped it in for, but that does commute
with the remainder of the reference frame. So here, R is the reference component of some object
identification system. And we can swap in some different way of looking at the object
once we've identified. So for example, if the object that we're identifying is a box that can
measure both Z-spin and X-spin, then P and Q can be the Z-spin and X-spin settings on that box
that allow us to effectively rotate the filter from this way to that way, so that we measure
vertical spin versus horizontal spin. And that's really it. I mean, those are the ways that one
can transform quantum reference frames. Of course, we can do arbitrarily many compositions of this
kind of transformation to do something very complicated, but they map very simply to TQFTs
with the structure, and you can construct categories out of this and find a fumpter that's
well-defined that maps one category to another. So it's an example of the niches of categorical
techniques for solving a problem that looks difficult, but in fact, it's very straightforward.
So using this simplified notation, it becomes very easy to see
that if we have two systems, Alice and Bob, on opposite sides of this boundary,
and we perfectly align their quantum reference frames, which is what the FEP says they will
tend to do, then they become entangled. And you can see that they're entangled by seeing that once
the reference frames are perfectly aligned, they jointly implement one quantum process.
And jointly implementing one quantum process just means you're entangled. The two sides no longer
have conditionally independent states. If one quantum process, which is time reversible,
information preserving, is implemented jointly by the two systems. So a lot of things like
this become very simple when we think of these processes as just quantum computations going on
inside some system implemented by some system and how those processes relate across some boundary.
So that's what we're going to do for studying communication today.
Another thing to recall from a couple of sessions ago, or last session, is that if two
reference frames Q1 and Q2 commute, we can always join them together to form a single
reference frame. And this is just a graphical depiction in this simpler language of how that works.
And topologically, there's no distinction between the left side and the right side.
What I've done is just squeeze the top two green circles together and the bottom two
green circles together into one circle. And that just makes a simple process connecting
the top one to the bottom one. So what we're going to be interested in is situations where this
doesn't happen, where Alice consists of two components that execute reference frames that
don't commute. And so the two components are conditionally independent. They do each have
free choice of reference frame. And so they have to communicate classically. They don't share
a single quantum process. So they're not entangled. And before we go ahead to do that,
I just wanted to remind you of some of the no-go theorems that follow from this situation
depicted on the right, where we have a single agent executing a single reference frame,
a single process, a single kind of measurement, any set of commuting measurements that can be
combined into one measurement. And here's some things Alice can't do. And we've talked about
some of these previously. So this is basically a reminder. But Alice can't, using just one
measurement, measure the entanglement entropy across her own boundary. So Alice can't know
that she has an independent state. She can't know that she's not entangled with Bob. And that's a
useful thing to think about philosophically, as it applies to you and me. We can't actually know
that we have independent states. Alice can't measure her own entanglement entropy. So she
can't know whether she has components that have to communicate classically.
She can't measure Bob's entanglement entropy. So she can't know whether Bob has compartments
that have to communicate classically. And if you think in terms of perception theory,
this says Alice can't know whether Bob consists of separate objects that behave classically.
Their behavior can look classical to her. But she's not able to determine that their
behavior is classical because she can't measure Bob's entanglement entropy.
She can't measure the dimension of her own boundary. And recall from a couple of times ago
that the boundary includes some sector that supplies free energy that Alice can't extract
information from for further processing. She can only extract free energy from.
So she can't measure the dimension of that sector. And so she can't measure the dimension of the
whole boundary itself. And this of course means that she can't measure her own dimension either.
And of course she can't measure Bob's dimension because the only information she can get about
Bob is the classical information that's encoded on this boundary. She can't reach past the boundary
to see how large a system Bob is. And that's clearly connected to this first point that she
can't measure the entanglement entropy across Bob because the entanglement entropy can only be small
if her dimension and Bob's dimension are both much larger than the dimension of the boundary.
So that's a condition she can't check. So all of these kind of no-go theorems lead off an interesting
direction. And the only one that we're really going to be interested in here is the third one,
the one about measuring Bob's entanglement entropy because we want to talk specifically about how
multiple agents, so multiple components of Alice, can access information about Bob's entanglement
entropy. Okay, so recall from the end of the last session that the last thing we talked about was
classical communication. And we talked about the fact that classical communication involves
assumptions and pitfalls and that we have to be very careful whenever we talk about it.
And what we're going to do today is standard practice in physics. We're simply going to stipulate
that of these components, A1 and A2, the separable components of Alice communicate
classically. And so we're going to draw out like this. We're going to draw a classical channel
between them. And that classical channel passes through Bob. It uses degrees of freedom of the
ambient photon field or the ambient atmosphere or pieces of paper or email or something like that
that's out there in the environment to exchange classical messages. And there are a couple of
things to note here. I haven't even written down here. We're assuming that A1 and A2 share some
language for this classical communication. That's a big assumption as we talked about last time.
But I will note explicitly that classical communication takes time. That's what defines
classicality here. It's causal. So it can't work faster than the speed of light.
This is a topological theory. We don't have an embedding geometry. So we can't at this point
talk about light, which is a relationship between space and time. Because we've got time,
we've got clocks, but we don't have any space. But we can say that whatever passes through
this classical channel requires at least one clock tick on Bob's side. So it's a process that
Bob has to execute. And executing that process takes time. So getting the signal from me to you
on the internet takes some time. So the environment's clock has to tick during that.
And all of these assumptions bundled together turn out to be a fairly serious set of assumptions.
And they involve assumptions about fine tuning, about the universe being just right.
And they should make us nervous. And I just want to leave it at that. We always assume
with complete aplomb that agents can communicate classically, but it's not a straightforward
assumption. And it's worth any of you are looking at, for interesting research projects,
can look into the nature of classical communication. It's full of hidden assumptions
and surprises and things that aren't at all straightforward, even though they look like
they ought to be. So there's a challenge. So why do we assume this? Why do we assume
classical communication? We do it because we have to, if we're going to talk about detecting
entanglement. And most of you probably know the history of the notion of entanglement.
It was first noticed by Einstein, Podolski, and Rosen ever after called EPR in 1935.
And they wrote a paper, which is infamous and called the EPR paper, in which they argued that
the phenomenon of entanglement made no sense and couldn't possibly be physical.
And since quantum theory included this notion of entanglement, it couldn't possibly be a complete
theory of what's going on in the world. And Schrodinger replied the same year with a very
detailed paper where he introduces among other things Schrodinger's cat as a paradox.
And he explains very clearly what entanglement is and why entanglement follows from quantum theory.
And he uses that discussion to argue that the classical notion of a physical state is not
actually applicable to the world as it is. So he answers the EPR paper very directly.
And this discussion is currently mostly known as the Bohr-Einstein debate because of course Bohr,
already in 1928, has said in print that the classical notion of causality in space and time
simply doesn't apply anymore. And Einstein objected to that vigorously. But that was 1935.
And it was almost 50 years later that entanglement was first observed in the laboratory. Here,
the 1982 picture is a picture of the interior of Alan Asbest laboratory when he performed
the first entanglement experiment for which he finally won the Nobel Prize last year.
And these days, this kind of experiment is done all over the world and is even done with
satellite-borne sources. Potential resource is the key to quantum security, quantum
security communication, as we'll discuss in quantum cryptography and quantum banking,
the quantum internet, all this other stuff that you may have heard of.
So before talking more about these experiments, I just want to provide a definition of entanglement.
Entangled simply means not separable. That's the definition. So a state, a joint state,
a b is entangled if and only if it does not factor into two separable states.
And that's it. That's the definition. And the literature and especially the popular literature
are, is absolutely rife with hype and various kinds of misjurification of entanglement. And
authors trying to convince you that entanglement is this amazing kind of woo-woo thing.
And whenever you run across that, go back to the definition. I mean, entanglement simply means
this simple mathematical condition of not separability or a state that isn't factorizable.
And that means that the state does not display classical conditional independence.
So classically, that's the way to think about it. It's a failure of conditional independence.
And it's ubiquitous in quantum theory, even though it wasn't actually hipster for almost
50 years after it was predicted. So here's what all these experiments look like. They're called
Bell EPR experiments after John Bell, who derived the statistical criterion for detecting entanglement.
And EPR, Einstein, Podolski, and Rosen, who did this as a thought experiment and said,
if this occurs in the theory, it can't possibly be real. And of course, it is real.
It's now amply demonstrated by experimentation. Here's how they work. There's a source.
The source produces a state that is entangled. And I've written the typical what's called a Bell state.
It's up plus or minus down divided by the square root of 2, just to normalize it.
But up plus or minus down is clearly not the same as up times down. So this is not a separable state.
And this state propagates outward in space and time to two observers who have independent laboratories,
for example, on different continents in that space-based experiment that I showed you the picture
of from the cover of Science a few years ago, 2017, I think. The two observers have freedom
to choose their own reference frame, their own z-axis for measuring spin. They do a spin measurement,
and they do this over and over and over again. They accumulate statistics, and they exchange their
results so that they can analyze the joint statistics of their experiment, and they check to see
whether that joint statistics is consistent with classical probability theory. And if it isn't,
to a statistically significant level, then they've been able to detect entanglement.
Now, notice that this process requires classical communication. They have to make their independent
measurements in their own laboratories, and then they have to exchange results.
Or one of them has to send results to the other one, or they both have to send their results
to some third party. But in all of these cases, they're exchanging some classical data, and so we
have the assumption that whoever gets that classical data knows the language it was recorded in,
and so can do a joint analysis. So I'll just show you another picture of this experiment
that's in a standard space-time diagram. Here, time is vertical, space is horizontal.
The two observers are labeled Alice and Bob. They share a quantum channel
that goes from Alice to the source to Bob. That's the entangled state.
They do some processing, and then one of them here, Bob, sends the results to Alice,
and that's a classical communication. It takes time, and it traverses space.
So this step is classical. So this is why we have to assume classical communication to talk about
detecting or using entanglement. So now I want to represent this in a different way,
using our little picture earlier. We're going to think of Alice again as two components,
A1 and A2. They're separable, so they have to communicate classically. They have a classical
channel that goes through Bob, and they also now share some quantum channel. They share an
entangled state, and the entangled state, of course, is produced by Bob. The source is part of Bob,
and their detectors, if you want to think about it that way, are located on this boundary B,
or their interface with the source is on this boundary B,
and each of them executes a process that accumulates data from the quantum channel
and communicates it to the other observer via the classical channel.
Now this picture illustrates what's called a LOC protocol. LOC means local operations
in classical communication. So A1 and A2 are each operating locally on their boundary.
They're making measurements locally on their boundary, and they're communicating via actions
locally on their boundary and observations locally on their boundary. So for example,
I'm communicating with my computer here, we can consider it my boundary, and stuff is happening
in the environment that's implemented by the internet, and you're receiving those communications
locally on your boundary, on your laptop, or whatever it is you're using.
So that's what local operations means, and these protocols specifically involve classical
communication, and so they're able to detect entanglement. And a Bell EPR experiment is just
an example of a LOC protocol. The observers exchange information about how they're going
to do their experiments, they're both going to measure the spin, they're going to use independently
chosen reference frames, and they're going to look at the output from some agreed upon source.
So that's all classically set up, then they actually make their observations, and then
they classically communicate the results. So classical communication front and back.
LOC protocols are not limited to this sort of Bell EPR sort of setting. We can also represent
a scattering experiment as a LOC protocol. So here's a representation of scattering as a LOC
protocol, and you can see all I've done is cut that previous boundary out the division between
8.1 and 8.2, and I've then extended it in some external time, the time that is
counted by Bob's clock, not by Alice's clock, that's what's meant by external, and I've relabeled
Alice 2 as Alice 1 at a later time. So now what Alice is doing is communicating with her past self,
or A1 is communicating with her future self, and they're each doing something different.
A1 is executing a procedure that in the laboratory we call state preparation.
She's preparing a state that we'll call N, which is just the initial state of some
scattering experiment. So for example, at the LHC, N is some state of two protons that are
quartering around the ring at the LHC at close to the speed of light, and Alice then later on
at t plus delta t is doing a different kind of quantum process. She's analyzing the data
coming out of something like the Atlas detector, which is a multi-particle counter that's located
at the LHC. So they share a quantum channel, which is the scattering channel that takes the
incoming state and produces the outgoing state, and I recall from the very first session, as Feynman
told us, to understand this transition from N to out, we have to integrate over all possible paths
that are consistent with conservation of spin-holicity, basically momentum plus spin.
All the different spins that are relevant in a high-energy physics experiment,
including things like lepton number, which is basically a spin.
Now, how do we know? How do we know what we have to conserve? We know what we have to conserve
because Alice is doing the experiment, has a classical memory that allows her to remember
what she prepared. She can remember that what she did back in the past was set to protons
counter-rotating in the LHC, and they had certain energies, and so they had certain momenta,
and they were protons, so they had certain spin variables. All of that has to be remembered to
make any sense of the output of the detectors, and so to actually come up with a measured state
that makes sense. Very often, this memory channel is neglected by physicists, and I'm going to pause
here and let Andrew ask a question. Thank you, Chris. Does this imply that every time you have a
block channel, the quantum part is like a scattering picture, like a unitary evolution,
even in the earlier EPR picture. Is that quantum channel portion always a unitary evolution
scattering picture? Thank you. Yes, for essentially the reason that I'll define the classical
channel, you're always assuming you have something that's protected from decoherence.
By the environment. So, yeah, if you're doing an EPR experiment, you have to assume that you
don't have any environmental decoherence between the source and the detectors,
and similarly, when you're doing a scattering experiment, you have to make the assumption
that the environment is not reaching in there and messing with the outgoing state that you're
going to see or reaching in and messing with the incoming state and changing it in some way
that re-prepares it in a way that you don't know, that you have no knowledge of.
So, yes, you're making a fairly strong anti-decoherence assumption in any of these settings when you're
talking about having a quantum channel. Does that answer the question? Yes, thank you.
Okay, great. So, we can think of, we can think of LOC, we can think of scattering as LOC.
And I just wanted to now emphasize that effectively what LOC is implementing is two
parallel memories, a classical memory, which as we said in the case of scattering is memory for
preparation. In the EPR case, it's memory for preparation for what the experimental setup is,
for what the instructions for doing the experiment are. And we also have a quantum channel,
which is effectively another memory. It's something that's extended through time,
and again, it's implemented by the environment, implemented by Bob, and it involves Bob's clock
ticking. So, whenever we have two memories in parallel, we can construct an error-correcting
code. So, think of a simple classical error-correcting code, for example, the use of parity bits
in exchanging digital data. So, if I send you a bit string, classically, and I send it to you
two or three times, so there's some redundancy in my signal, and I send you a parity bit.
I say, okay, add up your bit string, and the result should be one. It's one on my side.
If you've added up and you get zero, there's an error someplace. You can use that parity bit to
detect errors. So, you can throw out the bit strings that you receive that have parity as zero
and say, oh, the environment interfered somehow with the signal, or some eavesdropper interfered
with the signal and made a mistake, or something like that. So, this corresponds
to environmental decoherence not being a good assumption, even though it's classical. Environmental
interference is not a good assumption in this case. So, a quantum error-correcting code is
basically the same idea. I use some feature of the fact that I have two different memories,
and that I'm encoding something in time, I'm encoding multiple replicates of something in time,
to provide a way of checking to make sure that I'm sending the correct message.
So, I can, for example, consider the message to be my classical memory,
and consider the quantum process as a process that tests that memory. So, I remember that I
need to do experiment X, and I will get result Y. I actually do experiment X on this quantum channel
and see if I get result Y. And if I don't get result Y, then something's wrong. Either I can't
trust the quantum channel, or I've remembered my preparation conditions incorrectly. So, I'm
using one memory to check the accuracy of the other. And this problem
of using something about the environment, some channel in the environment, to check memory
is absolutely ubiquitous, and we use it all the time. So, for example, look around your room,
and your room hopefully looks more or less the same now that it did at the start of this session.
And that's very reassuring. It reassures you that something's not happening in the environment
that's dangerous and disturbing. And if you couldn't do that, if your environment was constantly
changing, and there was no familiarity about the environment, you wouldn't be able to check your
memory. You wouldn't be able to check your sanity. So, even though we don't think about
our local environments as effectively an error correcting code, that's exactly how we use it.
We use the emerging memory or memory out there in the environment as a way of checking our own
memories and assuring that our memory is okay. So, I talked a little bit about quantum security.
Here's how quantum security system works. Again, it's a lock protocol. We have some classical
signal that can be thought of as a code or a key or a one-time pad, for example,
that encodes a way of doing experiments. And once that's been exchanged, assuming it's secure,
then we can use the quantum channel to communicate information. And the classical channel has told
us what we have to do with that quantum channel. We have to make certain kinds of measurements
at, say, particular clock times as measured, and we'll get information sent from the past,
from the sender. And the classical channel protects the quantum channel from adversarial agents,
because anything that an adversarial agent does to the quantum channel, if some agent
tries to eavesdrop, for example, on the quantum channel, they'll disrupt the quantum channel,
and the results of our measurement will not be what's expected given the protocol that we run,
that we have run. So quantum communication is secured by the fact that interfering with some
entangled state actually destroys the state, so it's detectable. We can always know if someone is
trying to disrupt our communications, which isn't true if we just have two classical channels.
Charlie can always intercept a message and then recreate it, and that's not possible
with a quantum channel. So let's refold this diagram so that we've taken the external time
back out of it. And we have this picture where the two components of Alice are just interacting
via their shared boundary with their environment, Bob. And now we can see that the source of
redundancy is not time, it's the boundary itself. Just sharing the boundary allows
Alice's components, A1 and A2, to put copies of the same information on different places
on the boundary. So the boundary now becomes a resource for redundant storage of information.
So Alice 1 and Alice 2 can use different parts of the boundary
to check what other parts of the boundary say, to check the information that's encoded on other
parts of the boundary. So they can define an error correcting code on the boundary itself
using this lock protocol. So I just want to leave you with this idea that using classical and quantum
channels together allows us to define error correcting codes on boundaries that we share
as separate agents. And leave you to think about what shared measurements, what shared
quantum reference frames, let us as agents see the same things. And this is what we'll talk about
next time in September. We'll talk specifically about how space provides us with an error correcting
code and try to understand why space is treated as emergent from something else, basically,
from communication in most of quantum gravity. So thank you very much. I encourage you to use
the interactive QA and to attend the discussion sessions and we'll see you in September. Thank you.
Awesome. Chris, thank you for the lecture. Andrew, do you have any remarks or questions?
Not right now. Thank you. I'll just ask a few quick questions and if anyone has one quickly
in the live chat. So you mentioned the tick of the clock and in active inference, we often hold
up side by side both the discrete time models and the continuous time models. So do clocks have to
tick discreetly or how do we think about continuous time modeling? In this in this quantum setting,
they do have to tick discreetly because one has to be able to distinguish
Alice's preparation of the qubits on her boundary from Bob's measurements of the
qubits on the boundary. And this process can be extremely fast with respect to any kind of sense
of macroscopic time. You know, your eyes are responding to photons in I think it's hundreds
of femtoseconds. So the discrete transitions that are effectively time measurements for you
are at that very fast molecular time scale, much, much faster than our typical clocks.
When we try to do very fast timing, we're constructing a faster clock than that,
but it's a clock that we can only observe indirectly.
Awesome. Okay. Now this one maybe connects a little bit to application, but with all the
developments happening in theory, some of which you're reviewing here, and also in practice with
quantum computation, and then keeping in mind this distinction. Sorry, I've lost you. Back.
I've lost you, Daniel. Okay, we'll wait till you're back. I can see you. No. Okay. Yeah,
just repeat your question, please. Yeah, so given these rapid and ongoing developments in
theory and practice related to quantum information science and quantum information security,
how are people using this distinction of the classical Stigmergic memory and then the
quantum cognitive process to anticipate
how to develop information systems that are reliable going forward?
I don't know of any instances in which thinking about quantum cognition has entered directly into
any design of communication systems. The ability of humans to interact with these systems is just
assumed. So it's just assumed that the user can interact with, say, a computer interface,
which is the sort of interface that will be provided or is provided to any quantum computer.
So if you think about a quantum computer, a practical quantum computer, it has classical
interfaces front and back. So in thinking about interacting with the computer, I'm giving it some
classical problem statement, for example, and asking for some classical answer. And what it's
going to give me is a probability distribution of classical answers. But I can, by running the
calculation many times, make that probability distribution fairly tight.
So yeah, I don't know of anyone talking about quantum BCIs at this point. It'd be an interesting
question. Was it always understood these sorts of blind spots and axioms associated with classical
communication? Was it developed as kind of like a proposal or like a special case? And more unpacking
was left for later? Or are these blind spots things that we're now coming into awareness of,
given what we're learning in the quantum information sciences?
I think we're learning how serious they are. But they were certainly recognized even by Bohr
in his 1928 paper. And that's a very good paper, too. It's called the present state of quantum
theory or something like that, and it's in nature. And it's available on the web somewhere.
I have a copy of it. But it was written, in a sense, as Bohr's summary of the 1927 Solvay
conference, which was the conference at which everyone doing quantum theory at that time
got together to talk about their results. And in it, Bohr essentially presents what came to be
the Copenhagen interpretation, which I think is probably unfairly called an interpretation.
And it's sort of the Copenhagen pragmatic stance toward quantum theory. And essentially what Bohr
says is that if we're going to do science, we have to assume that people can talk to each other.
And if we're going to do science, we have to assume that there are instruments that we can
manipulate and have reasonable confidence that we know what manipulation we've done. So if I turn
a knob from one to two, I have to be reasonably confident that I'm making a particular change
that I can understand. And we have to have reasonable confidence that different laboratories can
replicate the same experiment. And if we think about any of those assumptions in purely quantum
theoretic terms, then all sorts of questions are raised, right? Every quantum system is unique.
We have the no cloning theorem. So every scientific instrument is unique. So there's no such thing as
exactly replicating an experiment, right? That's a coarse-grained description of what I've done
with a completely unique quantum system. And my brain, of course, is unique. And yours is too,
and everyone else's is. So talking about a sharing a language is essentially a coarse-grained assumption.
And what the Copenhagen stance is all about is coarse-graining, yielding, effective classicality.
Or what that really means is coarse-graining, yielding, a description that we can use in
the language that we understand. So these are very, very old issues that have been recognized for a
long time. But I think, in part, because of the disaster of shut up and calculate,
they haven't really been talked about in the classroom.
Awesome. I'll just read short questions from the chat. We can just, we can pass them to the
discussion section, but there's a lot of great diverse questions. So Alexi wrote.
I think I've lost you again. The Revenge of Zoom.
Well, we looked at the chart earlier where like Bob was talking to Alice,
the unidirectional communication. Okay, good.
Yeah. Okay. Okay. Okay. The unidirectional. The third party is recording it, I'm sure.
Alexi wrote regarding the environment for being used for error correction. A symptom of
derealization in psychological trauma breakdown. We don't recognize the environment around us and
it's scary. Makes sense. Makes sense. All right. From Bala. Nice presentation. I heard Chris say,
entangled states are LOCC for a specific reference frame. Is this entanglement unitary or
is it related to the numbers of degrees of freedom?
I think the quick answer would be both. If you have a complex system with many
degrees of freedom, some can be entangled while others aren't. It depends on what parts of the
state are separable. So again, entanglement is just a statement about
components of a joint state that factor or don't.
So you can have a joint state that looks separable along some dimensions, but
other dimensions. The other big complication here is that
whether a state looks entangled depends on the reference frames that you use to measure it with.
And if you pick entangled reference frames, then what we ordinarily think of as separable
does entangled states become separable. So you can move entanglement around.
Awesome. Okay. From Roland Rodriguez. Is the discrete temporality only within the context
of a given holographic screen interface? With time being bracketed otherwise,
beyond interface systems is continuity or discretion kept agnostic?
I think if I understand the question correctly, it's yes. If I don't draw any boundaries,
I just have the joint state, then the evolution is unitary. And in a sense, time plays no role.
And if unitary evolution is perfectly time symmetric, so time actually drops out altogether.
Awesome. So to talk about time, we have to draw boundaries.
Awesome. Time must have a stop. And I'll ask one last question from the appropriately
monocled question quanderer. All communication is abductive. Is a sentiment that I've been
using to develop some arguments? Does that scan for you? How do we connect what we're discussing
here with quantum to abductive logic? Yeah. I could go along with that. I want a lot more detail.
All communication is essentially analogical. I would agree with that. Yes.
Andrew? Yes, thank you. So going back to the picture where the scattering picture,
so we have so far everything is topological and certainly induces breaking the boundary
in different sectors. I suppose it induces a topology on the boundary. Now, I have a couple
questions asked for the geometry, and this might be getting ahead. Is it an emerging property of
those channels between different boundary sectors? And if that's the case, then what does it mean to
have a QRF for space? Yeah, this is really the topic for September. But you do point out the
fact that it's something of a chicken and egg situation. The way I think of it is I suppose
to choose the chicken side and think about what kind of reference frame does the agent have to
implement to see space on their boundary? And the reason I think about it that way is
that's a question I want to be able to ask about biological systems. And this actually gets into
probably what won't be talked about until October. But I want to be able to ask
essentially a phylogenetic question of what sorts of organisms, where in the lineage from Luca,
do we find systems that are able to assign spatial coordinates to their boundaries?
And what coordinates come first? And I suspect that sort of discrete location names with no metric
come first. That a system can talk about, for example, this part of their membrane versus
that part of their membrane without even having any ability to say how far apart they are.
That some sort of metric representation of this angular space comes later.
And that a radial space comes even later than that. That's at this point speculation. But I
think these are questions that we can end up asking given the right kind of formalism
and the right understanding of what it means to be able to make a spatial measurement.
So the conjecture is that the metric would emerge from a discrete network metric of counting ticks
sort of thing? Yeah, I think that's correct. And the sort of cemeteries of space that we see
are very much tied up with object identity. So if we think about something like rotational symmetry,
let's see. I should stop screen sharing.
So I've got this object, right? And I can do this and I say, oh, the space has this rotational
symmetry. But for me to say that, I have to recognize that this is the same object, right?
I have to implement object persistence, which we all learn to do when we're nine months old or
something. But we tend to regard those as separate things as, you know, we learn object persistence
because space is rotationally symmetric. But we can view it the other way around that space is
rotationally symmetric for me, because I implement these constraints that are called object persistence.
Do you think we can understand phylogenetics as a whole, as a kind of scattering experiment,
like the high energy Luca event, and then dissipating and propagating in a very tangled bank?
Well, I do want to be able to understand phylogeny in exactly the same terms as embryology.
And Mike Levin and I have published papers about that. We should be able to view the
lineage of Luca in exactly the same way that, you know, we view the lineage of the zygote that produced us.
So that's why it's no coincidence that during pregnancy, the development of the embryo
mirrors evolution in terms of the parts that are developed first?
Yeah, this is the old idea that phylogenia and ontogenia are related in some way,
which from an embryonic development point of view, they're certainly analogous in ways.
And sorry, if I may ask one last question, I think it should be very quick.
Regarding the weak rotation, I'm still a bit unsure of how it ties to this
diagrammatic notation that we had with quantum channels and so on.
And there was a note in the second session, we briefly talked about the weak rotation,
you know, being a reversal in the direction of time. Is there any relation to today's session?
Yeah, whenever we think about the flow of time as driven by the input output cycle,
the input output cycle for agents separated by a boundary is always, there's always a sign
change, right? My input is your output and vice versa. So when we think about the
Bob's clock ticking when Alice does something, his direction of time, in a sense,
points with respect to the boundary opposite to hers.
But that's only with respect to the boundary. He sees information flowing in and she sees
information flowing in. That's the only point being made here about the weak rotation as an
operation. Thank you, Chris. Very well appreciated by the viewers and by us. So we'll certainly
look forward to reviewing the Q&A and everybody is welcome and encouraged to join for the
participatory discussion in about two weeks on Saturday. So till next time.
All right. Thank you. Cheers.
you