Okay. Thanks. Starting my clock. I'm going to talk about Vim today, so I already changed
my clothes, as you can see. Just a quick, quick, raise your hands. Who's using Vim for
development? Okay, that's almost the majority. Who's using traditional graphical IDEs for
development? All right. Okay, so there are at least five people in the room that might
be able to learn something here. All the rest, you will probably know what I'm talking about.
Where do I come from? So to put this into perspective somehow, I guess when I was 12
or so, I started writing my first program in basic, I think, on an Amiga or C64, I can't
remember. Later, when the internet arrived at our home, I started doing PHP and using
Dreamweaver. At university, they taught us Java and we used Eclipse. My first job, I was
using C-Sharp in Visual Studio for a couple of years, and my second job, I used Python
and Wing IDE, which I enjoyed much more, by the way. Last year, when I came here to PyCon,
I figured that lots and lots of very smart people were actually using Vim. I already
knew about Vim, obviously, all the time, but I always thought that it's much too complicated
and I will never have the time to learn this and it will kill all my productivity for months
or so. But when I saw that, I don't know, guys like Jacob Kaplan, most of what, are using
Vim all the time and are being obviously very productive with it, I thought maybe I should
give it a try. It was actually PyCon's fault that I started using Vim last year. Thanks
to you all. Why should you care? I mean, most of you care anyway, so I probably can
skip the slide, but obviously, Vim is cross-platform, so if you're using Ubuntu, you can use Vim.
If you're using macOS, you can use Vim. At home, I've got several laptops and whatever
I feel like. Every day, I can just open my laptop and my Vim with my Vim config is there
and it just works and it looks the same and feels the same everywhere. It's standard on
most systems, so for example, when I'm doing web development, I SSH into my web servers
and you can be sure that Vim is installed there, so it's quite good when, I don't know,
there's an emergency and you have to SSH into the machine. You want to know that you have
a good editor on that server that you can use and that you can use in a fast and efficient
way and you don't want to screw up your files because there's an editor that you usually
never use because you are used to a graphical IDE. It's very fast. I mean, when I remember
back the times when I was using Eclipse, the startup time, I was usually leaving my desk
and getting a cup of tea or so. Vim is almost instantaneous, obviously. It's good for your
health, sounds funny, but I can testify it's true. When I was programming for like 10 hours
a day with a classical IDE and moving back and forth to the arrow keys to navigate in
the text file, it actually hurts. When I started using Vim six or seven months ago and I got
this idea of using HJKL for the movement only, I was really unbinding the arrow keys so that
I must force myself and hammer it into my muscle memory as fast as possible. It actually helps
but because you have your fingers on the central row when you are typing with 10 fingers, they
are naturally resting there and you can just switch to movement mode and use HJKL to move
and switch back to insert mode and you don't have to move your hand at all and it makes
a big fat difference when you work a whole day and when you code a whole day. It's highly
customizable, of course. It's great for pair programming which is something that I want to
demonstrate if we have enough time at the end. Yeah, you can work anywhere, anytime. It's interesting
when at my last job we basically had the opportunity to get any hardware that we wanted so I got
myself a big fat 30 inch screen and at that time I thought that dual screen setup is the most
awesome thing in the world and it makes you so much more productive but I realized that since
I'm using Vim, I use screen or T-Markz as a screen multiplexer so I can switch between tabs
quickly so suddenly I have lots and lots of windows and desktops at my hand, just a fingertip
away and I have actually not used my second screen for six months or what? I don't use it anymore
so I can just go, I can code on an airplane, I can code on a beach, I can code anywhere
and I don't need to have an office environment or something, I just need my laptop and internet
connection. Another cool thing that I came up with when I thought about this slide yesterday is
you can change jobs and keep your tools, like maybe today we are coding in Python,
maybe tomorrow we are coding in Haskell or C++ or whatever and probably Vim will have a plug-in
that suits that new programming language that we will use in the future as well so
we will probably, I mean if you use Vim, you will probably never have to change your editor
ever again. By the way, all this is probably also true for Emacs, I guess they are quite similar
but I've never tried that one. So what am I?
Pardon? Okay, so to me what do I need in order to say that yes this thing is a workable IDE,
I want to have fast access to all files, I mean those files that are currently open maybe in
several tabs or splits and files that I know that are in the project, I want to have a nice color
scheme and I want to be able to change it quickly, I mean some editors give you a good way to change
the color scheme but maybe there's no standard file format or what so you cannot really exchange
the color scheme easily, it's pretty easy with Vim. I want to have syntax highlighting for all
common files that I will use which are in my case Python, HTML and CSS files and JavaScript files.
I want to have static code analysis, I mean with Python everybody knows we have this great
PEP8 document which tells us how to code beautifully and there are tools for checking
like Flake8 or Pylint or PEP8, there are tools that can check your code against the PEP8
specifications and they will highlight if there are like I don't know unused imports or
unused variables and stuff like that or there's a space too much or too many empty lines at the
end of the file or something like that. Code completion obviously is the main thing why
people use IDEs and I will show you how to get that with Vim. Go to definition is another cool
thing like when I'm using Django the framework is so big it has so many classes and modules and I
usually although I know it by heart almost I usually cannot remember what parameters the function
accepts for example and I don't want to go to Google or to the Django docs all the time and
look it up so just jump to the definition and look at the actual implementation of the method
and see what kinds of parameters the function allows and then you will also see the doc string
and yeah it's quite useful. Refactoring is something that this setup that I'm going to show is able
to do but I have actually never used it so I cannot demonstrate it. I somehow feel that using
refactoring with a dynamically typed language like Python is I don't know a bit it feels dangerous
to me I wouldn't trust the system. Debugging I think it can be done from within Vim but I usually
don't do it I use iPython and IPDB and just open another terminal window and I will insert break
points using Vim with a short key and then open another terminal window and start my program and
just wait until the breakpoint is hit and inspect the scope which I will demonstrate here as well.
Okay so we have four topics here. I will show you how to install Vim. I will show you how to
configure it for the first time starting from scratch. I will show you how you can manage
your plug-ins because the standard way of downloading it, unsipping it and putting the
correct files into the correct folders is quite messy there's a better way to do it and if time
is left I will show how you can use Vim for pair programming with Tmax. Okay installing Vim is
pretty simple. This is a script that I always execute whenever I set up a new server for my
web project or when I reinstall my own system just clone the source and the important bit is here
this enablepython interpreter part which you will need because the the Python mode plug-in is written
in Python and so Vim has to be compiled with with Python being enabled and you know I used to install
it into my home opt Vim folder so I don't disturb any other users on the system and that's it basically
and when you've done that you can check if everything has worked by by just typing Vim minus minus
version and you will get a lot a lot of stuff and you should search for the plus Python flag it will
tell you that it has actually been compiled with Python support sometimes it goes wrong and when
there's minus Python you know that you did something wrong and you should try again um yeah so that's
installing Vim should take around five to eight minutes or so um your first .vimrc file so when
when you start using Vim people usually recommend or advise you to um to start from scratch don't
take a fully brown Vim file from from from some hardcore hacker or so there's so much stuff inside
you will get lost better start from scratch and and whenever you feel that oh I want to do this
how can I do this just google for it go to the Vim IRC channel there are super many super smart
people inside and they are extremely helpful whenever I ask a question I get an answer within
two minutes um vimbits.com is a pretty cool website where it's like hacker news people can post their
their snippets and people can upvote and downvote it so it's like every month or so I just go there
and see what's what's hot and and what's bubbling on top and you usually can find lots of crazy ideas
you wouldn't you would never think of yourself um and I can only advise you to save your .vimrc
file on on your own .files repository on github many many programmers do that and it's a great way
to get inspiration just like for example I was talking to him right now and and and and he was
showing me some great tricks that I didn't know about and I immediately asked him is your .vimrc
file on github he's like yes of course so I know what I'm going to do when I'm home today um yeah
so let's do it I I just deleted my own .vimrc file and and created a new one um
so when you start Vim for the first time it will look like crap it looks just like the terminal
doesn't really look like an editor um so let's try to make this thing beautiful and look like an IDE
the first thing I usually do is um I put this buff write post thing here so I don't have to
close and reopen the file all the time when I do changes from now on when I when I save the file
will be uh reload it's like doing source on the terminal for when when you change some your bash
rc file you do source bash rc and then the changes will happen so now we will do the same when we
save um the standard behavior of the clipboard is something that I never really understand
so when you do clipboard equals unnamed it's basically the way you would expect it to be
with any other editor so when you copy something from a website you can just paste it into Vim
and when you select and copy something inside of Vim you can just paste it somewhere else
which wouldn't work right away then you can enable the mouse so now when I press the option key I can
use the mouse cursor to yeah to do what the mouse cursor is supposed to do and this backspace equals
to um it's quite useful because the standard behavior of the backspace key is a bit weird I
don't actually know what it what it does normally maybe somebody here can explain it to me uh so
when I oh shit sorry um I will comment this out and save again so now let's say I'm typing something
and then I'm typing something more and I want to press the backspace key
oh no it works okay usually um maybe some other settings have fixed this behavior as well but
usually when I try to use the backspace key it just stops there is some text in the line I'm
in insert mode and I'm pressing backspace but it just stops I don't know why this happens and this
setting this BS bullshit equals to will make will turn the backspace key into a real backspace key
I like to remap my map leader key the map leader key is the special keys because the
the keyboard is so full with shortcuts already that they ran out of keys so the map leader
key gives you the possibility to bind another full set of keyboard keys um because when you
press the map leader key them will wait for one second and see if you press any other keys so
suddenly we can press comma and something else to have even more um places to bind stuff to
then okay this is something that I cannot demonstrate right now because the color scheme is not installed
um saving as you have seen I usually have to you have to type call on w to save
I don't like that I it's like I was using ides for so long I I just have the habit of typing
and pressing ctrl s for save okay I can't press ctrl s here in vim but I remap it to ctrl z and
now it's already in my muscle memory again so from now on with these settings in whatever mode I am
I can just press um ctrl z and it will save very convenient the same thing is true for quit usually
you would have to type call on q for quitting I don't like that so I like leader e for quitting
it's much faster to me but this is like this is the reason why you should start from scratch because
you will probably have different ideas of where all these bindings should be for you for yourself
um okay you can have tabs and splits in vim and you want to be able to easily navigate between
them so let me demonstrate that uh when you when you create new tabs it's like this it's just tabs
very normal um but the standard way to navigate is like pressing ctrl w and then um one of the
movement keys for tabs I prefer to press the leader key and then n for going left and m for
going right so the leader key I put it on on comma and m and n is just all next to each other so
it makes it allows me to fast to to to switch between tabs very fast the same is true for splits
so when I have a horizontal split here you would have to press ctrl w j for going downwards into
the uh uh bottom split I I don't see why I should press two keys so I I know I remap that so that I
can just press ctrl j for going down ctrl k for going up or if you have a vertical split you can
press ctrl h and l to go left and right so it's it's basically just like moving around the cursor
just to press the ctrl key then you will be moving around the splits so very convenient
okay um yeah here's a very useful thing that you will probably use when you develop with
python because it's encouraged to have all the imports sorted alphabetically and
vim users will always do this because it's so easy I just bound it to con to to leader s and I can
just select a block of code press leader s and it will it will be sorted alphabetically very nice
um oh yes this one is cool I found this on vimbits.com I can select a block of code and
and then and use the um greater than and less than signs to move the whole block of code usually
you can easily do this this with vim anyways but it will lose its selection so um with this snippet
it will remain its selection so you can press it multiple times yeah
uh okay um this one I cannot demonstrate it right now but it will show trailing white space
usually you don't want to have trailing white space in your code because I don't know when you
submit a a patch to an open source project and most people will have a script that deletes all
white space when they save and when you inserted some stupid white space and the next person is
editing the same file you will end up with lots of diffs where you didn't actually do anything
it's just because the other person automatically deleted your stupid white space so just make
sure you never insert any unwanted white space and this this line here will make sure that
its big fat red block showing you here's white space delete this um color schemes can be installed
easily in I have um all this file is on github so if you want to start from scratch you can clone
this repository um and um do the same that same thing as well sometimes you will find
comments here like this one this will explain how you do actually install a color scheme so it's
just create a dot vim slash colors folder go inside that folder and then download this one
bad color scheme and there you go um syntax highlighting this is something that will not
work when I save so I have to restart this file and now we have syntax highlighting so vim knows
its own syntax for its own configuration file and here are a bunch of settings for now we are
getting into the area of making this more look like an IDE so now we have column numbers and
the 80 characters line usually you don't want to write your Python scripts longer than 80 characters
so there's a very subtle line here I don't know if you can see it it's just a little bit darker
huh thanks and um this one is pretty cool when you when you write a doc string for example
and maybe you don't want to care about um I'm wrapping it correctly and you are writing over
the 80 characters line after that just point the cursor somewhere into that block and press Q
huh why does it not work I'm confused
okay I I entered awesome okay but why does this happen
hmm because I didn't save ah yeah okay okay let's try that again press Q and it
wraps the block of text accordingly so that nothing goes over that line it's not always useful
because like when you have when you're using markdown or restart check text and you have for
example you have bullet lists it doesn't really know that the bullet lists belong under each like
how to explain sorry so it's like when you have bullet lists like this and then this
and you press Q it will destroy your bullet list and put everything into one line so don't use it
all the time but sometimes it can be quite useful um under history of 700 yeah something that I like
um for pison you don't want to use tabs you want to use spaces and you want to use you want to indent
by four um this one is for when you do regular use you use regular expressions for search that
they are case insensitive ah come on this one um it's a bit tricky I don't know if everybody
needs this um vim creates a lot of swap files and and backup files when when you save and I like
to use file system watches so that whenever I save all my tests get executed immediately in another
in another terminal window and the standard behavior seems to be that it creates three or
four file system events and my tests get executed three or four times in a row which sucks so and
with these three settings I got to fix this and when you save it's actually just one file system
event okay so that is about the vim rc now we'll talk about some plugins that will
introduce all this id stuff that I want to have it's it's four plugins I won't I won't say much
say much about them right now I will just show you how they look like um oh yeah when you when you
want to work with plugins within the the standard way is you have to download a zip file or a tar ball
and you have to unpack it and you have to install it into the dot vim folder and then there can be
several different subfolders there can be an ft plugin folder there can be a syntax folder
and each plugin more complex plugins will have so many files that you have to you have to read the
readme and it will tell you like copy this file into that folder and this file into that folder
and it's a big huge mess and for you and especially when you want to get rid of that plugin later on
you can't remember which files did belong to that plugin and in which folders are they so
it's a mess use pathogen instead it's very easy to install you have to create this autoload folder
uh and a bundle folder then download the the pathogen file and that's it and and
insert this call pathogen infect setting here and you are good to go from now on you can install
plugins by just unpacking them into the bundle folder so for example if we want to install
vim power line we will go into the bundle folder and we will just clone the whole power line
repository and usually vim repositories repositories of vim plugins on github are
created in a way that the root folder has the files all in the current in the correct folder so
you can just clone the thing into the bundle folder and it will work okay um so here's a setting for
vim power line you will see when i demonstrate it just a second control p is a plugin for quickly
navigating through files and opening files and python mode is is a very very great project
i think it's a wrapper around uh several other plug vim plugins that deal with python and and
and make vim more like a python IDE so it's it's much easier to just install this one plugin
then several others okay this one is some stuff okay and python folding allows you to collapse and
expand your your whole code so now that i have installed these four plugins let's go to some
test repository so i've created a stupid little demo project here python project um so the first
thing we can see we have code we have syntax highlighting it looks like python code python
code it's it's it looks nice um yeah the folding plugin now i can use f to fold and unfold blocks
of code or i can use uh capital f to fold everything which is quite handy if the file is a bit long so
i don't want to scroll down and then press control d control d control d to go down um i just fold
everything and maybe do a search for the for the function name and i will be i will reach the
code that i want to work on quickly um yeah yeah then you should use my version i don't know it just
works i never have problems with the doc strings yeah when i when i point the cursor here and press
f it will only okay i don't have a class in the syntax but if you would point the cursor at the
class definition and press f it will collapse the whole class uh yeah um functions are too long
okay yeah um there is the i think py lint or or py flag or so has a feature of telling you that the
function is too complex where if you have too many nested if and else things it will say this
function is too complex and usually those functions are also too long okay um one thing about rope
rope deals with all this go to definition stuff and code completion stuff uh when you when you use
it for the first time you should execute rope open project and this will create a dot rope project
folder which contains a config file and in that config file you will find a line about python pass
and here i would insert my the parts to my virtual environment for example when i'm using
when i'm working on jango project i would insert the pass to the virtual environment of that jango
project so that python rope actually knows where jango is otherwise it like code completion wouldn't
work right um yeah so let's try this um no we will try this later so um static code analysis
when i'm when i'm doing stuff like this it will open a quick fix window down here and it will tell me
that i have just inserted invalid syntax very useful uh or for example here it will tell me
there is a variable that is never used or for example if i import something that i never use it
will tell me there's an import that is never used and uh when i go down to this quick fix window
i can navigate through these items and when i press enter it will jump to the actual line that has
the error and so i can quickly fix this error go down to the to the quick fix window jump up here
fix this error as well and and then i'm good to go um yeah code completion very obvious so let's
say i i know there's a method that starts with l and i press control space it will give me all options
that it guesses it it is usually also assumes some python build in functions it assumes variables
that i have defined in this module before or it assumes functions that i have imported by using
the star import for example um okay now control p is the other plugin that deals with opening files
so when i press control p it gives me a list of all files in the project and it has some fuzzy file
file pattern pattern matching logic or whatever so when i know okay i want to open this file that
is called something with u utils or something i just press u it narrows down the results to everything
that has a u inside or maybe everything that has an r o rope okay config rope config there i am right
so you can even um just type down parts of the passes like maybe you know some folder names and
you know some parts of the file name so you just type down some parts of the folder name or some
parts of the file name and you will get the file so let's open utils in a in a new tab for example
when you press control t it will open a new tab whereas when you press control v it will open a
new vertical split um what else do we have oh yeah jump to definition so let's let's assume
i want to use the url join methods and i forgot the possible parameters to this method so i can
just press control g and it would jump to to my uh python installation and and look up the url join
methods so i can just have a look at the method declaration and implementation and i can see
ah a low fragments that was the name and i can read the doc string and find out what it does
yeah last but not least debugging by pressing con leader b i can insert breakpoints
and i think it will also also automatically save the file not sure maybe it doesn't and
now i will open another terminal window and execute this demo project and it will stop at the
breakpoint and you can get you can get this by just doing pip install or easy install ipython
and easy install ipdb it's extremely useful um ipython ipdb will give you um color some syntax
highlighting here it will give you tap completion um so to get started you should just type question
mark there are the few commands that are available it looks like a huge list but most of them are
duplicates like a and alias is the same and so you can just press question mark a or you will get
an example what a does so some useful commands are l to give you a little bit more context
around the line we are currently on when you press it several times it will go down
you can say show me line 10 to 40 for example if you want to go more up um n stands for next
well that's going to be bt backtrace very cool it will show us that we are actually
here in this line in this file in this function and we came from here from this file this function
from this line so maybe you will realize that okay the bug isn't actually here it's it's up here
by when you when you use bt for backtrace maybe you will realize that ah something is is fishy up
here so you can just use you and you will go up the backtrace so now we will you can see that now
we are in the demo file so it jumped up here and we are now in the one frame above the
in the backtrace and you can use arcs to inspect the currently available variables and the current
scope so um oh what did i do that was not good sorry so arcs to inspect the variables and i mean
this is just a python interpreter you can you can type anything that there's a valid python command
for example type data what type was data oh it's a dictionary so cool then i can press dot
and press tap twice and it will give me all options that the dictionary has so um i remember
there was something about keys to get the keys so oh yes keys there it is and yeah so this i mean if
you are a python beginner this is the best way to to learn actually to actually learn python put
breakpoints into your code inspect all the stuff and then play around and see what what the
python built-ins and all the data types have to offer all right um that's how i use them as a
python ide i think that's pretty good already um last thing i think a few minutes i left um i will
talk about how you can if you are still not convinced why you should use a terminal editor oh come on
um this will take just two minutes um if you're still not convinced i'm in a situation that my
team has um spread all over the world so the person that i work with the most is is sitting in
germany i'm sitting in singapore and um usually we want to do pair programming right he has a
question i have a question he has a bug and he doesn't he doesn't know how to solve it and
then i usually want to look at his code and what we did all the time until recently is
we start skype and we do skype screen sharing and then it crashes so we switch over to team viewer
and try that and it's super slow and laggy whatever i'd say i'm like saying and talking quickly and
jumping through the code and whatever i'd say he will see it 10 seconds later or five seconds later
and it's it's just big brain fuck it does it's not fun right so there's a tool called vmax it's
some wrapper around tmax and um i can start a vmax session by just typing vmax as i did just now
and the other person i will i will do um i will set a port forwarding in my router at home
to port 22 and i will give the other person my ip and so the other person will be able to do ssh
pair pair proger at my ip so i i created a new user with lots of restrictions so this person
is not able to delete my home folder or something oh why does this not work now
j i think oh yes you are correct thanks pair proger
okay
okay and then the person can type vmax attach and now he will see what i see and i will see
how big his screen is or how small so i will i will scold him and say hey please resize your terminal
um
yeah and now we can basically whatever i type here will be uh will be done on the other side
as well so we can do we can start using vim and we can start implementing our python code together
so i can type and he can take over and he can type again he can type as well pretty cool and since
this is only some bytes of of of text being sent over the wire this is absolutely fast and instantaneous
all right um where's my keynote thing
thank you so much questions
yeah yeah it's on my system he's he's doing ssh into my machine and then he's attaching to the
vmax session and we are working on exactly the same file
questions so what was power line oh yes sorry
i assume it's that no no this this is tmax this is uh something that i have configured my tmax to do
power line is this thing below here so um yeah it shows you it gives you a graphical feedback
if i'm in insert mode it's blue if i'm in select mode it's orange yeah it's it's it's just helpful
usually it's like when i come back from from from lunch break i can't remember oh where did i left it
was it was i in insert mode or was i in select mode so i always press control c to go or press escape
to to go back into the other mode but maybe i just want to be in insert mode and i come back
oh i'm in insert mode i i can go i can go on typing i have some of the things that you've got
in store but i don't have some of the other cool things you've got um uh where are you going to
share all this information yeah um i have it on on my github repository very long url
github that's github slash mbroch and then you will find my
vim as a python ide talk and yeah
no my dot files is a different repository but yeah of course
yeah i will um i will export them as pdf and upload what is the best what is the best service
to upload and share slides slide share speaker deck no okay speaker deck
uh fun github
the pdf you mean yeah just check out github okay yeah i will do that as well
pardon hey i i i just started using vim last year i i i still have to get deeper you know
maybe next year i will give a talk about uh creating slides with la la la leitec okay
um
uh thank you very much