It's my great joy to introduce Daniel Schmockenberger to you all.
Daniel is a wonderful polymath, really extraordinary public speaker who is the head of the Civilization
Research Institute and co-founder of the Conciliance Project and is probably, this is kind of the
personal story, there's two people in the last five years of my life that have really
dramatically shifted my world view, my spirituality, etc., and of people living, of living people
I would say that Daniel and Robin Wall Kimmerer, who are brave and sweet grass, have been
the two kind of major ships for me and have greatly not only shifted my view of the world
and what we need to be doing in it, but also have really grounded me spiritually, have
shifted my kind of heart sense of how to relate.
And so obviously Daniel and I have met once before, but anytime I get to see Daniel, it's
just a joy to bring him in and a joy to introduce him to the Quaker Earth Care Witness community,
all others.
So QEW is an organization, a Quaker organization that focuses on Earth Care concerns, we're
a global network, and we're really excited to bring Daniel in here today to talk about
a civilizational rite of passage, and obviously a rite of passage is something you don't know
what the end of it is, you don't know if we're going to make it, if we're not going to make
it, but what you can do is you can be faithful in the process, you can be true in the process.
And I think that this being true is something that Daniel often refers to as deep earnestness.
And so we're going to sort of investigate today some of what Daniel calls the metacrisis.
It's a term that's kind of thrown in a number of sort of sense-making communities that are
working on these large big picture topics, and how seeing that metacrisis coming under
the weight of that, how we can respond to it in a powerful and spiritual way.
So with that, I just want to, those are my opening comments, and I just want to invite
Daniel, do you have anything you want to share before we kind of dive in?
My mom went to a friend's school when she was a kid and always spoke very highly of
her experience and had a mentor for a while when I was a kid named Dr. Everett Slumis.
He was one of the kind of pioneers of natural medicine in the West and got to live on a
health retreat that he had when I was young, and he was a Quaker.
And so I have not got to experience Quaker community very much myself, but I have very
positive associations.
And so it was cool when you told me about this.
And if my schedule is not overful with the timely things we're working on, I would have
joined you for the whole day because I like the tone of what you shared with me that you're
exploring here together, the spirituality that is in service of ecology, life, well,
deep earnestness and deep humility.
So being that you've had a full day and I haven't had all that, I hope that this weaves.
And I'm just happy to be here.
And I also said yes to coming just because of the way that in our limited interaction,
talking once, but also just the way I've seen you post online is clear that you are a very
caring, thoughtful, earnest person.
And I, yeah, I like to support activities and people like that.
Yeah, I think Daniel, some of the people in our community have probably heard me say things
like humanity has reached a point where we've become too powerful to remain in rivalry with
ourselves.
And that, you know, the problem is that we have a profound gap between our capacities as a
species and the wisdom that guides them.
And I would say that of everyone I attribute that sort of framing to, it's you.
And I think that the beauty of the really extraordinary thing is that you bring out that
framing, not just as a way to understand our own times and what needs to be done in them, but
also as a way of understanding of how we got here.
How did a species that clearly does not want to destroy its own climate do that collectively,
nonetheless, right?
How is it that collective decisions that no one would want end up becoming, you know, almost
unavoidable, like the momentum is so extraordinary that nothing can seem to overcome it.
And so if we can kind of talk about that and talk about its relation, this is what Daniel calls
the metacrisis and talk about how that relates to our understanding of history.
I just want to open that, open that to you.
What is the metacrisis and where are we in that?
Yeah, I just share in starting that in general, I don't like talking about this publicly,
because it's mostly not empowering and just kind of despair causing uselessly.
I mostly talk about it to institutions and flancer pests and whatever where there is
something they can do and try to tailor it to what they they can do.
It's not that there isn't any way we can relate to it more effectively.
You come to understand the whole picture more.
We it's devastating before it's empowering, it can be motivating and ennobling, but it also the
analysis shows that most of the things that one could be hopeful about work.
And so there is like a there's a lot of faith actually required to want to engage with that in
a meaningful way because you have to go through a kind of crucible to come out on the other end
in some way empowered.
And I think if it I think it's because there's a spiritual practice and a community holding
each other here that I feel okay talking about it.
You're mentioning climate change and you know this kind of obligate nature.
The first paper on scientific paper on climate change was published in 1938.
The United Nations Environmental Programme recognizing the need for international coordination
on global commons issues was made in 1972 well over 50 years ago.
And climate change has become one of the biggest existential risk topics in the world.
It has over a trillion dollars a year in climate funding.
And every with the exception of global recessions every single year we use more fossil fuels
in the year before.
And during that whole time all of the solar wind renewable energy all the hydro and the damaging
effect of the dams and all of the nuclear and the entire risk of the nuclear energy hasn't even
slowed the increase in fossil fuels use one year.
And so when you look at and yet the most fascinating thing is there is literally no one
who wants climate change as like a strategic objective.
There I mean yes you can say that the Russians are capitalizing on the fact that they get a
new shipping route through the Arctic.
But no one has climate change as an objective and yet nobody can stop it.
Because everybody wants energy because energy is one for one course
related with GDP and this ability to actuate anything and money has to exponentially grow
every year to keep up with the interest which means that the energy demand has to exponentially
grow every year.
And the solar plant is going to take 10 years worth of the energy that it produces out of
fossil fuel energy to make up front.
And then we don't decide to make less fossil fuel energy it's we just make all of the stuff in
which there is energy return on energy investment.
While there are plenty of groups that don't care enough about species extinction nobody
really wants species extinction and nobody really wants
PFOS in literally every raindrop in the world which it is now.
As an ubiquitous carcinogen and stuff or
there's 230 million chemicals in the American Chemical Society database almost all of them
are toxic cancels, antigens, endocrine disruptors whatever.
The curve of the increasing autoimmune diseases, the increasing autism, the increasing
Alzheimer's, the increasing psychiatric diseases follows the curve of those chemicals
and nobody wants a toxic planet and also nobody can stop it.
And the total set of all activities that has been done since Silent Spring was written
since the environmental movement started we have put more toxic chemicals each year into
the environment than the year before and innovated more new ones.
And it's not just that the processes have been ineffective it's that many of them have made
things worse right that if we say okay because of climate change and fossil fuel use we really
need to push non-fossil fuel energy so we push more nuclear and so now we get increased risk of
warfare associated with nuclear and toxic waste and etc and it doesn't slow fossil fuels and
then you do more dams and so you destroy more ecosystems and create more geopolitical tensions
between the countries that share the river it's typically the case that the way that we go about
solving the problems doesn't work and makes them worse and I didn't have that analysis when I was
young and started and was kind of like hopeful that we could just put more energy into the things.
So why? Like why is this? I would also say when you were talking you mentioned that
there are certain kind of like principles that come from conscience that were things people
could choose before but they're obligate now because self-termination on this path is the
otherwise impending possibility. I wouldn't even say that they were possible before they were impossible
because if you held a set of views that did not mount effective military forces and Genghis Khan
and his men or Alexander the Great or the Ottomans or whatever were coming you were slaughtered.
And there have been a lot of peaceful beautiful cultures throughout history that listened to their
conscience and got slaughtered. We just did an analysis of this on you know the history of
selection via warfare and you know Genghis Khan and his men alone in his life not the entire
Mongols killed 50 million people on horseback without nuclear weapons without industrial weapons
killed 50 million people. That was 11% of the entire global population
including lots of lovely cultures that because they were lovelier didn't mount huge militaries
and
fascinatingly it's actually a really just weird irony that the current estimate is that 11% of
all Asians today are Genghis Khan's descendants because the amount of rape that he and then the
genetics of that family did so kill the people do all the raving. So
and then when you look at that for
Dutch colonization in the Congo and Attila and blah blah blah you realize that we alive today
are the descendants memetically and genetically of the most successful conkers
and that the Tibetans could keep a relatively nice set of ideas as long as they were remote
enough that nobody cared about their land that much and as soon as it became clear that they
controlled the watershed between two billion person populations uh then a violent culture
slaughtered them and the same with the Native Americans and the colonizers here the the population
of North and South America before colonizers came was 140 million people and colonization
wiped out over 90% of them that's it that's a lot of people and that means those those ways of being
those those non-alphabetic languages those non-written languages those systems of medicine
those poetries those all of that you know wiped out of history so I don't think it was possible
like an individual could try to be lovely and the tribe could try to be lovely but you didn't
actually make it through history that way and you most certainly didn't shape the world very much that
way and so this topic of the you know kind of a multipolar trap somebody does something that provides
so much near-term competitive advantage that everyone else is obligated to do that or lose
and lose means your ideas don't make it through selection that has been an amazingly powerful
part of a very perverse selection process and this is still the case and this is why open AI that
was founded to because of the fear of market-driven AI and the need to make a very well-funded
research institute to focus on slowing down market AI risk became the company like switched
from a non-profit to a for-profit and accelerate AI risk more than any and it's why then
seeing that that was happening and saying it was bad a part of open AI broke off created
anthropic to really do AI risk work and then realized that in order to do that they needed
a lot of money to have big AI systems they took the money became a for-profit and now are also racing
and so again what that happened is pretty much everyone got into the multipolar trap of
the dude with more power wins there is no way out of this and unless you want to just die with
dignity you okay we have to win and we have to do whatever violent etc thing is going to let us
win but then we'll be the good guys and this is basically the state of geopolitics between
us and china right now and many many places so in that way ethics are constraints on strategic
possibilities and those who have less of them have less constraints and those win at strategy
and so one cannot afford to have them right which is why there are so many
real politic theorists to basically say if you have any ethics you're an asshole
because what you're actually saying is that you don't care about anything enough to be effective
yeah and if you really want to be effective you have to win and you got to do what it takes
so if you care you'll be you know you'll you'll do the Machiavellian thing which is such a weird
you know basically it's what happened to Soromon and Lord of the Rings right it's what happens
again and again power winning is inevitable and therefore embracing it is actually ethical
because it's your only way to influence it and so that's the co-opting of the ethics right
but what's the other choice so there's a way in which just choosing to die with dignity well
we'll be ethical our hands will be clean while the world burns yeah um and if you look at the history
the Jane Goodall's of the world have not had the level of influence on the world system the
Kissingers have had not by a billion to one and the minds and heart the the developmental process
that makes a Jane Goodall does not give you Kissinger skills the developmental process
that gives you Kissinger skills does not give you Jane Goodall values they are almost developmentally
mutually exclusive yeah and yet we don't make it if we don't actually get both of those in
the same beings now but where those skills are not in service to power and the perpetuation
of the system but are in service to all sentience now and into perpetuity but that's that hard in
that mind together right in the same beings and yeah so right now we obviously you know
you know the crossed six of the nine planetary boundaries radically rapidly crossing the other
ones all of the curves are accelerating if we tried to turn it around it's not even clear that we
could um nobody really understands and obviously the the post-war order that maintained relative
peace between superpowers meaning we only proxy ward through korean vietnam and whatever other
places and economic warfare and etc that has completely broken down that kind of post-war
order is not uh effective anymore at preventing major power conflict and so we can see that we
have multiple three world war three escalation pathways hot right now which is why the atomic
scientists moved the nuclear clock closer to midnight than it was during the cuba missile crisis
and we see actually an increase in hawkishness everywhere and
if you look at just even the rate of say ai and the reason that ai is so important more than
any other category of tech it's because i can i can't use a nuclear weapon to make a bio weapon
i can't use a nuclear weapons to make a financial system i can't use a bio weapon to make a financial
system i can use ai to make better nukes and better bio weapons and better financial systems and
better manufacturing and better propaganda so the race there the you know more's law was completely
unprecedented in history being doubling the computing power every two years
but every 18 months so you get an exponential curve currently just the hardware alone on gpu's
is 10 xing the compute efficiency every six months not to mention that you also have an
exponential curve on the software on the amount of data on the parameters and so every and this
is why there's you know been about 30 trillion just invested in the last couple years trillion
to win ai supremacy as the ring to rule them all and nobody who thinks they can win has any
interest in multilateral agreements to slow it down so you could say these are times that were
prophesied you could say that the end of kali yuga and the beginning of the possible beginning of
satyuga you could say the time of purgatory or the end of the mayan calendar or whatever we're all
roughly speaking to a similar thing and you could say that once you got the written word
so you got history you know like a more kind of formal version of history
it wasn't that hard for philosophers of the time to recognize that with populations increasing
the wars killed more people because the number of people that gang is conkilled was more than
the entire world population at the beginning of the agricultural revolution like just to have a
sense right so with the increasing population killed more people with the increasing technology
we killed more people from further distance right you get the crossbow you get the cannon you get
the fowlings you get the and it's pretty clear to see that humans were not very good stewards of
their power right every culture had class subjugation torture or whatever once we got into empire not
pre-empire um and so the idea that we have that kind of mixed bag of some really lovely stuff
but really wicked stuff but that the wicked stuff is getting larger populations with more tech
and the wars are killing more people and we're like early civilizations were destroyed because of
environmental overshoot right if you read tainter in the collapse of complex civilizations you can
see that cutting down all the trees eroding the topsoil and the civilization fails has been
happening for thousands of years so um but obviously with the capacity to destroy environments at
larger scale you know the beginning of big belly ships and greater fishing and blah blah blah uh
so you could prophesize hey this time is going to come to an end there's going to be a great
reckoning the wickedness of our ways is going to have to be reconciled there's going to be a hard
fork and either everybody decides we stop this kind of wickedness of our ways we become good
stewards of power and as such as good stewards of power we reinstate the garden or something
like that or we don't and it goes from purgatory to hell some to an end uh because this thing self
terminates i i think those prophecies were pretty straightforward actually like pretty
straightforwardly accurate and i do think we are at a time now where until nuclear weapons that
couldn't have been you couldn't destroy everything that quickly obviously until industrial scale
globalization you couldn't destroy the environment so uh we're really to the first time in the history
of the world at this place where the ongoing viability of the world is up to us we couldn't
have destroyed it before even when we tried and so it is it is true that it is obligate for us to
become good stewards of power because if we continue to steward it the way we have we'll destroy
ourselves it is also true that some people doing that not in the presence of other people doing
it lose the game of influence if not the game of survival in the very short term to be able to make
it through there's a book of romans the path to heaven is narrow and steep the path to hell is
wide and many there is something like that there there is basically a needle that has to be thread
and that is the uh hope for this time is the ability to properly thread the needle of
that which will make us good stewards of power that can also navigate the space of power currently
to influence it enough that it on its current trajectory doesn't mess everything up
well i think that you know i want to talk a bit more about threading that needle
and in particular it's become pretty clear to me in my study of you know when in academia we would
call collective action problems or social traps which is what daniel just called the multi-polar
trap that situation where you know vying geopolitical entities seek power and that the only way to get
around this like i actually came to that realization at some level when i took western political
philosophy too and i was reading thomas hobs and hobs you know has that war at all against all and
i think that there's a lot of people in this room probably thinking well aren't there cooperative
forces not just competitive forces and human history as well as an evolution i think that's a
really valid argument maybe we'll come back to that but i want to talk about you know there's two
kind of ways to get around a collective action problem and one of them is what hobs refer to
as the little viathon which is you get enough power and you impose power and you make it so
anyone who would do something that's not good you know that's competitive and trying to do the power
gain you shut them down that's way one and the other way is through cooperation and that one's
really hard i mean if anyone is you know folks who might have started the eco village or something
like that in this talk and even getting just a few people to get along is hard right so we might
come back to that but i think that what is really insightful here is that um we have to at some level
through conscience through without ever getting you know you know as soon as you start down that road
once you start down the dark path right through conscience we gain influence through conscience
we have to at some level push in the same way that donby or others would have done you had
extraordinary influence but you know he gained that influence not by being a really terrible
player on the world stage but by acting in a conscientious way because we're a social species
and we respond you know we we have a an immediate response to you know a mirror neuron type response
if you're if you are acting a certain way i i feel that in my own self and and so there's a way in
which um i just i guess i guess i wanted to talk to that a bit daniel do you see um that sort of
path of like uniting conscience with um with uh i hate to call it spirit with strategy but i really
you know maybe emphasis on the conscience part and then the strategy part has to be born of that
right has to be born from the conscience piece um and then moving from there do you think that
there's a pathway to thread that needle through the force of conscience through um prophetic voice
now as a kid i was my mom was taking me to a bunch of protests and
um you know various nonprofits pita and greenpeace and like that engage in an activism work
i remember there was a few NGOs that came together to protest a nuclear waste dump being created
and i got to see how the activists were organizing and i got to see how the
nuclear and financial and legal entities on the other side were organizing a little bit just
watching as a kid and there was this insight that came the the first level of the insight was the
the activists are obviously motivated by something that is much less self-interest
they're chaining themselves to things where they get hurt um they're willing to go to jail they're
but their tools of strategy are chaining themselves to things and picket signs and like that
and the tools of strategy on the other side are employing heaps of mathematicians and physicists
and chemists and lobbyists and financiers and etc and it's just it's so obvious who's winning
and you know like who's going to win and why but also who should right that distinction and i saw it as
like a head heart divide at the level of humanity that had to be unified and then i looked a little
bit later and thought of it as like a a head heart will um because i could see people where
there if any two of the three didn't work right if someone had a lot of will and a lot of
heart meaning like there was a lot of care about other beings and the willingness to take a lot of
action but they didn't understand strategy well they were most activists if they could think about
the complexity of the world well and the perverse incentives of financial motivations the lobbying
on the other side etc and they cared a lot but they didn't have a lot of empowerment they were like
kind of broken devastated liberal academics um if the heart was kind of shut down and they were
mostly pursuing self-interest but they understood strategy and they were pretty empowered with
will they were the people who ran the world and ran big oil companies and finance companies and
military industrial companies and things like that and um so it was very clear that those coming
together was necessary kind of requisite right and it is obvious that the strategy does not actually
pick what is valuable it figures out how to do effective work towards what is valuable that
comes from deeper places and so uh intellect and strategy in service of conscience is necessary
right like there's no uh conscience that doesn't know how to be very effective
is kind of a death with dignity strategy um and you know for me seeing that and being like
if I work my ass off and all the animals are still in the factory farm I don't feel okay about that
I don't feel some self-relief I don't feel proud like I I want to be effective at it and so
a lot of people talk about not caring about the result as much but the process because in the
when one over focuses on results they can go out of integrity I care about the relationship between
the results and the process both right um now if you one other thing though is like let's say you
take a look at Gandhi which is you know as good an exemplars you could get of this
if you do a realism analysis right the kind of political school of realism coming out of
real politic analysis of non-violence movements you get a very different perspective than the
story the non-violence movements tell and I think it is a more historically and politically accurate
one and it's important to understand if you want to be effective the realist analysis is
Gandhi said that what happened with the British and India could have worked against Hitler
total gibberish like complete obvious total gibberish um and
in the only reason there were a few but the reason why at that particular time in India
that was able to work is because as he said early in the career in his career there 20,000 British
soldiers cannot rule 400 million Indians if the 400 million Indians don't consent they were already
getting to the place of the willingness to have enough of their people die to violently kill all
of the 20,000 soldiers there was a violence movement that he was holding at bay with the
non-violence which is why they didn't kill him and every non-violence movement that has been
effective against very against powers that are willing to enact violence has only been effective
when it was the better alternative against violence as the alternative and a very similar
thing was that in the assessment that so like if they'd killed Gandhi then the Indians would
have started killing British soldiers at scale right the only reason he didn't get killed and
so it's just important to understand that the reason that the US went ahead and made some
provisions with Martin Luther King was because the power Malcolm X and the Black Panthers were
getting a scaring the shit out of them and the idea of move the attention over here to the
non-violence thing was like positive so the reason I bring this up is because if you want to look at
previous precedents of things that were successful to be able to try to do successful work do your
research well enough to say was it actually successful and how did it work so that's really
powerful Daniel and I still you know sitting here I have a pretty deep conviction about
using moving from a place of conscience to to shift the world in a better way and I think
that conscience calls us to strategy I think that if we're really deeply in touch with conscience
we do the strategy because we actually don't want to live in a world where what's happening in
factory farms is happening in factory farms and we want to live in a world which is beautiful and
hopeful I think a one step beyond the three part will art mine the chakras are a lovely system
right if you I don't know if people here are familiar with it but the you know the yogic
system and the egyptian system the chinese system are pretty similar so whenever there's a bunch of
independent origination it's kind of interesting but each of them are different are thought of as
different types of intelligence and that a full human approach is all of them and so if you
I don't need to go through them here and take the time for it but if you are to think about
to it we want to engage not with a part of the world but all of the world but we want to engage
with all of the world with all of our self right and all of our self means all of our agency and
all of our intellect all of our intuition all of our instinct all of those things in service of
all the world so I think there was a talk that I really liked that Eckhart and the Dalai Lama
did together one time where Eckhart was saying something about like in his language when you
access the power of now you have increased coherence for capabilities at whatever it is that you're
going to do and then somebody in the audience asked something about when you access that is
it like accessing the Akashic records where you can just get anything and do anything
and Eckhart was like I don't have that experience because like a great soccer player
who gets quiet and goes into a place of stillness comes out and does the
the free kick better than he would have otherwise but he's like if I went to do that I still wouldn't
make the goal as Eckhart right he's like I don't I don't do that thing well when Einstein would go
into silence he'd come out with math but Eckhart was like I never get math like I never get
general relativity coming out of there and he asked the Dalai Lama he's like no I don't ever
get general relativity because I didn't take that in and the same reason that when someone goes
deeply into prayer they usually get answers in languages they speak they usually don't get them
in Sanskrit or Mandarin or some language they don't speak so there's a place where listening
to conscience it can only tell you things that you have also cultivated your being to understand
so this is where the the models of what does it take to be effective such that you develop those
in yourself such that as you're going into prayer and going into listening those languages exist
within you to be spoken to is also important yeah well I feel like we've gone really deep
and I think that I can imagine folks in the audience right now being like that is a harsh
view of human history or of what we're what we're up against I suppose and the strategies that might
work or approaches that might work and I mean I feel like I want to sort of finish out by
sort of entering some of that stillness together and wondering if there's in particular a message to
the QEW community to Quakers that you feel you know you were just mentioning you know like
Einstein comes out with this what is the unique role of faith communities in this time
and and what would what is the earnestness I don't know how many people here saw
when this pope got put in place and he wrote the Lodato si encyclical
if you saw it awesome if not it's really worth reading it's actually very beautiful and
basically what he said was and I'm grossly paraphrasing there's been this kind of
forever conversation or debate about is God transcendent beyond the creation or eminent
indwelling within the creation I would say that the error in the direction of an overemphasis on
transcendent over eminent has caused a lot of problems because we can destroy things here in a
holy war for going to heaven or for good reincarnation or for getting off the wheel or whatever it is
that makes that denies some of the sacredness of here and if you hold the creator indwells
within its creation and any harm against creation is sin against the creator uh there's a much safer
ethics that emerges so if you take the direction of eminence and basically what he said in the
Lodato si is the eminence matters and that if you aren't an environmentalist protecting God's creation
you aren't a Catholic now of course that was a fucking big deal to say like a God created all
of this thing this is all sacred if you are harming God's creation you're in sin that doesn't mean
that really changed anything because like so often would happen in something like Catholicism it's
kind of like easy to moralize people while not actually changing the things that dispose their
beliefs and behaviors and so what I would love to see follow is a okay what would it take then
the Vatican to leverage its resources to say how do we help people deepen their understanding
of nature their connection to it and change the perverse incentives that force you know
environmental harm and things like that that'd be amazing I think all the faith communities have
beliefs that could be emphasized you know like there are some Christians who focus on the wrath
of the Leviticus God and the reasons to kill someone for violating the Sabbath or who focus
on the forgiveness of Jesus and let he who has no sins cast the first stone you can kind of
emphasize different aspects of it I think most of the faiths have things that if they were emphasized
would be profoundly relevant to the situation today and when it comes to Quakers
I don't I don't know I would need to ask a lot of questions and spend some time
and to be very interested in but the you know there's like the starting place is
if
total global Quakers is a few hundred thousand right yeah probably yeah and
so if we were to say that well that's a small population in one way it's a lot of people
like a lot of people that have a some shared sense of what is meaningful sacred etc that
they're willing to obviously live their lives differently based on make some sacrifices based on
if they could come to understand the state of the world more rather than just kind of local issues
understand you know the metacrisis the drivers and what addressing that would take and have
their life as a group not just individually be coordinated in service of helping the world move
through this point in history
not to the direction of self-destruction or totalizing dystopias but in the direction of
you know something like reinstatement of a garden what would it mean for that to actually become
the timely imperative of Quakers as a whole that they could coordinate towards that'd be very interesting
yeah well I think it's actually we're almost perfectly on track I want to kind of transition at the 45-minute mark
since our opening worship to bring in some questions from the audience and do you want to ask your question
yeah um yeah so in humanity's phase shift which is what Keith the video that a lot of us watched before
coming to hear you today Daniel um you said that reconditioning our felt sense of
interconnectedness with everything um won't won't be easy and will require a fundamental shift of our consciousness
um and I thought that the ways you the three things that you offered as ways to reconnect were
we're humorous and I wanted to ask how that has changed but the three things you offered were
to be in nature, do psychedelics and have more intimate relationships with more people
and so how have your modes of reconnection changed in the last five years since that conversation in that video?
first I'll say um there's a woman named Vanessa Andreade she wrote a beautiful book called
Hospicing Modernity and I got to speak with recently um indigenous woman who's actually a
leading some amazing educational projects in Canada and we just talked and she told me that the way that her
chief defines colonialism and I thought this was very beautiful uh had nothing to do with taking other people's land or
violence or property ownership or whatever that those were all epiphenomenon that the heart of colonialism
is believing there are separable things
and deeper than believing that is perceiving the world as separable things the pattern of perception cultivated
and
that
that conditioning of mind
I don't think can avoid
creating more separation more externalities more rivalry in the process of everything it does
intrinsic to the nature of how it perceives and as a result in how it sense makes and what it does
so
and that's not intrinsic to the nature of mind it's intrinsic to the way that
most modern civilizations have cultivated mind
and so uh cultivating and
you know
David Bohm and Krishna Murthy and so many said something almost identical about what the root of all the problems is
so
at the basis having a
perception
where you don't see things as separate things that you label in words with a
packet of information
that is fairly static about what that thing is
you um
you have unmediated contact with reality not mediated through words and concepts
that increases the depth of your sensing because your sense making can't be better than your sensing is and most of the time
we were perceiving so shallowly so little of the total bandwidth of the thing and then our sense making is almost all based on abstractions
and the abstraction that the the world of our ideas of what a tree is and what everything is is not the world it's a simulation
and so we live in that simulation on the world so the ability to have much
deeper sensing that is not mediated through word and concept
where the interconnectedness of everything is intrinsic and the uniqueness of everything is intrinsic both
uh
I would say it's only from there all you know what you're calling conscience internally
in a
reality
that is
where there's no separation
there's no separability I can say i'm a separate thing but take plants away and I don't exist take the gravitational field away
I don't exist take the sun away I don't exist so the concept of me as a separable thing is nonsense because it depends
I depend on a lot of things that are outside of the definition of me
in that inseparable nature of reality
listening within and listening without are both kind of the same
I mean they're both valuable they're they have different qualities so
meditating and listen and
being still and listening internally
in different ways to the sensations in my body to the emotions
to
subtle intuition
is all very important
really deeply witnessing
nature and really deeply witnessing people and listening is just as important as another kind of prayer
So I I find conscience and spirit distributed everywhere right because there's nothing in which spirit is not indwelling
so
that mode of perception
the interconnectedness the uniqueness of everything and really being with the
instantiated details fully
is the only mode of mind from which strategies about how to make things better are rightly grounded I feel
How do you cultivate that I mean I think we could raise children in a way where that was the default state
We don't but I think that's a possible thing
for
people who
Have already been conditioned to see everything as separate things and are having to recondition that
Yeah, I think
time not just in nature but in wilderness particularly if you can get an old growth
Right where you can because a young forest does not have the complexity that's been clear cut and regrown with a few species of tree
Does not have the complexity of an old growth forest doesn't do the same thing if you can get
deep into wilderness and spend enough time there and enough silence
um
A tremendous amount of transformation in your mind and being starts to happen
And a tremendous amount of understanding about things so I think
That's about as good as anything
um
I think you know when I said psychedelics
There are lots of experiences that can induce states that change the nature of perception through
fasting through vision quests through sweat lodges through, you know
Medicines are one of them, but uh
Inducing states in which your perception of reality is experientially very different can help people realize more in a more embodied way
How limited their
perceptional space usually it's
And the thing that I had said then about relationships
Yeah, I think really
uh
deeply loving more
beings really helps
And in really deeply loving them seeking to understand them and imagine what it's like to be them and realize that you don't know
But really try to try to feel what it's like to be other beings
um
Your own ego can't actually imagine what it's like to be other beings
Because it's its own set of things like to really take on what it's like to be them
The part of me that the the aspect of me that can do that is not my identity. It's something deeper than identity
and um
And the pattern of putting myself at the center all the time
Is very transcended in that process
There's a bunch of other things for this a few
Um, so the next question we have is from hogan williams
So i'm someone who's deeply concerned about the sense-making crisis aspect of all of this
Addressing sense-making seems to call for humility listening and slow process
Yet addressing existential risk
seems to call for boldness
prophetic speech
and action
over contemplation
At least that would be one way to slice it. You may deconstruct that
It seems that if we have one without the other we are likely lost
Yet they seem so different as to be working at cross purposes
Can you speak to this tension between contemplation and boldness?
These divergent approaches and how might wisely weave them?
Yeah, totally. Um
Everybody's familiar with the dunning kruger curve
Uh this idea and sociology i'll explain it that
When someone doesn't know anything about a field
They can actually have a lot of unearned confidence in their ideas about the space because they're not aware of how much stuff
they don't know
and
Then as they start to study the field they their confidence drops radically because
All the things that were in the unknown unknown for them move into the known unknown. They're like shit. There's so much stuff
I don't know and so
It is common that people who have
Much less depth of thought have more confidence on a topic and people have more confidence
Understand how complex the thing is the idea of the dunning kruger curve as you start here
And then as you gain more knowledge you drop and then you slowly kind of come back up as you gain expertise
what I find
is
in
Trying to not study a specialty where I can eventually know most of the field I got my phd and it whatever but
In trying to study the nature of reality and trying to study how to make a big difference in the world
My uh
Sense of how much I know just keeps dropping forever the more I
The more I learn the more things i'm aware really matter that I don't know continuously so um
Uh, I don't I don't think you ever end up getting something like a similar type of confidence
I think what you get is a place where
You understand a topic well enough to know that your best ideas might not only be wrong but even harmful
And yet you're pretty clear that your assessment is factoring more things than the other assessments that are currently running the world
And so there's an obligation to start to act but not with confidence more with like
a
Sacred obligation that
Feels
It doesn't feel like egoic a empowered agency. Fuck I got this. I know what to do. I'm gonna go solve this thing
I'm gonna crusade doesn't feel like that. It feels like really fucking scared to fuck stuff up
And really continuously listening
um and
So
That's my sense is that if you are trying to address nuclear risk
Or ai risk or whatever and you proceed confidently you'll almost certainly make it worse
Which is almost always the case
So you want if you don't have good sense making about the cause of the issues and how
The nature of what you I mean
Classically
It's not just you can optimize for a project and end up externalizing harmels or what happens all the time
It's things like you create a movement the movement becomes very effective
But it appeals to some people and actually anti appeals to other people
So you drive the counter movement. It's called schismogenesis
and so
Uh
Has the like racial justice movement enlightened everybody
No, the anti woke
culture actually emerged as a counter response to the nature of how kind of
woke social justice moved forward
and
Every time the way that reparations were talked about
Uh was expressed that did not do good sense making about how that would appeal to everybody a lot more people joined the far
Are alt right and things like that so
um
if you
Want to actually make things better in the death hing it says uh
The master navigates the world as careful as one walking on black ice
And what I like about that so much is if you're walking on black ice
You don't have to want to split your head open just the the tiniest lapse of awareness and you can split your head open
And so recognizing that navigating the world is like walking on black ice, especially if you try to do things at scale
But it also doesn't say the master stays at home because there's black ice. He's navigating the world
But it is full and it's not full of fearfulness. It's full of carefulness the depth of care
Yes
Yeah, so I think we've got one last one from the folks who wrote any questions and then we've got um
Uh all I think seven six hands raised hands raised so hopefully we can get to everybody. Um
I want to turn finally to Pamela Haynes Pamela. Do you want to unmute and ask your question?
Sure. Yeah, thank you. I think that some of my question got answered by your response to mich and
um
Keith's suggestion that people speak that you speak to hope in response to everything. I'll just leave that part of it out
So my question is really simple and it's what do you love?
And I can't answer that very well
um
Because it because it is definitely beyond words
I I love reality
And all of the unique expressions
Um
If you like if you were to ask what motivates
My work like what I'm working for I'm not working for the end of
AI arms races or nuclear races or to get the chemicals out of the ocean or like
I mean, yes, those are specific things, but um
I
I close my eyes I meditate and I
see
kids
playing in the future
I see them and I see through their eyes and I see them learning to climb a tree for the first time and loving trees
I see them falling in love for the first time. I see them doing aw at sunsets
I see the mom falling in love with them. I see them learning to communicate with animals
And just that that gets to continue is what I love and I'm in service to
All the rest is complicated strategy in service to that
And for the non-human world as much as the human world
Daniel film
Daniel brilliant presentation
I'm a scholar of the relationship between the sciences and the world's religious and spiritual traditions
From that perspective, it struck me. It's really interesting the the pattern or the formal analysis of your presentation
Which is you gave us the facts the situations the background
You gave us the the practices that people engage in psychedelics meditation and so forth
You brought those two right next to each other
Keith and I and many people on this call engage in a kind of reflection right there at that meeting point of the two
You engage in almost no reflection at that particular point. You spoke of actions
and facts
wishes visions
But surely there's a kind of reflection
That is right at that intersection
I have the intuition that you'd be able to help us
If you sort of open up the doors to that particular room, I'm interested to see how you respond to that invitation
Yeah, you mean specifically at the intersection of something like
the sciences and spirituality
Right, which is a kind of self-involving intersection
You often answer like a religious studies scholar, which is what my tribe does and describes externally
powerful internal experiences
But there's a kind of internally driven reflection that stems from the motivation or the psychedelic experiences
And you're surprisingly silent at that that intersection point
The um when I when I was growing up I was um homeschooled and I
studied
I had a
Got to make my own curriculum didn't have a fixed curriculum and
The kind of braid of topics of interest was all the sciences all of the kind of spiritual mystical traditions
and philosophic traditions
and um
And then also the kind of all the domains of uh activism
And they all felt like the exact same thing to me. I had the same
And
And particularly because at that time growing up in the 80s
And what just a fortune of getting exposed to like my exposure to science was first fritchoff capra and david boom and
Like the whole idea that something at the nature of ecology and complexity science and quantum mechanics would reveal the perennial
truths of the spiritual traditions and things like that
So I didn't get science as kind of reductionist atheism first. I got the critique of that first
and um
There's a
Paper I wrote maybe Keith will share it with people called
The dance of the dow and the 10,000 things
and because you know
The dow that is nameable is not the eternal dow
Naming is the beginning of the 10,000 things typically we take it that then
Engagement with the 10,000 things deadens us to the dow
But it doesn't have to it can do the exact opposite right it can actually
Deep in the nature of the appreciation of the dow that's what I meant by the dance between them and uh
so
one of the areas that I really got into was uh limits of no ability
and whether it was kind of girdle and mathematics or the incompleteness theorem or
uh tarski with the limits of formal logic or
um
Heisenberg bell, you know on and on there's these kind of
Pearson semiotics the upper bounds of no ability are ways that logic can transcend itself because it can identify
its formal upper boundaries and then identify how much of reality is outside of it
And then there's the question. Well, what is the right epistemology for that then? What is the right way to relate to it?
Um, so there's like these are some of my favorite topics. There's a lot I could say there
I'm not sure exactly which part of the inquiry is um,
Most interesting and live for you, but it would be a fun conversation
At some point I look forward to that there is a way to speak at precisely that intersection point
Which is not just silence and many of the hundred people on this call are practiced in that
I would love to in in explore that openness
To a form of discourse that was surprisingly silent
Over the last hour. Thanks again for your talk
Yeah, well, that's really lovely film. I really love that invitation. Um, and I hope that connection happens
um
Stan I got Stan's message and I don't know if Stan's here, but he wrote it to me in the chat
So I'm going to go ahead and just read it out. Um, we have you mentioned population collapse and tainter's analysis
Four or five groups of ecologists have estimated that the world can only sustain
Sustainably support three or four billion people at a reasonable standard living i.e. the european standard
Given we are at eight billion now. This is not a small problem
Given this what is your prognosis on collapse or not in the years and decades ahead?
Um prognosis on collapse includes population as one factor but lots of other factors
um
The topic of caring capacity is a very tricky topic
It's very tricky for like so many reasons
Caring capacity meaning how many people can the earth sustainably?
uh support
um
The answer that comes up most commonly is like two three billion
but uh the numbers vary from
500 000 to tens of billions depending upon how people do the analysis
um
Obviously before the industrial revolution
I mean 500 million excuse me before the industrial revolution the population of the planet was 500 million and then
It went from 500 million to
8 billion almost overnight right to 200 years with the haverbosch and such
But as it did that as it's 16 that 16 x would have taken over 200 000 years to get in 200 years
It also increased the resource consumption per capita by about 100 x in the developed world
So that's obviously a 1600 x increase in um resource consumption
How you define it though is
What is the most number of people you can possibly fit on the planet without collapsing the biosphere versus what provides
the highest quality of life for all life including non-humans
um
Mediated through what kind of technologies gets into deep cultural questions of what a desirable good life looks like
And the enactment pathway of getting there
Is super tricky because the conversations almost always turn into eugenics and war and like pretty pretty difficult stuff
um and
If you look at the work of like
Um
I'm forgetting his name right now. It'll come to me in a minute
But you know elan has talked about this
Uh popularly a lot recently which is that um the topic of demographic collapse that the decreasing birth rates in china in particular
but all around the world
are
Going to destroy civilization as we know it not the biosphere because a smaller percentage of young people entering the workforce military force, etc
and a lot of old
people
Is not how civilization is designed to function
um and so
And that's obviously because we built a civilizational system that is incommensurable the biosphere
So the ongoing needs that it has for maintenance like growing gdp and growing population upon which it was predicated don't work with the biosphere so
um
Is population a topic that we have to figure out? Yes, it's a it's a it's a very tricky one
So I don't like to try to say much definitive about it quickly
When china tried to control its population growth
To the one child policy or when india tried to control it
Some of the unintended side effects were things like
over a hundred million too many men
Because they emphasize male children and now you have literally over a hundred million
more men than women that can't mate that are destabilizing civilization and so like
the
You always have the what is the ideal in state you have whose ideal which cultural
ethical
models and then you have the enactment to get there
And well, you know, there's a bunch of libertarian thought that is gibberish one of the libertarian
Questions that is often useful is, you know, think about your utopia
In the future
Think about all the people that don't want it right now that would violently resist it because of their different religious ideas or economic interests or whatever
And think about how much violence you would have to enact to force your utopia on them and ask if it's still utopia
And so the considerations about enactment are very real
I
Know, um, Stan pretty well. I'm sure Stan's got a lot to say particularly
on that topic of
There's a there's a qe w pamphlet critiquing. He's a you know, a demographer
beginning the which college but
Uh, critiquing the the elan analysis. So I'm sure he might want to share at with you afterwards, but I would love I would love to see that analysis
I think it desperately needs critiqued
Yeah
Oh, yeah
Great great job on the geopolitical understanding. Um, I'm really impressed with the depth of your knowledge and the realism of your perspective
I've been following Peter Zion and many other geopolitical thinkers sure many was the one I was about to mention who has been popularizing the demographic collapse
So thanks for mentioning it. That was the name I was forgetting. Yep, and I'm well aware of the mit study of
You know, very they tracked I forgot like six major
Measures and how they would change over the next century
Um, I I was exposed to this at university of colorado boulder while studying geology and economics
in geology is kind of a hotbed of
The counter perspective on a lot of these things because uh, we know the paleo climate very well. We know
My professors have been unerringly accurate about predicting how the climate is going to change
Which goes to say, um, the climate is a lot bigger problem. It's going to cause big migrations all over the place
It's going to change the rules all over the place
Um, the scientific humidity is just not up to the task of conveying news of that magnitude
Especially when the rate of change is faster than a peer review process will allow
So if you passed over the peer review process about five years ago
My question though has to do with the longevity and retirement aspects
because
We live a lot longer
And I remember a discussion at the university of colorado 42 years ago where they talk about how that would fragment our society
um
and
It kind of creates this dynamic to say the emphasis is really going to be on
the government to take charge and
Clear a path for the future
There's kind of limits to what you can do as far as social involvement. Could you speak to that?
How we economically support an increasing growth, uh, elderly population. Is that the main question?
Well, it's that
That there's genetically engineered, uh, pig organs that stands to increase life expectancy another decade or two
Um, you know stem cell inserts is all this technology to say we're going to live increasingly into our hundreds
Roughly some 80 percent of the federal budget is now devoted to retirement in some way or another saving for retirement or retirement itself
And so you're you're you're kind of say if we're going to have a massive social limit to change society
You're at some point going to run head-on into the cost of return the fact that we live longer. Yeah
um
Just having a conversation right before this, um the colleague about the
uh collapsing pensions and
Again realist analysis
everybody
who studies this knows that the
growing debt to gdp ratio is not there's no path to fix it
and the
growing not just debt but deficit spending
um
Also hitting diminishing returns on so many areas of industry because of planetary boundaries coming up climate change and others
means, uh, the imminent break of the economic system as we know it
um
When you mentioned climate and the climate predictions, obviously you look at like the jim Hansen recently said tin celsius is now the most likely scenario
and you look at the
uh
You know fact that the climate sensitivity numbers and some of the best models have went way up and are
like actually being
underreported because not wanting to sound alarmist
but even the un predictions are
billion climate refugees in the next 10 years
and when you look at where they come from
if you look at the Himalayan watershed and
You know India with over a billion people china with over a billion people in pakistan
and then the islamic world backing it with over a billion people on a dwindling water supply where a lot of those
100 million person plus climate migrations will occur all of which are nuclear equipped with massive geopolitical tensions. It's not just like
Some people die from that. It's like disruption of the entire world system. Um
so I think
I think that we don't continue to see business as usual, uh into the
uh
decade ahead
in retirement as a part of that
Yeah, I would just add um north america has a radically different fate than asia
and um north america we don't have these existential problems and we've got oceans to protect us
I mean there's a limited amount of threat you can convey over an ocean
So I want to jump in I just want to make sure that we have um some time
for uh, in particular, I noticed we've had an all men audience uh or question
Asking for so far. So I know we have uh two men and two women left and I want to give precedence to the
To jenny and shelly
So jenny if you would like to ask your question now and then um, we can spin back around
Is um, I it's not particularly a woman's question, but nevertheless I will
I wanted to try to bring us back
to the question that
I'm actually finding it very difficult to articulate so please forgive me
um
The the question of love at the root of of our response to this crisis
and you
So a couple of things one is that I I think that what you were saying earlier daniel
about
One of the one of the primary things that's gone
Gone wrong and I'm a scientist and I've been trying to deal with
the integration of science and spirituality and and technology and economics and the whole thing for many many years so
trying to see the roots of these things is is is um leads you to a place where
You're you're faced with uncertainty and radical humility. So let's start there, but the sense of separation
to me is
allied to
a corresponding faith in our
In justifying justifying our actions, which which um, I I don't really explain that at the moment, but
We are we have a moral ground for our being that co exists with our egotistical power sense and our
um
Our ability to justify what we're doing in terms of violence and so on so I wanted to
ask you about how you see
Love as as a guiding principle for how we can act in this complex world that we're now living in
because
When we talk about our faith tradition as quakers
We're often looking towards our conscience our spirit
And that spirit is also the the the ground of love
for life truth that the truth of our unity
And the and that which guides us into doing action whether or not we really can be certain of the outcome
Does that make some sort of sense? Yeah, totally
um
I don't think we can ever be certain of the outcome right
I I don't think that we shouldn't try to engage in
Uh, you just went away to look at you while you were talking
I guess not so I'm here. There you are. Okay. Um
I
Think that
consequentialist ethics have a role
Where you think through what will provide the greatest good for the greatest many and you try to think through the causal dynamics of it
But uh consequentialist ethics on their own ends up generally making people evil
Because you pretend that you have more certainty about the future state than you possibly can
You identify certain bad things that are inevitable which justifies why you have to do some other bad things because they're less bad
And so the basis of that is actually the excessive
certainty that isn't epistemically warranted, which is why the epistemic humility is so important
So there is a there's a kind of virtue ethic, which is I don't know how the future is going to unfold
There's unpredictable complexity everywhere
But I know that the choices that have the most integrity in the moment put out the kind of ripples that will ripple well
Right, so that's kind of a virtue ethic
There's kind of a utilitarian ethic that tries to think through what is a viable in-state here
What is a viable or at least new homeodynamic state and can I reverse engineer steps? They're both important
right
And then there's something that is kind of deeper than either of those even deeper than the virtue ethic which is
uh
Something like the feeling guidance that comes from deep enough prayer
And again, that's all the aspects of self being involved
As far as love at the basis
I think if anyone really explores why they are motivated to do something
There's it's not purely a rational thing
Because a purely rational thing doesn't actually have motive. It doesn't care, right? Like there are some basis for care
Otherwise it'd be like well, if this doesn't happen then this thing will be harmed
But if I don't care about that thing being harmed who cares, right? So like
in a purely rationalist
Ontology then I'm being nihilistic
So I want to change this because this is horrifying
Because I'm fucking pissed that they're doing this because I'm heartbroken over here. Well, but any of those emotions
I'm heartbroken because there is some these kids lives in Gaza these animals in the factory farm
Are beautiful they're sacred which is why I care
So underneath the heartbreak and underneath the anger and underneath the depression and the devastation underneath all of the sense of
Injustice is actually love because if I didn't find some reality
beautiful
That I loved there would be no basis for the other emotions
So that the idea that all of the other emotions are actually responses to love to care
Then you recognize the anger the sadness the depression the anxiety are all actually sacred
They all have a place but they're not at the source. So you embrace them and then you trace them back to where they come from
When you trace them back to where they come from rather than being angry at who the bad guy is what I love becomes clear
and then
That is actually an even deeper motive and then how
Do I be effective in service of what I love is a clearer focus?
So it's just the deep reflection on what the motivation is and tracing it back to the source
right and I
I agree and I think it's also that
You know love love is one of the most misunderstood words and most
Misunderstood concepts. It's overused and underused all the time
But it's also to me the great attractor what I call the great attractor. So it actually applies to science as well
It's not it's not a it's not a there's not a place where love doesn't exist
In this whole concept, you know, and it can it can be the root of guiding very very practical action
It doesn't have to be something that oh, this is just a feeling state or this is just the way quakers talk or something like that
It's actually the concept of oh total unity. It's a unified consciousness. If you like
Yes
Reminds me of the harmony of the spheres and you know, uh, Daniel has a beautiful talk on emergence that um, if you
Want to look that up on youtube at some point. Daniel talks about something very similar to what you just said, jenny
But um, shelly, I would like to invite you to ask your question
Thank you and I appreciate the opportunity
Daniel, I really um
I learned from I want to take us back to some of the things you said at the beginning your analysis of the different
Factors you you mentioned three different factors that
motivate
individuals and society to and
And determine whether we're effective or not and and as I understood it one of them was
Understanding how the world works and the other has the second has to do with your ethics or whether you care about
The global world or not
And and third was an effective strategy to
Take action
And if I I'm not sure I got that all that right, but if that's
Correct, um
I find that most of the people if not all of them on this on these screens
Are pretty well versed in the first one how to you know, how messed up our world is
And the second one all deeply caring and wanting to make the world a better place
Um, so going beyond their own personal
Satisfaction and needs to wanting to to create a better world
But what we mostly almost all of us fail is we don't know what to do about it
We don't have an effective strategy and I think you've kind of answered
With your answer to jenny, but I wonder if you could reiterate it in another way
So like we all understand
What are the best?
Strategies for us to figure out what is an effective strategy and not just individually
But how can we collectively as a quaker community take action?
Is this being
Posted on the internet
That was the intention, but if you want to cut anything
I don't know. I don't know where you're gonna go, but I we can totally work out whenever
Feels feels good there
Okay
In a different setting I can say more about this
I'll say a couple things
The
Study of effective strategy is different in kind than studying like environmentalism and the fact that the environment's messed up
It because you're studying
How power works and you're studying it not just to critique it but to engage in it
And so that is a very different kind of study
It looks at how is it that corporations are able to lobby governments and put
Corporate agents into regulatory positions to regulate the government and their interests and things like that
and all those critiques of that the
Rotating revolving doors of somebody from big ag or big pharma than running the fda and you know
Or the public private partnership where the private side writes the law that the public side implements
Or the massive subsidies to fairly toxic things that happen because the big companies that have the patents have the money to pay a lot
More lobbyists than the things that are inherently decentralized like regenerative versus conventional agriculture or whatever
There's the way the critical theorist studies this which is basically to just say it's really bad
Like look at all this bad stuff. It's really bad
There there is the way that one studies it from the perspective of
How does
Influence at scale operate? What are the various
Modalities that when the world has changed who changed it and what were the tools they used to change it?
And if
Someone does not
Feel good about using those tools they counter as they have to say do I feel good about letting those who are using the tools currently continue to do it for those goals?
so
Being able to lobby a government for subsidies that ends up affecting
Market dynamics profoundly is something that big corporations are good at and that
Non-profit groups are not good at
Non-profit groups don't study how finance works and how lobbying works and you know those types of things well
Being able to figure out how to write a very complex
Operating agreement for a public-private partnership that has all the fine print to do everything you want for many different government
Jurisdictional bodies are now doing your will is something that the financial sector and various large corporate sectors are very good at and
You know people trying to do good things are not good at
um
and so
If you want effective strategy you have to study effective strategy
And so let's say for instance i'll give a historical example
And it's it's a fake example, but it'll you'll get a sense
Let's say that we had a chance to talk to
The Tibetans before Mao and they did let's say we had a chance to talk to them a couple decades before
They were not studying effective strategy because that was not their jam
That was not what their culture was about right they were doing different things and they were doing lovely things
They obviously did not study that
And the results are also quite obvious
Now
If they were to think about geopolitical strategy for a minute
It would be pretty easy to say oh
There are two billion person populations on either side of a watershed and we are at the source of the watershed
I bet we don't get to stay here
Like it seems pretty obvious that we don't get to stay here one of these sides is going to take the head
Top of the watershed. Also, this is going to be key to the strategic communications and missile defense
so
Geographically the fate is already written that we don't get to stay here
Given that what should we do and either
They would have done something like
Uh, anticipatorily create a partnership with one of the sides
In which they had something unique to offer
They would have left
Or they would have done something like finlanded between the ussr and eu to be in a
Buffer zone
relationship where both sides militarily protected them because of that or like switzerland did to say, you know
all of the international agreements between the two of you were going to be able to host
and
So let's say that
Tibet had realized that 30 years before the kind of rise of Mao and they had went to
The european powers at the time and said look, here's what's going to happen
China's going to get this otherwise
And it's going to help their rise to power that is going to end up threatening you and blah blah blah
And here's why you want to help protect us like offer kind of military legal support protecting us here
And then here's how what we're going to tell india here's what we're going to tell china such that in the same way that nobody
Invaded switzerland because everybody was invested in being able to store their gold and stuff in switzerland because switzerland was thinking about strategy
Then tibet could have done that
This would not have been this would have not arisen from the minds of the tibetan people with the culture they had
It did arise from the minds of some religions like jews, right? They had a different they had a
Different type of spirituality and mind arising that thought about strategy in a different way
So
It's not that there aren't places like tibet that had the same geographical determination that
Did a better job than they did it said it required a different type of mind
And that as as i've mentioned the people who are good at strategy
Are almost always strategy is a military term it gets then gets applied to business and other things, but it is about
Effective achieving of goals which are almost always narrow goals where you externalize costs in the process and against adversaries
right like that's
so
The mind that gets good at strategy
Is almost always co-occurring with something that is self-centered either at the level of the individual the nation state the corporation but not
The commons in all life and perpetuity
When you're thinking about the commons in all life and perpetuity you're not thinking how do I win stuff?
and so
but it's kind of like
let's
Let's take star wars
Let's say there were no sith
right
There wouldn't have to be jedi if there were no sith
Everybody could just be farmers and poets and parents and teachers would be lovely
But if there are sith there must be jedi and the jedi are not trained in farming. They are trained in warfare
protective warfare
right
um not in service of
empire and conquest purely like the white blood cells and immune system
and
So what I would say is if you
Want to be effective
At serving things that you care about in the presence of other groups that are effective at serving the goals they care about
You need to engage in that field of study
The jury
Yeah, what was that?
It's almost as if what you're saying is that
In order to be effective
We need to let go of our ethics
because in order to be effect the way you're most effective is
by being um
self-serving and you know with a narrow focus
So there's a real problem. I'm not saying that
Okay
I'm saying that it is inethical to do something that you know is for sure ineffective
To let
uh
Horror and tragedy and species extinction continue because you aren't willing to engage in effective strategies unethical
we are responsible not just for what we do but what we don't do
and
So there is an ethical responsibility to effectiveness
That doesn't mean you justify any amount of harm in the process. I'm not and that's the tricky thing is that the
The cultures
That
Said okay, we don't want wiped out therefore we have to build a standing military or whatever
We're not the same culture anymore because they had to reinvest things that had went into
Arts and child education and whatever now into military and and those types of things so
The two fail modes that we have to avoid is
Uh a culture that is doing something that is more
Ethical in its goals that just gets destroyed by a more dominant culture. That's a fail mode
Or even if it doesn't get destroyed because no one cares about it because it has no power but it it
Fails to prevent harm in the rest of the world happening
That's a fail mode
and one the other fail mode is that in the aim of
Not being destroyed and being effective. It also becomes a dominated culture
That's also a fail mode
So you can either be destroyed by the machine or become the machine is the answer
So you have to do something that is neither of those
So in learning how to be effective obviously the long-term
Play there is a change of all of the systems that mediate game theory itself
The consciousness and the systems which will look like not capitalism not nation states and not minds that see everything as separate things
But we don't get there if we don't if right now everybody
That is effectively getting lawmakers to write law or doing it in narrow short-term private interests
I would rather environmentalists know how to do the corporate thing as well as the corporate guys do
Or a different set of purposes
Well, of course, I would like to have a government that is not hijackable by anybody's interests
And that has a good collective intelligence guiding it. We obviously don't have that so having
The more inclusive goals be effective in the current dynamics while seeking to upgrade the underlying systemic dynamics
Both have to happen simultaneously
It's a tall order
Yeah, well, thank you for now being effective
At a local level is different because you don't have great power vested interests in the same way
And that's awesome
And I encourage most people to actually feel really good about that as opposed to hopeless about the scale that it's not operating at
And
For those who can't not think about the world at scale and can't not
Endeavour to become more effective at it
It's just a different study
Thank you Daniel for sharing that and
Yeah, I think that a core tenant of quakerism is about is about peace, right?
I'm guessing you might have ran across that, you know, so from the 1650s onward is this sort of
testimony on peace and so
There's much more to endeavor into there, but
And into that so let me give you for instance
Yeah
So the nuclear clock got
Moved closer to midnight
Associated with the escalation in ukraine
Yeah
You have not heard
A good thought on a plausible end game
When you watch the news because there is not one
The there is
On one side a bunch of rhetoric
Like putin is hitler and if he takes part of ukraine then
Bad guys everywhere will start taking other places and he'll take all of Europe and whatever and this is why we have to
But there's no thought about
What okay, so we're closing
Possible de-escalation pathways. What is the end game that we're going towards instead?
And engaging with this pretty directly. I can tell you that there's very wacky conversations about our first strike
nuclear dominance
And stuff like that
so
If you
Are focused on peace. It's not just we don't want to wage war
It's that we want to be effective at de-escalating everyone who is waging war and there are increasingly hawkish people on all sides
Absolutely
So learn how to be effective at influencing what is happening at the level of national security councils
Yeah to be able to have the more de-escalatory voices get into more positions of power and the escalatory hawkish voices not be there
so it
It takes a particular
But unless you know how to talk to security councils in language that will move them
Then you don't have the ability to help de-escalation in those ways or the other forces that you'd need to work with
so
the like
I think
One time when I was like nine years old
I
Had an experience probably many people here have had where I was horrified at my inability to not cause harm
that I
I couldn't avoid
When I was walking on the grass maybe killing some bugs. I couldn't I
at least my nine-year-old mind the
mites that were destroyed with my breath and my eyelash flutters
You know, it was just like so kind of horrifying. So I was like just stood there frozen didn't want to move
Wanted to breathe the little as possible
and
Okay, I realized I have to breathe and move but really tried to think about how do I not cause any harm and I'm complicit with all these systems that are
Fundamentally ecocidal and genocidal to be able to just get my stuff
right
and even if I'm eating a vegetarian diet
but
The shipping processes the oil that was involved in shipping at everything, right? There's like there's
Blood in all of that stuff and so I'm like, okay, so I have to only have things I make myself from stuff that I find
and
The idea that then for me to have my hands clean. I'm not causing harm
Also means I am totally complicit in allowing all the harm of the system to happen because I'm not willing to interact with any of it
There's a kind of humility that says no, I'm going to drive a car with fossil fuels that
Not only are destroying the environment but create wars that kill children
That I am partly driving the demand for
Then there is a place where like you don't I don't get to have my hands clean in this world
I do my very best but
There's a humility in that that's important. There's a realism in it. That's important
There's a not superiority over everybody else just being like we're in this thing together
At this time. That's the time that we're in
And then say like if I'm a pacifist
I'm not the one who controls the nuclear buttons
I'm not the one who controls the rapid proliferation of drone weapons
If I'm really a pacifist meaning I don't want there to be
Killing anywhere. How do I become increasingly influential over the people who are in control of the nuclear buttons and who are building all of the
AI empowered drone weapons
But that means maybe I have to learn how to engage compellingly with places that I would rather never engage with
Well, we've got two more questions and I want to kind of finish out with those
I think we'll we'll finish here at uh six o'clock Pacific nine o'clock Eastern
Um, so David, I want to give you an opportunity and then Eric and then Daniel any closing words?
Hi, greetings Daniel and everyone from Wajak Nga Buja in
Western Australia, where it's now 8 53 a.m. Saturday morning
And it does make me think of Edward Wilson's classic line. You know, we have a paleolithic emotions
medieval institutions and godlike technology
So I did enjoy your talk very much Daniel and I love that you
refer to sort of evolution or at least cultural evolution
And I have great respect for the United States of America two years away from your declaration of independence
And um, you know, essentially founding a republic
So it's pretty amazing for me living in what is a fairly robust democracy here
Um, but I do Dothma cap at America's abilities. Uh, so in terms of evolutionary
Perspectives, I mean, I I remember in the early 90s after the collapse of the Berlin Wall
One of the classic lines was because we went from two superpowers to the one superpower
And one of the classic lines was, you know, the new world superpower
is global public opinion
And uh, now it's a little bit more mixed up, but I'm just wondering
overall
What you think of the prospects of democracy modern representative democracy, which of course is nothing like
ancient greek democracy
Not good
Um
You just went away again, why do people go away right after they talk? I can all go ahead and um
I'm here. I'm still here. I'm still all right. So, um
It's a long complicated answer, but
when
The u.s. Democracy was founded
We did have an ocean separating us
And so the idea that the
There were a few things but one the idea that the people could know
Everything so they could be democratically, um, you know, participatory
Once we started to get the telegraph and then kind of mass telecommunications and then, um
Satellite spying sig intel and hypersonic missiles
Anything the american public know the russians the chinese the iranians instantly know
That means you started having a situation where almost everything became a national security secret and could not be shared with the public or even
got congress mostly
Because where the fertilizer is stored is a is a weapons knowledge where the aquifers are where the so increasingly
The most critical information can never be known by the public because it's national security secrets
That's you can't run a democracy where you have to classify everything
um
And yet you also can't make have a world that is in that kind of warfare where you share all of the things that
Are national security secrets with the public, you know, that's one example of a context change
In which the ideas that kind of made sense just totally don't make sense
The thing that we call the democracy obviously did all of its labor with slavery
and which means that all the shit jobs that people had no boat in
and
Then we kind of got rid of that
obviously
After the emancipation proclamation, we didn't really get rid of slavery
We just got a p and h slavery system where we put people in jail for for false reasons and then you know forced labor out of them
We really only got rid of it when we when globalization allowed us to ship the slavery overseas
and by the step back and effectively
and
You know, so if you were to say
Can a democracy make the decisions where the totality of the decisions it's of everyone that it's affecting all have a voice
All the stakeholders have a voice that's never happened
right so
A country will look at its genie coefficient and say what the inequality is but it buys its stuff from a country
Where almost everybody is poor
In which case it depends upon so the only level at which genie coefficient makes sense is global
Right, the only there's so many things like that where you really have to think about that
Which you depend upon and are driving the supply and demand of so
um
If if you really look at did we ever have democracy?
There was actually a thing where the stakeholders that were being affected really had any say it's not it's not a very good analysis
and then when you say
Does the thing that we have now even resemble the elements of that totally not
Now
Uh, how do you deal with that moving forward?
There is no system of governance in the history of the world that can deal with the issues that we need to deal with now
Because
Or instance
Uh gene synthesizers are becoming cheaper on an exponential curve
And it is already the case that quite inexpensively you can get the ability for gene synthesis and amplification and
It's a couple couple years at the current rate away from incredibly cheap like desktop capability for everybody
So if you even have open publishing of science
Where the science is doing gain and function research to look at incredibly variable empathogens and you publish the genome sequence
The information file alone, which is now open published on the internet is enough to make catastrophe weapons
And you can't monitor and control that the way you can nukes because nukes obviously are very very hard to make and you can see
The facilities the uranium enrichment etc from space
But we're talking about devices anybody can have in a tiny basement lab
And so that either means you
You just stop science mostly
Because it's all Pandora's boxes
Or you stop open publishing
Totally in the proper idea of kind of democracy there because the knowledge itself has weaponizable applications of that scale
Or you get increasing
Truly global catastrophes or you create a massive surveillance state
Those all are bad
There are better answers, but they're not obvious. They require innovation and totally new types of governance
Governance of lots of things. So, you know, those are things we work on
but um, I
Don't think that there are any systems of governance known to dates that can deal with these kinds of issues
I
Yeah, thank you so much here. I'm gonna unspotlight folks real quick. Um
And you know, we're coming in right here on the end of our conversation. I know Eric
Eric, I know well, uh, has a question raised if it's quick, Eric
If you still want to ask it go ahead and ask and then, um, daniel can share some closing thoughts
So, um, in fact, shelly asked very similar question to what I was going to ask
and I do want to thank you for your answers to the questions afterwards because
their monologue seem to have been a
um, basically a list
And it includes numbers like, you know, the however many people the Mongols killed and how much money is being put into ai
which
Are are nice to know, but I think you could assume that the people in this audience
Have been working on the basic questions for a long time
So my hypothetical hypothetical question is suppose we all knew
Everything that you had to say except for those little numbers
What would you say instead?
It's always hard to talk to an audience that you don't know what is shared knowledge
Um, what's shared world view? It's always a tricky tricky thing. Um
So my
Uh ideal situation is
To get to understand what a group is working on like what the shared knowledge is and what they're already
working on together and what things
Would be useful or empowering for them. What are the things that they're working on and then see do I know anything?
It would be useful. Maybe you don't
um
You know, it could be things about
Uh
Pathways of enacting solutions like specific strategies for enactment could be things about
prioritization of amongst all the problematic things which ones make sense to sequence attention on
it could be
um
deepening the understanding of the problem assessment in terms of the causal dynamics more such that
Um clear insight about what the effective kinds of strategies would be
But it would depend upon what was already known and what wasn't and what was interesting
And
Well, Daniel, we might need to talk more at some point
But uh, I just uh want to give you a chance. Uh, it's uh 904 your time
I know, um, but do you want to share some closing thoughts with with the group here?
I
I was um
I didn't know who was in the group uh beforehand, you know, and you invited me here. I was uh
uh
Happy to see how many people were scientists and where people who've been working on these issues for a long time knew
Uh a lot about it. I um
That's not the case of faith communities in general. Um, so I think that's awesome
if there was a
Follow-up of okay, let's kind of share
What our state-of-the-world assessment is and what our current thoughts for how to what we care to do and how we
Think about how to enact that are and be able to engage there. That would be really interesting
um
and
Uh, if there are people who are like have backgrounds and things and are working on things that feel like there are
Interesting follow-ups we might engage in if Keith maybe you send me a list about of that and that would also be really cool
Definitely will do. Yeah. Well, maybe we can end with some stillness and getting back in touch with that sacred center and
Thank you so much Daniel for sharing your thoughts. I would like to hear the harvest
From this so if some of you stay and continue to talk Keith if you would share
um harvest and there are interesting follow-ups to the intersection of the
um
kind of spirituality that
is not
incommensurable with any other
worldview or religion that has uh
In sacredness listening conscience at the center that also has environmentally interested people and scientists like this is
Really delightful. I'm really happy to have met the people here and so I look forward to hearing more
Thanks
All right, so um the folks who are staying I um
Want to just share with you all um the queries that we have uh, if this is not like I think any time with queries
It's really where's spirit drawing us?
But the questions I've written ahead of time are how might QEW as an organization respond with deep earnestness
to the crisis we face today
Given Daniel's talk what new insights or challenges are we seeing?
And three how might our Quaker faith inspire us in taking on our civilization all right at that?
So I'll drop those in the chat and then I just want to invite folks to start raising their hands and maybe once five hands are up
um
So I'll drop those in the chat and then uh as folks are led just raise your hands and we can begin this discussion
Thank you so much everyone
I'll note as someone who really loves
Daniel's analysis that i'm like
A little nervous because he does get laid something laid on pretty heavy sometimes
But I think it's really important for us to actually um as people who are called to spirituality not to avoid those facts
But to to really face up to them and ask a couple of us what conscience
How conscience would have have us respond?
so
at that
Just waiting for hands. We got four hands
and
Yeah, five
Okay, or four, but anyway story if you want to go ahead and start us off
Yeah, I I can only speak to number two because i'm i'm lutheran
And I have a very different um
Well, let's just say we do things a little differently
Um same general idea. Love your neighbor. Love god with all your heart mind and soul
The the thought that occurred to me
is
I as having deep roots in the scientific community
Going back over 50 years
uh, I'm
I'm
Feel motivated to say how can we kind of merge these points of use?
And for example in the geologic view, there's the oceanographers. There's the astrophysicist. There's the geochemists
There's the paleoclimatologist
There's all these sub branches all the way going down to high temperature superconductors because that's part of the same physics
And so we know we're very good at working with other groups and seeing things from their point of view because they're all valid
And together you you kind of get a broader more deeper perspective
Because I I heard very solid analysis from daniel on geopolitics and the reality of certain
government interactions and you know
history
but there's a
There's a climate aspect that is not well socialized
There are our demographic aspects that are not well socialized. My wife is from taiwan
And having that kind of personal connection
You notice things they don't publish because they're right there in front of you on the ground
And i'm just wondering where would it be best to kind of fuse those perspectives into a greater one
because
I really firmly believe if you're going to make wise
powerful decisions, you gotta know what you face
Hey
Ronnie, I think you know, I think everyone can see this list and
if we
um
Yeah, so um, we'll try to I see your hand raised. Don't worry. Ronnie. You want to respond?
for sure I do, um
I mean I pushed back at the end because
Not everybody here is a scientist and I sure as hell don't want to be in a a group with just scientists
There's people like me who are more social scientists and and the strategist for
Community organizing and all of that kind of thing and so, you know
I one of the things that I find is, you know, we are I don't think we have
Some of the answers we truly need and and yet
I also bring a strong native american orientation to this and
You know, we can do this from a um
Whatever this is, I mean native peoples have been, you know, destroyed
For centuries and and whatnot. So it's nothing new
I think, you know, it just to put that into a perspective and I think it's, you know
I was fascinated with the elder discussion because that's an area where I have a
High a law, you know, a large expertise and and cooperative structures that we're a bunch of older people in this country
And we could start playing and organize around how we're going to take care of ourselves
So that burden isn't on the younger generation
But we did talk about there being guidance from younger people and some of the younger people are starting to organize for
What do we do after things break down?
So, you know, I just um
I don't think we're going to come to terms with it scientifically
I sure don't think we're going to come to terms with it if we do a whole bunch of philosophizing
I think we've got to
Hit the ground with our boots on
Whatever that is
I
I just want to invite folks who have their hand raised just speak in order that your hands are raised. Um
Yeah
So that's jenny jenny wrackliffe right now
Uh, I I just want to mention a couple of things and and because I spoke earlier. I'll be quick
That there are several examples. I can think of
Of given given that you're number two and number three
keys
I look to people like e f shoe marker
gandy
Martin Luther king
And and others that some of us are already familiar with as to how we can actually build a bridge between the spiritual root
and our
This transformation that we're trying to bring about at the deepest possible level and turn that into practical action
and when
gandy
Made the savo dear movement in in india
I think as much as the satyagraha movement where he was is which he's known for about peacemaking and and and
An indian liberation from the british and so on
um
his his practical program of of appropriate technology
Deep economy deep deep ecology in effect
thomas berry spoke to this and
We're we're trying to integrate those things in our own lives. I think I mean daniel sort of
Painted a picture where in a sense we're faced with a dilemma
Do we do we have to enter the corporate world in order to be able to understand how to fix it?
Do we do this
Are we are we compromising our purity of our intentions if we understand how
You know the the armaments industry works or something like that and if the criteria is to be effective
But the criteria it has to be to be effective from in a spiritually guided
And transformative way
And that's the challenge we're facing and I think that people like shoe marker
Gandy and others actually gave us practical examples of how we can do this on the ground real practical stuff
And and also what you were saying rain you is it about integrating
Indigenous knowledge. We're trying to do that as well to bring
Bring out not just the sort of way that we might be able to adapt to the doom that we're already facing but to
Make the transformation ahead of time so we minimize the amount of chaos that we're producing
And I think yeah that that really resonates with me jenny that the root of it is actually conscience at spirit
And conscience leads us to act
Um, so I just want to share that and that the power the potency of that cultivating the potency of that
Is I think what I'm calling prophetic voice
But um, nancy
Thank you, I was really really grateful
Our keith that you brought daniel here
And began a dialogue with him that I think will circle back into
I have heard him a number of times before so
Much of what he had to say
Was not as hard to hear
In a way as it was the first time and there's a certain relief
In the the speaking of that and then engaging with it
In his models emphasizing strategy
He omits another way of thinking
That can bring together the guidance of spirit
Which is particularly a central in clarity being clear about our goals
And then being the right kinds of goals
Some of which can be put into words
Some of which is a response of the moment of the kind jenny is talking about and he spoke of
Where spirit takes you over
What I'm interested in the complementarity with it is comparable to strategy is the notion of design
Of social design where science
All the sciences both the physical the biological
The social sciences
Each have a contribution
To naming the givens the art of design
Is comprehending the givens
In combination
With the aspirations of the heart led by spirit
And among the givens understanding the realities
Of the situation you're in and the path dependencies and so forth
And then with a collective effort of mutual creativity gained by really hearing each other
To then begin to lay out what are the system requirements and what are
The places in the system of leverage points
Where the changes of the right kind could shift the outcomes
And at those points what are what I would call at that point design specs for solutions
And looking at stories
It's important to understand the stories of failure. It is equally important to understand the stories of success
I would say to him
Look at the open government movement in taiwan
Talk about an adjacent possible that just suddenly exploded. Nobody could have guessed not only a different way of governing at scale
A truly participatory governance at scale
But a different strategy for a kind of different kind of revolution that would occur
Look at the reamp project in the u.s. And the notion of collective impact and
And the notion of collective impact and
Stanford's
Social design and so forth. Let us look for
those places where there are not only
The accidents of the right person at the right place at the right time
that history yields
But those things that are replicable replicable that suggest
These are ways of being together ways of meeting our needs
That as I have put it to meet the needs of all by healing not harming
Planetary people our material needs. Where are their examples?
Of that and then where are the examples?
Of as in the reamp project bringing all the elements
Of a system that was resulting in horrific pollution in the american midwest
Each of them as human beings to come together and jointly map
The systems that they were in coming to know each other's human beings and the roles of each and then together saying
If we change these leverage points in this system
We could dramatically change we could reverse instead of being the most polluting part of the country
We could become the model of the opposite as you know Keith. They were stunningly successful
They stopped the production that going online of 30 power plants
So I want us to study closely where those things do come together
And the ways in which deep listening and love towards each other opens up creativity
That is otherwise again the adjacent possible. We don't even yet know what it could look like and lastly
The situation we confront we're all part of the problem and potentially all part of the solution
Is radically different
Than confrontational one issue even if the issue is colonialism one issue one shot warfare
This is a really different opportunity in human history
Thank you so much Nancy for sharing that and I couldn't agree more and I just that that um
I do think that that first example about taiwan is actually something I've talked directly to daniel about before
Um, so it's something on his radar
Brad
Uh, I apologize zoom is uh decided again that I shouldn't you shouldn't see me except in a uh a picture
So i'm gonna leave the picture there. Um
A couple of things struck me in terms of what he what he was saying. Um
I was struck by when he grabbed me when he said uh one of our alternatives is to die with dignity
um and i'm um
And working out of that one of the things that that and then he gave he gave a model
I mean he gave a lot of examples
But one of the examples he gave I thought was by moving was he said about to bet and how to bet could have anticipated
But their culturally weren't set to it, but they could have anticipated
by their geographic
placement
That they were between two major powers and that they were vulnerable and done something about it and interestingly
what he
Said this they could have gone to europe and asked for
um, essentially military support it sounded like. Um, or some kind
What i've noticed is and and i've and i've um
Is is a lack on
On on certain of many of us are not wanting to push back
Um, and what I was hearing him say was you need to study
The you need to study the the opponents so to speak and you need to understand them in order to know how to how to resist them
In a way that's going to actually be effective and what he said was if not being effective is immoral
And I and I thought that was extraordinary to say
um
It always struck me that that obama had told us in his books
He was a compromiser and when you have him come into a situation where
for a while they
His his his party controlled all three
Parts of government, you know the executive in both houses and they didn't just do what the
What the republicans would have done which is roll over everything they could have just put in you know
um
Changed medicare and had universal health and two years of it before and then try to take it away
They they could have when they were doing the so-called bailout
They could have bought out everybody's mortgages
Taking over the banks. They had the rules to take over the banks and control them and they didn't do that
They they chose to just to give the money to the ceo's to be able to retire and what we and we all kind of
Okay
That's okay
And part of what what really has been bothering me, you know, and I and I
I grew up in a union house. I grew up, you know, and my died in the bowl
Democrats and
Is this that the the fear to be called liberal even it's like, oh, you're a liberal. Oh my god, you know and and running away from it
And and the pause what I'm hearing here is we need to resist we need to be more active
It doesn't necessarily mean for quakers to take up arms, but it does mean to fight
And there are ways to fight without
Taking up arms and shooting people, but it doesn't mean rolling over it doesn't mean dying with dignity
It doesn't mean letting it happen
And and and that's what it's what what I feel I'm surrounded with too often in the so-called liberal world
Is that kind of well, let's get along. Let's not make waves. Let's compromise. Let's find a way out and you know
And not instead of saying no, this is wrong. We're going to stand up and resist
um
and remember
peace teams one time had a
A picture of a girl this is before the current situation of a girl standing in front of a tank
in
Palestine and and protecting a trying to protect a house and and the tank ran over her and the house
And and the line was that they had they posted was people are willing to die for war. How many people are willing to die for peace
And it's at that level that we're talking about and I just feel um
I just feel like that's what he was asking of us
And in between the lines is is to have that kind of same level of energy and commitment
To really push back and push back effectively. Thanks
Brad, I I just want to say you're speaking to my condition. I um really
Really appreciate that and um
I'm not going to dominate this conversation, but I want to invite Brian. Yeah
I
Do want to
I believe what Brad was just saying there
but
I do want to um
At least point out that
There was an underlying fear
That really wasn't being talked about
Daniel has
of
Where we are
And I think that it's important that we
Understand that fear
As we move forward
That it's not an excuse for not moving forward
But that it's an important thing to understand perhaps that the
Time frame that is available to make the changes that are required
Is no longer with us
And how do we respond to that?
The
Fear of where we are with AI
The fear we are with how much
Information needs to be controlled cannot be talked about that he was afraid that
He would be recorded and that that might be extended to the rest of the world that he might misspeak
And he was afraid of that
So I think that we need to understand his fears and we need to understand
Should we hold on to those same fears or
Is that something that we have something special
within our approach
That can work past those fears
He is speaking to the fact that we need to
Completely change the institutions the systemic
Approaches that are already in place all need to be changed and they all need to be changed simultaneously and that
There's nothing to be left behind
that's revolution
and
Are we willing to
step out
to the levels of what does that mean and what does that mean within a
nonviolent approach
And what does that mean to
our families
and our neighbors
And the people that are you know that we love
That that we hold dear and what will the consequences be
Of what we're going to make for the changes that have to happen
To be able to prevent the worst of the things that have been outlined in front of us
Just an acknowledgement
Thank you
Thank you rye, um David
Um if you can hear me
Um
I'm reminded of somebody's quote who suggested an effective strategy
Is to develop some sort of system which absolutes the existing system
Yeah, yeah
We're never going to have the time to develop the skills to be able to
Change corporate corporate america from the inside
I don't see that as something that makes sense for
qe w
I'm intrigued by the idea of wilderness
There isn't any
But at least there's little pieces of nature that still exist
For us to develop the kind of intuition that he was talking about by exposure to nature
It seems like qe w needs to be
Looking for and attempting to preserve
What little bits of nature there still are in all growth forests in wilderness
Those are the kinds of things that we might be able to be effective in our strategy of
Probably not at a federal level but more likely at a local level
And pointing out to the society around us
That those pieces of nature that still exist
have
things to teach us and
Are beautiful and affect our lives
If that makes sense
Thank you, David, uh, we have another David
Good morning friends 9 33 a.m. Now in
Yeah, it was uh
I think I will have to try and get in contact with daniel if I know he's a busy man, but his responses about
governmental processes
fascinate me because i'm certainly fascinated in
democratic
which seems to me like peaceful ways of
You know moving the overton window as it were, you know, what's acceptable. What's not acceptable and so on so forth
I do think that 17th century britain was a most fascinating time
Because of course it not only gave birth to friends
But in many ways it gave birth to at least the beginnings of democracy
You know, uh, we basically had the parliament taking the power over the monarch and I think it was you keith who mentioned
Hobbes and whatnot earlier, you know, and there's you know, there's a whole lot of changes here that are happening. So I
personally am still holding the faith
Very much that democracy is still evolving
and so I
sometimes say that
Quakers are my spiritual community
which I dearly love
Golf is my other religion because on the golf course nearer to thee am I and my lord when I'm
In that spiritual space
But I will say that modern representative democracy is my true
Religion in the latin sense of that word religion, which basically means
Bonding what bonds us
you know, and
I know we are very
Symbolic we work through symbolism a lot
And so I think always I think my my holy of holies
is the two red lines down the center of the house of commons, which are
mythologically as it were
Two broadswords apart
Now the symbolism of that is if you are the
Speaker in the house of commons
to your right
sits his majesty's
loyal government
and to your left
sits his majesty's
loyal opposition
and
So, you know, they clash thoughts
But that's the essence of having to live in the age of reason
Because if we are to live in the age of reason
we must
live in the age of
contention rivalry
because
Reason can give a valid answer on both sides
And I know many friends here
have spoken about as it were
think
locally act globally, you know
now I
Warning, I may say something which upsets people here. Okay, but I will say first and foremost
I am very very very pro
choice
okay, and
I can respect
the united states supreme court's decision
To make it a state thing
Okay, so I hope that doesn't upset anybody too much
But on I would absolutely always go for pro-choice
But I see the reasoning in it
It's up to you folks
individually
As states or what have the case would be locally to decide what you as a community wish
And I think that is all the way through
You know, um, but of course how we're lessing that into a
Global public opinion as well is another matter. Anyway enough from me. Thank you
And Leoma
A couple of things one it seems to me that
Finding spaces for you know, like the scientific the internal all these different states
doesn't seem to me like such a
big conundrum
We just I think we might be well suited to find a way to
honor all the different ones
uh our
practice with
Unity decision-making might help us be a place where we can
help model the structure of
Honoring all the different ways of knowing
Going with the basic
fundamental belief
That there is something larger and deeper than us holding us
And that we also are not wise enough to know more than part
I mean, we're wise enough to know the QEW needs more diversity to have more
more contention and more
points of view, but um
And so that was one thing and the other thing is I've been wondering
Considering our size. I mean, I'm troubled by this idea that we need experts
um
Seems like a
Very sound idea. We need experts in how to be effective
In the places that are controlling resources
Which essentially what the big corporations and governments are
they're
channeling the way resources go
and
That but that's very daunting to get the amount of expertise to be
Effective there
So I'm just putting that up as wow
Because if we don't maybe we won't get a chance
to do where our
strengths is
Or where our contribution is
but um
The other last thing I wanted to put forward is this idea that's been
playing with me
about
As a compliment to the gentle warrior
Which Keith seems to be your archetype in some
Some days at least
um
The humble holy trickster
Which is the one who's
Uh, and there are other archetypes that we might well embrace in there or invent but
But the humble holy trickster is the one
Who is attuned to the emergence?
I've been wondering about emergence as a compliment to good design, which is essential
How do we
How can qe w as a small organization?
catalyze
emergence
By being alert to places where
A small group can shift conversations
And connect
Groups, I mean we're in our silo. We need to get out of it. How can we connect groups?
That
When put together might come up with something we don't expect
I mean, I think there are ways that emergence can be encouraged
and there are ways in which
it's
Being channeled towards emergence of pathways
We all know too well from our history in terms of the rival or stuff that daniel talked about etc
but
Well, I think our next person is suellin
Thank you, liana
You
Um, I
I want to in general say that I keep wanting to say that friend speaks my mind
And so and what many of you have said so thank you
I have heard
Maybe one thing but I also may have misheard it that concerns me
And um, and I want to respond to the first query
Um
So let me say that now and then I can because it relates to what concerned me
How could qe w respond with deep earnest?
I don't have it in front of me, but deep earnestness to what we just heard from daniel. That's the way I'm going to truncate it
And I will say
By actually honoring because we don't and no progressive groups do
I think
That's a black statement that I should don't have the right to move but we don't
honor
the study of effective strategy as much as we honor
Having a phd in science
We don't honor that and as a person who has been an organizer since I was 13 years old
I will tell you the studies are out there
And what they tell you is you'd better read them because for example people always bring up the civil rights movement
well guys
Read I've got the light of freedom that explained that it worked those marches to a large degree
Not their only person. There's never one reason something works to a large degree because for 20 years organizations went into
The black towns and did door-to-door canvassing and had community meetings
For 20 years before you saw any sit-ins and marches
Yet when people think they have studied effective strategy
They think they're looking at the surface
They haven't studied the effective strategy
and we do not as
I
Well, I don't call myself a liberal anymore because I call myself a lefty
because working class of economic things are always in front of me
uh, and but what I'm going to say is
You can't study it
But you can't study it just thinking you kind of know what people have said in a few places
You got to really find the studies
It took me years to find I've got the light of freedom and the Duke university professor who wrote it
And that was 20 years of door knocking that your university professor who wrote it said I have looked for this book for years
and I finally decided I had to write it
And uh, uh, so you it is not easy, but we cannot tell ourselves
surface things
If we wanted to change so if we wanted to be earnest
We would study effective strategy, but we'd really study it the other thing the thing that has concerned me two things
One has been the idea that if we
Play in the some of the power circles to try to help things be better
And we can't be sure it'll save the world but to do our best and play in some of us
We will be corrupt like corporations. I think I've heard that in various words more than once
No
That isn't at all necessary
Instead what we need to do is again go to root cause and figure out why corporations
Have so much power. Well
partly right
They have so much power because they've elected people who care so much about
I mean
It was so different when I worked for congress when all the members of congress or a lot of them had been
Planned by the vant and a vietnam war and the civil rights movements. You guys it was a different world
And that's people
so we need to respect that
Power is a really
One of the things to do and I will finally say I do not believe conscience leads to action
I believe
love
Of things like as I said in my five-year thing looking in the eyes of a wolf not frankly to be honest
I know often people talking about carbon credits, which I think are really important and stuff because people just go
Look in the eyes of the wolf and tell me if it's okay with you
Vow's eyes go extinct
Because you're approaching love
And what I want to say is that
We need some love to help
There be tactics
But as he as Daniel said about the 10,000 things put you in touch with the dow
The knocking on the doors
The canvas is what puts off is as valid at put for putting us up in touch with spirit as sitting in a me for worship
And we don't really
All that we don't
and I think because it is
The story of that I tried to find from organizing is people did a little bit
They were reinforced and then they did a little bit more
So that door knocking or whatever is where god is I believe
I'll go ahead and share just a bit. My hand kept dropping. I think it's because my mic's off
Um, and then we're back. I'll invite you but I I really did want to share just a bit that um
Yeah, I think I mean, I think that Naomi both knows me well
And says it well that I think that the the orientation towards this that I'm called to
Is something like a peaceful warrior, which is the one that's willing
That you know, there's a beautiful some beautiful quotes from some very peaceful warriors, uh in the 19
Bear uh, I'm trying to remember his first name right now
There's a few but you know, essentially, um
admonishing
Quite, you know peacemakers people who claim to be peacemakers
But who are unwilling to pay any significant price for that and they you know claim. I want peace
I want peace but they do it with half a heart and half a will and because of that
The war continues because all they really want is the volaties of peace all they really want is
peace in my little bubble
Right and I think as long as that's what we're going for we're actually completely out of line with conscience
That's what I I think gardening is a beautiful thing. I think rooting ourself in that deep
Groundedness with the earth is so foundational to transforming ourselves and transforming the world
But if we're not stepping outside of our bubble
We're not aligned with god. We're not aligned with conscience. We're actually just
Faking it. We're we're middle-class white people
wanting to feel good
And so I think
Is I hope doesn't admonish people so much that they don't feel that every small thing you do makes a difference
Every little thing even if you didn't step
You know, you didn't bat your eyelashes to kill that little
Or whatever it is everything even if you die tomorrow the little things you did today
Made some difference and so that's that's the ground that we work from is that foundation
Everything makes a difference
but if I'm going to be
Absolutely if I'm going to be true to our bigger ancestry and I'm going to give my life to god
I'm going to give my life to conscience
There can't be any
Cans and butts about that. It's actually everything is on the line
And that means I'm willing I'm going to recognize that we do live in a world
That's much more complicated than it was
100 years ago and if human envy is going to be a good steward of this planet
We're probably going to get it need to be a little bit better at sense making what's going on
we're also
Going to get a lot better at solving our problems interrelationally with one another we're going to have to get better at peacemaking
Um, I think that the main thing I would say is you know, we were saying the problem is the institutions
The problem isn't the institutions. We don't have a global institution
There's its complete rule of power by tooth and claw and in our anarchy and its worst sets
At the at the global level
That's not that's not entirely true. I want to you know, the un has been amazing
There's been things that have progressed us against that trend towards violence
um, and and there's really earnest people fighting for that. Um
but
We need global cooperation
If we want to be a wise steward of this planet and to do that we have to do deep peacemaking
Not shallow. Oh, why don't you just all get along kind of peacemaking but like
Resolving historical trauma kind of peacemaking and creating peace between peoples
um
And then we have to I think humble ourselves before the living world that we're all apart and realize that there's a wisdom
Implicit in all of this that is so much faster
Than anything we have to touch with and if we're able to surrender ourselves to that and say that's actually that's the prime objective
Is just to be a an instrument
of that that's
To me what conscience would have me do and I do think I would push back against any one didn't today
but I I I see
Maybe it's just a mystical sense
That uh, the force of non-violence is as of yet
Unrealized in its fullness in the world
And that's what I want to see qe w leaning into
Um not tomorrow but today
You
And Rebecca I'm realizing sorry I was thank you Rebecca
So I want to thank you and I want to thank sue ellen. I think sue ellen you have a lot of wisdom about
a strategy for
moving forward
But I I really want us all to listen to one another by
listening in tongues because I'm going to
Speak to the first question
um
I don't usually come to these gatherings, but I I really felt compelled after listening to
a
Presentation daniel spoke
That was sent to me
So I came tonight
I'm a part of new england yearly meeting on abinackey unceded territory
and
in their earth care ministry committee
And um
number one
I've got three points one is that
The love of god
However, you interpret that
Calms our fears
The second point as a social scientist
I really believe in something that he's just shared about
We need to create
places of trauma
informed
gatherings
That are part of our
Specialties
Our specialties as scientists
Whether that be social or natural
Or physical sciences
Whether that be as farmers
Or as
Pastors or as
Economists
Whatever that is
To humbly sit together
And listen for spirit to talk to us deeply
And then come together and share those truths
That we have discerned
That will move us forward
On a path
That maybe
able to speak to some of those entities that
Know our language and would be able to hear us
From the voice that we have that is
somewhat unique as a people of faith
And lastly
Live into those paradigms that we have discerned
Through the spirit
That we don't have to keep doing what is being done
We can move in that new way just like our early early forebears
Moved in a different
Way than the culture around them
We can do the same
We can be known as those wacky quakers
Don't quite walk the same walk or talk the same talk
That was number three so anyway, thank you very much. Thank you for this program
I'm noticing that Juniper is on the move but Chamba, Nora and Juniper's hand is raised. Nora, are you wanting to share?
Yeah, sorry Juniper was needing constant movement right now and I wasn't going to be able to think in
So dad took him for a second
I
I mean what what was really pulling at me raising my hand um
Why was my hand was
I think that
I actually don't want to frame it that way. I I have a deep felt knowing
I'm not even going to say sense. I have a I have a deeply felt knowing
um
That
Quakers are being called and have been just for some time to get really uncomfortable
And I think that's been dawning on us slower than it should be slower than it needs to be
Um, I mean, I think it there's of course
I've heard echoes of that today already, but there's a
There's a deep discomfort that we need to step into
And I think QEW is a part of that. I think we
I think any moment that we feel righteous we should question
And I heard that in Daniel's talk around
You know, if you think that you if you think you know, you're probably causing harm
We are having a conversation in this house. I think it was last night my sense of time is a little weird since having a baby. Um
Um
But we are having a conversation about different
Different cultures in different ways of
Of just approaching things and
And how what we think is like what's needed
Is coming from our own cultural frame and I think those kinds of conversations are really important
But I think that we can't get too hung up on trying to be so perfect as to know everyone's cultural frame
As to know
What's going to be the deep understanding that's underneath all of it. It's okay. We have our cultural frame
If someone came into our circle, they were like, well for my political frame, this is what we understand
We wouldn't say, oh, well, let's go deeper than that because that's not
That's cultural frame. That's not valid. We we'd say, oh, thank you so much for bringing that
We need to get uncomfortable enough to say
This is my frame
This is where I'm coming from and I'm a piece of the puzzle and I'm gonna step in
And that's uncomfortable. It's so uncomfortable to claim something because when you claim something you can be ostracized for it
And actually you're gonna have to change it the moment you claim it
You have to change it because the moment you claim it you start learning about it and you start learning about yourself
Oh, this is my experience of being human
And then it starts to shift and how uncomfortable to be on shifting sand all the time
But I think that's where god wants us to go. I think that's where spirit always has lived
You
You think there's other things that that come to me about the whole question of rite of passage and and
And the frame of a rite of passage feels really powerful, but um
Honestly, none of that is feeling very led for me to say so I'm I'm gonna I'm gonna stop there
As your partner, I'm very moved
Um, that was really powerful
Thor
Man so many many good people that talks tonight. I just I'm thoroughly impressed
I'm gonna summon up the game of rock paper scissors
because
A lot of us would like to pick up a sword and battle it out, but that's just not
Politically correct anymore, especially in a democracy
So that we switch over the paper and it's really a political legislative process
Getting out the vote going to door to door getting the right people in congress and we already know what they're gonna vote on
They're gonna vote for reforms. They're gonna do the right thing or close enough. That's how represented democracy works
And some of us well, let's just say rock is easier to break up than to change your mind
We've got brains. We soak up information
Um, I mean I I I was faced with a genetic condition my son. I went into a medical library
No background in medicine 10 hours later. I had the diagnosis
I can do those kind of mental gymnastics
Most people can't
Most people can't spend a couple hours a day just trying to keep current on what's going on out there in the science world
But I find hope in knowing what's going on
Even if it's in the early stages, you know, vanadium peroxide soaks up carbon dioxide
Maybe it's a good thing. Maybe it's not but I'm sure it's going to be either replaced by something better or it will do
That that's the realm of people spend two hours a day every day
Soaking up information because that's something I'm good at
So I'm a rock. I know it. I'm a lousy politician and I certainly don't want to go with a broadsword out there
But we got a system of domination. It's a kinder, gentler one. We see it in our housing. We see it in our financial system
We see it in our retirement system
And I I
I love the problems we have in the United States solely because I know they're worse everywhere else. They go in the world
so
I'm just saying being aware is so powerful
And getting out and you know, if you're really going to say you love your neighbor
You're willing to get outside. You're a little little bubble
And I hear you say you love nature, but I really like meeting people that are really different than me
They think differently. They're culturally different
That's what's really going to change and I think that is the the singular strength of a group like this is we can get out
and meet our neighbors
And we can make a persuasive story that you know
I think God calls us to be a servant
We are called to do the right thing. We're not supposed to be a reactionary. We're not supposed to be afraid to change
We don't have such rocks, you know
Set rules about the way it should be like it was in 1940
And that is I think you're this the signature power of this group
I don't know. I got I'm really impressed
You
Thank you Thor we'll keep in conversation. Um, uh, allen
Oh, I was kind of hoping you wouldn't call on me
I
I've I've been listening to everyone and really
appreciating all the deep and moving wisdom and the um
And and I feel like what I mostly have to bring is uh confusion and I'm I'm kind of wrestling deeply with a lot of what uh
Daniel brought forth, but um
there's
Part of me that is pushing back
Against uh, I found I found a lot of our conversations and but there's been little
glimmerings
Of something else, but I found a lot of them tonight to be very human bounded
um
That uh, when I look from my geo and it's really I think more my geological perspective than my quaker perspective
this kind of pushing back on that that uh, when I look at nature
I don't see
um
Well competition is certainly the norm, but it's always
eventually ultimately bounded
and cooperation
Is also the norm and um
I think this it's not just human bounded but time bounded but that
In the rise of western civilization there was this domination mindset that emerged
and it's uh, it's a fire and the um
lack of fire
It's burning
Literally, I mean every time we drive a car
We're burning the earth
and
Like all fires
It's a
Daniel referred to exponential growth a number of times. This is growing exponentially that is growing exponentially and
I think uh for years I taught my students that all exponential growth
Is ultimately self limiting that nothing can grow exponentially and it's only in the last year
That I realized that was wrong
That there's another kind of fire
That uh, there are things it's only things
That consume
That can't grow exponentially things that produce
Things that are generative love
No
No wisdom, I won't say know how know how governed by wisdom
That can grow exponentially
And so the question the confusion the thing I'm wrestling with
I have I keep having this image of moses
In the uh
Meeting the burning bush
And it was a burning with a fire that did not consume
And my theory of that my thought of that has always been that what was transformational there
Was not that that bush was any different than any other bush or any tree
Any animal or any being including us
Is that moses
Saw the life force in it
Whether there was some
Sometimes I've looked at our redbud trees and
In spring and I've thought oh, is that the burning bush? Is that the
That life force
And he recognized
The spirit
In that
The god and he took off his shoes to make himself more like the bush to grow to find that deep rooting
And I there there he was often the wilderness in some ways. I think you're one person
Meeting god
Yet he transformed the world from that experience
And I think that fire and genia alluded to it and other people alluded to it ultimately I think it's love
And
So my question is what kind of fire burns in us
I
I'll just leave it with that
I'm just gonna
share something and I think when you're talking about cooperative and competitive forces
But I think in I mean sew on if you feel called, please do share but I'm thinking that that might have been
That might have been our moment
Just leave it with what I'll say. So if you want to share though, please do great. Well
All right, Thor if you're willing
Is it a final?
Just a final piece
Yep final piece and it's kind of a prayer
I'm going to just relate
That after my first son died
I gave thanks to him
I gave thanks for his life
I gave thanks for the influence it had on me
And it felt like the sky burned
So when I read that mozo saw the burning bush
I know he was in that
mindset
To be thankful for the things that we all fear
The things that scare us the things that challenge us
And I've never felt so in awe and so strong in my life as that day
And that's what I wish for you and all the challenges we face
That you look them in and understand them and give thanks for them
Because we are born in a time where there's good great promise and great challenge
And if you are so blessed
The sky will burn for you
You
I was gonna post this in the chat, but
I couldn't find it. I just didn't want to disturb the silence, but
There's a prayer from pema children that she shares
In her book the places that scare you and she says
May the roots of all suffering diminish
May hatred violence addiction and neglect also decrease
And we see all that separates us as as insubstantial as our dreams
May we go to the places that scare us
May you be a warrior of light