Hello everybody and welcome to the Mindscape podcast. I'm your host Sean Carroll
And this is going to be one of those podcast episodes that people have been clamoring for for a long time
I get a lot of suggestions and a lot of people suggest the same guest over and over again
Sometimes I ignore the people, you know, I love the people, but I don't always agree with them other times
I think you know what the people are right and in this case
I think that they are so I invited Stephen Wolfram to be on the podcast now Stephen Wolfram was a physics prodigy at a
young age one of the youngest winners of the MacArthur genius grant started out in particle physics before he moved to think about
complexity and cellular automata
Maybe best known right now for inventing the Mathematica
programming language and analysis system as well as the underlying Wolfram
Language that was used to write it and Wolfram Alfa answer engine
I use Mathematica all the time many people in my field use Mathematica
But he's also still interested in fundamental physics a few years ago some years ago
He wrote a big book called a new kind of science where he suggested that cellular automata
Might give a clue as to different ways of thinking about all sorts of science right biology economics as well as physics
More recently he has launched what is called the Wolfram physics project
Which is simply an effort to start with almost nothing and get the fundamental laws of physics out of them
Now there's a lot to say about this and we don't say everything in this podcast even though it's a long one
I wanted to focus the podcast on
giving a sketch for what the main ideas are of the Wolfram physics project and
How they are not yet fully developed but might be developed going down the line
There were a lot of criticisms and some kudos about how he developed it sort of outside the mainstream
Physics research and so forth and then you know late on us hundreds of pages of work with he and his collaborators at the same time
And you know, it's not the mainstream of theoretical physics
Most physicists who are doing their own thing did not drop everything to work on it
But some became interested and they're inviting people to help out
So you'll learn a lot in this podcast not about I'm not gonna talk about you know
How the research was done or the fact that it was uploaded and shared with the world or whatever you can draw your own conclusions
about that I care about the substance of the actual ideas and
Mostly I'm giving Steven here the opportunity to explain those ideas
But there is a family resemblance between what he's trying to do and what I and my collaborators are trying to do in
Quantum mechanics stuff like that. So let me very briefly tell you what I how I see that relationship
What we're trying to do is to start with the
Simplest most stripped-down version of the best theory we currently understand namely quantum mechanics, right?
To start from almost nothing but quantum mechanics and see how things like space and time and matter and energy
Emerge from that fundamental description
Steven Wolfram and his friends are trying to be way more ambitious than that. They're starting with a kind of
automata a kind of discrete system called a hypergraph and
generalizations thereof and
Basically, you have a guess as to what the rules are for how hypergraphs are updated
And the point that they're trying to make is that some guesses lead to things that kind of look like the real world
So the hope is that eventually we find specific guesses for what those update rules could be that actually get us the
Specific real world or very very close to it. My own attitude is you know, good luck to them
I'm very much in favor of lots of different approaches to fundamental physics. This is one of them
Great let a thousand flowers bloom, etc. I actually think that our my and my collaborators
Approach is more promising because it leans heavily on something we already understand quite well
Which is quantum mechanics as I see it if the Wolfram physics project works
They're first going to have to find quantum mechanics in exactly the right way and then
Find all of the features that we have about the real world
So it's kind of a precursor to what I'm trying to do, etc
But you know, I might be wrong about that
It could be that this particular way of doing things leads to not just quantum mechanics
But a specific implementation of quantum mechanics that gives us other clues to understand the nature of space and time, etc
So as I said what we're trying to do here in this podcast is help you the listener
Actually understand what the ideas are and where they're going. Hopefully we succeed in that
Let me very briefly take an opportunity to as I occasionally do
Remind you that we have resources for the mindscape podcast
We have a web page proposterous universe.com slash podcast
So every episode has you know links to stuff about the authors and other resources and also full transcripts of the complete episode
So you can search every mindscape episode for the last three years. We're hitting our three-year anniversary roughly speaking
And also we have a patreon if you would like to support mindscape you can go to patreon.com
Slash shawnam carol donate a dollar or two or whatever your local currency is
Per episode and you get ad free versions of the podcast as well as the ability to ask questions in our monthly
Ask me anything episodes mostly. It's about gratitude. I'm very happy very
Pleased that so many people enjoy mindscape very much and therefore
Choose to donate just a little bit. It's the thought that really does count in this case. So with all that let's go
You
Stephen wool from welcome to the mindscape podcast
Hello
So it's been a little over a year I guess since you announced your physics project and I think I finally
By no means have become an expert
But at least I know enough about it to ask a whole bunch of ignorant questions to help us all understand it a little bit better
I mean maybe to start off
Is this do you consider this current project be a continuation of the cellular automata type of stuff?
You did in your book a new kind of science or is it a new branch somehow?
Yeah, so I mean it builds on basically a tower of ideas technology
intuition and so on
that
Uh, actually, I'm sort of amazed we've managed to get to the point we've managed to get to
But all those previous pieces seem to be necessary to get to where we are
And for example, you know, I studied a lot in new kind of science 20 years ago. I studied a lot
cellular automata, which are these very simple programs with
You know arrays of black and white squares and so on and from studying those things
I developed both a bunch of intuition about how sort of things work in the computational universe
And I managed to figure out some fairly general principles
Which we've been able to get more and more evidence for which are necessary to kind of launch into
Figuring out things about physics now when I wrote new kind of science, you know
It has 12 chapters and one of those chapters was called fundamental physics and it had two sections
One was about thermodynamics and one was about kind of the fundamental underlying theory of physics
And for me at the time I viewed it as being an incomplete
potential application of the general kinds of ideas that I was developing a new kind of science
And I had a bunch of specific ideas about thinking about space as a network
Thinking about the way time would operate and so on
I was very pleased with the fact that I had managed to get a fair distance in deriving general activity from that kind of
Theory of gravity from that kind of approach. I was not satisfied with where I had got with quantum mechanics
And you know that project so so now
restarting that project nearly 20 years later
with energetic young physicists and so on and
One kind of initially rather technical new idea that kind of made the model just seem much cleaner to me
It was kind of it's been a new development and and really now I've seen a lot of things that I say to myself
I should have been able to figure that out 25 years ago
Welcome to the club. That's that that does not distinguish you from anyone else working on science, right? Yeah, you always look back
with that
No, I think I think what's what's so I view it as being what what's really neat is that the formalism that we've now got
Is something which was sort of there were precursors of it a new kind of science
But the full sort of story of it is just emerging now
And it's really neat because it really it gives one sort of a to me
There's sort of this way of understanding things in terms of how simple programs behave
Developed a bunch of intuition a new kind of science now
There's a whole another level of intuition and results that we're getting that provide in the sort of formalism for this project
And that's so it's it's both applicable to fundamental physics and to a bunch of other things
And I'm I'm pretty excited about that
So let's imagine that first I'm sure this is not true
But let's imagine that there's going to be a listener who only listens to the first few minutes of this podcast
And we want to let them have a takeaway for what is going on here
I mean is it accurate my vague impression to say that the cellular automata
Had a grid right like you had some checkerboard or something like that and some rules for updating them and some discrete model
Which you're going to hope that if you squint and look at very far away
It looks like physics whereas here you still have a discrete set of models
But you're not starting with a fixed grid. You're kind of building things up by rules as you go
Right. Yeah, that's right. I mean, I never thought that that cellular automata would be relevant to fundamental physics
I mean other people were sort of saying cellular automata are going to solve fundamental physics
And I was like, no, please don't say that that's just not going to work
And you know cellular automata are very minimal models once you have a fixed notion of space and time
And they've been extremely fertile models for huge numbers of different kinds of things from, you know, road traffic flow
To chemical catalysis to you know leaf growth all kinds of different things
But they assume a pre-existing notion of space and time and so in thinking about physics
I had realized ages ago that we really need to go underneath the notions of space and time that we're familiar with
And see how to build those up from something more fundamental
And so sort of the real starting point of our project is to think about just these that they're just
Space is made of something that's not that has not been sort of in the tradition of physics
And the traditional mathematics as well
That's not really been a thing that people think about space just is a is is something in which
Things are placed at certain positions and so on
And so, you know in this and it's kind of like what people might have thought about a fluid like water
It's just water. It's just flows. It does all these kinds of things
But you know 150 years ago we found out no those greeks were actually right some of those greeks were right
It's made of discrete molecules bouncing around and with space
We haven't yet sort of made that definitive leap and one of the sort of starting points of this project
Is to think space is made of something. What's it made of?
It's just made of these disembodied discrete points and each point is just an abstract element
It doesn't it doesn't have a position. There's nothing. It's just this element
And then what we say is what all we know about those elements
Is how they're related to other elements
How they're effectively connected to other elements
So it's like you think about all these points in space all they have is a friend network, so to speak
They don't know where they are. They just know who their friends are so to speak
And so the you know the first big sort of realization is from something as unstructured as that
By looking at that on a large enough scale. It's kind of like how you know continuous fluids emerge from lots of discrete molecules
Underneath bouncing around
There's a there's a notion of a kind of continuous like space that can emerge when you look at that on a large scale
And that's that's kind of the you know, that's that's one starting point
I mean another important thing to realize is that in our setup
The only thing in the universe is space
And there's no
You know, we're not saying space is a background and there are things placed in space
We're saying everything in the universe is just kind of made of space
So what I have in mind is a bunch of dots you write nodes that are connected by lines to form some kind of graph
and
Do I imagine that the line that the dots rather the nodes are they labeled?
Do they come are there different kinds of dots or is there just a an ur.ness that they all share
It's an ur dot. Okay. That's just all identical
the only thing the only thing about them is
They are two dots are either identical or they're not identical. That is there's there's a there's a particular dot
Or there's another dot and so the only the only thing about them is is kind of their their
You know their identity so to speak they don't have
They don't have colors. They don't have they don't have positions
They just know i'm this dot and not that other dot right
So there's some dots and there's some lines. They make a graph or a hypergraph, I guess and there's a rule
There's a rule for updating to go from one collection of dots and lines to
The next one and then we just iterate that forever, I suppose
That's right and the whole universe comes out of that. That's very nice
That that that's the idea. So, I mean, you know, there are many pieces to that setup
For example, one thing is all there is is these kind of atoms of space and connections
There's nothing in space. There's nothing. It's not like you then say we've got space now. Let's put
A an electron in space if you want an electron you have to make it out of space so to speak
You have to make it from features of that pattern of connections between the atoms of space
So that's kind of the that's that's sort of the
The base story of what what is the data structure of the universe?
What is the universe sort of made of and that's the idea it's made of these discrete elements
And relations between those elements which we can think of as being kind of lines joining them
It's actually convenient and this was the sort of technical innovation of a couple of years ago
To realize that the best way to think about this is in terms of a so-called hypergraph
Where we just have elements and relations
In a graph you have you have nodes and you have edges connecting those nodes and each edge connects two nodes
In a hypergraph you can have any number of nodes involved in a hyper edge
And that sounds like a it is really a technical detail
But it makes the whole model much much easier to deal with or at least I thought it made it
Much easier to deal with in the end it doesn't make much of a difference and I could have figured this out 25 years ago
But that's that's that's the that's the way these things work
It it seemed to make it easier technically to make forward progress
But I think you were you were then talking about sort of what do these
What do these atoms of space do and you're describing kind of the rules that they use to get updated?
And um, yeah, you're right. I mean the the basic idea is you look at the local structure of this graph
And you say whenever the local structure of this graph looks like this particular pattern
Then it should be updated to be a local piece of graph that looks different, right?
And that's the whole story
Some things are just better at home
You can pause the movie whenever you want you can have two desserts and no one will judge you
An exercise is one of those things peloton delivers a workout experience that you'd never imagine was possible
Right in your own home one of the things
I especially like about peloton is the variety of classes driven by different kinds of instructors
If you're the kind of person who needs to be encouraged by your instructor
Robin Arzon is especially good at that whereas if you just want to get down to business and get the workout in
Adrian Williams might be the instructor for you
Whatever your mood or overall fitness goal you can mix and match classes for a total body workout experience
Choose from cardio strength yoga pilates outdoor runs meditation and more
With the peloton bike, there's nothing like working out from home
Learn more at one peloton.com new members can try peloton classes free for 30 days at one peloton.com
Slash app terms apply. That's o-n-e-p-e-l-o-t-o-n.com
I like I like the fact that you just use the word hypergraph because I like to
Share the jargon with the audience so they can go look it up because especially I mean I should note you
I don't want to talk too much about like style and procedure here because there's far too much physics to talk about
but you did announce this project with a website and a call to
Participate right if people want to dig into the details. What is the url? They should be going to
Well from physics.org there you go and and people can find out what the details are and do their own calculations
So that's that's yeah. I mean the other thing we've done kind of in terms of the public
Which has been really a big success is we've we've live streamed a lot of our internal working meetings
And we've you know all the notes from this project are all
You know posted on the web basically the the day after they're made typically and that's some and and it's been really
Interesting because a lot of people who are you know a lot of professional physicists have gotten involved
But also a lot of people who are for example
Involved in computer kinds of things and understand
Sometimes more of some of our jargon than the physicists would understand have also gotten involved
And it's it's really been an interesting process to sort of do science live and in public so to speak
it's you know and I
the it's like
It it's a good kind of generator of reality because you know we say some things that are right
We say some things that are wrong it kind of a a place where you can get to see kind of the process really happened
And there is something that is very different about what you're trying to do in terms of fundamental physics
I would I would argue and then correct me if i'm wrong
Usually not always but usually physicists work from the phenomena
To try to come up with an explanation right like there are stars in the sky. They're planets moving in certain orbits
What can we do about that? There's an apple falling from a tree
But in some sense you're just saying well here is the simplest possible thing that physics could be
Let's just see if we can guess the right one. Is that more or less accurate?
Yeah, I mean it is closer to that than the reverse engineering approach
and in fact when I see people try to sort of understand what we're doing and
Sort of say well, what about doing this and that and the other the great tendency is to try to reverse engineer
And this was a thing that that I kind of uh, you know, I as
You know, I used to do sort of mainstream standard physics back in the late 1970s early 1980s
And you know, that was what one did in those days
And the thing that was really for me very liberating
Was when I started studying well, I got interested in how the complex phenomena occur in the natural world
And the question was what are the right models to study that and my initial thought was
Let's use all the fancy stuff from physics all those differential equations and all these kinds of things
I tried doing that total failure
So I said, let's step back and see, you know, is there an alternative approach to modeling that we can use
And I had the very fortunate experience that I had been working as a practical matter on building my first computer language
as a forerunner of mathematics or more from language
This was back in 1979 1980
And what one does when one builds a computer language is one saying
Let's take all these computations people might want to do and let's in a kind of natural science type way drill down
And try and find out what are the primitives from which we can build up all these computations
What are the kind of atoms of computation and then build up from there?
And the thing that's really interesting about that process is you're just making up these atoms of computation
It's not like, you know, it's not really the same kind of oh, we've also we've got to make sure we get
You know, einstein's equations here. We've got to do this and this
You're just making it up and you're hoping that it will be in that case useful to people
And so that experience got me into this idea of just figure out the most minimal model and see what it does
And that's what I did with cellular automata and it worked great in that case
So in a sense with physics
What I was trying to do with this project is find
The most structuralist model of structure in the universe
because that was and
And it is not it is by no means self-evident that that will work
I mean, that's sort of the ultimate Occam's razor type idea is you know, just make it, you know, absolutely minimal
Now the thing that's really neat and maybe we'll talk about this a bunch later
Is that now that we have this foundation
We can start to see how a lot of ideas that people have had in mathematical physics
Over the last many decades actually plug into this idea and both inform it
And help make those other ideas more more, you know founded and it's it's I think come
So so this this notion which basically
You know this idea of find the simplest primitives and then see what they do
This is what I get for having spent 40 years being a computational language designer
This is what that's what that's what that involves and it's different from what people do traditionally
In sort of reductionistic science where you say start from the phenomena and then say how do I get this phenomenon?
right and
I do want to it's a somewhat different methodology
I do want to definitely get to how we recover all of known physics or at least you know
Move in the direction of recovering all of known physics
But there also seems to be like a couple of deep principles
That you have in mind when you're working on this stuff that maybe it's worth sharing
I mean one of them is this idea of computational equivalence, right?
I could try to gloss it, but why don't you tell the audience what that means?
Yeah, yeah, right so
You know you set up some simple program you run it you see what it does
You might think if it's a simple program it will always do simple things
That turns out to not be true
That's sort of the big thing that I discovered in the early 1980s
That for several years
I kind of resisted that conclusion and eventually realized that is really the way things are
When you look in the sort of computational universe of possible programs
If you just sort of pick a program at random
Even though the program may be very simple its behavior may be very complicated
Programs that we typically build as humans for some particular known purpose
Will tend to not have that feature because we want to have them achieve the particular purpose
We want them to achieve which is one some purpose that we can describe
And so you avoid this thing that the simple programs producing complicated behavior
That idea of simple programs producing complicated behavior
I think is sort of the essence of the secret that nature uses to make complicated stuff
And that's why you know we look around in nature. We steal this complicated stuff
We say how could it possibly make all this complicated stuff?
That's just the formal fact about what happens in the universe of possible programs
So first thing is is the realization simple program doesn't necessarily have to have simple behavior
And then the next question is okay, so you see this very complicated behavior
How do you characterize it? You could just say oh, it's very complicated
And in fact a lot of the you know people had seen these phenomena for centuries actually of you know
Fairly simple setups like you know the digits of pi
Specifying them is quite easy yet once you've generated the digits
They seem completely random and people would typically say oh, it's very complicated
There's not much we can say about that and they would try to find you know
Like the distribution of prime numbers or something
They work for a long time to try and figure out what regularity can be teased out of this thing that seems quite random
And so what I was interested in was trying to understand how do we characterize this complexity that gets generated
And so the thing that I realized is the way you can think about what's happening is
Any process of generating some pattern for example you can think of as a computation
And then the question is how sophisticated is that computation?
So for example, it might be that computation is just like adding numbers together
It's something very simple or that computation is something more sophisticated
And the question is can you kind of can you rate the sort of sophistication of computations?
And so the big discovery of the 1930s and so on was that you might have thought
Every different kind of computation you want to do you'd need a different machine to do it
But then with Turing machines and combinators and a bunch of other ideas
This notion of universal computation arose that says you can just have one piece of hardware
You just feed it different programs and it can do different things
And you know, that's been a that's been a pretty centrally important idea in the technology of the last 15 years
You know, that's the origin of software the sort of developments of the computer revolution
But in for science the implication there is well, perhaps these simple programs
Might actually be for example computation universal
They might be able to do essentially any computation you want
So this principle of computational equivalence of mine is basically the the idea that
When you pick a program if the program doesn't do something obviously simple
It will be doing a computation that is as sophisticated as the computations that anything can do
So in other words, what that's saying is, you know, you might think you start off with an incredibly trivial program
And only those trivial computations as you make the program a little bit more complicated
It would gradually do more and more sophisticated computations
And as you make a really really really complicated program
It would do really really complicated computations
But the the the somewhat surprising claim of the principle of computational equivalence is that that's not true
Once you get above some very low threshold
You're immediately at the max you're immediately doing computations that are as sophisticated as anything
And that that principle, I mean that has that principle has many implications
And um, I mean probably the most important for for immediately for physics is this phenomenon
I call computational irreducibility. That was the next one. So go ahead and say that yeah
right, so so I mean the um
You know the question there is
If you are running a program, can you tell what it will do?
One way you can tell what it will do is you just run every step just like the program would run itself
But another thing you can do is say I'm much smarter than that program
I can jump ahead and it's going to run for a million steps
But I can just jump to the end and say the answer is going to be 42 or something
and so
You know one of the ideas of
Of sort of the exact sciences the mathematical scientists for a long time has been
Sort of a sign of doing wonderful things is that you can jump ahead like that
You can make you can readily predict, you know, where will the planets be at some time in the future and so on
But so that's that's what I call computational reducibility the ability to reduce the computational effort necessary to find the answer to jump ahead
So the claim is
Actually, there are lots of systems that are computationally irreducible in the sense the only way to find out what they'll do
Is just to run every step or in effect just to observe what the system does
And the reason that happens is because the principle of computational equivalence because if you think
You're the observer you're the predictor
You are you are a computational system as well
And the question is how do you as a computational system compete with the system?
You're trying to predict
So if it was the case that you could really be smarter than the system you're trying to predict
Then yes, you could potentially jump ahead
But what the principle of computational equivalent says is no actually that won't be that way
You will be exactly computational equivalent to the system. You're trying to predict
And so the system you're trying to predict
Its behavior will seem to you sort of irreducibly complicated. So that's that's one of its implications
So in some sense, this is saying, you know, both of these principles the equivalence and the irreducibility
There are computers as we've known since touring that are universal computers
They can calculate any function you want to calculate and what you're saying is in the space of all computers computations
Computations with that capacity are generic in some sense. They're all over the place
They're much easier to find than you might have thought and there's no way to simplify the the typical one into a something that you can just leap ahead
Right. I mean principle of computational equivalence
One of its predictions in effect is that universal computation will be ubiquitous
It actually goes considerably further than that because at a technical level one of the things that one talks about in universal computation is
It is possible to program this system to do whatever computation you want
It's a little bit of a different statement to say if you are presented with this system and it is fed
Even this very simple program
Then it will already do something complicated. So it's a couple a couple of additional steps
But one of the one of the key predictions is computation universality is ubiquitous
And that that has many implications. I mean it has implications in terms of the practicalities of building computers
It has implications in terms of what aspects of physics we can expect to understand
It has implications at a more philosophical level about things like free will and so on which maybe we'll talk about
Well, and one of the implications is that it it if we buy into the philosophy of it
It gives us some optimism for this program of starting program in the human sense
Not the computer sense for this project of starting with some very very simple rules and getting the actual universe out
Right if all sufficiently complicated computations are at the same level of
Ability in some sense
Yes, that's true. I mean one of the things that is sort of a key
I would you could even say prediction statement of our physics project is
What can be done in our universe is just computation and not hyper computation
That is it's the kind of computation that can be done by a Turing machine
It's not the kind of computation that can be done by a thing that is infinitely more powerful than a Turing machine
Right that you can conceptually imagine
But you can't uh, you know the claim is no such thing exists in our universe
And in fact you can get a bit more technical about it
And the the claim of these models is even if it exists
It will be hidden by behind a cosmological event horizon from us
Um, we will never be able to observe it
So it's kind of like well, you can say it exists
So you can say it doesn't exist doesn't really matter because we'll never be able to interact with it
But so, you know, that's one of the the key statements. Yes, and and the idea that
That it's sufficient to have something
That is a simple a computational system that we humans can kind of understand how it's constructed like a Turing machine
Or like one of these hypergraph rewriting systems that is a you know
That's a that's a supposition of this project
And it's a supposition that in a sense is is sort of encouraging for us humans that that it might be the case
There's something we can kind of hold in our hands that represents everything the universe does
Even if the implications of that thing we can hold in our hands are irreducibly complex
And even if we couldn't tell, you know, given that you give us the rules for the universe
If you say can I make a warp drive the answer might be it's really hard to tell
It's an irreducibly complicated thing. Yeah, it's like, you know
Recapitulating the whole history of mathematics and so on to get to the point, you know, can we prove this theorem that there is or isn't a warp drive?
so it's
but but to me that's yes that that that's
That's that's the concept. I'll take all the reasons for optimism I can get I'm all on board with that so so good
So with those in mind, I mean, let's go back to the physics that you're actually constructing here
We have a hypergraph
We have some rules for updating it now
Should I read the specific
Is it is the idea that there is a specific correct rule for our universe and that rule basically is the fundamental laws of physics?
Okay, so this this is where things get a little bit more complicated. Yeah, so I think
That it is probably the case that there will be a rule that we'll be able to hold up and say
With this rule, we can reproduce what we observe in physics
Now footnote, which is really interesting footnote. I think you might say why did we get this rule and not another rule?
You know, it seems very particularly if the rule is simple
That's like, you know, Copernicus was wrong. So to speak, you know, there isn't nothing special about us
We got the simple universe so to speak or we got the universe with the simple rule
Not the universe with the to us incredibly complicated seeming rule
So the the thing that is then very surprising
Is that and and this is you know, we probably have to go a few more steps before we can really really dig into this properly
Is the idea that actually you can think of the universe
as running all possible rules
And we as observers of the universe are essentially exist in a particular in a sense reference frame
In a particular position in rural space as we call it
That essentially gives us a particular sampling of this sort of universal possible universities
And that particular sampling has is is given our way of parsing what happens in the universe
That is something that we could attribute to a particular underlying rule
But actually we can also think of it as just a slice
Of this kind of universal or possible universities
So it's a it a little bit more but but I think you know, operationally
I would hope that we will be able to
Produce a rule that will have the property that if we work out all its consequences
And we cannot because remember one of the very tricky things is we as observers of the universe are embedded in this universe
And so as you change that underlying rule, you not only change the rule for the universe
You also change the rule for us
And so that those two effects
In some very very vague sense cancel each other out so that there is a large class of
rules for the universe and rules for us
Which all seem the same
And which which all have the same laws of physics effectively
So to give an analogy to make this a little bit less less bizarre
The you know, so let's go back to fluid dynamics, for example
And you know, we have the laws of fluid dynamics there the navier stokes equations all these kinds of things
And you might say, how do we derive these?
Underneath there are a bunch of molecules bouncing around
Well, there can be water molecules which have their particular, you know, h2o form
There can be you know air molecules there, you know, n2 or whatever it is
These different kinds of molecules bouncing around
All of their physics is quite different all the details of what happens when those molecules collide is quite different
Yet on a large scale the laws of fluid dynamics are the same for air and for water
They have some different parameters, but they're basically the same laws
And it's the same kind of thing that I think happens in the derivation of laws of physics
That is certain aspects of the laws of physics are quite generic
I think general relativity and quantum mechanics are quite generic
And they are things which if you are an observer even vaguely like us
They are inevitable that you will observe
And if you want to home in on well, do we have the fine structure constant where the particular value it has
You probably have to home in on more features of us as observers
Right. I mean, do you think that do you anticipate that at some step in understanding the relationship between these rules and our universe
There will be an anthropic move of some sort where you say there's a lot of things going on
But intelligent observers will only observe this subset of things
Intelligent observers, no
Observers with so the question is what is the right idealization of the human observer, right?
So I'll give you a couple that
That seem to be enough. Okay. So one important one is we're computationally bounded
We don't get to observe. So let's take the gas molecule example again
If if you are, you know, you have this gas has got a bunch of molecules bouncing around
If you're a sophisticated enough observer, you can see every single molecule you can work out all the collisions
And in particular that will allow you. So, you know, a big principle of statistical mechanics is second law of thermodynamics
Which says, you know, typically the the sort of typically things get more random as the molecules bounce around in a gas
But if we are not computationally bounded observers and we can
You know, we can figure out what all these trajectories of all these molecules are
We don't get the second law of thermodynamics as non computationally bounded observers
The second law of thermodynamics simply isn't true
And so the first and that same idea of a computationally bounded observer is necessary
I think for us to believe that space has a continuous structure and various other things about the universe
So that's kind of step one. So we're not Laplace's demon
What's that? Sorry. We're not Laplace's demon
That is correct. We're not we're not Laplace. We're not Maxwell's demon. We're we're um
We are we are we are thoroughly non-demonic in that sense
And finite and bound we only have this sort of bounded ability to understand to look at the details of the universe
That's step one step two. I've understood more recently actually and step two is
Something which I think is sort of the the physics essence of consciousness
Which is that we have this idea that there is a single thread of experience that we that we have
It might not be that way
That is in the universe and we didn't talk about this in detail yet
But in the universe all these little updates are happening all over the universe
But we think that and in a sense there's sort of microscopic pieces of time
Happening all over the universe, but we believe we have a single identity through time
And that there is a single thread of experience that we have through time
Now it's it's by no means self-evident that that would be the way it is because in our model of physics
Everything about the universe is being rewritten, you know, 10 to the 100 times or something or something like this
And so the fact that we have the idea that we are still the same us
A second later is non-trivial
And so I think that an observer who has that idea that there's a single thread of time
Has that is that is the one of the things that you need in order to get the laws of physics that we humans observe
And I think that's a so there's this idea of we maintain our identity through time
Yeah, which we might not
Um and the thing I realized actually even more recently, although I should have realized this earlier
Is there's a similar idea for space? It is not self-evident that there is a notion of pure motion
So in other words, you take an object you move it somewhere else
In our models, you know, I take an object. I move it somewhere else
It's made of different atoms of space by the time it gets to its destination probably
And so then the question is how come there's an idea of pure motion
How come a thing can just be moved without changing now?
Obviously we know in general activity, you know, you're close to a black hole funky thing can happen to you if you move
Because the structure of space is changing
But this is a very basic fact that most of the time, you know, something moves
And it is still the same thing
And so this idea of this sort of this this single thread of experience in time
This idea that it is possible to have pure motion
And it's possible to maintain your identity as you move around in space
Those two attributes seem to be what you need to derive generic log of physics
That is that that's what you seem to need to derive general activity and quantum mechanics
Now if you start asking
Why does the electron mass come out to be the actual value it has
For us humans, we probably need a little bit more information about us humans to be able to figure that out
I think I'm not sure. I mean, for example, one of the things that's a current
Challenge is the the local symmetry groups local gauge groups
It is looking very likely that it is an inevitable feature of our models that there will be local gauge invariance
And the thing that looks conceivable. I don't know yet
Is that the actual
Gauge group will be determined
So in other words, even though we don't yet know why the universe has three dimensions
We might actually know why the internal symmetry group is maybe a subgroup of v8 or whatever it is
Before we even know this thing about
About about space and so that would be an example
But we don't know, you know, if you ask what's the electron mu on mass ratio
You know, we're we're still a fair distance away from figuring that out the classic my expectation would be
That there'll be a particular rule that we'll find
Which will have where a whole bunch of those things will come out
And one of the features if you believe that the rule is simple is if you move from one simple rule
To another nearby simple rule everything's going to change because there just aren't very many rules
That are that simple and so instead of having, you know, electron mu on mass ratio
It'll be well
There actually are an infinite number of generations of particles and there are
You know a bizarre number of dimensions of space and all this kind of thing. It'll just be completely different
But that's that's the current expectation
I think you you raised the anthropic principle and to me the anthropic principle is sort of a story of
Of lack of imagination so to speak
Because it's saying, you know
The only way that we can have life intelligence consciousness, whatever
Is the particular way we've seen it
and you know, I
My one of the consequences of this principle of computational equivalence is that actually
Something like intelligence is ubiquitous
That is you might have thought to get something as computationally sophisticated as us humans with our brains and all this kind of thing
You need the whole process that's led to us humans
But what the principle of computational equivalence says is that's not true
Even these very simple the system with various simple rules can do it
And that has well has lots of consequences, you know, if you're if you're worrying about extraterrestrial intelligence, for example
That tells you it's everywhere. It's a question of whether we are sufficiently aligned
with that intelligence
To be able to recognize it as something that for example has purposes that we can understand as sort of human like purposes
So, you know, it's a and I think this idea intelligence requires liquid water is almost laughable
I'm on your side when it comes to that but but intelligence might require space time in some sense
So let's let's at least try to get that I mean
Do I is this naive picture that I have in mind where you have the hypergraph you update
It's a discrete updating should I can I think of the graph at any one update as space and the update itself as time?
Or is that too simple minded?
Okay, so it gets a little complicated and in fact
The complexity of the rises is quantum mechanics, I think
and so it's in a sense you try and make it that simple
and
You okay, so so the basic point is the sort of the rule says if you have a lump of
of atoms of space that are connected in this way
Transform it into a lump that's connected in this other way
And it basically the rule just says that's what you do. It doesn't say where you do it
Doesn't say when you do it
It's just any time there's a lump that looks like this
You can transform it into a lump that looks like that and so those transformations can be happening all over this hypergraph
And so it is not at all obvious that that is the only thing that's defined that these can happen
The question of when they happen what counts as the sort of simultaneity surface?
What counts as that moment in time is something that's really in the eye of the observer
Okay, but the updated graph is supposed to represent spacetime and the things within it or is it a more subtle map there?
No, no, so so so at any given
What's happening is this graph is getting updated and there are lots of little places where it can get updated
And you can say okay, I'm going to consider the graph with this collection of updates having been done
I am going to consider that as time t equals zero let's say
And then another situation
You're saying I'm going to say now I'm going to say this collection of updates is time t equals one for example
And each one of those time slices at each one of those sort of well in the language of physics space like hypersurfaces
the
You know that represents
An instantaneous structure of space
But it is somewhat arbitrary what you consider to be this instantaneous sort of structure of space
Just as it is in general activity. Well, sure right and that's that's very familiar from general relativity
But I'm just saying is the collection of the whole shebang
spacetime
And the things within it. It's just space a single hypergraph a single the collection of all the updated hypergraphs
That's what I'm asking. Oh, yeah. Yeah, right the sequence of updates
The hypergraph together with all its updates is supposed to be spacetime
Okay, and and one of the things that is is interesting and non-trivial here is
You know a lot of most traditional views of physics have thought of space and time as being the same kind of thing
In this model, they're really not sure spaced as the extent of the spatial hypergraph
Time is the computational process of updating this hypergraph
So time is a time is the is the progression of a computation
Space is just oh, you follow these these connections in the hypergraph. Okay, and so
That makes it not at all obvious that you're going to get things like relativity
Out of the model because it's some
You know because one is breaking apart the sort of traditional
Connection between space and time
But it does sound you say that the whole the whole shebang is spacetime
one of the reasons I hesitate a little bit about that is
The shebang is made by a computationally irreducible process
So we don't get to it is a you know to say let's just unroll the whole structure of the universe forever
Well, we don't get to do that in the universe
I mean the universe will do that as the universe does it but we can't just say this is what's going to happen
Because there is this phenomenon of computational irreducibility
But I do want to just distinguish between this idea and something that someone like myself would be very fond of which is
Some combination of quantum gravity and ever ready in many worlds
Where there are different branches of the wave function where the geometry of spacetime is just different perhaps radically different
It sounds like that is not something that is coming out of your hypergraphs. Oh, no, no that that will come out
Okay, I was simplifying a bit. Okay. Okay, so what's happening is at every
You know these updates they get they you're just saying whenever you see a piece of hypergraph
That looks like this you can do an update. Okay
There are many possible sequences of updates that there are many possible
Sequencings of these updates that could occur each one of those sequence things
Defines a different path of history effectively
Now the nontrivial fact another additional piece is this thing we call causal invariance
and so what's happening is if you look at this um, uh, this
Okay, so if you if you look at this this hypergraph and you imagine
You roll up the whole universe
Into a single lump that you can kind of hold in your hand and then you say that single lump is going to evolve to another whole universe
That process of evolution
Is not a single thread that that process can branch because the whole universe
If you did two updates in different orders, for example, you would get different outcomes
You would get different whole universes and that's very similar to the many worlds story
And one difference is that in our models
We're really, you know taking seriously this idea that there's that there's
branching as a result of these different possible orders of updating and so on
And that there's this thing we called in a multi-way graph
Which is just this this description of all these different possible paths of history
But for us, it's very important that the paths of history can branch and they can also merge
and they merge when
two
Two outcomes for the universe end up you apply two different rules
And it so happens that they end up with an identical universe
They end up with a hypergraph that is isomorphic that you can rearrange to be exactly the same hypergraph
And so that branching and merging process is really important because one feature
Of many of our models and in fact it seems to be in the end
It's a ubiquitous feature of all of them, but that's not how it initially looks
Initially, it looks like you have to pick it specially but in the end you don't is this thing
We call causal invariance and so essentially what causal invariance says is every time there's a branch
There will be a subsequent merge
So in other words, even though you thought you were going to go in two different branches of history
Even though for a while
You've got two completely incompatible structures of spacetime
In the end they will merge
In the end there'll be and that's some and so that's why
In our models, that's in the end. Why you get objectivity and quantum mechanics
Well, let me see. So what happens if I'm just a conventional many worlds person
Um, there's perfectly deterministic evolution of the entire wave function
it will branch and part of the reason why it branches and
Operationally they never merge is because there's some environment
Which is huge numbers of degrees of freedom and the different states in the environment will never exactly line up
So eventually you might imagine them emerging back together 10 to the 100 years from now
Is that the kind of thing you have going on or is you're
Remerging much more rapid. No, the the remerging is faster than that
But again, it's a little complicated
But the the fact that there is divergence and merging is basically
So what what in the end happens is that the uncertainty principle is a story of essentially curvature in this
Uh, in this basically multi-way graph space
And it's just like in in spacetime one of the sort of you know, the classic feature is you go around a square
Does it does it, you know, you you go around a square with all the right angles and distances
Does it close up if space is curved it doesn't close up and what's happening in our models is
It's the exact same thing. Although the space is more complicated and more like a Hilbert space
that
What's happening is the same exact kind of thing is what leads to the uncertainty principle in quantum mechanics
It's that same failure to close up and now what ends up being the case and we don't understand this
As completely as I would like yet
So so just to give some sense of the sort of the situation with respect to you know, what we know and what we don't know
So these multi-way graphs
Okay, so first thing to say about multi-way graphs is they represent the sort of branching and merging of paths of history for the universe
So what you one thing you can do is you can say at any given time
What is the structure of all of those possible branches of history?
So just like in in spacetime, we're going to say let's pick a space like hypersurface
Let's pick a
A simultaneous moment for all these different parts of space
What does space look like or we can do the same kind of thing for this multi-way graph
If we do that we get this thing which has all these different all these different sort of possible
States of the universe and how are they connected?
Well, they're connected in what we call a branchial graph
A graph that represents these different branches and so one
Convenient way to construct a branchial graph is to look at the common ancestry of those states
So if two of those states just branched one step before they're close together in the branchial graph
If they branched many many many steps before they're further apart
And so you can you can construct just like from this sort of
Structure of spacetime you can construct a sort of instantaneous structure of space
So from this multi-way graph you can construct what we call branchial space
This is the instantaneous representation of the possible branches of quantum history
And in a sense, it's a map of entanglements because every one of these branchings
That the fact that they had a common ancestor and that they will is is a story of entanglement
That's saying that these two branches of history are not independent
They are connected by the fact that they are entangled
So in a sense this branchial space is a map of quantum entanglements
And so it's really I think incredibly cool because branchial space
Has many of the same attributes the physical space has
It's more like a Hilbert space. It's a little bit complicated and we don't fully understand it yet
It's something like a a what is the analog in spacetime?
We have this idea of minkowski space which has both sort of the the usual euclidean type space for space
And then this notion of time being a separate thing
And exactly how that works for a Hilbert space the analog of minkowski space for the Hilbert space of states
We don't understand it. Maybe something related to twister space. That's a special case of it
But it's something we don't yet understand
But one thing we do know is
You know in terms of what we understand what we don't understand
We do know that our multi-way graphs
Reproduce a an approach to quantum mechanics called categorical quantum mechanics
And we can just show that they are equivalent basically and it's known that categorical quantum mechanics is equivalent to standard
standard quantum mechanics that people studied from the 1920s and so on
And not only can we show that they're equivalent
One of the recent things in the last month or two has been we can actually use our models to model quantum circuits
And we can essentially compile a standard quantum circuit into a multi-way graph
And the big excitement of the last few weeks has been and we can do better
Circuit optimization in multi-way graphs than you've been able to do in standard quantum circuit formalism
So in other words, we can we can if you want to simulate a quantum circuit
It's better to do it through our model than it is to do it through the standard mechanisms of quantum mechanics
But we know the answers have to be the same
So that's that's what we know for quantum mechanics. We don't yet know
Fully how that works for quantum field theory quantum mechanics just for other people's benefit
I know you know this very well, but but you know quantum mechanics is a story of you know, what do individual particles do
Quantum field theory is a story of even if you can make particles and the particles are
A sort of spread out through space. How does that work quantum mechanic play?
And that's a more difficult thing which we're just starting to understand
I do want to dig in I want to dig in more specifically to the different to
Mapping your approach onto the different interpretations of quantum mechanics, but but let me let's just give
Back up a little bit and keep it simple for the folks who are who are trying to stay with us here
If I look at the pictures of the graphs of the hypergraphs that are following the rules
Very naively it looks super duper classical. There's a graph something is happening at every point
So could you just explain why you know, you even get something like the double slit experiment where you can get interference?
But then if you look at it, you don't get interference. Is that something that pops out of your model? Yes
Yes, um, I mean by pop out there's a little bit of there's a little bit of effort to make that pop. Sure, of course
The okay, so when you see pictures of these hypergraphs
They are pictures drawn for a particular branch of history particular branch of quantum mechanical history
That's what we're easily able to visualize now. It's been a big project
To make what we call local multiway systems, which mix
spatial extent
With branch ill extent that is mix
Things which are moving around in space with things which are going to different branches of history
And we've been this has been a big challenge because it's pretty hard for us humans to visualize that stuff
And we've been we've been working on it for the last year actually
We're getting fairly close to having pretty good visualizations of that
But those are those are significantly more difficult to understand
But the the typical pictures you'll see
Our our project is full of graphs
So there are many different kinds of graphs that show up and they're they're kind of in all the one of the things
That's been a big kind of practical win is that we at some moment
We kind of did the colors for our model and you know picked this graph is going to be this color
This kind of this other color and so as soon as you see one of these things you can tell that's a causal graph
That's a branch ill graph or whatever. Um, that's just a uh, and and um, you know
Because all the all the code for our models is all openly available
People have been just using that code and so people have been following kind of the the color standards
Which really help but so there are there are
Probably six different kinds of graphs that show up the ones that are the most common and colored bullish are
The ones that are the the hypergraphs that represent the instantaneous structure of space
So there are then these multi-way graphs that represent the um, the kind of the the um, the branching and merging of quantum histories
Then there are branch ill graphs, which are traditionally pink in our world
That represent these slices
through the multi-way system they represent so
in
In space time
We are taking a slice through space time and finding this is what space instantaneously looks like
In the multi-way graph you take a slice and you're saying this is what the instantaneous map of quantum states looks like
And in fact what happens is in in relativity
We're used to having this idea of reference frames of how do we label what space and time are how does an observer
Decide what counts of space what counts as time and so on if the observer is going at different speeds
You know you're tipping the reference frame all those kinds of things
We have exactly the same kind of thing in quantum mechanics. We have what we call quantum observation frames
Which are basically the the the thing that represents
This corresponds to a a particular state of the quantum world
And you can think of these in branch ill space
You can think of these points in branch ill space, which are histories of the universe
as being
different quantum eigen states
So you you can think of them as being different
basis elements
So different different things from which you would make up a quantum state
And so then what happens is when you have one of these quantum observation frames you've you've sliced the this multi-way graph
You've got this whole collection of quantum states
And now you ask
In for example, so so now okay, this is a
One other thing I have to explain
In quantum mechanics the sort of the big idea
You know is this notion of quantum amplitudes. That is you just get to know there's this this
object
Which is that you know has complex numbers, you know associated with and all this kind of thing that is the quantum amplitude
and so the question is
That that quantum amplitude the the the complex numbers that are associated with it
That you know one of the things that we've realized is the idea that you can think of a quantum amplitude in some of the complex numbers
Is confusing in fact the right way to think about it is it has a magnitude and it has a phase
And in our models the magnitude of the quantum amplitude
Is the result of path counting in the multi-way graph?
So in other words if there are many ways to get to that state in the multi-way graph
The magnitude of the quantum amplitude is determined by the number of ways to get to that that point in the multi-way graph
The phase of the quantum amplitude is determined by the position in branch shield space
So in other words the idea is as you move around in branch shield space
You are changing the the the phase that coordinates a branch shield space are essentially phase coordinates in quantum mechanics
Sorry, you might need to tell me what branch shield space is again
Okay, so so okay, so that then we've got this
All possible histories of the universe which correspond to this multi-way graph. They branch they merge
It's a complicated thing now. We're saying let's let's and and and that graph is being formed through time
So every every and so now we say let's take an instantaneous time slice across that graph
It is the quantum analog of a reference frame in relativity
Okay, and that and by the way those reference frames can get quite wild in quantum mechanics
They're somewhat wilder than the ones you would typically use in general activity at least that's that's our
View of how this works. So so those reference frames are sort of the choice of the observer
They're not they're not something that is intrinsic to the physics
They're just oh, we've got this multi-way graph now. We're going to say for our purposes
We're going to say this is what the time slices of that will be like
Okay
So that what this branch shield graph is the structure you get by slicing through this multi-way graph
So you're asking the various points in this multi-way graph. How are they arranged?
Well, we can say they're arranged nearby if they correspond to something which just had a common ancestor
Just one step back. We had a common ancestor and other ones, you know
You have to so basically what happens is the the simplest way to make these branchial graphs is you simply join by an edge
every pair of nodes that have a common ancestor
Okay, and then so what that means is if there are if there are things are far apart on the branchial graph
It means their common ancestor was probably many steps in the past
And and the idea then is that that okay
so the claim
Which is again mathematically quite non-travel is that the coordination of branchial space
That is if you try and assign coordinates just like in in physical space
You'd say there are all these atoms of space and they're just connected in certain ways
But now we say based on those connections
It is we can say this one has coordinate position blah blah blah
And it's next to this other one which has a very similar coordinate position
Okay, so the same you can do the same kind of thing in branchial space
You can try and coordinate to i's branchial space
And the claim is the coordinates of branchial space are the phase of the quantum amplitude
So in other words what that means so so just to sort of perhaps for for people's benefit
Maybe we can explain something about so, you know
I don't know how how to we can try doing let's see you probably can do this better than I can but but explain the quantum phase
But you know the idea the way that I just say it is that you know the
The wave function for a single particle is like a wave sometimes. It's positive sometimes. It's negative or plus or minus i so
different contributions can
destructively interfere as well as constructively interfere
Right but the critical idea in a sense is as you have that wave that's going up and down
The phase of the wave is at a particular moment in time
Are you up or are you down right and the phase is kind of the shifting of that wave relative to a particular moment in time
so what we're saying is the these the the um
This branchial space represents kind of where the
Where that thing is shifted that a position in branchial space corresponds to a certain shift of that of that thing
So so here's the place where where it's actually my favorite result so far in our physics project, okay
So um, which is worth explaining because then we can talk about double-slot experiment a little bit more easily
Okay, so let's talk about physical space
One of the questions is if you are if you have an object a particle for example in physical space
How will it move in physical space and the standard idea of general relativity?
Is an and of actually Newtonian physics is it moves?
You know according to a shortest path from one from one point to another
So it's like whatever the shortest path is in space. It'll go
Along that shortest path if space is flat the shortest path will be a straight line
If space is curved the shortest path might be deformed and the big idea of you know
In einstein's equations and so on is the deformation of space the curvature of space
Is produced by the presence of energy momentum by the presence of mass in space
So essentially what we're saying is gd6 in space are deflected by the presence of energy gd6 shortest paths in space
Are deflected by the presence of energy. That's kind of a version of what's happening in general relativity, okay
So now let's look at these multi-way graphs
so the the derivation of the einstein equations and the
Deflection of gd6 by the presence of energy is something we can do on in terms of our
You know rewriting of hypergraphs and a bunch of mathematics associated with that
So it's sort of a mathematical result from that
Now something very analogous to that mathematical result is also true for the multi-way graph
and what then happens is the gd6
Essentially in branchial space the shortest paths in this branchial space
Are also deflected by the presence of energy momentum
Okay, so this is where it gets that's really fun because the the the sort of the
You know the sort of a good core formulation of quantum mechanics is the Feynman path integral
And the Feynman path integral says you look at all these possible paths of history
And you say the phase the quantum phase associated with the path of history
Is you know e to the is over h bar where s is this quantity the so called the action
Which is a an integral of Lagrangian density
Which is essentially the aversion of the amount of energy momentum in a particular region of something
Now in our world that that's a particular region of branchial space
effectively the density of energy momentum in branchial space
Leads to the deflection of gd6 in branchial space
And so what does that mean if the if the position in branchial space is the phase of the quantum amplitude
That means the deflection of a gd6 is a change of phase
And the Feynman path integral is precisely telling you that the presence of energy momentum
Leads to a change of phase in a quantum amplitude
So what it's saying is the sort of the the bigger picture here is that the the same mathematics
That leads to the Einstein equations in space time
Leads to the Feynman path integral in in multi-way graphs and branchial space and so on so in a sense
these two sort of fundamental principles of 20th century physics
General relativity and quantum mechanics and our models are basically the same thing except that the
General relativity is a story of what happens in space time and
the
In quantum mechanics the story of what happens in what we sometimes call branch time
The thing you get which is the sort of class of branchial space
together with time
So this might be this might be a very unfair question
But I think there's something super simple that I am missing here, which is I just don't see where the negative numbers come in
I hear you saying that
There's this position in branchial space as a phase and I get that if that is true you get the result you want to have
But why are there a little bit more complicated?
I just the simplest possible
Explanation for the negative numbers would make me happy in other words the reason why you can
Interfer as well as add your probabilities. Let me explain. Yeah, I explain so so let's say you're doing a double-slut experiment
Okay, the photon can go through one slit. It can go through the other slit
Those two possibilities
The question is
Where do those different possible paths for the photon? Where are they in branchial space and physical space?
They're going through two slits the question is where are they in branchial space?
If those two possibilities wind up
At essentially the same point in branchial space
That is that they end up with the same phase
If those two things wind up at opposite ends of branchial space
Those two possible paths of the photon end up in two radically different pieces of branchial space
Okay, so what so the issue is how does an observer?
Observe what's going on. So this is again. I'm afraid there's another level of concept. We have to have here
Which is how an observer
Makes sense of what's going on in the quantum universe. Sure. So the one of the issues is
When you are an observer embedded within the universe
you
Well, we can talk about spacetime and causal and the
Let's forget spacetime for a second in this in this world of multi-way graphs and branching and merging and so on
One of the things that's a little bit brain twisting is you as an observer
Are also branching you're part of this multi-way graph
So the question of quantum mechanics is how does a branching brain perceive a branching universe?
So in other words, your brain is branching just like the universe is branching
Okay, and so now what you have to do and this is where for example
The idea of a single thread of experience a single thread of time is important
Because the whole notion of us as observers is we have at least the fiction that our brain doesn't branch
We have the fiction that definite things happen
And so the question is how do we implement that fiction?
And then is the is our implementation of the fiction consistent with what we actually observe in the world
Okay, so the way that we a convenient way and this is an idea of jonathan gorod who's one of the people who's been working on this project is
The the what he calls the completion interpretation of quantum mechanics
Okay, and what it has to do with is
Imagine we've got a branch
But then say but the observer has to corral those branches together in order to believe that something definite happens
So how is the observer going to do that?
What the observer does is to just say i'm going to imagine that these two branches are equivalent
I'm just going to make a mathematical equivalence between them
And then i'm going to see what consequence does that have for my view of the universe
Okay, and and so that's the thing
So it might be the case that the view of the universe knitting together these branches would rapidly become incredibly inconsistent
But this causal invariance property implies that eventually these branches will merge
So eventually it's going to be okay
But the question of whether the observer can kind of speed that up
And say no i'm going to insist it's okay right now
Even though it might take a century for these branches from different parts of the universe to merge
It's okay to think of them as merging right now
So that's a that's a consequence mathematically of this causal invariance idea that it's possible to do that
But so in that interpretation what you're doing is you're essentially making completions
That try and corral back together these different branches of history
Okay, so what happens if the two photons wind up at opposite ends of branchial space
Basically, what happens is you and as an observer have to construct completions
That basically complete the whole universe
Because you're trying to get from one end of branchial space to another you're trying to knit everything together
And that means basically that photon as far as your concern isn't there
Because and so that's so essentially the reason that you're getting
You know destructive interference is that you as an observer simply can't knit it together to say there really is a photon here
It's like the photon has been just smashed
Into into pieces that are scattered over all over branchial space. You know what I could say
I actually did understand that
Even though I wasn't necessarily expecting to but
Uh, it seems and maybe this is again an unfair comment, but I'll let you riff on it
It seems like just like we thought we needed interpretations of quantum mechanics in the 1930s that somehow we need interpretations of
hypergraphs or growing hypergraphs. I mean it
The the story you just told which I'm perfectly willing to grant gets you the double slidics, etc
Does seem to involve some metaphysical
Interpretational steps along the way
Fair point. I mean this is this is why
This is a fundamental point in in our models
If we were not
Roughly the way we are we would not conclude that the laws of physics are the way they are
So consider the case of the gas molecules again
If we were one of these little demons that's able to compute everything about the gas molecules and do all those things
We wouldn't conclude that
Thermodynamics and hydrodynamics work the way they do. That's right. We would say
Oh, actually we noticed that these little correlations of of of molecules here and more on the other
And we'd get a completely different conclusion
So the fact that we derive quantum mechanics is a consequence of the fact that we are roughly the way we are
Not in detail with two eyes and you know all this kind of thing
But but in you know, so and in particular the fact that the branching brain
Perceiving the branching universe has the idea that definite things happen
That's critical if we didn't have that notion
And you can think about it in terms of how our brains work, you know
We got all these neurons firing all over our brains
And in a sense there wouldn't be any real reason to think that there will be a definite threat of experience that we have
It could just be you know, there's all these different things happening all throughout our brain
And it's you know, this is a this is a fundamental feature of our experience of the world
Is that we believe there's a definite threat of time and so yes, that is necessary
And you know, I think without that and it's interesting to think about it
You know, what do the aliens so to speak think physics is like?
Because you know, for example
It it matters probably that we are roughly the size we are it mattered that we have this notion of single threat of time
Um, you know, I I don't think we would recognize the aliens so to speak if they didn't have something like a single threat of time
It doesn't just doesn't you know, I'm fond of making the comment, you know
The weather has a mind of its own, you know
It's got all this complicated hydrodynamic processes happening in the atmosphere and so on but yet
We don't have the idea that it has some sort of, you know, human-like consciousness
Usually at least depending on our animism our level of animism and psychism. Yeah
But so but would I be then correct to conclude from that that you think that from this kind of
fundamental setup with the hypergraphs and the updates and so forth
We could not get a universe that was fundamentally classical and had you know observers like ourselves in it
I think our models are very fundamentally quantum mechanical. I think that you can't really get, you know, what you can okay, so
What you would have to do is say there is only one okay, here's a way you can get something that's like a classical universe
And at first it sounds completely crazy, but let's say the universe was built using a Turing machine
So a Turing machine is this model of computation that has
You know, it's tape that has all this data on it and has this head that moves up and down
Along the tape and at any moment it's only doing one thing
It's only at the position of the head that anything changes
And so you could say imagine a universe
Where the where the Turing machine does a definite thing. Let me think about this for a second
Um
Yeah, I I let me think about this
Is that right? Well, okay, so you can certainly imagine setting it up so that there is only one possible thread of time
Because the Turing machine is an ordinary Turing machine and for every state it gets into it has only one possible successful state
Um, and so you might say and so that would be a kind of degenerate form of model like ours
That is classical. Yeah, okay. That's fair
But but usually what's happening is there are many different places where things can happen
So there are many choices of what can happen
What what what you do
Now what you do next et cetera, et cetera, et cetera
And you know, I keep on I'm sort of dancing around one issue which we haven't talked about which is the notion of causal relationships
Between updating events. So we've got two different updating events
And we could say which one happens before which other one
Well, if one of them
Specifically if the output from one of them is used as the input to another one
Then it better be the case the one whose output is being used occurs before the one that needs that output as input
Right. So that defines a certain ordering on certain events have a definite ordering
I mean in physics terms, those are the time like separated events
Um the uh, and those those are events that are necessarily time like separated
so then then there are other events that
Could happen you could decide that you're going to say these two events happen simultaneously the the spacecraft landed on mars
Right as I was eating lunch so to speak and you know, that was those were considered in the simultaneous events
So one of the issues is given this
Set of events that are happening
There are certain causal relationships that is one event must occur before another event and you can make another kind of graph
A so-called causal graph that represents that net of relationships
And just to make things more complicated in the multi-way graph
There is a multi-way causal graph
Which says there are these events happening and events can be separated
They can either be time like that is one event must occur before another event
They can be space like in the sense that they can be at different positions in physical space
Or they can also be branch like in the sense that they occur on different branches of quantum history
And so all three of those things are possible time like space like branch like separation
and that's uh
And in fact the interplay between those things gets pretty interesting when you start talking about
You know things in black holes and adf cft and all this kind of stuff
That that's that's that's how though those kinds of things seem to come out is the relationship between
Time like space like branch like separated events
I mean you hinted at this a little bit, but uh, maybe to concisely say how you would characterize
The solution to the measurement problem of quantum mechanics in your view
I mean, there's a standard list of options with many worlds and hidden variables and dynamical collapses
Are you different than all of those?
probably
I mean, you know, I'm not sure because I I think that um
Let's see. We have a much more microscopic view of what happens in measurement
Because we're trying to describe the whole universe. We don't get to say
Here's my quantum system and then outside of my quantum system is my measurement system
Everything has to be part of the description that we're giving of the universe
And so that's that's the first big big difference now. I think
um
If it depends what you mean by what the quantum measurement problem is
So one one thing that I think is a a significant piece of the quantum measurement story
Is why do people think that definite things happen?
And um, so what essentially is going on is different quantum measurement different quantum frames
cause people to believe at some moment that different things have happened
But there's some sense in which there is a global consistency to what must happen
So again in other words, so so the fact that there are two different outcomes from this measurement
Is a consequence of the fact that the observer
Can have defined two different quantum observation frames
And that is what causes those different possible outcomes from the experiment
It sounds like you're in some sense your closest in spirit to many worlds in the sense that
Someone who believed in hidden variables or dynamical collapses would say that there just is one outcome for every measurement
You don't need to think very hard about it
Right. No, that's correct. I mean this this does not have that idea this this has the idea that the outcome
Is in a sense based on the the frame in which with which the observer observes it
So in a sense, it's kind of like a many worlds thing where you know, which branch did you go on?
But the the difference is in a sense that in our situation those branches always eventually merge
So in other words, even though you've picked a particular this observer at this moment has got this outcome
That there will be eventual consistency in how the universe behaves
Now, you know, have we figured all of this out? Not completely
Let me give you an example of where sort of the frontier of what we understand and don't understand
So an obvious question is what does it mean for quantum computing?
So in quantum computing, there's kind of this notion that has been around since
Since I first studied this stuff around 1981 or so that gosh in quantum mechanics
There's this, you know, all these different possible paths of history
And I happened to study this with dick Feynman
So he was very into the multiple paths of history idea because that had been his his idea for a way of setting up quantum
It does make sense
It's like just think, you know, if you could get this this computation to not just go in one
Not just do one computation at a time
But follow all these different possible paths of computation
You could in parallel work out all these different different results and you'd be able to, you know, factor in just fast
We didn't know about that at that time, but those kinds of things
The so so the idea of quantum computing, you know
The big hope is just use all those paths of history to do a different computation on each path
But the you know, the next question is in the end
We have to observe what the answer was
And so in a sense, we've got all these threads of history that have all split apart
They're all doing their different things
We've got to corral all those threads of history back together again to make a definite measurement and say what happened
And so in our models, we can actually ask what is microscopically involved in corraling those those threads of history back together
And so in jonathan's setup of this completion interpretation
We have at least a model of that
Which is it involves these these completions these places where you assume that two branches are connected
And by the way, the mathematical underpinning of that somewhat interesting the the mathematical underpinning comes from the theory of automated theorem proving
Which is might seem irrelevant
But it isn't and so the point is when you have in mathematics
You say there's some axiom system you say, you know x plus y is always equal to y plus x
You know x plus zero is equal to zero it's equal to x and so on and then you say
Given those rules
uh
Is it, you know, can you prove that?
x
I don't know x
You know some some some results in algebra
Can you can you prove that results by by just and you say can I one way to think about that is can I get from one algebraic expression?
To another algebraic expression just by making this series of moves that correspond to applying particular axioms
So then if you say well, i'm starting off from one expression
Now, let me apply those axioms in all possible ways and build up this whole graph of possible outcomes
Well, what you build is precisely one of these multi-way graphs
And that the the space of possible results that you can get starting from one expression
What can you get as a multi-way graph and so automated theorem proving is the question of
The proof of a theorem is a path that goes from one expression to another expression
So automated theorem proving is about finding that path
And so completions become the formation of lemmas
So in mathematics you would say let's make a lemma that where we assume where we where we prove that this particular thing is equal to
This thing and that's a piece that we'll use in our big proof
And so these completions are essentially lemmas
They are their assumptions about how the universe works
That we are that we as observers are making and so one thing we can then ask for the quantum computing case
Is how many such lemmas do we have to produce?
Do we how much effort of knitting together the structure of branchial space?
Do we observers have to do in order to conclude the result of the quantum computation?
And it seems we're still nailing this down
It's still a little bit messy, but it seems that you can never win with quantum computing
That is that when you branch out in all these different ways
The effort to corral things back together is at least as great as the gain that you get from things branching apart
Now, you know to really nail that down
We have to get ever better models of the observer and that's just not something that traditional models of quantum mechanics
Traditional interpretations of quantum mechanics. They are out of that business because they just say
And the observer works like this
External to the quantum system, but we have to be more microscopic
And say no, we're actually going to describe how the observer is working
And so our best model so far is Jonathan's completion interpretation that
That involves these potential lemmas being produced. I'm sorry
There's a traditional understanding in well, there's an understanding in traditional quantum computing that there are some problems for which quantum mechanics
Certainly gives you a speed up. Are you saying that's not true in your model?
Yeah, I think I think it's not going to be true. That's my guess
I think what's going to happen is, you know, if you take like Shaw's algorithm for factoring
Yeah, which is primarily a quantum Fourier transform
The you know that Fourier transform is done beautifully quickly because there are all these threads that are running in parallel
The problem is every thread is somewhere in a different place in branchial space that thread
But us observers, we have to corral all those things back together again in order to tell what actually happened
And that's you know, so there's a you know, usually in quantum computing one just says and then there's a measurement
Now in in actuality when you have an actual device
You have all kinds of issues in making that measurement all kinds of how quickly does it deco here all these kinds of things
There are all these kinds of very practical experimental
You know features and I think people have generally said given the formalism of quantum mechanics
It you know, it's like well all this quantum stuff happens and then boom
We do a measurement and the boom we do a measurement is actually pretty difficult in practice with actual experiments
But people have said but you know if we do these experiments well enough
It'll become the mathematical idealization that you know von Neumann and others made about how measurement works
And I don't think that's going to be true. I mean we're not sure yet
But it seems likely that there will be no way to do to sort of that
If you're honest about how the measurement works the measurement takes effort
But are you saying that that's going to be a generic result about even conventional quantum mechanics?
Or is this specific to your approach?
Um, if you could if you could study how measurement works well enough in quantum mechanics
Yes, the problem is in in traditional quantum mechanics
It's like this is all the quantum. These are all the quantum amplitudes and the hammer comes down
And it's you know the born rule or whatever and that's the end of it
Um, and and so you don't you don't get to look inside that measurement process
And when people you know, I'm I'm probably not you know
one of the strange things that's happened to me in this physics project is that
You know, I I knew about everything that was going on in physics
Not everything perhaps but a lot of things 40 years ago
And then I kind of went to sleep for 40 years and woke up again
And it's remarkable. It's it's really cool actually to see you know a lot of stuff really didn't change
And some stuff advanced and it's like, you know, I used to know the masses of all these elementary particles
You know the mass of the lander is 1115 mev and now I look it up again. It's you know 1114.962 or something
It's like that's um, uh, so, you know, there are things like that and they're also also mathematical ideas and so on
But I'm not sure that I would know
everything that people have done and kind of
Sort of models of quantum measurement, but certainly back when I last knew about it in in great detail
People were sort of starting to say and then we take the small number of quantum degrees of freedom
That we're looking at as the quantum system and we let that sort of spread out in a larger number of quantum degrees of freedom
Where eventually it will become unambiguous what happened
For essentially thermodynamic reasons. Yeah, because it's it's more or less like, you know
What happens in the gas getting randomized and in fact, this was a thing dick feinman and I worked on back when we were
We were both consultants for a computer company in boston and we were
I was insisting that we try to do something useful and we try to invent a quantum randomness chip
And so we tried to think about how would you make?
You know and those days one gigahertz seemed like an impossibly fast
Cockrate for this chip, you know, how would you make quantum randomness that one gigahertz?
And what we realized is, you know, you have this little quantum effect
But then when you measure that effect you have to amplify it into a sort of classical number of degrees of freedom
And that process in order for you to have an unambiguous result in in order for successive
Bits that you measure to be uncorrelated
You have to essentially have essentially sort of a thermodynamic phenomenon going on
You have to be you know, it has to randomize then that that randomization has to not be correlated with the next thing
It happens and that was that that was to me the first sort of sign
That there was going to be a cost to measurement so to speak
Well, if you if you start a podcast of your own you can have me on and we can talk about interpretations of quantum mechanics
And that would be fun, but okay, you can teach me all about
But I mean, I think that that that does help me understand a little bit because what you're what you're saying is that it's possible that your approach
Um has a different attitude toward let's just say the measurement problem of quantum mechanics
So the next obvious question is do you have a different attitude toward the schrodinger equation towards the unitary evolution?
I mean the conventional schrodinger equation is continuous in time and you're not continuous in time
Are you getting the schrodinger equation as an approximation or is there some sense of which it's exact?
Yeah, right. So so it's very similar and we don't know all the details of this yet
But let's talk about the spacetime case
In the spacetime case
We've got these atoms of space and we've connections and so on
And we're looking at things on a large scale
And what should happen is that just like in a fluid where the molecules are bouncing around but on a large scale
We get the fluid equations on a large scale. We should get the Einstein equations and that's what theoretically
Theoretically we should get now when I say theoretically this is, you know, when physicists do mathematics
They're really sloppy and you know, there are many limits that have to be taken
Of um, uh, you know, it's the these these there's a certain amount of computational
Reducibility which leads to a certain amount of randomness which leads to certain statistical averages
working out in a certain way when you look at the
You know the distances have to be large compared to the elementary distance between atoms of space
And small compared to the size of the universe and the curvature has to be small blah blah blah blah blah
A whole bunch of conditions
But with all of those conditions in physicists level mathematics, we can derive Einstein's equations
Now it's worth pointing out that the effort to derive the fluid equations from molecular dynamics
Has been unsuccessful for a hundred years
That is with with a level of you know
We can derive Einstein's equations with the same level of kind of mathematical rigor that you can derive the fluid equations
Which is to say it isn't really mathematically rigorous
But if you take all kinds of limits that that and one advantage that we have actually one big advantage
That I always forget is that we've done endless simulations
But we actually know what limits work and what don't right so it's not like it's just let's hope this works based on
You know some mathematical
Sort of hope it's it's like we we ran an experiment with a billion cases
And this is what happened so we can kind of check those assumptions
But but okay, so so what then happens is what we are saying is that
The from this kind of microscopic atoms of space thing
When we do that when we look at that on a large scale we reproduce steinstein's equations
So one of the things that we've been doing recently
Jonathan has been much involved in this has been saying well, what about practical numerical relativity?
So people study, you know black hole mergers and they do that by taking
You know the the the structure of the black holes and they say we have steinstein's equations
which are partial differential equations and
Then we will but in order to make those work on a computer
We have to discretize them because a computer deals digitally with with
sort of digital elements
and
So then you make numerical relativity where you've made some kind of mesh
That represents some approximation to spacetime as
You know approximating the spacetime of steinstein's equations. So that's kind of the traditional approach
Now what we're doing instead is to work upwards from the atoms so to speak
So we're saying instead of going down from the steinstein equations
Just come up from this kind of structure of this this hypergraph
and and
Look at you know, what is the aggregate behavior of all these atoms of space?
The neat thing is that it actually works and it's a practical method for doing numerical relativity
So and in fact, it's looking really promising to
As a and what's interesting. So this is now a general relativity just a side comment for general relativity
So one thing you can ask is so obviously in our simulations
The
We have these atoms of space and we simulate on a computer
I think the extreme kind of amusing version is jonathan has been doing all these simulations on his laptop
Just to prove that that's possible
Which I think is totally crazy. Yeah, but so he has these simulations of black hole mergers and things done on his laptop
Using our models you could do a lot better if you weren't just using a laptop. But anyway the the um, uh, the thing
That is a so it's not obvious that we would be able to get enough approximation to continuum space
Just kind of on a laptop from our atoms of space rather than having to go
You know many many many orders of magnitude, but it seems that that works
So the next question is in physical space
Where might we see evidence of discreteness in spacetime?
So in other words the in other words, is there a way of making essentially a gravitational microscope that will
see into the structure of spacetime and so one of the things we've looked at
Is rapidly rotating back holes right close to the critical, you know close to j equals m
What happens and it's pretty neat because in these in these simulations that jonathan has
What you see is the thing eventually as you go above the critical angular momentum critical spin rate for the black hole
A piece of space simply separates
So okay another thing to explain is in our models of physics
This network doesn't have a built-in notion of dimension
So, you know our experience is space is three-dimensional, but this network
Doesn't have any particular number of dimensions that are built into it
It can be the case that on a large scale it approximates three-dimensional space
But because it doesn't have a fixed number of dimensions because it isn't
Microscopically a manifold so to speak it can do things like it can change its topology things can there can be tears that form in it
There can be holes that form in it and so on and or more extremely there can be pieces of the universe that just break off
And so what we see happening at for critical supercritical black holes is a piece of the universe just breaks off
and as
as it at the critical
Angular momentum what you see is that a piece of the universe is hanging by a thread
And so there are these small number of causal edges that essentially connect one part of the universe to others
And so it's conceivable that we may get some kind of
signature maybe in gravitational radiation
Of that discreteness, you know in physics terms probably shot noise
Associated with the fact that there is a that there are a small number of causal edges that are associated with that with that situation
So anyway, that's but that's just the general relativity case
In the quantum mechanics case, you're asking about the schrodinger equation
So the schrodinger equation has to emerge
As a pile of limits
From the things that we're doing because the schrodinger equation is a non-rotivistic limit of a et cetera, et cetera, et cetera
So the answer is I I think I mean, I'm sorry just to be just to be super clear
I'm using the generalized version of the schrodinger equation
That would be just as true for quantum field theory and relativity and everything just h psi equals i d by dt
Psi unitary evolution of the wave function, right?
So so we are
From the setup of these multi-way graphs and the interpretation of quantum amplitudes. We are guaranteed unitary unitary evolution
100 not as an approximation
that that
You think about that for a second
It's a little tricky because you have to define what the initial and final states are
And if you if you say I have the whole multi-way graph of everything
I think you're guaranteed it
But if you say if you say i'm going to make an i'm going to look at a particular region of spacetime
I think it's not so obvious. I think there. Oh sure. Yeah, that's that's that's just true and even in the regular schrodinger equation
So that I'm yeah, yeah, I think that I think let me think about that for a second. I think
that
Let me see. I mean quantum measurement is non unitary
That's a that's a thing that we that we have to deal with but a many worlds person says
That's just because you're only seeing part of the wave function in exactly the same way that you are
Right, right, but I'm a little concerned about the statement that the um, uh
See the
That the statement about the the way the hamiltonian appears there
In the in the non relativistic schrodinger equation is certainly not what we're seeing
So because we have a you know, our thing is sort of relativistic from the get-go
Um, and so what I think let me think about this for a second. Well, you could define it in terms of the path integral
I mean, is any unitary evolution from one one wave function to another one quantum state to another between an initial
Hypersurface and a final hypersurface. I think you inevitably get unitary evolution
But you have to define what those hypersurfaces are as you do and you know
As as you do when you merge your relativity and quantum general relativity and quantum mechanics. So I think it's um, I'm
uh
I think that's right. I I I would have to um
I mean the the part of this
Yeah, I think that that has to be that way
Okay, I mean the part that we've been interested in recently
Is can we make a practical scheme for doing quantum field theory in the same way that we can make a practical scheme scheme for dealing with
Einstein's equations
And so in a sense, you know, one of the things that all it encourages me in this project is
What I might call proof by compilation
That is the fact, you know, you say do you really get Einstein's equations?
Well, we can do numerical relativity and it actually works and we can do you know black hole mergers and things
So if Einstein's equations, I'll write them, you know, what we're doing is the same
and
In quantum mechanics, we've been able to do this compilation of quantum circuits
The next big challenge is to do quantum field theory and to do
And to be able to do things like few particle quantum mechanics
And you know those kinds of things
You know, for example, let me give you an example of how things got a little bit complicated
So in in quantum mechanics, you know, a very traditional thing is the harmonic oscillator
Just kind of the analog of you know, things bouncing on a spring back and forth
In order to get that in our models you have to have closed time like curves
So in other words to get a perfect harmonic oscillator
It's very easy to have a perfect harmonic oscillator if you have closed time like curves
In other words, if the if the history of the universe recapitulate if the history of the universe repeats itself
That's kind of how you get something like a harmonic oscillator. That's how you get the idealization of a harmonic oscillator
Now in the real situation in physics, we probably don't believe that there are perfect harmonic oscillators
We can decompose quantum fields into you know, as
Let's think of it as a sum of harmonic oscillators, but we're not imagining there's a perfect harmonic oscillator here
But if you say you might say and this is relates to the kind of reverse engineering versus building from the ground up
So to speak you might say gosh, how can you think you have a model of quantum mechanics?
If you can't even have the harmonic oscillator
But well, we can have a harmonic oscillator
But it's a weird idealization, which in our models shows up with with closed time like curves
And so that's you know, that's an example of how things get a little you know
If you insist on these idealizations
You end up sort of stressing
As I think you should you kind of stress the model. So it's similar to you know, if you said
I'm you say I'm studying molecular dynamics. Okay, so then somebody says well, why can't you get rigid body mechanics?
Why can't you get you know, this thing with a solid object that just moves around and doesn't distort?
Well, that's a complicated limit of molecular dynamics that involves, you know
Input atomic forces are large compared to the you know forces on the whole object blah, blah, blah
You know, it's it's um
That's a complicated story
And I think we're seeing some one of the things that's difficult about our model
Is that it attempts to be a model for everything so you don't get to say
We're going to have them of this piece. We're going to make a model for that piece
We're going to idealize away
You have to kind of everything has to come together and that means that seeing things like how does the harmonic oscillator work
It's a weird idealization. Yeah, that that does make sense
If you get exactly unitary evolution that is to say you get something like the Schrodinger equation
Um, I mean a many worlds person will say all there is is the Schrodinger equation. You just need to pick the Hamiltonian
Um and someone like me if I can indulge myself, you know
Our project is to start from a nothing but a Hamiltonian expressed as a list of energy eigenvalues and show how there's an emergent
Geometric structure that looks like a graph you get Einstein's equation and the whole thing
It's it's similar in spirit. Uh in that sense to what you're doing
But so then the question is
If you exactly get unitary evolution
What is the benefit to not just starting with quantum mechanics in the Schrodinger equation versus starting with hypergraphs?
Well, because you have a whole structure that you're building. So I mean for example when you say, what's the Hamiltonian?
You know
That better come out of our model. So for example, you could ask which we haven't discussed. What is energy in our model?
Okay, this is one of the things that surprised me
I thought energy was going to be a very difficult to derive idea
That was going to require notions of what particles are and so on and so on and so on
It seems that energy is very simple
it's basically the amount of activity in the hypergraph
And a little bit more formally
It's the flux of causal edges through space like hypersurfaces and it's concerned and it needs to be said
I mean that so a causal edge is
Is a is a causal connection between two updating events?
And so the question is if you have a
You have to say it a little bit more carefully because if you say it's the density of activity
It's what the heck does density mean when we don't have a notion of space yet
So the more formal thing is energy is the flux of causal edges through space like hypersurfaces
momentum is the flux of causal edges through time like hypersurfaces
and
the
um
Actually, you you now make me wonder and I don't think I know the answer to this
What is the flux of edges through branch like hypersurfaces?
I should know the answer to that and I don't immediately know and that's that's um
That that's related to okay
So so the point here is there's a I think see one of the things that's interesting in our models
Is the relationship between quantum energy and classical energy?
Because in our models, it's the this notion of in classical energy
It's the you know, you've got this single thread of history
You've got this causal graph associated with that thread of history and you're asking this flux of causal edges
But now you can also have this multi-way causal graph
Which not only has space like separation of events, but also branch like separation events
So events can be separated in in in in branch of space and in and in physical space
and then the idea is that quantum energy
is that activity in
uh
in
This whole multi-way graph
So it's the amount of activity in the multi-way causal graph
And so then like the Lagrangian is this relatively invariant
That this is the you know the Lagrangian density is that
that kind of
You know relatively invariant notion of the amount of activity in this multi-way causal graph
And so for example one one little mystery that this
Seems to clear up is the thing if you look at the Planck length
You know the characteristic length people often talk about for where
Sort of quantum mechanics and gravity have to kind of come together
In our models the elementary length is much smaller than the Planck length
And in the a typical thing is the Planck energy
Well, whereas the Planck length is you know 10 to the minus 34 meters or whatever it is the the Planck come
The Planck energy
Is 10 to the 19 electron volts if I remember correctly gv
And um
What's that 10 to the 19 g e v g e v. Okay. Thank you
But it's about the you know, it's about the energy in a thunderbolt or something and a lightning strike
It's huge not a very small quantum thing
um in our models
The elementary energy is also small
because the elementary energy is
an individual causal edge in the multi-way causal graph
And the fact that what you observe
Is is this thing that the the analog of the Planck energy is something that has been average
That has been sort of summed over all possible branches in this multi-way causal graph
I mean, this is maybe this is a footnote. Don't forget this
This is just a there's just a part of the the story
But but so you're you're saying
Why do we care about this whole structure that we're building? Why not just put a hamiltonian in there?
and what i'm saying is the um
For for listeners who don't know this hamiltonians and lagrangians are closely related. Sure. They're they're sorry
We did that I think for you and me. That's pretty obvious, right? Yeah, that may not be um
That may not be obvious
But but in some sense you're like we said there's a simple set of rules that you start with and I mean maybe maybe I can just jump
I'm going to try to guess what you're uh thinking here and then you can tell me whether I'm right or wrong
There's an infinite number of hamiltonians I can write down
But at least for simple ones there's a finite set of little rules that we can write down for our hypergraphs
So maybe there's a map from the set of rules to hamiltonians
But it's a very very, you know one, you know few to few rather than covering the whole space of possible hamiltonians
Right. Well, so this is a good question
As you look at
simple
You know rewrite rules for hypergraphs
You get some set of hamiltonians if you say oh, I'm gonna have a million line program to represent my rules for the hypergraph
Then you're going to get some other, you know, you can kind of custom engineer
Whatever hamiltonian you want probably got it. Okay, so it is not self-evident, you know
What kind of hamiltonians you get?
From simple update rules. We don't entirely know so for example
It looks like we get ones that show local gauge invariance
And then we have to ask, you know, and that's a that's a, you know, if you just pick your average hamiltonian
There's no particular reason for it to have local gauge invariance
But in our models it probably does
And so that's a good sign now, you know, will we get
You know, what other attributes will we like our hamiltonians for the universe to have?
Well, I mean, you know my approach here is to just say let's see what we get
And for example, okay, so here's one of the complicated things
So the hamiltonians that you will typically write down in in in quantum field theory. They are
The things that are in those hamiltonians, Lagrangians, whatever are quantum fields their quantum fields that represent
You know
Field operators that correspond to particular particles
Right, so there'll be an electron quantum field. There'll be a photon quantum field and so on
Now in our models, we're not yet talking about particles
So those
Hamiltonians have to be
What we have is a description of things at a much lower level
Than a place where you've got actual field operators for particles
So for us that what are the particles the particles are locally stable
kind of
Defirmations in this in this hypergraph. So for example an analogy in fluid mechanics
If you say what's like a particle in fluid mechanics, well a vortex
You know a kind of whirlpool like thing in a fluid that is locally stable and it can move through the fluid and it can
Trap with other vortices. It's something vaguely similar to that in our hypergraphs
More a kind of topological structure
That is some kind of not yet very well understood
feature that is locally stable under the rules
And so when you talk about field operators that would occur in, you know, your average
communal garden particle physics Lagrangian
those
field operators are effective
descriptions of
These deformations these topological
These topologically stable objects in this hypergraph the hypergraph is a lower level description
And so it takes, you know, it's not obvious
And it's a very good question and we don't know
You know, how does
How does the thing that looks like it operates in terms of particles?
How does that emerge?
You know, what kind of things that look like they're in terms of particles emerge from this lower level structure because because in our models
You know
All we have at the beginning is the structure of space
Particles are just features of the structure of space
And they are, you know, so there's an underlying dynamic
I mean one of the things that sort of a little shocking in our models is that most of the activity of the universe
Is is associated with the maintenance of the structure of space and has nothing to do with all the particles that we observe in space
So that that's a and so what what?
I mean
So it's a it's a it's a very reasonable question
How the Hamiltonians that we're used to in particle physics emerge as effective Hamiltonians from this underlying dynamics
And we don't yet know the answer. Well, you know, I mean you mentioned the particles
As something that does come out as these persistent structures. So
But but as you certainly know
Quantum field theory the the usual modern physics way of saying things is that fields are somehow more fundamental when you perturb them and excite them
You get particle like things. There are
Circumstances, you know, like the condensation of the Higgs field where the particle language is not appropriate
Is there is there a view toward a more field like ontology coming out of this?
Well, I think that okay, so again, this this is if we say
When we talk about particles in particle physics
They are as you say sort of, you know, what we imagine is oh, there's a particle. It's not interacting with anything
It's you know, it's separated from everything else. It has a definite momentum
It is a definite mode of the quantum field and when it comes close to other particles
Then, you know, it gets more complicated and there are other modes of the quantum field that get excited
And eventually some other particle goes out and you observe it in a particle detector, but the the
So for us we have to think about what do those scattering experiments look like?
What is an experiment where you have that separated particle?
And this is one of the cases where, you know, the we are building everything from the ground up
So we don't get to say. Oh, it's just a separated particle in the vacuum. So to speak
It's a an excitation of some kind
Embedded in the space that is that has a lot of activity in it. So so for example when we talk about
You know, so one of the things that I'm wondering is will there be bizarrely different kinds of stable structures
In our hypergraph that aren't like the particles we're used to
So in other words, you know, you mentioned the Higgs field the Higgs field is a case where we have this condensate
Where we have a sort of uniform value of the Higgs field throughout space
And that's you know, that's a simple case. There are, you know, people know about, you know, soliton type solutions to field equations
And you know, there are other kinds of things like that and one of the possibilities is that in our models
Particularly because we have this dimension variation that there might be bizarrely different stable structures
That could exist in the context of our models that don't seem like particles of the ordinary kind but that wouldn't mentor
And things like that might be something bizarrely different. Maybe it's even related to something, you know
Maybe it's related to dark matter for all we know
I mean, it's just something that could exist
As a as a sort of stable feature of our universe that goes beyond just the structure of space
But it has a form that we don't yet don't yet understand and I think I mean in in
The the other thing to realize so in standard particle physics
We talk about virtual particles, you know, you can they're always part these particle antiparticle pairs that
That are sort of popping into existence in the vacuum for a very short time and then annihilating
So in and and one of the features of that it's always been somewhat mysterious in quantum field theory
Because quantum field theory says there's an infinite number of these virtual particles that are occurring all over the universe
And that corresponds to effectively a very high energy density of stuff in the universe
How can that be?
How can it not in einstein's equations say, you know, whenever you have energy
You're going to curl up the universe with, you know, gravitational attraction
Associate without energy. How can the universe not curl up into a tiny ball because of these vacuum fluctuations of virtual particles?
Well in our models the those the sort of limiting case of those virtual particles
Is these actual?
rewrite rules in our
In our hypergraph
So in other words the this sort of the ultimate version of all of those virtual particles
It's just all these little rewrite rules in the hypergraph
Which in our models are exactly what create the structure of space
So in a sense that makes it a little less mysterious
That, you know, all of this virtual particle stuff doesn't have this terrible effect
This terrible gravitational effect on the universe
Now you can ask things like, you know, can you imagine how the Higgs mechanism works and all these kinds of things?
And yes, I've thought about that and there's a there's a certain amount you can say
I don't think we we we can't um
I mean, I was very disappointed when the Higgs particle was discovered
I kind of knew it was going to happen
but it was it was um, uh, it was kind of like like it's kind of a hack and it's disappointing that
You know, it it looks
So far the Higgs mechanism looks like a hack
And the question is can we make it look less like a hack and that will be really neat
So one little footnote is that uh, you might be interested in work by tom banks and willy fishler who have
Emphasized within the context of more or less conventional quantum gravity
The point you just made about the cosmological constant that we should not think about it as the sum of all these virtual fluctuations
We should think of it as an input a boundary condition
They call it that uh, just sets the size of space in some sense. So that's more in line
I think with the philosophy that you're thinking of. I knew tom banks, but when we were both at the institute for advanced study in the
In probably 1980 or something. I haven't I'm great. I'm glad he's I'm glad he's doing interesting things
and then the and the other point was I mean
I don't want to dwell on all of these, but I presume that
If your program pans out we will want to find
Solutions to the classic puzzles of particle physics
So not just the cosmological constant problem, but the hierarchy problem, you know, the strong cp problem barrio genesis
Are these the kinds of things I'm guessing that I would have heard already if you would solve them
But maybe are they solvable you think within the program?
Uh, you know eventually they should be I mean we can we can start sort of teasing apart what each of them involves
I mean, you know the oh, there are three generations of particles and um, you know
The question is what's generic and what's not so the surprise for me is that general relativity and quantum mechanics seem to be generic
Just as thermodynamics is generic
And the question is how far does the generosity go?
Because I wouldn't have expected
Well, for example, I wouldn't have expected the the detailed form of Einstein's equations to be as generic as they seem to be
so, um, and you know, it could be
I I'm I have this vague suspicion that
The structure of the gay local gauge group might be generic. I might be completely wrong about that. Yeah
Well, that that you can hope um, I I I don't think the three dimensions of space are generic
I don't think the three for the three dimensions of space is generic
Um, whether the you know, there are bizarre possibilities like, you know, maybe the two threes are related
You know the three generations and the three dimensions of space may be
Uh, you know, and I don't know. I mean that that's uh
These things are all certainly possible. I think that when it comes to things like, um
Well, one example is cpt invariance
So that's a the question of why is there cpt invariance and I can explain a little bit about that
We don't know completely
I mean, so in sort of in the stack of things you need in particle physics
A big feature of particle physics is fermion versus bosons
You know particles like electrons put a fermion and have the exclusion principle don't want to be together versus photons which are bosons
and are very happy to be together and
Those are distinguished by the, you know, the spin statistics theorem says if you are an
You know, if you're a half integer spin particle, then you will be a fermion
And if you're an integer spin particle, you'll be a boson
So one question is what are fermions and bosons in our models and can we derive the spin statistics theorem?
And that's an example of a sort of
You know one of the achievements of quantum field theory is the derivation of the spin statistics theorem
and so for us
Fermions versus bosons. We have a guess. We're not sure the the guess has to do with
In these multi-way graphs
We suspect that bosons are associated with in a sense
Branches that merge very quickly and fermions are associated with branchings that do not merge quickly
And so that's what leads you in a sense the the branchings that don't merge quickly
Wind up with opposite sides of branchial space things that can't happen effectively or things that are not observed to happen
and and in fact at a mathematical level it is the the
You actually will then sort of see the fermions are kind of the square root of the bosons
Because the fermions are it just branches. It doesn't do the it doesn't merge as well
Whereas the bosons are both the branches and it merges
and so now the question is can we relate that to
Rotational symmetries that are associated with with the spins and so on and looking promising not done yet
but looking promising
so then then if we can do that then we can derive the spin statistics theorem and
uh, then the next question is well cpt invariance just to explain for people the the um
This is a a fundamental symmetry that's believed to exist in quantum field theory
Is if you turn particles to anti particles you reflect space
and and you uh reverse time
Then you'll always get something where the laws of physics work the same way
So for us
Again, it's kind of neat because it seems like
C charge conjugation, which is particle to anti particle
is
effectively like
It is an it is an inversion in branchial space. It seems to be in other words. It's a reflection in branchial space
Uh
Uh parity is a is a reflection in physical space
And time reversal is a reflection in time
And so what this is saying is in the end that our multi-way causal graph is invariant under
Uh a reflection in all three of those
In all three of those uh those directions so to speak now we we so it's at least a very clean formulation
Of what it means to be cpt invariant
Whether we have not yet shown that we necessarily get cpt invariance
But at least we know what it corresponds to but that gives some sense
So so when you ask about cp violation, for example
That's still a little ways away because we don't yet understand cpt invariance
um
In in regular quantum field theory cpt
Invariance is tightly connected to lorenz invariance the invariance under boosts and and so forth
I'm guessing that
In a discreet graph model lorenz invariance must be once again
Approximate right and and they'll be at some point even if it's very very
Experimentally inaccessible where it will break down
Absolutely. There is a maximum boost you you can't get you know, there's a in other words as eventually you start seeing the granularity of spacetime
Yeah, so you can you can do um
and so
Yes, the the um the relationship between
That is that is in fact the derivation path that we're aiming for is causal invariance
in the ordinary causal graph
Leads to ordinary lorenz invariance
And the guess is that some kind of that causal invariance in the multi-way causal graph
Is associated with the essentially extension of lorenz invariance that is cpt invariance
So that's that that's the guess about how it works
Right. That's yeah, we don't we don't know if that's really and you know, obviously cpt invariance is a complicated story
in general activity and in non
You know non
Non, you know non flat spacetime and so on and and no doubt we will run into those issues
There are very good experimental limits on lorenz violation from different propagation speeds of photons of different wavelengths from gamma ray bursts
They can put limits up to the Planck scale, but as you said your scale is much tinier. So it might not be anywhere close
Right. I mean, I think the thing that I'm most interested in with respect to those propagation experiments
is finding
Kind of dimension fluctuations in the universe
Because in our models the you know, there's no reason for the dimension to always be three
In fact, one of the things that's a possibility is so one of the more bizarre possibilities again not properly explored
Is that the Einstein equations are usually formulated in terms of change of in terms of the
Change in curvature of space
One possibility is you might be able to say that curvature is always zero
But the dimension changes and that's and it might be that those are there is some mathematical equivalence between those for small
Curvatures small dimension changes
But but but you know one of the things that we suspect in our models is that the universe started infinite dimensional
And only gradually sort of cooled down to be three dimensional
And so that then a lot of the problems about you know
These horizon problems in the early universe and so on disappear because when it's infinite dimensional
Everything is closely connected. The the graph distance between things is small
Now the suspicion from this is that as it cools down to be three dimensional
There may be dimension fluctuations left over and so obviously, you know
The question is would those be visible at the time of recombination?
Can we see that in the microwave and the cosmic microwave background?
Of course, we don't know but the the the first question is what would a dimension fluctuation do to the cosmic microwave background?
And then if there was a dimension fluctuation that exists
In the current universe, what would it do to the propagation of a photon through that dimension that region of dimension fluctuation?
And I this is this is a piece of in a sense classical physics
That I keep on meaning to work out and I keep on hoping somebody else is going to work it out
Because it's kind of like that. I've been I've been collecting this inventory of of laws of physics in d dimensions
Well, I think I mean, I'm just guessing here because I haven't thought of it myself, but um
If the effective dimensionality space is not exactly three
Coulomb's law would not be exactly true. And wouldn't that have dramatic effects on qed scattering rates?
Um
Well the question is something like the thompson cross section, for example does how does that depend on so
uh, I am
well, you you're
You're correct that in d dimensional space
So so the way to think about I think proton propagation
Is using huygens principle where you're saying that every on this wave front of a propagating
Propagating, uh, you know light wave or whatever
Every every point on that wave front is a source of a spherical wave
That is going to build up the next piece of the wave front
And if you are in d dimensional space where d isn't three
Those little spherical waves have a different, you know, there there's a different density on those spherical waves
So to speak when you project them into three dimensions
That's at least my thinking about how to do this now
question is
So the question is so so in particle physics
Back when I used to do particle physics a long time ago. I was a big enthusiast of this method called dimensional regularization
Which is the idea that you know
Well, you're doing an integral and if it's if the dimensionality of space time is four the integral diverges horribly
But if we can only say it's four minus epsilon
We can do the integral and then we take the limit epsilon goes to zero at the end
So I'm sure I've worked out back in the day what the low-energy electron photon scattering cross-section is indeed dimensions
And that's uh, that would be a good
Uh, that that'd be a good case to look at. I mean, I think that that that I will not be surprised if there is some
Thing that one can some fairly sensitive test of the dimensionality of space. For example, I don't know and I've been meaning to look it up
what
uh, the anomalous magnetic moment of the electron or the muon
You know, it's it's one minus alpha over two pi. But that certainly depends on the dimension of space. I just don't know how
Yeah, there's probably some sensitive particle high
High precision particle physics experiment that that is uh sensitive to that so, okay
I think I only have two questions, but they're both huge questions. So I suspect they're going to take more than two minutes each
but uh, one of them is you you
Referred to this idea that in the early universe, uh, maybe we have some
Bundle of dimensionality or dimensionality is not well defined and that sort of comes out in the wash as the evolution happens
um
So I've thought very much about the arrow of time problem
But I've thought about it in the context of fundamentally reversible
Directionless laws of physics, which is a little bit different from where you're coming from. So for me the huge question is, you know, we're
Evolving toward an equilibrium
Empty space situation where all the galaxies are all dissolved around and we have nothing around us
But the cosmological horizon and that's the highest entropy state
Uh, but we came from 14 billion years ago a very very very low entropy state and in conventional cosmology
There's just no good explanation for that except the papers I've written and even those are not universally accepted yet
But it sounds like you have a possible completely different point of view where
It's just natural that you start with what we would expose fact or label low entropy
So I think the the discussion about entropy is kind of confusing
Okay, that's my first statement
I I remember actually I remember having these vigorous arguments with Dick Hyman about this very topic of whether the universe was
You know, he made this claim the universe is a fluctuation
You know the fact that we are in in the state where we're not kind of you know
Where we aren't at sort of the maximally disordered state and I kept on saying that's just a completely crazy claim
Because it's like everything we know is a fluctuation
So, you know, I think I I would be more eloquent these days than I was back
I'm on your side. Yeah, and um
And explaining why that was such a such a
A wrong idea, but anyway, no the first the first thing to understand is that
People say oh, you know, eventually the universe will kind of unwind and there'll be nothing interesting in it
There'll be no structure in it. It will all just be in a high entropy state
Okay, my claim is the reason you say that is because you're not an adequate demon
That is in fact
In the future of the universe if it turns out that it's all just seems like a gas and equilibrium and so on
That you might say that's completely boring. That's all just random. It's the high entropy state
But to another kind of observer they might say but look at all those little details about what's happening
This is the most amazing complex structure that you can imagine
I mean, I I happen to think if we if we ask
What will we look back on this time in scientific history and say how could those guys have missed this point?
My guess is one of the bigger things will be when people describe something like a gas and thermal equilibrium
They just say it has a certain pressure and temperature
They don't consider any other features of the gas. They don't say
Oh, it's got the little microscopic, you know
Things that we can measure in this way and that way
But my guess is that there are a lot of other features now this question of are they computationally boundedly observable?
Are they are they measurable by a computationally bounded observer? I don't know the answer to that really
Um, but the the the point the the claim I'm making is that when you say it's going to a high entropy state
You're saying oh that all you're saying is so I as a as an observer of the kind of observer
I am
Can't make anything out of it other than to say it's uniform and random
I think I'm actually saying more than that. I think in this case
I'm going to disagree with you because I think that it actually goes to the vacuum quantum state the
the bunch Davis vacuum of decider space it's it's
It's a dissipative system because there are
There's a horizon around us and within our horizon all the excitations above the vacuum
Go away and and there is no structure there to be seen by any observer
Computationally bounded or otherwise. What do you think is in the vacuum?
Well, it's a single quantum state thinking in quantum mechanical terms. It's a unique
The lowest energy state that's
So I would claim that's the mistake and it's it may be interesting to try and take that apart
so in our models
The very fact that there's space there
Space is a thing in our models. You have to make space. You don't just get to say
Oh, there's this big area of space
Space is made of something and in our models space is made of this sort of teaming collection of atoms of space doing all these
complicated things
So our vacuum cannot be just the boring. There's nothing there vacuum
Our vacuum has to have a lot of structure in it. Now if you ask the question if you say
Every particle excitation has gone over the horizon. That's what you're basically saying
So let's think about that for a second. What does that mean in in our models?
So horizons in our models are visible in essentially
Breaks in the causal graph. So the causal graph says this is the you know causal effects can propagate between these
Between these at this event can affect this event can affect this event
And you make these light cones where one event is having an effect on a whole sort of increasing size cone of other events
Right. So what is a what is an event horizon an event horizon?
Is and you literally see this in our models when you run them and like these black holes
You can literally see the event horizon and it's a place where the causal edges
For example in a black hole the causal edges go one way
The causal edges go in and they can't come out
And that's it's very concrete
And so a cosmological event horizon is something where you're separating in the causal graph
You have two different regions of the causal graph
And they are you simply have no causal edges that go from one side to the other
So what you would be saying is what what you're claiming is every particle excitation has
Somehow is is in a region of space that is causally disconnected
From the region of space that that we care about so to speak
So I think my my statement would be
I mean your claim is an interesting one because
Basically what you're saying is that all the big particle excitations all these sort of identifiable topological excitations
Will be gone and outside the you know outside of this event horizon
Now what I would be saying is that in order for there to be space inside there there still has to be stuff going on
Now what so what this turns into is an argument about
Is is there
Stuff that is there useful stuff in that region of the universe and by useful stuff
You might say it's this complicated topological structure that represents a photon
But that depends on you know, and so you say the observer an observer
That you know about right now is observing things like photons is observing these big complicated topological structure
But you know in terms of the pure underlying structure of the universe
You could still have all these little atoms of space doing their thing. It's just maybe
Maybe it's smoothed out enough
Conceivably that there aren't any of these sort of identifiable topologically stable structures that still exist there
That's a possible that's a possible kind of and then the observer would have to be at the demon level
So to speak in order to observe that there's anything interesting happening there
And not at a level if the observer is made of particles for example is made of photons
That might be the case that you you couldn't get with an observer made of photons
You simply couldn't get information about that more microscopic structure
So, yeah, I think we should postpone this to either an in-person conversation or me appearing on your podcast because
It does get kind of technical at some point, but I don't want to
Not give you an opportunity to talk about the beginning of the universe. You talked about the end there
But is there is I
I'm going to guess that you're going to say that there is a principled reason within this approach to
Start in what looks something like very roughly the big bang
Well, okay, so the question is what you know in these models
Okay, this gets us into another
This is a deep rabbit hole that we're about to enter but but let me let me say a few things about it because it's something
I've recently been thinking a lot about the the um
so
The
Okay, so in these models
You might imagine that the universe starts as a fairly small
Hypergraph and gradually expands
And so one of the mistakes I've been trying to not make
Is kind of a repeat of the einstein mistake so to speak because in our models the most natural thing is that this hypergraph
Just expands dramatically with time. Okay, and you know, I'm I'm not
I I have a great tendency and this is kind of a reverse engineering type tendency to say no
No, there's got to be these other rules that reduce the size of the hypergraph so that it doesn't expand insanely
You know just like einstein was saying well, you know, even though the einstein equations predict the universe should expand
Of course, we know it doesn't expand except it turns out actually we discovered it does expand
So i'm trying to not repeat that mistake, but um, uh, you know, I think that the current
Expectation would be that just as there's a simple rule
So also there's a simple initial condition and that is a small hypergraph
And which is something that doesn't really even define a dimension because it's just a tiny little hypergraph and it starts expanding
And at the beginning that expansion is like, you know is is uh, uh, is something which effect
It has high dimension then it goes down
So one of the things we've been trying to do which is probably more in your in your day job wheelhouse
So to speak is we'd really like to know what the analog of the Friedman Robertson walker
Model of the universe is
For dimension change
So we were pretty sure that there is a an analog for a homogeneous isotropic universe
That there's something just like the usual model just as it's homogeneous and the universe is homogeneous and isotropic
So what does the scale factor of the universe? What does the you know?
How does that how does that work with time?
We're pretty sure there's a directly analogous thing that describes dimension change in the universe
And that will be the effective equations that describe in our models the very early universe
Yeah, I think
There it's actually i'll just sort of mention a couple of things for your benefit as well for the audiences
If you want to imagine you have a bunch of dimensions that start small and some of them start expanding
There's a very set of cute models from brandenburger and wafa
Based on string theory, but they have a way why only three
Dimensions of space would start expanding and it's basically because you can tie your shoes in three dimensions
But not in four dimensions, right strings will generically intersect in three dimensions
But not higher numbers of dimensions. So that was there. I wrote that down. I'm gonna look that up. That's yeah, that's a fun one
The dual of that the converse was actually
By me and lisa randall and matt johnson where we showed how if you start with
Higher dimensional decider space you could actually create a sub universe with fewer
Microscopic dimensions by spontaneously compactifying some dimensions. So I think dynamically given curve space time
You're allowed to go either way you can have them all small and let some grow or you can have them all big and let some shrink
Oh, that's interesting. I mean, you know in the question is if it's homogeneous and isotopic
Whatever the generalization of that for dimension changes
What I expect is that there's going to be some equation that eventually will have the dimension and the scale factor in it
And it will be a only those things. So you don't in the things you were just describing
There's presumably non homogeneity because you're saying that there are some, you know
Pieces some dimensions that grows some that shrink and so on this will be kind of the the homogeneous isotropic analog of that
I mean, I think this is a in a sense
This is a quintessential not particularly easy mathematical physics problem
But it is in a sense. It's it's the reason one reason it's not easy
And it's perhaps of perhaps interesting to say is that
Calculus which is what all of this stuff is based on is a story of changes with respect to a variable like time
But in our models and you know when people do multivariate calculus
They're doing calculus with you know with two variables or three variables
But they never get to do calculus with two and a half variables
That's not a thing and nobody knows how that works
And so in our models what we effectively have to do is go below the level of where we talk about variables
And we're actually in our hypergraphs
You can think about a direction in the hypergraph as being like a variable
So as you move through the hypergraph in a certain direction, that's like a variable
But if the hypergraph is a big mess, it's not obvious what you mean by a direction
If the hypergraph was a nice orderly like crystal like thing, then you'd have a well-defined notion of direction
But in the actual hypergraph you don't right and that's some and that's kind of where you begin
I mean that there needs to be a generalization of calculus made
That works in fractional dimensional space on these hypergraphs and so on and that's kind of the that's the technical difficulty of this
But but that's I mean it's interesting. I'm I'm I'm gonna look up that that that reference
That's that's very useful. Well good and and I think this leads actually very naturally into the final big issue
I wanted to address
Which is locality and you know you talked a lot
I think even though I never got to sort of specifically ask
I think you've done a good job of explaining how spacetime arises and einstein's equation and general relativity and as you said
Three dimensions doesn't seem to magically come out
But maybe we can figure that we get it with the right rules so that that's future work good
But locality is an interesting thing by locality. I just mean the fact that in space
The laws of physics for the most part have the property that if you poke the system in one location of space
The effects ripple out locally right only to nearest neighbors as you go forward in time
So that's one thing you might want to get out of an approach like yours is that you have this notion of locality
Quantum field theory is based on locality
But in the real world, there's at least two interesting places where we think locality breaks down
One is in quantum measurement with bells inequality, right?
And the other is potentially in quantum gravity with the holographic principle complementarity adscft
So what is your feeling about how you can thread that needle of getting enough locality out of your rules but also
slight deviations from locality when you need them
Okay, my current guess is the following in space and physical what in these hypergraphs
We are saying there's a a certain
clump of
Of nodes in the hypergraph that have this structure. They get transformed into one of that structure
That's an essential local in space in the sense that it involves this local region of nodes in the hypergraph
Okay
Now there's two kinds of locality one is spatial locality and the other is bronchial locality
In other words is it and so my guess is and the way that things like bells inequality that the violation of bells inequality
come out is through
non
That that
bronchial space
Is differently laid out than physical space physical space
We we know in this hypergraph that it's you know, we are we are choosing to a rule
That is local with respect to the hypergraph
But the question of what counts as local in this in in bronchial space
Locality is a different story
Locality is a story there of well, it's it's just a different kind of thing because it involves these the ancestry
Ancestry in the multi-way graph and so on so I think that the the story there
is
Locality in bronchial space is a different issue and for example, you can ask what's the analog of a light cone in bronchial space
So in physical space, you know, you make a perturbation somewhere it expands at the speed of light
What happens in bronchial space? Well, it also expands at finite speed in our models
And that means there is a maximum entanglement speed in quantum mechanics
and
That the the value of that we only need we only have one parameter we really need
So if we knew the elementary length
Or if we knew the elementary time or the elementary energy right or if we knew the maximum entanglement speed
Any, you know, any one of those parameters is enough to determine the length scale for our models
But the this maximum entanglement speed is saying in bronchial space
you have a
One vague estimate that we have is the the
Maximum entanglement speed is 10 to the 5 solar masses per second
I don't know if that's correct. That's based on a very hokey
Calculation that I did which makes a bunch of assumptions
But it gives you some sense of scale if if that was the right value we would observe
We would observe
limitations on black hole mergers
Of big black holes or very rapid mergers that are associated with maximum entanglement speed rather than speed of light
So in a sense, it's a limit of the rate of quantum measurement or the rate of quantum
Effects and so one question is
Which which we were just thinking about recently
Is can we actually bound in other words in in these violation of bells inequality experiments where you're looking at?
Propagation of physical space and you're saying it seems to happen instantaneously in physical space
Well, the reason that's happening is because that propagation
So to speak is actually happening in our models in bronchial space
Which is a different story than physical space
But if we knew the maximum entanglement speed we might be able to make bounds
On that speed in physical space, which would mean that even though
You know these these various bells inequality, you know entanglement experiments and so on are
Are much, you know, they seem instantaneous so to speak that actually there might be a finite bound
We're not sure about that yet
I think it's probably not exactly the same, but this is certainly
Spiritually a similar answer to what an ever-ready and would give to the whole bells inequality
Question there's there's not a unique
measurement outcome in in space
So the the rules that bell was assuming do not necessarily apply
right, I mean, I think that so
In so by the way, this maximum entanglement speed has all kinds of consequences. So for example, you can have entanglement horizons
so you can have a a
Essentially a horizon in bronchial space
And so one of the things we suspect but we don't yet know is that there's an entanglement horizon outside of the
physical event horizon in black holes
And so what that means is so so far we can get black holes in our single thread of history
You know not dealing with multiway causal graphs
It's just a technically difficult thing to do the analogous
Calculation for a multiway graph, but we think we'll be able to do that and at that point
We will see black holes that have an event horizon in physical space
And an event horizon in bronchial space
And so the question is and that is an interesting thing because you know
If you think about the propagation of information in the history of a black hole
There's a question of can information be trapped between the entanglement horizon and the physical event horizon
And that and so one of the questions is if you're an observer falling into a black hole
And you're you know, when you when you're an observer falling into a black hole to the outside world
You know time has stopped for you know your and so the question is what's the analogous thing that happens in the entanglement horizon?
And I think what happens is kind of cute
I think what happens is that the observer at the entanglement horizon cannot form a classical thought
So sorry from the from the observers point of view, they just fall right through though in classical gr
Yes, yes, right, but to a person correct
So that is to a person far away from the entanglement horizon
They would conclude that the observer at the entanglement horizon could not form a classical thought
So that means they could never in the in the sort of traditional quantum mechanics world
They could never collapse the wave function. They could never and so what would happen is for them
You know that they're observing, you know some virtual particle pair, you know
You know did that did that electron go into the black hole or not?
Well, they don't know because they can't form the classical thought
To determine whether it went into the black hole or not
And so that's how that's our kind of at least qualitative thinking about
uh
That's sort of black hole information paradox kinds of things in our models
I I would suspect that that that um, I know I haven't worked on this
but Jonathan Gorat has worked a bunch on the er equals epr
story in our models and
Claims that he is about to produce an actual sort of explicit
Simulation of an er equals epr thing
So that that um, uh, which has been I mean, it's an imminent claim. So it will have to arrive in the next
That's fine low
I mean maybe by the time the episode comes out, but it does remind me of a potential and I promise is the last thing a potential
quantitative question
The entropy of a black hole is its horizon area divided by four measured in plank units according to Hawking and Beckenstein
Someone like me would interpret that as saying that the black hole is described by a factor of Hilbert space
With a dimensionality approximately e to that number
But the plank length is not fundamental for you
Is there any chance that you would be able to calculate the Beckenstein Hawking entropy and get the right answer?
Yeah, that's an interesting question. So I mean in
Uh
You know the notion of what black hole entropy is what is entropy
Entropy is basically a measure of the number of states the number of microscopic states of a system
Consistent with the macroscopic thing that you identify as being the system so to speak
So this is basically saying given this thing that we say is a black hole
How many possible microscopic states are consistent with this macroscopic observation that it is a black hole?
so
I would think
That we should be able to compute that
um
And let me think how would we
uh
Yeah, I mean I can imagine how we would compute that. Um, and I think it will you know what we have to do
Okay, so in spacetime
We can see these event horizons in the causal graph you can explicitly
I've even studied them a bunch and you can see all kinds of exotic black holes inside black holes and all kinds of
Interesting and wild things that can happen. Um, but uh, the I just I started looking at the multi-way version of that
It's just computationally hard
Because that what's happening is you you you get these, you know, it's for the exact reason you've got this big exponential in there
Yeah, you've got this, you know all these different threads of history that you have to account for
And as I say, there is an optimization of this that another person working on this project max piscinoff has been working on
For most of the last year actually, um, which is the theory of local multi-way systems, which are systems. So
So, um
The idea is okay, so so roughly the idea is the following so you have
In when you're looking at this causal graph that represents all these different events and they're happening through time
And you say i'm going to take a slice of this causal graph at a particular
What I consider to be a particular moment in time
Then I've got a structure of space associated with those causal connections and so on
That is that is getting us a version of space
When we also have this multi-way graph
There are
There are many different configurations for space
But so there's this notion that I was calling multi space
Which is this thing where every place in space
There's also the essentially this stack of multi-way possibilities
And what's difficult is to understand we can say, okay, there's this multi-way graph and the whole universe is one node in this multi-way graph
Or we can say we've got one path in the multi-way graph and now we're going to look at what happens in space
But the the the thing we're trying to do is to see how do we get a representation that knits those two things together
Where we are looking at
locality in space
And essentially locality in branch real space
And being able to sort of have those two things combined if we can successfully do this
I'm pretty sure we can do essentially numerical quantum field theory and we can do it in
You know in the traditional way this is done. It's either Feynman diagrams or it's lattice gauge theory
Lattice gauge theory is an imaginary time
Which is kind of a you know, not great
And in in this in this setup
We will be able to do it in actual time
And and we'll be able to do it and then you know the question of whether we see
Sort of perturbation theory and Feynman diagram is a story of what happens with our
You know with our topological excitations and so on that might be a more complicated story. But anyway, that's a
Uh, yeah, I mean the the thing that's really
To me
You know just tremendously exciting about this whole thing is you know, there's this underlying structure
And we keep on being able to figure out more and more stuff. It's not easy to figure out these things
But it's like nothing is we're not ending up running into something where we say, oh my gosh
That's you know, we just can't explain that that's just a thing which just is you know
Totally orthogonal to what our models are saying
And that's some and the other thing that's happening
Which I think is that we keep on running into things which say, oh, that's just like causal set theory
Oh, that's just like, you know, constructor theory or whatever. Oh, that's just like one of these other
theories that's been developed and what's you know, to me both
intellectually and sociologically
A terrific thing is that you know the results that people have developed in these theories
Like take causal set theory for example
There's been kind of a mystery, you know, you're just throwing down events in spacetime
And you're saying just look at the relationship between those events in a causal graph
But there's been kind of a mystery. Why are the event thrown down in just such a way that you get Lorentz invariance?
Yeah, well in our models we have an algorithmic procedure for generating those events
Which immediately gives you Lorentz invariance
But yet the all the mathematics that people have done in causal set theory
Which works on arbitrary collections of events in spacetime can be applied to our models
And so that's a that's a really neat thing and I'm you know, it's looking and the same thing
I mean, we've been
In higher category theory is another, you know, very elaborate area of mathematics
Which is I mean our stuff is a concretization is a concrete instance
Of higher category theory and all kinds of rewards that exist in higher category theory that have been extremely abstract
Basically, my test is I can now understand a bunch of these results
Which I've never been able to do before
So because they have a concrete instantiation and you know, one of the things which we which we are not going to have a chance to talk about here
But the question of of um, which we sort of started to talk about is why this universe and not another one
You know, why does this universe exist at all?
That we seem to be able to have some things to say about
And it turns out that it's all to do with this limit of higher category theory
Which turns out to also be this limit of running all possible rules in a multi-way graph
And these are things related to this thing
called the infinity groupoid, which was
you know
introduced by this chap growth and deke who was a very
Abstract, abstruse mathematician
And I never thought I would have any reason to care about the infinity groupoid
Except that it seems that it is the limit of a bunch of our models
And it seems that it's it's deeply related to a lot of things about sort of
Why this universe and and why does the universe exist anyway?
And you know just as a teaser of something we're not going to have a chance to talk about but but one of the things that I've been excited about recently
is
Just as we are making this sort of
foundational model for physics. I would like to make a foundational model of mathematics
And we're talking about the set of all possible rules for a physical universe
You can also talk about the set of all possible rules in mathematics
And one of my recent conclusions is if we believe that the universe exists, which presumably we do because that's a notion of existence that we
Are pretty familiar with then it necessarily follows that mathematics exists
In the same way and that our doing of mathematics
Is kind of carving out pieces of this kind of structure that is all of mathematics
In much the same way that we're kind of carving out pieces of the universe to observe
But anyway, that's a that's a that's a a coming attraction as yet
I mean what I want to do is to find a bulk theory of mathematics
In the same way that we have bulk theories like relativity and quantum mechanics and and physics
Well, I can I can tell you that uh, it was just a couple months ago that we had a podcast episode with emily real
A mathematician from johns hopkins a category theorist and we talked about the infinity groupoid
Oh, good. Very good. We talked about the infinity groupoid, which tells me both that there's a unity to all of knowledge
But also there's a plenty of room to go, which I think that everyone
Listening to this episode will definitely get that impression. So steven wolffron. Thanks very much for being on the mindscape podcast
That was fun. Good stuff