Hello, everyone. Welcome to the Mindscape Podcast. I'm your host, Sean Carroll.
I bet that most of us out here have had the experience of trying to put together a bookshelf
or something like that from IKEA or from wherever, some somewhat complicated piece of furniture or
something to have around the house for which you get blueprints, instructions, as well as pieces,
the raw materials, right? And so we have a certain paradigm in mind about how something
complicated like a bookshelf comes to be. There's a blueprint, a set of instructions,
there's stuff that we're going to put together, and there's some agent, us, that does that work.
It's very natural then, because we're familiar with that kind of process, to think that something
like that also happens when you put together a living organism, right? When you put together
a person or a whale or a tree, there is some blueprint set of instructions, which presumably
is in the DNA, right, in the genome of the organism. And then there is some agents putting
them together, presumably the proteins that get their information from the DNA via the RNA,
and they go off and they build things, and voila, you get an organism. So it turns out,
it's almost not at all like that pretty much, okay? That's some truth to the idea that there are
instructions or information contained in our DNA that will go into constructing an organism such as
a person. But the actual process by which it happens is much more nuanced, much richer, not quite
that simple paradigm we have in mind of an instruction kit and agent and some raw materials.
And partly that's because, you know, we are not intelligently designed, right? This whole system
that we have in us of DNA, genome, RNA, proteins, the organs that we have, the cells in our body,
this all evolved in a complicated process and whatever kinds of dynamics and process was
important and useful as far as evolution is concerned is what we ended up using, okay? It's
not supposed to be code in a computer where it's carefully commented or anything like that, it's
just what was thrown together and what eventually got used. And as a result of that, biologists
keep finding ways in which the morphology, the shape and the way things are put together in
organisms comes to be in fun and different ways than you might expect from the simple Ikea paradigm.
So our guest today, Michael Levin, is a biologist at Tufts University and it's actually a little
bit difficult to describe what he specializes in because it's kind of many different projects that
are all fascinating to me. But in the overall space of talking about how information and physical
dynamics come together to make organisms and all their different functions and things like that.
Not only does it help us understand the particular features of organisms that we know and love,
but to someone like me who cares about emergence and different levels of description of reality,
it's fascinating because we can start asking questions like, at what point is a decision
being made by an organism or by the processes that are going into making that organism? Is it
anything like a computer? Is there a separation between hardware and software? What is the role
of memory? What is the role of dynamical processes? All these fun questions. So we're going to be
talking about how cells, how information and how organisms all fit together. I'm not sure that I am
capable or qualified to draw a single unified theme from it, but I think you'll find that it's a
fascinating conversation that touches on many kinds of things we've been talking about on
Mindscape for quite a while now. So let's go.
Michael Levin, welcome to the Mindscape podcast. Well, thank you so much. Pleased to be here.
This is an interesting podcast for me to think about organizing and talking about because you
do so many different kinds of things. And I finally hit on a starting point of asking you about
one of the experiments you described in your papers with the Xenopus tadpole. I think that's
how you pronounce it, the Xenopus. You basically, if I understand correctly, you in your lab or
your collaborators rearranged the face of a little baby frog tadpole and it somehow,
nevertheless, grew correctly into the right shape. Is that roughly speaking correct?
Yes, that's correct. And I do think it's a pretty important experiment and it's one that we can
definitely form this conversation around because it illustrates something very important. So it
used to be thought because all tadpoles look the same and all frogs look the same that basically
what the genome could do is somehow encode a hardwired set of movements that would transform
a standard tadpole into a standard frog. So the idea would be that the nostrils, the eyes,
the jaws, all these things have to rearrange themselves to become a frog. And so what we
did was a start out by making something we call Picasso tadpoles where everything is in the wrong
place. So the jaws might be off to one side, the eyes might be on the top of the head or
everything is sort of mixed up and we can talk about how we make those. And then the remarkable
thing is that they largely become normal frogs. So all of these little pieces that make up the
head and the face will move in novel unnatural configurations until they land in the correct
positions to make a frog face. And so what this is telling us is that the genetics in fact gives
us a system that's very good at reducing error. That what it does is continuously work to sort of
reduce the difference, the delta between the configuration you have now and the configuration
that it in some way remembers as a correct frog face and that things stop moving and stop proliferating
when that error is sufficiently small. Yeah, which is a remarkable way of thinking about it
because it's probably not what most people have in mind. Well, I say most people, I mean me,
you know, not being a biologist myself. I mean, I think that we think of what's packed into our
genome as roughly the equivalent of the instructions you get from Ikea or something like that, right?
Here are some building blocks. Here are the steps you have to take in order. And at the end, hopefully
you get the finished product. But so you're saying it's not like that. No, it's absolutely not like
that. And on the one hand, we kind of already know it's not like that because if you actually,
and look, the view that you've described is definitely the kind of the mainstream perception
that everybody has. And I've given talks to nine year olds in middle school and so on. And when I
ask them what determines what comes out of an egg, you know, it can be a bird, a dinosaur, a snake,
you know, what determines the shape of what comes out of an egg, everybody says the genome.
And in a certain sense, that's true. But if you actually look at now that we can read genomes,
if you actually look at what's in the genome, you're not going to find anything in there about
the size, the shape, the type of symmetry of the organism that's going to come out. And what's
important to realize is that we currently do not have the ability to look at a genome and guess
anything about what the shape of the organism is going to be. Now you can cheat and compare it to
the genome of another organism that you do know what it looks like. But this idea that you can
read the genome and sort of understand what the anatomy is going to be is not the case.
And that is because the genome does have a recipe, but it's not a recipe for shape, it's a recipe
for proteins. So what the genome does is prescribe what protein hardware every cell in your body
gets to have. So these are the smallest sorts of building blocks from which cells build various
structures. And so it's sort of like you're not getting the design of the IKEA shelf,
you're getting a description of the metal that goes into the screws and the wood or whatever
it is that goes into the other part. It's a description of a very low level aspect of the
system you're actually interested in. Yeah, and it's what do you say we can't look at the genome
and see what the shape is going to be? Is that our fault? I mean, is it implicit in there,
but there's just a lot of steps? Or is it really that even in principle you couldn't look at the
genome and figure out what the animal is going to be? Well, that's a great question. So let's
think about what we mean by in principle. So if you were to sort of a laplace kind of simulate
all of the micro interactions, then certainly you could. If you take into account the environment,
even things like let's say turtles, which use external temperature to determine the sex of
the offspring, you could figure out what was going to happen. So in a certain molecular sense,
if you were to simply absolutely model the lowest level of physics, yes, it's in there.
But we would like to do something better than that. We would like to understand the encoding.
And from that perspective, it's not our fault in the sense that that's not what's encoded there. So
what's encoded is not the actual anatomical features. What's encoded are the proteins and a
little bit about the order in which some of those proteins will appear as a function of time. So
from that perspective, even though developmental biologists are doing a very nice job trying to
understand how all of these organs come to be, we really need to understand a lot more. And you
can sort of, an example you might think about is the kind of bell curve that you get from dropping
marbles into a Galton board. Where does the shape of that bell curve come from? So in a certain
sense, at a micro level, you could probably calculate it out and predict it maybe if the errors
were small enough. But in a larger sense, that shape is not encoded anywhere in the material of
the marbles or the definition of the board or anything like that. It's because what that device
is doing is harnessing particular laws of physics. And what embryos do and all living structures
do is they harness the laws of physics and the laws of computation. So this is very important.
And so what you get in the genome is the description of a very important and very
interesting machine, which is able to generate and process information exploiting various laws of
physics and computation to make certain outcomes. And what's super cool about it is that these
outcomes are reliable most of the time. So most acorns give you oak trees and most fish eggs
give you a fish. But actually, it's way better than that because it is not only robust to all
kinds of perturbations, but it's actually reprogrammable, which I think is one of the most
exciting aspects of it. I guess it's very hard for us to escape the metaphors that we use to
think about these things, like as if there were blueprints or an instruction manual in the DNA.
But the reality is more, I guess, like you're saying, the DNA makes RNA, the RNA makes proteins,
and the DNA is chosen not because someone wanted to design something, but just because
making these proteins in this right environment gets us the morphology, the shape that is been
selected for by natural selection. Yeah, this is correct. So natural selection, of course,
shapes the proteins that cells will use. I think a really good analogy, and we can come back to
the status of metaphors in this field because I think it's not quite what a lot of people think
it is. But one useful metaphor for this is the distinction between software and hardware.
So if you can imagine that if you had a bunch of electric parts, you could connect them together.
And if they were the right kind of parts, one of the things you would get would be an electric
circuit that might do something. And one of the things that might do if your parts included
transistors is that it might carry out logic functions. And so it might be able to carry out
certain operations that would be logic that from which you could build up all kinds of complex
computations. And so now you could ask where the laws of computation live. That's an interesting
question. Certainly, right? Certainly, you know, the operations of AND gates and NOR gates and
things like this were not in the electric parts that you got a specification to. But what evolution
did was shape the parts. And it shapes the parts in a way that when those parts interact together,
they make a circuit. And the part that we study in my lab is largely the electrical aspect of it,
which is why I keep coming back to these kind of electronics analogies. The amazing thing about
these circuits is that they take advantage of really interesting laws of physics having to do
with electricity and how that propagates. And the laws of computation, which allows cells and
tissues to make decisions and to have memory and things like that. And that's where evolution
really shines is to exploit these laws of physics. Right. But I guess what I'm trying to
understand better is this idea that there's no top down directing of what's going on in the
individual cells. I mean, the cells that make up my liver and my brain have the same DNA in them.
And they're just doing their production of proteins. And it sort of all fits together at
the end of the day. And it's not that anyone wrote software to do that, right? It's just that
the DNA that makes that happen is the one that gets passed on.
Well, I'll say two things about that. Certainly, no one wrote the software in the sense of some
sort of designer. So that's for sure. But I will say that this issue of top down control is tricky.
And what I'm about to say is probably not the mainstream sort of story of developmental
biology that you'll get from a textbook. But this is how I see it. If you look at it, it's
a multi-scale problem. So if you look at it from the scale of individual cells or molecules,
then that's basically correct. They are simply following sort of local rules about what they're
going to do. But I think the evidence is pretty good now that there is a larger level of organization
that you can look at. And this larger level of organizations at the tissue and organ level
is performing some interesting computations that deforms the possible action space for the subunits.
So what that means is that it basically alters the space of what's possible for the cells and
the molecular networks to do so that by simply following very mechanical rules, sort of minimization
of free energy and things like this, they end up doing things that are in line with a global
body plan. So you can look at things that tissues and organ level structures are doing
that are very large-scale computations and decision-making about things like, hey,
is our face patterned correctly? Do we have the right number of fingers? Are the limbs long enough?
And the outcome of those computations are instructions to individual cells to either
proliferate or turn on certain genes or turn off certain genes. And at that point,
the cells are just doing what the chemistry sort of suggests in the sense that there isn't
any magic there. But if you look at the level above, what's happening is that all of those
low-level reactions are being harnessed towards a higher-level goal that none of the individual
cells are capable of perceiving. So at the single cell level, there's no such thing as an arm or an
eye or anything like that. No single cell can perceive that. But the group agent, and so I
think fundamentally this is a problem of swarm intelligence and group cognition. The group agent
has very sort of rough memories of what the correct pattern should be, and it has the ability to make
decisions about whether or not the current state is close enough to the target state,
and if not adjust behaviors. So I think from that perspective, there is a bit of top-down control,
and we can talk about some of our worm experiments that tend to show this,
that is not in the sense of some sort of rational designer that writes software,
but in the cybernetic sense where there are systems that reduce error from a stored set point.
And so as long as they can remember what that set point is, they can then have this kind of
homeostatic cycle that harnesses the parts of the machine towards the goal, which is again,
not something magical, but is a representative target state towards which the whole system tries
to get to. There are times when we have a long stretch of time ahead of us where we're doing
something, but our attention is not completely absorbed. That's when Audible.com and their
audiobook selections can come to your rescue. I know that I've driven across the country several
times, and my favorite thing to do is to listen to ancient poems. I listen to the Iliad, the Odyssey,
the Aeneid, Beowulf, helps make those long highways in Nebraska fly by. If you'd like something a
little bit more modern, my own books are on Audible.com. I was the one who read Something
Deeply Hidden and The Big Picture. The other ones were read by others, so let that color your choices.
As an Audible member, you get one credit every month, good for any title in the entire premium
selection. And those titles are yours to keep forever in your Audible library. Now is the best
time to try Audible because with their Presidents Day event, you're getting one of their best
offers of the year, only $9.95 a month for your first six months. Just head to Audible.com
slash Mindscape or text Mindscape to $500, $500. That's Audible.com slash Mindscape or text
Mindscape to $500, $500. So is there a sense then in which the frog genome literally has
the shape that it wants, that has encoded in it, the shape that it wants its body and
its face to have? And then the large scale, whatever shape it currently has, reacts back
against that genome to sort of say, well, what do we do next to move us closer to that goal?
Is that the right way of thinking about it? That's close. I would say what the genome encodes
is a bunch of parts that when implemented in parallel, it makes a piece of hardware that
has a very reliable default behavior. That default behavior is a set of biochemical,
biomechanical and bioelectrical circuits that if nothing weird happens to them by their normal
behavior in their normal environment, they will generate a set of patterns that give rise to a
standard frog. And so the real outcome, if you ask the question of where does a frog face come from,
it's a sort of interplay of the constraints imposed by the genetics which specifies the machine
and the laws of physics and computation which exist around it. Now, there's an additional
factor as it turns out that this machine has some really interesting properties. It isn't,
evolution apparently doesn't just favor machines that only have one outcome,
but they favor, at least in many cases, it favors machines with a particular capability which is
a separation of hardware from software. What I mean is it's able to represent
different possible set points and what the cells know how to do really well is to build
towards the set point. And if the set point changes, you don't have to rewire the cells.
I mean, that's a really interesting, that reprogrammability is a really powerful
aspect of all this. I guess this is what I'm learning, not just from this conversation,
but from other podcast interviews I did with Carl Friston, for example, with his
free energy principle. I'll make a grandiose claim and then you can fact-check me here.
In many ways, the way that biological organisms work, either in sort of day-to-day dynamics or
evolution or development of the organism, is not this sort of Laplacian idea that you give me
exactly the state right now and I will tell you what direction to move in. It's this almost
teleological way of thinking about things. Just had David Hague on the podcast and he
wants to let us talk in teleological terms. It's like, rather than saying, if this, then that,
if this is where we are now, here's where we should go, it's like, well, here's where we want to get
to, figure out a way to get there. Yes, I think that's absolutely correct. I think
biology has been trapped in this teleophobia, which is doing us a great disservice. I think
it's completely, not only fine, but absolutely necessary to talk about those kinds of things.
I think that's exactly what biological systems do and we can talk about how I think this aspect
of goal-directedness, this multi-scale goal-directedness, is crucial for evolution. I think it's what
makes evolution work. It's what makes for much greater evolvability. I'm a big fan of Friston's
work. We've used it in our own research. I think it's absolutely correct in that not only do living
things have to predict their environment, but they actually have to predict themselves. Living
things are a patchwork at different scales of systems that cooperate and compete with each
other. Part of all of that is being able to guess what's going to happen next and having a
preference about what you'd like to have happen next. Everything is working towards minimizing
that delta from what it expects and what's actually going to happen. This is critical for
evolvability. I think those kinds of, what's important about that that teleology isn't simply
that we allow it or disallow it, but I think we need to move it from a philosophical problem,
which a lot of people have argued in a vacuum about whether it is or is not okay to talk this way
or whether all models in biology should be framed in terms of biochemistry and molecules and not
goals and things like this. I think it's an empirical. It's a very practical problem. The
question, it's a little like Dan Dennett's intentional stance, where it's very simple.
You just say, what level of intentionality do I ascribe to my system that best gets me
to new prediction and control? Sometimes you'll err on the side of attributing too much agency and
it's wasted and you can do better with a simpler model. Sometimes you're applying simple laws to
systems that internally have a very rich protocognitive structure that should be much better
off taking advantage of. I've argued that for regenerative medicine and just in our lab and
others, it's driven a ton of work to novel experiments that otherwise would not have been done
and to actually ask, what does the system know? What does it expect? What are the preferences?
What goals is it trying to achieve? This is on all scales of organization.
You and I are probably familiar with the distinction between in physics Newtonian mechanics
versus the principle of least action. I noticed that the principle of least action is actually
quoted on your web page. It's interesting because it's two different ways of conceptualizing
exactly the same problem and getting exactly the same answer, but from very different languages.
So maybe for the people out there who don't hang out on the wrong street corners and hear
about the principle of least action, why don't you tell us how physicists think about that?
Because it's clearly related to what you're saying about biology.
Well, I'm probably going to make a massive fool of myself here because I'm not a physicist.
I'm sure you are a much better place to give a proper definition of it.
But what I understand is that there are lots of physical systems and probably all of them
where one of the things you can do, so let's say trying to understand how light is going to
propagate through a bunch of lenses stacked one after the other things like that, you could go
after the micro details and try to use Maxwell's equations and things like this to really model
every piece of it and eventually you'll crank through and you'll get the answer.
Apparently, it turns out that you could get the exact same answer with a lot less effort if you
simply make an assumption that what the light wants to do is to minimize the effort, so to speak,
or the action that it will take to get there. That's a rough, that's how I understand these
things. And I think that's an incredibly powerful concept because asking about how much effort
does it take to compute something, I think is really important because when people, especially
in the biosciences where things impact medicine a lot, when people say, well, everything should
be done at the lowest possible level, and he said, well, you don't really mean the lowest,
you don't want to talk about quantum foam, but you really want to talk about his biochemistry,
right? That's often when people say to me, ah, you got to reduce, and you don't really mean that.
What you mean is you've picked a level and that level is biochemistry. And my point is you can't,
and this is people like Dennis Noble have been saying this much better than I, that you can't
simply pick a level because you like it, you have to pick the best level. And how do you know what
the best level is? And the best level is how much effort do I need to put in to control the outcome?
And in the case of regenerative medicine, that outcome might be we're going to replace a complex
finger or a hand that's way too complicated for anybody to build by hand from stem cells or anything
like that. So the question is going to be, to what extent is your system persuadable? There's this,
you know, I visualize this axis, right? On the one hand, you have things like cuckoo clocks,
which are not persuadable. You are, you know, if you want to make a change in the way that system
works, you have to rewire, you have to physically change the hardware, there's no getting around it.
And then you have systems way on the sort of on the right side of that spectrum, which might be
humans or they might be other kinds of advanced cognitive systems where trying to intervene in
their activity on the molecular scale is maybe possible. But realistically, you know, the sun's
going to burn down before you figure out how to tweak all the cells in a person's brain to get
this or that to happen. So there you're probably better off with stimuli, with experiences, with
inputs that take advantage of the cognitive structure of the system to convince them or
motivate them or train them to do various things. And then in between are all kinds of agents,
many of which we know, so animals and simple AIs and basic life forms and cells. And then
all kinds of agents that don't exist yet. I mean, I think one of the fun things to talk about is the
space of possible agents, which I think is going to be actually enormous in our lifetime. And
somewhere on that scale is the correct way to interact with everything you come into contact
with. And you really have to ask, what is the, what are, you know, are there goals that your
system is trying to achieve? And are you better off rewriting those goals or motivating the system
than micromanaging it? And I think it sounds it seems like physics is telling you at the
lowest level that this kind of stuff is already baked in. Yeah, I mean, I can't help but talk
about the physics and least action just a little bit more because it's really fascinating to me.
I mean, like we said, there is this way, I even did a video on this in my summer quarantine project
video series called The Biggest Ideas in the Universe about how you can either be Newtonian and
say, well, I know where I am now and all the laws of physics tell me is what to do next. Or you can
be, I don't know, Lagrangian or whatever it's called. You can you can say, well, of all the
histories I could have in the future, I will take the one that minimizes the certain function,
right, the action. And that latter one just seems a little magical. I mean, you're saying like,
well, how did it know? But you show that in fact, secretly, they're mathematically exactly the same.
It's just, you know, a matter of convenience. But, but the convenience is extreme when you're
when you become a modern particle physicist, you're constantly writing down this action, this
this thing that is the thing you minimize globally rather than locally. And it's just a much more
convenient way of talking about it. So I guess the question that is obvious to me now is,
is there a reason why it doesn't have something to do with the fact that biological organisms
are these multilevel systems where there's collective action from all of our tiny little
cells coming together? Is that does that help explain why it is convenient to talk in these
more global terms rather than just locally following the action of every little atom or
molecular cell? Yeah, I think well, I think there are there are two two aspects to this. The sort
of more metaphysical aspect is in which I'm not sure how much value this is, but I'll just say it
because it's it's something I've been thinking about is that if you ask yourself, you know,
let's say people who are who are into panpsychism or this idea that, you know, sort of some sort of
intentionality is everywhere fundamentally. What one of the problems that people often have with
this is that they scale down the physical system, they say, Okay, now let's consider a rock or a,
you know, something like that. And then they fail to scale down the intentionality that I think
I'm seeing is they say, Well, it's ridiculous to say that a rock has hopes and dreams. And
well, of course, it is so right. So what you need to do is you need to proportionally scale
down the cognition. So if you ask yourself what would intentionality or freedom in the sense of
indeterminacy look like in the simplest possible case, I think what you get is exactly what particle
physics is telling us. So so if you ask, you know, what would freedom look like at the most minimal
kind of instantiation, I think you would you would predict something that looks like quantum
indeterminacy. And if you ask, what does what would goal directedness look like at the at the
simplest possible layer of reality, I think you would get exactly what these action principles
look like. So from that perspective, I think I think it's a it's a it's a scale. And the way I
think it scales is this, you know, when we when we look at living things now, all we're seeing are
it's a selection effect, all we're seeing are things that survived the gauntlet of competition
and and selection. So we don't have any objects in that we don't see any living forms that are
not good at pursuing goals, those things disappeared very early on. Now, maybe we'll be able to create
some life that doesn't do that as as people work on synthetic, you know, origins of life and synthetic
life and so on. But any sophisticated life that makes it past, you know, the first few the first
few steps of competition is going to be great at pursuing goals in the very simple sense of
homeostasis. So one of the things that we're working on now is to try to understand the
scaling of goals from tiny homeostatic goals, like either chemical reactions that try to keep
certain entropic principles in particular ranges, or single cells like bacteria that try to keep
metabolic states in particular ranges. How do you scale goals from these very modest types of
goals to something that's much larger, like the goal of having a properly shaped hand or face
with particular, you know, and then how do you pivot the whole thing to from from early organisms
that, and in fact, still current organisms that execute goals in morpho space, meaning the the
space of possible anatomical configurations. And you sort of pivot you run the same algorithms,
but now your space is three dimensional space outdoors. So now you can run around and have
behavior and have goals that are, Hey, I'm going to run this maze because I remember the structure
of the maze. And at the end, there's some cheese and along with the way I'm going to do this and
that. So this this idea, you know, life has to start out with with homeostatic loops, I don't
think there's any way around it. And those loops scale into progressively more impressive goals
that what's what's what one way to organize all this is to is to ask yourself, what are the
spatiotemporal boundaries of the goals that any given system could potentially have. So it's
sort of like like think of a light cone, so to speak, that that says, okay, here, right in space
and time, here is the boundary of things I can possibly have goals about. So if you're a goldfish
or a tick, those both in space and time, it's rather modest, you can only conceive of things
that are right in front of you and not too far in the past. And you maybe have a little bit of
anticipatory ability. But by the time you get to great apes or humans, you know, you could have
goals that are that are that are massive in scale. And you know, you just just a huge both both in
terms of time in terms of memory and anticipation that you could be working towards things that are
going to happen long after you're long after you die and things like that. So that's one way
to organize all this is by the by the scale of the goals that these systems are capable of maintaining.
It can be hard sometimes to get up the motivation to start exercising. But once you get going,
it can be really thrilling. Peloton is an easy way to overcome that barrier to getting started
and staying motivated once you're there. Peloton has inspiring instructors, amazing music, endless
fitness variety and an engaging community. Whether you're looking for some extra encouragement,
structured workouts or just in the mood to laugh, their instructors are there to bring out the best
during each class. And with epic artist collaborations, and there's specially curated music, whether
you're in the mood for some hip hop, pop country, the Peloton bike has the right music to keep you
entertained and motivated all year long. With the all access membership, you get more like a family
plan for no additional cost, you can bring home the Peloton experience for your whole family with
access to their entire class library. So get started on your Peloton journey, go to onepeloton.com
to learn more. That's O-N-E-P-E-L-O-T-O-O-N dot com.
I thought of myself a lot about levels of description and reality. I mean, my book,
The Big Picture, just talked about levels a lot. And I'll be honest, I've always been very resistant
to the idea of causation acting between levels, downward or upward. It seems to me, and I think
this is just my fundamental physicist training kicking in, that levels should be autonomous
from each other. And I mean, you can derive one from another maybe, but they act differently. But
maybe I should just start thinking differently when it comes to biology or human scale things.
Certainly, the words you're using seem to indicate to me that you find it useful to
speak as if what's happening on one level, like organism wide or network wide or whatever,
is important to take consideration of even when we're talking about what's happening on lower
levels. Yes, I think that's true. And I think that actually, you may have seen this, but there's
very interesting work on this coming out of Giulio Tononi's lab and Eric Hall about
quantifying some of these things. So there's now math that will help you understand for a given
system, what is the causally most potent level at which to manipulate it. And it's not practical
to compute some of those things for a lot of real systems that we care about. But certainly,
there are techniques that we use all the time in the lab to ask what is the most appropriate level
at which to try to manipulate the system. And inevitably, it bleeds down into the lower levels
in the following sense. So in Plenaria, let's say, so we have these flatworms and they have one head
and one tail and you chop them into pieces. And each piece knows where the head and the tail are
supposed to go and it reliably sort of regenerates whatever is missing. So what we've been able to
show is that this is partly the result of a circuit, which is partially electrical,
which stores the pattern of what a correct Plenarian is supposed to look like. And we can now see this
pattern, we can rewrite it, we can alter it so that now the pattern memory says two heads instead
of one. And then that's exactly what sells Bill, Bill, two-headed flatworms.
I don't want to go over this too quickly because I know you do this all the time,
but this is just amazing to the rest of us. You can chop off the tail and head of this little worm
and train it to grow back two heads or two tails instead of one head and one tail.
That's correct. Yeah, it's an amazing thing. So Plenaria, basically, I think every important
question of life is found somewhere in Plenarian biology, I think you could say. They're an amazing
creature. First of all, they're flatworms, not roundworms, so they are bilaterians,
meaning they are similar to our ancestors. They have a true brain. Most of the same neurotransmitters
that you and I have, they're smart, they can learn, but they have this incredible property.
You can chop them into pieces. The record, I think, is something like 275. And every piece
will regenerate exactly what's missing, no more, no less, and make a perfect, tiny little worm.
Now, they are so regenerative that they're immortal. They don't age. There's no such thing as an old
Plenarian, which means, first of all, that the worms that we have in our lab are in a direct
physical continuity with worms that were here half a billion years ago, and that's mind-boggling
to think about. And also, it's telling us that, in fact, it is possible to be a complex organism
with a good brain and so on, and never die. These ideas of thermodynamic limits on aging and so on,
I don't think are correct. But anyway, so that's what the animal does normally. Now,
of course, lots of interesting work has been done on how this works. They have a bunch of stem cells
that lots of work has been done on the molecular and genetic networks that specify different
cell types out of these stem cells. But what's really important to understand is the stem cells
produce the building blocks, all the different things that you need to make a Plenarian,
but you still have to decide how to arrange all this stuff. And all of it can be arranged in many
different configurations. Now, people learned long ago to manipulate the lower levels of the system,
meaning to get in there and take some of the genes that are required for making heads and tails,
regulate their expression, and get one-headed or two-headed worms. We found something that's,
I think, it takes us to the next level, which is two things. First of all, that you can actually,
that there is a real-time bioelectrical circuit that stores an active pattern, which you can see
using special dyes that reveal electrical states and microscopy. You can actually see this
this anatomical pattern towards which the thing is going to build.
And so that's the first thing. The second thing is that you can, by turning on and off
these ion channels, which are these little protein batteries that exist in cell membranes,
by turning these things on and off, you can manipulate that circuit and get pieces to build,
let's say, a two-headed or a no-headed animal. And one of the most amazing things about it
is that if you then, if you have a two-headed animal and you recut that animal in plain water,
so no more manipulation, no more doing anything to the ion channels, you will once again get
a two-headed worm. Now, this is worth pausing here because what has not been done in this case
is to manipulate the genome. The genome has a wild-type sequence. You've not altered the genetics
at all. This is a great example and maybe the best example of the separation of data from machine
in this case because the cells are standard planarian cells. There's nothing wrong with
them that you would identify on genomic sequencing. And they are happy to build whatever it is that
is specified in this large-scale pattern memory that is kept by the tissue electric circuit. And
if the electric circuit has two heads, that is, in fact, what they will build. And so this goes
on in perpetuity. As far as we can tell, you can keep doing this. We now know how to set it back
from two-headed to one-headed. Again, there's a change in the electrical state that you can make.
And so this goes back to your question about downward causation because what you can say is,
well, it makes a second head. What happened to the molecular pathways? Well, of course,
the molecular pathways that are required to build a head are all activated on the posterior side
of the animal. So you still need all... It's not like the Bioelectricity Act by itself. You still
need all the building blocks. The hardware still has to make all the cells that create the brain
tissue and eyes and all of that. But the decision, the early-on decision of what this tissue level
agent is going to build, is made at this higher level, which then inevitably filters down to the
lower level. So you can track that lower level. You can look at the gene expression. You will see
nothing but chemistry. There's no magic. You will see every gene being triggered by some other gene
or something like that. But if you ask the practical question of what is the best way to
make a two-headed worm, you've got a couple options. You can try to manipulate these lower level
activities. And it's quite hard. Or you can go up to the master regulator level and you can just
interact. And this happens roughly between three and six hours after cutting. All the transcriptional
changes happen in the next 24 hours. The first thing after amputation, that circuit acts between
three and six hours. And it triggers both scaling so that the heads are correctly scaled with respect
to the rest of the worm and the identity of the tissue. So head versus tail. All of that stuff
is downstream. So I do think from that perspective, I do think there's a kind of downward causation
regardless of some of the philosophical aspects in the sense that you simply ask what's the best
control knob. And in some cases, it will not be by electricity. And in many cases, we've seen that
that's exactly where the decisions are made. And I think that's not surprising. Looking at the way
the brain works, brains are basically an elaboration of the system that evolution found probably around
the time of bacterial biofilms, actually. Oh, you'll have to say more about that. But
in what sense, how are you relating bacterial biofilms to brains?
Sure. So actually, there's a lot of work on some of the early work on ion channels,
actually, was done in bacteria. It was known from decades ago that bacteria can be electrically
active. And there was some recently some really nice work from UCLA, where there's a set of papers
by Arthur Prindle and colleagues who have shown that bacterial biofilms drive a lot of very brain
like electrical dynamics. So individual individual bacteria coordinate with each other. And what you
get are waves, potassium waves that in many ways are similar to what happens in brains. And I see,
right. And basically bacterial biofilms, you know, they're kind of proto body, right? They're
individual organisms learning to live with each other in a way to make a larger agent that can
do things that individual agents can't. Good. That is actually very helpful. And I'm sure that's
worth the whole podcast by itself. But I do want to get back to the planarian there because I am
not personally an expert on the planarian reproductive strategy. So I don't even know
do they lay eggs or give birth. But how exactly is the information about one headed versus two
headed planarian set down traveling down to future generations? Like where in the organism is it?
Yeah. Yeah. So so this is a great question. A couple of things. Let's let's start back with
the question of how they normally reproduce. So which which already tells us that there's a
lot we don't know. So so planaria is some at least the species that we work with, they are capable
of laying eggs and producing sperm and sexual reproduction. But mostly what they do is fission.
So when they feel happy or in fact, when they're stressed, either either one leads to the same
outcome. Oddly enough, they are good model organisms for human beings too. Yeah. Right. Yeah.
There are lots of lots of I mean, people use them actually for to study addiction to drug
addiction. And you know, they get addicted to all the same stuff that we do and so on.
So when you know, when they want to fission, the back end grabs on to the dish, the front end
keeps going and they tear themselves in the middle and then they regenerate. Now you've got two worms.
So that's their normal reproductive cycle. Now, already before we even get to the two headed
stuff, there's something really interesting here, which is that you and I and most animals, when
we reproduce, our children do not inherit the mutations that happen to us during our lifetime.
So if you get a change of DNA in your arm, your kids don't get that. So that is, that's really
important. And but the thing with planaria, because each piece rebuilds a new body out of
the cells that were in that piece, this means that unlike the rest of us, they practice somatic
inheritance. They do inherit every mutation that doesn't kill the neoblast, the stem cell, they
got it. And those things proliferate. So for, let's say 400 million years, they've been accumulating
mutations. And you can see this in their genomes are an incredible mess. We don't even have a proper
genomic assembly for the kinds of worms that we work with. They are mix deployed, meaning every cell
might have a different number of chromosomes. So you don't even really know what you're sequencing
when you sequence these things. The genome is an incredible mess. And yet, the regeneration,
the anatomy is rock solid 100% of the time you cut that thing into pieces, you get normal worms.
So this is already telling us that there's some very interesting room between the genetics and
the anatomy that we don't understand because the genetics could be very messy and the anatomy is
rock solid. So now let's get to your next question, which is the two heads. So if you have a two-headed
worm, they can reproduce by fissioning. When that happens, generally speaking, one of the pieces
will end up two-headed and one of the pieces will end up one-headed. So you can imagine a scenario
where we take some two-headed worms and we throw them in the Charles River here in Boston and sort
of at some point, some scientists in the future come along and they scoop up some samples and they
find some one-headed forms and some two-headed forms and they say, ah, cool, a speciation event.
Let's sequence the genomes and see where that happened, right? And they're not going to find
anything. And the reason is precisely your question, where does the information live?
So we have found, so far, we've found two places where that information lives. In the strict two-headed,
there's actually another part of this that I hadn't mentioned yet, which is called cryptic
worms, which I'll talk about in a minute. In the two-headed worms, one of the things that happens
is the molecular structure of the cytoskeleton, the thing that allows cells, especially neurons,
but all kinds of cells, to know a direction from basal to apicalers and so on. This cytoskeleton
is actually carrying a lot of the information. And it goes back to a really interesting
experiment, which is classical epigenetics. So now, right now, if you say epigenetics,
people normally think about chromatin modifications, all the things that can happen to the genome
to mark it for future generations. There's an older example, which is that if you take
a single cell organism, like a paramecium, they have these little hairs that point a particular
way, and they swim, they wave the little cilia, and they swim. So what somebody did was they took
a glass needle, and this is an amazing experiment because these things are tiny. They took a glass
needle and they cut a little square in the surface of the animal. I don't actually think it was a
paramecium, but it was a related thing. And they rotated it 180 degrees and they put it back. This
is doing this to a single cell, mind you, with my hand. Under the microscope. And so what they
found is that these things give rise to a line of animals that all have a little square looking
the wrong way. And this was incredible. This was the first real example of epigenetics because,
of course, they had a wild type genome. And in fact, there's a beautiful line in one of the
papers that says these things are always on the verge of starvation because they're trying to
use the little cilia to waft food into their mouths. And there's a little square that's, of
course, kicking the food out the wrong way so they're never quite good. And he says they're
always on the verge of starvation and their normal genome is powerless to help them. And this is a
very powerful point because, yes, the genome has done everything correctly. All the proteins have
been made. They have all of the proteins that it takes to make a normal structure. But the reason
these guys aren't normal is because the information is being templated off of the mother cell. So when
the mother cell makes a daughter cell, it templates that abnormal structure of the cytoskeleton,
you know, almost like a crystal templating, it templates it and creates an offspring with
the same structure. So there's something like that in Plenaria where actually that subcellular
polarity is being scaled up from individual cells to the whole organism. And then, of course,
there's the one that I think is also extremely interesting, which is the bioelectric circuit.
So one of the things that we can see is that the way that the ion channels in Plenaria have been
shaped by evolution is that they make a circuit that has memory. And now engineers, of course,
are pretty familiar with this. It's a really convenient way to make memory circuits. As long
as you keep powering them, you can have flip flops and things like this where you make a transient
electrical change. And the circuit keeps that change until you come back and reset it. So it's
sort of like like like volatile RAM, so to speak. So so this electrical circuit, there's a there's
another type of worm that we can make, which is really interesting. We call them cryptic worms.
And the thing with cryptic worms is that they they every time you cut them, they toss a coin,
and they make a more or less random, although it's a weighted it's a biased coin, but it's more or
less a random decision as to whether they're going to make one heads or not. And if they
don't, what results is again, a cryptic worm. And if they do, you get a two headed worm that is
forever a two headed worm. These cryptic worms, the as far as we can tell, all the molecular
aspects are normal. But what's abnormal is the bio electric pattern that is stored by their real
time electric circuit. And it is this pattern that makes them be this it makes them have this
destabilized anatomy where they're not quite sure if they should be one headed or two headed.
And you can you can manipulate that electrical pattern and convert them back into one headed
worms or into two headed worms or whatever. One of the interesting there's a there's a paper that
from our lab that's about to about to come out in a few weeks, that looks at this as as as a as a
by stable perception problem in the nervous system. So you know, when you look at these things that
are like the rabbit duck illusion, right, or the necker cube or these kinds of things. Yeah. So
so there's a there's this there's this ability of nervous systems to exist in almost the almost
superposition of states where you're and this is very much top down control, right, because it's
driven in both cases, the the photons, the pattern of photons hitting your retina is exactly the same.
The reason that you keep flipping from one to the other is because you have expectations
in the firstonian sense, right, you think it's got to be a cube and if it's always got to be
facing in or out. Yeah. So so that kind of top down control in the nervous system is very similar
to what happens in these electrical circuits in non neural cells, where there can be this this
by stability where there's kind of two ways to interpret this electrical information. And that's
what that's what the cells do. So so I think I think and all of that is not to say that we've
plumbed the depths of this. There's absolutely more open questions than there are answers. So there
may be other pieces to this puzzle. But I feel very strongly that the question of where is this
information is in part, it's kept as electrical memory in the electrical circuit. And partially
it's in the in the in the in the sub cellular architecture of the cells that are copying
previous architectures when they when they form. And we should, you know, you might also be interested
in the the shifting of worm heads to other species, because you can do that too. It's not,
you know, making multiple, you know, making multiple heads of the same species is one thing.
But you can actually, again, by by interfering in the normal electrical electric in the normal
electrical circuit, you can get these cells to build heads that belong to other species of
planaria 150 million years distant with with no genetic change at all. And to go back to put
this in the context of the tadpoles whose faces we rearranged, and they figured out how to get
them back. The idea there is a goal in mind as to what the ultimate face you want is.
Combining that with what we've just been talking about with the paramisi in the planaria,
that means that wherever this goal is, that's not all by itself encoded in the genome either,
right? It's encoded a little bit more globally. Exactly. Exactly. Yeah, it is absolutely not
directly in the genome. I think I think again, the way to think about this is is good. You know,
our concept of software running on electrical devices, I think is actually really good to
to get us an intuitive understanding of this. I think what the genome does is encode a system
that when you turn on the juice, it encodes a set of electrical, and of course, there's also
biomechanics and biochemical signals that are important. But when you turn on the juice,
it reliably executes a pattern of activity. There's symmetry breaking, there's amplification,
there's robustness, meaning if you have some extra potassium in the in the pond that you're
growing in, it's not going to destabilize the whole thing. There are all these important
properties that allow you to spontaneously form a pattern of activity in this electric circuit.
It's like, you know, you got a bag of parts that were specified for you, you connect them all
together, you turn on the juice, and it does something. And the parts were fine tuned over
eons to make sure that what it does by default is is reliable and adaptive and useful. But then
you find an amazing thing, which is that there's actually that the thing's actually reprogrammable
that while it does have a default mode of behavior that would that it will execute every single time,
there is in fact a set of stimuli or experiences that you can give it without going in and having
to rewire it, that will push it into a different mode. In particular, what it will do is what you
can do is you can rewrite the part of that electric circuit that serves as your homeostatic
set point. It's like, you know, if you had a thermostat, there has to be some physical
structure that encodes the range that this thing is trying to maintain, and you can just go change
that, you don't need to, you know, rebuild your thermostat, you can you can change the set point.
So it looks like in many cases, living things have a set point. Now, this is much more complex
than let's say pH or some sort of metabolic level, these are anatomical set points that are that are
rough, not to the cell scale, obviously, but a rough description of what the thing should look like.
And these set points are in many ways, we call them target morphologies, it's the pattern to
which the cells are trying to build and it's the pattern that once they achieve it, then they stop.
These things are rewritable. And once you rewrite them, the cells will build something different.
And what we don't know, of course, is the limitations. We don't know if cells are a
universal constructor in the sense that can you make absolutely anything or are there constraints?
People talk about developmental constraints. I'm not 100% sure what that really is, or if there are
any constraints, in the sense that if we knew, I think we just don't know the code enough. If we
understood how to reprogram correctly these target patterns, I think we would be looking at something
like an anatomical compiler. This is like our vision when I talk about what's the end game for our
group, when can you give up and go home? Because everything's done. I think what we're looking
at is something like an anatomical compiler that you sit down, much like computer aided drawing,
you basically just draw a picture of a schematic of the animal or plant that you want. And if we
knew what we were doing, the system would decompose that into a set of stimuli that you would give
cells to get them to build that particular thing. Not because you're going to micromanage,
you're not going to 3D print individual stem cell derivatives, but you're going to rewrite the
goal state that the cells are accessing the cell collective. I should be more precise. The cell
collective is accessing to know what to build and when to stop. The idea that there's all these
different levels that are interacting with each other is a very powerful one. And not just because
there are levels with different levels of coarse graining, if you want, but that there are
right levels in some sense. This is what you sort of got to earlier. There are ways of describing
these complex systems that just give you an enormously more powerful handle on what they're
going to do. And one of the issues that you've talked about, it's even come up a little bit
in what we've already said about the planaria and the biofilms with the bacteria, which is
at what point do a bunch of either cells or molecules or whatever constitute an organism?
I mean, at what point are they a self that you can pinpoint? That's a level of analysis.
I can talk about the morphology and the hopes and dreams of that little bugger right there.
Yeah, I think that's a great question. And there's two aspects to this, I think,
that we at least that we focused on. One of the aspects is how cells come into being. And this
is the scale up of, and I think this is both philosophically and empirically, this is one
of the most fascinating problems in science, is the fact that all cognitive agents are made of
parts. There's no such thing as a sort of this monadic kind of diamond like cognitive thing
that's not divisible. We are a bag of cells in between our ears. And when people say, oh,
what are you talking about? This collection of cells has memory and goals. So, well,
you have memory and goals, right? And they say, yes, I certainly do. And I say, well, very good,
because you're a collection of cells. And so the question isn't whether cells can have goals and
hopes and dreams, that question has been settled, at least if for no one else but for yourself.
This is other mind's problem, maybe, but at least for yourself, you know, that's the case.
And so now the only remaining question is the scaling. How do you scale up from a collection
of competent agents to some sort of unified single agent that has that has a coherent
integrated cells that is larger than these others, right? So I actually have a model of this,
of how this works, although much work remains to be done. But I have a beginning model of this
that has to do with these really important elements called gap junctions. So these are
things that, these are proto synapses. This is what synapses were before they became modern
synapses. They're basically, think about two, they're little proteins that hang out in the cell
surface that can dock with each other. And you can think about like two submarine hatches underwater,
sort of docking and opening up a path that you can go from cell to cell. So the interesting thing
about that is that, and these are critical for multi-cellularity. They are an important part
of electric circuits because they are themselves voltage gated. So not only does electrical potential
propagate through these open gap junctions, but it actually controls whether they're open or closed.
So that means that this is a voltage gated current conductance, which a.k.a. a transistor.
And we know that once you have a transistor, you can make almost anything, you can make logicates
and so on. It gives them memory historicity and so on. So what's really neat about these things,
if you imagine two individual cells coming together and forming this kind of gap junction,
unlike every other kind of cell signaling. So cells produce all kinds of molecules in their
environment. They secrete all kinds of molecules. And if you're a cell in the environment,
you can receive those molecules. And then you know perfectly well that they're not yours. You
know perfectly that they originate from the outside. You can choose to interpret them or you can think
that they are false. You know that somebody's taking advantage of you or cooperating or competing
or whatever. But something very different happens when you connect with these electrical synapses.
When you connect with these gap junctions, both cells get access to each other's internal
milieu. This means that things that happen to one of the cells very rapidly propagate to the other
cell. And all the metadata as far as what the originator of that information is is stripped.
So if something happens to cell A and there's a calcium flux and that calcium flux propagates to
cell B, it doesn't you know, all cell B sees is this flux. It doesn't know whether what triggered
it happened to it or to its partner. This has a couple of really critical implications. The first
is that it makes lying or cheating almost impossible. Because anything you do right,
anything you do to your neighbor is immediately going to come back to you. So if you try to poison
your neighbor in some sort of you know competition, you're going to get it too. And what it also means
is that it becomes really difficult to maintain ownership of individual thought. So if what you
have are a bunch of information molecules that were a track record of things that happened to you.
And you know, we don't have to think about complex thinking here. We can just say
there are events that happen that trigger molecular reactions and these molecular reactions are
a record that you use to adjust future behaviors in all cells to this. So now you're sharing those
molecules and you can no longer tell which are true memories that you accumulated, and which
are false memories that are incepted into your cognitive structure by the fact that they floated
in from your neighbor. So now this erases it's like an amazing form of telepathy, so to speak,
because it merges the minds of these two cells into a group agent where they literally cannot tell
what belongs to what. And in that case, that is the origin of this I would claim that is the
origin of a simple compound self. It's because you're erasing it's kind of cool. I mean, I think
and again, this is far outside my field, but I think there's a lot of important quantum computation
work as far as erasures, right? The fact that erasing information is critical. I think this
is an example of that erasing this metadata that, hey, here's a memory that belongs to this
unit over here. All of that is gone and that helps create a kind of larger mind, so to speak. And
of course, this is a proto cognitive sort of thing, but you can imagine the scaling larger and larger
to allow this agent now to have bigger horizons of those goals that I mentioned so that you can now
contemplate much, much, much bigger things in both space. And you have the computational machinery
to remember further back in time and to anticipate further into the future. Now, this kind of thing
has a has a cool implication, which is that he would think that okay, if this is the origin of
the self, then you have two questions. Number one is can it break down and what the how would it
break down? And what you can imagine is imagine that you're part of this sensation, you're connected
to a bunch of neighbors, you're this multicellular kind of creature. And for whatever reason,
your gap junctions get closed, you can no longer hear the electrical signals from your neighbors,
you are now sort of isolated from all this, you no longer get the information input, you no longer
get the consequences of things you do directly fed back to you. You could imagine that you would
then in a game theory sense, instead of previously where you're sort of forced to cooperate. And
by the way, this is very interesting. This is where we're doing now simulations of prisoners
dilemma, where the agents instead of just cooperating and defecting, they actually have a new ability
they can merge. And once you merge, what you see is that, right, it's the as to my knowledge,
it's the first time that the number of agents in a prisoner's dilemma is not constant, usually
define the agents, and then you see what emerges and there's cooperation, whatever. But what happens
is, if you don't, if you don't fix the number to be a constant, and you let agents merge,
you find out that cooperation doesn't just emerge, it's inevitable, because you can't
cheat against yourself, because your yourself is now bigger. So what happens when this breaks down,
you can sort of imagine the consequences. And this is precisely what happens in cancer. So in
cancer, what they've known since the late 70s, that one of the first steps of carcinogenic
transformation is a closure of the gap junctions. And then it wasn't quite clear why. And I think
this is exactly what happens. When you as a cell, which your identity was smeared out all over this
tissue, you were part of this larger group cognition, as soon as you are now back, your
computational boundary, that surface from which you're getting signals is now shrunk back down
to the level of a single cell, you basically revert to your unicellular ancient past you.
And this has been borne out by transcriptomics studies by Paul Davies group and others,
where you now basically treat the rest of the body as just environment. You do what single cells
always do, they go where life is good, they migrate, they proliferate as much as they can.
And this is metastasis. And so one way to think about this as a cancer is a breakdown of multi
cellularity. And it, in fact, can be caused, it doesn't have to have a genetic component,
it can be caused by purely physiological cause. We've shown that we can make
metastatic melanoma in perfectly normal tadpoles by preventing electrical communication briefly.
And these cells, this is what happens, the self literally shrinks. So going back to your question
of how you get the, when can you talk about cells, I think it has to do with the boundaries of these
goals. So that as soon as this cell no longer has a goal of building a proper, you know, liver
or kidney or whatever it was doing, all of its goals have now shrunk down to things that a single
cell can understand, which is very simple. I'm going to go down, I'm going to go, I'm going to
follow some, some gradients to where, where, where food is more plentiful. And I'm going to make as
many copies of myself as I possibly can. And this is, this is how cells shrink. So, you know, and
of course the implications of that are that you ought to be able to reverse it, which suggests
that cancer doesn't just have to be treated by trying to chase down all these irrevocably
broken cells and killing them with some sort of toxin. You might be able to convince them to
rejoin the collective. And we've done this in the frog model. We've shown that you can use either
optogenetics or drugs or iron channel misexpression to take cells that are expressing really nasty
human oncogenes or KRS and things like that. And basically just normalize them and force them
artificially to connect back into this, into this group, group agent, and normalize and, and when
go back to normal morphogenesis. You must know you're exactly describing the Borg collective
from Star Trek, right? I mean, in Star Trek, all these individuals, it's, it's treated as bad
that all these individuals melt into a single collective. But when we, when it's our cells
melting their individuality to make us, we think it's good.
Yeah, yeah, you're absolutely right. And I'm not, I'm not big on, on, on collectivist
kinds of things in general. I think that key is, but I think this is telling us something
important. I think what it's telling us is that we need to come up with optimal strategies. And
these are the sorts of things I do a lot of work, for example, with Josh Bongard at the University
of Vermont, he's a roboticist, computer scientist. We, we want to work on identifying optimal policies
that try to get the best of both worlds. Because you see, when you do combine into this,
into this collective, there are some good things about it, which is, which are that you achieve
higher computational capacity cooperation is goes through the roof, all of that. But of course,
the downside is that this collective agent, the goals of the collective agent might have
absolutely nothing to do with the goals of the individual. And so, you know, when, when, when
you lose some skin, you don't worry about it and so on. And so, right. And so, so this is,
this is a real problem. And so what we need to do is to figure out now, evolution has, has optimized
this in particular ways. That's not to say that that's necessarily what we want. We need to come
up with optimal ways to, to enhance the, the, the, the benefits of this kind of cooperativity,
but still retain the multi-scale nature of it. You see, that's the key is you don't want to lose
the, the agency of the, of the pieces. You want to retain it while reaping the benefits of some
of the larger scale features. And it's hard to say at this point how well that's going to work,
but I think that's a really important thing to work on in the future.
Does this whole philosophy help us either philosophically or practically when it comes
to our ambitions to go in there and change organisms, not just solve cure diseases, but to
make new organisms to do synthetic biology, to create new things from scratch? And vice-versa,
does it help us in what we would think of usually as robotics or technology? Can we learn lessons
from the biological side of things? Yeah. Yeah. I think, I think absolutely. And there's two ways
to, there's sort of a short-term view and a longer-term view of this. The short-term view is
that absolutely. So, so we work very closely with, with roboticists to take deep concepts in
both directions. So, on the one hand, take the things that we've learned from the robustness
and intelligence. I mean, the intelligent problem solving of, of these living forms is, is incredibly
high. And even, even organisms without brains, you know, this whole focus on, on kind of like
neuromorphic architectures for AI, I think is really a very limiting, limiting way to look at it.
And so, so we, we try very hard to export some of these concepts into machine learning, into
robotics and, and so on. Multiscale robotics. You know, I gave a talk called, why robots don't get
cancer. You know, and this is, right, this is, this is exactly the problem is, is we make devices
where the pieces don't have sub-goals. And that's the, the good news is, yes, no, no, no, you're
not going to have a robot where part of it decides to defect and do something different. But on the
other hand, the robots aren't very good. They're not, they're not, you know, very, very flexible.
So, so part of this, we're trying to export. And then going in the, in the other direction and take
interesting concepts from computer science, from cognitive science
into biology to help us understand how this works. I fundamentally think that
computer science and biology are not really different fields. I think we are all studying
computation just in different media. And I do think there's a lot of opportunity for, for, for
back and forth. But now the other thing that you mentioned is really important, which is the creation
of novel, novel systems. We are doing some work on, on synthetic, synthetic living machines and,
and creating new, new life forms by basically taking perfectly normal cells and giving them
additional freedom and then, and then some stimulation to, to become other types of organisms.
We, I think in our, in our lifetime, I think we are going to be surrounded by, you know,
Darwin had this, this phrase, endless forms, most beautiful. We, I mean, I think the reality is going
to be a variety of living agents that he couldn't have even conceived of in the sense that the space,
and this is something I'm working on now, is to map out at least the axes of this option space of
all possible agents. Because what the bioengineering is enabling us to do is to create hybrid,
to create hybrid agents that are in part biological, in part electronic, right? The parts are
designed, parts are evolved, the parts that are evolved might have been biologically evolved,
or they might have been evolved in a virtual environment using genetic algorithms on the computer.
All of these combinations and this, we're going to see everything from household appliances that
are run in part by machine learning and part by living, living brains that are, that are, you
know, sort of being controllers for various things that we would like to optimize to, to,
to humans and animals that have various implants that make, allow them to control other devices
and communicate with each other. These, you know, the space of possible agents and possible bodies
is enormous, right? I think that, right, the plasticity of cells and the ability, look, we,
we put eyes, eyes on the tails of tadpoles and those animals can see perfectly well, you know,
these, the plasticity with which cells can organize into a, into a functional form,
even though it's completely different from their genomic default is, is, is massive.
And there's a few things important about that. One of the things that's important about that
is that, and Josh Bongart and I are currently writing a paper on this,
it blows up a lot of the vocabulary that we normally use. You know, people argue about
whether, there's a lot of papers arguing that living things are not machines.
Well, they're certainly not 18th century machines, right? That's for sure, right? But,
but if you look at what machines are now, you know, all of the, all of the kinds of things that
people say, well, machines are predictable and they're, and they're made by a human and they're,
none of those things are true of machines anymore. And things like, what is a robot?
What is a, what, what does it mean to be evolved? What does it mean to be designed? You know,
if you dig into this question of what are we actually doing when we design something and
how is that different from testing variants over long times, you know, time span,
all of these words like robot, program, machine, all of these things, I think, are operating on
categories that are no longer good categories. They served us well in the past when our
engineering was, was primitive and we couldn't make these, we couldn't fill in the middle of
these continuum between all of these kinds of things, but now we can. And so all of these terms
have to, all of these terms have to be redefined to really pick out what's essential about these
terms to really, I think, you know, sort of carve a nature up better than, than they used to. And
that will, will have massive implications not only for, let's say, regenerative biology and
biomedicine and robotics and things like this, but there's, there are ethics issues here too.
We have to think very hard about what we owe to different kinds of agents with different kinds
of cognitive capacities. And, you know, I've been in a lot of debates with people talking about
brain organoids and human brain organoids and what, you know, what human brains are and so on.
Because these things are now continua, you know, we could, you could now make a system that's 80%
human brain cells, 20% drosophila cells and 10% electronics with machine learning. Is that a human?
Is it not? You know, something like, you know, if your neighbor got the brain implant that allowed
it to, that allowed him to mentally run a vacuum cleaner, no big deal. We have people with assistive
devices now and wheelchairs and things, right? No problem. And if your other neighbor had a
vacuum cleaner that had some human brain cells that were sort of a controller and enabled to get
around, also no big deal, still pretty much a vacuum cleaner. So in those cases, you have,
you know, a 90-10 split and a 10-90 split and that's easy. But what about the 50-50 split?
And so we really have to, I think this idea where we clearly know what a machine is, we clearly
know what real preferences are as opposed to just sort of as if, you know, algorithm following by
robots, none of these distinctions are as robust as a lot of people think they are. And the implications
for ethics are at least as large as they are for biomedicine and robotics.
No, I completely agree. And I think that, you know, for example, people have cared a lot about
the possibility of uploading our brains onto computers. Whereas I suspect that just like you
say, blending the boundary between humans and computers is going to be a much nearer term thing
that we're going to have to worry about in this domain. But the stuff you just said brings up,
you know, about 12 podcasts worth of topics to discuss. So we're running out of time here.
Let me just pick one that I really want to get to before we go, which is you mentioned the idea
that robots don't get cancer. And that's very interesting to me because the thing when I have
artificial intelligence discussions, the things that I always want to bring up is that robots
don't get bored. You know, there's no sort of motivation or irritability or desire to come
back to some homeostasis built in automatically. You can try to build it in, but it's not automatic
in an artificial system. And what you've said has given me the initial idea or the additional idea
that maybe the point is not just that robots don't get bored, but that robots are not
or the way that we currently make robots, they're not made of pieces that get bored,
the get bored, right? I mean, this is the extra little insight that real biological organisms
are made of these collections. And the collections, you know, should be thought of in quasi-teleological
ways as well. Absolutely, absolutely. And there's this notion of info taxes, where
everything from molecular networks up are in a constant search for information to update their
ways of representing themselves and the world in a kind of Fristonian sense.
Yeah, I think there is a really interesting question about motivations and the fact that
with any living system, we can tell very quickly how to motivate it. We know what it cares about,
we know what it likes, what it dislikes, because we can train it with positive and
negative reinforcement. Maybe these things will be a little harder in the exobiological arena,
where we can run across new life forms. But I bet even there, in short order, you can figure out
what you could use to train this thing with what it's going to enjoy and what it's going to be
about punishment. There have been papers dealing with this issue of motivation in artificial
agents. You know, you can have an algorithm that causes this thing to do A or B, but does it really
care? You know, does AlphaGo really care that it wins, right? So the problem with this question of
does it really care, like a lot of problems, you start to see the limitations of our categories
when you think about the chimeric case. So I can take cells out of a brain, an animal brain,
and we can connect them in culture to some sort of device that has machine learning or whatever.
And now, if those cells had some sort of magic intrinsic caring that enable human brains to
care about things, does that now carry over to the machine? Because this new sort of compound
organism has some of that. And what is it about? You know, can you take out the human pleasure
center and culture it alone in addition? Is it just activated all day long? And if you've got like
a little chunk of happiness there in addition, these kinds of things are really important.
These chimeric constructions are really important to push us to develop better concepts, because
we don't know really what it means to have intrinsic preferences or how they might carry
over to hybrid devices. All of that needs a lot of overhaul.
Well, I'm looking forward to our brave new cyborg future that you've outlined for us here.
It's certainly, certainly things are changing really, really rapidly and we're not able to
really predict where it's going to go, even though apparently that's what we're supposed
to be doing, having a goal and trying to get there. So, Mike Levine, thanks so much for
being on the Mindscape podcast. Thank you very much. Yeah, it's been a lot of fun.