Hello, everyone. Welcome to the Mindscape Podcast. I'm your host, Sean Carroll.
When you think about how we conceptualize human beings, someone once pointed out that
we're always using metaphors that depend on our current best technologies, you know, when clocks
were just invented, wristwatches and so forth. It was the clockwork universe when robots and
machines came on the scene. We thought of organic beings kind of like that. And now we have computers,
besides which we have, you know, cameras and video cameras and audio recorders and so forth.
So we tend, very, very roughly, you know, we tend to think about a person as kind of like
a robot with some video cameras for eyes and audio recorders for ears hooked up to a computer
inside. And the sensory apparatus brings information into the computer, which then tells
the robot body what to do. It's a simple, kind of straightforward, compelling picture. It's also
wrong. That's not actually a very good description of what we are, how we behave. For one thing,
intelligent design is not the way that human beings came about. We evolved over many, many years,
and we weren't aiming for that. We have to think about what is the kind of architecture that actually
best serves the purposes of surviving and procreating and reproductive fitness and so forth.
And it turns out to be very different. So today's guest is Andy Clark, who is a philosopher and a
cognitive scientist. In fact, his title at the University of Sussex is Professor of Cognitive
Philosophy, very well known in philosophy, very, very highly cited for thinking about the brain
and the mind and how they're related and how they work. He became very famous with a co-author
paper with David Chalmers, where they proposed the extended mind hypothesis, the idea that what
you should count as your mind is not just your brain, but also all the little extensions of
the brain that help us think, whether it's inside our bodies, or whether it is things we scribble
down on a piece of paper or used to enhance our memories or calculation abilities, and so forth
and so on. He also has a great interest in the idea of the brain as a predictive machine. And
that is the subject of his new book, The Experience Machine, How Our Minds Predict and Shape Reality.
So the idea here is that the brain is not a computer just bringing in sense data and then
thinking about it. Our brains are constantly constructing a set of predictions for what's
going to happen next, what is going to be the situation in which the body finds itself, what
is the sensory data that we're going to bring in, and then you compare what you're actually
experiencing versus what the brain was predicting, and you try to play the game of minimizing the
error between what you predicted and what you're actually perceiving. This sounds like maybe a
small change of emphasis or an angle on a similar kind of process, rather than the brain just being
a passive receptor of information. It is sort of actively engaged in a feedback loop, but it has
very, very significant consequences for how we think about thinking, how we think about fixing
thinking, right? When we go wrong one way or the other, whether it's being in pain or having a mental
disorder of some sort, how do we get better at it, taking seriously how the brain is a prediction
machine is very useful here, as well as for philosophical problems about how you carve up
nature, how you think about what the brain does, what is consciousness, what is free will,
and so forth. So this is one of those podcasts that touches on many issues that we're interested in
here at Mindscape, from consciousness to time all over the place. And occasional reminders,
you can support Mindscape by pledging at Patreon, go to patreon.com slash Sean M. Carroll, and pledge
a dollar or two or whatever you like for each episode in return, sense of fulfillment, but of
course also add free versions of the podcast, as well as the ability to ask questions for the
Ask Me Anything episodes. You can also, if you're interested, leave reviews of Mindscape at Apple
Podcasts or wherever there are reviews. Those reviews help draw other listeners in. So if you
think Mindscape's worth listening to, make it an even bigger community listening, and that would be
awesome for all of us concerned. So with that, let's go.
Andy Clark, welcome to the Mindscape podcast. Hey, it's great to be here. Thanks for having me.
You know, you've done, as many people have of a certain age, many interesting things over your
career. Your new book is The Prediction... What is your new book? What is the title?
It's The Experience Machine. The Experience Machine. I keep wanting to say The Prediction Machine,
because obviously prediction is playing a big role there. The Experience Machine with how predictions
shape and build reality. Good, good. Yeah, reality will be a theme that we want to get to, but I can't
give up the opportunity to also talk about extended Mind and extended Cognition and things like that.
So I thought it would make sense to talk extended Mind first, and then get into prediction. Does
that make sense logically to you? I think that's a good route. That's certainly that was my route,
so why not? Good, good. Let's do it. So apparently there are people out there who think that, well,
there are people who think that the Mind is not even related to the Brain, which is funny to me,
but there are other people like yourself, perhaps, who think that the Brain is just one little part
of our minds and our thinking. So I'm not going to put words into your mouth. What does it mean
to talk about the extended Mind? Yeah, I mean, this is a view that I've kind of held and defended
for many years. It goes back to a piece of work that I did with David Chalmers, who's famous for
his kind of almost dualistic views on consciousness after all, many years ago, back in 1998. The basic
idea that Chalmers and I agreed on is that when it comes to unconscious cognition, then there's
no reason to think that the Brain is the limit of the machinery that can count as part of an
individual's cognitive processing, where that has to include unconscious processing, because it's
unconscious processing that we think mostly is what gets extended. There's a whole other debate
about conscious processing. And the idea there is that moment by moment, the Brain doesn't really
care where information is stored. It cares about what information can be accessed, how fluidly
you can get at it, whether or not you've got some idea that it's there to be
got at at all. So the idea was that calls to biological memory and calls to external stores,
like a notebook or currently nowadays, maybe a smartphone or something like that,
are working in fundamentally the same kind of way. And actually, interestingly, it's that that I
think the predictive processing story ends up cashing out in an interesting way. So we can
circle back around to that later. That's the core idea is that the machinery of mind doesn't all
have to be in the head. David Cholmers, of course, another former Mindscape podcast guest. So we
have an illustrious alumni base. But let's let's make it a little bit more concrete. What do we
mean? You know, I think that what immediately comes to mind is I can remember almost no phone
numbers now, because they're all in my smart phone. Does that count as extended mind?
That counts. I think it's after all, you have a fluent ability to access at least a functional
equivalent of that information as and when you need it, because, you know, you just pick up the
phone and there it goes. If on the other hand, you had all those numbers stored in a notebook,
but the notebook was in your basement. And, you know, you had to run down into the basement to get
it whenever you needed it, that wouldn't count because you wouldn't have the constant robust
availability of that resource woven into the way that you go about every kind of problem that
daily life throws at you. So there is, I think, a genuine intuition, which is that whatever the
machinery of mind is, it better be more or less portable. It better more or less kind of be going
around the world where you're going around the world, where bio you is going around the world.
And so for that reason, I think you need robust and trusted kinds of access, but only to the
extent that biological stuff is robust and trusted. You know, now and again, my biological memory goes
down. Now and again, I don't trust what it throws at, but it should be more or less in the same ball
part. Well, okay, so robust and trusted access. Is that the criterion? I mean, I guess an immediate
question that comes to mind is, where do I draw the boundary? Does everything in the world count
as my mind? Yeah, I mean, it's a, it's one of the original worries about this view. It's one that
we used to call, or I used to call cognitive bloat, why it somehow is no good way to stop in this
process. But actually, if you take that robust availability and trust of the product stuff
reasonably seriously, that does rule an awful lot of things out. But I think in addition,
there's something which I've never, I've never given a full account of, to be honest, but there's
something about the sort of delicate temporal nature of the integration of the biological system
with this non biological crop or aid or resource or whatever it is. So that you can have the brain,
if you like, making calls to this stuff in ways where it kind of knows about the temporality of
that, it doesn't all have to go through a little bottleneck of attention, you don't have to kind
of think to yourself, oh, I'd better get that information from over there. That's not what
it feels like to go about your daily things as you. So it's this sort of idea of something where,
if it were taken away suddenly, you would feel very much at the loss of a sort of
kind of general purpose loss. There'll be many situations that you'd find yourself in
where you were no longer able to perform in the ways that you expected yourself to perform.
There's something there that could do with a bit more unpacking about temporal dovetailing.
Does it relate to ongoing conversations that I'm very interested in about emergence and strong
and weak emergence or just being able to coarse grain in the world in such a way that you have
units that have explanatory power? Yes, I think it certainly relates to a lot of stuff about
emergence because the idea here would be that by dovetailing things together in this way,
you get basically an emergent you. You are the emergent property. You, the thing that goes around
with a sort of sense of its own capacities, but doesn't really care how they get cashed out.
So something that I think comes out quite strongly in the predictive processing stories
is that brains are kind of location neutral when they estimate where they can get good
information back from. So they're very good at estimating what they're uncertain about and
going about getting more stuff, but it doesn't really matter where that stuff is. So as long as
it's accessible, trusted, there when you want it, that's fine. And then there'll be a story to tell
about how the actual selection process operates, but we'll come around to that once we talk about
predictive processing. Let's stick with TXM. I mean, I guess one way that philosophers think
about their job is that they're supposed to be carving nature at the joints. And does this
count? Is that this? Is it a sort of betrayal of that goal because you're including all my
smartphones and my card catalog as part of my mind? Or is it an improvement of that because
really the action of our brains relies on all this stuff? Yeah, that's a very good and very
delicate kind of question. So, you know, when when those charmers and I put it forward, we tried to
argue that this was, this was where the right way to carve nature at the joints because of
functional similarities. That said, you know, it doesn't intuitively always seem like the right
way to carve nature at the joints. So I think that we're making a decision here, and that that
decision, or the enough is in part a moral decision. So, okay, I, I'm very much moved by the analogy
with prosthetic limbs, for example, if you took somebody with a well fitted prosthetic limb,
and then looked at them and said, but you know, your basic physical capacities are just those of
you without the limb, we would in a way be doing them a certain kind of injustice. And I think we
be doing ourselves a certain kind of injustice. If we treated people say with mild dementia that
rely very much on that on a smartphone or on their home environment, in just that kind of way, we
would be, we would be sort of regarding them as less, I think, than they really are. So for me,
the sort of non moral route, the kind of functional similarity route is a kind of stalemate, because
it's kind of carving nature at the joints, and it kind of isn't. And then it's when you chop the
moral or ethical considerations into the pot, that I think you have a strong argument that
overall, the best way to go is to err on the side of caution, and buy into the picture of the extended
mind. I bet that depends on one's definition of caution. But
I think, all right, is there intermediate, there probably is an intermediate stance in which
your whole body, your physical body counts as your, what goes into cognition and the mind,
but things outside the body don't. Is that a well populated space in the thoughts about this?
Yes, I think that is reasonably well populated. I personally, I think it's an unstable space.
So I think you better go one way or the other. I think that, as soon as you start thinking, okay,
if I'm using my fingers to help me count, then my fingers somehow count as part of the machinery
of mind. A lot of people do feel that, but I think that's true. But I think you can't think that,
and then simultaneously, you think that the constantly carried pocket calculator can't count
as part of the machinery. So yes, I think the body is often, for me, it's a very useful step in
stone because I can suck people in by getting them to agree that continuous reciprocal interactions
between brain and body do a lot of what really looks like cognitive work. And there are good
examples of that from even things like the role of gesture as we speak. So spontaneous gesture
by Susan Golden Meadow and colleagues have shown that it kind of eases a certain sort of problem
solving. If children are forced to explain how they solved the maths problem, but not allowed
to gesture, they're actually a lot worse at it. So there's something going on, continuous
reciprocal interaction that is probably allowing us to somehow offload aspects of work in memory
into these gestures, stick what they're in the world, which is good news for philosophers that
worry about hand waving. It's just part of my thinking.
Respectable cognitive task going on right there. Can we
ask how this was different back in the day? Obviously, a lot of the things we've been
talking about are technological or modern. So was the mind of a human being 100,000 years ago
very different? I think I would say it was, despite the fact that the brain of a human
being 100,000 years ago wasn't very different. So yes, I would say that the mind of 100,000 year
old humans was very different. But the brain obviously wasn't. But think of intermediate
technologies before maybe we go back that things like just using pen and paper. And
in particular, I'd like to think about the example of sort of scribbling while you think
the thing that many of us, those of us at least old enough to be brought up with pen and paper,
do an awful lot of. And so as we try and think a problem through, we write things down.
I think it was Richard Feynman, who has a rather famous exchange with a historian,
Weiner, I think the historian was, where Weiner said,
these, so this is a record of your thinking. And Feynman said something like,
no, it's not a record. It's, what did he say it was? It's not a record. It's working. You have to
work on paper and this is working. And I think there he had an intuition that this is a just
offloading stuff onto a different media. This is actually part of a process that solves the problem.
Do we see this then in other animals? I mean, I presume the answer is yes. But is it more
less dramatic depending on the species? Yeah, I mean, I think we humans do this to a really
ridiculous degree. And it's because we invented symbolic culture somewhere along the way. We
came to create these arbitrary systems of recombinable elements that we could then,
you know, re-encounter as objects for perception. So creating these sort of structured encodings of,
in some sense, our thoughts and ideas and putting them out in the world is a huge opportunity
for any creature that is a good information forager, any creature that is very good at reaching out
into the world to resolve some of its current uncertainty. And once again, that's a theme that
we'll look back to later on. So humans do it a lot more. Other animals do it too. I don't think
it's a purely human thing. It didn't just suddenly arise. You know, if you have a chimpanzee that
or the orangutan, better example, that constantly uses a stick to gauge the depth of rivers before
going into the rivers, I think there's enough of a sort of weave in and robustness for that to
count as part of a sort of extended cognitive load. I guess I'm very interested in phase
transitions, you know, small changes in things that allow enormously different capacities,
et cetera. Clearly, the ability to think and communicate symbolically was a big one. It
opened up things. But I guess what you're saying is one of the things that opened up is not just
we can think more abstractly or generally, but we can think in literally different ways because
these symbols allow us to more easily offload some of our cognition. Yes, I think that's right.
I think that one thing we can do is we can use one of our biological capacities in very,
very different ways. And that capacity is a tension. So when we put something out into the
world in that sort of way, kind of clothe it in materiality, that lets us attend to it in a whole
bunch of different ways. And interestingly, I think by doing that, we can often break the grip of our
own sort of over-constructive internal models of what kind of thing it is and how it might behave
and how you might re-engineer it. So even think about something like designing a new training
show or something. If you build a big-scale model and then you start looking at it and poking it
and prodding it, you can come up with all kinds of ideas that you wouldn't come up with just by
kind of sitting down and trying to imagine all that in your head. So I think we're unusual in
that respect, but it's a great power of us being perception action machines, that we can really
make the most of this. And then you look at current more disembodied AI, they've got really
no use for this kind of strategy. The way they work is just not such that they get to start putting
stuff out into the world and then poking and prodding it just to think better. They might do
that for all kinds of other reasons. But is that their fault or ours? I mean, we haven't really
given them the capacity to do that. I think that's right. I think it's our fault. I think we've,
to be honest, I think, well, it's our fault. We've designed a class of tools that are really,
really useful for what they're useful for. But I don't think, actually, that those tools will
ever achieve what I would call true understanding because they don't have their grip on reality
grounded in perception action loops. And it's that grounding in perception action loops that I think
we're leveraging with material symbolic culture when we just create these things and poke and
prod them in different ways. We're super specialized for being good at perception action loops.
So I think that's, there's a trick there that disembodied AI is missing out, but then it gets
all kinds of other things instead. Sure, sure, it does. But okay, I'm going to, I'm just going to
download a little bit because what you just said sparked several ideas and it's,
it's prefiguring things we'll get to later. But two things. One, an idea I heard more than 10 years
ago that attempts to make AI systems suddenly work much better when you put them in a robot
that can go out there and interact with the world. And secondly, a podcast I did with Judea Pearl,
who claims that babies spend all of their time making a causal map of the world by poking at
things and seeing what happens. And I know that the whole prediction models that we'll be talking
about are kind of this, like, you know, the brain making a model of the world. So all that
together, do we imagine that if we do put modern large language models in an embodied
context and let them go out and poke the world, they would change dramatically how they think?
Yes, I think it would. You know, there are companies out there that are kind of trying
to do this, like versus AI is one of them. And, you know, the idea certainly is to
see what happens if you kind of leverage the active inference framework as a way of creating
these sorts of new ecosystems of human artificial intelligences. Although I wouldn't start, I
think, with a large language model, exactly, just because, you know, something like that has been
trained to predict basically the next word in corpuses of text. And that's a very funny place
to start if what you want to be is a perception action machine. It seems much more like
developmental trajectories where you start without that huge body of, nonetheless, maybe
relatively shallow successor item information. You want to learn basics about causation and flow,
and you probably want to understand those things in a way that is more grounded than it would be
if you just knew how all the words about causation and flow tend to follow one.
It sounds like you-
This isn't a very cool question. It remains to be seen. It might be that if you ban a large
language model in a good enough robot, that it's just like giving a baby a super head start or
something. But it does sound like you might be at least sympathetic to the idea that we need,
that I've had some people on the podcast advance, that AI would be better off if we didn't just
dump large data sets into deep learning networks and instead also poked and prodded the AI to have
a symbolic representation of the world. Yes, I think that's right. I do agree with that. I think
if our goal is not good tools to think alongside, but rather something like artificial general
intelligences, so colleagues. If you want to build an artificial colleague, then I think
large language models are not the right place to start. But if you want a really lovely tool
that can do an awful lot of work and that you can work with, then they're really interesting.
Honestly, I don't want an artificial colleague, but an artificial graduate student or postdoc
would be very, very helpful or someone who could answer my email. I guess it would be weird not to
ask the obvious question. I get annoyed when sometimes my philosophy colleagues seem to claim
to have an immediate and obviously true view of what is natural and real in the world,
but maybe I'm going to do that right now by saying, I feel like I'm inside my body. I feel
like the I myself is located maybe even in my head. Is that just I have old intuitions that
haven't quite caught up to the modern world? No, I think that that's a valid intuition,
if you like, because I think that we infer that we are wherever it is that the perception action
loop is closing. We're basic. We're perceiving the world and we're launching interventions and
we're receiving the effects of those interventions. That's such a fundamental part of how we learn
about things. I think it's no surprise that that's where we think we are. Notice that that's where
we think we were, even if part of our brain was located in a nearby cliff top communicating
wirelessly with the rest of the brain. We'd still think, oh, this is where the perception action loop
is closing. This is where I am. Dan Dennett has a beautiful old philosophical short story called
Where Am I? where he plays with that idea where there's someone whose brain is in the cliff top
and they think that they are closing perception action loops using a body in the world,
but then at some point, you know, it gets cut off and suddenly they think, oh, now I'm claustrophobically
stuck in the cliff top. They knew their brain was there. Anyway, it's a beautiful story.
No, that is very interesting. Okay, so we might as well dig into this phrase that you're using
over and over again, the perception action loop. I think the word loop crucially important there,
right? The way I like to think about it is, and perhaps this is true because of technology,
but we have a naive metaphor for how the brain works as kind of like there's a video camera
with a computer hooked up to it, right? Just taking in our sense data, processing it and
doing something. And a big part of your message is, no, it's really not like that at all.
Yeah, no, that's exactly right. I mean, let's think about one way, which is not like that.
If you think about something like running to catch a fly ball in baseball, where you're kind
of running to try and catch this is ball that's flying out there. The way to do that isn't to
take in all the information about the flight so far, and then plot where you think the ball's
going to go and then tell the robot you as it were go over there. Instead, what you do is you run
in a way that keeps the apparent trajectory of the ball in the sky looking motionless as you
look up there. It turns out that if you just keep doing that, then you'll be in the right place when
the ball comes down. You need to do a bit more to actually catch it. You'll be in the right place
when the ball comes down. And there's a way of solving an embodied action problem that involves
keeping the perceptual signal within a certain sort of bounds and then acting so as to, well,
so is to do that, basically. Something that, again, prediction error minimizing systems would
actually be rather good at. So perception action loops, I think, the important thing to think
about there is that they're not solving problems all in one go generally. It's sort of like,
I do a little bit of this, I do something that gets more information or that keeps the perceptual
stuff within bounds, and then repeat the process again and again and again until the thing is
So I do appreciate your use of a USA based sports metaphor there, but we have an international
audience. I have no idea what it really means. But okay, so the motto then is the brain is a
prediction machine. And I just want to sort of home in on what is the difference between that
view and another view. I think maybe if people don't think about the brain too much, they would
say, okay, sure, yeah, my brain makes predictions, but you really want to put that front and center
as the point of what the brain does. Yeah, yep. I mean, it's both the beauty and the burden,
if you like, of this story that it is really all this account. I'm told about to use the word
story because it doesn't sound scientific. It's a count that it's basically saying this is a
canonical operation of the brain, if you like, the canonical computations that the brain performs
and that it strings together in different ways to do motor control and interception and extraception
is basically one in which you're attempting to predict or the brain's attempting to predict
the current flow of sensory information. Of course, there are different timescales at which
you could predict it. And the basic timescale, the bedrock one is predicting the present,
which of course is a rather funny use of prediction that was saying predictions about the future
somehow, but this is a sense in which the brain is a guessing machine. It's trying to
guess what the current sensory evidence is most likely to be and then crunch in that guess based
on past experience together with the current sensory evidence. And that turns out to be a very,
very powerful way of estimating the true state of the external work. It goes wrong sometimes,
but it's a very powerful strategy. It allows you to use what you've learned in the past
to make better sense of what the raw sensory energies are kind of suggesting in the present.
This seems very related, certainly, to Carl Friston's ideas. We had him on the podcast,
the free energy principle, the Bayesian brain. What is the relationship between all these ideas?
Yeah, I mean, basically, I'm just being an apologist for Carl Friston here.
So, Carl's basic picture, the free energy minimization picture is a sort of high road
version of the low road version that I give you. So, the low road version comes kind of out of
thinking about perception and thinking about action, whereas the high road version comes out
of thinking about what it takes to be a persistent, living system at all. You have to
preferentially inhabit the kind of states that define you as a system that you are. That means
that you end up in the states that in some broad sense, you predict you ought to be in.
So, in that broad sense, the fish kind of predicts it ought to be in water
because its actions are all designed with that in mind. The low road is a bit less
challenging. I guess that'll be why I take it. The low road is just sort of saying, look,
we have good evidence that the canonical computations that human brains and the brains of
many other animals perform involve this attempt to guess the sensory signal. And it turns out
that you can use that to do motor control in a very efficient way. It's been known for a long
time, I think, that it's important in perception. And the other thing that I think Carl Friston's
work has really done has been shown that that old story about perception becomes so much more
powerful when you see that it's got a direct echo in an account of action. So, the idea there is that
perception is about getting rid of prediction errors as you try to guess the state of the world
using everything you already know. And action is getting rid of prediction errors, but it's
getting rid of them by changing the world to fit the prediction. So, you have these two ways to
get rid of prediction error. You find a better prediction, or you change the world to fit the
prediction you got. One's perception, the other's action, but they're performed using the same kind
of basic neuronal operations. There are differences between motor control and sensory perception.
But if you look at the wiring of motor cortex, it turns out it's actually wired pretty much like
ordinary sensory cortex. In fact, so much so that many people don't like to talk about sensory
and motor cortex just for that reason. So, these stories or these accounts give you a sort of
principled way of understanding that. In each case, you're predicting a sensory flow,
but in one case, you're trying to retrieve an old model of the world to fit the flow,
and that's perception. And in the other case, you're trying to change what you're
getting to fit the prediction. We can circle around to that. I think I can say that a bit better
Is the idea that it's the same neural circuitry that is doing sensing and control, or is it that
the two circuitries look parallel? Yes, it's that they look very much parallel.
They operate in the same sort of way. The reason they're not the same is a proprioceptive prediction,
is playing a very special role in motor control. So, the idea is a proprioception is a sort of
system of internal sensing that lets us know how our body is currently arranged in space.
So, the idea is that in order to reach to pick up the coke can that's in front of me,
I predict the proprioceptive flow that I would get if I were reaching for it,
and then I slowly get rid of those errors by moving the motor plant in just that sort of way.
So, you get rid of the errors by moving the arm, in this case, to reach up the coke can.
So, proprioceptive predictions are especially placed here. They act as motor commands.
The other kinds of predictions don't. So, I hesitate to use the word think here,
because thinking and cognition and thought I'll have technical meanings that are slippery to me.
But the idea is that your brain sort of thinks intentionally or unintentionally that your arm
is somewhere slightly different than it is, and then the muscles move it to make that more accurate?
That is one way of putting it. And people have put it that way. So, some people have said,
look, you've got to kind of lie to yourself. Brace will go to lie to itself. It's got to
ignore all that good information that says that my arm isn't moving. It's got to predict
the trajectory of sensation that you would get if it was moved in. And that prediction is given
so much weight that the other information is overwhelmed and off it goes as a way you get
rid of the errors by moving it. I'm not sure personally that's exactly the best way to put it.
I kind of think it's really about attention. So, I think it's like you've got information
that says that you're not moving the arm. You've also, because of your current goals,
you're predicting this proprioceptive flow that would correspond to reaching for the
coke can. And by, as it were, disattending to the information that says that it's stationary,
you allow the other prediction to do its work. So, I think it's sort of targeted
disattention rather than actually lying to yourself. I'm not quite sure why I prefer that.
I think we're probably saying the same thing. You know, the math and the models all work out
yesterday. But I think if we call it targeted disattention, we understand it a bit better.
I think it makes more contact with sports science, for example. But you don't really want to be
attending to the position your body is currently in. You want to attend to something like how it
ought to be. You want to entrain yourself by knowing what it would feel like if you were doing it
right, right now. So, is it similar to the idea of file compression? You know, if we have a JPEG
or an MPEG, that there are some patterns that are repeated so you don't have to keep track of every
pixel. You can just assume that they keep going. And then you pay attention to the differences.
And those are what we're talking about as errors in the brain case.
That's certainly correct when we come back to thinking about perception and something like
that is involved in action too. But it does seem like it's easier to think about that bit in the
case of perception, where the idea would be that, you know, I predict the current sensory flow and
it's only the errors in that prediction that then need further processing. So, you know,
I think I've woken up in my bedroom and I predict a certain sensory flow and as I turn my head around,
I'm not getting any information that corresponds to that. I might have to go scrabbling or use
these prediction errors to retrieve the information that actually I'm in a hotel room and it's going
to look pretty different. So, I think it's in that sense that when you don't have to scrabble that
hard, this is a super, super efficient way of doing moment by moment processing because
if you already predicted it properly using what you know about the world, you don't need to take
any further action. So, in that sense, it's exactly like JPEGs and motion compressed video where the
idea is, you know, if I've already transmitted the information about this frame of the video,
then in order to know what the next frame is, all I need to do is react to whatever the errors
would be if I assumed it was just like the frame before and normally then there's a few residual
errors and if you use those as the information that you need to deal with, you get the right picture.
So, these prediction errors, these residual errors, they carry whatever sensory information is
currently unexplained. They'll explain whatever you can with prediction and then just you don't
need that much bandwidth really to just use the rest to refine it. I remember hearing, it might
have been in a conversation with David Eagleman here on the podcast, the idea that the reason why
the years seem to go by faster as we get older is because there's less novelty in our lives. You
know, the first time we go to a beach, it's all new and we really expend a lot of mental energy
taking it in. Whereas the 20th time, we already have a background and the errors are not that big.
Does that fit into this story? It sounds like it does.
Yeah, I think that fits really, really well. It also helps explain why it's so hard to learn
new things at a certain point in your life because the inputs that you're receiving get sucked into
these well-worn troughs in your current world model, if you like. I think us academics find
that a lot as we get older in something like, oh, yeah, I understand that. That fits with this
kind of story that I've already got. Sometimes it's very, very hard to give the new evidence it's
proper due. Of course, attention is a tool for doing that, but that takes a lot of deliberate
effort sometimes to really, really attend. Attention reverses the dampening effect that
prediction normally has. Part of the evidence base for this story, this account, is that
well-predicted sensory inputs cause less neural activity than other sensory inputs.
There's something odd there. These are the ones we deal with very fluidly,
and yet there's less going on in the brain when you deal with them than in other cases.
That's one of the signatures that led, I think, to predicted coding coming on the sea.
You open a can of worms when you say how the old academics get stuck in a rut there,
but I have to just follow up a little bit. I think there's two different perspectives
I could put forward. One is more or less what you just said. As we get into our ruts, it takes
more and more energy, activation energy or whatever to think in new ways, but the other is,
maybe this is more optimistic, because we are older and good at certain ways of thinking,
we forget that it was hard to not be good at any ways of thinking. We forget how hard it was to
learn calculus or French or whatever. Therefore, we're just not willing to put in the work anymore,
even if it were exactly the same amount of work. Yes, I think that's right. We end up in a situation
of expert perceivers in general, where expert perception clearly is being able to take this
unruly sensory information and just see what it actually means for victory on the chess board
or whatever it or whatever you happen to be engaged in. I think, in a way, all successful
perception is expert perception in that sense, and academic expertise is in the same sort of
ballpark. It has the same sort of blind spots as well. If there is something interesting going on,
but it doesn't fall within the bounds of the existing generative model to use the right
vocabulary for the predictive processing story, then the only thing you can do with it is use it
to drive torturous new slow learning and see why a lot of time we don't really want to do that.
Don't want to do that. No. Well, look, you've used the word, relatedly, use the word efficiency as
one of the benefits to this model. If we think of probably the first ever video storage software
was more or less like a movie where you just had every frame and you stored it, right? Then only
later did you realize it was much more efficient to just update the changes. Presumably, since our
brains were not intelligently designed and grew up through evolution, this is a nice feature to
have. We're trying to do the most with finite resources. Is that a big part of the attraction
of this story that it requires less thinking or energy or calories or what have you?
Yes, I think that's right. I think if the brain didn't work this way, but we were able to do the
kinds of things that we do, we'd probably have brains overheated, repeated. The amount of energy,
there is a trade-off here. The trade-off is keeping the world model, the generative model
you're using to make the predictions going. That, of course, is a big metabolic cost. That's kind
of the cost that is being his signature you see in spontaneous cortical activity. There's stuff
going on all the time. All the time, the kind of thinking about the resting state work from
Raeckel and others as well. That is a cost, but that is traded against a moment by moment cost
of processing all this incoming information. I think what we're doing is we've traded the cost
across time there and we're using a fairly metabolically expensive upkeep of a world model
to allow a much more efficient moment-by-moment response, a faster one as well. Being somewhat
anticipatory about what's going on in the world around you is a pretty good thing if you're an
animal involved in all kinds of conflicts and dangerous situations. Also, there are wiring costs.
It's hard to know how best to think about the wiring costs, but the amount of downward flowing
wiring and information seems to very often outnumber the inward flowing stuff,
sometimes up to 10 to 1, certainly 4 to 1. It looks as if brains have decided. It's been
decided over evolutionary time that this is a good thing to do, and I think that that means
it is overall the most efficient way to proceed. I also worry that in a way if you want understanding,
there might be no other way to proceed. That's kind of maybe there's something more
abstract or philosophical going on there, but I don't know what understanding would look like.
As it were, you weren't bringing a world model of some kind to bear on the current sensory
evidence in a context sensitive way. There's a question there that I don't know. I really
don't know the answer to because I know they're a kind of formal proof. Anything that can be done
using a system that has feedback like that can be unfolded into a feed-forward system.
Maybe the upshot there is, well, maybe you could unfold us into a feed-forward system for a few
bits of processing or something, but it would require a huge brain and a ridiculous amount of
energy, but somebody out there maybe might want to think about that.
Yeah, exactly. I was going to say this does sound like a research project for somebody,
but there's the benefit of this mechanism that the brain uses, the predictive processing model.
Presumably, there's also downsides. Maybe one is that we're very susceptible to illusions.
We think we're seeing things that aren't there because it's part of what our brain
is predicting very, very strongly. Yes, absolutely. I'm subject to several of these illusions. I'm
sure we all are. Phantom phone vibration is probably a good one. I often might think that
phone's going off in your pocket when it's not even in your pocket. I'm now susceptible to phantom
wrist vibrations since I gave in and bought a smartwatch. The hollow mask illusion, I guess,
is a classic in this area where an ordinary joke shop mask, if viewed from the concave side,
so viewed from behind in a certain sense with a light source, behind the mask, you'll think that
it's an ordinary outward face that you're seeing. Again, that seems to be because we have very strong
predictions about the concavity of normal face structures. We very seldom see anything that
isn't like that. That prediction now trumps the real sensory evidence specifying concavity,
except it doesn't in everyone. Autism spectrum condition folk are slightly less susceptible
to that illusion and to the McGurk illusion, for example, from a predictive processing viewpoint.
That's probably because of a slightly altered balance, one where sensory inputs are somewhat
enhanced relative to expectations. What was the other illusion you mentioned, the McGurk?
Oh, the McGurk. It's like a ventriloquism illusion. Yes, sorry. It's this one where
it's a sort of Bargar illusion. There is a sound which you can be played such that
if the lips are moving a certain way, you'll hear it as Gar, and if they move in a different way,
you'll hear it as Bar, but it's exactly the same sound. Exactly the same sound.
It's not entirely clear whether that's an illusion or something else. It's hard to know exactly where
the boundaries of illusions and other kinds of inference lie. I mean, these kind of optical
and auditory illusions almost seem fun and benign, but presumably we can take the basic picture that
there's an enormous amount of information coming into our senses at every moment,
and we can't possibly process it all. Therefore, we filter it. We filter it to fit our perceptions
and then correct for the errors. That must also work with abstract concepts or news items just
as much as pictures that we get through our eyes. Yes, I think that's right. There is a tendency to
not just to see what we expect to see, which can be very damaging too, but sometimes to read what
we expect to read. Well, by read there, I mean sort of read into a text, what you expect to be
learning from that take. I think many of us do this. I think all of us probably do this when
we read news articles where it looks like they're saying something that we're very much either sympathetic
to or opposed to, but maybe when you look at that text again or you go over it with a fine tooth
car, when you look at it with someone that's got a different perspective, you realize that's
really in that text. It's just what I brought to bear in some way. In the visual case, Louise
Feldman Barrett, Lisa Feldman Barrett has this lovely but very, very scary example of the way that
interceptive predictions, predictions about your own bodily state, are getting perhaps crunched
together with extraceptive ordinary sensory information in ways that could perhaps give you
experiences where an object that is reached for in a dark alley might actually appear to you as a
gun when really it's just a smartphone. In sort of much less worrying and sort of more
controllable cases, you can show that if you give people false cardiac feedback,
so you make them think their heart's beating faster than it is, then a face that would otherwise
look neutral to them is judged to be an angry face or a worrying face. So it does seem as if
we're using internal information to help make the predictions that structure our experience of the
external world. And so that's something that can go right or go wrong as well. So we end up seeing
what we expect to see and maybe even believing what we expect to believe in some sense.
Yes. I mean, there is a sort of, you know, some people say seeing is believing, but in these cases
believing is kind of seeing. And maybe in these interception cases, feeling is seeing as well.
That's the way that Feldman Barrett puts it. Another former Minescape podcast guest,
I got to say Lisa Feldman Barrett. Are there therefore features or things out there in the
world that we are systematically bad at perceiving because of this way that we process information?
It's a lovely question and one that I haven't thought about. So things that we just, all of us,
tend to miss because, well, I suppose the most obvious answer there is unusual events.
So, you know, you would have seen the, you know, the footage of the gorilla walking across the
scene where you're trying to count the passes of the baseball. So he's worked by Simon and
Chappris. Anyway, it's his classic work that in sort of attentional blindness and sorry,
inattentional blindness. So the idea there is that if you're concentrated on one task,
something really quite dramatic could happen and you just wouldn't notice it. I think we're all very,
very subject to that. So outliers, I suppose. So predictive brains are tuned in to patterns
that have helped them solve problems before. And so whenever we're confronted with an outlier
situation, we're likely to miss it unless for some reason we're attending right there. But why
would we be? Because attention is driven by where we expect the good information to be.
And this is why, for example, expert drivers are very, very good at a lot of things,
but they can miss a cyclist if they're approaching a roundabout from entirely the wrong direction.
Somewhere that, you know, no one comes from that direction at the roundabout. So there's a lot of
these looked but didn't see, as they call them, accidents where people might even move their
heads in that direction. But if it's that unexpected, they just don't see what's going on.
Presumably, these are all quantitative questions. I mean, if something is
blatant enough, we're going to see it even if we didn't predict it. Is that fair to say?
I think, yes, that's fair to say as long as we're able to attend to it. So it needs to be able to,
and some things will try and grab our attention. So like a loud noise. It's a really loud noise,
like those scaffolders I had out my window earlier happened. Then that will grab my attention,
unless I'm really, really desperately focused in all my attention somewhere else as I might be.
So if you think about stage magic, stage magic is a really nice case where rather dramatic things
can suddenly appear on stage. And most people don't notice them because attention has been so very,
carefully controlled by the magician. Because attention is up in the waiting on either specific
predictions or prediction errors. So it's a really, really super important part of the
predictive brain story, this balancing act that is very in moment by moment.
That's a great example. I like the idea that professional illusionists are just
leveraging the fact that our brains are predictive processors.
That's true. Yeah, no, there's a beautiful book. I can't remember the title now,
but it's by Luis Martinez. And it is a book written by neuroscientists about stage magic,
leveraging the picture of the predictive brain as a way of understanding a lot of it.
Very, very good. Okay, so let me then be put on the skeptical hat just a little bit.
And this is similar to questions that are raised for Carl Frist and etc.
Look, if our brain is trying in some sense to minimize prediction error,
can't it do that best by not collecting any data just by hiding away and being completely
unsurprised because we never leave our room? Yeah, I think that's such a nice worry to have
because it leads right into this hugely important dimension of intraceptive prediction and
artificial curiosity. So let's maybe talk about these things for a moment. So there's this
sort of worry that it's sometimes called the dark and room. But the best place for a predictive
brain to be would be to lead us into a dark corner and just keep the same. So all of those sensory
inputs they just keep on keep on coming just the same. You predict them perfectly, but you wither
and die. Now we don't do that, obviously. Does that mean the predictive brain story is wrong?
Obviously, I don't think so. I think what it means is that there's more to the predictive
brain story than just bringing extra sensitive sensory information into line with predictions.
We're making all these intraceptive predictions all the time. I'm predicting
the state of my own body. I'm predicting, for example, that I should at all times have
sufficient supplies of water and glucose, for example. And then action is automatically taken,
not when I don't have enough water or glucose, but long before I don't have enough water or
glucose. So if you start to feel thirsty, that will be happening before you've reached the
point at which you're going to wither and die without water. And if you take a drink when you're
thirsty or feel relief, but that water will have no effect on you physiologically for about 20
minutes. So the relief is as much a prediction as the original thirst was. This again is an example
from Lisa Feldman Barrett. So once you put intraception in that way into the picture, then of
course we're not going to stay and not eat and not drink in the darkened room because we have these
kind of chronic systemic expectations, if you like, of staying alive. But then there's a bit
more to it than that, I think, as well. Because we don't stay in boring rooms either. So you could
put me in a very boring room, but give me enough food and water and all of that stuff. And I wouldn't
like that very much either. I might even start to do things. I might start to play games by
drawing on the wall or something like this. And so this now falls under the umbrella of kind of
work in artificial curiosity. And predictive brains are naturally artificially curious brains
because minimizing prediction error is their basic reward. So you could sort of say for brains like
that the only thing really that's rewarded is minimizing prediction error. That's what they
want to do. And if they're not performing any particular tasks, they'll still try and find
some prediction error to minimize because that's the kind of thing that they are. And this is what
makes predictive brains general purpose structure learners. So there's some rather nice work that's
been done by Rosalyn Moran at UCL. I think it's UCL. And what she's been doing is comparing reward
driven learners with prediction driven learners and finding that the purely reward driven learners
will learn a way of solving the problem more rapidly than the prediction driven learners
very often, but frequently a more shallow way of solving the problem. Because as soon as they find
a way to reliably get the reward, they kind of stick. Whereas a prediction driven system,
it basically wants to minimize prediction error as much as possible. And that leads it to explore
its environment repeatedly learning more and more about it. And if you then seed it with a goal,
and simultaneously, it will outperform a pure reward driven agent. So that I think when you
put those two things together, you kind of see that the darkened room isn't really much of a
threat. We don't like death and we don't like boredom. And both of those things seem to be
natural effects of being driven to minimize errors in prediction.
I guess the way out that comes to my mind directly, which I'm not sure if it's the same
thing as what you are proposing or it's something different. But in physics, when we calculate
the entropy of a system and we say is that maximum entropy, that's telling us some distribution of
all the possible states it could be in, blah, blah, blah. But famously, we can calculate maximum
entropy of a system subject to different constraints, right? Like subject to it's at a certain
temperature or it's at a certain pressure or whatever, and we'll get different forms for that
probability distribution. So couldn't we just say that there are two things going on? We want to
minimize prediction error, but we also want to survive. So there's a constraint we want to survive.
And under that constraint, it's actually useful to go out and be surprised sometimes so we can
update our predictive model. And I think that would, I don't know how mathematically that would
work out, but it does seem a little bit intuitive to me. Yeah. And I think that does mathematically
work out. I think this is the sort of stuff that Carl Friston can speak to more reliably than I can.
But it looks as if, very often, the correct move for a prediction-driven system
is to temporarily increase its own uncertainty, so as to do a better job over the long time scale
of minimizing prediction errors. And that looks like the value of surprise, actually, and that we
will, I think we artificially curate environments in which we can surprise ourselves. I think,
actually, this is maybe what art and science is to some extent, at least, we're curating
environments in which we can harvest the kind of surprises that improve our generative models,
our understandings of the world, in ways that enable us to be less surprised about certain
things in the future. I wonder if you could use this idea or a set of ideas to make
predictive models for what kind of games people would like to play or what kind of stories or
novels or movies people would like to experience. Or, I guess, in music, it's very famous, right?
You want some rhythm, some predictability, but you also want some surprise also. There's a sweet
spot in the middle. Yes, I think that's exactly right. Karen Kukonen, a literary theorist in
Scandinavia somewhere, has written a nice book called Probability Designs. And so she is using
the vision of the predictive brain as a way of understanding the shape of literary materials,
poems and novels. Okay, there you go. And my idea is that we should think of every novel, every poem,
as a probability design, leading us through sort of building up expectations, cashing them out,
building up at multiple levels, giving precision, weighting to some of the expectations versus
others. And clearly, you know, this makes sense of music as well. There's an awful lot of that
going on in music. And probably it applies to all sorts of things, even like roller coaster design,
I imagine. It's exactly that. A roller coaster is a kind of probability design. What's interesting
is how we get surprised again and again, even if we ride the same roller coaster or read the same
novel or listen to the same piece of music. And I think that shows the skill of the constructor
in giving us inputs that activate bits of our model, drive in expectations again and again,
to the point where you're still surprised in some sense, even though you could have said beforehand,
that's what's going to happen. You still can't help but be surprised. And this, in some sense,
at some level would be the best thing to say. And I think this speaks a little bit to the idea that
as prediction machines, we are multi level machines, we're not just, it's not just there's a prediction,
and it's either cashed or it isn't, but this prediction exists as a high level abstraction
predicting a lower level one, predicting a lower level one, predicting a lower level one,
all the way down to the actual incoming notes of the tune or words on the page.
It's because we're multi level prediction machines, I think, that things like honest
placebo's work. So you know, placebo's obviously for rather nicely under this sort of general
account, because expectations of relief thrown into the pot can make a difference to the amount
of relief that you feel. But if you're told that you're being given a placebo, it can still make
a difference to the amount of relief that you feel. Presumably, that's because there are all
these sub levels of processing that are getting automatically activated by good packaging delivery
by people in white coats with authoritative voices on this sort of thing. So I think that's
something that we might learn from these accounts too, that we should maybe medicine and society
could make more use of ritual and, yeah, ritual and packaging and things that in some sense,
I don't know, in some, well, I want to say ineffective. What I mean is they don't,
they bring about their effects, but not through the standard routes.
Good. Okay, very, very good. Okay, when, you know, we're late in the podcast, we can get a little
bit wilder and more profound here. So you, in the book, you gesture toward ideas along the lines of
we are not only, you know, the thing that the thing to get in mind is that we're not just
sensing reality and writing it down, we are in some sense participating and bringing it about.
Maybe even using phrases like what you think of as reality is really a hallucination.
Tell us exactly how far we can go along that rhetorical road.
Yeah. Proceed with caution would be the right thing to say because lots of people talking
about these things, myself included, use this phrase perception is controlled hallucination.
And you can see why, because the idea here is that perception is very much a constructive process
in which your own expectations get thrown into the pot and they help you see what you see.
And those same expectations are thrown into the pot of feeling your body the way that you feel it.
And so a lot of our medical symptoms, in fact, all our medical symptoms reflect some kind of
combination of expectation and whatever sensory evidence the body is actually kind of throwing
up at that time. So this is really a very, very powerful story. But when you think about perception
of controlled hallucination, we need to take the notion of control pretty seriously.
For that reason, in some slightly more philosophical works, I've tried to argue that we should
flip the phrase around and think of hallucination as uncontrolled perception.
And that that, as it were, puts a boot on the right foot somehow. It lets us say that when these
things are working properly, you're in touch with the world. This is a way of using what you know
to stay in touch with the world as it matters to an embodied organism like you trying to do the
things you're trying to do. But then of course, when it goes wrong, when the perception is
uncontrolled, if you like, then you get hallucination. You will get a hallucination when
you're kind of disconnected from the world in your predictions, your brain's predictions are
doing all the work. And then if you turn the dial in the other direction, and your brain's predictions
aren't doing enough work, you fail to spot fake patterns in noisy environments and be easily
overwhelmed. So I feel like thinking of hallucination as uncontrolled perception is actually the
better way to do it, even though it's clumsy to say, and it doesn't even roll of my tongue that
easily, which is why I don't think I actually bothered making that move in the experience
machine book. You know, it's really hard to resist drawing a parallel with large language models
here, because of course, their entire job is predicting what's supposed to come next, right?
And guess what? They famously hallucinate. They say things that are completely false,
but interestingly, they do things with apparent confidence, right? They don't hesitate or mumble
when they're hallucinating to them. It comes out just as definitive as the truth does. And maybe
there is a parallel there. Yes, I think that's right. I mean, their hallucinations are in a way,
I think, partly at least the result of them not being anchored in perception action loops in the
right sorts of ways. So, you know, it's this anchoring in perception action loops that sort of
teaches us a lesson when we're young. It's like, you know, if you get things wrong, bad things are
going to happen to you. If I don't spot the edge of the path as being the right place, then I'm
going to fall over and I'm going to get signals that I chronically don't like as it were. So
all the interceptive predictions are coming into play there. Whereas if all you're doing is predicting
the next word in the sentence, and your reward is basically being kept alive as a large language
model, then why not just, you know, go the whole hog and be confident about a nice structured piece
of bullshit that you can generate? At the same time, it's interesting that by changing the prompts
to the large language models or to chat, chat GPT anyway, you can make it do substantially better.
So you can say something like, you know, writes this for me in the style of a well-informed
scientific expert. It makes less mistakes. It still still tends to hallucinate references,
but at least it's a little bit better. But yeah, so something very thin about just predicting
the next symbol. You know, I just feel like it's not very well anchored in reality. And so
hallucinations are kind of, you can't tell the difference between a hallucination and
something else. Maybe that's the point. Unfortunately, when we're in the grip of hallucination,
we can't tell the difference either. Someone on Twitter coined the term
hallucitations when chat GPT makes up papers you haven't written. I like that. I like that.
Yeah, they appear all the time. I'm going to start including them on my CV.
Are there implications, you know, if we get down and dirty and not philosophical for how to treat
mental issues that we have, whether it's, you know, depression or pain or anything like that?
Or do we get actionable intelligence from this way of thinking?
Yes, I think we do. I mean, it's early days. But I think particularly in the case of pain,
there are some clear sorts of recommendations here that are being implemented by people working
in what they call pain reprocessing theory, which is just to find a high pollutant label for the
idea that you reframe your pains. So, you know, the thought would be that we tend to treat pain
as a signal that we shouldn't be doing something. If you reframe it as, okay, my pain
signaling system is misfiring, then you can begin to think, so this pain doesn't mean that I shouldn't
be doing it. And it turns out that if you get people involved in those regimes, they start to be able
to do a bit more because they're not scared of stopping because of the pain. And actually, as
they find that they can do more, the pain itself presents itself to them as lessening. I think
because the brain sort of infers, well, if I'm doing this stuff, it can't be that bad, can it?
So there's a kind of virtuous cycle that replaces a vicious cycle that was there before, which was,
you know, this is going to hurt, so I'm not going to do it. And then if I do stop to do it,
oh, it really seems to hurt, I'm not doing it. So pain reprocessing theory is one nice case.
I suppose self affirmation is another case, the idea that the idea that, you know, if you're prone
to thinking that perhaps you're not going to do well in some tests because you're in a certain
minority group or you're female and it's an ass test or something like this, self affirmation
in advance of the test can really make a difference. You know, I'm good at this, I can do this,
lots of people like me do this, that kind of thing. It's important, of course, not to over
over egg the custard, as we might say on this side of the Atlantic anyway.
You know, you can't reframe, you can't reframe having this sort of bacterial infection in a way
that is really going to make any difference, the bacterial infection that you've got and
reframing makes a big difference to cancer related fatigue, it doesn't make much difference to cancer.
So I think we have to be, you know, we have to be aware of the limits. And in general,
I don't think that these stories, these counts are kind of positive thinking sorts of account,
they're kind of, they're more like, you know, there are many factors that are involved as we
construct our experiences. And some of those factors are our own expectations.
Yeah, okay, that sounds perfectly sensible put that way. I'm not an expert, but my rough
impression is that we don't, we know embarrassingly little about pain and how it works. It's an
understudied area, I guess, I don't know whether it's for moral or psychological reasons. So any
little insight might be very helpful. Yeah, yes, I agree. And I think that I think pain research
is actually moving into some very, very interesting stages now as we understand more about the ways
in which people's own expectations make a difference. So even where, where there's a very
standard physiological cause, it, people's experiences of their, of their pain, very tremendously,
and even within a certain individual, their experiences, very tremendously from context
to context and day by day, in ways that just aren't tracking the organic as well. I don't
like this word organic, there's always something organic going on, aren't tracking the sort of
the standard, the standard calls. So what's probably happening is that different contexts
are activating different expectations of pain or disability. And without the standard organic
calls changing in any way, that's making a difference to how you feel and what you can do.
I actually just realized I forgot to ask a crucially important question earlier.
We had Nannis Mayel on the podcast a while back and my new colleague at Johns Hopkins,
and talking about physics and the arrow of time. And you know, through talking to her and
through talking to other people, I have this vague idea of why we think that time flows,
why we have the sense of time passage. And it's because we are constantly predicting a moment
in the future and also remembering a little bit in the past and updating, right? And you know,
the updates happen in one direction of time and that's what gives us this sense of flow or passage.
Given your expertise, does that sound at all on the right track?
Yeah, that sounds very, that sounds like a really nice story to me or account even.
There's an account there. I like story. Go ahead with story.
It's, I mean, it reminds me a little bit actually of Husserl, the kind of classic
philosophical phenomenologists who had this idea that experience is this sort of,
this thing which is rooted, rooted in the past, but always looking towards the future.
And the present is this sort of just a kind of just where those things meet,
where the, you know, I don't know what really gives us the arrow of time, that sort of sense that
the idea that you can't sort of unscramble the egg or whatever it is, it's not obvious to me quite
why my prediction machinery is kind of what's delivering the fact that it looks like I really
can't recreate the egg from scratch. Well, I think that's one for you. That is one for me.
And I think that I halfway agree in that the account has not been fully fleshed out, although I'm
100% sure it's ultimately because entropy is increasing. We just have to draw the connections
there, which is the useful work to be done. It sounds like a great account of why we think
there's an arrow of time. Yeah, why we feel it. Right. Why that's part of our image of the world.
Okay. So then the last question is the flip side of the pain question. There's this idea called
the hedonic treadmill, which I think some people have said have been, has been discredited. But
the idea that we get happy not because of our overall welfare, but because of changes in our
welfare. And if we win the lottery and now we're rich and living in luxury, soon we have exactly
the same happiness as we had before. There are challenges to this view. So I'm not even sure
if it's true. There's a replication crisis in psychology. Everything is very easy to me. But
it does seem compatible with the whole predictive modeling view of what the brain is doing. If
what we're doing is constantly predicting what's happening next, then can happiness be understood
as noticing that our prediction was a little pessimistic and things are actually a little bit
better? Yeah, that's interesting. I hadn't thought about this, but it sounds like it should for
rather neatly into place with this sort of dampening of the well-predicted. So the fundamental
starting point for a lot of these accounts was that the neuronal response to well-predicted
sensory inputs is dampened. So if these sensory inputs are supposed to be driving pleasurable
experiences, but you've really been through that 100 million times before, then the pleasure is,
I think, going to be diminished, perhaps unless you can actively reach in there with a tension
and try to stop that. So I wonder whether someone that really loves the taste of a particular wine
that they had a million times before, as long as they can reach in with a tension and up the dial
on what's coming in through the senses, then maybe they can artificially surprise themselves
a little bit, if you see what I mean. I do. I'm not sure about that, but I feel like there's
something there of wine tasters are told to do this to sort of sit back and let it speak for
itself so that you don't get sucked into your own expectations.
But now it brings up questions. I know I said it was the last question, but
there's an issue here of high versus low pleasures or simple versus subtle pleasures, right? I mean,
I'm a big wine fan and I absolutely do get pleasure from very fancy complicated sophisticated wine,
because I can't afford to have it too often, so that it's not boring to me. But I also get pleasure
from like the perfect slice of pizza, which is very simple and predictable and whatever, but
I get that comforting pleasure. So now I'm not sure what to think.
Yes, I mean, you know, I think I'm not quite sure what to think about those cases either. I mean,
it does seem to me that we, you know, because our brains of prediction minimize in engine,
then in a way, we do kind of want to live in worlds that we can predict well and that have
certain sorts of things. And so when those things are bringing hedonic benefit, then I think
existing there is going to be a rather comfortable way of existing, even though we also have
a sort of a company and drive to increase our states of information to sort of, you know,
learn a bit more in case it lets us generate a slightly alternative future in which, you know,
the pizza is square, but we're liking it even better or something. But I think that
I think that if we think about these things delicately as sort of multi level and multi
dimensional prediction engines, then we can accommodate both the both the drive for novelty
and the attractions of staying within the space where where actually all that stuff that wants
us to minimize errors is doing rather well in a local sense. Even just looking at a pizza,
you're minimizing lots of errors. After all, just to see the shape of the pizza in front of you,
you're kind of moving your eyes around, harvesting information, minimizing errors,
you're getting some hedonic kick out of it, nothing bad is happening anywhere. It's a pretty
comfortable place to be. You know, I'd like to leave messages for the young intellectuals out
there who are deciding what to do with their lives. It sounds like there's a sweet spot here
where we do know something about the brain and the body and how they work and how they fit together,
but there's still a lot of good questions left on the table to be answered by the future.
I think there's a huge number of questions. You know, every story, every account we've had so
far has turned out to be wrong and I'm sure this one will too. So the question is, you know,
what's a stepping stone towards? Well, it's a very good story. You're telling us Andy Clark.
Thanks so much for being on the Mindscape podcast. Thank you. It's been a real pleasure. Thank you.
you