my name is John Rovicki perfect okay John so would you tell us a little bit
about what you do for a living what is your life's work the main thing I guess
is I have sort of two things I'm doing one is I'm a bona fide academic I'm an
associate professor at the University of Toronto in cognitive psychology and
cognitive science so I study the nature of cognition how we learn solve
problems I also study related phenomena like wisdom meaning in life
consciousness mindfulness altered states of consciousness mystical
experiences and so that's something I've been studying as a long time as an
academic I'm also a longtime practitioner I been practicing meditation
contemplation Tai Chi Chuan for like 30 years so that's one thing I'm doing and
then starting I guess about was it 2019 I started an online presence I did a
video series called awakening from the meaning crisis in which I was
addressing the issue that most people are finding increasingly finding it
increasingly difficult to find meaning in life and to get a framework in which
they can cultivate wisdom or perhaps even an appreciation of the sacred within
a scientific worldview and then I've been doing a lot of series around that and
trying to get those two things those two aspects of my life thankfully are
mutually supportive and to try and get them even better coordinated to try and
address the meaning crisis that I mentioned great what is it about your
personality or even the events that have happened in your past life that got
you interested in all these different things well that's a really good question
and so for me the the pivotal moment or at least the pivotal episode perhaps it's
a better way of putting it I was brought up in a fundamentalist Christian
family and of course I love my family this is extended family and so I'm not
trying to criticize them as people but I found I guess given my personality my
own line of psychosocial development that I found that experience ultimately
traumatizing it really had a sort of profound negative impact on me but it
is very sort of bivalent for me because your first religion well we have this
term your mother tongue the first language you you you learn is with you
always and it informs everything else well you can you sort of have like a
mother religion too and so it left the taste in my mouth if I can put it that
way for transcendence and for seeking deeper connection and meaning in a sense
for the sacred dimension to reality but at the same time I was traumatized by
the existing religion and then I was I basically set out on this path to try
and resolve that sort of meaning crisis I was experiencing myself and when I was
in university I encountered the figure of Socrates in the cultivation of wisdom
and this opened up an avenue for me and so from there I started going down the
road but the academic study of wisdom it drops off the table after like first
year university even within philosophy which is ironic given that the love of
wisdom is literally what philosophy means now I went on to studies philosophy
because I valued the sort of meta science and medical to critique and the
tools it was giving but that hunger for wisdom and transcendence was missing and
so I started I went to a place and I started learning Tai Chi Chuan and
meditation and contemplation and then that started to really satisfy that
hunger for wisdom and transcendence but for me as I was doing this right the
cognitive science world was starting to move more and more towards these topics
and when I started to talk about these topics within my academic courses at
the university I was noticing that they were really catching with the students
these were the things they were like getting really fascinated in I think it
was the first person at the University of Toronto to start talking about my
mindfulness within a scientific perspective and then they started asking
me to teach the courses on meditation contemplation extracurricular and I did
that for a long time and so I noticed this confluence and I noticed that many
of my students were resonating with that confluence and so I started to do more
and more about building that bridge the bridge between science and spirituality
to address the meeting crisis
I really resonate with that on a personal level I always thought that that's what
college was supposed to be like and you expand you have these transcended experiences
but not that for me.
And your case is not by any means unique many of the students after sorry this
isn't meant to be self-promotional but many students after they're taking the
classes with me they will say something like that this is what I wanted
University to be and I don't know why the other courses aren't like that so
yeah very much there's a there's a need that's not being met right now now to be
fair there's a lot of other people like me doing this kind of work and one of the
advantages gifts of doing my series was I've got I've been able to meet them and
started interacting with them.
You had mentioned meditation and contemplation. Now meditation is something that many people are
familiar with whether they do it correctly or not but contemplation is a
word that you don't hear too often and I was wondering if you could explain a little bit about that.
This goes right towards my academic work but it also is something that I use
when I'm trying to train I talk about two languages we you have to coordinate
there's a language of explaining which you'd use in science and then there's a
language of training which you're using when people are trying to cultivate
things so let me let's not talk initially about meditation and contemplation
let's talk about their common root in attention and so what I want you to notice
is that your attention is we have a sort of a like a spotlight model of
attention that what we do is shine our attention and on something that makes it
stand out and that's right in so far as attention changes how things stand out
for you how salient they are but there's a lot more going on so for one thing one
of the things you can do with your attention is you can focus on me as a
whole gestalt or you can zoom in to a feature and you go back and forth and
that's dynamic you're constantly doing it because of what Marlo Ponte called an
optimal grip like you're constantly like it when you're looking at my hand
depends what your what your goal is whether or not you focus like let's say
if you wanted to see if I was married you might look at the ring finger but if
you want to see if I worked with my hands a lot you might go more gestalt
like you're gonna move in and out until you get the balance between detail and
the whole and you're constantly doing that with your attention gestalt and
feature so you're constantly doing that but there's another thing you can do
and let me use an analogy for that it's one that's become a somewhat of a mean
for my work but it's still good maybe that's why it became a mean and so I
use this when I'm teaching also my students meditation and I want you to
notice something think about my glasses my glasses are literally framing my
experience there's right and I'm looking through them in both senses of the
word I'm looking past them and by means of them now so right now my glasses are
actually transparent to me but I can do this sometimes I have to step back and
look at my glasses rather than looking right through them so now my glasses are
opaque and why would I do that because I might want to clear some gunk off on my
glasses right you're always mentally framing so your mind you're not at most
the time looking at your mind you're looking through your mind at the world
and you're framing it in terms of what you're focusing in on as salient what
you're focusing in on as relevant what your backgrounding and foregrounding do
you see how dynamic it is like soon as you and it's been it's constantly
shifting it's like this I call it a shifting salience landscape so you're
constantly doing that now just like your glasses are transparent to you and you
might not notice how they're distorting your vision your mental framing can be
transparent to you and you're not noticed and what you do in meditation is you
first learn to step back and look at your mental framing rather than looking
through it this is really what's meant by centering your attention it doesn't
mean just focusing it's you're stepping back and looking at and you also are
trying to break up the Gestalt patterns into the feature details right so
you're stepping back and looking at the mind right and then instead of just
gestalting you're also going in and trying to break up the features notice
the patterns and processes that are going on because you're trying to see how
that might be distorting now think about this that's a valuable thing to do in
meditation but what would you need to do in order to see if you've actually
cleaned your glasses what would you need to do wow no because what I would
think you'd do first is put them on and see if you see differently right that's
what contemplation is contemplation is going the other way it's trying to look
more deeply into reality and to grab the the big picture the Gestalt and to see
if you can seem better than you could before that's contemplation the word
contemplation you can hear the word temple in contemplation temple means to
to look out to look up to the sky the Latin contemplatio is a translation of
the Greek word theoria which means to look deeply it's where we get our word
theory from to look deeply into things and so what you have to do is you
actually have to cycle between these you have to step back and see if it's
distorting you make changes and see if that makes a difference in how you see
the world and if you see the world and you start to see how more how it really
is that guides you in saying oh I bet this is distorting my vision and then
you see what you do you cycle back and forth between meditation and
contemplation one of my criticisms of how the West is appropriating or
misappropriating mindfulness traditions is they tend to only concentrate on one
of these typically meditation if you look at the ecology of practices what in
cultures where the mindful these mindfulness practices are more
indigenous what you find is people have a whole set of practices they have
meditative practices contemplative practices moving practices and
interpersonal social practices because you need to be cultivating them all
together because they act like checks and balances on each other
that's great I want to step back a bit and talk about the state of the world
right now so we can for sure cover why this is important so we all know we're
living in an interesting time it seems cordial but it's stressful it can be
stressful people are on edge there's a lot going on you can see that with
suicide rates last couple of years and I was wondering
a leading question why you think the reason for that is so in science you
you find things that seem disconnected and you do what's called an inference
to the best explanation you try and come up with the best explanation for all of
these disconnected things that unites them together that's how you afford
understanding so I have a proposal in that sense I think it's a theory that's
born out by evidence that a lot of these that you can see a lot of what I call
symptoms almost like the way a doctor looks at various things and through
them sees an underlying disease I call them symptoms of the meeting crisis this
goes to work I did with Christopher Mastipriaccio Philip Misovic and the
idea is that you can see a lot of markers of distress as negative symptoms
you can also see a lot of markers of positive response and you can give a
unified explanation of this in terms of how people are responding to the
meeting crisis either in a malfunction a way or in a functional way so as you
already mentioned you know suicide especially among the younger generations
and going out child suicide is now becoming an issue which is a that's a
profound marker that something's going wrong interestingly Tatiana
shell has Chanel has got provided good evidence that there's a direct line
between a sense of loss of meaning and suicide that doesn't have to pass through
clinical depression so we used to think people are clinically depressed and they
sort of sense meaninglessness or meaninglessness try triggers clinical
depression and that leads to suicide but it looks like no people can go directly
from the sense of meaninglessness into suicide there was a survey in Great
Britain I think it was 2017 something like 89% of the adult survey thought
their lives were meaningless and there's overwhelming evidence that that is
predictive of a lot of things going wrong the survey also showed another
symptom of the meaning crisis a loneliness epidemic right as you
mentioned a mental health epidemic we're getting you know rise mark you know rise
we're getting an increase in the markers for depression measurements of
depression anxiety disorders related we're getting various addiction crises
the opioid crisis so these are all markers of this meaning crisis you get
the the rise it's funny I was actually interviewed by rebel wisdom just at the
beginning of COVID and I was predicting a rise in what Jules Evans calls he
resurrected the term conspirituality which is a mixture of conspiracy theories
and spirituality practices like QAnon and things like that and you see that as
another marker but you also see some positive responses you see the rise
of and we've talked about it already although I have some criticisms of it
but you see the rise of the mindfulness movement as an attempt to respond to that
you see the rise of Hellenistic philosophies like stoicism is going
through this huge revival that you see the attempts to import Buddhism and
stoicism Buddhism and Taoism into the West in order and you see the emergence
and I get to be involved with these people of new communities Rafe Kelly's
evolved move play where people are integrated he does where he takes
people out into the woods and they do parkour right and then they do mindfulness
and they do martial arts and then they do campfire discourse where people are
doing all of this to try and enhance meaning in life so this whole like that
would look sort of chaotic and disparate but if you pause it that all of this can
be seen as a response to a profound sense of loss of meaning or meaning being
under threat meaning in life then you can explain all of those in terms of this
idea of the meaning crisis and so I would suggest that the reason why a lot of
people are under stress right now and pursuing various strategies to try and
intensify meaning is exactly that meaning crisis
well I did 25 hours of lecture on the awakening for the meaning crisis to try
and give an answer to that question so I will do my best to try and collapse that
into a couple of minutes of a response there's two basic dimensions to
answering a question that are really important one is a structural dimension
what is meaning what are we talking about and why does it come under threat
why is it at risk and then the second is a historical so let me talk about the
first because I need the first to explain the second so here's the basic idea
and this is this this for me is this is where I'm placing all my epistemic and
career bets because for me this is this is the lich pin which is the centrality
of meaning so it goes like this you are a cognitive agent you can move in many
domains and solve many problems within many domains you're really really
interesting and I don't mean to make you sound like a specimen but I find that
so fascinating about human beings that they have this capacity and what's what
that what seems to be I would argue and what I published on at the core of this
is this really unique ability we have and which and why it strikes me is so
unique it's the thing we're trying to give artificial intelligence and we
haven't figured out how to do it and we're this is this is the although we're
making progress so I want you to notice that you're doing it right now and it
goes back to that salience landscaping I was talking about so the amount of
information that's actually available to you in the technical definition of
information is combinatorial explosive it's astronomically vast do you know
the amount of information you have in your long-term memory all the possible
combinations connections you could make astronomically vast you know all the
sequences of behavior you could put together astronomically vast but you
know what you're doing right now out of all of the information out there all the
information in here and all the possibilities of how you could behave
you're zeroing in on the relevant information like that like that how do
you do it it's a really hard question I dedicated my life to trying to figure it
out now think about how you need that moment by moment by moment and no
one has said it's not static you're constantly shifting and notice what's
going on even right and this gives you a bit of a clue I would argue as to how
you're doing it part of your mind is trying to select and focus in and part
of your mind wants to wander off and think about other things and so part of
your mind is trying to open up possibilities and then another part is
selecting from all those possibilities right and it's doing this and that's
just like the process of evolution you have variation and selection variation
and selection so notice what that does it makes certain things about me and what
I'm saying stand out and other things you don't even consider them now that's
that's what's so cool this sounds like a Zen coin you know what makes you
intelligent your ability to ignore most of the information that's available to
you so what you're doing and this is a very technical sense is you're
biasing your attention that's how you're intelligent but you pay a price for
that you're biasing your attention and there's check there's are you're always
always subject to this vulnerability that that bias is going to turn out to be a
prejudice that you actually missed the information you needed every year until
very recently because phones have made this go down but until the advent of
cell phones this would regularly happen people would go into a dark place where
they knew there was flammable gas dispersed and they knew they needed light
so they would strike a match and what were they focusing on what was relevant
to them is that the match is a source of light and what they ignored was a match
is also a source of heat and they would blow themselves up right so we are
always sub so the very processes these evolving dynamic processes that make us
intelligent also make us perpetually susceptible to self-deception self
destructive self-deception and we're doing it all the time a great place
people realize this is in the romantic lives I say oh I know what I did wrong
there I'm gonna do the exact opposite with this person and then they get into
it and they go oh I'm doing it again I'm doing the same thing again although it's
very hard for them to see it from the inside so across cultures across
historical context people have developed ecologies of practices for interacting
with this dynamic self-evolving relevance realization in order to try and
ameliorate the foolishness that self-deceptive self-destructive behavior
but there's a positive side because this is so central to you when people talk
about feeling connected that's what they're talking about they're talking
about that relevance realization it's relevant to me it's salient to me it
draws me in relevance is always about what you're caring about as opposed to
what you're ignoring and so people also not only do they need to ameliorate the
foolishness they want to enhance the connectedness so they also have
ecologies of practices that not only ameliorate the foolishness but enhance
the connectedness that connectedness is what meaning in life is
ameliorating foolishness enhancing connectedness enhancing meaning in life
that's wisdom this is what I do with my students so that's the structural
problem we need wisdom it's not optional for us to ignore it right and if you ask
people do you want to be wiser they usually say well yeah of course do you
want more meaning yeah do you want to be less self-deceptive self-destructive
yeah but I'll ask my students I'll say where do you go for information oh
social media the internet where do you go for knowledge a little bit slower
science the universities then I'll say where do you go for wisdom and there's
a silence some of them a little bit a shrinking minority will say maybe my
religion but they're not very confident about that and that is the historical
issue these ecologies of practices in which we cultivate wisdom have to be
situated into a worldview that homes them that valorizes them that provides
institutions and communities when I asked you what would you do you said I'd
ask somebody if there was gunk on my glasses somebody else that's right we
need a community transformation requires community it requires and a community
requires a shared worldview and it requires right so you got a shared
worldview a community an ecology of practices that's what religion provided
and what we see historically for a lot of reasons is that is the decline the
loss of what Peter Burger calls our sacred canopy I'm not advocating for
Christianity I'm not doing that but what I'm saying is when we lost it for what
the political and metaphysical and scientific reasons that we lost it we
lost all of the functionality it provided for us in the cultivation of
wisdom and meaning and here's the problem for us the scientific worldview and
let's let I want you to remember I'm a scientist I love science but the
scientific worldview can't address that problem and here's here's what I mean the
scientific worldview has no explanation for science itself or for the
meaning-making practices of the scientists that make science possible we
and our science don't actually fit in to the scientific worldview we're a whole a
gap but like a black hole within that worldview and so the very thing that is
so successful so beautifully successful in so many domains is precisely
incapable of addressing this historical loss of a worldview that homes wisdom
and meaning I'm glad you brought that up because I did want to ask you being a part
of the scientific community can mimic a spiritual community it seems like there
is a religion of science happening also there can be and then there even been
historical attempts like Auguste Comte to try and do that and there are I mean
one of the things you see in the history of the West is as Christianity
receded you get you get the attempt to fill in that vacuum with pseudo-religious
ideologies political movements you know I would recommend very strongly that
people consider that communism and Nazism are not just political phenomena
they're also pseudo-religious phenomena in a profound way and so I mean and
there's various ideologies left and right that people use and you can see
various academic communities trying to plug in the sense of the sacred into
the science by sort of fusing you know a particular political worldview
liberalism or leftism or right right wingism whatever right to try and do
that because science per se can't do that the attempt to turn science into
religious framework with some people called scientism you see it happening
with the with the academic community but on on its own science really can't do
that much so it's usually glued together with a not scientifically based
allegiance to a particular socio-political economic ideological vision of what the
good life is and what good people are and what's the good what's the good
future that we should be pursuing and things like that so we're talking about
science and spirituality and one of your passions for bringing them closer
together one of the things you'd mentioned on your first episode of your
series is the different types of knowing and yeah for me like I think people
need to know about that would you mind going through thank you for bringing that
up because that that goes exactly towards the kind of bridging that's a
wonderful question I deeply appreciate that and it's it's funny you're and I
don't mean this in any way to denigrate my my two boys who are like the jewels
of my life but your theories are kind of like your children and you don't know
which and you when you don't know which one of these is going to take off and
it's really interesting that this has been something that really that people
have found very central so the idea is and this is one of the ways in which
science is inadequate the idea is that there's four kinds of knowing and let's
start with the one that's typified in science and that's prevalent in our
culture especially in ideological movements which is propositional knowing
so this is knowing that you you practice you practice this knowing by
asserting propositions you say things like I believe that the earth is round
that's a proposition and I believe it and what I do is I gather evidence for
that particular proposition and if the evidence is enough I start to talk about
and it gives me explanatory power I start talking about a theory and I get a
sense of a conviction a sense of conviction that it's true and of course
ideologies make those same kinds of moves that's propositional knowing and for a
very long time because of the scientific revolution and Descartes and because also
of things going on in the Protestant Reformation we have started to think
that that's all knowing is just propositional knowing and we've done
we've done similar reductions we've reduced faith to belief we treat them
as if they're synonyms and we think that the most important thing for
explaining somebody's behavior are their beliefs and so we get this massive
reduction now what's happened in the cognitive science that I'm privileged
to participate in there's been a revolution going on in the last you
know 30 40 years it's called for e-cognitive science we can get into
that at some point if you want but the main idea is I draw from that is that
there are other kinds of knowing so there's procedural which isn't knowing
that something is it the case it's knowing how to do something it's knowing
how to catch a ball it's knowing how to kiss somebody right which isn't the same
thing as having a bunch of beliefs about kissing that's why you could read a lot
of books on kissing and it wouldn't make you a good kisser wouldn't make you a
good martial artist it can help but it's not it's nowhere near enough knowing
how has a lot more to do not with theories it has to do with skills about
how to right build up sensory motor patterns of interaction with the world
and and the sense of realness there isn't the sense of truth it's a sense of
power like when you have a skill you have expertise and that's why you give
authority to a doctor because they have a sense of skills obviously they have
beliefs but if they had the beliefs without the skills would you go to the
doctor no way right so that's procedural knowing it's knowing how
interestingly the forms of memory associated with the two kinds of
knowing are distinct your semantic memory your memory of facts is distinct
from your procedural memory your knowledge of skills so you can lose one
without losing the other so now related to that is another one which is think of
what you need for your skills you need what's called situational awareness so
is your skill of swimming relevant right now should you activate it should you
get you start swim now because it's not relevant here I mean if the room
suddenly flooded with water it could be so you need situational awareness to
tell you which skills to activate which skills you might need to acquire right
so what's the situational awareness what kind of knowing is that well this is
knowing what it's like to be here right now the here nowness so this is member I
mentioned it this is your knowing by salience landscaping how are you salience
landscaping how are you sizing up this situation right what's your state of mind
right so you have this this episodic memory which is a combination of your
state of mind in this situation so think of the difference in your memory
between remembering that two plus two equals four and your memory of your
last birthday one is just this fact that just hangs out the other is you recall
the situation a scene what stands out what's foregrounded what's backgrounded
and you recall your corresponding and co-determining state of mind so you
recall your perspective this is perspectival knowing now its sense of
realness isn't the conviction of truth or power we know what it is because and I
do work on this just published some papers on it with Dan Schiappi right in
terms of virtual reality so what are people looking for that they want the
game to be real what are they looking for it's called a sense of presence so
that perspectival knowing gives you a sense of realness when you have a sense
that you're really here really now really connected really present it's a sense of
presence as a realness okay what's under that what's under that is you don't come
into this situation as a blank slate contrary to what John Locke said you
come in with your biology your biological evolutionary heritage and your
culture shaping you and the environment to fit each other this chair is
suitable for me I can sit on it that's an affordance it affords sitting it
wouldn't afford sitting for an elephant right this glass this glass is
graspable by me evolution has shaped me to pick up objects like this and then
culture has taught me to shape my hand this way and and made objects that fit
my hand so this if this for me this is graspable the graspability is not in the
glass it's not in my hand but in the way my hand and the glass have been shaped
to each other by evolution and by culture and by my ongoing state of mind
this is an idea from Gibson and it's at the core of 40 cognitive science right
that you have right the way though you and your environment are co-shaping each
other and opening up a whole network of affordances that are available to you
for interacting with the world this is your participatory knowing this is your
knowing by being this is the relationship between your agency and how the world is
disclosed to you as an arena for action and they're mutually belonging together
now you have semantic memory for propositional knowing you have procedural
memory right for procedural knowing you have episodic memory for
perspective knowing what kind of memory do you have for this participatory
belonging in the world a profound kind of memory you call yourself your sense
of self your sense of identity this is the deep kind of memory a deep kind of
knowing so when you know something by binding yourself to it perhaps the way
you should know your partner right so your self-knowledge and your knowledge
of your partner are bound up together and they co-evolve and they shape each
other right and the two people right more and more conform to each other and
afford each other's transformation so you know love is the the medieval's had
this that love is its own way of knowing love is a primary example of
participatory knowing the kind of knowing that you can only have by loving
something right so the participatory knowing sets out the affordances the
perspective of knowing makes certain affordances salient and stand out so
it and then that activates what skills you're going to bring into the
interaction and then as you're interacting you bring out the facts
that are relevant to your interaction and that's how they all work so the
scientific worldview locks us here in the propositional and most of that
relevance realization that connectedness is happening on at the levels of the
non propositional knowing this is another profound reason why science
qua science can't give us the meaning now what science can do is give us the
science of those kinds of knowing so that we can better engineer the
psychotechnologies the practices that will enhance them that will make them
wiser and more meaningful enhance that connectedness so this is taking me to
altered states of consciousness I would love to talk about that of course you
should I think that so many of us are stuck focusing on the wrong things or
just at least very narrow things on our TV screens social media and the few
people that we have in our very small circles now how do you feel that how do
you feel altered states of consciousness fall into helping us with this
meaning so that is also a really profound question and I would I would
suggest to you that the renaissance of interest in psychedelics both
academically and culturally is another symptomatic response to the meaning
crisis people are craving enhanced connectedness the kind of union and
self-transcendence and as you said they're trying to break out of too narrow
of framing on reality and that's why they're seeking them out and of course
there's been a you know cross cultures cross history a long-standing
connection between psychedelics and mystical experience so they're not the
same but and and the cultivation of wisdom so we have to be very cautious
about this because we have the very thing that the very reason why people and
this is almost ironic the very reason why people might take psychedelics is the
kind of misframing they could bring to the psychedelics which is they could get
too focused and too narrow a framing of this psychedelic experience so altered
states of consciousness psychedelic experience mystical experience one of
the ways of thinking about them one of the ways I've been arguing up with lots
of people like Dana Craig and others we've been working on this idea Jensen
Kim a bunch of people is I want you to remember an experience that probably
happens to you every day and I want to use that and put it on a continuum with
altered states so you've had an aha moment can you remember one recently
where you realized oh I'm looking at this in completely the wrong way at that
aha experience where you've been thinking about something you're right I
should think about it this way I was the wrong I was concentrating on the wrong
thing the fact that you asked me that question means you've had that experience
so I study this I study is called insight and notice what it means to see
a to see into something right so what's happening in an insight experience notice
that we often talk about it like a flash of insight what's happening is your
salience landscape is suddenly shifting often they'll represented in movies with
things coming in and out of the foreground of the background right so
what's happening is a very dynamic reconfiguration of your salience
landscape right so you ask people well what grows from an acorn and oak what's
this stroke what's the gray stuff that comes off fire smoke what's the white of
an egg called and people say the yolk and you were gonna say right but the
answer is the white of the egg but what were you doing you were concentrating on
the oak sound you foregrounded that as relevant and then so you looked for the
part of the egg that has the oak sound in it you said yolk and then you laughed
because humor is related to insight because you realized that you had
misframed the situation okay now we are doing that all the time because like I
said the relevance realization process is constantly evolving and sometimes
though that evolution goes through this dynamic shift of self-correction this is
why insight is so associated with wisdom if you ask people could somebody be not
that educated but really wise they go yeah I think so what if they weren't very
artistic could they be wise yeah I think so could they be not very insightful and
wise they go no they got to be insightful to be wise there's a deep
connection there because they realize that insight is a little micro moment of
increased wisdom it's a little moment of self-transcendence it's a little moment
when you're breaking out of that narrow frame and you've got a moment when you
realized oh I was looking at it the wrong way now what I want you to consider is
that capacity for self-transcendence self-correction right and it comes with a
change in consciousness there's a flash it's on a continuum so if you get a
bunch of these insights at least that's what I published with Leo Ferrero and
Erin Herobinat in 2018 and you start chaining them together so an insight
leads to another insight leads to another insight like think about somebody
playing jazz they're playing jazz and they pick up and they break frame and
make a new frame and then they have to break the frame and make and they're
constantly they get into what's called the flow state athletes seek this out
because it's optimal you're at your very best and it feels like the most
amazing experience like in your act right so you're in the zone and I get it
like as a martial artist I get it when I'm lecturing and notice what people say
it's like they now talk about the whole world being super salient they feel that
one with their environment they feel deeply connected that's that enhanced
meaning right and flow states is when they start to feel like they're they
have that really deep connectedness but they're self-transcending they report a
loss of self-consciousness my consciousness you know that mattering
narrative nanny in your head how do I look how are people thinking of me what's
going on do they like me all of that all of that goes away because they're so at
one and like when you're a martial artist like if you're sparring in your
in your flow like it's so amazing you know at one level you're making all this
effort but your hand just goes for the block and you just find the opening for
the punch right or right or it's so that's the flow state notice how that's
already a profound altered state of consciousness now one of the interesting
features about flow Chikset Mahai has studied this for decades is it's a
universal it happens to people regardless of their gender their socio-economic
status their language their cultural background across all of this people
describe the flow experience in almost the same light the same terms of the
same level of detail so it's something profound going on because it's enhancing
right this this relevance realization this connectedness this capacity for
self-transcendence now take flow and its altered state of consciousness and ramp
it up instead of flowing as I'm sparring right or as I'm writing poetry or as I'm
playing jazz what have I flowed at the level of my grant my relationship to
reality as a whole what have I got into a flow state at the level of my world
view so I was doing what Blake said I was seeing a world in a grain of sand
that everything is interpenetrating and I'm getting this flow that's from the
gestalt to the feature and in and out to the center of my psyche out to the
depths of the world as a flow experience and imagine how that's going to
transform your salience landscaping and how it's going to even more reduce that
that self-consciousness it's going to be like a super awe experience those are
mystical experiences and then there's an overlap between psychedelic
experiences and even lion I just I interviewed him from my one of my
channels he's writing a book it's coming out called psychedelic experience
and he points out that psychedelic experiences don't have to use substances
there's other ways of triggering them and so you got you so you got insight
flow psychedelic experiences mystical experiences and then when mystical
experiences put people in touch with what they call the really real the most
real this is what's so fascinating about it they will transform their lives their
roles their relationships often their occupation in order to conform more and
more to that really real they'll invert everything so normally what we do is the
everyday is the real and anything that's off that's aberrant from that like a
dream or when we're drunk we go that's not real people do the opposite in these
experience they have these experiences the real really real and they say that's
real and all of this is less real and they change their lives because we want
to be in touch with what's most real and so altered states of consciousness are
are so sought after now because they give us the capacity for enhancing all of
that continuum from insight to transformative experience giving us the
self-transcendence the opportunity to get profound insight cultivate wisdom and
transform our sense of self all the kinds of knowing and so of course we're
seeking it but here's the danger here's the danger right if you don't have that
situated within an already existing ecology of practices in which you're
cultivating wisdom and a community that is giving you a worldview you can spin
off you can spin off from these altered states you can go down various rabbit
holes you can get into echo chambers you can come up with wacky metaphysics all
kinds of strange things happening so and I get into a little bit of trouble not
like officially but with the university and also I think I pissed people off a
little bit because I say two things and it sounds like contradiction I say we
should not prohibit substances doesn't work doesn't work I'm really confident
about that doesn't work okay but we should also license the use of them like
we do for a car or a handgun these are powerful tools you don't give a five
year old a chainsaw you don't give somebody in fact who doesn't know how to
use a chainsaw a chainsaw if you're gonna cut through the cords of your life
because you're seeking profound transformation you better know how to
use that tool right it's called the mind sword in you know in some of the
Buddhist traditions you know you better learn like and that's what decisive
means by the way it means to cut right if you if you don't know how to wield
that properly there's a potential for getting into some very significant
self-deceptive self-destructive behavior so I think that if we're cultivating
altered states of consciousness through mindfulness practices through movement
practices through group practices through the use of substances through
breathing techniques that should always be properly situated within a
sapiential sacred community I can see the problem with that argument where many
things that are licensed start to become really rigid so I'd imagine that the
whole licensing process of this look very different than anything else I mean
we talk about doulas for example yeah licensing at least in the US for a long
time because of that yes about the person and how can you license or restrict
how that process goes for each human well we do it for other things so here's my
counter example and you know this has become you know the case and there was
this discussion around it but we do it with psychotherapy we like it's now the
law that you can't practice psychotherapy unless you are approved by the
college and the idea here is because we're engaging in something that has the
capacity to you know radically transform people and therefore there is a power
and we have to make sure that people have both the scientific and the skill and
I would even add perhaps the moral training education so that they will
wield that power responsibly thank you okay I want to back up to something about
insight that it was great that you brought together the humor is human
insight somehow go together yes so humor from all the people that we've
interviewed so far has come up humor and martial art yes interestingly enough
and it was funny I was thinking about the aha moment how it's like a aha moment
yeah yeah yeah that's great I like that did you come up with that I have that's
beautiful I like that so I was right you can talk a little bit more about humor
and how that plays a role oh cognitive science but also very much and one of
the things that intrigued me is you know the cross-cultural for study of spiritual
traditions that have humor in them Zen has a lot of humor in it and others
where the humor is much more much more backgrounded and held down so humor these
three things are related humor metaphor and insight and and they don't come
naturally to human beings we have to practice it with kids for a long time so
try and get a four-year-old to tell a joke they're not very good at it try and
get them to understand metaphor they're not very good at it and their insight
capacity is also not that explicit to them so one of the ways of thinking about
this goes to work that's been really developed well by you McGill
Kristen I was privileged to have a conversation with him about but it lines
up with work from Cuneas Beeman Bowden a whole bunch of people that they have a
book called the Eureka factor having to do with the relationship between the
hemispheres so we were talking about like your ability to solve problems and
humor is actually making use of the problem-solving ability so I am getting
there right now there's two kinds of problems you're facing all the time one
is a problem that's very familiar to you it's very well-defined look like a
prototypical example is a multiplication problem you know what kind of problem it
is you know the actions you're supposed to perform you know when you're doing it
right you know when it's doing wrong you know what the results supposed to look
like very well-defined problem now compare solving a multiplication
problem with going on a successful first date what's the rule there so what's the
initial state well you're with some stranger okay what kind of problem is
this well what should I do I don't know like when I was dating I remember did
the advice my friends would give me was so useless was like look at her eyes but
not too much laugh at her jokes but not too often try to be funny but not to ask
questions but it's like right and so these are called ill-defined problems
and ill-defined problems are pervasive in your environment and what your brain is
really struggling to do again the framing is try and convert as many of
those ill-defined problems into well-defined problems that you can
build up habits and routines for right left hemisphere is about well-defined
problems step-by-step narrow focus attention to detail not language that we
people say languages in both hemispheres and that's stuff about drawing on the
right side of your brain and you have an artist in your right hemisphere and you
have some sort of fascist in your left hemisphere that's all ridiculous but the
left hemisphere tends to focus on well-defined problems the right tends
to focus on ill-defined problems so instead of focusing on detail it reaches
for the gestalt so think of like I think of a classic ill-defined problem
predator something's attacking you like you don't oh well what kind of predator
is it let's get very clear you're dead right so you want to do open up you want
to gestalt you it's ill-defined you want some very coarse-grained things you want
to grab associations as fast as you can so what typically happens when people
come into situations that are very ill-defined is you can see activity
being initially predominant in the left of the right hemisphere now what happens
in insight is you come to a problem and you think you know how to frame it oh
yes I know how to do this the left hemisphere is very dominant and then
you realize I don't know how to do this and you'll see the aha moment is when
activity shifts from the left to the right and then what happens in the right
is in here you're you're you're working within a frame and in here you're going
all that frames don't and now you're looking for a frame and then when you
get an alternative frame you bring it back you reframe your problem and that
that that's aha something else that does that is metaphor metaphor also does
that shift so when I say and we notice notice how much your cognition is
drenched in metaphor I just did it by the way so you'll say things like we're
halfway through this interview halfway way through we're not moving through
space the interview I hope it's not too hard John I hope right I hope you're
seeing what I'm saying I hope you're getting it I hope you're understanding
it I hope you're right to see in fact try to say anything profound and
meaningful to somebody without invoking a metaphor because you're trying to
afford insight this is the work of lake often Johnson although I have some
criticisms of the specifics of their theory okay so metaphor and insight and
we use metaphor we use propositional metaphors to try and trigger non-
propositional insight so and of course Shakespeare is an exemplar of this
humor involves metaphor when it's verbal humor of some kind right and it
involves a sudden reframing you have to get the punchline you have to have the
aha moment that's why people will often retrospectively see a failure of
insight as something funny they'll go oh haha so humor is it like one of the
things you're doing when somebody gets a joke right is you're playing with things
you know don't live leave alphabet soup on the you know boiling on the stove it
could spell disaster okay it's a bad joke but but the point is notice how I'm
playing right on two different meanings and moving between them and you got to
shift the meaning right you got a reframe you have to have that insight and
you do it retrospectively and it alleviates the tension between like
there's a there's an initial problem and then you resolve it with insight and you
play with sort of the metaphorical aspects of language we've got humor and
then with other humor that's non-verbal we're doing sort of something
analogously I would argue with like perspectival knowing things like that so
humor metaphor insight are bound together and you can see why people who are
seeking transformation would rely on them because they're what you're doing is
you're trying to fuel and prime the engine of cognitive flexibility of your
ability to reframe right and to alter what's salient and relevant to you in a
way that connects to you that matters to you that's meaningful to you and of
course that's going to help you take ill-defined situations like when
something traumatic has happened to us or when some opportunity that's golden
has suddenly opened up to us should I get involved with that person should I
try that new career we're going to turn to these as a way of trying to enhance
our ability to deal with ill-defined situations
I need to believe so many people are resistant to taking their glasses off and
seeing what's on there because I mean part of it is part of it is cultural we
have truncated and reduced people's sense of their mind and their self and
those aren't identical but they're related and so we people don't when
people don't have the ability to access that cognitive flexibility and when
they're in a meaning scarcity this is called scarcity mentality when human
beings face any significant scarcity of food water of you know friendship
relationship meaning they become very rigid they become very narrow they become
very short-term in their thinking this is why you know sort of you know blaming
people for bad behavior because they're poor is is perhaps getting things the
wrong way around right instead right you think of people in scarcity so if we've
taken all of the meaning and wisdom machinery away and we've really reduced
people's sense of what they're what they are you are your beliefs and they're
shrunk down here and they're starving of course they're going to be resistant to
taking their glasses off they're going to be rigid and resistant and they're in
fact they're going to double down on holding on to the beliefs with which
they identify if you feel comfortable talking about this I'm not sure if this
is your area of expertise so rebel wisdom yes they talk about sense-making yes
sense-making and meaning making what's the relationship between them so they're
they're they're they overlap to a great degree so sense-making was a term coined
I think I believe by maybe it was O'Shamel but it was made prominent by
Francisco Varela who is one of the pioneers of 4e cognitive science and
then by my former colleague Evan Thompson who is like if you want to
understand 4e cognitive science you have to look at Evan's work Evan is
brilliant and profound and it was it was a loss when he left University of
Toronto go to UBC so they coined this term of sense-making and the the basic
idea is this that even a paramecium right is doing it's detecting its
environment right and it's adapting and responding and so in its sensory motor
behavior it's it is treating it's not seeing it doesn't have consciousness or
everything like that but it's detecting this molecule as food food isn't part of
physics like if you look in a physics textbook you won't you won't find a
definition for food food is an affordance relationship between this
chemical and this the autopoiesis the self-making of the paramecium the
paramecium because it's constantly taking care of itself because it's a
living thing it's caring about this I don't mean full blow in emotion but
there's a kind of caring very small scale right there's a kind of caring of
and it's also that molecule is poison so it swims away from that one and swims
towards this one so it's doing sense-making it's making sense of its
right of its environment now if you lift that sense-making up into what we
could call kinds of knowing then the sense-making I would argue is meaning
making in this time right now where people are trying to make sense of so
much why do you do you feel that this is a skill that people could work to get
better at I would be I'd be really strong about that I would say it's a
necessity if you do not get better at waiting through all the bullshit and I
use that in a very technical sense maybe you can ask me about that but if we do
not get better and one of the other symptoms of the meeting crisis we
track this in the book is people feel like bullshit and bullshitting is
expanding both quantitatively there's more of it and it's in more domains and
it's people are getting more and more shameless about the bullshitting which
is really egregious if you don't do something about that toxicity right the
way that that is radically undermining your capacity to connect to reality and
exacerbating making you more and more prone to self-deceptive self-destructive
behavior if you don't do anything about that given the way right social media is
complexifying and with it the bullshitting is complexifying and
permeating your life and percolating into the depths of the psyche and ways
you're not aware of if you're watching if you're using lots of social media I
will predict that you are suffering more depression and anxiety I'm confident
about that if you don't do something to address and ameliorate that I strongly
predict it's going to get worse for you with time and not only with you as an
individual but with you and your group
would you explain echo chambers sure so remember we talked about you know the
way we we have to focus in and and and these are very adaptive now one of the
things you do and I do too is we do what's called the confirmation bias now
in a lot of environments this is adaptive so I want I want to understand
that I want you to understand that but what does it mean well what does it mean
is generally we don't look for information that challenges or
disconfirms our belief we look for information that supports it that's
confirmation bias again one more time right in a lot of environments messy
environments complex environments right that's adaptive that's why we do it but
it makes us vulnerable to environments that aren't ones we evolved to fit like
the internet where we can rapidly get access to hundreds and hundreds of
people confirming our belief in something and then when that goes to that
starvation for meaning then we don't want to give up any beliefs we can just
again and then we can we can just do this we I can reinforce your confirmation
bias you can reinforce mine my my collaborator and good friend Leo
Ferrero he calls this confirmation porn we can get into this kind of
pornography of just confirming and confirming and we get locked in and
then we more and more identify with it because you're telling me yeah yeah
that's the way the world is and so I'm more and more and then we just cycle in
this is a phenomenon that my friend and colleague Mark Lewis in his work on
addiction calls reciprocal narrowing and then I think that the and I said I
said this to Mark I think the platonic wisdom tradition talks about an opposite
thing we can cultivate which is reciprocal opening so echo chambers are
reciprocal narrowing and when look think what happens to the addict the addict
loses cognitive flexibility and so their options in the world go down so the
world gets more and more narrow and then they internalize that and then they get
more and more narrow and that until I can't be any other than I am the world
can't be any other than it is and that's addiction so this echo chambering is
very analogous to that reciprocal narrowing that's going on in addiction
and we we are addicted to a lot of stuff I mean the addiction crisis as I
mentioned is one of the issue we're more and more finding ourselves addicted to
more and more things and there's more and more people that are exploiting us
politically economically by getting us addicted and the internet has algorithms
that do that. I think that this is a really really important topic right now
because PTSD is a household term yes but post-traumatic growth very few people
have even heard of that I know the lack of awareness that things can be great on
the other side of difficult experiences that just seems like a responsible thing
to know yes talk about so this is a serious concern of ours as we put this
documentary out there is an invalidation or perception of an invalidation of an
experience people assuming that because we're talking about post-traumatic
growth PTSD doesn't exist or we're anti PTSD and so I would love to talk to you
about this or if you can explain a little bit about or just if I were to speak on
behalf of that person right now my echo chamber makes me feel heard you know I
feel like I have a community yes I'm infertile and I'm seeing how hard other
women have it yes yes that feels good but to what extent and when does that
become a negative experience right and so that's that's a really beautiful
question I thought that's well well framed and a problem well framed is you
know the the beginning of insight so I mean there's a lot of variables and and
the and this is not to derail what we're doing but the literature on you know
post-traumatic growth is going like the scientific literature is in this
liminal place because we're sort of through first wave and then there's been
a second critical wave and now people are coming out of that and there so we're
trying to get a more sophisticated answer to a very complex phenomenon but let's
go back to the so I want I want that as sort of the general frame in which we're
talking about this let's go back to the what's the difference between a support
group like AA and right an echo chamber because they do share important
similarities and so one of the things you given what we've said one of the things
you should look for at least a set of things is you should look for is your
group actually promoting cognitive flexibility is it promoting reciprocal
opening is it helping you to gain more flexibility are you having more aha
moments now the thing about these groups is they give you initial oh I didn't
realize that the leprechauns were behind it all and stuff like that right so
right and they give you sort of pseudo insight so you have to ask yourself this
question are the insights in the cognitive flexibility within the group
transferring to your life outside of the group let me give you a really good
analogy for this think about different kinds of video games or let's comply
one kind I'm not saying all video games are like this I'm not let's say one kind
of video game and something like Tai Chi Chuan and this was a transformative
thing for me not the video games of the Tai Chi Chuan okay so you know people
one of the reasons kids love video games is because video games are flow induction
machines they they're they're like jazz they are reliable for putting people
into the flow state right so within that world they're just but you get video
game addiction the WHO has designated an addiction when that doesn't transfer to
your life so the skills like all and the perspective of the states of
consciousness in mind their sense of identity and self because you're
manipulating those and video games like a religion
right is that is that percolating through the rest of your psyche is it
permeating through your life is it transferring
when I was doing Tai Chi and I started back in 91
before cell phones right the ancient times I was in grad school like I said I
was doing the Tai Chi for cultivating wisdom I was in grad school at the time
and it's funny because when you're in grad school you're always you always feel like
you're an imposter right I don't really belong here they're going to find out
eventually right the people came up to me my friends and I've been doing the
Tai Chi like religiously in both senses of the word I was doing it every day for
two or three hours a day and I was having all these amazing experiences you know
the days when you you're as hot as fire and the days where you're as cold as ice
and you're getting into the flow state and it's amazing but I was just I was just in that world
they came up to me and they said what's up with you what do you mean they said you're different
you're way more flexible in your thinking you're way more empathetic and picking up on other
people you're way more balanced in your argumentation and I realized oh the Tai Chi was moving beyond
the martial art arena and it was percolating through my psyche it's permeating through my
lives it was transforming and that's because I wasn't just doing the Tai Chi Chuan I was doing
these ecologies and I was learning the philosophy of Taoism and so it was like and that's what
religions do they give you these and it does that that's my criteria if you're in your support
group and whatever's happening here you feel that it's percolating through your psyche in a way
that's permeating through your life and opening up your life and you've got a support group if you
feel it's taking you down and you're getting locked in and you can only find that in the group
then you're moving towards an addiction you're moving towards kind of spirituality
you're moving towards a cult now those are on a continuum I present them as opposites for contrast
but we they're on a continuum and there's going to be stuff in the gray zone it's going to be I'm
not sure when I get that and that's going to take discernment and discussion and reflection
but that's how I would say is it open are you reciprocally opening comprehensively
about across more and more in your life are your existing relationships getting better
are you feeling more in touch with reality are you able to cultivate new friendships are you
able to cultivate new virtues the answer is yes chances are you have a support group if the answer
to those increasingly if those is increasingly no chances are you're locking you're locking into
an echo chamber thank you okay last question for me um is are there any other areas of research
that if you had another you that can explore whatever and you just don't have time for right
now is there any like like epigenetics or something that feel like could be a really cool thread to go
down with your work oh boy um I I joke with my colleagues um like my dear friend Dan Chappie
we've published a bunch of stuff together we're always working together I don't know if you know
but there's a there's a science fiction classic show called Dr. Who and he has the TARDIS which is
you know trans dimensional and all this I want a TARDIS where I can go in there and be outside
time and space and do a bunch of stuff and then come back out there I have to tell you Jessica
there's so many books that I'm like I'm currently reading about 30 books at a time it's a skill I've
been cultivating for like three decades I don't recommend it for anybody as a novice but even
that I feel like just I look at all the books I'm not reading and I go I need to know this because
you know I'm more ignorant than than than than I have knowledge I would like to know a lot more
about neuroscience I would like to know a lot more about like I I've studied some I've studied both
from the outside as an academic and from the inside as a practitioner Taoism and Buddhism
Christianity Neil Platonism Stoicism but there's a whole bunch like I don't know very much about
Islam not enough about Judaism not enough about lots of aspects of Hinduism Vedanta the indigenous
stuff I know a bit about shamanism but to equate that to indigenous culture is like terrifically
racist and ethnocentric so I admit that I'm mostly ignorant I want to know I just yeah like so I
the hard neuroscience up to you know you know the cultural anthropology those are the two ends of
my where I feel that I need to know more that's where I mean I need to fill in a lot in between
that sounded arrogant pretentious but where I feel the gap most prominently is on those ends
awesome thank you thank you so much