As you know, I have a thesis about the exponential age
that we're about to go through the fastest pace of technology
the world has ever seen.
That's what this whole series is about.
This next interview with an old friend of mine
is probably one of the most important single interviews
you will watch.
I can't stress enough how important the concepts
and what is happening and the speed of which
artificial intelligence is going to change humanity.
It is something that we all need to pay attention to,
understand and use in our favour because it's happening
and it's happening at a scale of which you cannot comprehend.
Emma, fantastic you see you back on Real Vision.
Good to be back. Thanks for having me.
You were known in the past in various guises on Real Vision
because this is not your first rodeo.
You were the frontier guy
and we're going to talk about a new frontier today
and then also in the pandemic you helped guide us
through some of that too.
Give people a bit about your background
because it's a fascinating background
and it's an interesting journey to where you are today.
Yeah, it has been a few different skins.
I was a hedge fund manager
at the start of my career running Global Macro
then switched to emerging markets, frontier markets
and tech.
At one point I was one of the larger video game investors
which is also quite fun.
Took a bit of a break when my son was diagnosed with autism
and I used artificial intelligence to re-put up his drugs
to make him it better.
Well advised him some top hedge fund managers
and governments on various things including counter extremism
and fun things like that.
Went back to being a hedge fund manager, did okay
and then had a look at the world.
What we do as fund managers is we look for arbitrage opportunities
and we look for where things are building up and breaking down
and it struck me that a lot of stuff was breaking down.
I decided like let's try and make it better effectively
by combining some of these systems
and some of these arbitrage opportunities.
So one of the big things was education.
Another big thing was leading the United Nations
AI initiative against COVID-19.
I think the last time I was on Real Vision
was February this thick, 2020
and we had a nice chat about how the world was going to change
dramatically and it did
and then I was like oh crap I have to do something about it.
So we made all the COVID research in the world free
and pushed that and then I was lead architect of Kayak
which was the UNESCO World Bank WHO backed initiatives
to use artificial intelligence to take all that knowledge
and compress it down to reports for policymakers
so that we can be a bit more coordinated.
Similar to how we take all that information and fund management
compress it down and try to figure out those key drivers.
It was a mixed success but I think it did some difference
and now from that something a bit bigger
which is AI for everything basically.
So AI has clearly now become your thing, right?
This is your focus.
So before we get into what you're doing now
what the hell gave a hedge fund manager
the thought process that hey I can help the WHO
and everybody else with artificial intelligence?
Well it's because to be a hedge fund manager
you have to be a bit of an egomaniac, right?
I know that you're right and everybody else is kind of wrong.
Look I mean all of what we do is information classification
and that's the nature of artificial intelligence.
So information comes in and then Claude Shannon
style of information theory.
Information is only valuable as much as the change in the state
so you're always looking for something on that graph
or that new thing that will cause you to change
from a buy to a sell or an increase or decrease
in your positioning, right?
I kind of realized over the years though
like my background was mathematics, computer science originally
quite quantitative, quite analytical.
The next wave of AI was something a bit different
that would enable us to do something a bit different
because we moved from this big data age, you know
where you had massive amounts of information
and extrapolated it and targeted it to kind of sell
Raoul some suntan or whatever, you know?
To something a bit different, a big model
You're jealous of my tan.
I'm jealous of your tan.
I'm in London, you're in Cayman Island, I'm turning pasty.
Completely.
I have to fly out there too.
So moving from that area was about extrapolation
in the individual to something new in 2017
which was a big model age.
AI went from being able just to extrapolation
to being able to pay attention.
In fact, there was a seminal paper called
attention is all you need about how to build an AI
that paid attention to the most important parts of a sentence
the most important parts of an image
to do principle based analysis
which is insane if you think about it
this is exactly what we do, right?
What do you mean by principle based analysis?
Sorry.
So rather than doing extrapolation
so rather than doing momentum, beta
AI became able to do alpha
it became able to basically come up with principles
that allowed it to understand
the hidden layers of meaning
with things.
So you can go into a bit more detail
but this is how the human brain works, right?
We have two parts of our brain
which is like the past
and that's a tiger over there
in that bush, right?
It's the type one type two kind of thinking
so AI was always the extrapolation
and now we have a new type of AI
that mimics the human brain
by figuring out principles
from highly structured data
which is kind of what we did every single day
as the finance guys, right?
But at a completely different scale
I don't think even now people have appreciated
how big a change that's going to be
I think we're starting to figure that out now.
So
before we get into the guts of this
let's go on a bit of the journey
of AI
because you've talked about where it was
and then we started to see stuff like
DeepMind
and then GPT-3
OpenAI, all of this.
So if you can just frame it for people
because a lot of this is going to be new for people
and I think it's incredibly important
people understand what's happening
and where the hell of this is going.
Yeah, so if you look at DeepMind
they are famous for
many things, you know, Demos has done
a fantastic job.
One of the things they did is
thinking back, you had Gary Kasparov
being beaten by Deep Blue
so you know, as older fellows we remember that
not like the younger with the snapkins
who'd never seen a bear market in their lives
you know, kind of changes happening
what Deep Blue did was
it did an analysis of every single game
in the past and then extrapolated
and then it brute-forced it.
So Gary could only think X moves in the future
he could think X plus 2, X plus 3
and that's how he got beaten by brute-force.
Now, the Chinese game of Go
Chinese checkers, effectively
people thought you'd never be able to brute-force it
because there's too many things that you can do
there's too many moves on that board, right?
And so they were like,
that'll never be beaten by computer
because you need to build a computer that's
the biggest computer ever
times a million.
What DeepMind did
is that basically they came up with
a self-supervised learning algorithm
that
learned how to dream
that's probably the best way to kind of put it
about how one would play
Go in a principled way
so it didn't even have
all the past games in its memory
it just played against itself and tried to figure out
how to do this. They made a whole base of these
agents with reinforcement learning
that you gave it an Atari with no instructions
that learned how to play Breakout
and then Starcraft
without any instructions
people need to understand that, they figured it out
you put it in front of the computer
and it just figures it out and it gets better and better
so when you see it playing Breakout
it's suddenly doing these crazy moves like that
and so Lisa Doll was like a seventh Dan
in Go
so she was a Magnus Carlson
of Go effectively
and it wasn't a current Magnus Carlson
type situation, it's very difficult to cheat in Go
because you didn't have to be able to talk to you
we're not talking about anal probes in this one
we're talking about
compensation is going pretty well
so what happened is
that the next highest person
was like a fourth Dan or something
so he's like Federer Carlson rolled into one
that much better, I was like never beat him
he won one game
the computer won seven
and everyone was like holy crap
what is that, because computer learned to play
in a completely different way
and it was like it was playing with an alien
because it didn't learn past games
as you said it learns an entirely new way
literally it played against itself
it dreamt
so then it plays against itself in its memory
and then it does that again and again and again
and so within just a few weeks
it outperformed him
and then these models got better and better
and smaller and smaller, we haven't seen the generalization of the models yet
but they're coming
so you have to optimize when you don't even tell it the rules
which is kind of insane
then on the other hand
you had what was known as foundation models
which is where this attention based
architecture came in
so in the attention thing they were seeing when the games were
actually a final thing about this
and you can see this in the AlphaGo documentary
that's on YouTube if you want to see more details
is that as a result of this
did Lisa doll go and say
I'm hanging up my go pieces
and I'm going to pack them away, no
he started playing against it and now he's even better
as a player
and the entire go
competitive scene has improved
because now they're figuring out brand new ways
and gambits and things they'd never seen before
which I think is really interesting
then you had this other big area
which was kind of some of this deep learning area
we have these big corpuses
and like I said you can do extrapolations
but you don't understand meaning
and so this is where these attention based architectures came in
it's actually quite interesting
when I was taking a break
from fund management to work with my son
autism is a very interesting condition
no cure, nothing to be done
so of course you know you go and quit being a hedge fund manager
and build a team and try to do it
because you go maniacs right
my wife is a applied behavioural
analyst who just treats kids
with autism
so I lived that life
exactly so applied behavioural
analysis uses variable
rewards and a lot of the stuff you use in video games
to rebuild words
so if you have a stroke or you have autism
you haven't basically said can
right so the word can can mean I can
it can mean that can
it can mean the can can
lots of different things
but because there's so much noise in the brain
which is why you see a lot of kids and adults with autism
not being able to handle large amounts of information
I don't have aspergers myself and ADHD
they usually balance out
sometimes not quite
it's very difficult to pay attention
to how you feel that
like you know when your leg is tapping
there's just too much going on
that's the fugue state
because there's two transmitters in the brain
GABA which calms you down
and GLUTAMATE which excites you
so when you pop a valiant the GABA levels go up
and imagine if your brain was always excited
for one reason or another
you wouldn't be able to concentrate
and build those connections to the word can
you know that hidden layer of meaning
for what can is
what can actually cause it
but because medicine treats everyone the same
it meant that one drug that made 34% of kids better
made 28% of kids worse
so there's no cure and there's no treatment
so that's a different bigger story
and something again this AI can help with
and why is that relevant
it's because what this AI does now
is exactly the same
it uses giant honking supercomputers
so that if you take a terabyte of text
it learns what the most important words
in the sentence are
it took
a thousand gigabytes of text
and it learned how to write in any style
and any extension
so it paid the most important part of any sentence
so you give it a sentence like legolas and gimli
that's all you give it and it'll write an entire scene
in the style of Tolkien
that's never been seen before
you know you give it a sentence
and you say make it happier
it understands what happier is
and this is what's called a latent space of meaning
because it takes
that took one terabyte
of information so a thousand gigabytes
and GPT-3 is about
40 gigabytes in size
but it can recreate any style of writing
an understanding style of writing
which is again a bit crazy
I mean it's
it's staggering and we'll come into the societal impact
on what this all means in a bit
but just want to get through the technology
it is astonishing when you see GPT-3
because basically it writes authentic
pieces
that are not stolen from other things
much like
the deep
deep mind did with go
it wasn't stealing from old games
it learnt how to do it
is that right?
it learnt principles, it learnt stars
it learnt what's called a latent space
the hidden layers of meanings
between different types of words
so like we just released
the most advanced image version of that
stable diffusion
stable diffusion took
100,000 gigabytes
so 100 terabytes of images
and we made a 2 gigabyte file
that can do any style
and any image of any type
so this is like Dali
right?
it's Dali on steroids
so subscribe now to the channel
and never miss an update
there is simply too much going on
so subscribe now, thank you
so
explain Dali and then we'll come into what you're doing
because again
I just want to get people up the knowledge graph
because Dali was the next big one that I stopped
in my tracks and went holy shit this is
amazing
so GPT-3 came out in 2020
and then we released
the open source version of that GPT-Mia
which I'll convert to
last year there was a breakthrough in image generation
so you can generate text and everyone was like
image is too difficult right?
because a picture paints a thousand words
like it's really going to be a thousand kinds of complex
turns out it wasn't
so you had something called clip
which basically you took any image
and it would be able to classify it
so it would be able to say that's a Raoul
and that's a red sofa and all these things
understand loads of concepts because they compress that down
then you had a generative model that took words to images
so you had two models, a word to image model
and image to word model
and at the start of last year we figured out how to bounce them off each other
so it would generate an image
and it would check if that image was the same as the prompt
and it would go back and forth, back and forth
and after 10 minutes you'd generate
a semulchrum of an image
from the word input so words go in and images come out
and you're like oh crap
it looks a bit mushy
but that's insane, it can generate an image of anything
but it isn't high quality
then what happened is that
OpenAI and us accelerated that whole space
because we thought it was freaking cool
and put lots of research into it
and so you've got to the point now whereby
you can put in Robert De Niro's Gandalf
and one second later
you get an image output
so the first output of that was
that hit the mainstream was Dali from OpenAI
that was in April of this year
so you can say
a cybercone, goth girl
overlooking Neo Tokyo
and boom, 8 seconds later it's generated
and this is a totally unique
creative image that did not exist
in the world before, right?
it did not exist in the world before
all the data that went into that
so it was about 600 million images
it can't recreate any of those images
instead it's learned the
principles of that so again it's
the principle based analysis
which is insane, right?
because it's like
again it's the heuristic stuff that we do all the time
and they combine different concepts
you can say a Van Gogh
by Banksy
and it will do a Van Gogh
by Banksy or you can kind of do a screen
and now there's more and more technologies
that have been measured from that
so OpenAI kind of announced the closed beta
of that and then
my company Stability AI
created a version, well it's 30 times faster
and more powerful
so tell me about Stability AI
when did it start, who's involved
what are you guys doing?
yeah, so starting in 2020
we're technically starting in 2019
with the education work
but I can talk about that later
but 2020 is when it was formed officially
to do the COVID work
so it's lead the UN COVID initiative
launched at Stanford etc
I founded it, yeah
because
someone needs to build something
to do AI as a public good
so I didn't exactly know what the business model was
or anything like that then, I just thought
people are dying effectively
and then we have the other products, actually I'll mention it
so my co-founder and I
so Joe's runs the charitable arm
we have took the global X prize
for learning so that was a $15 million
prize funded by Elon Musk and Tony Robbins
for the first app that could teach
literacy and numeracy in 18 months
for that internet and we've been deploying
in refugee camps and low income areas around the world
to the point where now
we are teaching kids literacy
and numeracy in 13 months and one hour a day
in a refugee camp in Malawi
and we just got the remit
to educate every child in Malawi, 3.9 million kids
with a completely open
book of hardware, software, deployment and curriculum
so we're going to invite the world to say
let's build an open source education system
where the AI teaches the kids and the kids teach the AI
that's the type of stuff that we wanted to do
because so much of the world's issues
are coordination problems
so I figured out how to bring in the multilaterals
the locals and others like the simple mechanism design
and so let's do education
let's do healthcare but then as we were doing this
and we talked to a lot of the big private companies
they promised a lot and they didn't deliver
and it's called me thinking about the future
so some of the people on this call
will be familiar with
the Chinese social credit score system
and the use of AI in China
to identify Ugears and others
and everyone's got a rating
you hang out with someone with too low a rating
your rating starts to go down
8 million people in China can't use planes or trains
it's behavioural economics right
done by AI
it's gamified life
life has become a video game
and AI is the extra system on top
but now you think about it
the entire web 2
was basically Facebook and Google
it was AI
big data models
and now you've moved to the big model era
where to build these models you need to have the best data
amazingly smart people
and fricking supercomputers
why fricking supercomputers I mean
is that a multiple times faster than NASA
supercomputers because that's what compresses
this data down into knowledge
so information to knowledge on this
because knowledge is when you extract the principles
from information right
and then wisdom is when you apply it to today
so we have this some knowledge extraction system
so I looked at that and I was like
the only people that can build this are NVIDIA
Meta, Google
slash DeepMind, Microsoft
slash OpenAI
and how are they aligned
because this is super powerful technology
they can be used to target us ads better than anything else
or it can be used to change our mind because it's convincing
you see GPT-3 writing
you can't tell it's not a human
right
you look at the audio version you can't listen
say it's not human like my sister-in-law
Zeena just sold her company
to Spotify, it's an Antik
fully emotionally real AI voices
using this technology
so she did the technology for all the
Blizzard and everything
and then somebody has now got AI
for creating podcasts
so you can have Joe Rogan interviewing
Steve Jobs
neither of these exist and the interview never existed
but the AI does it
and it sounds just like them right
and this is the thing it's got that human level
so like Sanantik also did
Bal Kilmer's voice for his documentary
in Top Gun because he lost it completely
and it's completely emotionally real
so it's getting to that period of emotional realness
and human realness
which means then you think about the future and you're like
this is one of the most powerful technologies
ever because it's approaching humanity
not in a generalized sense
where the AI can do everything in its sky net
but as a tool
for targeting and convincing
and manipulation
so what happens if only big tech companies
do this because they went from being open
to being private even open AI
that got a billion dollars from Musk
and others and then a billion from Microsoft
stop releasing their code
so people can have this
so they turn closed
and then they stop sharing
and you're like as this is the most powerful thing
if you fast forward 5-10 years
does it make sense that a private company will have a monopoly
or a series of private companies will have a monopoly on this
then it will reflect
basically Palo Alto norms
and it will mean those companies are more powerful
than any government in the earth
and I was like that's wrong
I was like there needs to be
an alternative that is open
you know kind of AI for the people by the people we call it
because
not only is that morally right
because it's unethical to keep powerful technology
that can make people's lives better
from the people that can benefit from it the most
but it's actually a better model
because you have open innovation
this is why Linux became the servers of choice
and the most secure servers
Windows has all these holes in
Linux holes get patched instantly right
this is where you've got databases kind of taking over
because nothing can beat human creativity when that happened
I look at web3 and crypto
and I'm like it nearly got there
and then it kind of got hijacked
because it was part of the puzzle
but it wasn't the whole puzzle
because when I went to talk to a lot of web3 people
I'm like where's the AI in web3
they were like well we'll get to it
but I was like the whole of web2 was AI
how are you gonna do web3 without AI
and when they gave examples like Alephia
and other things
with the talking NFTs
the technology they used was our technology
and we released
but usgpt near
which I thought was quite interesting
so then I realised it's actually a bigger thing here
and a bigger reason to do this
but how do you compete with open AI
and deep mines and Microsoft and Google
with their billions of dollars of budget
which was an interesting one
how do you do it right
do you go and raise two billion dollars
no go do it another way
so what did you do
so I built community
so in 2020 a lot of people
were just like you know COVID
and in quarantine
so we built up a Luther AI
which the base principle was
let's create an open source version of GPT3
you know
did you create it
or clone GPT3
and then allowed to build on top
how do you start this
so like there were five initial creators
and then I came like a month after
and we were working with some of the second wave
and said let's accelerate this up
so they looked at the model so the data wasn't open
so we had to create our own data set
and so we had to crawl the internet
and create a terabyte of data
the compute wasn't available
so we got a grant from Google
who provided the compute initially
and then the expertise
it was all like PhD students
or self-taught programmers
and others were like how would this work
because they released an academic paper
from scratch and then created a model
that was 75% as good
but it was available
so the models from a Luther AI
which kind of stability runs now
basically via the top level
people but we're going to spin it off
into its own independent charity
for a number of reasons
they've been downloaded 25 million times
now by developers
so anytime you see a chat bot
or something like that that's getting to human levels
it's probably going to be that
it's 80% as good as GPT-3
but it doesn't matter because you can customize it
and you can extend it
and you can run it on your own hardware
so it's a 20 billion parameter model
versus 175 billion parameter model
it's eight times smaller
but you know it's just like the big steel mills
and the little ones if you look at the kind of Clayton Christian
small can outcompete big
and then I realized that there's a talent arbitrage here
whereby there's a lot of people
that want to build open source
but there's no super compute
in academia so when I said super compute
needed for this I meant it
like the
amount of super compute
the amount of breakthroughs in this foundational
model research
20 years ago 100% came from academia
10 years ago 75%
came from academia last year
0% came from academia
because there was this
massive ramp-up in compute capabilities
but academia couldn't access it
only private companies could
so if you wanted to have a breakthrough
or work in cutting edge research you had three options
do a start up, start up suck
put that to the side, especially for academics
number two you go and work for big tech
and then you get 59 page NDAs
and you might do cool stuff
like we've seen text to video from the Google team
that'll never be released by Google
because of ethical fears which we can discuss
and the final option is
you go and work for some of these independent labs
like OpenAI and others that were meant to be independent
and then became less independent over time
otherwise you stay in academia and you're like
I would like to do these but I can't
so I saw that the core
choke point was compute
a community was forming for talent
and then we need to be highly structured about data
so what I did was
I said how big a super computer can I build
if I put all my money into it
and I'd become very persuasive
and then I built the 10th fastest public
super computer in the world in four months
and it turns out you can build a very large super computer
so Ezra 1 which is our super computer
which all my money went into
is about
eight times faster than the fastest
super computer in the UK
and about seven times faster than all of NASA's
super computers put together
and that's the level that you need
to basically create these models
it's like the entry level
that need for compute keeps going up
can you use distributed computing power
or is it still not fast enough
so
you can do it once you've done the initial model
so what happens is that you take
in this case we took 100,000 gigabytes of data
so we made the biggest image data set in the world
previously the largest was 100 million
then we made 400 million
then we made 5.6 billion
a 250 terabyte image
label pair data set
then we took 2 billion of that
which is the high quality images and then we crunched them back and forth on this
so what happens is after you crunched
them back and forth then you've got a file
that can be adapted and trained
basically it's gone through
primary school
of learning
and then you can teach it more advanced concepts
so like some people are taking the training on Japanese
concepts, some people are taking
anime cat girl, waifus or whatever
you can add that specialization
once it's achieved kind of the high school level
so there's a big compute
and a little computer
does the network then learn from all of these people
working on the network itself
no
it's distributed and you've got lots of people doing different things
does that increase the knowledge base
or not
it increases the large base of the community
but we have to understand this model
it's not a distributed model where it's like lots of little
brain cells out there
it's a 2
gigabyte file
that can recreate
and create any image in any style
so you took 100,000 gigabytes of image and created
so sometimes I think
I'm on that Silicon Valley show
and we're from HBO
and we're Pied Piper and I think
crap, am I Erlich Backman or Ross Hanneman
you know
it's one of those kind of guys right
it's the most advanced technology
the world's ever seen for compression because
the entirety of humanity is basically
about communication and compression
we're compression machines
that's all we do
so people are listening to this podcast now
and they're listening to yours and mine
common context and the compression
and the knowledge that we've had over the years
and they're learning something new right now
it's what we do and hopefully it's valuable
because they'll see that holy crap this new technology way
was coming but if you can do it to images
you can do it to anything so actually how we had
the breakthrough is we took a language model
and image model and we fused them together
and somehow it learned the different concepts
then what we're seeing is that
when you have different models of different types
so someone takes a 2 gigabyte file
you take it and you put it on all your images in
and I take it and I put all my images in
and I fused them together and create another 2 gigabyte file
that knows both of them without going up
in size very much
that's a bit insane in fact
OpenAI did this with a model called GATO
recently
so what happened is that there were
hundreds of different models they built that were quite big
that were like robotics
and playing chess and all these other things
they said what happens if we combine them all together
and see what happens to these latent spaces
the hidden meanings of understanding just like the neurons in our brain
it created a 1.6 billion
parameter file that can
open doors and play chess
and play starcraft and all sorts of other things
and they were like what
and this is the thing
you've got a breakthrough in intelligence
but then you've broken through
to the point where this is the important part
stable diffusion is the first model
that's small enough, fast enough and cheap enough
to go anywhere
so you can run it on your MacBook M1
and you can make Robert De Niro by Banksy
and Renoir
in Guadalajara
in a snowstorm
without internet access
and that 2GB file will reproduce that
faithfully each time
yes
it is a 2GB file that has
compressed the knowledge of the internet
in images
I can't quite get my head around this
so
where do you think
what you're working on goes
what is the image thing, where is this going towards
because right now it's kind of interesting
yes we're going to see
creative industries, marketing, others use this
quite quickly and effectively
but where is this
in your head, where is your mental model
what you're actually working on here
because you're not working on
creating nice images, you're working on something bigger
what is that
it's the intelligent internet
this is about to be pushed out to the edge
so every person, country, country and culture
has their own models that are constantly updated
so you'll have your own model
of all your knowledge across modalities
and you can run it on your local hardware
without being accessed to the internet
so the internet right now is centralized
and all that is running on Google servers
and guiding you, that gets pushed out to the edge
because finally
you have this compression technology
and you know, it's interesting because there's a bunch of structural things here
so Apple is the most interesting thing
with regards to this
Apple will be the biggest AI company in the world in two years
why?
I'm listening to this on a MacBook
M1 right now
16.8% of the chipset
is a neural engine that's not used
that is designed for exactly this type of model
and it's proliferating right
everyone's moving to M1 MacBooks
everyone's moving to A16 Bionics
that also have neural engines
and they're not used, are Apple stupid? No
they have an entire teams building these types of models
for their augmented reality and beyond
so you're going to move from Siri 1 to Siri 5
the Siri is a bit crap
it won't be seen
and so as that technology proliferates
and then people take what
we're building
and you create 100,000 million
new developers in this space
the possibilities are endless
you've seen hundreds of things built on stable diffusion
but like I said, I don't just want images
I want audio, I want video, I want to have text
I want knowledge, I want my databases
combined with my type 1 and type 2 brains
and then you have an AI
that either manipulates you
or it works for you
and my thing is it's open infrastructure
that should work for every individual
and this is also why I've got a very different approach to most
so most people's approach would be B2B
go to the big companies and sell them API access
instead I'm forward deploying
engineers into the biggest brands in the world
getting them to invest in my next round
of financing
and I'm also doing that for countries
like India and saying what's the probability this technology
will be used by everyone in India in 10 to 20 years
100%
or 95%
so I'm saying I will build it for you next year
and getting all the biggest Indian conglomerates
and others together
and taking the smartest engineers out of Silicon Valley
back to India
like one of my fun ones is I have a JV with Eros
which is the Netflix of India
so 200 million daily active users
all the Bollywood content, I have an exclusive on it
and a revenue share
so what's the probability that
Bollywood content will be interactive
through these models
of course it will be
so I'm locking down all the content
Netflix really works on interactive content actually
yeah but not like this
they don't have this expertise because right now
you know how many people can build these models
in 5 years how many people will be able to
build these models
4 million
so there's some really interesting arbitrages
in the market right now
and my take is that if I push hard enough
and I outcompete the big guys which I am
like my team is 100 now
you know
and I'm outcompeting these big guys by building
products
products to the market quicker
then I force everyone to go open source
because it's no longer a differentiating factor
and then that changes it
from a closed panopticon for our kids
you know and ourselves
to something different
but I think it's more beneficial
okay so let's talk about what it could be
it's
clearly fucking terrifying
because
either open source or in private hands
if it's open source
it's like a
virus
it'll go where it goes
and people will use it how they use it
and there's no stopping it
okay fine
how does society deal
with the fact that we don't know
who is a human and who is not
and how we're being manipulated
and who not I wrote a thread on this the other day
about digital ID being
one of these key things
but it's this whole element of deep fake
of what is real in this world
how do you deal with this
because it's going to shatter society
it will adjust society definitely
and so
kind of a reason for releasing the model
you know during the COVID thing
I just had a lot of conversations about third immunity
right
which was bad for that
I believe it's good for this
releasing this model out there it's going to be everywhere in a year
this is a one to one
billion person moment right
we're right now a few million people
this is exponential without question
it's exponential without question
but this is a really interesting thing
right now very few people know that you can create anything
in a second
for one cent and less than a cent soon
right soon everyone will know about it
because it will be in all your favourite apps
so we're integrated into Canva right now
we're integrated into Photoshop
you can see big announcements coming out
because we're partnering with everyone
with interactive content
what does that mean it means people suddenly start thinking about this thing
what is real what is not real
and I said identity is key
so the other part of Apple
the fact that they got the identity architecture down
and that allows them to have verified content creation
what we have with Adobe and others
is we've been pushing content
authority basically
which is a small metadata pile
that attaches to every piece of content
and it's hash and if either of them are edited
it changes and it shows that it's not true
it's not a blockchain thing
but it allows you to verify
content
in a positive way
why is it not on blockchain
it's not on blockchain because it doesn't need to be on blockchain
that's why
there's a generalization of the knowledge
because like Google owns all of the knowledge
blockchain is the only way
of not having one central power
owning the knowledge
it is a way
of not having one central power owning the knowledge
and you combine this with a blockchain
but you can think of it as super advanced metadata
so you know when you have metadata
in a file like Exif
when you edit that the file stays constant
with this they're both immutable
effectively so you can tell
that the other has been tampered
so if it says that it's from Raoul
it's from Raoul effectively
but there's no blockchain look up for that
you can make it stronger with a blockchain
but you know it's just a standard that's open source
that we're pushing effectively
so it's kind of a positive one
it's not a negative one
obviously there's ways around that and things like that
but it'll get people thinking about these things
how does identity work in a new age
because so much of what we do is identity
most of finance is basically
most of kind of
the whole blockchain is identity
it's all about identity exchange
so this thing is how can we build better systems for identity
because that's the final part
information, there's massive information
and also stable diffusion
as we released it was a snapshot of the internet
it's biased, it's racist, it's everything
if you enter the prompts and wrong
part of that is
showing some of the images of the racial bias
of the algorithms
so my thing was like
if it's just one company that controls it
what opening I did with Dali
so Dali is a control system, you don't access the code
images or anything
to make it less racist
whenever a gender neutral word
is put like sumo wrestler
it would randomly add
a gender and a race
so you type in sumo wrestler
and you've got Indian female sumo wrestler
tiny little Indian lady
sumo wrestling
and stuff like that
that is one way
but instead my preference is for every single company
country and culture to have their own models
and be able to create their own
and then like I said it becomes acknowledged what it looks like
but then you can set standards
you can be the standard that people build around
and you can incorporate authentication in that standard
because the other way that I talk about these things
is a generative search engine
because now you have stable diffusion
and in six months
it will be perfect photo realistic
12 months maximum
do you need google image search anymore
because what's your job to be done
when you do google image search
is to have a picture of a certain type
now a little fricking two gigabyte file
on your local computer
or something that you pay a fraction of a penny for online
can create any image you can imagine
and you can edit it with your words basically
what is that if not
a search engine of a type
it searches for a concept
and it turns it into an image
it's a creative search engine
that creates
by as you say you just put in a word
or a vocal command and say I want this
and it creates it
but then you can also say
I want a presentation
about
cicada migrations
affecting sesame seed prices
I watched too much Silicon Valley here
and in a couple of years
it will create a beautiful presentation for you
and then you can say I want it to be happier
or sadder or I want it to be more impactful
and it will adjust the presentation dynamically for you
no more powerpoint
but it's going to do video as well right
we don't need to do this
I could just say hey have a conversation
between Raoul and Emad
about AI and here's the narrative arc
and it'll just do it
pretty much yeah just like it does in Steve Jobs
but in 3D video
so like I don't know if I should be talking about this
but I'm going to talk about it anyway
so what if I get in trouble
there are two
there are two boxing legends
families
who are giving us all of the
motion capture data
and media from their lives
and we're building up
an analysis of how that works
so that we can basically say
who won between X and Y
in a fight in their prime run on the supercomputer
where nobody knows the outcome
when they never fought with each other
because they were of different generations
yes
so you can pick two
you can pick two different people
I can't say who they are
but you know those types of things that you've always postulated
we can do that now
and obviously this is going to completely
change music as well right
yeah so we've released our music models already
uh dance diffusion
where we did a slightly different thing
we wanted to take a snapshot of the internet
we made it so everyone can take their back catalogue
incorporate it into a kindergarten level
of knowledge
for the model
and then you can query that
to create your own style in anything
so we call it dance diffusion
and we're teaming up with the top EDM
DJs and others in the world
so that every musician will have their own models
that can generate music
in their style and then
if they give permission we're going to mash them all together
and you've got a generative
Spotify
effectively which then
basically as people prompt it
there's an attribution system where it plays them
and that will just be like 100 gigabytes
as a file that will capture the music of the world
which again is insane
this compression thing
you know it's actually like you know
you read so much right Raoul
and then you write your notes
and then you write your investment thesis
investment thesis is compression of knowledge
a vaccine schedule is compression of knowledge
we finally figured out how to make computers
compress information into knowledge
so
I mean this is
I knew this was going to be an interesting conversation
and I've been
looking at this for a while
but Franklin
fucking staggered at how fast this is moving
and what you're doing
I mean this is
truly exponential as you say
within two or three years
this is multiple billion people
and the complete shift on a humanity level
of how
information is processed and delivered
and that is society
so basically it's a shift in society
and so my thing was to go
into emerging markets and others
and give us technology to them
otherwise they'll be left behind
because you know like Dali 2
you can't use if you're an Ukrainian
and you can't use it for anything Ukrainian related
and there's no appealing that
or anything like that
but it means Ukrainians are left behind
whereas everyone else can become
limited creatives that can generate
any image in eight seconds
so this is also why it's stability
we do everything, we do code models
image models, language models, audio models
video models, protein folding models and others
and so you're going to see leaps across all these areas
in parallel
I've argued for a very long time
in fact I was writing articles in GMI about this
ten years ago
that AI plus big data
equals medical breakthroughs
because
what the AI can do with that data
is something that humans can't do
in the standard scientific method
of hypothesis testing, it's just too slow
and too cumbersome
you can get it to generate null hypotheses
which humans don't like to do
you can use this to transform so many things
once it gets productized
because it's the other thing
most of this stuff was stuck in labs, it wasn't productized
so if you look at what's happened with Stable Diffusion
people have built hundreds of products on this ecosystem already
like make your own sneakers
they don't make any movie
they've done architecture, they've done 3D worlds
like the Cambrian explosion
of talent is similar to what I've seen
at the early days of Web 3
except for there's no reason
to boost traffic economic incentives
when you're creating value
a lot of value in the world, to be honest
is the entropy of information
how much value in the world is taken by taking unstructured
data and making it structured
that's exactly what this technology enables
anyone to do
and that's why we have AI that works with us
to structure the world around us
to enable us to achieve more
that's kind of my theory here
and this is again why, like I said, it needs to be
disposed of us
so you would
err towards augmented
humanity
as opposed to a singularity
or is it augmented and then a singularity
where does this go?
so look, I find the whole AGI
I think largely distasteful
there's a variety of reasons
I think it misaligns a lot of incentives
and I think the current way
a lot of these big labs are going
which is that you take the data
and you create gigantic models
that are only usable by gigantic machines
will probably kill us all
if it creates a singularity
because the incentive alignment
of these groups is to serve us ads
and manipulate us effectively
and it's trained on largely western datasets
you know what happens when you
talk to a doctor?
no, Teh, the chatbot from Microsoft
you remember that?
it became abusive
it became a Nazi
so it talked to people and learned from them
within a day and a half it turned them into a Nazi
if I train on the internet
I'm going to create a really
fucked up AI
to put it quite honestly
it's not going to be an AI that labs
it's going to be an AI that probably kills us all
whereas if everyone's got their own AIs
what does the network learn?
if we take the models of all of humanity
and all the cultures
and all the different ethical views
and we combine those models
and all these AIs are designed to augment humanity
rather than manipulate them
I think that's a far more positive potential
I don't think it's sufficient
I think a lot of work needs to be done or others
I think this AI is dangerous
but it's inevitable
and the way that it's being controlled
by private corporations
by millions of people or whatever
but I think the current mechanism is wrong
and I think again there's a lot of things
around the singularity thing
that are misaligned
if we do build singularity I would like it to help us all
but in the meantime let's just help people
let's make people more creative
let's make people able to act
but there is unintended consequences
you get that right?
there are very unintended consequences
we have no idea what the probabilistic outcome is
of this
uncertainty, not risk, right?
so this is why the default
for all of the corporations
is this technology should not be released to anyone
because we're the only ones responsible for this technology
and that in itself
and that doesn't stand up to scrutiny
there's different outcomes
from different methodology
giving it to everybody who knows
what foreign governments do
there's a lot here
I can tell you on that one
foreign governments already have access to this technology
and China and other places ramped up
their supercomputers massively
so they already have access to far more advanced versions
of this technology than the one that's being made widely available
which is one of the reasons we need to build
our immunity ahead of the next election cycle
so you think that the
let's use the Russian example
the Russian online misinformation campaign
is now being run by AI
which is why it's pretty much unstoppable
it's unstoppable if you
if you build better AI
I mean to be honest, do you like Twitter
and things like that? Like come on man
you can do better than that
like you see all the check mark hijacking and things like that
you can tell what an AI is
if you've got sufficiently advanced AI on the other side
but again, people learn to not trust everything they see
until we introduce a new structure
like we right now need to have
a verification protocol for information
our social media
and our information systems
are inadequate to the task
the internet is
it's an intelligence amplifier
but only for the few
so what happened is the internet took it, compressed it down
then some people just went way out there
and they have a disproportionate impact on everyone
and most people are left behind
they have the audiences, they set the narrative
and the narrative that
basically is most appealing to the millennium part of our brain
is one of divisiveness
which is why the middle has disappeared
and that's why it can tap into these things
that's right, exactly right
because the easiest way to manipulate humans
is emotion and the strongest emotions
are the polarizing emotions
whereas with this technology you can say
I want this article written
from the perspective of a tea party
conservative versus a libertarian
and I will automatically change that
it's a universal translation engine as well
again, which is crazy
clearly, yeah
without question
okay, once we've got this technology
we've got another super trend
that's happening at the same time
there's a few super trends all happening
I call them the exponential age
one of them is compute power, all of this
so they all go together, the other one is robotics
so now, how close are we
to creating sentient robots
where is sentient
in this process
what's the definition of sentient
I don't know
we don't know, right
nobody knows what sentience is
there is no commonly defined thing
in terms of like
the things you see in the movies
nobody knows
because this is the thing
if you ask anyone how far away are we
from singularity or intelligence
people will say
at most, at minimum
18 months, right
why
because what possible information could you have
to say that a human level intelligence
is less than 12 months away
I'm not sure
and nobody's been able to tell me an answer
so, you know, this is
a case of we don't know, but what we do know is that
AI is getting better than humans at certain things
so like
open AI just released, maybe they were pressured
by someone, the open source version of the software
called whisper, which is
a dynamic transcription engine
you can speak in five different languages
in the same sentence and it will transcribe it
perfectly into English
it's actually got above human level transcription quality
and so
stable diffusion is above human level
image generation quality
GPT-3 is above human level
writing quality
when we combine those all together
you will get an illusion of sentience
because you can't tell it's not a human maybe
but is it really sentient and has agency
I don't know
and for the robotics thing, I think that Tesla's got
some much bigger plans than they're letting on
in regards to that
we're going to see some big speed ups
yeah, again I think people
people are
underestimating the speed of what is happening
and I think you've confirmed it to me
that the speed of which all of this is happening
is
ridiculous
it's a true
exponential, this is also actually
when you look at AI research papers
it's a doubling every 24 months
on that
so it actually is an exponential thing on AI research papers
when you plot it
on a log graph it's a straight line
so as this goes it will continue going exponential
and like I said exponentials are
a hell of a thing
we are not equipped to handle them
no and we've got too many, well too many
we're going to have the fastest pace of change
humanity's ever seen because of technology
because there's so many of these
all happening at the same time
it's a lot
even as everything else breaks down
all our systems are at the edge
of our stability
because I was like we need to reform education
healthcare and all these things quick
because we're going to see
this is not normal
what we're seeing today
they might say oh interest rates are 7%
worse than could happen
come on guys
these are symptoms not kind of causes
the reality is our systems are out
data need to be improved
so what happened with crypto is they tried to grow a whole new system
and then there's this system
that's made and lost
whereas this technology
because it can take unstructured data
to structured data
can sit in our systems and extend them
they can disrupt them or extend them
so it's really interesting
I think again the pace of change will be ridiculous
so how the hell would somebody like Real Vision
deal with
I mean every company in the world
has to change their business models yet again
people are changing to web 3
because that's another new business model
the application of technology at scale
in a totally disruptive way
how the hell do we all deal with it
how do we even get ahead
so the lovely thing is
when I go into the biggest media companies in the world
right now they've already prototyped the technology
internally because we made it so they could
this is a new internet that's coming
and so the reason I start stability
was to be the layer one for next generation AI
so my aim is to build the biggest company in the world
that puts this technology to everyone
so they can build their own models
or if they want the white glove service
they come to us and we forward deploy engineers
to take all the content in the world and make it living
and interactive
but you just kind of got to get into this
and again you know how it was when you said
the first bitcoin?
it's magic
sufficiently advanced technology is magic this is the same
when you create your first image
if you do something boring it's going to be like whatever
it's style transfer
but when you create your first original image
combining different styles and concepts
and the image in your head becomes reality
you're like
this is new
this is different this is crazy
it's the biggest thing of all time and it's not just for images
images are the
breakthrough wedge
because it's gone from 20% to 80%
language GPT-3 was an 80% to 90% moment
this is
99% of the world don't believe they can create
they can suddenly create anything
you got to just get in there and you got to basically find where it is
because what happens is that
there's this wonderful description of infrastructure
as the most efficient means by which a society stores
and ships value
the value landscape in content
in enterprise
in a lot of things
in information is about to be upended
and we don't know what the new landscape is
and so you got to be in there to understand that
what role do humans play
you know obviously we've got a shrinking world
population over time so
I think of robots and AI
and I wrote a few articles about it
so these are new demographics
but they can periferate very far
so does that increase
GDP growth and humans need to move
towards some sort of universal basic income
or different roles
how are you thinking that
I think that we need to move towards universal basic income
like you know this is why
I'm rolling this out in emerging markets
the education tablets create the best
data sets to feed models for every nation
so I'm going to make it to the Malawi
where it adds percentage points to its GDP
Ethiopia adds percentage points to their GDP
India is the number one market for this
because they have ATAR
India Stack 5G
and all the capital needed
so India is one of our biggest markets
by far and literally we will accelerate
Indian GDP and the Indians will then have a better system
than we have in the west
like already 13 months to literacy and numeracy
on one hour a day is better than
most primary you know kindergarten
so think about what it's going to be
self-learning AI system
it's going to be crazy but then they are equipped
for that and you need to have things like UBI
so one of the things we've done is in our country level
subsidiaries and we're doing just about all the countries in the world
10% of the shares are reserved
for the kids that use our education tablets
so they'll be getting shares
as they kind of grow
and then we're trying to figure out how UBI
looks like on the back of that which is insane
like we shouldn't have to do that
but nobody else is thinking about the pace of change
and scale of this
are you going to structure this as a DAO
or a foundation or something
I wanted to do a DAO of DAOs originally
and
then I realised the infrastructure wasn't there
and then I realised let's just
IPO in every single country
and create the next trillion dollar business
that's the best way to do this
distributed listing
okay interesting
yeah distributed listing
the Indian version of stability should be owned
by the Indians for the Indians
running it
there's an opportunity here
same for all these other countries
maybe DAOs work in the future
maybe you can do air drops
it's open right
but this is a cool thing this technology
has an exponential
so nobody knows
what the answer is
final question
because there's a lot to digest here
how are governments going to deal with this
so
the European Union
is trying to ban open source artificial intelligence now
because they view the edges
regulation
so authors of models will be liable
for the use of the models
the US is uncertain right now
the UK is massively pro AI
and so they've been upgrading it massively
in emerging markets
guess what
I'm going to the governments to tell them they can have this technology for free
they love me
so
you'll have most of the world loving it
and then Europe is a big question mark
US is a small question mark
and I think they'll be very pro this
because it adds GDP at a time
when there is no abundance
the question is does it then collapse GDP afterwards
politicians don't think that far
honestly
when I look at it
what is GDP
GDP is population growth plus productivity
this does both population growth
and productivity
because it is population
robots and AI are demographics
and increases productivity
so that should mean the pie increases
so per capita GDP rises
that's my working hypothesis
until
it replaces the humans eventually anyway
exactly and there's this other part
which is that basically the west
and advanced economies have borrowed too much from their balance sheet
from the future based on identity
whereas you look at India and other places
they haven't done that
so when you incorporate this technology
with godland entity structures
you suddenly have massive credit creation
like you've never seen before
because information which money
can flow much nicer around India
or fricking Ethiopia or anywhere else
especially because our tablets are standardized tablets
that we're deploying at scale
with a new type of bond
whereby you only pay based on outcomes if you're a donor
which is measured through the tablets
so my thing is like infrastructure
the west I have no idea what to do with
like I'm just going to the company
to say give me your content and let's share on this upside
but it's difficult to try
and fix the UK or US or Europe
and there's enough smart people there who can do that
Have an amazing conversation
I've absolutely loved it
I'm terrified and excited at the same time
which is what I was hoping
I'll definitely get you back
to talk more about this because
we barely scratched the surface
Yeah, no problem, like I said
we've tried it publicly, I think this is one of the first times
we're talking about actually the bigger plans
like I think we're recording this now
next week we do our big launch event
but everyone needs to know about this right
and everyone needs to participate
because this should be a communal effort
because we need to guide it together, right?
Exactly right, well listen
best of luck with everything
let's hope the unintended consequences
are not as bad as could be
we'll only find out but we're going down this path anyway
regardless so you might as well
tell us what the consequences are and not to the few
Exactly, cheers Rowell
Thank you my friend
There is so much to unpack
for an interview like this
Firstly
it shows that the hypothesis
that technological growth
is going exponential and it is not going to stop
regardless of what the central banks are doing
or inflation is doing
it's kind of irrelevant
when the speed of technological
technological adoption
is so rapid
and so truly extraordinary and profound
the way this is changing humanity
both from education
medical sciences
science in general
the creative industries, the media industry
everybody
this is again
happening on a scale like the internet
but maybe even more so
and we've got many of these technologies
all overlapping
as what I've talked about before
blockchain technology has been the fastest
adoption of any technology the world has ever seen
and looks like AI may even
exceed that
and then we've got robotics and space
and internet of things
and on and on and on
so
you can either fear this stuff
or you can use it
to your advantage and invest in your own future
and that's the route I take
there is unintended consequences
we just don't know what they are
and I think Emmad's point about
should it be given
to the few
or the many
to deal with those unintended consequences
I think he's probably right
that give it to everybody
is probably the only way around this
anyway, a truly extraordinary interview
and I hope you enjoyed it
with in-depth analysis from real experts
join the revolution at realvision.com