Abram was 75 years old when he left Haran.
Abram took his wife Sarai, his nephew Lot, all of their possessions and those who became
members of their household in Haran, and they set out for the land of Canaan.
When they arrived in Canaan, Abram traveled through the land as far as the sacred place
at Shechem, the Oak of Mora.
The Canaanites lived in the land at that time.
The Lord appeared to Abram and said, I give this land to your descendants.
So Abram built an altar there to the Lord who appeared to him.
The religious beliefs of Israel are rooted in the shared culture of Canaan,
although it had unique attributes that differed from the Canaanites.
It still found expression in shared practices and language.
Some traditional practices could not be merged with Yahwism,
but others like the sacred poetry, the music, and the architecture of the Canaanites
were adopted and became integral to the Israelite religion.
The Old Testament's embrace or rejection of these elements
means that the Canaanite religious influences still affect us today through biblical narratives.
The things that the Bible are condemning in the Old Testament are, in fact,
the culture that the Israelites at the time of writing the Bible
are trying to distance themselves from in their own past.
Things like human sacrifice, idolatry, and the worship of more than one God.
These are the things that they themselves practice just like everyone else in the world.
And these are the things that they will polemicize in the text to divorce themselves from their past.
Before the findings at Ugarit Rosh Shamra in 1928,
our knowledge of Canaanite religion was minimal and largely from indirect sources.
The Old Testament didn't mention Canaanite deities and rituals,
but these were often in a negative light making interpretations challenging.
Mentions of Canaanite gods and rituals were also found in Egyptian, Mesopotamian, and Phoenician writings,
including the Karatepe inscriptions from 1946.
However, these weren't enough to form a complete understanding.
Greek historians provided accounts of Canaanite beliefs,
but it was hard to distinguish authentic traditions from later additions,
excavations at places like Biblos and Megiddo.
Give us glimpses, but only a fragmentary picture.
Thanks to the discoveries at Rosh Shamra, ancient Ugarit in North Syria,
the Canaanites tell us their own story.
Hundreds of clay tablets found here, written in a dialect close to the biblical Hebrew,
and offers rich insights.
These tablets feature extensive mythological poems, records related to the temple services,
lists of deities and sacrifices, and details about temple workers and rituals.
Additionally, artifacts linked to gods like Baal and Dagon,
including temple remains and stelae, have been discovered.
It's crucial to understand, though, that while there was a core Canaanite religious belief,
local variations existed.
I mean, they didn't have the internet and no email and the mail system wasn't very great.
So every city you went to had their own ideas.
Not every Canaanite city would have worshiped all the same gods that we know from these texts.
There were variations at play.
The Canaanite religion was more of a public affair than a personal one.
Its rituals, mostly centered on ensuring fertility, were community events.
Though there were individual acts of devotion as seen in the Phoenician inscriptions,
the religion was mainly a communal way to connect with nature's forces.
This involved practices believed to ensure continued creation and rejuvenation.
The prominence of some deities in mythological writings
doesn't always reflect their actual popularity among Canaanite devotees.
Conversely, some gods like Dagon had a minimal role in myths,
merely acknowledged as Baal's father,
but seemed quite revered as evidenced by a dedicated temple and two stele in Ugarit.
El, the Hebrew word for God, is the supreme God and Creator
and shows up as Allah in Arabic.
Variations in the name El are found in many Semitic languages,
Ugaritic, Phoenician, Hebrew, Aramaic, Akkadian.
In Northwestern Semitic cultures, El was a term for any deity
and also specifically for the primary god.
He often stood at the top of many divine hierarchies
and played roles like the god of creation
or the father of gods in certain Canaanite and Ugaritic sources.
Yet, using the name El can be confusing
because sometimes it refers to the main god and at other times to different gods.
For instance, in Ugaritic texts the phrase El-Melik means El the king,
while El Haddad refers to the God Haddad.
In Ugaritic, the plural for gods aligns with the Hebrew term
that sometimes means the singular god Elohim, for example.
Some believe that various authors change stories from polytheistic context
into monotheistic ones.
I myself subscribe to this idea and I will show this in this video.
And this causes many inconsistencies in the text,
but once you see it, everything starts to make sense.
Names with the stem El appear in many Semitic regions
among the Amorites and Sabaic people in the southern Levant.
Several ancient texts in inscriptions mention El
or connect him with other deities from different cultures,
indicating his widespread recognition and influence.
For instance, the Egyptian god Patah shared an epithet with El
and an ancient script described El as the god of eternity.
The Egyptian deity Patah was labeled Lord of Gath in a prism from Tel Lakish.
And on the other side, it bears the name of Amenhotep II, Pharaoh from 1435 to 1420 BCE.
This title also appears in Serabit text 353.
Ta is frequently referred to as Lord or the Eternal One.
This association between El and Patah that brought about the consistent use of olam,
meaning eternal, for El.
Although in Ugaritic records, Ta seems to be more closely related
to the artisan deity Kothar Wachasus, an additional link is observed
with the Mandian angel Patah El, blending the names Patah and El together.
Herodotus, the famous Greek historian who wrote in the 5th century BCE,
who never mentions anything about Israel, Jerusalem or Yahweh or anything like King David or Moses,
does have some interesting things to say about the god Patah,
who he calls by his Greek equivalent Hephaestus.
After the reign of the priest of Hephaestus Patah, the Egyptians were made free,
but they could never live without a king, so they divided Egypt into 12 districts and set up 12 kings.
These kings intermarried and agreed to be close friends,
no one deposing another or seeking to possess more than another.
The reason for this agreement, which they scrupulously kept, was this.
No sooner were they established in their districts than an oracle was given them,
that whichever of them poured a libation from a bronze vessel in the temple of Hephaestus Patah,
whereas in all the temples they used to assemble, would be king of all Egypt.
Now what I found interesting about this text is the division between the 12 tribes, if you will,
of the ruling class of Egypt at this time, and it makes you wonder,
could this be some of the source material used for the curation of the 12 tribes in the story in Genesis?
The 12 districts itself wouldn't be too convincing,
but when you take a look at El or Yahweh, being a god of metallurgy and craftsmanship,
and the uncreated one, like Patah, there's might be some connection here.
Patah is an Egyptian deity responsible for creating the world, manifesting it through
potent force of spoken words. A hymn from Egypt's 22nd dynasty praises Patah for shaping the world
with the vision of his hearts. Meanwhile, the Shabakha stone, originating from the 25th dynasty,
mentions Patah bestowed life upon all deities and their spirits using his heart in his voice,
the curation by the voice, something we see in the god of the Old Testament. His worship then moved
beyond the borders of Egypt, all the way into Syria, and was exported throughout the eastern
Mediterranean. Through dissemination by the Phoenicians, we find figures of Patah and Carthage,
his epithets, Patah, the begetter of the first beginning, Patah, Lord of Truth,
Patah, Lord of Eternity, one who listens to prayers, master of ceremonies, master of justice,
the god who made himself to be God, the double being, the beautiful face.
Now, some of you watching this right now may be familiar with the Heliopolis in Aeneid,
and the creation myths that say that Amun, or Atum, is the self-created craftsman
who created the other gods. And though this is certainly true, the priesthood in Memphis and
Crocodopolis and the elephantines have competing mythologies that make Patah the self-created
demiurge who creates the other gods and humans. An elephantine, Cunum, who like Patah, is also
depicted as a craftsman or demiurge with the potter's wheel behind him, just as Patah has
images of himself with the potter's wheel behind him, as he creates gods and humans alike.
Porphyry once said, At the city of Elephantine, there is an image worshiped, which in other
respects is fashioned in the likeness of a man and sitting. It is of a blue color and has a man's
head and a diadem bearing the horns of a goat. He sits with a vessel of clay beside him, on which
he is molding the figure of a man, and from having the face of a ram and the horns of a goat,
he indicates the conjunction of sun and moon, ra and ya, in the sign of the ram, Amun, while the
color of blue indicates that the moon in that conjunction brings rain, Tefnut. He goes on to say,
in the mysteries of Eleusis, the Hierophant is dressed up to represent the demiurge and the
torchbearer, the sun, the priest at the altar, the moon, and the sacred herald, Hermes. Moreover,
a man is admitted by the Egyptians among their objects of worship, for there is a village in
Egypt called Anibis, in which a man is worshiped and sacrifice offered to him, and the victims
burned upon his altars, and after a little while, he would eat the things that had been prepared for
him as for a man. They did not, however, believe the animals to be gods, but regarded them as
likenesses and symbols of gods, and this is shown by the fact that in many places,
oxen dedicated to the gods are sacrificed at their monthly festivals and in their religious
services, for they consecrated oxen to the sun and moon.
What I find the most striking about this passage is his comparison to the Eleusinian priests,
Abakus and Demeter, Na'kunum, who Pharaoh Khufu was named after, the famed builder of the Great
Pyramid, Giza. Almost seems like a perfect synchronization between the competing creator gods
Amun Ra and Patah. Patah is one of the three major gods of the Memphis Triad,
along with Sekhmet, and he's also the father of Nefertim, and Kunum has an almost identical role
within the Elephantine Triad. The temple of Elephantine was dedicated to Kunum, his consort
Saitis and their daughter Anuket. Elephantine is the city where dozens of Jewish Aramaic texts were
found, that not only physically predate every fragment or manuscript of Hebrew Bible in existence,
I repeat, the Elephantine city where we found older Jewish Aramaic fragments than any
existing fragment or manuscript of the Hebrew Bible in existence. But also, it shows that the
Jews at Elephantine in the 4th and 5th century BCE were still polytheistic during this time.
Following the 587 BCE destruction of Jerusalem, some Judean refugees traveled south in what may be
called an Exodus in reverse, settled at Elephantine. They maintained their own temple, the House of Yahweh,
or Yahoo in this case, in which sacrifices were offered, evincing polytheistic beliefs
functioning alongside that of Kunum. Gods like Osiris and Isis are all over the place in these texts.
The temple was destroyed in 410 BCE at the instigation of the priests of Kunum.
So, what happened? Was Yahweh in direct competition with Kunum over who is the true
divine craftsman? Possibly. One of the most common attributes among these metal-ergy
craftsmen gods like Hephaestus of the Greeks, Ta of the Egyptians, and Vulcan of the Romans,
is their connection to volcanoes and mountains due to the richness of metal ores found at these
places. It is very possible that Yahweh is no exception, although he is from an entirely different location.
In Exodus, the presence of fire and smoke is paired with the mountains quaking.
These tremblings, akin to small earthquakes, are typical of volcanic eruptions,
leading to the expulsion of warm gases from the cracks. This expulsion is accompanied by a
significant sound, referred to in the Sinai Theophany as powerful shofar sound.
Yahweh's revelation is always at a mountain, whether called Sinai or Horib, the event pictured
like a volcanic eruption. As these texts show, volcanism seems to be an essential attribute,
typically associated with Yahweh, linking him to the Kressman metal-ergy gods as I mentioned before.
The account of the Sinai revelation, with its volcanic imagery, is meant to show that Yahweh
himself is not just his divine emissary, but a demiurgic craftsman. Some believe Mount Sinai
might be one of these Arabian volcanoes, which the Israelites approached in the text when departing
Egypt. Jacob Dunn even theorized that Yahweh was once an Arabian volcanic deity. This ties
into the theory that Yahweh's worship in Israel has Midianite roots. This theory draws from biblical
references that depicts Moses' introduction to Yahweh in Midian. Near the mountain of God,
close to Jethro's residence, in Exodus 3, 1-6, here Moses is instructed by God to bring the
Israelites after their Egyptian Exodus, Exodus 312. Intriguingly, Moses' father-in-law is portrayed
as a Midianite priest, suggesting Moses might have adopted local religious beliefs from him.
In other passages, Moses' father-in-law is identified as a Kenite. Some Kenites settled
in Israelite lands and maintained a close alliance with them. The biblical figure Cain,
considered the Kenites founding ancestor, is significant in early biblical narratives,
highlighting this group's ancient proximity to Yahweh. Cain's role as the initial person
offered to Yahweh in Genesis 4-3 reinforces this notion. While Yahweh's association with the Midianites
might explain Israelites using volcanic imagery to depict the divine presence, linking Yahweh
to the Kenites prompts a reevaluation, especially considering the Kenites'
metal-urgical pursuits.
The Kenites seem to have been skilled metalworkers. Genesis 4 discusses Cain's descendant,
Tubel Cain, as a craftsman skilled in molding copper and iron. Semitic cognates of Cain hint
that metal-urgical activities were integral to its meaning. Hence, Cain might originally have been
represented the pioneering figure in metalurgy with the Kenites, both metalworkers and smelters,
as his successors. Their association with the volcanic deity, like Yahweh, becomes clear in
this context. Historically, deities linked to metalurgy were also connected with volcanoes.
For instance, Hephaestus was linked to Mount Etna in ancient Greece, and the term volcano
originates from the Roman god of metalurgy, Vulcan. The connection between volcanoes and
metal smelting is straightforward. Both release similar owners and plumes of smoke.
In past times, smelting was the sole human activity involved in melting stones,
lava pouring from volcano, mirror slag from a furnace, which once solidified resembles volcanic
rock. This similarity is evident in Exodus' description of the Sinai Revelation, comparing
the ascending smoke to that of a furnace, Exodus 1918. The persistent use of volcanic imagery
when describing Yahweh implies a deep-rooted metal-urgical aspect to his earlier identity.
Notably, the Song of Deborah associates Yahweh near Ereba's copper mines. This volcanic aspect
of divine revelation is also highlighted in Deuteronomy's account of the Horeb Revelation.
It notes that Yahweh communicated from amidst fire and smoke,
essentially from the volcano's core, while it erupted.
Oh Yahweh, when you came forth from Sire, advanced from the country of Edom, the earth trembled,
the heavens dripped, yea, the clouds dripped water, the mountains quaked or flowed before
Yahweh, the one of Sinai before Yahweh, God of Israel.
The writings in Zechariah support this idea. The book starts by sternly rebuking the earlier
prophets of Israel, accusing them of abandoning the paths of Yahweh and ignoring his call.
Zechariah 1, 4-6, this assertion is further elaborated when the text predicts the arrival
of four rescuers, dispatched by Yahweh, referenced as Smiths, and Zechariah 2, 3-4, Smiths,
and subsequent revelation, Zechariah 6, 1-5. Zechariah witnesses four soaring chariots,
representing the four winds, originating from the bronze mountains.
This terminology alludes to the copper mining regions, like Ereba and Sinai,
hinting at Yahweh's earlier residence. Thus, even in Zechariah's time, there were those who
recalled Yahweh's association with metalurgy.
Recognizing Yahweh's historical role as the deity overseeing metalurgy in the Southern Levant,
sheds light on various aspects of his biblical character. In fact, Yahweh is nowhere to be found
in any of the Ugaritic or Northern Canaanite texts or inscriptions, which are dominated by El
and Bell. As well as different craftsmen God, Kothar Wachasus, who I mentioned earlier,
who is identified with Ptah in texts that survive from Memphis, as well as Anki of the Babylonians.
So, Yahweh is most likely local to the Southern Levant, near the Sinai Desert and Midian.
In Isaiah 31-9, an oracle of Yahweh, whose fire is in Zion, in his furnace in Jerusalem,
imagery of metalurgy undeniable here surrounding Yahweh. This could also help explain the biblical
author's attempts to polemicize Bell as an evil opposition to Yahweh, considering how popular
Bell was to northern Israel, and being the prince and son of El. He only has to be opposed by Yahweh.
While many view this portrayal as merely a symbolic expression without deeper theological
meaning, considering the other metallic attributes associated with Yahweh, it probably reveals
a metallurgical facet to Yahweh's worship in Jerusalem. In this perspective, the numerous
metal artifacts in the Jerusalem Temple aren't just symbols of grandeur. Their context largely
details an exodus via the depiction of the Tabernacle. It specifies about the metals used,
hint at deeper theological importance they held. They symbolize the heavenly furnace
within the Israelite sanctuary, turning it into the earthly abode of the Israelite deity. Moreover,
the copperclad altar in the Temple's grounds lends a metallurgical undertone to the sacrifices.
The glow from this copper surface, when heated to nearly 1000 Celsius, for the burning sacrifices,
is reminiscent of the luminance of liquefied copper or gold.
The beginning of the Prophet Ezekiel's vision recounts his entrance into the heavenly realm
as follows. And I looked and behold, a stormy wind came out of the north, a great cloud
with a fire flashing up and brightness around it, and in its midst, something like Hasmal,
out of the midst of the fire. The vision illustrates Hasmal, an entity radiating
powerful luminance amidst celestial flames. This unique term is exclusively found in Ezekiel's
revelation within the Bible. However, comparable words appear in both Egyptian and Akkadian,
Hashmen and Hashmalu, referring to an amber or yellowish-orange metal or metallic mixture.
The Septuagint translates it as helectron, signifying either amber or electron,
a natural blend of gold and silver. While many translations peg Hashmel as amber,
this interpretation doesn't quite fit, given the reference to the glowing embers within the flame.
In Ezekiel 1.13, it's more likely that Hashmel alludes to something shining brilliantly due to
high heat, considering that burning amber emits smoke but not light. It stands to reason that
Ezekiel 1. Hashmal is more likely a representation of liquefied metal.
When they moved, I could hear the sound of their wings like the sound of mighty waters,
like the sound of Shaddai, a tumult like the din of an army. In Ezekiel's depiction of these beings
and their movement, it seems he's detailing the powerful gusts that fuel the celestial furnace,
enhancing the creation of shining embers. Essentially, this vision portrays Yahweh's
divine realm as a massive kiln encircling by winged entities that drive the air current
akin to bellows. Taking into account both Ezekiel's imagery and Isaiah's analogy,
it becomes clear that these prophetic insights symbolize Yahweh's manifestation
in both the celestial and terrestrial realms through the imagery of a colossal furnace.
This emphasizes the strong ties of his worship to the world of metallurgy.
The oldest plausible occurrence of his name is in the Egyptian land of Sashu Yahweh,
an inscription from the time of Amenhotep 3rd, 1390-1352 B.C. The Shasu, being nomads from Midian.
Yes, Midian, there you go again, and Edom in Northern Arabia. This gives the Yahweh as a Midian God,
way more plausibility. When we look at the Greek sources like Herodotus and Plutarch,
for which gods are worshiped in this region, they both claim that it's Dionysus and Venus
that are the main gods worshipped here. One might immediately dismiss this
due to the blatant differences between Greek Dionysus and Yahweh. However, the Bronze Age
Dionysian religion was so widespread and his worship flourished from Turkey down to Egypt
along the Mediterranean. So if Yahweh was connected to this ancient god in any way,
he would almost barely resemble him anymore by the time of antiquity. It's possible that Yahweh
could be a metallurgy volcano god with Dionysian attributes. For example, figures like Tacitus,
John the Lydian, Varro draw parallels between Yahweh and Bacchus Dionysus. Often Jews employed
symbols commonly linked to Dionysus, including chylixes, amphorae, ivy leaves, and grape clusters.
Plutarch highlighted these resemblances to argue that the Jews venerated a version of Bacchus
Dionysus. In Plutarch's questions in Moralia, he points out that Jews praised their deity
using the exclamations Iwa Sabao, chants that are typically related to Dionysus.
This is just many of the hundreds of Dionysian imagery that is found throughout the Hebrew
Bible, including the fact that the temple was designed with golden vines and golden grape
clusters throughout the sanctuary designed by Solomon, with golden satyrs who are the race of
daemons that are led by Dionysus to battle. In the ancient Greek text, many biblical parallels
and allegories are associated with the vine. The children of Israel are referred to as a vine
in Isaiah 5-7 and in Isaiah 9-10, Isaiah likens God as the owner of a vineyard,
and Israel is the vineyard. The grapevine is one of the seven species with which the land of
Israel was blessed. Deuteronomy 8-8, an ample supply of wine symbolized prosperity and well-being,
and overflowing that symbolized divine blessing. Every man under his vine and under his fig tree
symbolizes the idealized past and hope for a future peace. Threats of national disaster
were couched in terms of laying waste to the nation's vines and fig trees.
Hosea 2-14, Joel 1-7, the vines in blossom symbolized the passing of winter. Song of Songs 2-13,
and the ripening of fruit represented a fulfilled state of being, Joel 2-22. Although the fruit
of the vine was eaten fresh or dried, the plant was primarily valued for its fermented juice,
which was considered an appropriate gift of royalty. A description of Israelite culture
is provided by Isaiah and his parable concerning a vineyard. Let me sing for my beloved. A song
of my beloved about his vineyard. My beloved had a vineyard on a fruitful hill. He broke the ground,
cleared it of stones, and planted it with choice vines. He built a watchtower inside it. He hewed
a winepress in it, Isaiah 5-1-2. Many ancient depictions of Dionysus are shown as a man riding
a donkey, according to multiple sources, one of them which includes Manacias of Rhodes, who claims
that Antiochus IV raided the temple of Jerusalem, found within the Holy of Holies a golden donkey
with a man riding on it. According to Tacitus, when Pompey the Great raided the temple of Jerusalem,
all he found within the Holy of Holies was a golden ivy diadem, a symbol of none other
than Dionysus Bacchus. A coin was released by Pompey to commemorate his triumph over Judea,
which displayed a bearded individual on his knees holding a branch with the caption Bacchus
Judeus. This can be translated as either the Jewish Bacchus or Bacchus from Judea. Some interpret
this figure as representing Yahweh as a regional version of Bacchus or Dionysus. However, considering
such coin designs usually showcase subjugated individuals, rather than the deities of the
conquered, others believe it might symbolize a Judean whose name was Bacchus. This figure is
sometimes thought to be the Hasmonean king Aristobelus II, whom Pompey defeated. Regardless,
one of the many titles of Dionysus was Yaho or Yacus, and the Phrygians in the east called him
Savatsios, a god who was later identified by Romans as Theos Hipsistos, which means god most high,
the initial Jewish settlers in Rome faced expulsion in 139 BCE. Cornelius Hyspilus,
acting under a law that forbade spreading the corruption of worship of Jupiter Savatsios,
banished the Chaldean astrologers and the Jews. Nias Cornelius Hyspalus pray to our
peregrinus in the year of the consulate of Marcus Populus Lannis and Lucius Calpurnius,
ordered the astrologers by an edict to leave Rome and Italy within 10 days, since by a fallacious
interpretation of the stars they perturbed fickle and silly minds, thereby making profit out of their
lies. The same praetor compelled the Jews who attempted to infect the Roman custom with the
cult of Jupiter Savasios to return to their homes. This action suggests that Romans possibly equated
the Jewish Yahweh Tsavaot, meaning lord of hosts, with Job Savatsios.
Plutarch posited that the Jews revered Dionysus and celebrated the Sabbath as a tribute to Savatsios.
Additionally, he explored the idea of equating the Jewish god with the Egyptian entity Typhon,
although he later dismissed this association. Meanwhile, the monotheistic Hypsasterians revered
the most high using a name that might have been linked to the Jewish deity Herodotus,
who, like I said, never mentions Israel or Jerusalem or Yahweh, does happen to describe
a local religion somewhere between Mount Sinai and Phoenicia, possibly Midianite territory,
who have a similar ritual as described in the Hebrew Bible, such as the priests wearing similar
white and blue robes with golden tassels that are seen among priests of Dionysus and Demeter
and Eleusis and the blood oath rites, which seem to look very similar to Leviticus blood oath rites.
He is to dip his finger into the blood and sprinkle some of it seven times before the Lord
in front of the curtain of the sanctuary. Now compare this to the right the Herodotus records
among these local Arabians. There are no men who respect pledges more than the Arabians.
This is how they give them. A man stands between two pledging parties and with a sharp stone cuts
the palms of their hands near the thumb. Then he takes a piece of wood from the oak of each
and smears with their blood seven stones that lie between them.
Meanwhile, calling on Dionysus and the heavenly Aphrodite. In both cases, the blood is sprinkled
or smeared exactly seven times to seal the oath. A painting on a jar found at Kuntalit
under the inscription Yahweh of Samaria and his Asherah dated to 800 BCE, possibly the male
and female pair that Herodotus thought was Dionysus and Aphrodite. In an inscription discovered in
Iron Getty and dated around 700 BCE, Yahweh appears described as the Lord of the Nations.
While in other contemporary texts discovered in Kierbet Laya near Lakish, he is mentioned as
the ruler of Jerusalem and probably also of Judah Yahweh in the form of Yaho. It is frequently
invoked in Greco-Roman magical texts dating from the 2nd century BCE to the 5th century of the
Common Era, most notably in the Greek Magical Papyri under the names Yaho, Adonai, Sabaoth and
Eloi. These are also used as Bacchic chants among Dionysian religious revelers at this time.
Use of Yaho becomes blurred by the usage. Since the 2nd century BCE, Egyptians, Greeks, and Romans
had identified the evil god Seth Typhon, often depicted as a donkey-like creature with the Jewish
god Yahweh. The Seth Yahweh tradition with all its negative valence was then applied to the
Creator worshiped by the Christians as well. Evidence for this view comes from the early
Christian depiction of the Creator and his sons in donkey or typhonian form, the oldest manuscripts
of the Greek Septuagint, Old Testament in Greek, before the Church editions came in the 4th century
show Yaho in them for Leviticus 327 and 427. These are replaced with the uniform Curios or Lord
in the 4th century Church codexes of the Sinaiticus, Alexandricus, and Vaticanus.
I think it is very possible that we have in Yahweh a warrior, Demiurgic craftsman,
with ancient Bronze Age Dionysian elements passed down through the rites and traditions.
Although much closer to something like Vulcan than of Dionysus, this Yahweh, the local craftsman
metal-urgy god of the southern Levant, became infused with El, the chief god of the Canaanites,
to become Yahweh Elohim. This also puts him in direct opposition to Baal, the prince and son of El
in the northern Canaanite religion.
For Canaanites in the broader Levantine region, El was the highest god,
fathering notable gods like Baal and Yam. In Ugrit, El was married to the goddess Asherah,
but no temple was dedicated solely to him. Numerous titles and attributes describe El
from being a creator and king to a wise elder. Some myths feature him prominently, such as
a tale where he encounters two women by the sea and fathers the deities of dawn and dusk.
In an Ugritic story, El hosts a feast for the gods on Mount Lel, which may indicate
he lived in a tent explaining his lack of a dedicated temple. This text also suggests
he might have resided near sources of saltwater and freshwater in the text Palace of Baal story.
Baal Haddad, commonly known as Dagon's son, is occasionally referred to as El's son,
hinting at El's overarching authority over the gods. Another fragmentary text depicts El
inviting gods to a banquet where he gets embarrassingly drunk, showcasing his human-like flaws
Regarding the god El, he was seen as the preeminent deity residing atop the monumental Mount Saphon
where all gods convened, similar to Mount Olympius. Ugritic texts referred to the collective gods
as El's offspring, or all the gods to divine assembly. El was esteemed with titles such as
creature maker, the monarch, the Baal El, and humanity's father. Even though royal attributes
were primarily ascribed to El, he often came across as a figurehead, sometimes distant and
inactive, resembling what experts termed far-off supreme deity, something like we see in Zoroastrianism
with Zorvan. He lived in a celestial realm, termed the sources of the two deeps, where he
attended to visitors and dispatched directives via envoys, imagined as a kind of elderly figure.
El was sometimes named El the Benevolent. Eisfelt suggests that this particular characteristic
might have influenced the Israelites to envision their god Yahweh with more compassionate traits.
The name El likely stems from the root Yowl, meaning powerful or chief, and is believed to be
a descriptive term, as referenced by W. F. Albright in his works.
But the belief system of the Canaanites, a group of Semitic peoples from the ancient Levant,
spanned from the early Bronze Age up to initial centuries of the common era.
This religion was characterized by the worship of multiple deities and, in certain instances,
the exclusive veneration of one god while acknowledging the existence of others. The
Pantheon and Ugarit referred to the deities Elohim or El's descendants. Thilo of Biblos,
in the first century, Phoenician writer, who cited Sakoniethin of Beirut,
priest from the Bronze Age apparently, identified the chief creator god as Elian.
He was considered the progenitor of other gods. Greek records mention his union with Beirut,
symbolizing the city of Beirut. Such divine city unions can also be drawn parallel with
Melkart and Tyre, Kamash and Moab, Tanit and Balhaman in Carthage, and Yah with Jerusalem.
El-Eliyan's relationship with Asherah can be likened to the Greek tales of Kronos and Reia,
or the myths of Saturn and Ops.
At about this time, the descendants of the Dioscary put together rafts and ships,
and made voyages, and, being cast ashore near Mount Cassius, consecrated a temple there,
and the allies of El, who is Kronos, were surnamed Elohim, as these same were surnamed
after Kronos, what have been called Kroni. It was a custom of the ancients in great crisis
of danger for the rulers of a city or nation in order to avert the common ruin to give up the
most beloved of their children for sacrifice as a ransom to the avenging daemons, and those
who were thus given up were sacrificed with mystic rites. Kronos then, who the Phoenicians
call El, who was king of the country subsequently after his disease, was deified as the star Saturn,
and had by a nymph of the country named Anna Brett, an only begotten son, whom they call on
this account, Ye dude, the only begotten, still so called among the Phoenicians,
and when very great dangers from war had beset the country, he arrayed his son in royal apparel,
prepared an altar, and sacrificed him. Kronos also, in going around the world,
gives the kingdom of Attica to his own daughter Athena, but on the occurrence of a pestilence
and mortality, Kronos offers his only begotten son, as a whole burnt offering to his father Orinos,
that circumcises himself, compelling his allies to do the same. This has obvious parallels to the
story of Abraham, sacrificing his son Isaac on the altar. But then being stopped at the last minute,
which is the polemic against the old ways, the story of Abraham is an obvious euhemerization
of the text about El and Kronos, and archaeologists and Canaanite scholars
claim that the practice of child sacrifice was rampant among Canaanites in the first millennium
BC, as is clear from the frequent biblical allusions, as well as from the fact that tested
by Roman witnesses that the Carthaginians were migrated from Phoenicia in the 9th and 8th century
BC, practiced human sacrifice on a large scale. Down to the fall of Carthage, the root of this
practice in Punic religion is illustrated by the fact that it had not seized by the 3rd century
of the common era. Despite repeated Roman efforts to wipe it out, the Babylonians also
practice this due to the ritual of dressing sacrifice victim in royal purple to imitate a
substitute king and slaying them in public square. Our best source occurrences are the archaeological
remains from the royal death pits at early dynastic Ur from 2600 to 2500 BCE, and textual records of the
substitute king ritual that was practiced at least from the early 2nd millennium BCE,
down to the time of Alexander the Great. These rituals were known and practiced far and wide,
and El, who was also called Cronos, was at the center of these.
Again, would it not have been far better for the Carthaginians to have taken Critias or
Diagoras to draw up their law code at the very beginning, and so not to believe in any divine
power or god rather than to offer such sacrifices as they used to offer to Cronos.
With us, for instance, human sacrifice is not legal but unholy, whereas the Carthaginians
perform it as a thing they account wholly and legal, and that too when some of them sacrifice
even their own sons to Cronos, as I daresay you yourselves have heard.
And from then on to the present day they perform human sacrifices with the participation of all,
not only in Arcadia during the Laikeia and in Carthage to Cronos, but also periodically
in remembrance of the customary usage. They spill the blood of their own kin on the altars,
even though the divine law among them bars from the rites, by means of Perahenterra,
and the herald's proclamation anyone responsible for shedding of blood in peacetime.
Was chosen as a sacrifice for the city, for from ancient times the barbarians have had a custom
of sacrificing human beings to Cronos.
In Leviticus 1821, in Deuteronomy 1230, the Torah contains a number of in-laws forbidding child
sacrifice and human sacrifice in general. The Tanakh denounces human sacrifice as barbaric
customs of Baal worshippers. For example, Psalm 106-37, this is another example of the
biblical authors detaching themselves from the past of ancient Israel. It is impossible to
reconstruct some of the details of Canaanite ritual from references in the Old Testament.
1 Kings 18 describes the contest of Elijah, the prophets of Baal, on the summit of Mount Caramel.
The latter are said to have leaped about the altar, to have cut themselves after their manner
with knives and lances, till the blood gushed out upon them. The gashing with knives is found in
the description of El's mourning of the dead Baal, as well as in the writings of Lucian of
Samosota in the 2nd century, whose states that the custom was characteristic of the ceremonial
mourning of Adonis, which was performed annually at the Syrian sanctuary in Hierapolis, also known as
the Holy City. Moloch, sometimes written as Molech, was a Canaanite god mentioned in the
biblical accounts with child sacrifice. The name combines the consonants from the Hebrew word
Melch, meaning king, with the vowels from Boshet, meaning shame. In the Old Testament,
Boshet is often used as an alternative name for the widely recognized god Bael, who translates to
Lord. Moloch is also depicted in the Septuagint in Amos 6, with the star god Rhefane.
In the Hebrew, it's Sikkoth and Chion, instead of Moloch and Rhefane. This text directly connects
Saturn with Moloch in the following way. Sikkoth is a celestial god, recognized from the
on-god list discovered at Ugarit, originally sourced from Nippur and various Mesopotamian
origins. Here, it's represented as Ninerta, who is the principal deity in Mesopotamian culture
that is associated with this planet Saturn, and also acknowledged in the West and occasionally
equated with the god Horon, a god worshiped by the Samaritans. The name Sikkoth in Amos
precisely echoes this star god's name. Its title being Melch, or king, suggests the deity's prominent
status. It becomes the god Moloch in the biblical text. This indicates that Sikkoth holds the highest
significance in the ritual mentioned by Amos. Meanwhile, Chion correlates with the Akkadian term
Kajmanu, denoting the steadfast, the steady one, which is a reference to the star god Horon,
who is also equated with Sikkoth, is considered one of the most attested deities of the ancient
sources who shows up in text from the southernmost ends of Egypt all the way up to Turkey. He is
considered a god of healing, drugs, magic, forbidden knowledge, and doom. A possible forerunner to the
serpent in the garden, adding yet another layer of ancient deities that get polemicized in the
biblical text. In the Hebrew scriptures, Moloch is depicted as a foreign god who occasionally found
a foothold in Israel's religious practices due to the adoption of synchronistic beliefs by some
of the unfaithful kings. The divine commandments given to Moses explicitly prohibited the Jews
from engaging in the practices of the Egyptians or Canaanites. The edict stated,
you shall not sacrifice any of your children in fire to Moloch, thereby defiling the name of your
god, Leviticus 1821. Yet it is documented that influence kings like Ahaz and 2 Kings 16 and
Manessa, 2 Kings 21, under Assyrian sway, paid homage to Moloch at Tofeth, a hilly area just
outside Jerusalem. While this site thrived under the leadership of Manesh's son, King Omnon, it was
eradicated during King Josiah's rule, who was known for his religious reforms. He is quoted,
he desecrated Tofeth in the valley of Benhenom, so no one could use it to sacrifice their son or
daughter in the fire to Moloch, 2 Kings 2310. In Canaanite tales, two mountains,
Targitzi and Therimagi, support the sky and enclose the terrestrial ocean. W. F. Albright
suggests that the term El Shaddai stems from a Semitic origin found in the cating words
Shadu, meaning mountain, and Shadau, translating as mountain dweller. This associates with one of
the Amurus names. Philo of Biblos also claims that Atlas was an Elohim, just as he is a Titan
in the Greek text, aligning with El Shaddai's mountain god interpretation. Harriet Lutzky
offers another viewpoint, linking Shaddai with the Hebrew word sad, meaning breast. This suggests
a connection with the Semitic goddess, posits the twin mountains as symbolic breasts of the earth,
dual mountain themes are recurrent in Canaanite lore, similar to Horib and Sinai from the Bible.
Their religious beliefs of the Canaanites were shaped by their geographical location,
nestled between Egypt and Mesopotamia. These neighboring regions significantly impacted
Canaanite spirituality. For instance, during the role of the chariot rhyoning Mariano in
Egypt's Hyksos era, Baal began to be linked with the Egyptian deity Set, especially Set's Setaka form.
From that point on, Baal's depictions included the crown of lower Egypt and a distinct Egyptian
posture. Likewise, deities like Athoret, later known as Ashura and Anat, started being illustrated
with Egyptian wigs reminiscent of Hathor or Isis. From another perspective,
Jean Batarro proposed that Yah of Ebla, potentially a precursor to Yam,
god of the sea, was aligned with the Mesopotamian god Ia during the rule of the Akkadian empire.
The Canaanite faith in the middle and late Bronze Age
showed evident influences from the Hurrians and Mitonites. The Hurrian goddess Hibat found devotees
in Jerusalem, while Baal was often equated with the Hurrian storm deity Teshub and Hittite storm god
Tarhunt. When compared to the neighboring Eastern Arameans, the nature and roles of Canaanite gods
seemed remarkably similar. Early Amorite invaders of Mesopotamia previously recognized deities like
Baal Haddad and El. Phoenician sailors spread Canaanite religious beliefs to the west,
leaving imprints on Greek mythology. This can be seen in the division of power among the
Olympian gods Zeus, Poseidon, and Hades. Reflecting Hittite, Canaanites, Syrian divisions among Baal,
Yam, Moth, or Marduk, and Nenerta. Additionally, Hercules labors echo the tales of the Tyrian
Melkhart, who was frequently likened to Hercules. If we bring our attention back to the Elephantine
Jews living in Egypt in the 5th and 4th centuries BCE, we notice that Judaism at this time is still
polytheistic. The majority of the Aramaic fragments show either Jov, Yahu, or Kunum as the major head
of the pantheon, but some, like this Aramaic text, Carpentra Stella says,
In the top part of the stele, the Egyptian god of the underworld, Osiris sits on the throne,
recognizable with his characteristic crook and flail. Behind him is a goddess dressed in a long
skirt, could be Isis or Moth. The table, a lady perhaps, the deceased stands with her arms raised,
an adoration pose. In the lower image, the deceased is shown lying on a lying bed.
The embalming god Anubis is shown, assisted by the falcon god Horus. The four canopic jugs with
the entrails of the deceased are under the bed, with lids likely designed as heads of the four
sons of Horus. Emsit, Hopi, Duomatef, Kebehessenuf, Nephthys kneels at the feet of the dead, and Isis
is shown at the head. What happened? How is it that when we get to the time of Ptolemy II,
the creation of the Septuagint, that we all of a sudden had the monotheistic approach to theology
from these Israelites? I think the answer to this question is very simple. The popular philosophy
of any given time period is going to dramatically affect the theology of that period. For example,
we see how much the Stoics and Epicureans influenced the Middle Platonist, who in turn
influenced Christian theologians and church fathers of the second century.
But what about the third century BCE? At the time when the Pentateuch was being put together,
Platonism was on the rise, along with Aristotle's School of the Peripatetic and the skepticism of
Pyrrho. These philosophers, with the resources of the Great Library of Alexandria,
with access to thinkers like Zoraster, the Magian, and Heraclitus, some of the earliest thinkers
to exhibit monotheistic or skeptic tendencies against the dogmas and superstitions of the day.
Initiation here into the ancient mysteries so honored among men mocks holiness.
They raised their voices at stone idols as a man might argue with his doorpost.
They have understood so little of the gods.
Thales was the first master of the School of Athens. He was known for traveling to see the
greatest minds of his day in Egypt and Babylon. He taught that water was the first principle,
archaic, in which life can spring from. Thales believed in an uncreated being who crafts
fuses, nature, which all things are from. In the beginning, God created the heavens and the earth.
Now the earth was formless and empty. Darkness was over the surface of the deep,
and the spirit of God was hovering over the waters. Notice how water is the first thing that
is formed. This is in line with the philosophical thinking of Thales in the School of Athens,
and is also possible of the Egyptian sages or Magile Xoraster, believed in something similar.
Heraclitus describes Thales as a Phoenician by remote descent.
When Thales died, Anaximander became the second master, who was said to be the teacher of Pythagoras,
who brought these teachings to Italy. Anaximander is the earliest use of the word
eperion, or infinite, limitless, to designate the original first principle of the cosmos, uncreated,
beginning of all things. The first philosopher to employ in philosophical context, the term
archae, which until then had meant beginning or origin. Anaximander called this something by the
name fousis or nature. Next after him was Anaximinis, third master of the School of Athens, from the
Melesian school, who was a material monist, who sought to discover the archae, the beginning or
origin, the one underlying basis of all things. Anaximinis also believed that air was divine.
He identified air with the breath of life, and thus the soul as well as the air and the atmosphere.
Only a single sentence long quote by Anaximinis arrives, just as our soul, being air,
holds us together, so Numa and air encompass and guard the whole world.
This is the first extant source to use the word Numa or breath. Genesis 2.7 says,
the Lord God formed man from dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life,
the Numa, and the man became a living being. Genesis lines up perfectly with the philosophy
of the Presocratics. After Anaximinis you get Heraclitus, who claims to announce an everlasting
logos or word, according to which all things are one in some sense. Opposites are necessary for life,
but they are unified in a system of balanced exchanges. The world itself consists of a law-like
interchange of elements symbolized by fire, and Anaximinis is criticized by Parminides,
who starts the School of the Eliatics. He is called the Father of Logic. It is during this time
that superstitions and dogmas are being challenged. Anaxagoras would be the next master, Vathens,
and his innovative theory of physical nature is encapsulated in the phrase,
a portion of everything in everything. Its primary expression is found in the following
difficult fragment, and since the portions of both the large and the small are equal in amount,
in this way too all things would be in everything, nor can they be separate, but all things have a
portion of everything. Since there cannot be as smallest, nothing can be separated or come to
be by itself, but as in the beginning now too all things are together, but in all things there are
many things equal in amount both in the larger and the smaller of things being separated off.
God is one, is also a phrase that is attributed to him, who in response to the challenges imposed
by the competing schools of Parminides and Empedocles is able to unify the leading theories of
the day. Anaxagoras introduced the concept of the noose, or the cosmic mind, as an ordering force,
and one of his students would be Archelaus, the next master of the school, who was also at this
time a staunch skeptic and natural philosopher. He is the one who teaches Socrates, and Socrates
is the teacher of Plato. Plato would be the one to unify the entire base of knowledge that Athens
had been accumulating from the world for the past 200 years and bring them into his dialogues
through the character of Socrates, who was his teacher.
Plato wrote a dialogue called Timaeus, an exposition of cosmology in which the Demiurge,
the agent who takes the pre-existing materials of chaos, arranges them according to the models
of eternal forms, produces all physical things of the world, including human bodies. The Demiurge,
or the craftsman, if you want to say that, is sometimes thought of as the platonic personification
of active reason. What is so striking about this is that the Demiurge is the craftsman of the universe
like Yahweh or Ptah or El in the Ugritic text. He is the uncorated creator of the gods and humans
alike. Plato's idea of the cosmos is identical to what is taught in Judeo-Christian cosmology
in the time when the Pentateuch is put together. Plato, like his predecessors, were challenging
the dogmas and superstitions of his day, and he even sought to replace Homer and Hesiod,
the two most famous poets of ancient Greece, where most religious ideas of the day
are found in the stories about their gods. For instance, take Plato in Republic Book 3
through the mouth of Socrates says, There was another motive in purifying religion.
Which is to banish fear. For no man can be courageous, who is afraid of death,
who believes the tales, which are repeated by the poets concerning the world below.
They must be gently requested not to abuse hell or Hades. They may be reminded that their stories
are both untrue and discouraging. Nor must they be angry if we expunge obnoxious passages,
such as the depressing words of Achilles. I would rather be serving man than rule over the dead.
In the verses which tell of the squalid mansions, the senseless shadows, the fitting soul mourning
over lost strength and youth, the soul with a gibber going beneath the earth like smoke,
or the souls of the suitors which flutter about like bats, the terrors and horrors
of cockatice and sticks, ghost and shapeless shades, and the rest of their tartarian nomenclature
must vanish. Such tales may have their use, but they are not the proper food for soldiers,
as little can we admit the sorrows and sympathies of the Homeric heroes, Achilles the son of Thetis,
in tears, throwing ashes on his head, or pacing up and down the seashore in distraction.
Or Priam, the cousin of the gods, crying aloud, rolling in the mire. A good man is not prostrated
at the loss of children or fortune, neither is death terrible to him, and therefore lamentations
over the dead should not be practiced by men of note, they should be the concern of inferior
persons only, whether women or men. Still worst is the attribution of such weakness to the gods,
as when the goddess say, a loss may travail, and the worst of all, when the king of heaven himself
laments in the inability to save Hector, or sorrows over the impending doom of his dear Sarpadam.
Such a character of God is not ridiculed by our young men, is likely to be imitated by them,
nor should our citizens be given the excess laughter. Such violent delights are followed
by violent reaction. The description in the Iliad of the gods, shaking their sides at their
clumsiness of Hephaestus, will not be admitted by us, certainly not.
Plato is clearly not satisfied with the pagan religions of his day, and wants to replace it
with a more up-to-date or mature theology, with a perfect god who has no mistakes and is never
depicted doing anything that we can look at as weak. Plato says, let us declare then for what
caused nature, and this all was framed by him that framed it. He was good, and in none that is good
can there arise jealousy of ought at any time. So being far aloof from this, he desired that all
things should be as like unto himself as possible. This is that the most sovereign cause of nature
in the universe, which we shall most surely be right in accepting from men of understanding,
for God desiring that all things should be good, and that so far as this might be,
there should be not evil having received all that is visible, not in a state of rest,
but moving without harmony or measure, brought it from its disorder into order,
thinking that this was all in ways better than the other. And Plato continues,
in the forming the universe, he curated reason in soul and soul and body, that he might be the
maker of a work that was by nature the most fair and perfect. In this way then, we ought to affirm
according to probable account that this universe is a living creature and very truth possessing soul
and reason by the providence of God.
Plato also rejected Athenian democracy in favor of a republic guided by a priesthood
and a philosopher king, whose laws were given by the gods and are the most ancient and holy.
He rejected even things he once said were great before, such as the Dionysian mysteries of love
and passion, which he now argues in his last work are empty pleasures. For instance, in his last work
On Laws, 636b, these common meals, for example, and these gymnasia,
while they are at present beneficial to the states and many other respects,
yet in the event of civil strife, they prove dangerous. And moreover, this institution,
one of old standing, is thought to have corrupted the pleasures of love which are natural not to
men, but also natural to beast. For this, your states are held primarily responsible
and along with them all others that are especially encouraged the use of the gymnasia.
And whether one makes the observation in earnest or in jests, one certainly should not fail to
observe that when a male unites with female for the procreation, the pleasure, experience is held
to be due to nature, but contrary to nature, when male mates with male or female with female,
and that those first guilty of such enormities were impelled by their slavery to pleasure.
And we all accuse the Cretans of concocting the story about Ganymede to justify unnatural pleasures.
In case you didn't know, Ganymede was the boy lover of Zeus.
When we look at this, in context to the story of Maccabees, you see the laws enacted and followed
by none other than the Maccabee dynasty, who revolts against the Greek pagan king Antiochus
IV for putting a gymnasium in Jerusalem, which they called an abomination. Looks like Judas
Maccabees and Plato believe the same thing about gymnasiums. I also think there is clear ties to
ancient Babylon, Assyrian and Sumerian laws, stories woven in the text. These are in no doubt in my
mind authentic and ancient Near Eastern texts that the Greeks inherit from the Jews. For example,
Deuteronomy, an eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth, is clearly an ancient law that we see present
in Hammurabi's code. As Plato said in the Republic, though, for people to respect the laws,
they need to be the most ancient and given by the gods from the oldest times. But I also think
there is no reason to believe that the philosophers and scribes of Alexandria, like Demetrius Filarium,
did not have any oversight over what was written and edited.
What solid evidence do we have that Platonism has any influence on Judaism? If we continue down our
line of masters, schools, methods, as I trace the roots of Thales down to Plato,
the next three school masters after Plato is Aristotle, who, after the conquest of Alexander
the Great, is sent into exile by the Ellusinian priest, who charged Aristotle with blasphemy
against the gods, and Aristotle is replaced by Theophrastus, who was also charged by the Athenian
religious leaders with blasphemy against the gods. Now keep in mind, all of this is happening after
Socrates. What is happening with these masters of Athens being at odds with the religious leaders
of the priests of the Ellusinians? They're obviously challenging the dogmas and superstitions.
Now Theophrastus was the student and new master of the school who taught Demetrius Filarium.
Demetrius Filarium was also exiled, and he moves to Alexandria with Pierrot the Skeptic
after traveling the world with Alexander the Great, meeting Brahmins and Magi and living
amongst the Chaldeans and Babylon, and they went down to the court of Ptolemy and Alexandria
to help build the library. According to multiple sources, Demetrius Filarium was trying to collect
all the books in the inhabitable world and was commissioned by Ptolemy to translate the laws
of the Jews into Greek. In my personal opinion, it is at this time when the Pentateuch is put
together in its current monotheistic form, with influences from the Platonist of the time period.
You see, we have a direct line from Thales the Presocratics all the way down to Plato
and then continuing down to Demetrius who moves to Alexandria Egypt and creates the Pentateuch.
Here's what Josephus says about this. When Alexander had reigned 12 years and after him
Ptolemy sought her 40 years, Philadelphius then took the kingdom of Egypt and held it 40 years
within one. He procured the law to be interpreted and set free those who come from Jerusalem into
Egypt and were in slavery there, who were 120,000. The occasion was this. Demetrius Filarius,
who was library keeper to the king, was now endeavoring, if it were possible, to gather
together all the books that were in the inhabitable earth. And buying whatsoever was anywhere valuable
or agreeable to the king's inclination, which inclination of his Demetrius was zealously subservient.
And when once Ptolemy asked him how many tens of thousands of books he had collected, he replied
that he already had 20 times 10,000, but that in a little time he should have 50 times 10,000.
But be said, he had been informed that there are many books of the laws among the Jews worthy
of inquiring for and worthy of the king's library, but which, being written of characters and in
dialect of their own, will cause no small pains in getting them translated into the Greek tongue,
that the character in which they are written seems to be like that which is proper to the
character of the Syrians, and that its sound when pronounced is like theirs also, and that this sound
appears to be peculiar to themselves, wherefore he said that nothing hindered why they might not get
those books to be translated also. For while nothing is wanting that is necessary for that
purpose, we may have their books also in this library. So the king thought that Demetrius was
very zealous to procure him an abundance of books, and that he suggested that this was exceeding
proper for him to do, and therefore he wrote to the Jewish high priest that he should act accordingly.
Demetrius wrote in a letter, It is not fit for us, O king, to overlook things hastily
or to deceive ourselves, but to lay the truth open, for since we have determined not only to get
the laws of the Jews transcribed, but interpreted also, for thy satisfaction, by what means can we
do this, while so many of the Jews are now slaves in thy kingdom. For both these people, and we also
worship the same God, the framer of all things, we call him, and that truly by the Greek Xena,
or Jupiter, because he breathes life into all men, wherefore do thou restore these men
to their own country, and that this do the honor of God, because these men pay a peculiar excellent
worship to him. Known as how Demetrius is already comparing his framer of all things,
the divine craftsman or demiurge, who he was most likely comparing to Yahweh in order to
unify this God with Jupiter. Keep in mind, less than a century before this, the fragments of the
Jewish communities that we have are still polytheistic. We have a direct line from the masters of the
Athens Academy, from Thales all the way down to Demetrius, who is writing this letter to the Jews,
who is the face of the creation of the Pentateuch. I think there is more than enough evidence to
lay this argument out, that this is the beginning of the trend of monotheism, and at this time,
the priestshoods of Yahweh and El, synced with that of the craftsmen and demiurgic
creator gods of Egypt and Greece, Yahweh of the Elohim, and the God who has its roots all over
Mesopotamia and the Mediterranean world, such as Kronos, El, Pita, Yahweh, or Zeus, or Amen Ra.
The so-called pagans that lived after this time period also adopt the same monist trends
the Judeo-Christians adopt. The soul-invictus religion would come from that and the neoplateness
philosophers and theurgists were no exception to this. The Chaldean oracles also show a
one who is above all gods. The philosophy of the time, Platonism to Middle Platonism,
and eventually Neoplatonism, would continue to influence the theology of whatever time matched it.
I'll leave you with this. In a text from Plutarch called Moralia, he says,
moreover, most people believe that Amon is the name given to Zeus in the land of the Egyptians,
a name which we, with a slight alteration, pronounce Amon. But Menitho of Seventus thinks that the
meaning concealed or concealment lies in this word. Hecateus of Abdera says that the Egyptians
use the expression one to another whenever they call to anyone. For the word is a form of address
when they therefore address the supreme god whom they believe to be the same as the universe as
if he were invisible, concealed, and implore him to make visible himself and manifest to them.
They use the word Amen. So great then was the circumspection of the Egyptians and their wisdom
touching all that had to do with the gods. Plutarch is proposing that the term Amen
is a shout or chant that is used to call on any of the gods, not just Amon, but any of the gods
including the supreme invisible one. He also cites Hecateus of Abdera for this very idea. And it
turns out the Hecateus of Abdera is the oldest fragment that we have, citation of Moses outside
of the Hebrew Bible. Let me know what you guys think about this stuff. Leave it in the comments,
make sure you like and subscribe. You have attained true noses.