Hello, everybody, and
welcome to another YouTube
video. In this video, I'm
going to be showing you
how to make a planet
simulation using
Python. Now, the goal of
this is going to be to
simulate the orbits of
different planets
around the sun. We're
going to use real
astronomical values. So
the real mass of the
sun, the real distance
from Earth to the sun,
all of that type of
stuff. And we're going
to apply the force of
gravity between all of
the different planets.
So we actually get an
accurate elliptical
orbit. Now here it does
look like the orbit is
circular. It is not. You
can see I'm actually
writing the distance of
the planet to the sun on
each planet. So it's
changing as we go
around the orbit. Well,
this is really cool.
We're kind of mixing a
bit of physics with
Python and looking at a
cool simulation. Now, I
will mention that this
tutorial is not designed
for complete beginners.
You should have some
knowledge of Python.
However, if you don't
know anything about
physics, don't worry.
I will teach you the
different physics we need
to know to actually, I
guess, perform this
simulation. It's not
very complicated. I
myself am not a physics
major or a physics guy.
And I was able to figure
it out pretty quickly.
Anyways, with that said,
let's go ahead and get
into the code after a
quick word from our
sponsor. Thanks to
Backtrace for sponsoring
this video. Backtrace
provides application
monitoring, as well as
error and crash reporting
for games. We've all
been there excited to
launch a brand new
video game just to be
tormented by crashes,
bugs and an overall bad
user experience. Backtrace
wants to help limit that
by providing a platform
that gives game developers
the best error and crash
reporting with the most
complete and helpful
information. Backtrace
works with any platform,
any engine and at any
scale and provides 24 seven
monitoring so you can
retain more players and
get better ratings.
Backtrace helps you fix
issues fast by providing
accurate call stacks,
regression detection,
querying and analytics
and integration with
Microsoft teams,
Discord, Slack and more.
You can get started with
Backtrace today and
manage up to 25,000
monthly errors with one
month retention and 10
gigabytes of storage
completely for free.
Check it out from the
link in the description
and thanks again to
Backtrace for sponsoring
this video. All right.
So let's go ahead and
get started. Now, I will
mention that right here,
I'm not simulating every
single planet. You can
easily adjust the
simulation to add as
many planets as you
would like. You can even
put something like stars
or satellites, whatever.
You can put any of that
here because of the
way we're going to set
this up. However, the
planets I'm simulating
right now are just the
four closest to the sun.
So we have Earth, Mars,
Venus and Mercury.
We're just doing that.
So we get a nice visual
and we can see
everything nice and large.
If you were to simulate
the planets that are
much further away from
the sun, then you're
going to see all of
these plants kind of
smushed really close to
the sun and then the
huge orbits around the
sun from the larger
planets, if that makes
sense. And the planets
that are much further
away. So this is just
a nice visualization.
Again, you can adjust
this however you like,
and I'll show you how to
do that. So with that
said, let's dive into
this. I'm going to
close this and just
open up a new window
here and we'll start
writing some code. Now,
the first thing we do
actually need to do is
install Pi game. So if
you don't already have
Pi game installed, then
just open up your
terminal or command
prompt, depending on
your operating system
and type in the
following command, PIP
install Pi game. That
doesn't work for you.
Try PIP three install
Pi game. If that
doesn't work for you,
try Python hyphen M and
then PIP install Pi game.
If that doesn't work,
try Python three hyphen M
PIP install Pi game.
And if none of those
commands work, I have
two videos that I'll
put on the screen that
show you how to fix
your PIP command.
Anyways, I'm going to
assume that you have
Pi game installed.
This is just a 2D
graphics library that
we're going to use for
the simulation. If you
don't know Pi game,
don't worry, we're going
to use very limited
features from it. And
I'll talk about how all
of them work. So the
first thing I'm going
to do here is just
import Pi game. And
then I'm going to say
Pi game dot a knit
just to initialize the
module. I'm also going
to import the math
module because we're
going to have to use
that in this code.
Okay. So continuing
since I'm using Pi game,
the first thing I want
to do is set up my
Pi game window. Now to
do this, we need to
pick a width and height
in pixels for our
window. So I'm going to
say the width comma the
height in all capitals
because this is a
constant is going to be
800 800 can make this
whatever width and
height you want, but I
recommend you make it
square. And then we're
going to set up a
window. So I'm going to
say when is equal to
Pi game dot display
dot set underscore
mode. Now this is just
going to take in the
coordinates for the
size of our window. So
we're going to pass as
a couple here, the
width and the height.
This is going to give
us what's known as a
Pi game surface. We're
going to call it the
window because it's the
main window that we're
going to draw onto. And
we need to have access
to this surface to be
able to put something
on the screen and
actually see something
moving around. Now what
I'm also going to do is
just set a caption for
this window. So Pi game
dot display dot set
underscore caption. Now
the caption is just
going to be kind of the
title of the window. I'll
show you what it looks
like in one second. And
for this, we'll just do
planet simulation. Okay,
perfect. So now that we
have this, what I want to
do is create something
known as the Pi game
event loop. Now this is
essentially an infinite
loop that's going to run
the entire time that
the simulation is going.
Whenever you're working
with some type of game,
you need some type of
loop that's constantly
running. They can keep
track of the different
events that are occurring.
In this case, the only
event is going to be
moving the different
planets, but we need to
have some type of loops
that the window doesn't
just open and instantly
close. We need something
keeping the program
running. So I'm going to
make a function here and
I'm going to call this
main and inside of here,
I'm going to make a
variable. I'm going to
say run is equal to
true. Then we're going
to say, well, run like
this and this loop will
run while this variable
run is true. Now inside
of here, I'm going to
get the different
events that are occurring
in Pi game. So I'm going
to say for event in Pi
game dot event dot get.
Now this is going to give
us a list of all of the
different events that
occur. So key presses,
mouse movements,
whatever. Now when you're
coding a more complex
game, you're going to
handle those different
events. However, the
only event that we want
to handle is when the
user presses the X
button to close the
window. Now that event
is the following. I'm
going to say if event
dot type is equal to
Pi game dot quit in
all capitals, then all
we're going to do is
say run is equal to
false. And then outside
of our wall loop, we're
going to say Pi game dot
quit. So this is
literally all we need
for the event loop,
at least for right now,
what's going to happen
is we're going to
continually run, we're
going to get all of the
events. If one of the
events that occurred
was we hit the X
button in the window,
then we are going to
close the window by
making run equal to
false. Since that's
going to exit our loop,
we're going to quit
Pi game and then we'll
be done. Perfect. So
all we need to do here
is just call this main
function. And now that
we do this, we should
see a Pi game window
pop up and then we can
close it and get out of
the program safely. So
let's try this. And
there we go. We get
planet simulation.
This is the caption I
was talking about. You
could see it kind of
right here beside the
little Pi game logo.
Then if I click the X
button, we're going to
close and we are all
okay. We have set up
our event loop. Nice.
So now that we have
done that, I just want
to show you how we can
draw something onto
the screen and kind of
update the screen. So
let's do that. So at
the top of this loop
here, I'm actually
going to set up
something called a
clock. Now a clock
is essentially going
to make it so that the
frame rate of our game
won't go past a certain
value. I'll talk about
why we need this, but
the idea here is that
if we don't implement
some type of clock, so
some way to synchronize
our game, essentially,
you're going to run
the simulation at the
speed of your computer.
Now, some people want
that to happen. They
want it to run super
fast. If you're on a
super fast computer and
then super slow, if
you're on a super
slow one, but ideally
for me, I don't care
about what type of
processor you have. I
just want you to run
the simulation at the
same speed. So it
looks normal. Hopefully
that makes a bit of
sense, but we can
kind of regulate the
frame rate and how
many times our game is
refreshing. So the way
we do that is we say
clock is equal to
pie game dot time
dot clock. And then
we go here and we say
clock dot tick. And
then we put in the
number of times that
we want this to update
per second. Now, this
does not mean you're
always going to update
at, in this case, 60
frames per second.
However, this is the
maximum that you will
be able to update at.
So we're saying clock
dot tick 60. That
means we're going to
update this loop or
run this loop a maximum
of 60 times per second
to ensure our games
not going too fast.
Okay. So now we have
our clock. And as I
was saying, we want to
draw something on the
screen. So to draw
something, I'm going to
use my window right
here. And I'm going to
say win dot fill. And
then I need to pass an
RGB color here that's
going to be the color
that I want to fill the
entire window with on
the screen. So I'm just
going to define a
color. Let's just go
with white for now. And
white will be equal to
255, 255, 255. Okay.
So that's our RGB value
for white. And then I'm
going to pass white
inside of here. And we
should see in a second
that we're going to get
the screen actually
updating. And now it's
going to have a white
background rather than a
black. However, I will
show you if I currently
run the code, we
actually don't get any
white on the screen. And
the reason we don't get
any white on the screen
is because we're not
updating the display. So
what I need to do is say
pie game dot display dot
update, not clear. And
what this does is
actually take all of the
drawing actions that
we've done since the
last update and then
kind of paste them and
draws them onto the
screen. So what I'm
doing is every loop, I'm
going to fill the
background with white
and then I'm going to
update the display. Okay.
So now if I run this,
you're going to see that
we get a white back. Now
we don't actually want
a white background. I
want a black one. So
I'm going to get rid of
this. I just wanted to
show you how we fill the
screen. Okay. So let's
comment these out for
right now. Perfect. So
now that we've done this,
let's start implementing
a plan because obviously
we want to put some
planets on the screen.
And to do this, I'm
going to make a class.
So I'm going to say class
planet. And inside of
here, I'm going to define
an initialization. I'm
going to say define a
knit. I'm going to say
self. We need an X and a
Y. Now the X and the Y
is going to be the
position that we want
this planet to be on
the screen. We also
are going to need a
radius. We're going to
need a color. And then
let me just check if we
want to take anything
else. We're also going
to need a mass for the
planet. Okay. So these
are kind of the
initialization values
that we have. So I'm
going to say self dot
X is equal to X self
dot Y is equal to Y
self dot radius is
equal to radius.
Obviously we're going
to have circular
planets, self dot
color is equal to
color. We might want to
make our planets more
detailed and have
multiple colors, but
for now we're just
going to go with a
single color. And then
the mass is going to
be the mass in
kilograms of this
planet. We're going to
have to use that mass
to calculate the
attraction between the
different planets and
then generate the
actual circular orbit,
which we'll get to when
we start talking about
the physics. Now there's
a few other things that
we want our planets to
have. They're going to
have to have an X
velocity as well as a
Y velocity. So I'm
going to say self dot
underscore X, well, is
equal to zero and
self dot Y, well, is
equal to zero. Now
I'll explain how all
of these concepts work
in a second, but the
idea is we're going to
be moving our planet
in a circle. And in
order to move in a
circle, we have a
velocity in multiple
directions. So we're
going to have it in the
X direction, which is
the horizontal
direction and then in
the Y direction. And by
moving in two
directions at the same
time, we're able to
generate a circle and
have kind of, I don't
want to call it
centripetal force or
some, some tripetal
motion, but something
along those lines, right?
Well, we're actually
moving in a circle
around an object at a
constant speed. Okay.
Hopefully this is
making sense so far.
Another thing that I
want to do here is I
want to have something
that says self that
sun is equal to false.
Now this is going to
tell us if the planet
is the sun. The reason
we want that is because
we're going to draw the
orbit of the planet
moving around. And I
don't want to draw the
orbit for the sun. So I
need to know if it's a
sun to either draw it
or to not draw it. And
then I'm going to have
the self.distance to
the sun. I'm just going
to make this equal to
zero right now. And
we're going to update
this value for every
single planet that we
have so that we know
what its distances and
we can then draw that
on the screen. And then
the last thing that I
want is self.orbit is
equal to an empty list.
We're going to use this
to keep track of all of
the points that this
planet has traveled
along so we can draw a
circular orbit
representing well, the
orbit of the planet.
Okay. Again, all this
will start to make sense
as we get into more of
these concepts. I'm just
kind of setting up all
of the initialization
values. Now, a few
other things that I
want to do here is
just write out a few
constants that we're
going to use for our
simulation. Now, the
first constant we're
going to do as a class
variable in the planet
class. And this is
going to be a you. Now,
a you is astronomical
units. And this is
approximately equal to
the distance of the
earth to the sun. Now,
I want to use a you
because it's going to
simplify the math that
we need to do to
calculate the distance
between the current
planet and the sun and
allow us to initialize
our planets at the
correct a you from the
sun. So they're kind of
the correct distance
away. Hopefully that
makes a bit of sense,
but one a you is equal
to. And I just have to
copy this from my other
screen. One point four
nine dot six to the
exponent six, which is
what this E six stands
for, and then
multiplied by a
thousand. And I don't
actually need these
in parentheses. So I
don't know why I had it
there. Okay. So what
this is saying is we
are one hundred and
forty nine thousand. I
guess this is sorry,
one hundred forty nine
million and then six
hundred thousand
kilometers. That's what
this stands for right
here, but we want this
to be in meters. So I'm
going to multiply it by
a thousand to get the
distance from the sun
in meters. One a you
that that's what this
is. Hopefully that makes
sense. Again, want to
use the distance from
the earth to the sun
approximately. And here
we're converting this
from kilometers to
meters by multiplying
it by a thousand. Okay.
Now, we also want the
gravitational constant
now. This is not
negative nine point eight.
That's the acceleration
of gravity. I actually
yeah, I think it's
the acceleration of
gravity. I might be
messing that up, but
it's something to do
with gravity, but the
gravitational constant
is used in finding the
force of attraction
between objects, which
is what we want to do.
And G is different than
the regular gravity one.
It is six point six seven
and actually is four
point two eight either
the negative eleven.
Okay. That's great. My
autocomplete is working
very well there. Nice.
Now, the last two
things we want here is
a scale. Since we're
actually going to be
simulating the real
values here for the
orbits, we can't draw
them at the position
that we have them at.
I know that's probably
a confusing line, but
the idea is if our
planet is moving at,
you know, something
kilometers per second,
seven kilometers per
second, 29 kilometers
per second, I can't
draw my planet at a
million kilometers in
my pie game window.
I need to draw it in
a kind of appropriate
scale, right? So I'm
going to have to figure
out what one meter
represents in terms of
pixels in my pie game
scale here, because I'm
only working with 800
pixels high and 800
pixels wide. Hopefully
this is making a little
bit of sense. What I'm
going to do here is say
250 divided by A.U. is
the scale. Now, this
scale essentially says
that one astronomical
unit is going to be
about 100 pixels in my
pie game program. You
can look at the math to
figure out how that
works. But for now, I'll
leave a comment. We're
going to say one A.U. is
equal to 100 pixels.
OK, that's kind of the
scale that we're going
with here. So we can
draw things to scale in
the window. And then the
last thing I want is the
time step. And this is
going to represent how
much of time I want to
represent in my
simulation or that I
want to simulate is
being a lapse. So the
idea here is every time
I update the frame, I'm
going to pass a certain
time step and say, OK, I
want to look at one hour
of this planet's movement
at a time or one day of
this planet's movement at
a time, because I don't
want to look at one
second. It's going to
take a really, really
long time to simulate.
Instead, I want to look
at a larger time step.
So what I'm going to do
is say 3600, which is
the number of seconds in
a what is this in an
hour? Yeah, I think
this number of seconds
in an hour. And then I'm
going to multiply this
by 24. And that's going
to give me one day. OK,
so this is representing
one day. I think that's
correct. Yeah, OK, I'm
pretty certain that is
correct. This would be
the number of seconds in
an hour, right? If you
go 60 times 60, I think
that gives you 3600.
And then multiply that by
24. And that is the
time step that we're
going to be doing the
simulation on. So kind
of one day at a time
will be updating the
planet. All right.
Hopefully I'm not
confusing you guys too
much. I do understand
this is a lot. We've
got to go through a
bunch of physics and
stuff here to make this
work. But there you go.
That is a planet. Now,
the next thing I want to
do is implement a draw
method. Now, this draw
method just going to
draw the planet on the
screen. So what I'm
going to do is say
self and I'm going to
take a window that I
need to draw this
planet on. So the X and Y
for my planet, as well
as the X velocity and
the Y velocity for my
planet is going to be
in meters. So the
number of meters that
I am away from the sun,
that's what X and Y is
going to represent. So
I need to take those
values and then draw
them to scale, right?
Because I again, I
can't draw like
something million
kilometers or million
meters away. I need to
draw it in accurate
scale in pie game. So
this is where the
scale is going to come
in. I'm going to say
that my X is equal to
and then this is
going to be the self
dot X multiplied by
my scale. OK, so it's
going to be self
dot scale and self
that scale is going to
be a really, really
tiny number that will
now take this number
and bring it to scale.
And I'm going to say
Y is equal to self
dot Y and I'm going to
multiply that by self
dot scale. OK, nice.
Now, one other thing
I need to do is make
sure that I'm drawing
all of this in the
center of my screen
because I haven't
mentioned yet when
we're talking about
pie game, zero, zero
is actually the top
left hand corner.
So let me just
quickly open the
window here, right
here where my mouse is.
So top left hand corner.
This is zero, zero.
If I go all the way
to the right, this would
be eight hundred zero.
If I go all the way
to the bottom right
hand corner, this would
be eight hundred, eight
hundred. So rather than
having zero zero in the
middle, which you might
be used to, it's the
top left. So I don't
want to draw my stuff
in the top left.
I want to draw it in
the center. So that
means I need to take
every single value I
have. I need to offset
it by the center of
the screen so that we
draw stuff in the
middle. Hopefully that
makes a tiny bit of
sense. But the way we
do this is we say plus
and then this is going
to be width over two,
to be plus. And then
this is going to be
height over two. And
those values are
right here. OK, so the
width and the height.
We could just write
four hundred, but I'm
going to do width and
height. So that if we
change the width and
the height, this is
going to update
automatically. OK, so
now we have our X and Y
and now I can actually
draw this onto the
screen. So I'm going to
say pie game dot draw
dot circle. And I'm
going to pass the
window, which is where
we want to draw this
circle. I'm going to
pass the color that I
want to draw the
circle in. So this is
going to be self
color. I'm going to
pass the position that
I want to draw it in,
which is going to be
X, Y. That's the
center of the circle.
And then lastly, I'm
going to pass the
radius. So self dot
radius. OK, so now
we're actually going
to draw the circle on
the screen when we
call this draw method.
OK, hopefully this is
all making a bit of
sense. And let's now
go and actually draw a
few planets and
initialize some of
their constants. So the
first planet we probably
want to draw is the
sun. Can you call the
sun a planet? I guess
it's a star. Again, not
a big physics guy, but
the first thing we
want to draw is the
sun. OK, so I'm going
to say sun is equal to
planet. And we're
going to pass zero, zero
for its X, Y. OK, so
zero, zero right here
for the radius of the
sun. We can kind of
pick whatever value we
want here. We're just
going to be kind of
randomly picking the
radius is based on
the relative mass of
the planets. So we
want the sun to be the
biggest. And what I
have in my other
program here is 30 for
the radius. So we'll go
with that. And for the
color, I want this to
be yellow. So just
make this a bit easier
to read. I'm going to
define yellow up here
and yellow. Actually,
how do you even make
yellow? Let's look at
this. Yellow is going
to be 255, 255 and
zero. OK, so that's
the RGB value for
yellow. Obviously,
that's the color we
want the sun. So let's
now put the color as
yellow. And then the
last thing we need to
pass is the mass and
the mass. I need to
look at my cheat sheet
here because,
unfortunately, I don't
have this memorized
is going to be the
following. Let me
paste this in 1.9 8 8 9
2 times 10 to the
exponent 30. And in
case you're wondering
this is in kilograms.
Again, we're going to
use the accurate masses
on astronomical units
and stuff for all of
these planets. OK, so
that is the sun. And
for the sun, we're just
going to say sun dot
sun is equal to true.
Because remember, we
have this property
here that says sun. And
we're going to make
this true so that we
don't draw the distance
to the sun from the
sun and we don't draw
the orbit for the sun,
which we don't need.
OK, so now that we
have this, let's just
see if we can draw this
on the screen. So
let's go. Planets is
equal to and let's
make a list of all of
the planets, because
we're going to add a
few more. And then
inside of our loop
here, we're going to
say for planet in
planets. And we're
going to say planet
dot draw. And we're
going to pass the
window that we want to
draw it on, which is
win in all capitals.
OK. Nice. And we
also need to make sure
that we're updating
this place. So let's
steal this here. And
let's put it down
there. OK. Nice. So
we're saying for planet
and planet plan to draw
by game display
dot update. Let's see
if this works. Fingers
crossed. Let's run the
code. OK. There we go.
We get a sun in the
middle of the screen.
Very nice. That is
exactly what we want.
All right. Now, the
next thing we want to
do is draw a few more
plans, right? So let's
create earth, mercury,
all of those. OK. So
we're going to start
with earth. I'm going
to say earth is equal
to planet. Now, the
earth is actually
going to be negative
one multiplied by
planet with an all
capital dot a U. This
is going to be the
distance from the sun.
So we're going to put
that as the X
coordinate. And for the
Y coordinate, we're
just going to make it
zero for right now.
The color of the earth
is going to be blue.
We'll write that RGB
variable in a second.
And then the mass of
the earth. Actually,
sorry, we need the
radius as well. Let's
put the radius first.
What was the radius
of the earth? I had
60 in here as the
radius. And then the
mass of the earth is
this number. Let me
copy it in 5.9742
times 10 to the
exponent 24. OK. That's
a mass of the earth.
Now, I will actually
mention here before I
continue that there
isn't a great article.
I'm going to open it up
so I can show it to you
guys. Let me get it on
my Google Chrome here
that I'm actually
inspired by making
this program that has
all of these values
already. So this is
the article. Leave it
in the description, but
it essentially
implements the same
thing we're going to
implement here in
turtle. Now, I didn't
want to do it in turtle
because pie game is a
lot better and it's a
lot faster. But if you
look here, all the
values that I'm using
are just coming from
here. Right. So like
the earth mass, the
earth distance, negative
one times a you, the
sun mass, just wanted
to give credit to this
article. I'll leave it
in the description.
Anyways, enough of that.
We have the distance to
the sun, which is this.
We have zero, 16 blue.
This is the mass. And I
think that's all we need
for the earth right now.
Let's now put earth
inside of here and see
if when we draw it, we
get it in an accurate
position. OK, so let's
run this. And we get
blue is not fine. OK, I
forgot to do that.
Let's define the color
blue. Blue is going to
be equal to. And then I
want kind of a nice
light blue. So I just
picked one of these
before. It's going to be
100 149 237. This is
the RGB value for kind
of a lighter blue. If
you just wanted to be
regular blue, then you
could go zero, zero,
and then 255. And I
give you a nice dark
blue. OK, so let's run
this now and see if
this works. And there
we go. We get the the
earth, which is, you
know, one way from the
sun. Hopefully that
makes sense. But this
is how the scales
working. We put it at
negative one, which
means we're going to
the left. If we put at
one, we would have gone
to the right. Doesn't
really matter where we
started. And there we
go. OK, so now we have
the earth, the next
planet that I want to
do. Let's look here is
going to be Mars. So
let's say Mars is equal
to a planet. Now, the
distance for Mars is
going to be this. Let
me just copy it in.
It's going to be negative
one point five to four
times planet.au. Again,
we're going to put its
Y coordinate at zero.
The radius of Mars,
it's much smaller than
Earth. We're going to
go with 12. It's going
to be red, which I'll
define in a second. And
then the mass of Mars
is a little bit less
than Earth as well. So
that's going to be six
point three nine times
10 to the exponent
twenty three. Now, for
red, we need to define
this. Now, again, I
want to kind of a nice
looking red. So I
picked a custom RGB
value here, and this
value is going to be
one eighty eight thirty
nine and fifty. OK. And
now we have Mars. So
now that we have Mars,
we're going to put Mars
inside of here, and we
should now draw Mars
at the appropriate
scale. So let's look
at this and we see the
Mars over here. So
notice that Mars is
kind of right by the
border. I'm fine with
that. But if you wanted
to move everything in
closer, then what you
would do is reduce
this number right here.
So rather than doing
250, you would do
something like 200. And
you're going to notice
this is going to move
us in a little bit
closer. So that's kind
of how you can mess
with things. Just make
the number here
smaller. If you want
everything to get
closer to the sun. OK,
so we'll go to 50
AU for now. All right.
So now we have Mars.
Let's do our other
planets. So the other
planets we have is
Mercury. This is going
to be equal to planet
this distance.
This is the closest
one to the sun.
My understanding is at
least this is going to
be zero. We're going
to have to make this
smaller. So we're going
to go to zero. The
color is going to be
dark gray, which
will implement in the
second. And then the
mass. Let me just
copy this in is going
to be 0.3 30 times
10 to the exponent 24.
If you wanted to be
consistent, we could go
3.3 times 10 to the
exponent 23. That
gives us the same thing.
OK, so let's implement
dark gray now. So let's
go up to colors.
Dark gray is equal to
and then what did I
have dark gray at?
Let me just look here.
This is going to be 80 71.
No, 78 and 81.
Getting a mess with these
colors. If you want,
I'm just picking some
custom ones that look
a little bit nicer.
OK, so now we have
Mercury. So let's put
Mercury in here and we
can just go right on
to Venus, which I
believe is next planet.
So we're going to say
Venus is equal to
planet. It's distance
is going to be 0.7 to
3 times planet.au.
In case you're wondering
planet.au is referencing
this right here, just
because it's inside of
the planet class. OK,
so planet.au, we're going
to have zero. This is
a little bit larger.
So we're going to have a
14. The color of this
will just be a regular
white. And then the mass
is going to be this.
Let me copy it in 4.8685
times 10 to the exponent
of 24. OK, let me zoom
in so you guys can read
that a little bit better.
Let's now put Venus in
the list. And let me go
ahead and run this and
see if we're getting all
of our plants. OK, nice.
So there we go. And I've
just put the plants on
different sides. Again,
you can kind of put put
them wherever you want.
Doesn't really matter.
We could put them all in
the same side and have
them move at the same time.
I'm just staggering them a
bit. Maybe some of you
will have issue with that
based on your physics
knowledge. This is what
we're going to do for
right now. OK, there we
go. We have all of our
plants. So now that we
have all of our planets,
the next thing we need to
do is start moving them.
Now, moving them is
complicated. But again,
as I mentioned, we're
going to be moving them
by their X velocity and
their Y velocity. But we
need to determine what
those velocities are.
And those velocities are
determined by the force
of attraction. So
essentially the force of
gravity between the
different planets. All
right. So I'm going to
start explaining the math
that's going to go on here
to actually move the
planets around the sun.
And before I can do that,
I just want to give you a
general understanding of
gravity and how planets
actually orbit around the
sun, in case you're
unfamiliar. So the reason
why when we jump up, we
fall down. And when we
throw a ball up, it comes
down is because of gravity.
Now, we all know gravity,
but gravity is relative
to different objects. OK.
So all objects are
actually attracting one
another. And the force of
attraction that they have
on one another is based
on the mass of those
objects. Now, this only
really becomes relevant
when you have very, very
massive objects like
planets. So when we're
talking about something
like Earth, this a massive
body, right? Is something
like, you know, six to six
multiplied by 10 to the
exponent, 24 kilograms
or whatever the number is.
It's a very, very massive
body. So relative to our
mass, which is maybe 60
kilograms, 70 kilograms,
80 kilograms, whatever it
is, it's way, way larger.
So it actually exerts a
massive force on us that
pulls us downwards
towards the earth. Now,
what actually determines
the strength of this force
is the distance from us
to the center of the earth.
Hence why when you go up
in space, you have zero
gravity because you're
much further away from
the earth. Now, all objects
again, exert forces on
each other. And those
forces depend on the two
masses of the objects, as
well as the distance of
the objects. But if you're
just naively looking at
this equation here, which
is actually the force of
attraction, you'll see
that the distance between
the center of the two
objects is the most
important when it comes
to what type of the force,
what type of force you're
going to get, because it's
R squared. So the further
away you go, exponentially,
the less gravity you're
going to have the closer
you get exponentially,
the more gravity you're
going to get. Now, again,
I'm not a physics major,
so take everything with a
grain of salt here.
That's the basic
understanding of gravity.
Now, when we're talking
about planets, we're
talking about multiple
massive objects that
are moving around each
other. So when we talk
about an object like
earth here, right? The
earth is moving at a
constant velocity. Well,
not necessarily constant,
but it's moving at a
relatively constant
velocity around the sun.
Now, what forces it to
move around the sun is
gravity. So the earth is
already on a trajectory
moving in the x direction.
OK, so it has some speed
going in the x direction.
And then there is a force
pulling it towards the sun.
That force is gravity or
the attraction between
the earth and the sun.
Now, the reason why
there's an attraction is
because the sun is much,
much larger than the earth.
If the earth was larger
than the sun, then the
sun would be orbiting
around it. Great example.
If you think of the moon,
right, the moon is much
smaller than the earth.
It's very close to the
earth. And so it orbits
around the earth.
OK, hopefully this is
making a little bit of
sense. But the idea is
that you have some force
and that force,
essentially, is causing
the earth to move around
the sun. And the reason
why the earth doesn't just
shoot directly towards
the sun, like we shoot
directly down on earth
when we jump up is
because it already has
momentum moving in
another direction.
And so there's multiple
forces affecting it,
causing it to go in an
orbit. Again, very
simplified explanation
of what's going on.
But hopefully that makes
a bit of sense. Now, the
reason I'm saying this
is because we have
multiple planets that
are orbiting around
the earth, right?
Maybe we have another
planet. I know I
probably shouldn't have
drawn it in blue.
But the point is there's
a distance between
these two planets, and
they also have a force
of attraction on each
other. And that's why
you're going to have
different orbits and
different speeds based
on the location of
other planets and kind
of their orbital
trajectory. So if you
have two planets here,
as well as a planet
here, well, this guy's
still orbiting around
the sun, because the
sun is much larger
than him, but he's going
to be orbiting slower
than the earth is
because he's not as
close. However, the
earth is going to be
attracting or having
some force of
attraction on this
planet, and this
planet is going to have
some force of attraction
on the earth. And so
you need to take that
into account when
you're actually
calculating the
different orbits of
the planets. All right.
I know this is a lot.
Very, very math and
physics has heavy here,
but the idea is every
single object exhibits
some force on each
other. And we need to
calculate what all of
those forces are when
we are actually
determining the orbit
so that we are going
to be orbiting
appropriate to where
the other planets are.
So we can't just
calculate the force
to the sun. We need to
also calculate the
force to the other
planets, and that's
going to give us a
somewhat elliptical
orbit as well. OK.
Hopefully this makes a
little bit of sense.
Now let's talk about
how we actually do
this. So as I kind
of already hinted at,
if you look to the
left of my screen,
you can see that I
have the equation here
for the force of
attraction between
two objects. Now, this
force is the
straight line force
between two objects.
So let me just move
the earth a bit here.
So I can explain kind
of what I mean by that
and why we need to do
a little bit of
trigonometry. So let's
say we have the earth
over here. This will
say is the force of
gravity or the force
of attraction between
the two objects. Now
to calculate this is
fairly simple. We just
need to first calculate
the distance between
the two objects, which
we can do. We then
need to know the masses,
which we already know
and the gravitational
constant, which we know
as well. So let's say
we know the force.
Well, if we know the
force, the issue is
it's giving us the
straight line force.
We want to break this
force into two
components so that we
are able to move the
earth in an X direction,
as well as a Y direction.
So we need to kind of
understand this, that
it's giving us the
straight line force.
We need to break that
force into X and Y
components so we can
actually move the earth
around the sun in both
the X and the Y
direction. Now, this is
the same way that we're
going to calculate the
distance. It's very
easy for us to actually
find the distance
because we're looking
for. Let me just
redraw all of this,
this right here. So
this is going to be
R. We don't know what
R is, but we know what
the Y distances and
the X distance distances
between these two points
because for both these
points, we have an X and
a Y, right? So we have
like X two and Y two.
So if we know both of
those points, we can
calculate the difference
in X and the difference
in Y. And then to
figure out what R is
relative to our right
triangle here, what
equation do we use?
Well, Pythagorean
theorem. I know I
completely butchered
that that name, but
it's going to be X squared
plus Y squared. Take the
root of that and that's
going to give us R. OK,
so we are able to
calculate R. Then
obviously we can take
the square. So once we
do that, we calculate
the distance, then
we're going to calculate
the force and then we
need to go in the
opposite direction
from the force back
to the X and Y components.
OK, so let's redraw this.
So now let's say we know
the force. OK. And again,
we need to split this
into X and Y. So we
need to have, I guess,
F X and F Y. Now, the
way that we do this is
we need to calculate
the angle here, because
if we have any two
aspects of a triangle,
so if we have one
side length and an
angle and it's a right
angle triangle, we can
calculate any other
angle or any other
side length, right?
That's just a property
of a right triangle.
So we know F and we
should know this angle.
And the reason we know
this angle is because
we know X and we know
why. So the way we
calculate this angle is
we take the arc tangent,
so the tan inverse of
Y over X. Now, to
derive why this is
going to give us the
angle, theta, let's
look at the equation
of tan of theta is
equal to. And then
this is going to be
the opposite over the
adjacent. Now, I like
to remember this as
Toa. OK, but this is
the equation. You know,
this is a property of a
right triangle. So if I
have tan theta is equal
to the opposite over
the adjacent, and
we're talking about
this right here, the
opposite side length is
why the adjacent side
length is X. And so we
can kind of sub those
values in, right? And we
get Y and X. If we want
to isolate for theta, we
need to take the inverse
tangent. So that's what
we do. We take tan inverse
of Y over X. That gives
us theta. OK, so now
that we know theta, we
can now use theta to
calculate what the F force
component is or the X
force component is as
well as the Y force
component. So to do
that, we need to use
some other properties.
So we have a property.
It is so let me write
this property. So
katoa, this is the way
that I always remember
these, but we can say
that the sign of theta
is equal to the
opposite over the
hypotenuse. And since
we're looking for the
opposite, which is F Y,
we can say sign of the
angle theta, which we
know is equal to the F
of Y over H. H is F.
We know F and we're
able to find what F of
Y is by just isolating
for F of Y. So multiplying
F by sine theta. And
then same thing. If we
want to find what F X
is, we can say F X is
equal to this is going
to be the coast of theta
multiplied by F. That
will give us the F X
component. And then once
we know the X and Y
velocity, we can very
easily move this around
the sun. All right.
Math lesson is now
over. Hopefully I
didn't confuse you too
badly. Again, I'm trying
to squeeze in what is
probably taught an entire
year of grade 12 physics
in about 10 minutes. But
that is the math that
we need to understand to
be able to move these
objects around. Can't
really make it much
simpler than that. If
you don't understand
basic trigonometry,
then I'm sure this was
a lot, but you can
kind of just trust the
properties that I showed
you here and I will
show you how to
implement them in code.
You don't understand
totally fine. You can
still follow along and
you will have a working
simulation. With that
said, let's go back to
the code. All right. So
I'm back in the code and
it is time to do some
math inside of code. Now
I know we just did a
lot of math, but now
we're doing it in code.
Hopefully that gave
you an explanation of
what I'm about to write
here. So I'm on my
planet class and I'm
going to write a
method that will
calculate the force of
attraction between
another object and the
current object. Okay.
So I'm going to say
define attraction like
that. I'm going to
take in self and I'm
going to take in an
other object. Now the
other is going to be
another planet. Okay.
So the first thing I'm
going to do is say that
my other underscore X
other underscore Y is
equal to other dot X
and other dot Y. Okay.
Now, the first thing we
need to do here is we
need to calculate the
distance between the
current object and the
other object. So let's
do that. We're going to
say the distance in X
is equal to, and this is
going to be the other
X minus the self dot X.
Okay. And then the
distance in Y is going
to be equal to the
other Y minus the
self dot Y. Now it
doesn't matter if you
take the self dot X and
subtract it from other
dot X. It doesn't matter
what way you do it. It's
going to give us the
the magnitude, which is
what we, which is what
we want. Sorry, because
once we take the square
of both these values,
we're going to get a
positive value, no
matter what. So I have
the distance X and the
distance Y. Now I'm
going to say distance is
equal to, and this is
going to be the math dot
sqrt of the distance X
to the exponent to plus
the distance Y to the
exponent to. Okay. Let
me just check and make
sure I haven't messed
this up yet. Looks
good. We have found the
distance. Okay. Now the
first thing I'm going to
do is I'm going to say
if the other dot sun,
then I'm going to say
the self dot distance to
sun is equal to distance.
Now the reason I'm doing
this is because if the
other object that we're
calculating the force of
attraction with is the
sun, I just calculated
the distance to the sun.
And I just want to
update the distance to
sun property here so that
I can use that when I
actually want to draw
the distance to the sun
on top of the plan. Again,
we're just checking is
the other object, the
sun. If it is, okay, we
know the distance. So
let's just plug that in
and save that value
inside of the class. That
way we're not
recalculating it later
on. We already have the
value. Okay. So now that
we've done that, we need
to calculate the force
of attraction. So we're
going to say the force.
Yeah. I think it's force
is going to be equal to
self dot G. We're going
to multiply this by
our self dot mass
multiplied by the other
dot mass. And then we're
going to divide this by
the distance to the
exponent to why did I
write it like that? It's
going to be distance to
the exponent to. And I
think that's good. Okay.
Now we don't need to do
any parentheses because
these have the same order
of operations and
exponent to the exponent
to is going to happen
first anyways. Okay. So
this is how we calculate
the force. Now remember,
this is the straight line
force. We need to break
this force down into the
X and to the Y component,
which is why we had to do
all of that trigonometry.
So now we need to
calculate the angle theta.
So we're going to say
theta is equal to, and
then this is going to be
the math dot arc tangent
of, and it's actually
going to be here at the
distance Y over the
distance X. Now, the
reason I'm doing a 10 to
is because this is a
special function in
Python that's going to
take the Y over the X
and then give us the
angle associated with it.
So make sure you use a 10
to from the math library.
If you just use a 10,
that's not going to work.
You need a 10 to. Okay.
So math dot eight and
distance X, distance Y.
Now we know the angle theta.
Now that we know the angle
theta, we can calculate
the X velocity and the Y
velocity. So we're going to
say or sorry, not the X
velocity, we're going to
calculate the X force and
the Y force. So we're
going to say the force X
is equal to this is going
to be math dot cosine
of theta multiplied
by the force.
OK, and then the force
underscore Y is going to
be equal to the math dot
sign of the theta.
Multiplied by the force.
OK, and then we're going to
return from here the force
X and the force Y.
OK, let's break down what we
did here. I understand this
is probably a little bit
confusing still.
We first calculate the
distance between the two
objects. There we go.
We have distance.
Great. Then what we're
going to do is determine
if the other object is the
sun. If it is, we're just
going to store that
distance in a property
here, because we want to
know what that value is.
Now, after that, we want
to calculate the force of
attraction. So this is
the force of attraction
here. It's F equals M,
lowercase M over
R squared multiplied by
the gravitational constant
G. OK, so that's what
we're doing. So self that
G times mass multiplied
by other mass over
distance squared.
OK, then we want to
break this distance down
into the two components.
So the sorry, the force
into the X force and the
Y force. So we first need
to calculate the angle.
So we say the math, the
arc tangent to of the
distance Y over distance
X gives us the angle
that we want. Then we're
going to say the force X
is equal to the math
dot cosine of theta
multiplied by force and
the force Y is equal to
the math dot sine theta
multiplied by the force.
Now, remember here that
all of these distances
and all of these forces
are real distances and
forces. These are
actually the distances
and the forces that you
would see. I mean, it's
an approximation in the
real solar system. So I'm
not using really small
pixel values in pi game.
I'm using massive, you
know, meter per squared
kilogram squared values,
whatever the units are
of these forces, I'm
actually using the
correct numbers, like
the large two scale
numbers. I just want to
make that clear here
because like if we were
to print out what X
were and print out what
the force were, you
would see really, really
massive numbers
because that's actually
what they are in the real
world because we're trying
to do a simulation here.
Okay. Anyway, so we have
attraction. Now that we
have the force of
attraction, what we need
to do is actually update
the position of each
planet based on the
force of attraction
between every single
other planet, because
we can't just do it from
the sun. We need to look
at all the other planets
as I was discussing kind
of in the whiteboard
section. So what I'm
going to do is make a
method here. I'm going
to say update position.
And this is going to take
in self and planets.
Okay. So what we're
going to do is loop
through all of the
planets. We're going to
calculate the force of
attraction between the
current planet and all
of the other planets.
We're then going to
calculate what the
velocity needs to be
for these planets. Then
we're going to move them
by that velocity. So
we're going to say the
total force in the X
direction is equal to
the total force in the
Y direction, which is
currently equal to zero.
And we're going to sum
all of the forces
together from all of the
planets. So we're going
to say for planet in
planets, we're going to
pass a list of plants
here. That's what we're
taking in. We're going to
say if self is equal to
planet, then continue
because we don't want to
calculate the force with
ourself. In fact, that
would just give us a zero
division error because
the distance between
ourself and ourself is
zero, right? So we can't
do this division with
the arch tangent or
sorry, with the distance
squared, that would give
us an issue. Anyways,
continuing. Now what
we're going to do is say
that the force X force Y
is equal to, and this is
going to be the self
dot attraction to
this plant. Okay. So
again, for every single
planet, we're going to
calculate the force X and
the force Y that's
exerting on this planet.
We're going to say self
dot attraction is equal
to planet. That's what's
doing the calculation
here that gives us the FX
and FY. Now we're just
going to sum these two
variables or add to
these two variables. So
self that X FX plus
equals FX and total FY
plus equals FY. Okay.
So now that we know what
the total forces that's
being exerted on us and
the X and the Y direction,
we need to use these
forces to actually
calculate with the
velocity of the planet's
going to be. All right.
So the way we calculate
the velocity here is
we're going to say that
the self dot X underscore
Vell is equal to the
total FX divided by
the self dot mass
multiplied by the self
dots. And then this is
going to be time step.
Now, I'm going to explain
how this works, but this
is using kind of the
famous equation F equals
M a case. We have this
equation F equals M a
and this stands for the
total force is equal to
the mass divided by
the acceleration. Now
you can use this to
solve for the acceleration,
which is what we're doing
here. So we're saying
the acceleration is equal
to F over M. So I'm taking
my total FX and my total
mass, right? And I'm
dividing those to get
the acceleration. Now,
the thing is I'm going to
be adding to this. I'm
saying self that XL plus
equals. So the way this
works is I'm increasing
my velocity by my
acceleration multiplied
by the time step. Now,
there's another equation
that has to do with time
and acceleration to
equal velocity and all
those kinds of things.
Anyways, the point is
though, since we're
simulating this over a
period of time, we're
going to take the time
step, which is right
here, which is one day
we're going to multiply
that by whatever the
acceleration is. Now,
we're going to take that
value and add that to
the current velocity. Now,
why this is going to
give us a perfect
elliptical is because as
soon as we start going
to the left or to the
right of the planet and
the distances and the
angles change, our force
is going to be either
negative or positive,
saying that we're going
kind of right or we're
going left or we're
going up or we're going
down. So by doing a
total summation of all
of these forces, what
ends up happening is we
go in a complete circle
because by the time we
get to a certain point in
the orbit, the velocity
is going to be changing
and either getting more
positive or more negative,
moving us to the left
or to the right. Hopefully
that makes a tiny bit of
sense. But the point is
we're going to constantly
add this and you'll
notice that we're not
going to go faster.
We're just going to
change in directions
because what's going to
happen is X velocity is
going to be decreasing
while the Y velocity is
increasing when we're at
a certain point in the
circle. And then that's
going to continually
change and change
directions as we move
around. So you'll see
when we start running
this, but that's how
this works. Now we do the
exact same thing with the
Y. So plus equals the
total F Y over the
self dot mass can then
multiplied by the self
dot timestamp. OK, so
now that we have that,
what we need to do is
just increment the X and
the Y because this is
just the velocity. So
from acceleration, you
get velocity from
velocity, you get
displacement or distance,
which is what we're now
going to do. So we're
going to say self dot X.
And then this is going to
be plus equals self dot
X underscore Vell. And
then we need to multiply
this by the time step as
well. And then we're going
to say self dots Y plus
equals. This needs to be
self dot Y Vell multiplied
by self dot timestamp. And
then let's fix this to be
self dot X. Well, OK, and
then lastly here, we can
actually say the self
dot orbit and then dot
append. And I'm going to
append just a tuple
here, which is going to
be self dot X, self
dot Y. And yeah, I think
that's actually good for
the orbit. OK, so let me
break this down one more
time. What we're doing is
we're getting the total
forces exerted on this
planet from all other
plants that are not
itself. We are then
going to figure out with
the X and the Y velocity
is using the equations I
describe. Then we are
going to update the X and
Y position by using the
velocity. We need to
multiply by the time step
to make sure we're moving
in the accurate amount of
time here. OK. And then
we have self that orbit
dot append and we're
appending the X and Y
position that we're
currently at so that now
we can draw the orbit
forward this planet,
which I'm going to do in
a second. OK, so there
we go. We actually have
all of the hard stuff
done. Now we just need
to call the update
position method here on
all of our planets. And
you'll see that they'll
start moving around the
screen. So I'm going to
go to right before planet
dot draw. And I'm going
to say planet dot. And
then this is going to be
update position. And I'm
just going to pass to it
planets. OK. And that's
actually all we need to
start moving the planet.
And let's just run this
now and see if it works.
OK, so let's see. And we
can see that our planets
are moving, but we're
getting a bit of an
issue. And I'm going to
explain why that happens.
So first of all, the
reason why we were seeing
our planets like thousands
of times on the screen is
because we need to
refresh the screen by
kind of redrawing a
background on top of it
before we draw everything
again. So what's
happening right now is
we're continually
drawing the planets,
we're not drawing
anything on top of the
old planets. And so we
keep seeing the old
planets. So all I need to
do here, say wind up
fill. And I'm just going
to put inside of here
zero, zero, zero, which
is just the color black.
And now if I run this,
you're going to see that
the planets just zoom
towards the sun. Now,
the reason they're
zooming towards the sun
is because they don't
have a velocity in the
Y or sorry, in the X is
the X. No, it's in the
Y direction. So
currently, right? If
again, if I run this,
you see that they just
zoom right towards the
sun and then keep going.
The reason they're
doing that is because
we don't have another
velocity. And that's
what would happen if
they weren't already
moving in another
direction. So we need to
apply an existing
velocity in the Y
direction to these
planets so that they
will be moving around
the sun, so that the
force attracted them to
the sun causes this
kind of centripetal
motion or the circular
motion around the plant.
I know this is like
there's a lot of physics
that I wasn't actually
can considering how many
physics I would need to
explain here. But the
idea is for all of these
planets, they need some
starting velocity in the
Y direction. Otherwise,
the only force being
applied is directly X
because of kind of where
the planets are placed
and the fact that we're
just going straight down
towards the sun. That's
the only force being
applied currently,
because we don't have
another velocity. So
let's apply the other
velocities. I'm just
going to copy them in
from my other screen. So
this is the earth
velocity. I'll pause so
we can read them all in
a second. This is the
Mars velocity. This is
the mercury velocity.
And then this is the
Venus velocity. OK, so
the earth Y velocity is
twenty nine point seven
eight three. This is
kilometers per second
multiplied by a thousand,
which gives us meters
per second, because
that's what we're using.
Excuse me. The Mars
velocity, twenty four
point zero seven seven
multiplied by a thousand
again, this meters per
second. So kilometers,
then we convert to meters
forty seven point four
for mercury and then
negative thirty five
point oh two times a
thousand for Venus. Now
you'll notice that for
some of these, we have
positive and negative
or not positive, not
negative, right? Like we
have a negative plant, A
U moving us to the left
and then we have a
positive Y velocity.
Then for this one,
right, we have a
negative and positive.
And then here we have a
positive and this
actually needs to be
negative to make sure
that it's going to be
moving in the correct
direction. So if you
have one, this positive,
the other one needs to be
negative so that they're
all moving in the same
direction vice versa.
Hopefully that makes
sense, but you'll see
here when this starts
running. OK, so let me
actually just run this
now and we should see
that they orbit. So
let's have a look. OK,
so there we go. Now we
have an orbit. Obviously
doesn't look as cool.
We're not drawing the
orbits, but notice that
they're all moving in
the same direction and
obviously the ones that
are closer to the sun
are moving faster.
Perfect. So the
simulation seems to be
working. OK, so let's
now draw the orbits
around and the way that
we're going to do that
is we're going to use
all of the points that
we're storing in this
orbit list, because
every time that we call
this, we're going to add
a point to the orbit
list and we're going
to draw them. So what
I'm going to do is
add something here and
say four point in self
that orbit and I
actually want to draw
this. Yeah, I'll draw
this before I draw the
circle. I'm going to say
X Y equals point. And
then I'm going to say
X is equal to X
multiplied by self
that scale. And then
this is going to be
plus width over two.
And I'm going to say
Y is equal to Y
multiplied by self
that scale plus height
over two. And then
we are going to
actually store these in
an updated points list.
We're going to say
updated points equal
to this updated points
dot append point. And
then we're going to
draw all these points
as a line. So we're
going to say
pie game dot draw dot
line. And is it lines?
Let me just have a look
here to see actually
exactly what we need to
drew to do. So this is
actually going to be
lines. Sorry, we're
going to pass win. We're
going to pass self dot
color. We're going to
pass false, which means
this is not an
enclosed line. So we're
not going to draw an
ending line, essentially.
And then we're going to
pass the updated points
and we'll pass a
thickness of two. OK, let
me explain what I did.
I understand. I kind of
just went through this
without any explanation.
So what I'm doing is
I'm getting a list of
updated points, which
are going to be all of
the X, Y coordinates to
scale, right? Because I
need to get them to scale.
Otherwise, I can't draw
these properly. So I
take them. I do what I
need to do to get them
to scale exactly what I
did right here. And then
I update, I make a new
list here, updated
points and append, sorry,
not the point, the new
X, Y that I made right
here. OK, then I'm going
to draw lines. Now, what
this does is it takes a
list of points, which is
right here, and it
essentially just draws a
bunch of a bunch of lines
between the different
points, and it doesn't
enclose them because I
passed false. Now, this
is the thickness that I
want to draw the lines,
which is going to be two
pixels. Now, one thing I
do need to do is just
put an if statement here
and say if the length of
self dot points is less
than two, actually less
than or equal to two,
because I believe we need
at least three points,
then I don't want to do
any of this. So we're
going to say actually
the opposite. We're going
to say if, yeah, if the
line of points is
greater than two. So
meaning that it is at
least three, then it
will do this. Just
confusing myself there.
We need at least three
points. So if the line
of points greater than
two, do all of this.
Otherwise, don't do it.
That should give us the
orbit. So let's see now
if we're going to get kind
of the orbital ring
around. Let's run this
and planet object has no
actually points. Sorry,
it's not points. It is
orbit. And I think I did
this right. Self that
orbit. Yes. OK, self
that. Nice. All right.
Let's see. There we go.
Now we get the orbits
being drawn as the
planets are moving around.
Very nice. So I mean, you
can run the simulation as
long as you like and see
everything working. Now
what I want to do is
implement the distance to
the sun, just to show
you that this is not a
perfect circle. It is
actually elliptical. I
know it looks like a
perfect circle, but
since the scale is so, I
guess, small here that
we're drawing this out,
you can't really see the
ellipticalness of the
orbits. OK, so now what
I want to do is also
draw that distance on
top. So to do that, I
need to initialize a
font in Pygame. So I'm
just going to say font
is equal to Pygame dot
font dot S Y S font like
that. And I'm going to
pass inside of here,
comic sans as my font.
And for the font size,
we'll just go with
something like 16. So
this is the font you
want. And this is the
size. That's how you
initialize the font. And
then what I need to do if
I want to draw the
distance is I need to
say, first of all, if
not self dot sun and
forgot working in Python.
So let's use the actual
not because I don't want
to draw the distance
between the sun and the
sun, which is always
going to be zero. So I'm
going to say if not self
dot sun, then we'll say
distance underscore text
is equal to font dot
render. This is how you
actually create a text
object that you can draw.
I'm going to say font
render and do an F
string. And this is
simply going to be the
self dot distance to
the sun. And then this is
going to be in meters. So
what I can do is I can
divide this value by
1000 if I want to get
kilometers to make it a
little bit smaller. So
let's do that divide by
1000 in kilometers. I'm
also just going to round
this just so that we
don't get a massive
number here. So let's
just round this to one
decimal point, put that
in kilometers. And then
we want anti aliasing one,
which is the next
argument. And then the
last argument, I believe
is the color that I want
to draw this in, which we
can just make, I guess
it shouldn't be self
color. We'll do white.
OK, perfect. So that is
now the text object
created. Again, you have
to use a font object to
create a text object,
which then you can
render on the screen. Now
I want to draw it on the
screen. So I'm going to
say win dot bullet. I'm
going to pass the
distance text. And then
the position that I want
to draw this at is a
little bit complicated.
And also, guys, sorry, I
just realized I made a
little bit of a mistake
here. Actually, no,
maybe this is OK the way
it is. When I define X,
Y inside the for loop,
this might be
interfering with this,
although it didn't seem
like it was. So I guess
we can just proceed, but
I don't like having these
names shadow each other.
OK, we'll just proceed
for now, but that's kind
of what I was realizing
and why I pause there.
Anyways, what I'm going to
do is draw this at X, Y,
and we're referencing
this X, Y here, which is
going to be the center of
the circle. Now, the
issue is if I draw this
at the center of the
circle, since I start
drawing the text from
the top left hand corner,
you'll see actually, let
me just run the code
and you'll see what
happens here when I do
this. So you'll notice
that the actual text is
kind of at the bottom
right of the center.
Now, that looks really
ugly. Obviously don't
want that to be there.
So what I'm going to do
instead is I'm going to
make it so it's drawn
directly in the center.
Now, do that. I take the
X and need to subtract
this from the distance
underscore text dot get
underscore width divided
by two. So if I take the
width of the text and
divide that by two and
then subtract that from
the X that shifts me to
the left, some exactly
in the middle. And then
the same thing with the
Y. So why is distance
text dot get underscore
height over two? Okay.
Nice. Hopefully that is
all clear. Now, I'm
just going to take all
of this and we're going
to put this below when
we're drawing the circle
so that it gets drawn on
top and we don't have
any overlap or we don't
have the circle kind of
overlapping the text.
OK, so let's close that.
You guys can pause the
video if you want to
have a look at this.
Let's run the code,
though, and let's see
what we get. Nice. OK,
so now we actually have
the text being drawn on
top. And for some of
the planets, given it
is a bit hard to see,
but that is all working.
Nice. So with that said,
I think I'm going to end
this tutorial here.
This was a lot of stuff
to go through. I hope
you guys appreciated
this and all of the math
and explanations.
If you did, please make
sure you leave a like.
Obviously, you can
extend this as much as
you would like. You can
mess around with the scale.
You can mess around with
the speed. You can
change the time step.
This is a really, really
flexible program.
And all of the hard
physics and math is done.
So if you want to add
more planets, you can
really easily do that.
This is a realistic
simulation, something
I haven't done on the
channel before and that
I hope you guys
appreciate. All right.
With that said, I am going
to end the video again.
Please like the video,
subscribe to the channel
and I will see you in
another one.