Good afternoon everyone and welcome to MIT Success 191.
My name is Alexander Amini and I'll be one of your instructors for the course this year
along with Ava.
And together we're really excited to welcome you to this really incredible course.
This is a very fast paced and very intense one week that we're about to go through together.
So we're going to cover the foundations of a also very fast paced moving field and a
field that has been rapidly changing over the past eight years that we have taught this
course at MIT.
Now over the past decade in fact, even before we started teaching this course, AI and deep
learning has really been revolutionizing so many different advances and so many different
areas of science, mathematics, physics and so on.
And not that long ago, we were having challenges and problems that we did not think were necessarily
solvable in our lifetimes that AI is now actually solving beyond human performance today.
And each year that we teach this course, this lecture in particular is getting harder
and harder to teach because for an introductory level course, this lecture, lecture number
one, is the lecture that's supposed to cover the foundations and if you think to any other
introductory course like an introductory course 101 on mathematics or biology, those
lecture ones don't really change that much over time.
So we're in a rapidly changing field of AI and deep learning where even these types
of lectures are rapidly changing.
So let me give you an example of how we introduced this course only a few years ago.
Hi everybody and welcome to MIT 6S191, the official introductory course on deep learning
taught here at MIT.
Deep learning is revolutionizing so many fields from robotics to medicine and everything
in between.
You'll learn the fundamentals of this field and how you can build some of these incredible
algorithms.
In fact, this entire speech and video are not real and were created using deep learning
and artificial intelligence.
And in this class, you'll learn how.
It has been an honor to speak with you today and I hope you enjoy the course.
The really surprising thing about that video to me when we first did it was how viral it
went a few years ago.
So just in a couple months about teaching this course a few years ago, that video went
very viral, it got over a million views within only a few months.
People were shocked with a few things but the main one was the realism of AI to be able
to generate content that looks and sounds extremely hyper realistic.
And when we did this video, when we created this for the class only a few years ago, this
video took us about $10,000 in compute to generate just about a minute long video.
If you think about it, I would say it's extremely expensive to compute something what we look
at like that and maybe a lot of you are not really impressed by the technology today because
you see all of the amazing things that AI and deep learning are producing.
Now fast forward today, the progress in deep learning and people were making all kinds
of exciting remarks about it when it came out a few years ago.
Now this is common stuff because AI is really doing much more powerful things than this
fun little introductory video.
So today fast forward four years, about four years to today.
Now where are we?
AI is now generating content with deep learning being so commoditized.
Deep learning is in all of our fingertips now online in our smartphones and so on.
In fact, we can use deep learning to generate these types of hyper realistic pieces of media
and content entirely from English language without even coding anymore.
So before we had to actually go and train these models and really code them to be able
to create that one minute long video.
Today we have models that will do that for us end to end directly from English language.
So we can prompt these models to create something that the world has never seen before.
A photo of an astronaut riding a horse and these models can imagine those pieces of content
entirely from scratch.
My personal favorite is actually how we can now ask these deep learning models to create
new types of software even themselves being software to ask them to create.
For example, to write this piece of TensorFlow code to train a neural network, right?
We're asking a neural network to write TensorFlow code to train another neural network and our
model can produce examples of functional and usable pieces of code that satisfy this
English prompt while walking through each part of the code independently.
So not even just producing it but actually educating and teaching the user on what each
part of these code blocks are actually doing.
You can see an example here.
And really what I'm trying to show you with all of this is that this is just highlighting
how far deep learning has gone even in a couple years since we've started teaching this course.
I mean going back even from before that to eight years ago.
And the most amazing thing that you'll see in this course in my opinion is that what
we try to do here is to teach you the foundations of all of this, how all of these different
types of models are created from the ground up and how we can make all of these amazing
advances possible so that you can also do it on your own as well.
And like I mentioned in the beginning, this introduction course is getting harder and
harder to do and to make every year.
I don't know where the field is going to be next year and I mean that's my honest truth
or even honestly in even one or two months time from now just because it's moving so
incredibly fast.
But what I do know is that what we will share with you in the course as part of this one
week is going to be the foundations of all of the technologies that we have seen up until
this point that will allow you to create that future for yourselves and to design brand new
types of deep learning models using those fundamentals and those foundations.
So let's get started with all of that and start to figure out how we can actually achieve
all of these different pieces and learn all of these different components.
And we should start this by really tackling the foundations from the very beginning and
asking ourselves, you know, we've heard this term, I think all of you obviously before
you've come to this class today, you've heard the term deep learning, but it's important
for you to really understand how this concept of deep learning relates to all of the other
pieces of science that you've learned about so far.
So to do that, we have to start from the very beginning and start by thinking about what
is intelligence at its core, not even artificial intelligence, but just intelligence, right?
So the way I like to think about this is that I like to think that intelligence is the ability
to process information which will inform your future decision making abilities.
Now that's something that we as humans do every single day.
Now artificial intelligence is simply the ability for us to give computers that same
ability to process information and inform future decisions.
Now machine learning is simply a subset of artificial intelligence.
The way you should think of machine learning is just as the programming ability or let's
say even simpler than that, machine learning is the science of trying to teach computers
how to do that processing of information and decision making from data.
So instead of hard coding some of these rules into machines and programming them like we
used to do in software engineering classes, now we're going to try and do that processing
of information and informing a future decision making abilities directly from data.
And then going one step deeper, deep learning is simply the subset of machine learning which
uses neural networks to do that.
It uses neural networks to process raw pieces of data, now unprocessed data, and allows
them to ingest all of those very large data sets and inform future decisions.
Now that's exactly what this class is really all about.
If you think of, if I had to summarize this class in just one line, it's all about teaching
machines how to process data, process information, and inform decision making abilities from
that data and learn it from that data.
Now this program is split between really two different parts.
So you should think of this class as being captured with both technical lectures, which
for example this is one part of, as well as software labs.
We'll have several new updates this year as I mentioned earlier just covering the rapid
changing of advances in AI and especially in some of the later lectures you're going
to see those.
The first lecture today is going to cover the foundations of neural networks themselves,
starting with really the building blocks of every single neural network which is called
the Perceptron.
And finally we'll go through the week and we'll conclude with a series of exciting
guest lectures from industry leading sponsors of the course.
And finally on the software side, after every lecture you'll also get software experience
and project building experience to be able to take what we teach in lectures and actually
deploy them in real code and actually produce based on the learnings that you find in this
lecture and at the very end of the class from the software side you'll have the ability
to participate in a really fun day at the very end which is the project pitch competition.
It's kind of like a shark tank style competition of all of the different projects from all
of you and win some really awesome prizes.
So let's step through that a little bit briefly, this is the syllabus part of the lecture.
So each day we'll have dedicated software labs that will basically mirror all of the
technical lectures that we go through just helping you reinforce your learnings and these
are coupled with each day again coupled with prizes for the top performing software solutions
that are come up in the class.
This is going to start with today with lab one and it's going to be on music generation
so you're going to learn how to build a neural network that can learn from a bunch of musical
songs, listen to them and then learn to compose brand new songs in that same genre.
Tomorrow lab two on computer vision you're going to learn about facial detection systems,
you'll build a facial detection system from scratch using convolutional neural networks,
you'll learn what that means tomorrow and you'll also learn how to actually de-bias,
remove the biases that exist in some of these facial detection systems which is a huge problem
for the state of the art solutions that exist today.
And finally a brand new lab at the end of the course will focus on large language models
where you're actually going to take a billion multi-billion parameter large language model
and fine tune it to build an assistive chatbot and evaluate a set of cognitive abilities
ranging from mathematics abilities to scientific reasoning to logical abilities and so on.
And finally at the very very end there will be a final project pitch competition for up
to five minutes per team and all of these are accompanied with great prizes so definitely
there will be a lot of fun to be had throughout the week.
There are many resources to help with this class, you'll see them posted here you don't
need to write them down because all of the slides are already posted online.
Please post to Piazza if you have any questions and of course we have an amazing team that
is helping teach this course this year and you can reach out to any of us if you have
any questions.
The Piazza is a great place to start.
Myself and Ava will be the two main lectures for this course Monday through Wednesday especially
and we'll also be hearing some amazing guest lectures on the second half of the course
which definitely you would want to attend because they really cover the really state
of the art sides of deep learning that's going on in industry outside of academia.
And very briefly just want to give a huge thanks to all of our sponsors who without
their support this course like every year would not be possible.
Okay so now let's start with the fun stuff and my favorite part of the course which is
the technical parts and let's start by just asking ourselves a question right which is
you know why do we care about all of this?
Why do we care about deep learning?
Why did you all come here today to learn and to listen to this course?
So to understand I think we again need to go back a little bit to understand how machine
learning used to be performed right so machine learning typically would define a set of features
or you can think of these as kind of a set of things to look for in an image or in a
piece of data.
Actually these are hand engineered so humans would have to define these themselves and
the problem with these is that they tend to be very brittle in practice just by nature
of a human defining them.
So the key idea of deep learning and what you're going to learn throughout this entire
week is this paradigm shift of trying to move away from hand engineering features and rules
that computers should look for and instead trying to learn them directly from raw pieces
of data.
What are the patterns that we need to look at in data sets such that if we look at those
patterns we can make some interesting decisions and interesting actions can come out.
So for example if we wanted to learn how to detect faces we might if you think even how
you would detect faces right if you look at a picture what are you looking for to detect
a face?
You're looking for some particular patterns you're looking for eyes and noses and ears
and when those things are all composed in a certain way you would probably deduce that
that's a face right computers do something very similar so they have to understand what
are the patterns that they look for what are the eyes and noses and ears of those pieces
of data and then from there actually detect and predict from them.
So the really interesting thing I think about deep learning is that these foundations for
doing exactly what I just mentioned picking out the building blocks picking out the features
from raw pieces of data and the underlying algorithms themselves have existed for many
many decades.
Now the question I would ask at this point is so why are we studying this now and why
is all of this really blowing up right now and exploding with so many great advances?
Well for one there's three things right number one is that the data that is available to
us today is significantly more pervasive these models are hungry for data you're going to
learn about this more in detail but these models are extremely hungry for data and we're
living in a world right now quite frankly where data is more abundant than it has ever
been in our history.
Now secondly these algorithms are massively compute hungry and they're massively parallelizable
which means that they have greatly benefited from compute hardware which is also capable
of being parallelized the particular name of that hardware it's called a GPU right GPUs
can run parallel processing streams of information and are particularly amenable to deep learning
algorithms and the abundance of GPUs and that compute hardware has also pushed forward what
we can do in deep learning and finally the last piece is the software right it's the
open source tools that are really used as the foundational building blocks of deploying
and building all of these underlying models that you're going to learn about in this course
and those open source tools have just become extremely streamlined making this extremely
easy for all of us to learn about these technologies within an amazing one week course like this.
So let's start now with understanding now that we have some of the background let's
start with understanding exactly what is the fundamental building block of a neural
network now that building block is called a perceptron right every single percept every
single neural network is built up of multiple perceptrons and you're going to learn how
those perceptrons number one compute information themselves and how they connect to these much
larger billion parameter neural networks.
So the key idea of a perceptron or even simpler think of this as a single neuron right so
a neural network is composed of many many neurons and a perceptron is just one neuron.
So that idea of a perceptron is actually extremely simple and I hope that by the end of today
this idea and this processing of a perceptron becomes extremely clear to you.
So let's start by talking about just the forward propagation of information through a single
neuron now single neurons ingest information they can actually ingest multiple pieces of
information so here you can see this neuron taking as input three pieces of information
x1 x2 and xm right so we define the set of inputs called x1 through m and each of these
inputs each of these numbers is going to be element wise multiplied by a particular weight
so this is going to be denoted here by w1 through wm so this is a corresponding weight
for every single input and you should think of this as really you know every weight being
assigned to that input right the weights are part of the neuron itself now you multiply
all of these inputs with their weights together and then you add them up we take this single
number after that addition and you pass it through what's called a nonlinear activation
function to produce your final output which here we're calling y now what I just said
is not entirely correct right so I missed out one critical piece of information that
piece of information is that we also have what you can see here is called this bias
term that bias term is actually what allows your neural neuron to shift its activation
function horizontally on that x axis if you think of it right so on the right side you
can now see this diagram illustrating mathematically that single equation that I talked through
kind of conceptually right now you can see it mathematically written down as one single
equation and we can actually rewrite this using linear algebra using vectors and dot
products so let's do that right so now our inputs are going to be described by a capital
x which is simply a vector of all of our inputs x1 through xm and then our weights are going
to be described by a capital w which is going to be w1 through wm the input is obtained
by taking the dot product of x and w right that dot product does that element wise multiplication
and then adds sums all of the the element wise multiplications and then here's the missing
piece is that we're now going to add that bias term here we're calling the bias term
w zero right and then we're going to apply the nonlinearity which here denoted is z or g excuse
me so I've mentioned this nonlinearity a few times this activation function let's dig into it a
little bit more so we can understand what is actually this activation function doing well I
said a couple things about it I said it's a nonlinear function right here you can see one
example of an activation function one common one commonly used activation function is called
the sigmoid function which you can actually see here on the bottom right hand side of the
screen the sigmoid function is very commonly used because its outputs right so it takes as input
any real number the x-axis is infinite plus or minus but on the y-axis it basically squashes
every input x into a number between 0 and 1 so it's actually a very common choice for things
like probability distributions if you want to convert your answers into probabilities or learn
or teach a neuron to learn a probability distribution but in fact there are actually many
different types of nonlinear activation functions that are used in neural networks and here are
some common ones and and again throughout this presentation you'll see these little
TensorFlow icons actually throughout the entire course you'll see these TensorFlow icons on the
bottom which basically just allow you to relate some of the foundational knowledge that we're
teaching in the lectures to some of the software labs and this might provide a good starting point
for a lot of the pieces that you have to do later on in the software parts of the class so the
sigmoid activation which we talked about in the last slide here it's shown on the left-hand side
right this is very popular because of the probability distributions right it squashes
everything between 0 and 1 but you see two other very common types of activation functions in the
middle and the right-hand side as well so the other very very common one probably this is the one
now that's the most popular activation function is now on the far right-hand side it's called the
relu activation function or also called the rectified linear unit so basically it's linear
everywhere except there's a nonlinearity at x equals 0 so there's a kind of a step or a great
discontinuity right so benefit of this very easy to compute it still has the nonlinearity which
we kind of need and we'll talk about why we need it in one second but it's very fast right just
two linear functions piecewise combined with each other okay so now let's talk about why we need
a nonlinearity in the first place why why not just deal with a linear function that we pass all
of these inputs through so the point of the activation function even at all why do we have
this is to introduce nonlinearities in of itself so what we want to do is to allow our neural
network to deal with nonlinear data right our neural networks need the ability to deal with
nonlinear data because the world is extremely nonlinear right this is important because you
know if you think of the real world real datasets this is just the way they are right if you look
at datasets like this one green and red points right and I ask you to build a neural network
that can separate the green and the red points this means that we actually need a nonlinear
function to do that we cannot solve this problem with a single line right in fact if we used linear
linear functions as your activation function no matter how big your neural network is it's still
a linear function because linear functions combined with linear functions are still linear so
no matter how deep or how many parameters your neural network has the best they would be able
to do to separate these green and red points would look like this but adding nonlinearities
allows our neural networks to be smaller by allowing them to be more expressive and capture
more complexities in the datasets and this allows them to be much more powerful in the end so let's
understand this with a simple example imagine I give you now this trained neural network so what
does it mean trained neural network it means now I'm giving you the weights right not only the
inputs but I'm going to tell you what the weights of this neural network are so here let's say the
bias term w0 is going to be 1 and our w vector is going to be 3 and negative 2 right these are
just the weights of your trained neural network well let's worry about how we got those weights
in a second but this network has two inputs x1 and x2 now if we want to get the output of this
neural network all we have to do simply is to do the same story that we talked about before
right it's dot product inputs with weights add the bias and apply the nonlinearity right and
those are the three components that you really have to remember as part of this class right dot
product add the bias and apply a nonlinearity that's going to be the process that keeps repeating
over and over and over again for every single neuron after that happens that neuron was going
to output a single number right now let's take a look at what's inside of that nonlinearity it's
simply a weighted combination of those of those inputs with those weights right so if we look
at what's inside of g right inside of g is a weighted combination of x and w right added
with a bias right that's going to produce a single number right but in reality for any input that
this model could see what this really is is a two-dimensional line because we have two
parameters in this model so we can actually plot that line we can see exactly how this neuron
separates points on these axes between x1 and x2 right these are the two inputs of this model
we can see exactly and interpret exactly what this neuron is doing right we can visualize
its entire space because we can plot the line that defines this neuron right so here we're
plotting when that line equals zero and in fact if I give you if I give that neuron in fact a
new data point here the new data point is x1 equals negative one and x2 equals two just an
arbitrary point in this two-dimensional space we can plot that point in the two-dimensional space
and depending on which side of the line it falls on it tells us you know what the what the answer
is going to be what the sign of the answer is going to be and also what the answer itself is
going to be right so if we follow that that equation written on the top here and plug in negative
one and two we're going to get one minus three minus four which equals minus six right and when
I put that into my non-linearity g I'm going to get a final output of 0.002 right so that
that don't worry about the final output that's just going to be the output from that sigmoid
function but the important point to remember here is that the sigmoid function actually divides
the space into these two parts right it squashes everything between zero and one but it defines
it implicitly by everything less than 0.5 and greater than 0.5 depending on if it's on if x is
less than zero or greater than zero so depending on which side of the line that you fall on remember
the line is when x equals zero the input to the sigmoid is zero if you fall on the left side of the
line your output will be less than 0.5 because you're falling on the negative side of the line if
your output is if your input is on the right side of the line now your output is going to be
greater than 0.5 right so here we can actually visualize this space this is called the feature
space of a neural network we can visualize it in its completion right we can totally visualize
and interpret this neural network we can understand exactly what it's going to do for any input that
it sees right but of course this is a very simple neuron right it's not a neural network it's just
one neuron and even more than that it's even a very simple neuron it only has two inputs right
so in reality the types of neural neurons that you're going to be dealing with in this course
are going to be neurons and neural networks with millions or even billions of these parameters
right of these inputs right so here we only have two weights w1 w2 but today's neural networks have
billions of these parameters so drawing these types of plots that you see here obviously becomes a
lot more challenging it's actually not possible but now that we have some of the intuition behind
a perceptron let's start now by building neural networks and seeing how all of this comes together
so let's revisit that previous diagram of a perceptron now again if there's only one thing
to take away from this lecture right now it's to remember how a perceptron works that equation of
a perceptron is extremely important for every single class that comes after today and there's
only three steps it's dot product with the inputs add a bias and apply your non-linearity
let's simplify the diagram a little bit i'll remove the weight labels from this picture and now you
can assume that if i show a line every single line has an associated weight that comes with that
line right i'll also remove the bias term for simplicity assume that every neuron has that
bias term i don't need to show it and now note that the result here now calling it z which is just the
dot product plus bias before the non-linearity is the output is going to be linear first of all
it's just a it's just a weighted sum of all those pieces we have not applied the non-linearity yet
but our final output is just going to be g of z it's the activation function or non-linear
activation function applied to z now if we want to step this up a little bit more and say what if
we had a multi output function now we don't just have one output but let's say we want to have two
outputs well now we can just have two neurons in this network right every neuron say sees
all of the inputs that came before it but now you see the top neuron is going to be predicting an
answer and the bottom neuron will predict its own answer now importantly one thing you should
really notice here is that each neuron has its own weights right each neuron has its own lines
that are coming into just that neuron right so they're acting independently but they can later on
communicate if you have another layer right so let's start now by initializing this this process
a bit further and thinking about it more programmatically right what if we wanted to program
this neural network ourselves from scratch right remember that equation I told you didn't sound
very complex it's take a dot product add a bias which is a single number and apply a non-linearity
let's see how we would actually implement something like that so to define the layer right we're now
going to call this a layer which is a collection of neurons right we have to first define how that
information propagates through the network so we can do that by creating a call function here first
we're going to actually define the weights for that network right so remember every network every
neuron I should say every neuron has weights and a bias right so let's define those first
we're going to create the call function to actually see how we can pass information through that
layer right so this is going to take as input and inputs right this is like what we previously
called x and it's the same story that we've been seeing this whole class right we're going to matrix
multiply or take a dot product of our inputs with our weights we're going to add a bias
and then we're going to apply a non-linearity it's really that simple right we've now created a
single layer neural network right so this this line in particular this is the part that allows us to
be a powerful neural network maintaining that non-linearity and the important thing here is to
note that modern deep learning toolboxes and libraries already implement a lot of these for
you right so it's important for you to understand the foundations but in practice all of that layer
or architecture and all of that layer logic is actually implemented in tools like TensorFlow
and PyTorch through a dense layer right so here you can see an example of calling or creating
initializing a dense layer with two neurons right allowing it to feed in an arbitrary set of
inputs here we're seeing these two neurons in a layer being fed three inputs right and in code
it's only reduced down to this one line of TensorFlow code making it extremely easy and
convenient for us to use these functions and call them so now let's look at our single layered
neural network this is where we have now one layer between our input and our outputs right so
we're slowly and progressively increasing the complexity of our neural network so that we
can build up all of these building blocks right this layer in the middle is called a hidden layer
right obviously because you don't directly observe it you don't directly supervise it
right you do observe the two input and output layers but your hidden layer is just kind of a
a neuron layer that you don't directly observe right it just gives your network more capacity
more learning complexity and since we now have a transformation function from inputs
to hidden layers and hidden layers to output we now have a two layered neural network right
which means that we also have two weight matrices right we don't have just the w1 which we previously
had to create this hidden layer but now we also have w2 which does the transformation from hidden
layer to output layer yes in hidden you have just linear so there's no it's not is it a perceptron
or not yes so every hidden layer also has a nonlinearity accompanied with it right and that's
a very important point because if you don't have that perceptron then it's just a very large linear
function followed by a final nonlinearity at the very end right so you need that cascading
and uh you know overlapping application of nonlinearities that occur throughout the network
awesome okay so now let's zoom in look at a single unit in the hidden layer take this one for example
let's call it z2 right it's the second neuron in the first layer right it's the same perception
that we saw before we compute its answer by taking a dot product of its weights with its inputs
adding a bias and then applying a nonlinearity if we took a different hidden node like z3 the one
right below it we would compute its answer exactly the same way that we computed z2 except its
weights would be different than the weights of z2 everything else stays exactly the same it sees
the same inputs but of course you know i'm not going to actually show z3 in this picture and now
this picture is getting a little bit messy so let's clean things up a little bit more i'm going to
remove all the lines now and replace them just with these these boxes these symbols that will denote
what we call a fully connected layer right so these layers now denote that everything in our input
is connected to everything in our output and the transformation is exactly as we saw it before
dot product bias and nonlinearity and again in code to do this is extremely straightforward
with the foundations that we've built up from the beginning of the class we can now just define
two of these dense layers right our hidden layer on line one with n hidden units and then our output
layer with two hidden output units nonlinearity function does not need to be the same through
each layer oftentimes it is because of convenience there's there are some cases where you would want
it to be different as well especially in lecture two you're going to see nonlinearity is be different
even within the same layer let alone different layers but unless for a particular reason generally
convention is there's no need to keep them differently now let's keep expanding our knowledge
a little bit more if we now want to make a deep neural network not just a neural network like we
saw on the previous side now it's deep all that means is that we're now going to stack these layers
on top of each other one by one more and more creating a hierarchical model right the ones
where the final output is now going to be computed by going deeper and deeper and deeper into the
neural network and again doing this in code again follows the exact same story as before just cascading
these tensorflow layers on top of each other and just going deeper into the network
okay so now this is great because now we have at least a solid foundational understanding of how to
not only define a single neuron but how to define an entire neural network and you should be able
to actually explain at this point or understand how information goes from input through an entire
neural network to compute an output so now let's look at how we can apply these neural networks
to solve a very real problem that I'm sure all of you care about so here's a problem on how we
want to build an AI system to learn to answer the following question which is will I pass this
class right I'm sure all of you are really worried about this question so to do this let's start with
a simple input feature model the feature the two features that let's concern ourselves with are
going to be number one how many lectures you attend and number two how many hours you spend on your
final project so let's look at some of the past years of this class right we can actually observe
how different people have lived in this space right between how many lectures and how much
time you spent on your final project and you can actually see every point is a person the color of
that point is going to be if they passed or failed the class and you can see and visualize
kind of this this feature space if you will that we talked about before and then we have you you
follow right here you're the point four five right in between the this this feature space you've
attended four lectures and you will spend five hours on the final project and you want to build a
neural network to determine given everyone else in the class right that I've seen from all of the
previous years you want to help you want to have your neural network help you to understand what is
your likelihood that you will pass or fail this class so let's do it we now have all of the building
blocks to solve this problem using a neural network let's do it so we have two inputs those inputs
are number of lectures you attend and number of hours you spend on your final project it's four
and five we can pass those two inputs to our two x1 and x2 variables these are fed into this single
layered single hidden layered neural network it has three hidden units in the middle and we can see
that the final predicted output probability for you to pass this class is 0.1 or 10 right so very
bleak outcome it's not a good outcome the actual probability is one right so attending four out
of the five lectures and spending five hours on your final project you actually lived in a part of
the feature space which was actually very positive right it looked like you were going to pass the
class so what happened here anyone have any ideas so why did the neural network get this so terribly
wrong right exactly so this neural network is not trained we haven't shown it any of that data the
green and red data right so you should really think of neural networks like babies right before
they see data they haven't learned anything there's no expectation that we should have for them to be
able to solve any of these types of problems before we teach them something about the world
so let's teach this neural network something about the problem first right and to train it we first
need to tell our neural network when it's making bad decisions right so we need to teach it right
really train it to learn exactly like how we as humans learn in some ways right so we have to inform
the neural network when it gets the answer incorrect so that it can learn how to get the answer correct
right so the closer the answer is to the ground truth so right so for example the actual value
for you passing this class was probability one one hundred percent but it predicted a probability
of zero point one we compute what's called a loss right so the closer these two things are together
the smaller your loss should be and the and the more accurate your model should be
so let's assume that we have data not just from one student but now we have data from many students
we many students have taken this class before and we can plug all of them into the neural
network and show them all to this to this system now we care not only about how the neural network
did on just this one prediction but we care about how it predicted on all of these different people
that the neural network has shown in the past as well during this training and learning process
so when training your neural network we want to find a network that minimizes the empirical loss
between our predictions and those ground truth outputs and we're going to do this on average
across all of the different inputs that the that the model has seen if we look at this problem
of binary classification right between yeses and nos right will I pass the class or will I not pass
the class it's a year zero or one probability and we can use what is called the softmax function
or the softmax cross entropy function to be able to inform if this network is getting the answer
correct or incorrect right the softmax cross or the cross entropy function think of this as a
as an objective function it's a loss function that tells our neural network how far away these two
probability distributions are right so the output is a probability distribution we're trying to
determine how bad of an answer the neural network is predicting so that we can give it feedback to
get a better answer now let's suppose instead of training a or predicting a binary output we want
to predict a real valued output like a like any number it can take any number plus or minus
infinity so for example if you want to predict the grade that you get in a class right it doesn't
necessarily need to be between zero and one or zero and a hundred even right you could now use a
different loss in order to produce that value because our outputs are no longer a probability
distribution right so for example what you might do here is compute a mean squared error probably
mean squared error loss function between your true value or your true grade of the class
and the predicted grade right these are two numbers they're not probabilities necessarily
you compute their difference you square it to look at a distance between the two an absolute
distance right sign doesn't matter and then you can minimize this thing right okay great so let's
put all of this loss information with this problem of finding our network weights into a
unified problem and a unified solution to actually train our neural network
so we know that we want to find a neural network that will solve this problem on all this data
on average right that's how we contextualize this problem earlier in the lectures this means
effectively that we're trying to solve or we're trying to find what are the weights for our neural
network what are this this big vector w that we talked about in earlier in the lecture what is
this vector w compute this vector w for me based on all of the data that we have seen right now
the vector w is also going to determine what is the loss right so given a single vector w
we can compute how bad is this neural network performing on our data right so what is the loss
what is this deviation from the ground truth of our network uh based on where it should be
now remember that w is just a group of a bunch of numbers right it's a very big list of numbers
a list of weights uh for every single layer and every single neuron in our neural network right
so it's just a very big list or a vector of weights we want to find that vector what is that
vector based on a lot of data that's the problem of training a neural network and remember our
loss function is just a simple function of our weights if we have only two weights in our neural
network like we saw earlier in the slide then we can plot the loss landscape over this two-dimensional
space right so we have two weights w one and w two and for every single configuration or setting of
those two weights our loss will have a particular value which here we're showing is the height of
this graph right so for any w one and w two what is the loss and what we want to do is find the
lowest point what is the best loss where what are the weights such that our loss will be as good as
possible so the smaller the loss the better so we want to find the lowest point in this graph
now how do we do that right so the way this works is we start somewhere in this space we
don't know where to start so let's pick a random place to start right now from that place let's
compute what's called the gradient of the landscape at that particular point this is a very local
estimate of where is going up basically where where is the slope increasing at my current location
right that informs us not only where the slope is increasing but more importantly where the slope
is decreasing if i negate the direction if i go in the opposite direction i can actually step down
into the landscape and change my weights such that i lower my loss so let's take a small step
just a small step in the opposite direction of the part that's going up let's take a small step
going down and we'll keep repeating this process we'll compute a new gradient at that new point
and it will take another small step and we'll keep doing this over and over and over again
until we converge at what's called a local minimum right so based on where we started it may not be
a global minimum of everywhere in this lost landscape but let's find ourselves now in a local minimum
and we're guaranteed to actually converge by following this very simple algorithm at a local
minimum so let's summarize now this algorithm this algorithm is called gradient descent let's
summarize it first in pseudocode and then we'll look at it in actual code in a second so there's
a few steps first step is we initialize our location somewhere randomly in this weight space
right we compute the gradient of of our loss at with respect to our weights okay
and then we take a small step in the opposite direction and we keep repeating this in a loop
over and over and over again and we say we keep we'll keep doing this until convergence right
until we stop moving basically and our network basically finds where it's supposed to end up
we'll talk about this this small step right so we're multiplying our gradient by what i keep
calling is a small step we'll talk about that a bit more about a bit more and later part of this
this lecture but for now let's also very quickly show the analogous part in in code as well and
it mirrors very nicely right so we'll randomly initialize our weights this happens every time
you train a neural network you have to randomly initialize the weights and then you have a loop
right here showing it with without even convergence right we're just going to keep looping forever
where we say okay we're going to compute the loss at that location compute the gradient so which
way is up and then we just negate that gradient multiply it by some what's called learning rate
lr denoted here it's a small step and then we take a direction in that small step
so let's take a deeper look at this term here this is called the gradient right this tells us
which way is up in that landscape and this again it tells us even more than that it tells us how
is our landscape how is our loss changing as a function of all of our weights but i actually
have not told you how to compute this so let's talk about that process that process is called
back propagation we'll go through this very very briefly and we'll start with the simplest neural
network uh that's possible right so we already saw the simplest building block which is a single
neuron now let's build the simplest neural network which is just a one neuron neural network right
so it has one hidden neuron it goes from input to hidden neuron to output and we want to compute
the gradient of our loss with respect to this weight w2 okay so i'm highlighting it here
so we have two weights let's compute the gradient first with respect to w2 and that tells us how
much does a small change in w2 affect our loss does our loss go up or down if we move our w2
a little bit in one direction or another so let's write out this derivative we can start by applying
the chain rule backwards from the loss through the output and specifically we can actually decompose
this law this derivative this gradient into two parts right so the first part we're decomposing
it from dj dw2 into dj dy right which is our output multiplied by dy dw2 right this is all
possible right it's a chain rule it's a bit i'm just reciting a chain rule here from calculus
this is possible because y is only dependent on the previous layer and now let's suppose we don't
want to do this for w2 but we want to do it for w1 we can use the exact same process right but now
it's one step further right we'll now replace w2 with w1 we need to apply the chain rule yet again
once again to decompose the problem further and now we propagate our old gradient that we computed
for w2 all the way back one more step uh to the weight that we're interested in which in this
case is w1 and we keep repeating this process over and over again propagating these gradients
backwards from output to input to compute ultimately what we want in the end is this
derivative of every weight so the lot the derivative of our loss with respect to every
weight in our neural network this tells us how much does a small change in every single weight
in our network affect the loss does our loss go up or down if we change this weight a little bit
in this direction or a little bit in that direction yes neuron and perceptron are the same so
typically people say neural network which is why like a single neuron it's also gotten popularity
but originally a perceptron is the the formal term the two terms are identical
okay so now we've covered a lot so we've covered the forward propagation of information through a
neuron and through a neural network all the way through and we've covered now the back propagation
of information to understand how we should change every single one of those weights in our neural
network to improve our loss so that was the back prop algorithm in theory it's actually
pretty simple it's just a chain rule right there's nothing there's actually nothing more than than
just the chain rule and the nice part is that deep learning libraries actually do this for you so
they compute back prop for you you don't actually have to implement it yourself which is very
convenient but now it's important to touch on even though the theory is actually not that complicated
for back propagation let's touch on it now from practice now thinking a little bit towards your
own implementations when you want to implement these neural networks what are some insights
so optimization of neural networks in practice is a completely different story it's not
straightforward at all and in practice it's very difficult and usually very computationally
intensive to do this back prop algorithm so here's an illustration from a paper that came
out a few years ago that actually attempted to visualize a very deep neural networks loss
landscape so previously we had that other depiction visualization of how a neural network would
look in a two-dimensional landscape real neural networks are not two-dimensional they're hundreds
or millions or billions of dimensions and now what would those lost landscapes look like you can
actually try some clever techniques to actually visualize them this is one paper that attempted
to do that and it turns out that they look extremely messy right the important thing is that
if you do this algorithm and you start in a bad place depending on your neural network you may
not actually end up in the global solution right so your initialization matters a lot
and you need to kind of traverse these local minima and try to try and help you find the
global minima or even more than that you need to construct neural networks that have lost landscapes
that are much more amenable to optimization than this one right so this is a very bad loss
landscape there are some techniques that we can apply to our neural networks that smooth out
their lost landscape and make them easier to optimize so recall that update equation that
we talked about earlier with gradient descent right so there is this parameter here that we
didn't talk about we we described this as the little step that you could take right so it's a
small number that you multiply with the direction which is your gradient it just tells you okay i'm
not going to just go all the way in this direction i'll just take a small step in this direction
so in practice even setting this value right it's just one number setting this one number can be
rather difficult right if we set the learning rate too small then the model can get stuck
in these local minima right so here it starts and it kind of gets stuck in this local minima
it converges very slowly even if it doesn't get stuck if the learning rate is too large it can
kind of overshoot and in practice it even diverges and explodes and you don't actually ever find
any minima now ideally what we want is to use learning rates that are not too small and not too
large to so they're large enough to basically avoid those local minima but small enough such
that they won't diverge and they will actually still find their way into the global minima so
something like this is what you should intuitively have in mind right so something i can overshoot
the local minimas but find itself into a better minima and then finally stabilize itself there
so how do we actually set these learning rates right in practice what does that process look
like now idea number one is is very basic right try a bunch of different learning rates and see
what works and that's actually a not a bad process in practice it's one of the processes that people
use so that that's uh that's interesting but let's see if we can do something smarter than this
and let's see how we can design algorithms that can adapt to the landscapes right so in practice
there's no reason why there should be a single number right can we have learning rates that adapt
to the model to the data to the landscapes to the gradients that it's seeing around so this means
that the learning rate may actually increase or decrease as a function of the gradients in the
loss function right how fast we're learning or many other options right there are many different
ideas that could be done here and in fact there are many widely used different procedures or
methodologies for setting the learning rate and during your labs we actually encourage you to try
out some of these different ideas for different types of learning rates and and even play around
with you know what what's the effect of increasing or decreasing your learning rate you'll see very
striking differences
so so a few things what number one is that it's not a closed space right so there's an infinite
every every weight can be plus or minus up to infinity right so even if it was a one-dimensional
neural network with just one weight it's not a closed space in practice it's even worse than that
because you have billions of dimensions right so not only is your space your support system in
one dimension is it infinite but you now have billions of infinite dimensions right or billions
of infinite support spaces so it's not something that you can just like search every weight every
possible weight in your neural in your configuration or what is every possible weight that this neural
network could take and let me test them out because it's not practical to do even for a very small
neural network in practice so in your labs you can really try to put all of this information
in this picture into practice which defines your model number one right here defines your
optimizer which previously we denoted as this gradient descent optimizer here we're calling it
stochastic gradient center SGD we'll talk about that more in a second and then also note that
your optimizer which here we're calling SGD could be any of these adaptive optimizers you can swap
them out and you should swap them out you should test different things here to see the impact of
these different methods on your training procedure and you'll gain very valuable intuition for the
different insights that will come with that as well so I want to continue very briefly just for
the end of this lecture to talk about tips for training neural networks in practice and how we
can focus on this powerful idea of really what's called batching data right not seeing all of your
data but now talking about a topic called batching so to do this let's very briefly revisit this
gradient descent algorithm the gradient is actually compute this gradient computation the back prop
algorithm I mentioned this earlier it's a very computationally expensive operation and it's
even worse because we now are we previously described in a way where we would have to compute
it over a summation over every single data point in our entire data set right that's how we defined
it with the loss functions an average over all of our data points which means that we're summing
over all of our data points the gradients so in most real-life problems this would be completely
infeasible to do because our data sets are simply too big and the models are too big to compute those
gradients on every single iteration remember this isn't just a one-time thing right it's every
single step that you do you keep taking small steps so you keep me you keep needing to repeat this
process so instead let's define a new gradient descent algorithm called SGD stochastic gradient
descent instead of computing the gradient over the entire data set now let's just pick a single
training point and compute that one training points gradient right the nice thing about that is that
it's much easier to compute that gradient right it only needs one point and the downside is that
it's very noisy it's very stochastic since it was computed using just that one example right so you
have that that trade-off that exists so what's the middle ground right the middle ground is to take
not one data point and not the full data set but a batch of data right so take a what's called a
mini batch right this could be something in practice like 32 pieces of data is a common batch size
and this gives us an estimate of the true gradient right so you approximate the gradient
by averaging the gradient of these 32 samples it's still fast because 32 is much smaller than
the size of your entire data set but it's pretty quick now right it's still noisy but it's okay
usually in practice because you can still iterate much faster and since b is normally not that large
again think of something like in the tens or the hundreds of samples it's very fast to compute this
in practice compared to regular gradient descent and it's also much more accurate compared to
stochastic gradient descent and the increase in accuracy of this gradient estimation allows
us to converge to our solution significantly faster as well right it's not only about the
speed it's just about the increase in accuracy of those gradients allows us to get to our solution
much faster which ultimately means that we can train much faster as well and we can save compute
and the other really nice thing about mini batches is that they allow for parallelizing our
computation right and that was a concept that we had talked about earlier in the class as well
and here's where it's coming in we can split up those batches right so those 32 pieces of data
let's say if our batch size is 32 we can split them up onto different workers right different
parts of the GPU can tackle those different parts of our data points this can allow us to
basically achieve even more significant speed-ups using GPU architectures and GPU hardware okay
finally the last topic I want to talk about before we end this lecture and move on to lecture number
two is overfitting right so overfitting is this idea that is actually not a deep learning
centric problem at all it's it's a problem that exists in all of machine learning right the key
problem is that and the key problem is actually one that addresses how you can accurately define
if your model is is actually capturing your true data set right or if it's just learning kind of
the subtle details that are kind of spuriously correlating to your data set so set differently
let me say it a bit differently now so let's say we want to build models that can learn
representations okay from our training data that still generalize to brand new unseen
test points right that's the real goal here is we want to teach our model something based on a
lot of training data but then we don't want it to do well in the training day we want it to do well
when we deploy it into the real world and it's seeing things that it has never seen during training
so the concept of overfitting is exactly addressing that problem overfitting means if
if your model is doing very well on your training data but very badly in testing it
that means it's overfitting it's overfitting to the training data that it saw on the other hand
there's also underfitting right on the left hand side you can see basically not fitting the data
enough which means that you know you're going to achieve very similar performance on your testing
distribution but both are underperforming the actual capabilities of your system now ideally
you want to end up somewhere in the middle which is not too complex where you're memorizing all of
the nuances in your training data like on the right but you still want to continue to perform
well even based on the brand new data so you're not underfitting as well so to a to actually
address this problem in neural networks and in machine learning in general there's a few
different ways that you should be aware of and how to do it because you'll need to apply them
as part of your solutions in your software labs as well so the key concept here is called
regularization right regularization is a technique that you can introduce and said very simply all
regularization is is a way to discourage your model from from these nuances in your training
data from being learned that's all it is and as we've seen before it's actually critical for our
models to be able to generalize you know not just on training data but really what we care about
is the testing data so the most popular regularization technique that's important for you to understand
is this very simple idea called dropout let's revisit this picture of a deep neural network
that we've been seeing all lecture right in dropout our training during training what we're
going to do is randomly set some of the activations right these outputs of every single neuron
to zero which is randomly going to set them to zero with some probability right so let's say
50 percent is our probability that means that we're going to take all of the activation insert
in our neural network and with a probability of 50 before we pass that activation on to the next
neuron we're just going to set it to zero and not pass on anything so effectively 50 percent of the
neurons are going to be kind of shut down or killed in a forward pass and you're only going
to forward pass information with the other 50 percent of your neurons so this idea is extremely
powerful actually because it lowers the capacity of our neural network it not only lowers the
capacity of our neural network but it's dynamically lowering it because on the next iteration we're
going to pick a different 50 percent of neurons that we drop out so constantly the network is going
to have to learn to build pathways different pathways from input to output and that it can't
rely on any small any small part of the features that are present in any part of the training
dataset too extensively right because it's constantly being forced to find these different
pathways with random probabilities so let's drop out the second regularization technique
is going to be this notion called early stopping which is actually something that
is model agnostic you can apply this to any type of model as long as you have a testing set that
you can play around with so the idea here is that we have already a pretty formal mathematical
definition of what it means to overfit right overfitting is just when our model starts to
perform worse on our test set that's really all it is right so what if we plot over the course
of training so x-axis is as we're training the model let's look at the performance on both the
training set and the test set so in the beginning you can see that the training set and the test
set are both going down and they continue to go down which is excellent because it means that
our model is getting stronger eventually though what you'll notice is that the test loss plateaus
and starts to increase on the other hand the training loss there's no reason why the training
loss should ever need to stop going down right training losses generally always continue to
decay as long as there is capacity in the neural network to learn those differences right but the
important point is that this continues for the rest of training and we want to basically
we care about this point right here right this is the really important point because
this is where we need to stop training right after this point this is the happy medium because
after this point we start to overfit on parts of the data where our training accuracy becomes
actually better than our testing accuracy so our testing accuracy is going bad it's getting worse
but our training accuracy is still improving so it means overfitting on the other hand on the left
hand side this is the opposite problem right we have not fully utilized the capacity of our model
and the testing accuracy can still improve further right this is a very powerful idea but it's actually
extremely easy to implement in practice because all you really have to do is just monitor the loss
of over the course of training right and you just have to pick the model
where the testing accuracy starts to get worse
so i'll conclude this lecture by just summarizing three key points that we've covered in the class
so far and this is a very gem packed class so the entire week is going to be like this
and today is just the start so so far we've learned the fundamental building blocks of neural
networks starting all the way from just one neuron also called a perceptron we learned that we can
stack these systems on top of each other to create a hierarchical network and how we can
mathematically optimize those types of systems and then finally in the very last part of the
class we talked about just techniques tips and techniques for actually training and applying
these systems into practice now in the next lecture we're going to hear from Ava on deep
sequence modeling using RNNs and also a really new and exciting algorithm and type of model called
the transformer which is built off of this principle of attention you're going to learn
about in the next class but let's for now just take a brief pause and let's resume in about
five minutes just so we can switch speakers and Ava can start her presentation okay thank you