Well, we've just heard some wonderful lectures on RNA, coding, replication, evolution, but
we still have this problem about what was the first engine and indeed what was its fuel.
So I'm going to suggest that we should think about what life does rather than what it is
to understand that.
And what does life do?
It hydrogenates carbon dioxide.
Right down the bottom of the food chain and probably down the bottom of the evolutionary
tree it hydrogenates carbon dioxide.
So presumably that's how it started.
So here's what I'd like to also emphasize and people have already worried me about
the remark about entropy, but I think we shouldn't forget this wonderful book by Schrodinger.
To me there were two wonderful books about the origin of life.
One's worth reading and it's by Le Duc and by the way it's a century when it was published.
It was published in 1911 and really it's worth a read.
He had the Nianst equation, all the kind of things in it that in fact I'm going to allude
to, the only thing he didn't have was an alkaline spring.
Without taking the other book, of course, that is what is life and that's from Schrodinger,
I'd just like to emphasize he kept on saying what does life do?
It drinks orderliness from a suitable environment.
So yeah, let's find with this suitable environment.
What is a suitable environment?
It's got to offer us everything, all in one place.
We don't want any contingencies.
It's got to be right there, nothing, no false pleas.
So our suggestion then is basically we're looking at an earth which is a water world
and I'm going to go back on to that but there's probably at least twice as much water on the
early earth, probably more than that.
There is no land.
The day lasts about 12 hours, the moon's much closer, the galaxy's probably much closer
and the other galaxies are closer.
This is a different planet, don't think this planet, think another planet.
It's a third of the age of the universe ago and of course we've got the water covering
the planet.
It's a pretty oxidized surface, don't forget.
It's H2O and CO2 and without photosynthesis you can't do much better than that.
So we've got an oxidized exterior and we've got one compartment on this planet of water.
But we need to think about how we could get some tension on the planet because after all
what we have is water we know can descend into the planet and in fact oxidize the surface
or the near surface, oxidize it, carbonate it and hydrate it so much so that this water
up here which probably supports up to 10 bars of carbon dioxide and maybe more, don't forget
Venus has 90 atmospheres of carbon dioxide so we're not claiming much and as somebody
said yesterday Mars has a carbon dioxide atmosphere.
That's what these planets are like.
At high temperature through volcanoes you get carbon dioxide so that's the exterior
but the interior is electron rich.
One comes the water and suddenly we're getting a differentiation of this seawater which was
somewhat acidic up here, carbonic if you like, it comes down and it comes back up and it's
quite different now.
It's got a pH of about 11, it's got quite a lot of hydrogen so that's our fuel, it's
our favorite fuel after all, what we're all trying to aim for, some methane, not such a
bad fuel and some formate.
So this is coming up now and it's like a titration.
This water now is going to come out, there's five pH units different, it's going to come
up and it's going to titrate into this ocean but as many of you, at least when I was young
doing buretting you'd know that out of a burette or even a pipette you'd get some fouling
and here we've got some fouling and it's inorganic fouling.
This is all about an inorganic world to start with.
So my molecule, pre-bodic molecule, what I think about the pre-bodic molecule, it's carbon
dioxide.
So we're bringing this material back up here, this water back up here, we get some fouling,
we get some frustration, we get this therefore becomes the kind of creative place for interaction
between the carbonic ocean and the hydrogen and this is where we would say hydrogenation
of carbon dioxide would start and if we kind of blow this up a bit we've got our iron sulfide
and iron nickel sulfides, the iron by the way coming out of this reservoir of an ocean
and I'll explain that in a moment, some nickel, of course the CO2 and protons so we've got
even a proton gradient so we've got a proton motive force but also we've got things like
nitric oxide out here so we've actually got a redox gradient as well and the overall amount
of energy is about between half and one volt so it's a commensurate energy with what we
use today, so what life uses and we would suggest that life starts probably between
40 and 80 degrees centigrade in such a system, a compartmentalized system.
So I call this a two compartment entropy trap because we've had one compartment up here
which was of course the open ocean and then we can differentiate that water and bring
back the water and now we've got an entropy trap because we've got these two fluids constantly
interacting with each other.
So here's this turbulent water world, the Hadian water world, it's a single compartment
as I say, it's got eight times the amount of UV present day that you wouldn't want to
be on the surface of this planet, I mean it's really a hopeless place to be, there's no
land to stop the hurricanes, it's continually out of physical equilibrium as well as chemical
equilibrium so it's a turbulent world, the Hadian water world as I say and it's being
impacted of course by bolides and after the lunar impact the ocean probably rained out
around about 4.4 billion years ago and life would have started very shortly thereafter
and it would be very hard to kill after that and I think that life probably started around
about 4.4 and kept going.
So we know now and of course we're getting yet another experience of this from Iceland
that here's the volcano, this is last year's volcano from Iceland and of course out comes
this carbon dioxide, some hydrogen sulfide, sulfur dioxide, trioxide, nitric oxide, plenty
of nitric oxide not just because of the lightning but because nitric oxide is stable in this
magmatic material.
There's an interesting crossover geochemically so that really carbon, the state of carbon
in the mantle at low temperature would like to be methane but around about four or five
hundred degrees centigrade is a crossover between the redox condition of iron two to
iron three and carbon methane to carbon dioxide so at high temperature you always get carbon
dioxide.
In fact geologists since Darwin have always known that the early atmosphere of this planet
was carbon dioxide.
So here's our earth and as I say it's oxidized on the outside, it's even probably got some
ferric iron and yet the interior is reduced.
It's in fact a little bit of native iron and some ferrous iron and that's the material
that basically is oxidized by water to generate the hydrogen.
So hydrogen becomes the carrier gas if you like of the electrons from the interior and
actually it's a bit like an autotrophic bacterium, it just doesn't do the job fast enough but
it does make some methane as we know.
So we could think of this and I don't want to take this two series because I don't think
methanogens were very early anymore but basically here's the reaction and the world can do it
pretty well geochemically, hydrogen plus CO2 makes methane plus water.
So we can think of this a bit like a methanogen, here's the methanogen or an electrochemical
cell, the output as I say between half and one volt.
So what we'd suggest then is can we imagine life kind of bubbling off from the surface
of the planet and here we suggest that just as a bubble, here's the kind of inorganic
membrane that I hope to show you, inside is very low pH conditions, sorry very high pH
conditions, very low hydroxyl, very high hydroxyl amounts and on the outside you've got the
protons from the protonic ocean or the carbonic ocean and so we've got a kind of entropy
trap here because we've got order, continual order between the inside and the outside.
This is reduced and this is somewhat oxidized on the outside and as I say it's a rather
like bacterium except that bacterium transports the protons out of the cell to come back in
to drive things like ATP whereas we don't need to drive that system because it's out
here as part of the initial condition.
So the initial conditions we would say favor metabolism right from the start.
So here we have it again from Schrodinger order, from order.
You can't have, you don't want a hypercyclic, you don't want to drag life out of a chaotic
mess, you need to have direct delivery and there's one thing that if you're not a geologist
or don't know any geology, the one thing I'd like to remember as a rock type and that is
sub-pentanization and so this is sub-pentanide and you're going to see a few slides of this,
you've all seen it in shop windows and so forth on the sides of shop windows.
You can see how fractured it is, this is a kind of little engines of generation of hydrogen
actually as the water permeates through this rock and sub-pentanizes what is the crust and
this is why in a kind of analogy with Maxwell's demon, this is the demon that makes the difference
between this fluid, sorry, this fluid and this fluid, the sub-pentanization reaction.
So just to remind us that this is the United Nations building, by the way JPL said I really
shouldn't show this side because it was political.
Well I mean here's the president so I think it's beyond politics but anyway here's our
sub-pentanide it's as you, I'm sure you've become aware of this rock type and what we're
looking at is something called olivine plus water, basically here's olivine, magnesium
iron silicate plus water, generate some silica, some magnetite so we've oxidized the iron
now, magnesium and calcium go into solution to give you the hydroxyl, the alkaline fluid
and hydrogen in solution.
And if there's carbon dioxide, some a little bit of methane and this is the pathway, the
geochemical pathway, it goes from CO2, basically it goes pretty fast to methane, or fairly
fast to methane, although you can see some of them, you can get formate in the reactions
so you can find this in a hot spring, typically hot spring, nothing to do with life at all,
will generate methane and you'll have a little bit of formate, you don't see any methyl alcohol
that seems to be pretty unstable and go to the methane.
We've talked about the methane and I've just said that I don't think that this was an early
reaction for biology, but nevertheless it's kind of there in the wings, the reaction that
really takes place I think is the hydrogen plus the CO2 to acetate, so basically acetate,
it's CO2 plus CH4 by the way, makes you acetate, so here's, to me this is the key reaction
and in our lab we can never make this, we've never been able to make this chemically, so
we think that this really was the job for life and so that thereby hangs the tale that
we think that life, the beginnings of life was something that was a kind of microbe
that was an acetogen, something that generated acetate from carbon, oxide and hydrogen.
So we heard about the black smokers this morning, here they are and of course when, as soon
as they were discovered, they were predicted by somebody by Jack Corliss and John Edmund
were with Jack Corliss when these were discovered, predicted by the way in the Pacific at 360
degrees centigrade, of course the first thing to come to their mind was well maybe life
started here, Stanley Miller didn't like that and wrote a letter to Nature saying it was
ludicrous to think life could start at 400 or 360 degrees centigrade, I mean yeah I agree
with them, but interestingly there wouldn't have been black smokers on the early earth,
there'd been many more of these springs but they would have been 400 degrees centigrade
but they wouldn't be black smoke because the only reason why you've got black smoke here
is because it's acidic, hot solution, it's not because it's cooling, it's because it's
interacting with the alkaline seawater so you get the precipitation of this kind of
so-called black smoke which are things like iron, zinc, manganese, oxides and nickel and
a little bit of cobalt, so this basically they provide the trace elements into the early
ocean and that becomes a reservoir, perhaps a super saturated reservoir of just the kind
of metals we require for the first enzymes.
So we've seen this, so this I'm not sure if you can get this, this is the ocean floor
spreading, here's the actual spreading axis here and right here we've got the magma, here's
the magma chamber so the water comes down to just about its critical point, perhaps a little
bit higher, becomes very buoyant, shoots back up and as I think Jennifer said you know
they only last for about 10 to 100 years so that's not very long and let's say they're
up to 400 degrees centigrade, so it can't be here but we've been working in mineral
deposits in Ireland and Alpine ultromethic provinces as called so we assume that there
should be other kinds of hot springs on the early earth and we predicted in 1989 that
there should be alkaline springs and Fortune would have it, a PhD student was looking out
of the submarine window as they were going to the mid-oceanic ridge, the mid-atlantic
ridge and she saw that some kind of little wisps of white smoke material and she stopped
the submarine, told Deb Callie and they went back and they found this extraordinary structure,
it's still the only main one to be found so far but it's the Lost City submarine spring,
it lasts for at least 30,000 years, pretty certainly 100,000 years so that's a 10 to
the 17 microseconds and somebody also said yesterday or perhaps this morning that the
interactions, the chemical interactions, we shouldn't think in our terms of us, our
big bulky selves in our time, we should think in terms of how long it takes to make these
chemical reactions so 10 to the power of 17 microseconds I would think is plenty of time
for life to start. So what we got here, so we've got this made of calcium and magnesium
hydroxide, it's up to 94 degrees centigrade, not too hot, 15 millimoles of hydrogen so
that's plenty of fuel, up to 2 millimoles of methane and they make compartments so
in the precipitation there's always, always these springs, whatever the kind, always generates
some hollow compartments where the fluid makes its way through in a kind of labyrinthine manner
and some of them seal off and so forth and I think these compartments are all important
because we must have compartments I think for metabolism to make any sense, not only
to keep the goodies so to speak inside but also to use those gradients which are pH gradients,
redox gradients and of course even a temperature gradient. So here's, this is geochemistry
and one thing to say about it is if it was geochemically easy to make, to reduce carbon
dioxide to methane, there would be no life, no requirement for it, it's a very fact that
it's such an uphill task to add an electron to CO2 and then reduce it to formate and formaldehyde
and then once you've got there, downhill it goes but because of this life can come in
here as the catalyst to bring us up to formate or formaldehyde and then downhill, it's like,
it's a kind of geochemical siphon. So, and here's what the methalogens do, so they make
it easier, catalysis lowers the activation energy required for the reaction and also
an ionic gradient is required to help CO2 be reduced to formate and then after that
it's fairly well downhill but it's very complicated to get energy out of this so I don't think
that this was, the methalogens were not eaten early but we think the acetogens were. So
the acetogens now, they don't need an ionic gradient so much, well except in a sense
they need ATP or adenosine triphosphate and it's adenosine triphosphate that drives the
CO2 up to formate and formaldehyde and methylene and then downhill and then you add a methyl
group to carbon monoxide which is reduced elsewhere and you end up with acetate which
of course can take you on a pyruvate and eventually can aminate by the way all these reactions
taking place most easily in alkaline solution. So here, you put it all together and let's
think of this, you can think of this in all kinds of ways, it's the fractionation column,
it's a hydrothermal flow reactor and so, but what I've done is kind of dress it up as one
structure here but let me just remind you that here's, here are the reduced molecules
coming out, there's hydrogen of course, a little bit of methane, some ammonia, molybdenum
sulfide, soluble in alkaline solution as in, as our tungsten oxide which I think is pretty
significant because we, all life seems to require this molybdenum and tungsten at this
early stage of reduction and what I've plotted here really is basically the acetyl coenzyme
A pathway. So the CO2 comes from the outside, we think that we need some ferric ion or maybe
nitrate out here to help to oxidize the reduced molybdenum site so you lose an electron from
molybdenum from molybdenum 4 to molybdenum 5 and then you've got a very energetic electron
which can then reduce the CO2 and once you've done that then you're off on the, on that
pathway up through onto a cobalt enzyme which will take the methyl group onto acetyl coenzyme
synthase itself which is a nickel bearing enzyme, notice the importance of metals in
here, we've already required molybdenum, iron, of course iron sulfides as well and the cobalt
and the nickel and once we've got here then that the acetate can be taken either by what
is now the synthase, the thiol group and the thiol can then be phosphorylated to, to generate
acetyl phosphate and the phosphate can then with the help of other phosphate from outside
be, help to generate pyrophosphate from monophosphate so this in the acetyl coenzyme pathway is
ADP to ATP, here we're using just monophosphate or orthophosphate to go to pyrophosphate
and that then feeds into general biosynthesis, acetogenic biosynthesis, I should say that
there's also a methyl group here and I think that methanotrophy was probably early as well
and what was the oxidant for methanotrophy, probably nitric oxide on nitrate, so we've
got two different kinds of schemes here, one basically doing the main job for the world
and that's spending the hydrogen fuel and a little bit on the side spending the methyl
fuel, so what do we do with this, well we can take it into the lab and we can put a hydrothermal
solution on one side and ocean water on the other and we can mix them, we can heat them
up to 100 degrees centigrade, we can put them into a central reactor here with ultramafic
rock just like what's in the crust of the earth or the crust of Mars indeed or what
was Venus, all the same rock with a little bit of sulfide and out comes the fluid, we
then take this fluid and we take it to another lab and this is in the other lab and we inject
this fluid into what we think of as a Hadean ocean which we had a little bit of ferrous
chloride in up to perhaps 10 millimoles from those very hot springs, this kind of somewhat
acidic ocean and we get this immediate precipitation, oftentimes sulfide, a little bit of silica
and so on and what we, in that reactor we find we can make methane within actually just
about 10 hours, we've got 16 parts per million by volume, so this is an eight biotic reaction,
very easy to do and I think early life couldn't compete with geochemistry in this case. The
hydrogen sulfide goes up to about 14 millimoles and then down to about 1 to 2 millimoles but
again enough to precipitate such a membrane, here just to remind us is the sub-pentanization,
the requirement of sub-pentanization. So what do they look like? So we can now say
here's our main model, we're getting used to this now, now we know that we've got an
actual mound, a hydrothermal mound that's got compartments in it, here are the kind
of compartments, this is a chimney, within the chimney you get these small compartments
made of iron sulfide or ferrous hydroxide or oxyhydroxide with plenty of what looks
like catalytic surface to my mind anyway. So this is now the sequence and what we've
got here also is a propensity for waste, we can dispose of the waste, the things that
do not play, the molecules that do not interact can just be taken off as waste and of course
just like life itself, this is an entropy generator but ordering, there is ordering
going on within these structures but outside then entropy is generated through the waste,
polythermal, polychemical. So putting the whole thing together again, making it slightly
more reasonable to look at, here's our hydrothermal mound, submarine hydrothermal mound, it's being
fed with hydrogen sulfide, hydrogen ammonia, milliptin and tungsten, up to 120 degrees
centigrade pH 11 coming into this somewhat acidic ocean with all these electron acceptors
on the outside and the metals and phosphate and precipitating structures that are rather
similar, mineral structures that are rather similar to the active centers of enzymes and
just to emphasize this point one more time, here's the protons on the outside and we speculate
that the protons can basically drive monophosphate, phosphorylation to diphosphate or perhaps
through acetyl phosphate. So here's our proton motive force, it's all there, everything
you require for early life is there, all the metals, all the energy. So what I want to
emphasize is that biochemistry isn't just better geochemistry, there really is a discontinuity
and that discontinuity because people have been very unsuccessful in generating I think
organic molecules because they think that all you have to do is get the recipe right,
the chemical recipe and we'll get life. I don't think so, we've got to have that proton
motive force and redox gradients. So we can go to Gunter Vectors Heuser and Claudia Huber
for perhaps one of the first interesting structures. Now this isn't so good as it looks I admit
but what he's taken is a methyl group and a carbon monoxide and shown that on nickel ion
sulfide and indeed even nickel sulfate or nickel sulfide then he can make acetyl thioacidate
basically and hydrogen sulfide. He's done this at pH 6.4 which is very nice little spike here,
we haven't been able to reproduce that but that could be our failing but you could see that
actually it's very well satisfied this kind of reaction at pretty high pH. So again I want
to emphasize just how many of these reactions are promoted by alkaline conditions. So we take
a closer look at our membranes, our structures made in the lab and there are some peculiarities
to it and of course anybody's got any ideas about this I'd welcome them but here this is the kind
of membrane so we're inside the membrane here this is and you can see these love what are called
framboids it's kind of raspberry shaped ion sulfides that grow on the inside then here we've
got a mixture of ion monosulfide and something called Gregite Fe3S4 and on the outside is what
the outside looks like absolutely extraordinary ordering of the outside and indeed even the
inside looks like this and we thought that might be kind of claddeny plate material we're just not
I don't know why these make such beautiful structures I mean they're much more beautiful
and reliable and then waves on a beach in sand and we would say that most of the action takes
place here the alkaline flow goes out the acidic counter flow comes in and most of the
organic interactions or organic synthesis we would argue would be happening actually within
the membrane this membrane's about five to ten microns across pretty wide for a membrane and it's
inorganic so if we look again at this what what are the structures of the elements or the the
minerals that make make this well look the main mineral to precipitate is something called mechanawad
and it's made here it is an ion sulfa ion sulfur rom basically you put this together in such a way
that it makes for something that's actually a pretty good electron conductor in that direction
and a very good insulator in this direction it's it's uh so we've got a semi permeable and a
semi conducting membrane so this is one of the chimneys here's here's a chimney again and this
is kind of a little offshoot little compartment here and here are subcompoundments within the
membrane itself now if you look at that mechanawad how similar it is to the actual active center of
hydrogenase and one thing we need to do is if you've got H2 you've got to split into two electrons
and two protons so and this is what hydrogenase does and here here's a structure ion sulfur ion
sulfur so similar of course to this structure here so could it be that this was the first
hydrogenase it doesn't not a very effective one but effective enough and not only that could it be
that it's ready for co-option so that if it were to be co-opted by a short peptide maybe that would
make it even slightly more active so we if you have this at 80 degrees centigrade this hydrothermal
chimney then within about two or three days sometimes sooner you get the generation of
something called gregite which is fv well it should be fv5 ni s8 oftentimes there's not nickel
there sometimes there is if the nickel is there and it's going to be in this tetrahedral side here
so here we've got now we've put the two roms together so we've got ion sulfur ion sulfur and
behind it ion sulfur ion sulfur through two sulfas to nickel so and this is just slightly
oxidized and it's the ion that's oxidized not the sulfur so this is nothing to do with the
pyrite hypothesis because that's the pyrite hypothesis it's a sulfur that gets oxidized but
of course with it's much better i think if we have the ion going back from shall we say
2 plus to 2.5 plus on average again here's the what the membrane looks like this made of this material
and look how similar it is to acetylcoenzyme synthase which is kind of where we came in here's
the nickel side through sulfur and here's now we've got a box or a cubane structure which is
extraordinarily similar to the cubane structure in here so again we're wondering can this be
the kind of structure that is actually acting as acetylcoenzyme synthase type in the in the
vectus hyzer huba reaction so here we have those that kind of structure so what's next well of
course what we need next because what's easy to make with and and as everybody's agreed RNA is
hard to make almost impossible to make but but amino acids are easy to make in the lab so we would
say that that's first and here again huba and vectus hyzer has made some amino acids in the lab
and not only that they can amenate them and in this case they've amenated these various structures
with either iron sulfide or ferrous hydroxide so that's the kind of thing that should be able to
happen in our chimneys and they happen at pH 9 and the yield is extraordinary
well if we can do that can can we if we if pyrophosphates available and and I should say that
diswort and and Andy Pratt have produced pyrophosphate in the lab in a kind of substrate
phosphorylation technique using ferrous iron as the catalyst and iron sulfide and and using that
then yamanaka et al and others have managed to
uh actually phosphoryte and then uh basically dimerize uh with trimetaphosphate in this case
glycine to two glycines and that's pretty not a bad yield uh at about pH again right about pH 9
if you lower the pH uh then after after 20 days or so you can get up to glycine 4 or glycine 6 now
once you've got the glycine 6 that's getting quite useful anything before five four and six
becomes useful and one possible function for these is that they could then through uh then the amine
group uh directly bond to the delta negative on on the amine group things like cobalt and nickel
and could these be very inefficient but basically kind of pigment peptides and could they do we
know these structures exist uh they've never been shown to be active uh because I think they've never
been tested in this way but could these be for example similar to a transfer site for acetal
coenzyme synthase and uh and the site for reduction of the methyl group to to methane so we've got
structures again that everything as I say is kind of on the plate here uh so could we then have a
beginning of a peptide takeover now nobody's shown this this is just paper chemistry as people
would like to point out but here we'd suggest it could nevertheless ferredoxins are the uh according
to Ecken Dayhoff in a wonderful paper in science in 1966 uh have the longest of all pedigrees of all
metal proteins uh could it be the very first one was actually structured in a loop uh through
hydrogen bonding through to that to a thylated ion sulfide so here's here's our cubane structure
and here's the possibility of uh it's actually being thylated sorry uh hydrogen bonded to the
backbone it notice it doesn't matter what the side chains are just the backbone of a short peptide
now of course these days it's and probably fairly early on it's cysteines but cysteine is hard to
make in the lab it may be there were no sulfur bearing amino acid side chains right at the
beginning but you will notice if you people who worked on ferredoxins the ion sulfide is always
in a loop so we'd say then uh working with uh Wolfgang Nitschke uh he's he's suggested and for
various reasons including phylogenetics that the last universal common ancestor which we
would put further back uh but nevertheless uh we'd say that the last universal common ancestor
must have had millibitim di-terrin enzymes had nitric oxide, ridottes, nickel ion, hydrogenase
and acetylcoenzyme synthase and carbon monoxide dehydrogenase which you have to have metals for
this and we'd suggest the metals were right in there right at the beginning uh and eventually
were co-opted so that all sounds part of that is airy fairy maybe but the earlier part I think uh
it holds up well and now we've got the possibility that we've got a phosphate uh and we know we can
see phosphate and pyrophosphate in these situations and that really would interact with the with the
sidechain uh sorry the backbone of uh of short peptide to make a little peptide nest and and
James Milner White and I call this a phosphate egg in in a in a peptide nest and this looks I think
you'll agree very much like the P loop so here's the here's how we would dress that up but as a
slightly longer peptide and we turn this in taking our cue from Enric and Margareta Balczewski we take
the idea that perhaps uh they've the first kind of pyrophosphatase was a proton pyrophosphatase
and that we could drive the generation of orthophosphate from pyrophosphate from
orthophosphate by protons coming through the membrane and having a magnesium ion as the catalyst
of course to because of the repulsion between the phosphates this is required but also this is a
little kind of entropy uh to our mind kind of entropy catalyst as well holding things in because
of the hydrogen bonding from the back of it from the amine group through to the oxygens on the
phosphate so this would say perhaps this is what the early proton pyrophosphatase actually looked
like and perhaps it was uh fired up basically by protons coming through the membrane from the acidic
ocean so here we have the kind of rough equation for this magnesium phosphate plus the plus orthophosphate
plus the proton to give us your magnesium diphosphate if we've got these short peptides what we've
done here is to put four or five peptides actually in the hydrothermal solution the alkaline hydrothermal
solution and when we do that we make even more better ordered structures and these structures are
as you see just beautifully ribbed both inside and outside and glycine apparently gives us the
best structure of all for reasons we don't understand so then we go back then to think
where we've been with us and what we've done is to say take up an idea well a paper from Andrew's
et al who could show that you could get mixed acid fermentation via formate hydrogen hydrogen liase
and the reaction generates hydrogen and co2 from formate and protons and actually
generates a proton motive force and it what is required here is uh one of these molybdenum
enzymes and an iron iron sulfide factor as well and the nickel iron uh as well uh so what we've
thought of and of course this is something we're trying to do in the lab uh is perhaps we could
reduce it perhaps we can turn this around make the protons come inside using nickel iron sulfide
and molybdenum as the as a catalyst and see if we can generate formate and and perhaps formaldehyde
from the inside by reacting co2 and the protons and electrons to make the formate at pH 10 or pH
9 or pH 10 so this becomes uh really uh holy grail that's one question we'd like to answer
so what else does this kind of uh structure offer well we're not we don't know anything
in detail about the RNA well but uh cunin and uh using cunin and cunin and martin and
basket al have suggested that in fact if you've got structures like this then maybe the first RNAs
wherever they come from act like viruses uh and uh basically can permeate through and start to make
uh better replicators as we go through this the structure and but also if you were to make
DNA in this in this series in in this way you could have a polymerase chain reaction which
is run thermally or convectively because it's going to be cool on the outside and hot in the inside
so you're going to have a convective polymerase chain reaction to build up shall we say uh DNA
lengths and then thermophoresis or thermo uh thermal diffusion then tends to drive uh concentrated
molecules that are that are ionic into basically into the coolest area of one of these compartments
so so again we haven't just got the geotherm we haven't just got the redox gradient and the
the pH gradient we've also got a thermal gradient that may help right at the beginning as you start
to gain uh replication so this is the way then we would see the very emergence of life probably
between 50 70 degrees centigrade 40 to 80 maybe uh hydrogen and methane as the fuels
molybdenum tungsten absolutely required as catalysts along with iron iron nickel sulfides
and perhaps the the first actual microbe which we would assume was a bacterium
emanating from the spring not into the ocean by the way but down into the deep biosphere
because i think it's basically a desert in the ocean and it's a dangerous desert as we've seen
but these first this first uh microbes would be generating acetate or acetic acid and then
there'd be some more minor reactions that would generate uh using nitric oxide as the electron
acceptor uh carbon dioxide and nitrogen and water from this reaction uh and this would become to
our minds the methanotroph the methanotrophic archaea so if we put all that together and we've
heard other uh suggestions uh for example this morning about the big bang a big bang when i
go to parties people ask me what i do and i you know i i kind of finally cough if they really seem
to be interested and i tell them i'm working on the origin alive i see them six months later
and they always seem to say oh you're the guy working on the big bang and it kind of pushed
us in to this idea that you know we make the comparison and uh with shaw and carol on hand
he wrote this lovely book called from attorney to here which the older people in the audience
will understand there's a pretty good title and if he starts with a big bang and uh it's a very high
enthalpy low entropy big bang and here we are now and we do the same thing we'd have a big bang
we go from geochemistry to biochemistry but we can't just segue one from the other you you've
got to go through this discontinuity and what helps us through the discontinuity we would say
is the the proton motive force and chemiosmosis which are on tap in in the situation and then
after that uh we get this various evolutions parts of evolution part of which has been covered by
others of course this is huge yawning gap between metabolism and uh and replication and and we don't
deny that one thing i would say though and and that is that nearly everybody that's been talking
about RNA and DNA and uh enzymes are on the other side of a canyon for me i admit that but we can
see each other from either side we're not that down there or up there we've got there is a lot
in common between mineralogy and geochemistry and the very fact of the initial conditions
that uh i think will eventually allow us to converge uh and just to emphasize that you know
we've got 10 to the power of 17 microseconds and i really do think that's enough time for
life to emerge imagine what 200 postdocs could do for you in that amount of time uh 24 7 of
course 365 as usual that's it thank you very much