They don't care about AI safety.
What they care about is AI control.
Do I think we eventually get to a configuration like that?
Maybe.
Where you have an AI brain is at the center of civilization,
and it's coordinating all the people around it.
And every civilization that makes it
is capable of crowdfunding and operating its own AI.
You know, our background culture influences things
in ways we don't even think about.
So much of the paperclip thinking
is like a vengeful god will turn you into pillars of salt.
The polytheistic model of many gods, as opposed to one god,
is we're all going to have our own AI gods,
and there'll be war of the gods.
Man-machine symbiosis is not some new thing.
It's actually the old thing that broke us away
from other primate lineages that weren't using tools.
Then the question is, what's the next step?
Which is AI is amplified intelligence.
It is that the AI human fusion
means there's another 20 Elon Musk's,
or whatever the number is.
That's good.
Hello, and welcome to The Cognitive Revolution,
where we interview visionary researchers, entrepreneurs,
and builders working on the frontier
of artificial intelligence.
Each week, we'll explore their revolutionary ideas,
and together, we'll build a picture
of how AI technology will transform work, life,
and society in the coming years.
I'm Nathan LaBenz, joined by my co-host, Eric Torenberg.
Hello, and welcome back to The Cognitive Revolution.
Today, my guest is biology, Srinivasan.
In tech circles, biology needs no introduction.
But for folks from other backgrounds,
biology is a serial startup entrepreneur
who's founded and ultimately sold
highly dissimilar technology companies,
including Teleport,
which helped people move around the world
to realize opportunities,
Council, which provided genetic testing
for couples planning to have children,
and Earn.com, a paid email on the blockchain startup,
which ultimately sold to Coinbase,
where biology became CTO.
Along the way, he's also taught statistics at Stanford
and been a general partner at Andreessen Horowitz as well.
Today, as an independent thinker, investor,
and author of the network state,
biology is extremely prolific
in both text and audio formats.
And as you'll hear,
whether for the first time or the 50th,
he is an incredibly creative thinker
who relentlessly develops and iterates
on new paradigms for understanding
a fast-changing, often chaotic world.
He's also a very associative
and interdisciplinary thinker
who constantly adds dimensions to any analysis.
Such horsepower can be hard
for a podcast host to rein in,
but I personally find it extremely stimulating.
So in this conversation,
I tried to strike a balance
between letting biology go off as only he can do,
contributing what I hope are worthy versions
of core AI safety arguments
and supporting results from recent research,
and occasionally,
steering us back toward what I see
as the most critical questions for the AI big picture.
If there's one area where biology and I
disagree most consequentially,
it's on the question of how independent AI systems
are likely to become over the next five to 10 years.
Biology thinks that AI systems
need to be at least symbiotic with humans,
because physical computers
can't replicate themselves without human support.
While I think there's at least a significant chance
that we get AIs that are so independent of humans
that their behaviors and interactions
become the primary drivers of world history.
In biology's own words,
he does expect massive economic
and social disruption from AI,
but doesn't think that quote-unquote
can't turn the killer AI off scenarios,
are likely, at least for a long while,
due to factors like the existence of adversarial inputs
that can paralyze AIs,
particularly those with open model weights,
the observation that even decentralized programs
like the Bitcoin network can't run independently
without continuous human support,
and the premise that to control the physical world,
AIs will need to direct either large numbers of humans
who are notoriously difficult to control
or highly agile robots which don't yet exist.
With all that in mind,
in the first half of this conversation,
you'll hear biology's analysis
of the likely impact of AI
in a world where powerful AI systems do come to exist,
but humans retain control,
resulting in a human AI symbiosis
similar to how believers relate to their gods
or citizens relate to their governments.
Then in the second half,
we really dig into the question
of just how confident we should be
that AI won't prove to be even more revolutionary than that.
After more than two hours of recording,
I was the one who ran out of time today,
but I really enjoyed this conversation with biology.
He is as good-natured and curious as he is opinionated,
and we have continued to exchange links and arguments offline,
such that I hope we'll have another episode
to share with you in the future as well.
As always, if you're enjoying the show,
we'd ask that you take a moment to share it with a friend.
And with that, here's part one of an all-angles look
at how AI will shape the future with biology, Srinivasan.
Biology, Srinivasan, welcome to the Cognitive Revolution.
All right, I feel welcome.
Well, we've got a ton to talk about.
Obviously, you bring a lot of different perspectives
to everything that you think about and work on.
And today, I want to just try to muster
all those different perspectives onto this.
What I see is really the defining question of our time,
which is like, what's up with AI?
And how's it going to turn out?
I thought maybe for starters,
I would love to just get your baseline kind of table
setting on how much more AI progress do you expect us to see
over the next few years?
Like how powerful are AI systems going to become
in, again, kind of a relatively short timeline?
And then maybe if you want to take a bigger stab at it,
you could answer that same question for a longer timeline
like the rest of our lives or whatever.
Sure. Let me give an abstract answer,
then let me give a technical answer.
If you look at evolution, we've seen something as complex
as flight evolve independently in birds, bats, and bees.
And even intelligence, we've seen fairly high intelligence
in dolphins, in whales, in octopuses.
Octopus in particular can do like tool manipulation.
They've got things that are a lot like hands with tentacles.
And so that indicates that it is plausible
that you could have multiple pathways to intelligence,
whether we have carbon-based intelligence,
so we could have silicon-based intelligence
that just has a totally different form
where the fundamental thing is an electromagnetic wave
and data storage as opposed to DNA and so on.
So that's like a plausibility argument
in terms of evolution is being so resourceful
that it's invented really complicated things
in different ways.
Then in terms of the technical point,
I think as of right now, I should probably date it,
December 11, 2023, because this field moves so fast, right?
My view is, and maybe you'll have a different view,
is that the breakthroughs that are really needed
for something that's like true artificial intelligence
that is human-independent, right?
Maybe the next step after the Turing test,
I've got an article that we're writing
called the Turing Thresholds,
which tries to generalize the Turing test
to like the Kardashev scale.
Have you got energy thresholds?
What are useful scales beyond that?
And right now, I think that what we call AI
is absolutely amazing for environments
that are not time-varying or rule-varying.
And what I mean by that is, so you kind of have,
let's say two large schools of AI,
and obviously there's overlap
in terms of the personnel and so on,
but there's like the DeepMind School,
which has gotten less press recently,
but got more press a few years ago,
and that is game-playing, right?
It is super human-playing of go without go.
It is all the video game stuff they've done
where they learn at the pixel level
and they just teach the very basic rules
and it figures it out from there.
And it's also the protein folding stuff
and what have you, right?
But in general, I think they're known
for reinforcement learning and those kinds of approaches.
I mean, they're good at a lot of things,
but that's what I think DeepMind is known for.
Of course, they put out this new model recently,
the Gemini model.
So I'm not saying that they're not good at everything,
but that's just kind of what they're maybe most known for.
And then you have the OpenAI ChatGBT School of Generative AI,
and it includes stable diffusion and just as a pioneer,
even if they're not,
I don't know how much they're used right now,
but basically, you have the diffusion models for images
and you have large language models
and now you have the multimodals that integrate them.
And so the difference, I think with these,
is the reinforcement learning approaches
are based on an assumption of static rules,
like the rules of chess, the rules that go,
the rules of a video game are not changing with time.
They are discoverable.
They're like the laws of physics.
And similarly, like the body of language
where you're learning it,
English is not rapidly time varying.
That is to say, the rules of grammar
that are implicit aren't changing.
The meanings of words aren't changing very rapidly.
You can argue they're changing over the span of decades
or centuries, but not extremely rapidly, right?
So therefore, when you generate a new result,
training data from five years ago for English
is actually still fairly valuable
and the same input roughly gives the same output.
Now, of course, there are facts that change with time,
like who is the ruler of England, right?
The queen of England is passed away now.
It's the king of England, right?
It's just facts that change with time.
But I think more fundamentally
is when there's rules that change with time.
You have, for example, changes in law in countries, right?
But most interestingly, perhaps changes in markets
because the same input
does not give the same output in a market.
If you try that, then what will happen
is there's adversarial behavior on the other side.
And once people see it enough times,
they'll see your strategy
and they're going to trade against you on that, right?
And I can get to other technical examples on that,
but I think, and probably people in the space
are aware of this,
but I think that is a true frontier
is dealing with time-varying, rule-varying systems,
as opposed to systems where the implicit rules are static.
Let me pause there.
Yeah, I think that makes sense.
I think in the very practical,
just trying to get, as Zvi calls it,
mundane utility from AI,
that is often cashed out to AI is good at tasks,
but it's not good at whole jobs.
It can handle these small things
where you can define what good looks like
and tell it exactly what to do.
But in the broader context of handling things
that come up as they come up,
it's definitely not there yet.
And I agree that there's likely to be some synthesis,
which is kind of the subject of all the Q-star rumors recently,
I would say is kind of the prospect
that there could be already within the labs
a beginning of a synthesis between the,
I kind of think of it as like harder-edged reinforcement
learning systems that are like small, efficient, and deadly,
versus the language model systems
that are like kind of slow and soft,
and but have a sense of our values,
which is really a remarkable accomplishment
that they're able to have even an approximation of our values
that seems like reasonably good.
So yeah, I think I agree with that framing,
but I guess I would still wonder like,
how far do you think this goes in the near term?
Because I have a lot of uncertainty about that,
and I think the field has a lot of uncertainty.
You hear people say, well,
it's never going to get smarter than its training data.
It'll kind of level out where humans are,
but we certainly don't see that
in the reinforcement learning side, right?
Like once, it usually don't take too long
at human level of these games,
and then it like blows past human level.
Interestingly, you do still see some adversarial vulnerability,
like there's a great paper from the team at FAR AI,
and I'm planning to have Adam Gleave,
the head of that organization on soon,
to talk about that and other things,
where they found like a, basically a hack
where a really simple, but unexpected attack
on the superhuman go player can defeat it.
So you do have these like very interesting vulnerabilities
or kind of lack of adversarial robustness.
Still kind of wondering like,
where do you think that leaves us
in say a three to five years time?
Obviously, huge uncertainty on that.
It's really hard to predict something like this.
Just to your point, generative AI is generic AI, right?
It's like generically smart,
but doesn't have specific intelligence
or creativity or facts.
And as you're saying, just like we have,
you know, adversarial images back in full programs
that are trained on a certain set of data
and they just give some weird, you know, pattern
that looks like a giraffe,
but the algorithm thinks it's a dog.
You can do the same thing for game playing
and you can have out of sample input
that can beat, you know,
these very sophisticated reinforcement learners.
And an interesting question is whether
that is a fundamental thing
or whether it is a work aroundable thing.
And you'd think it was work aroundable, you know,
because there's probably some robustification
because these pictures look like giraffes, you know,
and yet they're being recognized as dogs.
So you would think that the right proximity metric
would group it with giraffes, you know,
but maybe there's some, I don't know,
maybe there's some result there.
My intuition would be we can probably robustify these systems
so that they are less vulnerable to adversarial input.
But if we can't, then that leads us
in a totally different direction,
where these systems are fragile in a fundamental way.
So that's one big branch point is how fragile these systems are
because if they're fragile in a certain way,
then it's almost like you can always kill them,
which is kind of good, right?
In a sense, that there's that, you know,
almost like the, you know, the 50 IQ, 100 IQ, 150 IQ thing.
Like the meme?
Yeah, the meme, right?
So the 50 IQ guys like these machines
will never be as creative as humans or whatever.
100 IQ is look at all the things they can do.
The 150 IQ is like, well, there's some like equivalent result,
you know, that's like some impossibility proof
that shows that we, the dimensional space of a giraffe
is too high and we can't actually learn what a true giraffe.
I don't think that's true, but maybe it's true
from the perspective of how these learners are working
because my understanding is people have been trying,
and I mean, I'm not on the cutting edge of this.
So, you know, maybe someone,
but my understanding is we haven't yet been able to
robustify these models against adversarial input.
Am I wrong about that?
Yeah, that's definitely right.
Hey, we'll continue our interview in a moment
after a word from our sponsors.
I've used it in the past at the companies I've founded,
and when we launch Merch here at Turpentine,
Shopify will be our go-to.
Shopify helps turn browsers into buyers
with the internet's best converting checkout
up to 36% better compared to other leading commerce platforms.
And Shopify helps you sell more with less effort
thanks to Shopify Magic, your AI-powered all-star.
With Shopify Magic, whip up captivating content
that converts from blog posts to product descriptions.
Generate instant FAQ answers.
Pick the perfect email send time.
Plus, Shopify Magic is free for every Shopify seller.
Businesses that grow, grow with Shopify.
Sign up for a $1 per month trial period
at Shopify.com slash cognitive.
Go to Shopify.com slash cognitive now
to grow your business no matter what stage you're in.
Shopify.com slash cognitive.
There's no single architecture as far as I know
that is demonstrably robust.
And on the contrary, even with language models,
there's a...
We did a whole episode on the universal jailbreak
where especially if you have access to the weights,
not to change the weights,
but just to probe around in the weights,
then you have a really hard time
guaranteeing any sort of robustness.
The conjecture is, see, for humans,
you can't mirror their brain and analyze it.
Okay?
But we have enough humans that we've got things
like optical illusions, stuff like that,
that works on enough humans
and our brains aren't changing enough, right?
A conjecture is, as you said, open weights.
Open weights mean safety because if you have open weights,
you can always reverse engineer adversarial input
and then you can always break the system.
Conjecture.
Yeah, that's again with Adam from Far AI.
I'm really interested to get into that
because they are starting to study,
as I understand it,
kind of proto-scaling laws for adversarial robustness.
And I think a huge question there is,
what are the kind of frontiers of possibility there?
How do the orders of magnitude work?
Do you need another 10x as much adversarial training
to half the rate of your adversarial failures?
And if so, can we generate that many?
It may always sort of be fleeting.
So, Far AI and they are working on cutting edge
of adversarial input.
Yeah, they're the group that did the attack
on the Alpha Go model and found that, like, you know,
and what was really interesting about that,
I mean, multiple things, right?
First, that they could beat a super human Go player at all.
But second, that the technique that they used
would not work at all if playing a quality human.
Or is, you know, it's a strategy that is trivial to beat
if you're a quality human Go player,
but the Alpha Go is just totally blind to it.
You know, that's why I say the conjecture is,
if you have the model,
then you can generate the adversarial input.
And then, so if that is true,
and that itself is an important conjecture about AI safety,
right? Because if open weights are inherently something
where you can generate adversarial input from that
and break or crash or defeat the AI,
then that AI is not omnipotent, right?
You have some power words you can speak to
at almost like magical words that'll just make it
power down, so to speak, right?
It's like those movies where the monsters can't see you
if you stand really still or if you don't make a noise
or something like that, right?
They're very powerful on Dimension X,
but they're very weak on Dimension Y.
A kind of an obvious point, but, you know,
I'm not sure how important it's going to be in the future.
Your next question was on like, you know,
humanoid robots and so on, and before we get to that,
maybe obviously, but all of these models are trained
on things that we can easily record,
which are sights and sounds, right?
But touch and taste and smell,
we don't have amazing data sets on those.
Well, I mean, there's some haptic stuff, right?
There's probably some, you know,
some work on taste and smell and so on,
but there's five senses, right?
I wonder if there's something like that where you might be like,
okay, how are you going to outsmell a robot
or something like that?
Well, dogs actually have a very powerful sense of smell,
and that's being very important for them, you know?
And it may turn out that there's,
maybe it's just that we just haven't collected the data,
and it could become a much better smeller or whatever,
or, you know, taster than anything else.
I wouldn't be surprised.
It could be a much better wine taster,
because you can do molecular diagnostics.
But it's just kind of, I just use that as an analogy to say,
there's areas of the human experience
that we haven't yet quantified,
and maybe it's just the opera term is yet, okay?
But there's areas of the human experience
we haven't yet quantified,
which are also an area that AIs at least
are not yet capable of.
Yeah, I guess maybe my expectation boils down to,
I think the really powerful systems
are probably likely to mix architectures
in some sort of ensemble.
You know, when you think about just the structure of the brain,
it's not, I mean, there certainly are aspects of it
that are repeated, right?
You look at the frontal cortex,
and it's like there is kind of this, you know,
unit that gets repeated over and over again,
in a sense that's kind of analogous to say,
the transformer block that just gets,
you know, stacked layer on layer.
But it is striking in a transformer
that it's basically the same exact mechanism
at every layer that's doing kind of
all the different kinds of processing.
And so whatever weaknesses that structure has,
and you know, with the transformer
and the attention mechanism,
there's like some pretty profound ones,
like finite context window, you know, you kind of need,
I would think, a different sort of architecture
with a little bit of a different strength
and weakness profile to complement that in such a way that,
you know, kind of more similar to like a biological system
where you kind of have this like dynamic feedback
where, you know, we have obviously, you know,
thinking fast and slow and all sorts of different modules
in the brain and they kind of cross regulate each other
and don't let any one system, you know,
go totally, you know, down the wrong path on its own, right?
Without something kind of coming back
and trying to override that.
It seems to me like that's a big part
of what is missing from the current crop of AIs
in terms of their robustness.
And I don't know how long that takes to show up,
but we are starting to see some, you know, possibly,
you know, I think people are maybe thinking
about this a little bit the wrong way.
They're just in the last couple of weeks,
there's been a number of papers
that are really looking at the state space model
kind of alternative.
It's being framed as an alternative to the transformer.
But when I see that I'm much more like,
it's probably a compliment to the transformer
or, you know, these two things probably get integrated
in some form because to the degree
that they do have very different strengths and weaknesses,
ultimately you're going to want the best of both
in a robust system.
Certainly if you're trying to make an agent,
certainly if you're trying to make, you know,
a humanoid robot that can go around your house
and like do useful work,
but also be robust enough that it doesn't,
you get tricked into attacking your kid
or your dog or, you know, whatever,
you're going to want to have more checks and balances
than just kind of a single stack of, you know,
the same block over and over again.
Well, so I know Boston Dynamics with their legged robots
is all control theory and it's not classical ML.
It's really interesting to see how they've accomplished it.
And they do have essentially a state space model
where they have a big position vector
that's got all the coordinates of all the joints
and then a bunch of matrix algebra to figure out
how this thing is moving and all the feedback control
and so on there.
And it's more complicated than that,
but that's, you know, I think the V1 of it.
Sorry, it was there.
I wasn't following this though.
Are you saying that there's papers
that are integrating that with the kind of
generator transformer model?
You know, like what's a good citation for me to look at?
Yeah, starting to, we did an episode, for example,
with one of the technology leads at Skydio,
the, you know, the U.S. is champion drone maker.
And they have kind of a similar thing
where they have built over, you know, a decade, right?
A fully explicit multiple orders of, you know,
spanning multiple orders of magnitude control stack.
And now over the top of that,
they're starting to layer this kind of, you know,
it's not exactly generative AI in their case
because they're not like generating content,
but it's kind of the high level, you know,
can I give the thing verbal instructions?
Have it go out and kind of understand,
okay, like this is a bridge, I'm supposed to kind of,
you know, survey the bridge and translate
those high level instructions to a plan
and then use the lower level explicit code
that is fully deterministic and, you know,
runs on control theory and all that kind of stuff
to actually execute the plan at a low level.
But also, you know, at times like surface errors
up to the top and say like, hey, we've got a problem,
you know, whatever, I'm not able to do it.
You know, can you now, at the higher level,
the semantic layer adjust the plan?
That stuff is starting to happen in multiple domains,
I would say.
Yeah, and so I think that makes sense,
is basically it's like generative AI is almost the front end,
and then you have almost like an assembly,
like you give instructions to Figma
and the objects there are their shapes
and their images and so on, it's not text.
You give instructions to a drone
and the objects are like GPS coordinates and paths and so on.
And so you are generating structures
that are in a different domain,
or it's like in VR, you're generating 3D structures,
again, as opposed to text, and then that compute engine
takes those three structures
and does something with them in a much more rules-based way.
So you have like a statistical user-friendly front end
with a generative AI, and then you have a more deterministic
or usually totally deterministic,
almost like assembly language back end
that actually takes that and does something.
That's what you're saying, right?
Yeah, pretty much, and I would say there's another analogy
to just, again, our biological experience
where it's like I'm sort of in a semi-conscious level, right?
I kind of think about what I want to do,
but the low-level movements of the hand
are both like not conscious,
and also if I do encounter some pain or hit some hot item
or whatever, there's a quick reaction
that's sort of mediated by a lower level control system,
and then that fires back up to the brain
and is like, hey, we need a new plan here.
So that is only starting to come into focus, I think,
with, because obviously these, I mean, it's amazing,
as you said, it's all moving so fast.
What is always striking to me,
and I kind of like recite timelines to myself
almost as like a mantra, right?
Like the first instruction following AI
that hit the public was just January 2022.
That was OpenAI's Text of Ingee 002.
It was the first one where you could say like do X,
and it would do X as opposed to having
an elaborate prompt engineering type of setup.
GPT-4 just a little over a year ago finished training,
not even a year that it's been in the public,
and it has been amazing to see how quickly
this kind of technology is being integrated into those systems,
but it's definitely still very much a work in progress.
Yeah, I mean, the tricky part is the training data and so on.
Like a large existing scale company like a Figma or DJI
that has millions or billions of user sessions
will have a much easier time training,
and they have a unique data set,
and then everybody else will not be able to do that.
So there is actually almost like,
I mean, a return on scale where the massive data set,
if you've got a massive clean data set
and a unique domain that lots of people are using,
then you can crush it.
And if you don't, I suppose,
I mean, there's lots of people who work on zero shot stuff
and sort of sort of, but it still strikes me
that there'll probably be an advantage to see those sessions.
I find it hard to believe that you could generate
a really good drone command language
without lots of drone flight paths, but you can see.
And where it doesn't exist, people are,
obviously you need deep pockets for this,
but the likes of Google are starting to just
grind out the generation of that, right?
They've got their kind of test kitchen,
which is a literal physical kitchen at Google
where the robots go around and do tasks.
And when they get stuck, my understanding
of their kind of critical path, as I understand,
they understand it, is robots gonna get stuck,
will have a human operator remotely operate the robot
to show what to do, and then that data becomes
the bridge from what the robot can't do
to what it's supposed to learn to do next time.
And they're gonna need a lot of that, for sure.
But they increasingly have,
I don't know exactly how many robots they have now,
but last I talked to someone there,
it was like into the dozens,
and presumably they're continuing to scale that.
I think they just view that they can probably brute force it
to the point where it's good enough to put out into the world,
and then very much like a Waymo or a cruise
or whatever, they probably still have remote operators,
even when the robot is in your home,
when it encounters something
that it doesn't know what to do about, raise that alarm,
get the human supervision to help it over the hump,
and then obviously that's where you really get the scale
that you're talking about.
And this raises a couple of questions I wanted to ask
that are conceptual.
So obviously there's huge questions around like,
again, highest level, how is all this gonna play out?
One big debate is to what degree does AI favor the incumbents?
To what degree does it enable startups?
Obviously it's both,
but I'm interested in your perspective on that.
Also really interested in your perspective
on like offense versus defense.
That's something that a lot of people
now and in the future,
that seems like it probably really matters a lot,
whether it's a more offense enabling
or defense enabling technology.
So I love your take on those two dimensions.
Hey, we'll continue our interview in a moment
after a word from our sponsors.
Omniki uses generative AI
to enable you to launch hundreds of thousands
of ad iterations that actually work,
customized across all platforms with a click of a button.
I believe in Omniki so much that I invested in it
and I recommend you use it too.
Use Cogrev to get a 10% discount.
If you're a startup founder or executive
running a growing business,
you know that as you scale,
your systems break down and the cracks start to show.
If this resonates with you,
there are three numbers you need to know,
36,000, 25, and one, 36,000.
That's the number of businesses
which have upgraded to NetSuite by Oracle.
NetSuite is the number one cloud financial system,
streamline accounting, financial management,
inventory, HR, and more, 25.
NetSuite turns 25 this year.
That's 25 years of helping businesses do more with less,
close their books in days, not weeks, and drive down costs.
One, because your business is one of a kind,
so you get a customized solution for all your KPIs
in one efficient system with one source of truth.
Manage risk, get reliable forecasts, and improve margins.
Everything you need, all in one place.
Right now, download NetSuite's popular KPI checklist,
designed to give you consistently excellent performance,
absolutely free, and netsuite.com slash cognitive.
That's netsuite.com slash cognitive
to get your own KPI checklist.
NetSuite.com slash cognitive.
So like offense or defense
in the sense of disenabled disruptors or incumbents?
Both in business and in like,
you know, potentially outright conflict.
I'd be interested to hear your analysis on both.
All right, a lot of views on this.
So obviously, if you've got a competent, existing tech CEO,
you know, like who's still in their prime,
like Amjad of Replit, or, you know, Dillon Field of Figma,
or, you know, those are two who have thought of,
who are very good and, you know, will be on top of it.
Amjad is very early on integrating AI into Replit,
and it's basically built that into an AI first company,
which is really impressive.
Those are folks who cleanly made a pivot.
It's as big or bigger than, comparable to, I would say,
the pivot from desktop to mobile
that broke a bunch of companies
in the late 2000s and early 2010s.
Like Facebook in 2012 had no mobile revenue, roughly,
at the time of their IPO,
and then they had to like redo the whole thing.
And it's hard to turn a company 90 degrees
when something new like that hits, you know?
Those that are run by kind of tech CEOs in their prime
will adapt and will AI-ify their existing services.
And the question is, obviously,
there's new things that are coming out,
like pika and character.ai.
There's some like really good stuff that's out there.
The question is, you know,
will the disruption be allowed to happen
in the U.S. regulatory environment?
And so my view is actually that, you know,
so this is from like the network state book, right?
You know, people talk about a multipolar world
or unipolar world.
The political axis is actually really important
in my view for thinking about
whether AI will be allowed to disrupt, okay?
Because we'll get to this probably later,
but the 640K of compute is enough
for everyone executive order.
You know, 640K of memory, the apocryphal,
he didn't delegate to actually say it,
but that quote kind of gives a certain mindset
about computing.
That should be enough for everybody.
So the 10 to the 26 of compute
should be enough for everyone bill.
I actually think it's very bad
and I think it's just the beginning
of their attempts to build like a software FDA, okay?
To decelerate, control, regulate, red tape,
the entire space, just like how, you know,
the threat of nuclear terrorism got turned into the TSA.
The threat of, you know, terminators and AGI
gets turned into a million rules
on whether you can set up servers
and this last free sector of the economy
is strangled or at least controlled
within the territory control by Washington DC.
Now, why does this relate to the political?
Well, obviously this, you know,
you can just spend your entire life
just tracking AI papers
and that's moving like at the speed of light like this, right?
What's also happening
as you can kind of see in your peripheral vision
is there's political developments
that are happening at the speed of light
much faster than they've happened in our lifespans.
Like there's more, you just noticed,
more wars, more serious online conflicts
like, you know, there's a sovereign debt crisis.
All of those things that can show graph after graph
of things looking like their own types of singularities, you know,
like military debts are way up, you know,
the long piece that Steven Pinker showed
that's looking like a you
that suddenly way up after Ukraine
and some of these other wars are happening, unfortunately, right?
Interest payments, whoosh, way up to the side.
What's my point?
Point is, I think that the world is going to become
from the Pax Americana world
of just like basically one superpower,
a hyperpower that we grew up in from 91 to 2021, roughly,
that we're going to get a specifically tripolar world,
not unipolar, not bipolar, not multipolar, but tripolar.
And those three poles, I kind of think of as NYT, CCP, BTC,
or you could think of them as,
and those are just certain labels that are associated with them,
but they're roughly U.S. tech, the U.S. environment,
China tech and China environment,
and global tech and the global environment.
And why do I identify BTC and crypto and so on with global tech?
Because that's a tech that decentralized out of the U.S.
And right now people think of crypto as finance,
but it's also financiers.
Okay, and in this next run-up,
it is, I think, quite likely about, depending on how you count,
between a third to a half of the world's billionaires will be crypto.
Okay, around, you know, I calculated this a while back around,
Bitcoin at a few hundred thousands,
around a third to a half the world's billionaires are crypto.
That's the unlocked pool of capital.
And those are the people who do not bow to D.C. or Beijing.
And they might, by the way, be Indians or Israelis
or every other demographic in the world,
or they could be American libertarians,
or they could be Chinese liberals like Jack Ma,
who are pushed out of Beijing sphere.
Okay, or the next Jack Ma.
You know, Jack Ma himself may not be able to do too much, okay?
That group of people who are, let's say, the dissident technologists
who are not going to just kneel to anything
that comes out of Washington D.C. or Beijing,
that is the, that's decentralized AI.
That's crypto.
That's decentralized social media.
So you can think of it as, you know,
where we talked about in the recent Pirate Warriors podcast,
freedom to speak with decentralized censorship-resistant social media,
freedom to transact with cryptocurrency,
freedom to compute with open source AI.
And no compute limits, okay?
That's a freedom movement.
And that's like the same spirit as a pirate bay,
the same spirit as BitTorrent,
the same spirit as Bitcoin,
the same spirit as peer-to-peer and end-to-end encryption.
That's a very different spirit than
having Kamala Harris regulate a superintelligence
or signing it over to Xi Jinping thought.
And the reason I say this is, I think that that group of people,
of which I think Indians and Israelis will be a very prominent,
maybe a plurality, right?
Just because the sheer quantity of Indians
are like the third sort of big group that's kind of coming up.
And they're relatively underpriced.
You know, China is, I don't say it's price to perfection,
but it's something that people, when I say priced,
I mean, people were dismissive of China even up until 2019.
And then it was after 2020,
if you look that people started to take China seriously.
And I mean, that is the West Coast tech people
knew that China actually had A plus tech companies
and was a very strong competitor.
But the East Coast still thought of them as a third-world country
until after COVID, when now, you know,
the East Coast was sort of threatened by them politically.
And it wasn't just blue collars, but blue America
that was threatened by China.
And so that's why the reaction to China went from,
oh, who cares, it's just taking some manufacturing jobs to,
this is an empire that can contend with us
for control of the world.
That's why the hostility is ramped up, in my view.
There's a lot of other dimensions to it,
but that's a big part of it.
So India is also kind of there, but it's like the third.
And India is not going to play for number one or number two.
But India and Israel, if you look at like tech founders,
depending on how you count, especially if you include diasporas,
it's on the order of 30 to 50% of tech founders, right?
And it's obviously some, you know, very good tech CEOs
and, you know, Satya and Sundar and investors and whatnot.
Those are folks Indians do not want to bow to DC or to Beijing,
neither do Israelis for all kinds of reasons,
even if Israel has to, you know,
take some direction from the U.S.
Now they're bristling at it, right?
And then a bunch of other countries don't.
So the question is, who breaks away?
And now we get to your point on,
the reason I had to say that is that that's preface,
the political environment, this tripolar thing of U.S. tech
and U.S. regulated, Chinese tech and China regulated,
and global tech that's free.
Okay, of course there's, even though I identify those three polls,
there's of course boundary regions.
EAC is actually on the boundary of U.S. tech
and decentralized tech, you know?
And I'm sure there'll be some Chinese thing that comes out
that is also on the boundary there.
For example, Binance is on the boundary of Chinese tech
and global and decentralized tech,
if that makes any sense, right?
And there's probably others, Apple is actually
on the boundary of U.S. tech and Chinese tech
because they make all of their stuff in China, right?
So these are not totally disjoint groups,
but there's boundary areas, but you can think of them.
Why is this third group so important in my view?
Both the Chinese group and the decentralized group
will be very strong competition for the American group
for totally different reasons.
China has things like WeChat, these super apps,
I mean, obviously not likely,
WeChat is a super app, but they also have,
for example, their digital yuan, right?
They have the largest, cleanest data sets in the world
that are constantly updated in real time
that they can mandate their entire population opt into,
and most of the Chinese language speaking people
are under their ambit, right?
So that doesn't include Taiwan, doesn't include Singapore,
doesn't include some of the Chinese diaspora,
but basically anything that's happening in Chinese
for 99% of it, 95, whatever the ratio is, they can see it
and they can coerce it and they can control it.
So they can tell all of their people,
okay, here's five bucks in digital yuan,
do this micro task, okay?
All of these digital blue collar jobs,
both China and India, I think,
can do quite a lot with that and they'll come back to it.
So they can make their people do immense amounts
of training data, clean up lots of data sets,
once it's clear that you have to build this and do this,
they can just kind of execute on that.
And they can also deploy, I mean, in many ways,
the US is still very strong in digital technology,
but in the physical world, it's terrible
because of all the regulations,
it causes all the nimbyism and so on.
It's not like that in China.
So anything which kind of works in the US
at a physical level, like the Boston Dynamic stuff,
they're already cloning it in China
and they can scale it out in the physical world.
You already have drones, little sidewalk drone things
that come to your hotel room and drop things off.
That's already very common in China.
In many ways, it's already ahead
if you go to the Chinese cities.
So the Chinese version of AI is ultra centralized,
more centralized, more monitoring, less privacy
and so on than the American version,
and therefore they will have potentially better data sets,
at least for the Chinese population.
And so we chat AI, I don't even know what it's gonna be,
but it'll be probably really good.
It'll also be really dangerous in other ways.
Then the decentralized sphere has power for a different reason
because the decentralized sphere
can train on full Hollywood movies.
It can train on all books, all MP3s.
And just say, screw all this copyright stuff, right?
Like what Psyhub and Libgen are doing.
Because all the copyright, first of all,
it's not, it's like Disney lobbying politicians
to put like another 60 or 70 or 90.
I don't even know what it is,
some crazy amount on copyrights.
So you can keep milking this stuff
and it doesn't go into public domain, number one.
And second, you know how Hollywood is built
in the first place?
It was all patent copyright and IP violation.
Essentially Edison had all the patents.
He's in New Jersey-ish, okay, that East Coast area.
And Neil Gabler has this great book
called An Empire of Their Own
where he talks about how immigrant populations,
the Jewish community in particular,
and also others went to Southern California in part
so they could just make movies
so that Edison coming and suing them
for all the patents and so on and so forth.
And they made enough money
that they could fight those battles in court
and that's how they built Hollywood, okay?
So one of my big thesis is history is running in reverse
and I can get to why,
but it's like 1950s, a mirror moment
and you go more decentralized backwards
and forwards in time is like these,
you have these huge centralized states
like the US and USSR and China, you know,
all these things exist and then their fist relaxes
as you go forwards and backwards in time.
For example, backwards in time,
the Western frontier closed
and forwards in time, the Eastern frontier opens.
Backwards in time, you have the robber barons,
forwards in time, you have the tech billionaires.
Backwards in time, you have Spanish flu,
forwards in time, you have COVID-19.
And I've got dozens of examples of this in the book.
The point is that if you go backwards in time,
the ability to enforce patents and copyrights and so on
starts dropping off, right?
You have much more of a Grand Theft Auto environment
and you go forwards in time and that's happening again.
So India in particular, for many years,
basically just didn't obey Western patent protections
and all these stupid rules basically, you know,
it's a combination of artificial scarcity on the patent side
and artificial regulation on the FDI side.
That's a big part of what jacksup drug costs,
where these things cost, you know,
only cents to manufacturing,
they sell them for so much money.
All the delays, of course, that are imposed on the process,
the only way they can pay for it,
the manufacturers, is to take it out of your hide.
What India did is they just said,
we're not going to obey any of that stuff.
So they have a whole massive generic drugs
and biotech industry that arose
because they built all the skills for that.
That's why they could do their own vaccine during COVID
and they're one of the biggest biotech industries in the world
because they said screw Western restrictive IPs
and other stuff, right?
So I was actually talking with the founder of Flipkart,
that's India's largest exit.
And we were talking about this a few months ago,
and what we want is for India and other countries like it,
do something similar, not just generic drugs,
but generic AI, meaning just let people train on Hollywood movies,
let them train on full songs,
let them train on every book,
let them train on anything.
And you know what, sue them in India, right?
And have the servers in India
and let people also train models in India
because that's something that can build up a domestic industry
with skills that the rest of the world,
people will want the model output,
they'll want to use the software service there,
and they'll be fighting in court on the back end.
This is similar to how all of the record companies
fought Napster and Kazaa and so on,
but they couldn't take down Spotify.
Do you know that story? Do you remember that?
Basically, because Spotify was legitimately a European company
and that a combination of execution and negotiation,
they couldn't take them down.
They did take down Napster, they took down Limewire,
they took down Groove Shark,
and Kazaa had Estonians,
I don't know exactly how it was incorporated,
but it was probably two U.S. proximal,
and that's where they were able to get them.
But Spotify was far enough away
that they couldn't just sue them
and they actually genuinely had European traction.
That's why the RA had to negotiate.
So being far away from San Francisco
may also be an advantage in AI,
because it means you're far away from the blue city
in the blue state in the Union.
This relates to another really important point.
When you actually think about deploying AI,
there's those jobs you can disrupt
that are not regulated jobs.
Like, obviously, programmers are not,
thank God, you don't need a license to be a programmer,
but programmers adopt this kind of stuff naturally.
So get up, co-pilot, replete.
We just, boom, use it,
and now it's amplified intelligence.
But a lot of other jobs,
there's some that are unionized
and then some that are licensed.
So Hollywood screenwriters are complaining.
Journalists are complaining.
Artists are complaining.
This is a good chunk of Blue America.
If you add in licensed jobs,
like lawyers and doctors and bureaucrats,
especially lawyers and doctors
are very politically powerful,
MDs and JDs.
They have strong lobbying organizations,
AMA and APN and so on.
Basically, AI is part
of the economic apocalypse for Blue America.
It just attacks these overpriced jobs.
And they say overpriced relative to
what an Indian could do with an Android phone,
what a South American could do with an Android phone,
what someone in the Middle East
or the Midwest could do with an Android phone.
Now, those folks have been armed
with generative AI.
They can do way more.
They're ready to work.
They're ready to work for much less money.
And they're a massive threat to Blue America.
Blue America is now feeling
like the blue collars of 10 or 20 years ago,
where the blue collars had their jobs,
going to China and other places,
and they were mad about that.
Factories got shut down and so on.
That's about to happen to Blue America,
already happening.
And so that's going to mean
a political backlash by Blue America of protectionism.
Again, already happening.
And the AI safety stuff,
that's a whole separate thing,
but it's going to be used.
I'm going to use a phrase,
and I hope you won't be offended by this.
Have you heard the phrase,
useful idiots, like by Lenin or whatever?
Okay.
It basically means like,
okay, those guys, they're useful idiots
for communism and so on.
So let me put it like naive people
who think that the US government
is interested in AI safety
are trying to give a lot of power to the US government.
And the reason is,
they haven't actually thought through from first principles
what is the most powerful action in the world to connect them.
They're trying to give power to the US government
to regulate AI safety.
But the government doesn't care about safety of anything.
They literally funded the COVID virus
in Wuhan,
credibly alleged, right?
There's at least,
it is a reasonable hypothesis based on a lot of the data.
Matt Ridley wrote a whole book on this.
There's a lot of data that indicates,
a lot of scientists believe it.
I'm actually like a bioinformatics genomics guy,
if you look at the sequences,
there is a gap and a jump
where it looks like this thing could have been engineered
or partially engineered or evolved.
There's Peter Dazak,
there's Zengli Xi,
there's actually a lot of evidence here.
So the US government and the Chinese government
are responsible for an existential risk.
By studying it, they created it.
Okay.
They're responsible for risking nuclear war with Russia
over this piece of land in eastern Ukraine,
which probably is going to get wound down.
Okay.
So they don't care about your safety
at all.
They're not like,
these are immediate things where we can show
and there's nobody who's punished for this,
nobody who's fired for this,
literally rolling the dice on millions,
hundreds of millions of people's lives
has not been punished.
In fact, it's like,
it's not even talked about
we're past the pandemic and these institutions
can't be punished.
So they don't care about AI safety.
What they care about is AI control.
And so the people in tech who are like,
well, the government will guarantee AI safety.
That's actually what we're going to actually get
is something on the current path,
like what happened with nuclear technology,
where you got nuclear weapons,
but not nuclear power,
or at least not to the scale that we could have had it.
We could have had much cheaper energy for everything.
Instead, we got the militarization
and the regulation and the deceleration,
worst of all worlds,
where you can blow people up,
but you can't build nuclear power plants.
And like even getting into nuclear technology,
forget about just nuclear power plants.
We don't have nuclear submarines.
We don't have nuclear planes,
all that kind of stuff.
I don't know if nuclear planes are possible,
but I do know nuclear submarines are possible.
You can do a lot more cruise ships,
a lot more stuff like that.
You could probably have nuclear trains.
You have to look at exactly how big those are.
I don't know exactly how big those engines are
and what the spies,
but I wouldn't be surprised if you could.
We don't have that.
Why don't we have that?
Because we had the wrong fear driven regulation
in the early 70s.
Putting it all together,
I think that the current AI safety stuff
is similar to nuclear safety stuff,
that the US government has a terrible track record
on safety in general.
It doesn't care about it.
It funded the COVID virus,
incredibly alleged.
It definitely risked nuclear war with Russia recently.
Hot war with Russia was the red line
we were not supposed to cross,
and we're now like way into that.
So it doesn't care about AI safety.
It doesn't care about your safety.
And it's also not even good at regulating.
And so what it cares about is control,
and we are going to have potentially a bad outcome
where Silicon Valley and San Francisco
is the Xerox Park of AI.
Maybe that's too strong,
okay, but basically it develops it,
and there's a lot of things it can't do
because it lobbied for this regulation
that is going to come back and choke it.
And then the other two spheres will push ahead
because it's not about the technology.
It's also about the political layer.
You know the Steve Jobs saying,
actually Alan Kay by way of Steve Jobs,
if you're really serious about software,
you need your own hardware, right?
So if you're really serious about technology,
you need your own sovereignty.
Because like what the AI people haven't thought about is
there's a platform beneath you,
which is not just compute, it is regulate.
It's a law, okay?
And if the law doesn't allow you to compute
so much for all of your stuff above that.
And I know you're saying,
oh, it's only a 10 to the 26 compute band
and so on and so forth.
Have you seen the first IRS tax form?
It's always, always super simple.
It's only the super, super, super rich
who's we're going to get in at first.
Doesn't matter to you.
So that's called boiling the frog slowly.
There's a million, you know, slippery slope.
Slippery slope isn't a fallacy.
It's literally how things work, right?
Apple, one of the reasons they talk about
not setting a precedent.
Zuck starts a very hard line on setting precedents
because he understands the long-term equivalent
of setting a precedent, right?
The precedent setting is that
they're setting up a software FDA.
And DC is so energized on this
because they know how much social media disrupted them.
That's why they're on the attack on crypto and AI.
That's why they're on the attack on self-driving cars.
They want to freeze the current social order in amber
domestically and globally.
So they think they can sanction China
and stop it from developing chips.
They think they can impose regulations on the U.S.
and stop it from developing AI.
But they can't.
And also, by the way, they're totally schizophrenic on this
where when they're talking about China,
they're like, we're going to stop their chips
to make sure America is a global leader.
This is this Gina Raimondo who's saying this.
And then domestically, they're like,
we're going to regulate you so you stop accelerating AI.
We're not about AI acceleration.
EAC is weird over there, okay?
So think about how schizophrenic that is.
Okay, you're going to be far ahead of China.
We're also going to be make sure to control the U.S.
So they want to try and slow.
What they actually want is to freeze the current system
in amber, try to go back to pre-2007
before all these tech guys disrupted everything.
But that's not what's going to happen.
So, but they're going to try to do it.
And so everybody who's still loyal to the DC sphere,
which includes an enormous chunk of AI people.
And because they're all in,
a lot of them are in San Francisco, right?
And the political chaos of the last few years
was not sufficient for them to relocate yet.
Not all of them.
I mean, Elon is in Texas.
And it may turn out that Grock, for example,
and what they're doing there, because he's a very legit,
I mean, he's Elon, so he's capable of doing a lot.
He was very early on OpenAI.
He understands, right?
It may turn out that Grock becomes red AI,
or the community around that.
And OpenAI in DeepMind are still blue AI.
And we have Chinese AI and we're going to have decentralized AI.
Okay, let me pause there.
I know there's a big download.
Well, for starters, I would say,
broadly, I have a pretty similar intellectual tendency as you.
I would broadly describe myself as a techno-optimist
libertarian just about every issue.
And I think your analysis of the dynamics is super interesting.
And I think a lot of it sounds pretty plausible,
although I'll kind of float a couple of things
that I think may be bucking the trend.
But I think it's maybe useful to kind of try to separate this
into scenarios, because all the analysis that you're describing
here seem, if I understand it correctly,
it seems to have the implicit assumption that the AI itself
is not going to get super powerful or hard to control.
It's like, if we assume that it's kind of a normal technology,
then you're off to the races on this analysis,
and then we can get into the fine points.
But I do want to take at least one moment and say,
how confident are you on that?
Because if it's a totally different kind of technology
from other technologies that we've seen,
you raise the gain of function research example.
If it's that sort of technology that has these sort of
non-local possible impacts or self-reinforcing kind of dynamics,
which need not be like an Eliezer-style snap of the fingers fume,
but even over, say, a decade, let's imagine that over the next 10 years,
that AI's kind of multiple architectures develop,
and they sort of get integrated,
and we have something that kind of looks like robust,
silicon-based intelligence, maybe not totally robust,
but as robust or more robust than us, and running faster,
and the kind of thing that can do lots of full jobs,
or maybe even be tech CEOs,
then it kind of feels like a lot of this analysis
probably doesn't hold, because we're just in a totally different regime
that is just extremely hard to predict.
And I guess I wonder, first of all, do you agree with that?
There seems to be a big fork in the road there that's like,
just how fast and how powerful do these AI's become super powerful,
or do they not?
And if they don't, then yeah,
I think we're much more into real politic type of analysis.
But I'm not at all confident in that.
To me, it feels like there's a very real chance
that AI of 10 years from now is...
And by the way, this is like what the leaders are saying, right?
I mean, open AI is saying this, Anthropic is saying this,
Demis and Shane Legge are certainly saying things like this.
It seems like they expect that we will have AI's
that are more powerful than any individual human,
and that becomes like the bigger question
than anything else.
So do you agree with that kind of division of scenarios, first of all?
And then maybe you could kind of say like,
how likely you think each one is.
And obviously that one where it takes off
is like super hard to analyze.
And I also definitely think it is worth analyzing
the scenario where it doesn't take off.
But I just wanted to flag that it seems like there's a big...
If you talk to the AI safety people,
any world in which it's like we're suing Indian AI firms
in Indian court over IP is like a normal world in their mind, right?
And that's not the kind of world that they're most worried about.
I think that there have been some plausible sounding things
that have been said,
but I want to just kind of talk about a few technical counter-arguments,
mathematical or physical, that constrain what is possible.
And actually Martin Casado and Vijay and I are working on a long thing on this
where Vijay did folding at home.
He's a physicist.
Martin sold in the Syrah for a billion dollars
and knows a lot about how a Stuxnet-like thing could work at the systems level.
And I've thought about it from other angles
and some of the math stuff that I'll get to.
So for example, one thing...
And I'm going to give a bunch of different technical arguments
and then let's kind of combine them.
One thing that's being talked about is if you have a superintelligence,
it can double it for a million years
and then it can make one move
and it's going to outthink you all the time and so on and so forth.
Well, if you're familiar with the math of chaos or the math of turbulence,
there are limits to even very simple systems that you can set up
where they can become very unpredictable quite quickly.
Okay. And so you can, if you want to, engineer a system
where you have very rapid diversions of predictability
so that, I don't know, it's like the heat depth of the universe
before you can predict out in timestamps.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
Right?
This is sort of akin to like a wolf from like simple...
Even simple rules can generate patterns
such that you can't know them without literally computing them.
Yeah, exactly, right?
So at least right now, with chaos and turbulence,
you can get things that are extremely provably difficult to forecast
without actually doing it, okay?
You know, I can make that argument quantitative
but that's just something to look at, right?
It's almost like a Delta Epsilon challenge from calculus.
Like, okay, how hard do you want me to make this to predict?
Okay, I can set up a problem that is like that, right?
It's basically extreme sensitivity to initial conditions
lead to extreme divergence in outcomes.
So you could design systems to be chaotic
that might be AI immune because they can't be forecasted that well.
You have to kind of react to them in real time.
The ultimate version of this is not even a chaotic system.
It's a cryptographic system where I've got a whole slide deck on this,
how AI makes everything fake, easy to fake.
Crypto makes it hard to fake again, right?
Because crypto in the broader sense of cryptography,
but also in the narrower sense,
I think crypto is cryptography as the internet is to computer science.
It's like the primary place where all this stuff is applied,
but obviously it's not the equivalent, okay?
And AI can fake an image, but it can't fake a digital signature
unless it can break certain math, you know,
and so it's sort of like a, you know,
solve factors each problem or something like that.
So cryptography is another mathematical thing that constrains AI.
Similar to chaos and turbulence,
it constrains how much an AI can infer things.
You can't statistically infer it, okay?
You need to actually have the private key to solve that equation.
So that is another math.
So I'm going to rules of math, right?
Math is very powerful because you can make proofs
that will work no matter what devices we come up with, okay?
You start to put an AI in a cage.
It can't predict beyond a certain amount
because of chaos and turbulence, math.
It cannot solve certain equations unless it has a private key
is because of what we know about cryptography, math, okay?
Again, if somebody proves P equals NP,
some of this stuff breaks down,
but this is within the bounds of our mathematical knowledge right now.
Physics wise, physical friction exists.
A lot of physical friction exists.
And a huge amount of the writing on AI assumes by guys like Elias
or who I like, I don't dislike it, you know,
but it is extremely,
there's two things that really stick out to me about it.
First is extremely theoretical and not empirical.
And second, extremely Abrahamic rather than Darmic or Sinic.
Okay, why theoretical and not empirical?
It's not trivial to turn something from the computer
into a real world thing, okay?
One of the biggest gaps in all of this thinking
is what are the sensors in actuators?
Okay, because like if you actually build, you know,
I've built in industrial robot systems that, you know,
10 years ago, you know, a genome sequencing lab with robots,
that's hard.
That's physical friction, okay?
And a lot of the AI scenarios seem to basically say,
oh, it's going to be a self-programming Stuxnet
that's going to escape and live off the land
and hypnotize people into doing things, okay?
Now, each of those is actually really, really difficult steps.
First is self-programming Stuxnet.
Like this would have to be a computer virus
that can live on any device, despite the fact
that Apple or Google can push a software update
to a billion devices, right?
A few executives coordinating almost certainly can,
I mean, the off switch exists, right?
Like this is actually like the core thing.
Lots of AI safety guys get themselves into the mindset
that the off switch doesn't exist.
But guess what?
There's almost nothing living that we haven't been able to kill,
right?
Like can we kill it?
This thing exists and this is getting back to living off the land.
Even if you had like something that could solve
some other technical problems that it'll get to,
it exists as an electromagnetic wave kind of thing
on a certain, you know, on chips and so on and so forth.
It's taking it out in the environment
is like putting a really smart human into outer space, right?
Your body just explodes and you die.
It doesn't matter how smart you are.
That strength on this axis,
where you're weak on this axis and, you know,
it's just strength on the X axis,
not strength on the Y or the Z axis.
An AI outside, you know, pour water on it.
This is, you know, this is why I mean the 50 IQ, 150 IQ thing.
You know, the 150 IQ way of saying it is,
it's strong on this X and weak on this X.
And the 50 IQ way is pour water on it, disconnect it,
you know, turn the power off.
Okay, right?
Like it'll, it'll be very difficult to build a system
where you literally cannot turn it off.
The closest thing we have to that is actually not Stuxnet.
It's Bitcoin.
And Bitcoin only exists because millions of humans keep it going.
So you, you need, so that gets the second point,
living off the land for an AI to live off the land,
meaning without human cooperation.
Okay, that's the next Turing threshold.
An AI to live without human cooperation.
It would need to be able to control robots sufficient to dig or out of the ground,
set up data centers and generators and connect them
and defend that against human attack, literally a terminator scenario.
Okay, that's a big leap in terms of, I mean,
is it completely impossible?
I can't say it's completely impossible, but it's not happening tomorrow.
No matter what your AI timelines are,
you would need to have like a billion or hundreds of millions
of internet connected autonomous robots that this Stuxnet AI could hijack.
They were sufficient to carve or out of the earth and set up data centers
and make the AI duplicate.
We're not there.
That's a huge amount of physical friction.
That's AI operating without a human to make itself propagate, right?
A human doesn't need the cooperation of a lizard to self-replicate.
For an AI to replicate right now,
it would need the cooperation of a human in some sense,
because otherwise those humans can kill it
because there's not that many different pieces of operating systems around the world.
I'm just talking about the practical constraints of our current world, right?
Actually existing reality, not AI safety guys reality where all these things don't exist.
There's just a few operating systems, just a few countries.
If everybody is going with torches and search lights through the internet,
it's very hard for a virus to continue.
So A, on the practicalities, there's the technical stuff with chaos and turbulence
and with cryptography itself where AI can't predict and it can't solve certain equations.
B, on the physical difficulties, it probably...
I mean, like to be a Stuxnet,
Microsoft and Google and so on could kill it.
The off switch exists.
Can it live off the land?
No, it cannot because it doesn't have drones to mine or stuff out of the ground.
Can it exist without humans?
Can it be this hypnotizing thing?
Okay, so the hypnotizing thing, by the way,
this is one of the things that's the most hilarious self-fulfilling prophecy in my view.
And no offense to anybody who's listening to this podcast,
but I think the absolutely dumbest kind of tweet that I've seen on AI is,
I typed this in and, oh my God, it told me this.
Like, I asked it how to make sarin gas and it told me X or whatever, right?
That's just a search engine, okay?
What basically a lot of these people are doing is they're saying,
what if there were people out there that were so impressionable
that they would type things into an AI and follow it as if they were hearing voices?
And that's actually not the model or whatever that's doing it.
That's like this AI cult that has evolved around the world,
like a Aum Shinrikyo that hears voices and does the sarin gas.
The point is an AI can't just hypnotize people.
Those people have to participate in it.
They're typing things into the machine or whatever, okay?
Now, you might say, all right, let's project out a few years.
In a few years, what you have is you have an AI that is not just text,
but it appears as Jesus.
What would AI Jesus do?
What would AI Lee Kuan Yew do?
What would AI George Washington do?
So it appears as 3D, okay?
So it's generating that.
It speaks in your language and in a voice.
It knows the history of your whole culture, okay?
That would be very convincing.
Absolutely be very convincing.
But it still can't exist without human programmers
who are like the priests tending this AI God,
whether it's AI Jesus or AI Lee Kuan Yew or something like that.
The thing about the hypnotization thing that I really want to poke on that,
are you familiar with the concept of the principal agent problem?
Basically, every time you've got like a CEO and a worker,
or you have an LP and a VC,
or you have an employer and a contractor,
every edge there, there are four possibilities.
In a 2x2 matrix.
Win-win, win-lose, lose-win, lose-lose, okay?
So for example, when somebody joins a tech startup,
the CEO makes a lot of money and so does a worker, okay?
That's win-win.
Lose-lose is they both lose money.
Win-lose is the CEO makes money and the employee doesn't.
Lose-win is the company fails,
but the employee got paid a very high salary.
So what equity does is it aligns people.
That's where the concept of alignment comes from.
It aligns people to the upper left corner of win-win.
That's when you have one CEO and one employee.
When you have one CEO and two employees,
you don't have two squared outcomes,
you have two cubed outcomes,
because you have win-win-win, win-win-lose,
win-lose-lose, et cetera, right?
Because all three people can be win or lose.
Because CEO can be win or lose, employee can be win or lose,
employee number two can be win or lose.
If you have n people, rather than three people,
you have two to the n possible outcomes
and you have essentially a 2x2x2x2x2x2xn
hyper-cube of possibilities.
Okay, it's literally just two dimensions on each axis.
There's tons of possible defecting kinds of things that happen there.
So that's why in a large company,
there's lose-win coalitions that happen,
where m people gang up on the other k people
and they win what the other people lose.
That's how politics happens.
When you've got a startup that's driven by equity
and the biggest payoff,
people don't have to try to think,
okay, well, I make more money by politics,
we'll make more money by the win-win-win-win-win column
because the exit makes everybody make the most money.
That's actually how the open AI people
were able to coordinate around,
we want an $80 billion company,
the economics help find the sell
that was actually the most beneficial to all of them,
help them coordinate, okay?
So you search that hyper-cube, okay.
That's a point of equity as lining.
Still, despite all of this,
that's one of our best mechanisms for coordinating
large numbers of people in the principal agent problem.
Despite all of this, the possibility exists
for any of these people to win while the others lose,
right, with me so far?
And I'll explain why this is important.
What that means is those 1,000 employees of the CEO
are their own agents with their own payoff functions
that are not perfectly aligned with the CEO's payoff function.
As such, there are scenarios
under which they will defect and do other things, okay?
The only way they become like actual limbs,
see, my hand is not an agent of its own.
It lives or dies with me.
Therefore, it does exactly what I'm saying at this time.
I tell it to go up, it goes up.
I tell it to go down, it goes down.
Sideway is sideways, right?
An employee is not like that.
They will do this and this and sideways, sideways,
up to a certain point.
And if you have them do something
that's extremely against their interests,
they will not do your action.
Did you understand my point?
Okay, that is the difference between an AI hypnotizing humans
versus an AI controlling drones.
AI controlling drones is like your hands.
They're actually pieces of your body.
There's no defecting.
There's no loose wind.
They have no mind of their own.
They're literally taking instructions, okay?
They have no payoff function.
They will kill themselves for the hoard, right?
An AI hypnotizing humans has a thousand
principal Asian problems for every thousand humans.
And it has to incentivize them to continue
and has to generate huge payoffs.
It's like an AI CEO.
That's really hard to do, right?
The history of evolution shows us how hard it is
to coordinate multicellular organisms.
You have to make them all live or die as one.
Then you get something along these lines.
Like an ant colony can coordinate like that
because if the queen doesn't reproduce all the ants,
it doesn't matter what they're having sort of genetic material.
Okay?
We are not currently set up for those humans
to not be able to reproduce unless the AI reproduces.
Do I think we eventually get to a configuration like that?
Maybe.
Where you have an AI brain is at the center of civilization
and it's coordinating all the people around it.
And every civilization that makes it
is capable of crowdfunding and operating its own AI.
That gets me to my other critique of the AI safety guys.
I mentioned that the first critique
is very theoretical rather than empirical.
And the second critique is they're Abrahamic
rather than Darmic or Sinic.
Okay?
And, you know, our background culture influences things
in ways we don't even think about.
So much of the paperclip thinking
is like a vengeful God will turn you into pillars of salt,
except it's a vengeful, you know, AI God
will turn you into paperclips.
Okay?
The polytheistic model of many gods,
as opposed to one God is,
we're all going to have our own AI gods
and there'll be war of the gods,
like Zeus and Hera and so on.
That's the closest Western version,
you know, the paganism that predated,
you know, Abrahamic religions.
But that's still there in India.
That's still how Indians think.
That's why India is sort of,
people have gotten so woke that they don't even make
large scale cultural generalizations anymore.
But it's true that India is just culturally more amenable
to decentralization, to, you know,
multiple gods rather than one God and one state.
Okay?
And then the Chinese model is yet the opposite.
Like they have like, I mean, of course,
they have their tech entrepreneurs and so on.
But they're, if India is more decentralized,
China is more centralized.
They have like one government and one leader
for the entire civilization.
Okay?
And that the biggest thing that China has done
over the last 20 or 30 years is they've taken various,
you know, U.S. things and they've made sure
that they have their own Chinese version
where they have root.
So they take U.S. social media
and they made sure they had root over Sina Weibo.
Okay?
They make sure they have their own Chinese version
of electric cars, the most Chinese version.
So the private keys, in a sense, are with G.
So that means that they also, at a minimum,
you combine these two things,
you're at a minimum going to get polytheistic AI
of the U.S. and Chinese varieties.
And then you add the Indian version on it
and you're going to get quite a few
of these different AIs around there.
And then you have War of the Gods
where maybe they are good at coordinating humans
who take instructions from them,
but they can't live without the humans
and the humans are giving input to them.
That's a series of things.
I could probably make that clearer
if I just laid it out in bullets in an essay,
but just to recap it, A, technical reasons
like chaos, turbulence, cryptography,
why AI is limited in its ability to predict time frames
and to solve equations, B, practical limits.
And AI cannot easily be a Stuxnet
because Microsoft and Google and Apple
can install software on a billion devices
and just kill it, right?
Like basically guys with torches come, all right?
It can't easily live off the land without humans
because they would need hundreds of millions
of autonomous robots out there to control,
to mine the ore and set the data centers.
It can't just hypnotize humans
like it can control drones
because of the principal agent problem
and the degree of human defection.
To make those humans do that,
you'd have to have such massive alignment
between the AI and humans
that the humans all know they'll die
if the AI dies and vies versa.
We're not there.
Maybe we'll be there in like, I don't know,
end number of years, but not for a while.
That's a total change in like how states are organized, okay?
Finally, let me just talk about the physics a little bit more.
There's a lot of stuff which is talked about
at a very sci-fi book level of,
it'll just invent nanomedicine and nanotech
and kill us all and so on and so forth.
Now look, I like Robert Freitas,
obviously Richard Feynman's a genius and so on and so forth,
but nanotech somehow hasn't been invented yet.
Meaning that there's a lot of chemists
that have worked in this area.
A lot of nanotech is like rebranded chemistry
because those are the molecular machines.
For example, DNA polymerase or ribosome,
those are molecular machines
that we can get to work at that scale, the evolved ones.
To my knowledge, and I may be wrong about this,
I haven't looked at it very, very recently,
we haven't actually been able to make artificial replicators
of the stuff that they're talking about,
which means it's possible that there's some practical difficulty
that intervened between Feynman and Freitas
and so on's calculations.
Just a sheer fact that those books have came out decades ago
and no progress has been made,
indicates that maybe there's a roadblock
that wasn't contemplated.
So you can't just click your fingers and say, boom,
nanomess, and it's sort of like clicking your fingers
and saying, boom, time travel.
Nanomess and exist, that was a good poke
that I had a while ago in a conversation like this
where the AI guy, AI safety guy on the other side was like,
well, time travel, that's too implausible.
I'm like, yeah, but you're waiting on the nanotech thing
you're thinking is like here,
and you're making so many assumptions there
that I want to actually see some more work there.
I want to actually see that nanotech
is actually more possible than you think it is.
As for, oh, we just need to mix things in a beaker
and make a virus and so on.
You know what is really, really good
at defending against novel viruses?
Like the human immune, that's something that's within envelope.
Right, like you have evolved to not die
and to fight off viruses.
Is it possible that maybe you could make some super virus?
I mean, maybe, but again, like humans are really good
and the immune system is really good at that kind of thing.
That is what we're set up to do, right,
to adapt to that billions of years of evolution
being set up for them.
Physical constraints are not really contemplated
when people talk about these super powerful
mathematical constraints, practical constraints
are not contemplated.
And I could give more,
but I think that was a lot right there.
Let me pause here.
Yeah, let me try to steal man a few things.
And then I do think it's before too long,
I want to kind of get back to the somewhat less,
you know, radically transformative scenarios
and ask a few follow up questions on that too.
But I think for starters, I would say the sort of Eliezer,
you know, he's updated his thinking over time as well.
And I would say probably doesn't get quite enough credit for it
because he's definitely on record, you know,
repeatedly saying, yeah, I was kind of expecting
more something from like the deep mind school to pop out
and be, you know, wildly overpowered very quickly.
And on the contrary, it seems like we're in more of a slow
takeoff type of scenario where, you know, we've got these,
again, like super high surface area kind of suck up
all the knowledge, gradually get better at everything.
Some surprises in there, you know,
certainly some emergent properties,
if you will accept that term, you know,
surprise surprises to the developers of nothing else,
right, that are definitely things
we don't fully understand.
But it does seem to be a, you know,
more gradual turning up of capability versus some like,
you know, super sudden surprise.
But okay, so then what is the alternative?
I'm going to try to kind of give you the,
what I think of as the most consensus strongest scenario
where humans lose track of the future
and or lose control of the future,
maybe starting by kind of losing track of the present
and then having that kind of, you know,
give way to losing control of the future.
And I think within that, by the way, the,
I'm not really one who cares that much about like,
whether AIs say something offensive today,
I'm not easily offended and like whatever.
That's not, that's not world ending.
I understand your point.
That's not like, who cares, whatever.
That's within scope, that's within envelope.
Within this bigger kind of, you know,
what is the real, you know, most likely path
to like AI disaster as understood,
I think by the smartest people today,
I think that is still a useful leading indicator
because it's like, okay, the developers,
you know, whether you agree with their politics,
whether you agree with their,
whether you think their commercial reasons are,
their sincere reasons are not,
they have made it a goal to get the AI
to not say certain things, right?
They don't want it to be offensive.
The most naive, you know, kind of down the fairway
interpretation of that is like,
Hey, they want to sell it to corporate customers.
They know that their corporate customers don't want,
you know, to have their AI saying offensive things.
So they don't want to say offensive things.
And yet they can't really control it.
It's like still pretty easy to break.
So I view that as just kind of a leading indicator of,
okay, we've seen GPT-2, 3 and 4 over the last four years.
And that's, you know, a big Delta in capability.
How much control have we seen developed in that time
and does it seem to be keeping pace?
And my answer would be on the face of it,
it seems like the answer is no.
You know, we, we don't have the ability to really dial in
the behavior such that we can say, okay, you're going to,
you know, you can expect, you can trust that these AIs
will like not do, you know, A, B, and C.
On the contrary, it's like, if you're a little clever,
you know, you can get them to do it.
You can break out of the sandbox on it.
Yeah. And it's, it's not even like, I mean,
we've talked about, you know, things where you have access
to the weights and you're doing like counter optimizations,
but you don't even need that.
You know, the kind of stuff I do in like my red teaming
in public is literally just like feed the AI a couple of words,
put a couple of words in its mouth, you know,
and it will kind of carry on from there.
So with that in mind is just the leading indicator.
You know, I don't know how powerful the most powerful
AI systems get over the next few years,
but it seems very plausible to me that it might be
as powerful as like an Elon Musk type figure, you know,
somebody who's like really good at thinking
from first principles, really smart, you know,
really dynamic across a wide range of different contexts.
And, you know, he's not powerful enough to like,
in and of himself take over the world,
but he is kind of becoming transformative.
Now imagine that you have that kind of system
and it's trivial to replicate it.
So, you know, if you have like one Elon Musk,
all of a sudden you can have arbitrary,
you know, functionally arbitrary numbers
of Elon Musk power things that are clones of each other.
Maybe I can pause you there.
So that's my polytheistic AI scenario,
but here's the thing that is, this is background,
but I want to push it to foreground.
You still have a human typing in things into that thing.
The human is doing the jailbreak, right?
What we're talking about is not artificial intelligence
in the sense of something separate from a human,
but amplified intelligence.
Amplified intelligence, I very much believe in.
The reason is amplified intelligence.
So here's something that people may not know about humans.
There's this great book, Cooking Made Us Human.
Tool use has shifted your biology in the following way.
For example, I'll map it to the present day.
This book by Richard Rang, I'm Cooking Made Us Human,
where the fact that we started cooking and using fire
meant that we could do metabolism outside the body,
which meant it freed up energy for more brain development.
Similarly, developing clothes
meant that we didn't have to evolve as much fur,
again, more energy for brain development.
Evolving tools meant we didn't have as much fangs
and claws and muscles,
again, more energy for brain development, right?
So encephalization quotient rose as tool use
meant that we didn't have to do as much natively
and we could push more to the machines.
In a very real sense, we have been a man-machine symbiosis
since the invention of fire and the stone axe and clothes.
You do not exist as a human being on your own.
The entire Ted Kojinski concept of living in nature by itself,
humans are social organisms that are adapted
to working with other humans and using tools.
And we have been for millennia.
This goes back, not just human history,
but hundreds of thousands years before,
100 gatherers are using tools.
So what that means is,
man-machine symbiosis is not some new thing.
It's actually the old thing that broke us away
from other primate lineages that weren't using tools.
Okay?
This is the fundamental difference between
what I call Uncle Ted and Uncle Fred.
Uncle Ted is Ted Kojinski.
It's a unabomber, it's a doomer,
it's a decelerator, the de-grocer who thinks
we need to go back to Gaia and Eden and become monkeys
and live in the jungle like Ted Kojinski, right?
The unabomber cell.
Uncle Fred is Friedrich Nietzsche, right?
Nietzsche and we must get to the stars
and become ubermen and so on and so forth.
This, I think, is going to become,
and I actually tweeted about this years ago
before the current AI debates,
between anarcho-primitivism, de-growth, deceleration,
okay, on the one hand,
and transhumanism and acceleration
and human 2.0 and human self-improvement
and make it to the stars, on the other hand.
This is the future political axis, the current one.
And roughly speaking, you can,
it's not really left and right
because you'll have both left status
and right conservatives go over here.
You know, left status will say it's against the state
and the right status will say,
the right conservatives say it's against God, okay?
And you'll have left libertarians
and right libertarians over here
where the left libertarians say it's my body
and the right libertarians say it's my money, right?
And so that is a re-architecting of the political axis
where Uncle Ted and Uncle Fred,
which is a kind of clever way of putting it, okay?
And the problem with the Uncle Ted guys, in my view,
is, as I said, yeah, if they go and want to live in the woods,
fine, go get them.
But once you start having even like a thousand,
forget a thousand, 100 people doing that,
your trees will very quickly get exfoliated,
the leaves are going to get all picked off of them.
Humans are not set up to just literally live
in the jungle right now.
You've had hundreds of thousands of years of evolution
that have driven you in the direction of tool use,
social organisms, farming, et cetera, et cetera.
The man machine symbiosis is not today,
it's yesterday and the day before
and 10,000 years ago and 100,000 years ago.
And how do we know we've got man machine symbiosis?
Can you live without, even if you're not living,
even if you're not using the stove,
somebody's using a stove to make you food, right?
Can you live without the tractors
that are digging up the grains?
Can you live without indoor heating?
Can you live without your clothes?
Frankly, can you do your work without your phone,
without your computer?
No, you can't.
You are already a man machine symbiosis.
Once we accept that, then the question is,
what's the next step?
And right now, we're in the middle of that next step,
which is AI is amplified intelligence.
So what you're talking about is not that the AI is Elon Musk,
it is that the AI human fusion means
there's another 20 Elon Musk's.
Or whatever the number is, okay?
And that's good.
That's fine.
That's within envelope.
That's just a bunch of smarter humans on the planet.
That is amplified intelligence.
That is more like, I mentioned the tool thing, okay?
The other analogy would be like a dog.
You know, a dog is man's best friend, right?
So that AI does not live without you.
Humans can turn it off.
They have to power it.
They have to give it subsidence, right?
Eventually, that might become like a ceremonial thing,
like this is our God that we pray to, right?
Because it's wiser and smarter than us,
and it appears in an image.
But the priests maintain it.
You know, just like you go to a Hindu temple
or something like that,
and the priests will pour out the ghee,
you know, for the fires and so on and so forth.
And then everybody comes in and prays, okay?
The priests believe in the whole thing,
but they also maintain the back of the house.
They do the system administration for the temple.
Same, you know, in a Christian church, right?
The, you know, it's not like it appears out of nowhere.
Somebody, you know, went and assembled this cathedral, right?
They saw the back of the house,
the fact that it was just woods and rocks
and so on that came together.
But then when people come there,
it feels like a spiritual experience.
You see what I'm saying, okay?
So the equivalent of that,
the priests or the people
maintaining temples, cathedrals, mosques, whatever,
is engineers who are maintaining
these future AIs, which appear to you as Jesus.
They appear to you, maybe even a hologram, okay?
You come there, you ask it for guidance as an oracle.
You've also got the personal version on your phone.
You ask it for guidance, but guess what?
You're still a human AI symbiosis until,
and unless, that AI actually has the terminator scenario
where it's got lots of robots
and it can live on its own.
I'm not saying that's physically impossible.
I did give some constraints on it earlier,
but for a while, we're not going to be there.
So that alone means it's not fume
because we don't have lots of drones running around.
The AI has to be with the human.
It's a human AI symbiosis.
It's not AI Elon Musk.
It is human AI fusion that becomes Elon Musk.
And frankly, that's not that different
from what Elon Musk himself is.
Elon Musk would not be Elon Musk without the internet.
Without the internet, you can't tweet
and reach 150 million people.
The internet itself made Elon what he is, right?
And so this is like the next version of that.
Maybe there's now 30 Elons
because the AI makes the next 30 Elons.
Yeah, I mean, again, I think I'm largely with you
with just this one very important nagging worry
that's like, what if this time is different?
Because what if these systems are getting so powerful,
so quickly that we don't really have time
for that techno human fusion to really work out?
And I'll just give you kind of a couple of data points on that.
Like, you know, you said like,
it's still somebody putting something into the AI.
Well, sort of, right?
I mean, already we have these proto agents
and the like super simple scaffolding of an agent
is just run it in a loop, give it a goal,
and have it kind of pursue some like plan, act,
get feedback and loop type of structure, right?
It doesn't seem to take a lot.
Now, they're not smart enough yet
to accomplish big things in the world,
but it seems like the language model to agent switch
is less one right now that is gated by the structure
or the architecture and more one that's just gated
by the fact that like the language models,
when framed as agents, just aren't that successful
at like doing practical things and getting over hump,
so they tend to get stuck.
But it doesn't seem that hard to imagine that like,
you know, if you had something that is sort of
that next level that you put it into a loop,
you say, okay, you're Elon Musk, LLM,
and your job is to like make, you know, us,
whatever us exactly is a, you know, multi-planetary species,
and then you just kind of keep updating your status,
keep updating your plans, keep trying stuff,
keep getting feedback, and you know,
like what really limits that?
There may be like a really good program,
but the whole AI kills everyone thing is so,
it's like, where's the actuator?
Okay, I hit enter.
What kills me, right?
Is it a hypnotized human who's being hypnotized by an AI
that he's typed into and he's radicalized himself
by typing into a computer?
Okay, that's not that different from a lot of other things
that have happened in the past, right?
So who is actually striking me, right?
Who's striking the human?
It's another human within acts that he's been radicalized
by an AI, okay?
He's not, actually, that's not even the right term.
We're giving agency to the AI when it's not really an agent.
It is a human who's self-radicalized
by typing into a computer screen.
And has hit another human.
That's one scenario.
The other scenario is,
it's literally a Skynet drone that's hitting you.
Those are the only two,
how else is it going to be physical, right?
How does the, the actuation step is a part
that is skipped over and it's a non-trivial step.
Well, I think it could be lots of things, right?
I mean, if it's not one of those two,
if it's not another human or a drone hitting you,
what is it?
Just habitat degradation, right?
I mean, how do we kill most of the other species
that we drive to extinction?
We don't go out and like hunt them down with axes one by one.
We just like change the environment more broadly
to the point where it's not suitable for them anymore
and they don't have enough space and they kind of die out, right?
Like, so we did hunt down some of the megafauna,
like literally one by one with, with spears and stuff.
But like most of the recent loss of species
is just like, we're out there just extracting resources
for our own purposes.
And in the course of doing that, you know,
whatever bird or whatever, you know, thing just kind of loses its place
and then it's no more.
And I don't think that's like totally implausible.
Wait, so that is though, I think, within normal world, right?
What does that mean?
That means that some people, some, some amplified intelligence,
and maybe we might call it HAI.
Okay, human plus AI combination, right?
Some HAIs out compete others economically
and they lose their jobs.
Is that what you're talking about?
I think also the humans potentially become unnecessary
in a lot of the configurations.
Like just a recent paper from DeepMind.
It's your marginal product workers.
Or negative.
Yeah, I mean, so the last, you know, DeepMind has been on Google,
Google DeepMind has been on a tear of increasingly impressive medical AI's.
Their most recent one takes a bunch of difficult case studies
from the literature.
I mean, case studies, you know,
this is like rare diseases, hard to diagnose stuff.
And asks an AI to do the differential diagnosis, compares that to human,
and compares it to human plus AI.
And they've phrased their results like in a very understated way.
But the headline is, the AI blows away the human plus AI.
The human makes the AI worse.
So here's the thing, I'll say something provocative maybe.
Okay, like I have in a very fine.
I do think that the ABC's of Economic Apocalypse for Blue America
are AI, Bitcoin, and China.
Where AI takes away their, a lot of the revenue streams,
the licensures that have made medical and legal costs and other things so high.
Bitcoin takes away their power over money,
and China takes away their military power.
So I've perceived total meltdown for Blue America
in the years and, you know, maybe decade to come already kind of happening.
But that's different than being at the end of the world.
Right?
Like, Blue America had a really great time for a long time,
and they've got these licensure locks.
But because of that, they've hyperinflated the cost of medicine.
It's like, how much, so what you're talking about is,
wow, we have infinite free medicine.
Man, Dr. Billing events are going to get ahead.
That's the point.
Yeah, and to be clear, I'm really with you on that too.
Like, I want to see, when people say like, what is good about AI?
You know, why should we pursue this?
My standard answer is high quality medical advice for everyone at pennies per visit, right?
It is orders of magnitude cheaper.
We're already starting to see that in some ways it's better.
People prefer it, you know, that AI is more patient.
It has better bedside manner.
I wouldn't say, you know, if I was giving my own family advice today,
I would say use both a human doctor and an AI,
but definitely use the AI as part of your mix.
Absolutely. That's right.
That's right. But you're prompting it still, right?
The smarter you are, the smarter the AI is.
You notice this immediately with your vocabulary, right?
The more sophisticated your vocabulary,
the finer the distinctions you can have,
the better your own ability to spot errors.
You can generate a basic program with it, right?
But really amplified intelligence is, I think,
a much better way of thinking about it.
Because whatever your IQ is, it surges it upward by a factor of three or whatever the number.
And maybe the amplifier increases with your intelligence.
But that internal intelligence difference still exists.
It's just like what a computer is.
A computer is an amplifier for intelligence.
If you're smart, you can hit enter and programs can go to...
Like thinking about the Minecraft guy, right?
Or Satoshi.
One person built a billion, or in Satoshi's case, a trillion dollar thing, you know?
Obviously other people continued Bitcoin and so on and so forth, right?
So what I feel, though, is this is what I mean
by going from nuclear terrorism to the TSA, okay?
We went from AI will kill everyone.
And I'm like, what's the actuator to, okay,
it'll gradually degrade our environment.
What does that mean?
Okay, some people will lose their jobs.
But then we're back in normal world.
Well, hold on.
Let me paint a little bit more complete picture,
because I don't think we're quite there yet.
So I think the differential diagnosis,
recent paper, that's just a data point where it's kind of like chess.
So this came long before, right?
There was a period where humans were the best chess players.
Then there was a period where the best were the hybrid,
human AI systems.
And now as far as I understand it, we're in a regime where
the human can't really help the AI anymore.
And so the best chess players are just pure AIs.
We're not there in medicine, but we're starting to see examples where,
hey, in a pretty defined study, differential diagnosis,
the AI is beating, not just beating the humans,
but also beating the AI human hybrid,
or the human with access to AI.
So, okay, that's not it, right?
There's a paper recently called Eureka.
Out of NVIDIA, this is Jim Fan's lab where they use GPT-4
to write the reward functions to train a robot.
So you want to train a robot to twirl a pencil in fingers.
Hard for me to do.
Robots definitely can't do it.
How do you train that?
Well, you need a reward function.
The reward function, basically while you're in the early process
of learning and failing all the time,
the reward function gives you encouragement
when you're on the right track, right?
There are people who have developed this skill,
and you might do something like,
well, if the pencil has angular momentum,
then that seems like you're on maybe the right track,
so give that a reward.
Even though, at the beginning, you're just failing all the time.
It turns out GPT-4 is way better than humans at this, right?
So it's better at training robots.
So all of that is awesome, and it's great.
But here's the thing, is there's a huge difference between AI
is going to kill everybody and turn everybody into paperclips.
Versus some humans with some AI are going to make a lot more money,
and some people are going to lose their jobs.
Yeah, I'm not scared of that.
I'm not scared of that, Snare.
I mean, it could be disruptive,
it could be disruptive, but it's not existential under itself.
Big deal.
Okay, so that's why I went, right.
There's a, the, the, to me, it comes, if I,
if I ask just one question is, what is the actuator?
Right?
You know, sensors and actuators, right?
What is the thing that's actually going to
plunge a knife or a bullet into you and kill you?
It is either a human who has hypnotized themselves by typing into a computer,
like basically an AI terrorist, you know,
which is kind of where some of the EAs are going in my view,
or it is like an autonomous drone that is controlled in a
starcraft or terminator like way.
We are not there yet in terms of having enough humanoid or autonomous drones
that are internet connected and programmable.
That won't be there for some time.
Okay.
So that alone means fast takeoff is,
and what I think by the time we get there,
you will have a cryptographic control over them.
That's a crucial thing.
Cryptography fragments the whole space in a very fundamental way.
If you don't have the private keys,
you do not have control over it.
So long as that piece of hardware, the cryptographic controller,
you've nailed the equations on that,
and frankly, you can use AI to attack that as well
to make sure the code is perfect, right?
Remember you talked about attack and defense?
AI is attack cryptos defense, right?
Because one of the things that crypto has done,
do you know the PKI problem is public key infrastructure?
I'll say no on behalf of the audience.
This is good.
We should do more of these actually.
I feel it's a good fusion of things or whatever, right?
But the public key infrastructure problem is something that was sort of,
lots of cryptography papers and computer science papers
in the 90s and 2000s assumed that this could exist
and essentially meant if you could assume
that everybody on the internet had a public key that was public
and a private key that was kept both secure and available at all times,
then there's all kinds of amazing things you can do
with privacy preserving, messaging, and authentication, and so on.
The problem is that for many years,
what cryptographers try to do is they try to nag people
into keeping their private keys secure and available.
And the issue is it's trivial to keep it secure and unavailable
where you write it down and you put it into a lockbox
and you lose the lockbox.
It's trivial to keep it available and not secure,
okay, where you put it on your public website
and it's available all the time, you never lose it,
but it's not secure because anybody can see it.
When you actually ask,
what does it mean to keep something secure and available?
That's actually a very high cost.
It's precious space because it's based on your wallet, right?
Your wallet is on your person at all times, so it's available,
but it's not available to everybody else, so it's secure.
So you actually have to touch it constantly, yes, right?
So it turns out that the crypto wallet,
by adding a literal incentive to keep your private keys secure and available,
because if they're not available, you've lost your money.
If they're not secure, you've lost your money, okay?
To have both of them, that was what solved the PKI problem.
Now we have hundreds of millions of people
with public private key pairs where the private keys are secure and available.
That means all kinds of cryptographic schemes,
zero-knowledge stuff.
There's this amazing universe of things that is happening now.
Zero-knowledge in particular has made cryptography much more programmable.
There's a whole topic which is, if you want something that's kind of,
you know, like AI was creeping for a while
and people, specialists were paying attention to it
and then just burst out on the scene.
Zero-knowledge is kind of like that for cryptography.
Thanks to the, you know, you've probably heard of zero-knowledge before.
Yeah, we did one episode with Daniel Kong on the use of zero-knowledge proofs
to basically prove without revealing like the weights
that you actually ran the model you said you were going to run
and things like that I think are super interesting.
Exactly, right?
So what kinds of stuff, why is that useful in the AI space?
Well, first is you can use it, for example,
for training on medical records while keeping them both private
but also getting the data you wanted.
For example, let's say you've got a collection of genomes, okay?
And you want to ask, okay, how many Gs were in this data set?
How many Cs?
How many A's?
How many T's?
Okay, like you just said, like that's a very simple down.
So what's the ACG T content of this, you know, the sequence data set?
You could get those numbers, you could prove they were correct
without giving any information about the individual sequences, right?
Or more specifically, you do it at one locus and you say,
how many Gs and how many Cs are at this particular locus
and you get the SNP distribution, okay?
So it's useful for what you just said,
which is like showing that you ran a particular model
without giving anything else away.
It's useful for certain kinds of data analysis.
There's a lot of overhead on compute on this right now.
So it's not something that you do trivially, okay?
But it'll probably come down with time.
But what is perhaps most interestingly useful for
is in the context of AI is coming up with things that AI can't fake.
So what we talked about earlier, right?
Like an AI can come up with all kinds of plausible sounding images,
but if it wasn't cryptographically signed by the sender,
then, you know, it should be signed by the sender and put on chain.
And then at least you know that this person or this entity
with this private key asserted that this object existed at this time
in a way that'd be extremely expensive to falsify
because it's either on the Bitcoin blockchain
or another blockchain that's very expensive to rewind, okay?
This starts to be a bunch of facts that an AI can't fake.
You know, so going back to the kind of big picture loss of control story,
I was just kind of trying to build up a few of these data points
that like, hey, look at this differential diagnosis.
We already see like humans are not really adding value to AIs anymore.
That's kind of striking.
And like similarly with training robot hands,
GPT-4 is outperforming human experts.
And by the way, all of the sort of latent spaces
are like totally bridgeable, right?
I mean, one of the most striking observations
of the last couple of years of study is that
AIs can talk to each other in high dimensional space,
which we don't really have a way of understanding natively, right?
It takes a lot of work for us to decode.
This is like the language thing?
We're starting to see AIs kind of develop
not obviously totally on their own as of now,
but we are...
There is becoming an increasingly reliable go-to set of techniques
if you want to bridge different modalities
with like a pretty small parameter adapter.
That's interesting.
Actually, what's a good paper on that?
I actually hadn't seen that.
The blip family of models out of Salesforce research
is really interesting.
And I've used that in production at...
Salesforce, really?
Yeah, Salesforce research.
They have a crack team that has open sourced a ton of stuff
in the language model, computer vision, joint space.
And this...
You see this all over the place now,
but basically what they did in a paper called blip2,
and they've had like five of these with a bunch of different techniques,
but in blip2, they took a pre-trained language model
and then a pre-trained computer vision model,
and they were able to train just a very small model
that kind of connects the two.
So you could take an image, put it into the image space,
then have their little bridge that over to language space.
And that everything else, the two big models are frozen.
So they were able to do this on just like
a couple days worth of GPU time,
which I do think goes to show
how it is going to be very difficult to contain proliferation.
It was just good.
In my view, that's really good.
As long as it doesn't get out of control,
I'm probably with you on that too.
But by bridging this vision space into the language space,
then the language model would be able to converse with you
about the image, even though the language model
was never trained on images,
but you just had this connector that kind of bridges those modalities.
It's like another layer of the network
that just bridges two networks, almost.
Yeah, it bridges the spaces.
It like it bridges the conceptual spaces
between something that has only understood images
and something that has only understood language,
but now you can kind of bring those together.
As I think about it, it's not that surprising
because that's what, for example, text image models are basically that.
They're bridging two spaces in a sense, right?
But I'll check this paper out.
So on the one hand, it's not that surprising.
On their hand, I should see how they implement it
or whatever, so blip to.
Okay.
Yeah, I think the most striking thing about that
is just how small it is.
You took these two off-the-shelf models that were trained
independently for other purposes,
and you're able to bridge them with a relatively small connector.
And that seems to be kind of happening all over the place.
I would also look at the Flamingo architecture,
which is like a year and a half ago now out of DeepMind.
That was one for me where I was like, oh my,
and it's also a language to vision
where they keep the language model frozen,
and then they kind of, in my mind,
it's like I can see the person in their garage
like tinkering with their soldering iron,
because it's just like, wow,
you took this whole language thing that was frozen,
and you kind of injected some vision stuff here,
and you added a couple layers,
and you kind of Frankensteined it, and it works.
And it's like, wow, that's not really,
it wasn't like super principled.
It was just kind of hack a few things together
and try training it.
And I don't want to diminish what they did,
because I'm sure there were more insights to it than that.
But it seems like we are kind of seeing a reliable pattern
of the key point here being model-to-model communication
through high-dimensional space,
which is not mediated by human language,
is I think one of the reasons that I would expect,
and by the way, there's lots of papers too.
I'm like, language models are human level
or even superhuman prompt engineers.
They're self-prompting techniques are getting pretty good.
So if I'm imagining the big picture of like,
and we can get back to like,
okay, well, how do we use any techniques,
crypto or otherwise, to keep this under control?
And then I would say this is kind of the newer school
of the big picture AI safety worry.
Obviously, there's a lot of flavors,
but if you were to go look at like a Jay Acotra,
for example, I think is a really good writer on this.
Her worldview is less that we're going to have this fume
and more that over a period of time,
and it may not be a long period of time.
Maybe it's like a generation, maybe it's 10 years,
maybe it's 100 years,
but obviously those are all small
in the sort of grand scheme of the future.
We have in all likelihood,
the development of AI centric schemes of production,
where you've got kind of your high level executive function
is like your language model.
You've got all these like lower level models.
They're all bridgeable.
All the spaces are bridgeable in high dimensional form,
where they're not really mediated by language,
unless we enforce that.
I mean, we could say it must always be mediated by language
so we can read the logs,
but there's a tax to that,
because going through language is like highly compressed
compared to the high dimensional space to space.
All right.
So let me see if I can steal man or articulate your case.
You're saying AIs are going to get good enough.
They're going to be able to communicate with each other
good enough, and they'll be able to do enough tasks
that more and more humans will be rendered economically
marginal and unnecessary.
I'm not saying I think that will happen.
I'm just saying I think there's a good enough chance
that that will happen,
but it's worth taking really seriously.
I actually think that will happen,
something along those lines,
in the sense of at least massive economic disruption.
Definitely.
Okay.
But I'll give an answer to that,
which is both maybe fun and not fun.
Have you seen the graph of the percentage of America
that was involved in farming?
Yeah.
I tweeted a version of that once.
Oh, you did.
Okay.
Great.
Good.
So you're familiar with this,
and you're familiar with what I mean by the implication of it,
where basically Americans used to identify themselves
as farmers, and manufacturing rose
as agriculture collapsed.
And here is the graph on that.
But from like 40% in the year 1900
to a total collapse of agriculture,
and then also more recently a collapse of manufacturing
into bureaucracy, paperwork, legal work,
what is up into the right since then
is the lawyers.
What is up into the right?
What is replacing that?
Starting in around the 1970s,
we used to be adding energy production
and energy production flatlined
once people got angry about nuclear power.
So this is a future that could have been.
We could be on Mars by now,
but we got flatlined.
Right?
What did go up into the right?
So construction costs,
this is the bad scenario,
where the miracle energy got destroyed
because regulations, the cost was flat.
And then when vertical, when regulations were imposed,
all the progress was stopped by decels and de-growthers.
And then Alara was implemented,
which said nuclear energy has to be as low risk
as reasonably necessary, as reasonably achievable.
And that meant that you just keep adding safety to it
until it's as same as cost as everything else,
which means you destroyed the value of it.
But you know what was up into the right?
What replaced those agriculture and manufacturing jobs?
Look at this, you see this graph?
We will put this on YouTube.
So if you want to see the graph do the YouTube version of this,
for the audio only group,
it's an exponential curve in the number of lawyers
in the United States from,
looks like maybe two thirds of a million
to 13 million over the last 140 years.
Yeah. And in 1880, it was like sub 100,000
or something like that, right?
And then it's just like, especially that 1970 point,
that's when it went totally vertical, okay?
And it's probably even more sensitive.
So, you know, if you add paperwork jobs, bureaucratic jobs,
you know, every lawyer is like, you know, sorry lawyers,
but you're basically negative value add, right?
Because it should, the fact that you have a lawyer
means that you couldn't just self serve a form, right?
Basic government is platformers
where you can just self serve and you fill it out.
And you don't have to have somebody
like code something for you custom, you know,
lawyers that's doing custom code
is because the legal code is so complicated.
So, you know, the whole Shakespeare thing,
like first thing we do, let's, you know, kill all the lawyers.
First thing we do, let's automate all the lawyers, right?
Only something that's the hammer blow of AI
can break the backbone and it will.
It's going to break the backbone of Blue America, right?
It's going to cause, that's why the political layer
and the sovereignty layer is not what AI people think about.
But it's like crucial for thinking about AI
because what tribes does AI benefit?
And again, we got away from, why does AI kill everybody?
Well, it's going to need actuators.
Who's going to stab you? Who's going to shoot you?
It's got to be a human hypnotized by AI
or a drone that AI controls.
A human hypnotized by AI is actually a conventional threat.
It looks like a terrorist cell.
We know how to deal with that, right?
It's just like radicalized humans that worship some AI
that stab you.
It's like the pause AI people are one step, I think,
away from that, all right?
But that's just like Aum Shinriko.
That's like allocated.
That's like basically terrorists
who think that the AI is telling them what to do, fine?
If it's not a human that's stabbing you, it is a drone.
And that's like a very different future where like five or 10
or 15 years up, maybe we have enough
internet connected drones out there,
but even then they'll have private keys.
So there's going to be fragmentation of address space.
Not all drones be controlled by everybody in my view, okay?
That's what AI safety is.
AI safety is can you turn it off?
Can you kill it?
Can you stop it from controlling drones?
That's what AI safety is.
Can you also open the model weights
so you can generate adversarial inputs?
Can you open the model weights and proliferate it?
You're saying, oh, proliferation is bad.
I'm saying proliferation is good because if everybody has one,
then nobody has an advantage on it, right?
Not relatively speaking, okay?
I have very few super confident positions.
So I wouldn't necessarily say I think that proliferation is bad.
I'd say so far it's good.
It has, and even most of the AI safety people,
I would say if I could speak on the behalf of the AI safety
consensus, I would say most people would say
even that the Llama 2 release has proven good for AI safety
for the reasons that you're saying.
But they opposed it.
Well, some didn't, some didn't.
I would say the main posture that I see AI safety people taking
is that we're getting really close to,
or we might be getting really close.
Certainly if we just kind of naively extrapolate out recent progress,
it would seem that we're getting really close to systems
that are sufficiently powerful that it's very hard to predict
what happens if they proliferate.
Llama 2, not there.
And so, yes, it has enabled a lot of interpretability work.
It has enabled things like representation engineering,
which there isn't a lot of good stuff that has come from it.
The big thing that I want to kind of establish is
you agree with me on the actuation point or not.
Like, the thing is this thing, like,
oh Llama 2 proliferates and so businesses are disrupted
and people, you know, maybe they paid a lot of money
for their MD degree and they can't make us a bunch of money.
That's within the realm of what I call conventional warfare.
You know what I mean?
That's like we're still in normal world as we were talking about.
Unconventional warfare is, you know,
Skynet arises and kills everybody.
Okay.
And that is what is being sold over here.
And when you think about the actuators,
we don't have the drones out there.
We don't have the humanoid robots at control.
And hypnotized humans are a very tiny subset of humans,
probably.
And if they aren't, that just looks like a religion
or a cult or a terrorist cell.
And we know how to deal with that as well.
The super intelligent AI with, you know,
lots of robots that control in a Starcraft form,
I would agree is something that humans haven't faced yet.
But by the time we get that many robots out there,
you won't be able to control all of them at once
because of the private key things I mentioned.
So that's why I'm like, okay,
everything else we're talking about is in normal world.
That is the single biggest thing that I wanted to get.
Like economic disruption, people losing jobs,
proliferation so that the balance of power is redistributed.
All that's fine.
The other reason I say this is people keep trying
to link AI to existential risk.
A great example is one of the things you actually had in here.
This is similar to the AI policy and two things.
It's a totally reasonable question,
but then I'm going to, in my view, deconstruct the question.
What would you think about putting the limit on the right
to compute or their capabilities an AI system might demonstrate
that you make you think open access no longer wise?
Most common near term answer here to be seems to be related
to risk of pandemic via novel pathogen engineering.
So guess what?
You know who the novel pathogen engineers are?
The US and Chinese governments, right?
They did it or probably did it,
credibly did it, credibly being accused of doing it.
They haven't been punished for COVID-19.
In fact, they covered up their culpability
and pointed everywhere other than themselves.
They used it to gain more power in both the US and China
with both lockdown in China and in the US
and all kinds of COVID era.
Trillions of dollars was printed and spent and so on and so forth.
They did everything other than actually solve the problem.
That was actually getting the vaccines in the private sector.
And they studied the existential risk only to generate it.
And they're even paid to generate pandemic prevention and failed.
So this would be the ultimate Fox guarding the hen house.
Okay, the only reason that the two organizations responsible
for killing millions of people novel pathogen
are going to prevent people from doing this by restricting compute.
No, you know what it is actually what's happening here is
one of the concepts I have in the network state
is this idea of God, state and network.
Okay, meaning what do you think is the most powerful force in the world?
Is it almighty God?
Is it the US government or is it encryption?
Right, or eventually maybe an AGI, right?
If what's happening here is a lot of people are implicitly
without realizing it, even if they are secular atheists,
they're treating GOV as GOD.
Okay, they treat the US government as God as the final mover.
No, I appreciate your little I take inspiration from you actually
in terms of trying to come up with these little quips that are memorable.
So I was just smiling at that because I think you do a great job of that.
And I try to encourage, I have less success coining terms than you have,
but certainly try to follow your example on that front.
It's like a helpful, if you can compress it down,
it's like more memorable.
So that's what I try to do, right?
So exactly a lot of these people who are secular,
think of themselves as atheists,
have just replaced GOD with GOV.
They worship the US government as God.
And there's two versions of this.
You know how like God has put the male and female version, right?
The female version is the Democrat God within the USA that has infinite money
and can take care of everybody and care for everybody.
And the Republican God is the US military that can blow up anybody,
and it's the biggest and strongest and most powerful America F. Yeah.
Okay.
And everybody who thinks of the US government as being able to stop something
is praying to a dead God.
Okay.
When you say this,
you actually get an interesting reaction from AI safety people
where you've actually hit their true solar plexus.
All right.
The true solar plexus is not that they believe in AI.
It's that they believe in the US government.
That's a true solar plexus
because they are appealing to,
they're praying to this dead God
that can't even clean the poop off the streets in San Francisco, right?
That is losing wars or fighting them to sell me.
It has lost all these wars around the world
that spent trillions of dollars
has been through financial crisis, coronavirus,
Iraq war, you know, total meltdown politically.
Okay.
That is now has interest payments more than the defense budget
that is, you know,
that spent $100 billion on the California train
without laying a single track.
It's like that, you know, that Morgan Freeman thing for,
you know, the clip from Batman,
where he's like, so this man has a billionaire,
blah, blah, blah, this and that,
and your plan is to threaten him, right?
And so you're going to create this super intelligence
and have Kamala Harris regulate it.
Come on, man, so to speak, right?
Like these people are praying to a blind, deaf and dumb God
that was powerful in 1945, right?
That's why, by the way, all the popular movies,
what are they?
It's Barbie, it's Oppenheimer, right?
It's, it's Top Gun.
They're all throwbacks the 80s or the 50s
when the USA was really big and strong.
And the future is a black mirror.
Yeah, I think that's tragic.
One of the projects that I do like,
and you might appreciate this,
I don't know if you've seen it,
is the, from the future of Life Institute,
a project called Imagine a World,
I think is the name of it.
And they basically challenged, you know,
their audience and the public to come up with
positive visions of a future,
you know, where technology changes a lot.
And obviously AI pretty central to a lot of those stories.
And, you know, one of the challenges that people go through
and how do we get there and whatever,
but a purposeful effort to imagine positive futures.
Super under provided.
And I really liked the,
the investment that they made in that.
You know, one of the things I've got
in the Never See It book is there's certain megatrends
that are happening, right?
And megatrends, I mean, it's possible for,
like one miraculous human maybe to reverse them, okay?
Because I think both the impersonal force of history theory
and the great man theory of history have some truth to them.
But the megatrends are the decline of Washington DC
the rise of the internet,
the rise of India, the rise of China.
That is like my worldview.
And I can give a thousand graphs and charts and so on for that.
But that's basically the last 30 years.
And maybe the next X, right?
I'm not saying there can't be trend reversal.
Of course it can be trend reversal,
as I just mentioned, some hammer blow could hit it,
but that's what's happening.
And so because of that,
the people who are optimistic about the future
are aligned with either the internet, India or China.
And the people who are not optimistic about the future
are blue Americans or left out red Americans, okay?
Or Westerners in general who are not tech people, okay?
If they're not tech people, they're not up into the right,
basically, because the internet's,
if you, I mean, one of the things is we have a misnomer,
as I was saying earlier,
of calling it the United States,
because it's the dis-United States.
It's like talking about,
you know, talking about America is like talking about Korea.
There's North Korea and South Korea,
and they're totally different populations.
And, you know, communism and capitalism
are totally different systems.
And the thing that is good for one
is bad for another and vice versa.
And so like America doesn't exist.
There's only, just like there's no Korea,
there's only North Korea and South Korea,
there's no America.
There is blue America and red America
and also gray America, tech America.
And blue America is harmed,
or they think they're harmed,
or they've gotten themselves into a spot where they're harmed,
by every technological development,
which is why they hate it so much, right?
AI versus journalist jobs,
crypto takes away banking jobs, you know,
everything, you know, self-driving cars,
they just take away regulator control, right?
Anything that reduces their power, they hate,
and they're just trying to freeze an amber with regulations.
Red America got crushed a long time ago
by offshoring to China and so on.
They're making, you know, inroads ally
with tech America or gray America.
Tech America is like the one piece of America
that's actually still functional and globally competitive.
And people always do this fallacy of aggregation,
where they talk about the USA,
and it's really this component that's up and to the right,
and the others that are down and to the right,
or at best flat, like red, but they're like down, right?
Like red is like okay functional, blue is down.
Point is, tech America, I think we're gonna find,
is not even truly, or how American is tech America,
because it's like 50% immigrants, right?
And like a lot of children immigrants,
and most of their customers are overseas,
and their users are overseas,
and their vantage point is global, right?
And they're basically not,
I know we're in this ultra-nationalist kick right now,
and I know that there's gonna be,
there's a degree of a fork here,
where you fork technology into Silicon Valley
and the internet, okay?
Where Silicon Valley is American,
and they'll be making like American military equipment,
and so on and so forth, and they're signaling USA,
which is fine, okay?
And then the internet is international global capitalism,
and the difference is Silicon Valley, or let's say US tech,
let me be less, you know, US tech says ban TikTok,
build military equipment, et cetera,
it's really identifying itself as American,
and it's thinking of being anti-China, okay?
But there's, US and China are only 20% of the world,
80% of the world is neither American nor Chinese.
So the internet is for everybody else
who wants actual global rule of law, right?
When as the US decays as a rules-based order,
and people don't wanna be under China,
people wanna be under something like blockchains,
where you've got like property rights contract law
across borders that are enforced by an impartial authority, okay?
That's also the kind of laws that can bind AIs,
like AIs across borders,
if you wanna make sure they're gonna do something,
cryptography can bind an AI in such a way that it can't fake it.
It can't, an AI can't mint more Bitcoin, you know?
Here's my last question for you.
AI discourse right now does seem to be polarizing into camps.
Obviously a big way that you think about the world
is by trying to figure out, you know,
what are the different camps?
How do they relate to each other?
So on and so forth.
I have the view that AI is so weird,
and so unlike other things that we've encountered in the past,
including just like, unlike humans, right?
I always say AI, alien intelligence,
that I feel like it's really important to borrow a phrase
from Paul Graham, keep our identities small,
and try to have a scout mindset
to really just take things on their own terms, right?
And not necessarily put them through a prism
of like, whose team am I on?
Or, you know, is this benefit my team
or hurt the other team or whatever?
But, you know, just try to be as kind of directly engaged
with the things themselves as we can
without mediating it through all these lenses.
You know, I think about, you mentioned like,
the gain of function, right?
And I don't know for sure what happened,
but it certainly does seem like there's a
very significant chance that it was a lab leak.
Certainly there's a long history of lab leaks,
but it would be like, you know,
it would seem to me a failure to say,
okay, well, what's the opposite
of just having like a couple of government labs?
Like everybody gets their own gain of function lab, right?
Like if we could, and this is kind of what we're doing
with AI, we're like,
let's compress this power down to as small as we can.
Let's make a kit that can run in everybody's home.
Would we want to send out these like gain of function,
you know, wet lab research kits to like every home in the world
and be like, hope you find something interesting,
you know, like let us know if you find any new pathogens
or hey, maybe you'll find life-saving drugs,
like whatever, we'll see what you find,
you know, all eight billion of you.
That to me seems like it would be definitely a big misstep.
And that's the kind of thing that I see coming out of
ideologically motivated reasoning or like,
you know, tribal reasoning.
And so I guess I wonder how you think about the role
that tribalism and ideology is playing
and should or shouldn't play as we try to understand AI.
Okay, so first is you're absolutely right
that just because A is bad does not mean that B is good, right?
So A could be a bad option, B could be a bad option,
C could be a bad option.
There might be, you have to go down to option G
before you find a good option.
Or there might be three good options and seven bad options,
for example, right?
So to map that here, in my view,
an extremely bad option is to ask the U.S.
and Chinese governments to do something.
Anything the U.S. government does at the federal level,
at the state level, in blue states, at the city level,
has been a failure.
And the way, here's a metaway of thinking about it.
You invest in companies, right?
So as an investor, here's a really important thing.
You might have 10 people who come to you
with the same words in their pitch.
They're all, for example, building social networks.
But one of them is Facebook,
and the others are Friendster and whatever, okay?
And no offense to Friendster, you know,
these guys were like, you know, pioneers in their own way,
but they just got outmatched by Facebook.
So the point is that the words were the same
on each of these packages,
but the execution was completely different.
So could I imagine a highly competent government
that could execute and that actually did, you know,
like, you know, make the right balance of things and so on?
I can't say it's impossible,
but I can say that it wouldn't be this government.
Okay, and so you are talking about the words,
and I'm talking about the substance.
The words are, we will protect you from AI, right?
In my view, the substances,
they aren't protecting you from anything, right?
You're basically giving money and power
to a completely incompetent and, in fact, malicious organization,
which is Washington DC, which is the U.S. government,
that has basically over the last 30 years
gone from a hyperpower that wins everywhere without fighting
to a declining power that fights everywhere without winning.
Okay, like just literally burn trillions of dollars doing this,
take maybe the greatest decline in fortunes
in 30 years and maybe human history.
Not even the Roman Empire went down this fast
on this many power dimensions this quickly, right?
So giving that guy, let's trust him.
That's just people running an old script in their heads
that they inherited.
They are not thinking about it from first principles that
this state is a failure, okay?
And like how much of a failure it is,
you have to look at the sovereign debt crisis,
you have to look at graphs that other people aren't looking at,
but like, you know, the domain of what Blue America can regulate
is already collapsing because it can't regulate Russia anymore.
It can't regulate China anymore.
It's less able to regulate India.
It's less able even to regulate Florida and Texas.
States are breaking away from it domestically.
So this gets to your other point.
Why is the tribal lens not something that we can put in the back,
we have to put in the absolute front?
Because the world is retribalizing.
Like basically your tribe determines what law you're bound by.
If you think you can pass some policy that binds the whole world,
well, there have to be guys with guns who enforce that policy.
And if I have guys with guns on their side that say,
we're not enforcing that policy, then you have no policy.
You've only bound your own people.
Does that make sense, right?
And so Blue America will probably succeed in choking the life out of AI
within Blue America.
But Blue America controls less and less of the world.
So it'll have more power over fewer people.
I can go into why this is, but essentially, you know,
a financial Berlin Wall is arising.
There's a lot of taxation and regulation
and effectively financial repression de facto confiscation
that will have to happen for the level of debt service
that the US is being taking on.
OK, just there's one graph just to make the point.
And if you want to dig into this, you can.
But the reason this impacts things is when you're talking about AI safety,
you're talking about AI regulation.
You're talking about the US government, right?
And you have to ask, what does that actually mean?
And it's like, in my view, it's like asking the Soviet Union in 1989
to regulate the internet, right?
That's going to outlive, you know, the country.
US interest payment on federal debt versus defense spending.
The white line is defense spending.
Look at the red line.
That's just gone absolutely vertical.
That's interest.
And it's going to go more vertical next year
because all of this debt is getting refinanced
at much higher interest rates.
That's why look at this.
You want you want AI timelines, right?
The question for me is DC's timeline.
What is DC's time left to live?
OK, this is the kind of thing that kills empires
and you either have this just go to the absolute moon
or they cut rates and they print a lot.
And either way, you know, the fundamental assumption
underpinning all the AI safety, all the AI regulation work
is that they have a functional golem in Washington DC
where if they convince it to do something,
it has enough power to control enough of the world.
When that assumption is broken,
then a lot of assumptions are broken, right?
And so in my view, you have to you must think
about a polytheistic AI world
because other tribes are already into this.
They're already funding their own, right?
The proliferation is already happening
and they're not going to bow to blue tribes.
So that's why I think the tribal lens is not secondary.
It's not some, you know, totally separate thing.
It is an absolutely primary way in which to look at this.
And in a sense, it's almost like a, you know,
in a well done movie.
All the plot lines come together at the end.
Okay.
And all the disruptions that are happening,
the China disruption, the rise of India,
the rise of the internet, the rise of crypto,
the rise of AI and the decline of DC
and the internal political conflict
and, you know, various other theaters
like what's happening in Europe and, you know, and Middle East.
All of those come together into a crescendo of,
oh, there's a lot of those graphs are all having the same time.
And it's not something you can analyze by just, I think,
looking at one of these curves on its own.
I think that's a great note to wrap on.
I am always lamenting the fact that so many people
are thinking about this AI moment
in just fundamentally too small of terms.
But I don't think you're one that will easily be accused of that.
So with an invitation to come back
and continue in the not too distant future,
for now, I will say apology, Srinivasan.
Thank you for being part of the Cognitive Revolution.
Thank you, Nathan. Good to be here.
It is both energizing and enlightening
to hear why people listen
and learn what they value about the show.
So please don't hesitate to reach out via email at TCR at turpentine.co
or you can DM me on the social media platform of your choice.
Omnike uses generative AI
to enable you to launch hundreds of thousands of ad iterations
that actually work customized across all platforms
with a click of a button.
I believe in Omnike so much that I invested in it
and I recommend you use it too.
Use COGRAV to get a 10% discount.