HTML is used to define the structure and content of a web page. CSS is used to give
style to that structure and make it look nice. And CSS is really easy to learn.
I'm going to start on paper by drawing out the design that I want.
I want a header on my web page, you can say my website. On the left hand side I want some
navigation with some links there. I want the main content to be to the right and then a
footer at the bottom. I can have a copyright notice. So in HTML each box is going to be a div.
To define the structure even further I'm going to put everything in a div. So then I can center
that in the middle of the page. I'm going to put this middle section in a div as well because
in HTML it's good to define roles and then split the roles up into columns if necessary.
So we're going to call this outer one container. I'm going to give it the id container. The hash
means it's the id. Then we've got hash header. This middle container I'm going to call content.
And inside of content we've got hash nav for navigation and hash main for the main section.
And then hash footer at the bottom. I want the background of the whole page
around here to be gray. I want the background of container to be white.
I want the background of header to be blue. And I want the background of footer to be gray as well.
I want the whole thing to be 800 pixels wide. I want the content to have 10 pixels of padding
around the outside. So this space here I want 10 pixels which leaves 800 subtract 10 and 10 780
pixels for the content. If I want main to be 600 pixels wide this leaves 180 pixels for navigation.
Now I'm going to quickly create that HTML structure. First in Windows Explorer you need
to go to folder options and untick hide extensions for known file types. Then create a new text
document. I'm going to call it index and then change the dot txt dot html. Index is the name you
give to the home page of a website. I'm going to use notepad plus plus to edit this. Any text
editor will do. So html tags then our head tags and we have a title my website body tags.
We have a Dave with the ID container. Then we have a Dave with the ID header
content and footer. Inside content we have nav
and we have main. If you just zoom out you can see all of those Dave's makeup the structure we
drew out on paper. Inside header we just want heading one saying my website. Inside nav
heading three. Now for the navigation links it's a good idea to put them in an unordered list
just for some nice structure. We might have about we might have contact inside main header to
home page. I'm going to add three paragraphs paragraph one paragraph two and paragraph three
of text. This is just Laura Mipson which is nonsense text. Then finally in the footer copyright
ampersand copy semicolon gives you the copyright symbol 2014 jQuery. So if we save that and open
it in a browser you'll see all of the content is there but it just doesn't look very nice at all
and it doesn't have the layout that we want. This is where CSS comes in create a new file I'm going
to call it style.css. First we have to define a relationship between the html file and the CSS
file. We do this with the link tag in the head section of the html. The first attribute is the
relationship rel and we tell it that it's a style sheet. The type of the file is text slash CSS
and then the link or the path to the file and since it's in the same folder we can use a very
simple relative path of style.css and then it's a self-closing tag like that. So the syntax of CSS
first you define an element that you want to target. So if I want to target an element with the
id header I type hash header and then open curly brackets and then further down close the curly
brackets and everything inside these curly brackets will be applied to the anything on the page with
the id header. For example I want to set the background color to blue so set background hyphen
color. Multiple ways to set colors I can just type blue but that doesn't give you much freedom and
control. The best way to do it is with a hex code. If you google html color codes you'll get a nice
list of these and I found earlier that 66ccff is a nice shade of blue. When you do this you must
prefix the number with a hash. So if we save this and refresh our page we get a blue background for
the header. We might also want to make the text inside that div white. We do that by saying color
colon and we can just type the word white and then each line must end in a semicolon. I mentioned
that I wanted the background of the whole page to be gray. You can target the whole page by targeting
the body tag. Now you don't need a hash just the word body and we can set the background color.
Hash eee eee is the shade of gray that I want. You'll often see when all of the numbers or
letters are the same you can shorten it and just type three of them. Then we wanted our container
to have a white background. I want the heading of the website to be centered. You can do that with
text hyphen align center. Remember the semicolon and I wanted the whole page to be centered in the
middle and I wanted it to be 800 pixels wide. This is why we wrapped everything in a container
div so we can set the width to be 800 pixels. Now to center it you need to set the margin hyphen
left to auto and the margin hyphen right to auto. This will center divs horizontally. This doesn't
work vertically but it's very useful for doing it horizontally. I've just noticed I've got a
home page in there twice. Sorry about that. Our next problem is putting the navigation and the
home page side by side. Let's start by defining the widths. We wanted the content div to have 10
pixels of padding. Now we could do padding left 10 pixels padding right 10 pixels but it's quicker
just to use the shorthand property padding and then the first number is the top the second number
is the right the third number is the bottom and the fourth number is the left hand side padding.
Now since these are all the same we can shorten this even more and simply just type 10 pixels and
that applies it to all sides. We then wanted our nav div to have a width of 180 pixels and our main
div to have a width of 600 pixels. Now the thing about divs is they always appear on a new line.
To stop that we need to set them to float. We want them to float next to each other. We want
nav to float to the left of its parent. Content is its parent. Now main can float either left or
right. It doesn't matter because there's no space for it to move but I'm going to put right so it's
so easy to see which order they come in. So that puts them next to each other. It makes a new problem
though since they're floating the footer now doesn't care that it hasn't finished it it they overlap.
To fix that we target the footer div and we apply a rule to this saying clear both. Now this means
we must be clear of any floating elements before we display ourselves. So you can see here there's
still a floating element here. Clearing both means let's get past all of the floating elements and
then display. Moving back to the HTML I'm just going to actually make these navigation links into
links with the a tag. They're not going to go anywhere and I'm going to apply a class to the
first one and call it selected because that is the page we're on at the men at the homepage.
So let's first make the selected link bold. To do that we can target the class
dot selected hash for ID dot for a class. Now if we had a selected class somewhere else and we
wanted to be more specific we could do hash nav hash selected just separate them with a space.
This filters it down to any object with the class selected inside of the object with the ID nav.
Then we can say font-weight bold. Since the links it puts an underline under them we might not want
that. We might want to get rid of underlines on all links on the page. So just like we targeted
the body tag we can target the a tag and say text hyphen decoration non. We might want our links to
be red color red and we don't like those bullet points. So let's do something about those. Let's
target the unordered list within the navigation div. Let's set the list hyphen style hyphen type
to non that removes the bullet points and let's set the padding to zero that removes the space
at the left. The reason we have a gap along the top is because this heading has a margin on it.
We can target the h1 tag and set the margin to zero. If we wanted to apply the same rules to a
number of different tags we can separate them with commas. We could apply to h2 and h3 as well
and that would remove the margin from all of the headings. To give the webpage a nicer font we can
set the font family property of the whole body tag. Now you need a font stack you start with the
name of the font that you want then you need some backups in case the user doesn't have that font.
So we could try aerial and just end with a type of font like sans serif.
Finally let's give the footer 10 pixels of padding.
Set the background color to gray. I'm going to choose 999999.
Set the color of the text to white and set the text a line to right.
And equally give the header 10 pixels of padding.
And there we go that's the webpage we designed on paper.
So to recap the syntax of CSS first you start by specifying what you want the following rules to
target. So that could be something with a particular id in which case you type a hash
and then the id which could be something like header. Then you open curly brackets
and then close the curly brackets and inside it's a good idea to indent just like an hdml so
easy to read. You can put the rules they come in the form of the property name a colon and then
the value you want to set. Each rule ends with a semicolon and it's useful to put each rule on
a new line. If you want to target something with a particular class you use a dot instead of a hash.
If you want to combine them if I wanted to to apply this rule to the object with id header and
all of the objects with class sidebar I can do that by using a comma.
If you want to target a tag instead of an id or a class you just type the name of the tag
so like a or body. If you want to be more specific just separate the identifiers with spaces so you
can have hash content dot sidebar and this means apply this rule to any object with a class sidebar
inside the object with the id content. Of course this doesn't have to be an id that could be a
class we could be even more specific. This chain can be as long as you want as long as in the hdml
this is inside of this and this is inside of this. One last thing I want to mention is that you don't
need to put the css in a separate file or two other places you can put it. You can put it
inside style tags directly in the head section just like that or you can use inline css. You
can add the style attribute to any hdml tag but it's better practice and much simpler if you keep
the css separate in its own file so I recommend doing that. Hopefully this has given you a good
introduction to css which will help you turn those plain websites into something presentable.
Thanks for watching. Number which is number plus number two and then we could output by typing
echo sum five plus three which will as expected give us eight.