Hey everyone, my name is Ajay and welcome to Philosophy Battle.
Before this video starts I just want to make clear that this video is about logic and whether
or to what extent there can be alternative logics.
Because if there can be alternative logics, then which logic we are using can be considered
relative to some other factors.
And typically logic is taken to be one of the strongholds against claims to relativism.
Logic is often taken to be as proof of something that isn't relative, much like math.
So this video will introduce also some basic logic and the basic concepts of logic and
if you are already familiar with logic, well just be a little bit patient.
The more philosophically gripping stuff will come at the end.
Either way it does get progressively more intense, but stick to it.
Even if you don't get certain parts or know what's going on, it could still be very well
cleared up later on at some point and at the end the main point or main conclusion will
be made pretty clear, at least I think so.
Now the video will be covering a section from a book of a philosopher, a lecturer at Trinity
College in Dublin, philosopher Paul O'Grady, because I think that his book has got a lot
of great and interesting battles in it and a lot for us to learn.
But if you don't care about O'Grady or the larger discussion of relativism I'm having
here, that's okay.
You don't have to watch anything else other than this if you're just interested in logic,
even if I'm suggesting it.
Just take it more as a kind of signpost if you want more information, if I do suggest
another video at various parts of this one.
Trust me, even if you don't watch any other things, this will still be a great video introducing
the ideas of logic and the possibility of alternatives in philosophy.
Finally, I just want to thank my Patreon supporters.
Slick Pockets
Now let's start the show and hear a short recap of how we got here first.
Logic vs. Relativism
This video is part of a series covering a few books on relativism before we go back to
the battlefield of the philosophy of science, where we had encountered some extreme relativists.
And trust me, it's going to be awesome when we do go back because of what we learn here
in the battlefield of metaphysics.
In particular, this video is covering a section in this green book simply called Relativism
by Paul O'Grady.
We previously already covered in a video his first chapter that explains the power of relativism
that I visualize as this philosophic weapon.
That video explains how this philosophic weapon came into being in modern philosophic warfare
as empowered by five great philosophers and thus how it's possible that even a reasonable
person may perhaps be led into believing that everything is relative.
Not just what flowers look the best, or what candy tastes the best, or who's the best
philosophy YouTuber, it's me obviously.
But that everything is relative.
They feel truth, knowledge, scientific fact, logic, even reality is relative.
Nothing is objective.
Nothing.
Absolute.
Now that's an extreme position.
But the powers of this weapon is actually based in philosophic writing and the history
of science.
It's not just some made up contrived stuff here, so please go check out that video if
you'd like to really understand why one can't just offhand dismiss a relativist.
When you really see the reasoning, it can be clearly a difficult enemy to challenge.
But also, this wickedly powerful weapon is an important one for philosophers to use ourselves
in investigation to challenge to question claims of objectivity.
It's just that unlike these extreme relativists, we will gain the understanding to see that
it does still in fact have limits.
And Paulo Grady in his book covers two places where he defends against the charges of relativism,
where those limits of this weapon should be, on truth and rationality.
So these are the two battles that I wanted to cover, one on truth and one on rationality.
And actually we already covered that first battle defending truth, and trust me it was
so awesome.
So if you're interested in just trying to figure out how to defeat this enemy in terms
of defending a non-relative truth in particular, then you can check out this video.
But to be honest, the way I presented it was that Ogrady does a kind of setup first, where
he actually uses a logical principle of non-contradiction to then go into battle on these two areas.
So it's understandable that he actually has a section devoted to relativism about logic
in particular right in that first chapter, where he's going to discuss whether or not,
or to what extent, we can have alternative logics, whether logic is relative.
So that's what we're going to be covering right now, and I did promise I'm going to
try and go a little faster in this normal one because it kind of was just an additional
section to that first great battle.
But I thought it might be also nice for me to show you all what formal symbolic logic
actually looks like if you're not familiar with it, it might be kind of cool to actually
visually see, and it will also give you a kind of good mental understanding to sit in
the background of what philosophers really mean when we're talking about logic.
First is just some, you know, I don't know, it's like a political hack on the internet
touting rhetoric about how logic is on their side, we mean something much more than that.
So despite me trying to blast through some stuff, since I am still covering what Ogrady
says, as usual I will cite things down to the line, and when I'm not speaking for or
giving my interpretation a presentation for our purposes of what Ogrady says in the text,
then the citation in the corner of the screen will just disappear.
That way you'll know it's coming from me, and what is coming from my interpretation
of what he's saying.
Cool?
Get it?
Okay, let's go.
Logic is intimately tied into issues of truth because of the notions of coherence and contradiction.
Not everyone feels that way though, some will say it's more noticeably about inferences
than about truth.
But I don't have time to deal with them here, and most do see logic as having something
to do with truth, and I already mentioned a couple of logical laws in the previous battle
against the Alithic Relativist, Alithic being about truth and relativism as in being dependent
on something else.
And namely, I mentioned the laws of non-contradiction and the law of the excluded middle.
And if you want to see that, you know what to do, hehe.
Anyway, the question is, even if yes, so say the truth isn't relative, even if the truth
is absolute, couldn't there still be legitimate alternative systems of logic?
Or is there just one most basic, one correct one?
Ogrity then tries to explain what logic even is, saying it's fundamental to human reasoning.
It governs the process of inferring beliefs in a truth-preserving way, such that if one
starts with true beliefs and then makes no mistakes in logic, one is guaranteed to have
true beliefs as a conclusion.
This is usually what we call validity, and it's the central notion in logic.
A valid argument is one where if the premises are true, then the conclusion must be true.
Now thousands of years ago, Aristotle was the first to codify logical laws and principles,
but they were around even before him, but this codification marks it as a formal discipline.
So I'm gonna try now and explain this as best as I can with some actual visual examples
that might help us for the background for the rest of this video.
Logic is a way of reasoning, and let's look at three examples of mine.
If it's true that if it rains you should put on a coat, and then you find out it is raining,
we can conclude you should put on a coat.
We just kind of reason it out, or for another example, if it's true that if it rains then
the street would be wet, but then you find out the street isn't wet, then you can conclude
that it didn't rain.
This is us using logic to figure this out.
But let's do one more.
Let's just for the sake of argument imagine that it's true that either it's raining
or we're eating pizza.
But we find out, hey, we're not eating pizza, we can conclude then it is raining.
So logic is the ability for us to figure out a conclusion that kind of preserves the same
amount of certainty as the stuff that led to the conclusion.
So technically logic isn't about figuring out if those premises are true or not, but
just that if they are the conclusion must be true.
So like in this example logic won't be telling us if it's actually true that it's actually
raining outside for example, unless of course you know it's raining is derived from some
other argument prior.
In any case logic is just what's helping us reason out this conclusion.
And philosophers have codified that like math has been codified.
And just to help us with a comparison to math which actually is going to be a running theme
later on, reasoning in math doesn't need to look like this.
This is kind of a codification and symbolization of math.
Technically one doesn't even need to know any of what these things even mean to reason
out mathematically.
In fact when we first teach this symbolic math to children we actually teach them the
reasoning in other ways first without this symbolic language.
For example we might say hey look at all your fingers put them up, you see there is one
two three four five six seven eight nine ten up.
Now put two fingers down.
Now see how many fingers you have left up.
One two three four five six seven eight.
So there are eight fingers up.
Thus children may be able to figure out how many fingers are up without even being literate
or even ever having to see these particular symbols ever.
But math has been formalized and symbolized and has functions that we slowly begin to teach
children moving away from saying something like I give you five apples but you eat two
apples to just saying you have five apples but take away two apples.
Then we just stop saying take away and start saying minus two instead.
Also we'll just stop saying the apples so we end up saying just five minus two.
Then again perhaps we will teach them a more appropriate way of saying it as five subtract
two while showing these symbols in particular.
Then we fully begin to discuss our numerical or quantified reasoning through this mathematical
symbolic language in ways that don't even have to connect to real world stuff.
We don't have to be talking about apples and oranges or whatever else anymore to do math
like this through symbols.
So now a similar type of thing has happened and from here I'm just going to ask you to
follow along as much as you possibly can but if you get lost don't worry we're going
to go back to O'Grady but I think this will be pretty fun.
So similarly philosophers have made it so that we can symbolize the process of this
stuff but by representing these propositions as letters we'll be using in our calculations
and having certain symbols to represent those relations between propositions kind of like
these symbols in math I guess you could say such as the if then symbol a conditional symbol
so if p then q or this symbol for negation and while we have these symbols we also have
inference rules that allow us to use these symbols and figure things out using these
symbols in different ways for example if p then q well given p therefore q this is called
modus ponens it's super simple and it fits pretty well with our first example but now
let's look at that second example if these propositions are represented by these letters
then we can show it as if p then q and we find out that not q thus we can conclude not
p this is called modus ponens again so like that first one was allowing us to show the
truth of p that led us to the truth of q this one kind of allows us to use the negation
to move backwards the falsehood of q or rather not q allows us to figure out not p backwards
and now for our third example if these are our definitions we can present this with an
or symbol and we can do something called disjunctive syllogism where p or q means either this or
that which means both can't be false if one is false the other has to be true so if we
have not q it means that we can conclude p so that's what these would look like but
again remember logic isn't actually figuring out if not q is really true for this argument
we have to find out other ways to actually verify not q in this case it's just that
if it were not q then we can conclude p must be the case and so this is a valid deduction
is either valid or not if it is valid it can be sound or not and we know if it is sound
by some other means by figuring out if this particular argument still has all its premises
are actually true now that might not seem like an important distinction but actually it's
very important for a philosopher because sometimes your enemy presents an argument and technically
their logic is valid as in these things really do lead to this conclusion logically so the
problem isn't that it isn't valid just that perhaps you question one or more of the premises
as being true so you're not saying the argument isn't valid but that it isn't sound because
say this premise isn't true for example now that may be not super important for what we're
going to be talking about in this video so don't worry about trying to remember all
these things if you don't know about it but it is super important for philosophers just
to be accurate about what we're criticizing in another to ensure our attacks actually
land but getting back to the symbols now let's go and make a big old puzzle but now kind
of like not needing apples anymore we're not even going to need these definitions we're
just going to show these letters because we don't even really care if it's sound we're
just going to be trying to figure out if it's a valid deduction so let me just add a couple
of other things so we can make a bigger one just as an example first of all dn or double
negation it's where there's two knots two knots cancel each other out so not not p through
double negation just makes p and vice versa that one's pretty easy we kind of spoke about
this previously in the previous video but also there's another one where p and q written
maybe with this symbol instead of ampersand could be simplified through the process of
simplification either as p or as q and the other process can happen too where if you
have p and q in different places you could actually just put them together through something
called adjunction and have p and q anyway now let's look at this one for funsies if
q then p q or r if r then not s given t and s prove q it's like a puzzle isn't it let's
solve it now so we're given p and s we can simplify that to just s and with just s we
can make it not not s through double negation right because it's the same thing but with
not not s and if r not s we can do modus tolens and therefore get not r because remember whoop
so that's not r and with not r and q or r we can do disjunctive syllogism therefore getting
us q because remember if it's not r then it has to be q and with q and if q then p we
do our basic modus tonens and therefore conclude p boom done that's the proof we proved p if
these are all true then given this one can prove logically this must be true fun huh
well if you don't think so that's okay it's like a puzzle and if you learn all the rules
intimately and do more puzzles it can be super fun just like doing math or stats puzzles
or playing chess or doing sudoku I don't know they can all be super fun if you play
them and it can really be cool and enjoyable to take the truth of this and run it through
this big ol process and get a result here considered a proof this is really basic stuff though
and actually there are far more advanced logics than this but let me just stop there before
I cut myself off too early when it comes to logic being presented in this way it's called
formal logic and it is a kind of symbolic logic so personally just to be clear when
I find some in the common regular non mathematicians non philosophers non computer scientists
saying logic they kind of just generally mean some kind of reasoning something like I believe
what I believe based on this this is what I think and I think this makes sense that's
my logic well that seems really loose and open and it seems to also sometimes mix or
not even regard the difference between soundness and validity but either way still there's
some understanding that logic has something to do with some kind of reasoning but when
philosophers say logic it pays to mention if you mean formal logic like this like as
in a system created for us to do reasoning in of a certain kind kind of like saying I'm
doing math to a mathematician they will tend to now really think of math in this way in
particular this may just seem like an aside but trust me we'll come into play later formal
logic just systematizes and articulates a kind of inferences we make in our everyday reasoning
processes to help us figure out valid reasoning versus fallacious reasoning fallacious is if
a conclusion doesn't actually follow from the premises well Aristotle's classic formal
logic was so good that a couple of thousand years later Emmanuel Kant was like logic is a
completed science nothing to add but then there was a renewed interest in logic in the 19th century
because of big developments happening in math and as we've been mentioning in like the last four
videos I think German mathematician and philosopher Gottlieb Frege made one of the most significant
contributions with his big big big riff bigger shrift forgive me for not knowing how to say
this properly read it a thousand times just don't have friends to tell me how to say things
and if a bigger shift actually kind of looks like this but it was Frege's writings who actually
brought for a more modern symbolic logic it was even more sophisticated than Aristotle's and
could articulate relations and generalities in such a way that one could even show mathematical
truths derived from logical truths so like I was saying earlier we can do a mental processing that
we call reasoning which makes use of a kind of logic in terms of inferring beliefs from other
beliefs and formal logic systematizes and makes a symbolic language of us doing that kind of
reasoning which actually helps us do that kind of thing but maybe we could say there's another
kind of mental processing perhaps we'll call it calculating which is the use of math and this
math stuff is also systematized and put into a symbolic kind of language which helps us do that
well Frege's articulation was actually so good it made it possible to show that maybe even math
actually is from logical reasoning that it isn't a unique different kind of thought processing
this was called logicism and Russell and Whitehead furthered that position in their famous
Principia Mathematica showing their logical systems and how they can derive mathematical
truths from them what logic was shown to be more fundamental to our mental processing than math
that actually math comes from it wow so cool at least I think that's pretty cool anyway they
only actually used five basic symbols in their logic but later Wittgenstein you know who came
after it goes Frege Russell Wittgenstein anyway Wittgenstein in the TLP the Tractatis logical
philosophicus which is his most famous writing from when he was younger actually suggested
breaking down all of logic to just one symbol actually I think Wittgenstein used the shepherd
stroke to show this and really shepherd was the first to show this I think to show that we can
do all of propositional logic with just one symbol but I'm not sure if he was the first to
actually show it so if you're a logician and you know who is actually the first to show this let
me know in the comments below but also if I remember correctly I think Wittgenstein was trying to
show that even predicate logic can be expressed with it too but anyway if that sounds like nonsense
don't worry about it basically we have these five symbols right the if then conditional the if and
only if by conditional this symbol which is basically and the or symbol which means that one of the
two must be true both can't be false and the negation symbol so there's five symbols right
but actually I can be fine doing it all with just one symbol what really just one symbol
how are you gonna do that well let me show you firstly this by conditional is pretty easy p if
and only q all it means that both if p then q and also if q then p it was just a combination of both
anyway to show that if you have one you can get the other and it goes both ways so scratch that one
since we can actually express it simply by using both of these in separate ways but now what about
this one the conditional if p then q how can I replace that well actually I can replace it with
the or symbol by saying not p or q wait what why well if you remember at least one must be true
so if one is false we know the other is true and so if q is false or not q then we can conclude
not p must be true and that's also basically modus tollens here if p then q but we have
not q then you know we would have not p so it works in both senses but now also if it's not not p
then it has to be q not not p is the same as p remember with double negation so that's the
same thing as saying if p then q so actually these are logically equivalent so I can express an if then
just using or so scratch that one too now what about these last three well check it out you can
take the chefer stroke to mean well it can either mean nand which is to say not and or nor which is
to say not or as far as I can tell I think you just got to be clear on which one you mean when
you're using it and for some reason it seems that people use the arrow down to be nor and is also
associated with pierce and this arrow the arrow up is more associated with nand and I don't really
know why I'm not really a logician or anything I'm just trying to be as honest and truthful as
possible here remember we're actually trying to talk about relativism but anyway I can't tell technically
why it is that way but as far as I can tell I think it just matters what you're actually clear on
when you actually do use it so if this lash means nor this chefer stroke then it means that both
must be false that neither this nor this so to show not p you would show neither p nor p
the only options for p here show that they are false so with this chefer stroke I don't technically
need this not symbol to show and p and q I can show it by saying neither neither p nor p nor
neither q nor q remember this is negating both sides saying both side must be false so to say
not p is to say this and if both of these are therefore not this and not this and both of
those are shown as being negative because they're shown with this and that flips them back to being
both true and thus you are saying p and q pretty cool huh anyway so that means I don't actually
need that symbol either I can show it all with just this stroke and also I can even show p or q
by showing neither neither p nor q nor neither p nor q and you can look at that and figure out how
that one makes sense yourself if you'd like but either way the point is I don't even need this
and so I can show all of these just by using one symbol this chefer stroke just this line and you
know what technically it doesn't even have to be this one symbol in fact I can make it all another
symbol or rather I can just take this line to mean something else the nand the arrow up instead
and they would look like this anyway this is not at all important to remember for us and our sake
so let's just take a deep breath and clear our mind a bit and not feel too bogged down if you
didn't get what I was saying let's just get back to oh grady the point is that we can break it all
down to just one symbol if we wanted or more if we wanted more depending on what suits us best
each would be its own system so we can make a new system with four or one with six but hey the real
question comes if maybe we can make an altogether new system we set up with new symbols that tell us
to do completely different things hmm anyway there's really no limit to how many systems you could
have one just set up a new set of symbols and a new system of rules of inference and a new system
appeared but these would be syntactic systems pure theoretical or formal like not connected to
anything outside of it when it comes to having to connect to things outside of it like those letters
representing real world stuff or true or false representing ones and zeros on a computer then
yeah then it seems like there's limits on what those systems could be and how are they these
new systems even related back to how we normally commonly just do reasoning logically you know
without these formal systems before us there were so many systems that could be very different not
just different from the principia mathematical but from the way we normally do daily common
logical reasoning now there were two fundamental laws in the principia mathematical that actually
go way back all the way as presented to Aristotle in ancient times those were the law of non-contradiction
and the law of the excluded middle the law of non-contradiction holds that a proposition
and its negation cannot be both true together the law of the excluded middle holds that all
propositions are either true or false there is no third value both of these came up before when
we battled against relativizing truth arguing to keep both of these and yo you really gotta
watch that previous video of truth versus relativism because Paulo Grady does some awesome stuff and
some important lessons there that could last forever in philosophy so please do check it out
well even those laws logicians have experimented with getting rid of them in these new various
systems that they can make but is it possible that even they can kind of represent how we in
common day do reasoning well well before we do that let's just be clear about the difference
between a classic logic with just a small change or a small difference and a full blown alternative
logic so philosopher susan hack actually has a very useful way of distinguishing between systems
that are actually rivals versus those that are just slightly added to so a basic logical system
is symbols that have rules on how to set up those symbols and what some of those symbols
mean as in what it says about their relation those are the inference rules or transformation rules
like modus ponens or modus tonens like i showed you earlier these things are also called well
formed formulas by hack but whatever anyway now this is just a syntactic characterization of how
thus a structure is set up a semantic characterization is the idea that truth of the premises that we
put into the system is preserved in the conclusion we get out now if we have two systems that are
set up the same with the same transformation rules but just looking different with different
symbols but they mean the same thing then that's not really a rival system the real differences
start when you get two systems let's call them a and b that share the same basic symbols but b
has more symbols and thus more theorems and greater expression we'll call this extended logic
it doesn't actually clash with the earlier classic system just adds to it ogready gives the example
of modal logic with the distinctions of necessity and possibility which is a kind of logic that i
didn't really do but i can imagine it one that i have done that i think would count here is called
quantified predicate logic is the one where you have the universal and existential symbols
logicians forgive me it's been a long time but anyway another difference here is if the symbols
actually mean something different if there's actually different rules of inference in that case
a would be a classic logic and b would be a deviant logic i assume because of how much it deviates
not because of how naughty it is in the bedroom to do or is it hey girl you down to do some deviant
logic with me back at my place okay sorry back to uh philosophy so an example of a deviant logic
would be a three-valued logic which we discussed three-value logic in the previous video again
please please do go check that one out it's a system where something doesn't have to be either
just true or false it can be even some other thing anyway another example would also be a
quantum logic where certain rules can be dropped in favor of different ones now some of these
deviant systems are actually proposed as a full-on replacement for classical logic like saying this
three-valued system is actually superior and should replace the two-valued one in all cases
to be clear for our question of relativism advocating that one is just right the right one
in all cases that we should always use it even if it is a deviant one therefore isn't relativism
it's still saying that just one is correct so it's not really relativism about logic even if
that one is a deviant one but how can we determine which is the true system of logic relativism
emerges if you say two or more systems are legitimate candidates and we can just choose
between them and even move back and forth even why would we want to be able to move to another system
well hack has four different sorts of reasons why one would want to do that that ogready outlines
and i'm gonna blast through these because i don't want this video to be too long like i said
i don't like how ogready phrase some stuff in here and really it's not all that important for us
to know the details of these only important that there are legitimate reasons to want to use a
deviant logic so this just goes to show that the issue goes well beyond just oh we can create them
firstly there's a general metaphysical reason an example of this is from dutch mathematician
bauer who thought unlike russell that math actually can't be derived from logic and while it can
exist as calculating in the mind in a way without an explicit symbolic language it is its own
fundamental way of thinking he felt the nature of math is that it is constructed by the intellect
so there couldn't be mathematical truths that are unknowable to the mind but this logical
principle of the excluded middle would mean that there are some math truths even things we don't
know that are still nevertheless true or false just we don't know them bauer denied this for
mathematical truth so he wanted to drop the law of the excluded middle so i guess like for bauer
that means math truths can't be unknown i'm not really sure here look this is a section where i
don't think ogrady says things right because clearly there's a difference between unknowable
or unjudgeable by the human mind versus just unknown or unjudged but anyway i guess if we really
wanted to see what's going on here or with any of these things i can just go and check out susan
hack's fuzzy book or maybe for this one in particular perhaps it came from bauer's two-part paper i
don't really know if that's where it came from i'm not sure because i didn't read susan hack's
book but if you want here's the journey for you you can read this and this and let us know anyway
maybe one day i can do hacks book in a series on logic like i'm doing these three books on
relativism right now but anyway the second reason hack presents is a desire to avoid philosophical
problems some philosophical commitments may be considered troublesome an example of that is
that someone wants to avoid fatalism the doctrine that events are predetermined and unmanable to
free will and one version of that comes just from accepting the law of the excluded middle
it is either true or false that i will be knocked down by a car tomorrow even though i have no way
of knowing which it is the case that one of these options is a determinate fact remember with excluded
middle something is either true or false not both not some new thing so facts about the future
must already be set in that way and for those of us who want to believe free will that my choice
which hasn't been made yet should impact what is true or false this could be seen as a problem
now there are different ways to deal with this one can just say that facts about the future can't
be true or false but doing that has a price you wouldn't even be able to say the sun will rise
tomorrow is true then so instead of doing that just denying the excluded middle could be one way of
diffusing the fatalist issue while at the same time allowing some future statements to be true
in any case the third source of reasons that motivates adopting another logic is a desire
to avoid scientific problems whereas the previous ones dealt more with dropping the excluded middle
this one's more closer to dropping the law of non-contradiction the reason being how these
deviant logics work with well-confirmed stuff happening in science namely quantum physics
now i had questioned this but whatever the idea is quantum particles behave in ways not
describable in the standard laws of logic like quantum superpositioning now ogrady uses david
z albert's quote about the path of quantum particles but ultimately says of this quantum
that it drops what are called the classical distribution laws but the distribution laws
isn't the law of non-contradiction i just want to be clear on that but anyway for the next one
the fourth reason is a desire for logical innovation systems can actually be made to
drop the law of non-contradiction why do that is it just useless well you know it's pretty much
just making them for the sake of expanding our minds sort of thing and maybe it can also help
us to understand paradoxes and stuff too so those are the four reasons ogrady outlines that hack
has for why someone would even move to an alternative logic it's not just a trivial or for the fun of
it type of thing that different systems can be made but now let's see some objections against
alternative logics ah the husband wife duo influential historians of logic w neal and
m neal hold that even from a purely formal point of view the ordinary two-valued system
has a unique status among deductive systems which can possibly be called logic since it contains
all others as fragments of itself in short they are not alternatives to classical logic
but this can be challenged truth for multi-valued logics actually may not appear in fact cannot
appear in classic two-valued systems i think that one's kind of obvious i don't know why they even
said that then ogrady says the distinctive position here seems just historical a long-standing tradition
but tradition can hardly stop philosophers and i agree with ogrady on that heavily but i would
like to note that from that quote though there's actually nothing in it to suggest that the neals
were making their claim on the basis of long-standing tradition but it reads like ogrady is saying
that's what it seems like their position also is but didn't cite that part or put a quote for it
not saying ogrady is wrong about them he certainly knows the neals ever more than i ever will but
just pointing it out that that quote actually had nothing to do with long-standing tradition of a
two-valued system anyway ogrady then devotes a few pages particularly to an argument by the
champion philosopher quine who uses the translation argument against deviant logics he gives us the
details of the background and all that and i don't really think that's fully necessary for our purposes
especially to show what ogrady's position ultimately is but i'll blast through it super fast
just so that i'm not depriving y'all of at least mentioning it given how much time ogrady devotes
to talking about it and i think you'll see why he's doing that though so like i said not to confuse
anyone but i'm gonna go kind of fast and be a little bit lax on this see first there was these
folks right and we'll call them rational intuitions who thought that logical truths can actually be
known in a special way prior to having any experience of anything so like you don't have to
make any observations in the world you can just kind of think about it and realize it's true
and so that's you using your kind of rational intuition to grasp its truth and while there are
a lot of logical truths that we know because we infer them from other ones some of them can actually
be known just straight up immediately with rational intuition no other premises required
and even some of those things that the rational intuition can figure out for us can even reveal
the nature of reality like some fundamental truths about how the world works anyway russell
who co-authored the principia of mathematically that book that shows logic more fundamental than
math you know logicism and whatnot well he felt this way too that logical truths are known through
our rational intuition not through any experience like other empirically dependent beliefs while at
first that kind of makes sense for us actually that would seem super spooky and mystical for the
positivists so they were all like yo f that but then to explain or make sense of how we grasp logical
truths then they claim that we know logical truths because they are dependent on the linguistic
framework we make or are using and if you think of it that also kind of makes sense based on what
we're saying remember we can make different syntactic structures if we want to so positivists
advanced a linguistic theory of logical truths holding that logic derives from linguistic rules
and there's different in many complex versions of this but carnap was one of them remember he was
a positivist philosopher who thought that we could make different linguistic frameworks or as we might
want to start calling it different logics for scientists to use so for those with the linguistic
theory of logic all logic really is is just following the rules within a linguistic practice
which if you think of it kind of implies there wasn't particularly anything special or deep about
logic beyond merely which linguistic framework we are using and i guess that's where we kind of are
now and now we're gonna see quine respond to this because quine ain't downwardist you see because
quine likes logic so quine agreed with the criticism against the intuitionist because he too wants to
be empirical in certain ways and we'll get to that in another chapter but he thought there was
actually no need to bother trying to explain logic with something else as if there's something more
fundamental to it quine be like logic is so fundamental to thought you can't explain or
argue for it with something else or gritty says of quine logic is so basic to our thinking that
nothing more fundamental could explain it so quine be like nah you don't need something to explain
it because if you understand the language you will just give a scent to logic anyway it's obvious
and anyone who correctly understands the language in question will just give a scent to a logical
truth as an obvious truth yeah you could have trivially different logical systems and textbooks
and whatnot but when it comes to actual deviant logics well if someone comes up to you and is like
ayo p and not p you will be like no this this isn't a sincere deviant logical person it's better to
just assume that they probably don't understand what and means or what not means or they actually
mean something completely different when they say it because the assumption is if they did know what
those things mean in the way that we do they simply would not be saying it it's just always better
to believe there's actually a mistranslation going on even if we don't know exactly what it is then to
believe someone is actually using a deviant logic he compares it to master david humes move of saying
if you come across some claims to miracles it's better to believe no there must be some explanation
to this than they're actually being a miracle and that it's always better to believe there is some
actual explanation for some event even if you don't know what that explanation is yet
then to believe there is a miracle and quines boy david sin well boy no uh sorry for my colloquialism
anyway that is quines former student david sin took this argument to a whole next level
not just for logic but even against different conceptual schemes now part of the reason of
this book isn't just to survey all the places where relativists can attack and where a gradey
can defend but also actually he wants to battle david sin to the death no i'm just kidding there's
no actual violence here and even what ogready wants to do isn't actually all that confrontational
with david sin i find he just wants to present a softer argument rather than a hard argument david
sin does in his chapter on rationality so maybe that explains why he went to some depth of the
background of this argument from quine 2 talking about it here even mentioning the positivists
and stuff like that which i didn't bother getting into ogready says he will talk about
both of these philosophers anyway in different places though when he gets to them but for
right now he's gonna suggest that quines argument ain't that perfect in part because it's coming
from him nothing personal just pointing out that this argument seems to anticipate or set up a just
offhand rejection of deviant logics a priori but quines whole epistemological thing is that there
are no a priori nothing we know before experiencing it everything can be changed with experience
no beliefs have any kind of special unchangeable place but at the same time it seems he's making
logic special here and remember the translation argument is an argument that a priori rejects
deviant logics so what's going on here quine you all over the place well ogready admits the
precise interpretation of quines position is a delicate and disputed issue so it seems ogready
is open to a quinian philosopher defending quine and clarifying the different positions quine has
taken and evolved over time in which particular ways also my presentation of quine would probably
make a quinian even more frustrated and heck this ain't even my own details covering of ogready
talking about quine it's just my blast through but to be fair again ogready does say he will
look into quine himself in more detail and clarify his position better than he has done here at least
in this chapter at least he will do better when he gets to his chapter in ontology anyway there's
other problems for quine's argument too like it just assumes a classic two-valued logic is what's
obviously deep in the mind fundamental and all so everything outside of it we kind of just translate
to it but there's no argument here in particular for why this obviously correct thing in the mind
can't be for someone else say an intuitionist logician having a three plus valued logic or
something else the argument just states that there is a base logic but there is no argument here
for what that logic has to be that it has to be a classic two-valued system and not a deviant one
also it seems quine is using considerations about translation because of his own commitment to
empiricism and behaviorism but one could argue that empirical evidence isn't appropriate to
determine the nature of logic i mean maybe there's some metaphysical underpinning that can explain
why logic is special in any case ogready seems to hold that there are indeed arguments against
deviant logics but they aren't all that perfect there's flaws in him ogready then goes on to
describe his own position that looks like this he says and we're going to quote this line by
line while i give my own visualization of it even if one accepts a deviant system and believes there
are good philosophical grounds for defending it there seems to be general regulative principles
governing the choice of a logical system these include consistency coherence simplicity efficacy
and so on our choice of a logical system is itself governed by a more general conception of
rationality he says there are notions of logic that operate up here and those are what he argues
for in his chapter on rationality the law of non-contradiction and he says he won't argue for
it but it's possible that for the reasons of simplicity we would also have up here a two valued
system the law of the excluded middle simply because then you don't have to mess around with truth
where does that leave the legitimacy of deviant logic well it's pretty clear that multi-valued
systems are possible and there's no compelling formal argument against having them but also
up here the meta level that governs the adoption of such systems is committed to at least the law
of non-contradiction and probably for reasons of simplicity to the law of the excluded middle lower
level contacts requiring suspension of this to require the existence of such a meta level
is to argue for the core conception of rationality which will be argued for in chapter five
this is an absolute non-relative conception governing degrees of diversity beneath it
so the upshot of this discussion is that there are legitimate alternative logical
calculi useful for various purposes but ultimately governed by a system adhering to the
traditional laws of logic and with that the chapter ends so we see ogredi does allow relativism
on logic in terms of the lower level but argues that there are some principles of logic on the
meta level or above which he defends and he will be calling the core conception of rationality
once again leading us to that second great battle where he defends against relativism
on his chapter on rationality so we gotta go and check that out this means though for some folks
that come up and be like hey this isn't relative it's logical you could say there are actually
different logics back to that but ultimately they may be just saying something about how
basic rationality that governs fundamental way we think is nevertheless beholden to logical
laws if that's what they are saying you could say so you mean rationality isn't relative
which is kind of different but maybe that's just not much criticism behind what they meant to say
only that it's probable that they don't really understand logic in the way philosophers or
logicians or mathematicians do certainly many people don't know there are different kinds of
maths as well different interpretations of what counts as the correct mathematical procedure
that perhaps mathematicians and philosophers are familiar with but the common person isn't so it's
much easier for the common person to say math and mean something about the fundamental ways we
think about things in any case is logic relative it seems like yeah it is but logical principles
kind of are necessary to the way we think certainly there are actual alternatives and you can actually
pick different logics depending on what you need but can we use a different logic at least in terms
of the principle of non-contradiction in the way we actually think in the way our rationality is
well Ogrady will argue nope we cannot so let's go see that awesome battle now against a relativist
that would argue even rationality is relative oh and before you go i just want to say very
quickly unscripted uh if you like my visualization or my videos here please go check out some of
the other ones and please actually do subscribe to my channel if you can please support me on
patreon or send me a direct donation to paypal it's really difficult and it takes hundreds
of hours to make these videos and i don't get much support even socially as you can see my subscriber
count isn't even that high so it's not like even youtube pays me for this so if you can do that that
would be great that could really be nice you know other than that i just want to say let's get to
the next battle of rationality versus relativism and remember philosophers keep battling