Philosophy Battle, the most entertaining presentation of philosophy you'll ever find on the internet, probably.
Now, entering the battlefield of metaphysics.
Hey everyone, my name is AJ and welcome to Philosophy Battle.
Before this video starts, I want to make clear this video will introduce ontology, what it is and to what degree it can be relative.
It is after all important to investigate because it matters if there are actual legitimate grounds
as to why someone might say we live in different worlds so you can't support or criticize one another.
Like, how exactly do we live in different worlds?
And how extreme can that claim actually be meant?
But it will actually lead us into an exciting discussion about realism and anti-realism in philosophy.
Trust me, it's gonna be awesome.
It's one of my favorite things to talk about in philosophy, so I may be a little bit theatrical at times.
We will be discussing pre and post Kantian views and well, it can be treacherous grounds,
so if you don't get certain parts or get lost or don't know what's going on, don't worry about it too much.
Just be patient as it could very well be cleared up later and the point at the end will be made pretty clear, at least I think so.
The video is generally covering the discussion as it is presented in a book of a philosopher, Paul O'Grady, a pretty recent work
because I felt his book has a lot of great and interesting battles in it as well as some important lessons for us.
Now, I may end up saying this again a little bit later after I do a sort of recap into the video, so forgive me if this is repeated,
but if you don't care about O'Grady or the larger discussion of relativism I'm having here, that's okay.
You don't have to watch anything else if you don't want to, even if I'm suggesting another video in this video.
Just take it more as a signpost, even an important signpost possibly if you want more information if I suggest other videos at various points, which I will.
I believe this will be a good video regardless for introducing one of the main problems in metaphysics about ontology or even in philosophy itself, so let's start the video.
Ontological Relativism
What is it and why are we talking about it?
Well, ontology is a field of study under the branch of philosophy called metaphysics, so we're doing philosophy and we're having a metaphysical discussion.
A discussion about what though?
Ontology is a discussion about what there is, what kind of things exist in the world and what the world is fundamentally made of
or what kind of properties are a part of the world.
So for example, believing there is only matter in the world that the world is just made up of matter only.
That's your ontological position.
Or if you think the world is made up of ideas, which includes these senses, you know, like the sense of touch and the sense of color, the sense of smells and so on.
All of these just being ideas coming to your mind and so the world is just that.
The world is just made up of ideas and maybe minds that give and receive ideas.
That would be an idealist ontology.
Or even if your view of the world is that there's earth and there's heaven and hell, that too is your ontological position.
A position about what there is in the world, what exists.
Though that has some religious connotations and we're not discussing religious views here.
This is not about religion.
We're just having a discussion about what there is in the world.
And this conception seems to have a view that the world has different planes of existence.
Perhaps for someone it's not about heaven and earth, but about universal forms and particular manifestations of that.
All of these fit within the field of ontology.
So perhaps in some sense, if we can just crudely say epistemology is about knowledge, then ontology would be about the world.
Or reality.
While people may have different views about what the world is fundamentally made of or what kind of structure reality really has,
our question today is about whether the world or reality is relative.
Now we commonly already are relativists about a number of things, not just things like taste in music or preference in Pokemon.
But even in descriptions of physical things, like things being big, such descriptions are known to be relative.
The bird is big compared to the ant.
But compared to the tree, it's not.
The tree is actually big compared to the bird.
But compared to the mountain, it's not.
The mountain is actually big compared to the tree.
And so on.
Big is a relative description.
In fact, if you imagine this self illuminated cube were the only thing in the universe, nothing else,
not even the edges of the screen as you look at it,
then there's no way of knowing if it's big or small.
Without anything to compare it to, calling it big is meaningless.
An empty idea.
And so there's no point here in talking about it like it could even be considered big.
So what if the world, reality itself, is relative?
What if our ontology is relative?
Wait, relative to what?
Well, guess what, we actually came here to the battlefield of metaphysics
just to discuss the power and limits of this philosophic weapon called relativism.
Why?
Because we actually came from the battlefield of the philosophy of science,
where we had encountered some enemies wielding this weapon to extreme degrees.
So because of that, I thought it would be beneficial to come here to the battlefield of metaphysics
just to dismantle this weapon.
To show its power and limits.
So while there are a few books I may cover,
currently I'm covering this topic mostly based on the writings of philosopher Paul O'Grady
in this green book called relativism.
In his book, he covers a variety of different philosophic areas to discuss relativism.
He's not going to be discussing ethics or morals, you know, what's right and wrong,
or aesthetics, like what counts as beautiful.
But he's more interested in cognitive things like truth and reality and knowledge
if even those things can be considered relative.
So after explaining the power of relativism, which is a wickedly powerful weapon,
he then goes on to defend against relativization in two areas.
He battles against relativization on truth and on rationality.
So I made a video covering his first chapter that I phrase as covering the power of relativism.
That's my phrasing though.
And I would really insist that you watch that video,
especially before thinking that one can just offhand dismiss this enemy.
If you think it's obvious or evident that relativism is wrong for any reason,
I put a lot of work into this video and I think you should definitely check it out
because it will definitely pay for any good philosopher who wants to conceptually grip
what the issue really is in order to understand the power of this weapon.
Not just in the sense to be able to dismantle our enemy to point out the flaws in their strategy,
but also as a weapon to be wielded by us ourselves
in order to challenge anywhere that there are baseless assumptions of objectivity
or naive thoughts about what's obvious and evident.
On the other hand, this weapon does have limits that our enemies did not appear to be aware of.
The dangers of thinking everything is relative.
So we already covered the great and totally awesome battle
where Paul O'Grady defended truth against relativism.
And please go check out that video.
It's definitely one of my favorite battles of all time
and certainly has important lessons that can go along with us in our philosophic journey forever, probably, I don't know.
But he did also use a kind of principle of logic in order to make that defense
and so it kind of made sense that in that first chapter he did also talk about whether logic itself can be relative.
So I guess I also therefore thought important to cover that topic
and made a video discussing logic itself.
Logic in the way that philosophers or logicians or kind of I guess also mathematicians know it.
This is looking at formal symbolic logic and really offers a much more in-depth understanding
of what logic is than the common person or lay person does.
It certainly goes beyond the mere rhetoric of political pundits online, for example.
There, however, Paul O'Grady did actually allow relativism
that we did seem to accept relativism in logic
but only in terms of a lower order.
That there seemed to be a higher order and a lower one
in the higher order there still seems to have maintained certain principles of logic
of which hasn't truly been argued for yet.
It will be argued for in that chapter 5, the next battle.
So I wanted to skip to that rationality battle
because I only came here to the battlefield of metaphysics
to discuss the power and limits of this weapon.
Having already covered the power, I only wanted to cover the limits
the places where he defends clearly against relativization.
But I kind of noticed that in that area of rationality
Paul O'Grady does seem to have certain strategies and techniques
that make reference to these previous chapters.
So it would leave something wanting if I didn't at least somehow explain
what's going on in these other areas.
So I thought it important to at least kind of cover what's happening over here
since it is part of his strategy in rationality.
But this video is going to be way different from what I normally do.
You see normally I cite everything I say down to the line
when I'm covering some philosophers writing.
But today I'm not really going to be covering Paul O'Grady that closely.
I'm just going to give a more general description of what's going on in ontology in some way.
So it's going to be much less structured and less scripted
since there's not much citation that I'm going to be giving anymore.
You see that kind of line to line citation that I was giving before
actually provided some kind of order and script
even though I don't ever use a kind of proper script
the kind of citation was still giving me a kind of order for my videos.
But without it this is much less scripted than my normal videos
so forgive me for that.
But nevertheless I will still try to present sort of what his framing
of the main battles and the main issues are in this chapter
as he presents it kind of.
Though I will still be clear about certain things that are framed in his way
versus things that are framed from me.
I'm just not actually going to be covering either of these chapters
like fully or in depth as I did the other battles
where the battles are happening that I'm interested in.
In any case I will come back to talk about this chapter maybe later
when I kind of finish off doing Paul O'Grady
and want to give a full evaluation of this book.
There's a reason why this chapter in particular is something that I might want to talk to
in more depth or detail in the future.
And I'll talk about what that reason is.
In any case the point of this video is just to generally cover ontological relativism
and the kind of issues that are happening here
the sort of battles that are going on
in the more modern type of take
both as O'Grady frames it and as I would
and then we'll just discuss where O'Grady lands on this issue going forward.
So if you don't know who O'Grady is or anyone else don't worry about it.
If you're here just to talk about ontological relativism
this video will still be very helpful
at least giving a kind of outlay of the kind of battle that's going on
and the different issues and different perspectives
that come to conflict with each other.
Okay?
Let's go.
As already discussed in the Power of Relativism episode
O'Grady points out a pre and post Kantian view
and don't let those words be spooky.
I'll explain them.
Basically back in the pre Kantian
or Kant days there was this kind of image
the idea that there was the world and us
or our mind
and we have beliefs and propositions
or observations about the world
the world as it is
so ontology was about that
the world that would be a certain way
even if we aren't there with our observations
beliefs or thoughts
so like the tree is here
not there
the mountain is denser than the clouds
et cetera et cetera
that the world independent of our minds is
and is a certain way
the world that would be that way
even if no humans existed
even if all species capable of having beliefs
and observations had gone extinct
the world in of itself
not relative to someone's perspective
would be there and be a certain way
so that's more of a pre Kantian kind of picture
and while we can all have different kind of ontological beliefs
about what that world is like
there still seem to be some agreement pre Kant
that that's what we were talking about
but then Kant came along
and he done messed that whole thing up
he changed the game for real
and now we have this new picture
where this world that we observe
that we have beliefs about
or thoughts of and make propositions about
is actually constructed in part by our minds
the mind by our categories of understanding
as Kant call them
needs to give shape to whatever it is that's out there
to make a world that is even understandable by us
in this sense we never directly observe reality itself
we can never really know in any way or form
what this outside stuff is
or anything about it
even possibly that it exists
so I represent it as this gray mush
but really I can't say it's gray
or say that it's mush
I can't really say anything at all
but I'm using this as a visual
just to show that the concepts of color or shape
that would come from us and our minds have not applied here
in fact Robert Kirk calls this cosmic porridge
and this is not that I or Kirk are advocating
that this is what reality really is
in fact Kirk argues against this cosmic porridge kind of picture
because as a realist we want there to be something
and that this something is a certain way
not that it's merely some indistinct gray mush
anyway we'll get back to that
you see Kant had these universal categories
that everyone's mind has
that structures the world as it is to us
as it must be to us
that ontology wasn't about the world
independent of the mind
but the world as it is known by us
as it is observed by us
for example when it comes to the understanding
of bodies actually existing in our world
we have this kind of structure of understanding
that a body must have extension in the three dimensions
and if it really is existing
perhaps extension within the fourth dimension of time as well
or perhaps we can think of it kind of like as a net
that applied from our mind results in producing
the kind of things that we have contact with
now those are different kind of takes about what's going on
but in general this is a post Kantian picture
however to have a better understanding about how it is
that our concepts or the structure of our mind
is actually structuring the world as we observe it
as we make sense of it or understand or think about it
please check out that power of relativism video
it will give a much more detailed discussion
about how the mind is in some sense constructing
and if perhaps you are just more specifically concerned
about science
you can maybe check out my video on the philosopher
and historian of science Thomas Kuhn
one video is his response to his predecessor Carl Popper
and the other one is a video I made
to explain how Kuhn's philosophy opened the gates
to those who wanted to bring this weapon
and make charges of relativism against even science
so if you're kind of more interested in that sort of construction
and the kind of relativization of even observation
you can go check out those videos
however while we're here in ontology though
let's continue with our discussion
in this case the world that we can know, speak of
or observe is only one that can exist
within the framework of our conceptual scheme
or categories or paradigm
or any other name used to describe how it is that our mind
is constructing the meaning of the world as we observe it
we have no access to this outside stuff
and because of this depending on who you ask
not only does it make no sense to talk about
whatever the outside is
it doesn't even make sense to say it exists
and I know that sounds kind of strange
but because they are not holding onto
or even actively denying the idea of a mind-independent reality
they are considered anti-realists
and they are opposed by those who hold on
to the existence of a mind-independent reality
who are considered realists
and this is a battle that is near and dear to my heart
anyway we should note that because Kant held
according to him a more universal account of the categories
that is the kind of conceptual structure that structures
and gives meaning to the world as we observe or understand it
he nevertheless wasn't a relativist in that sense
however because other philosophers such as C.I. Lewis
and I would argue also resources from natural science
would hold that these categories that we have
or concepts and conceptual schemes that we use
in making the sense of the world as we know it
are also a product of a social, historical
and cultural background
meaning they could actually be different
for different people
different people in different times in different cultures
have very different concepts
and the world as it is relative to those different sense of concepts
would be different
our ontology
what the world in this sense is
is therefore relative
this is ontological relativism
under that previous sense of anti-realism
again so we're clear relativism here is that
because people can have different concepts
and different conceptual schemes
the world is different for everyone with a different conceptual scheme
and also importantly
that these different worlds
perhaps not in small part because they are anti-realists
cannot be reduced to each other
or that there is one correct world type of thing
that is the ontological relativist position
they cannot be reduced
and one is not more correct
since certainly at least according to their conception
there isn't exactly a mind independent reality
in order to appeal to
in order to say one is correct
so Ogrady presents the main battle in ontology
between these two positions
an anti-realist position
called the ontological relativist
and a realist position
called the sophisticated realist
both in some sense actually accept
and have moved on to a post-continent type of picture
the sophisticated realist
is a realist because they still want to hold on
that there is a mind independent reality or world
but they are actually unlikely naive realist
that was probably far more likely to exist in the pre-continent picture
a realist that believed there was only one theory
one could say that we have
that is of a mind independent reality
one theory that is the most correct one
or that other theories can be reduced to just one theory
for example in the old school
perhaps we may have thought that physics is the ultimate theory
other stuff whether psychology or sociology
everything can be reduced to physics
and physics being not merely about the world as we know it
but about a mind independent reality as well
that's not really a sophisticated realist position
in the post-continent picture however
the sophisticated realist holds that we can actually have
different theories of the world
based in part because they give a sense to the idea
how different conceptual schemes are giving meaning to the worlds
different worlds
so there would be different theories of the world
and yet one of those theories isn't considered the correct one
or most correct one
that they can all exist and yet not be reduced to each other
but they are still nevertheless about a mind independent reality
that exists and is a certain way
it has certain properties
that I guess they would say either is successfully or not conveyed
or somehow connected to those theories
and so somehow or other structure
or perhaps how Paulo Grady would phrase it
constraint on what our theories can even be
is coming in part from here as well
a mind independent reality
not just there
not just the mind
in this sense the sophisticated realist feels that they have
accommodated relativism
and how our conceptual seems construct what we know
but still are realist about reality
this in modern philosophic warfare is the main battle
happening in ontology as it is presented by Paulo Grady
a battle between the ontological relativist
and the sophisticated realist
while it may seem like the sophisticated realist
is actually pretty accommodating
the ontological relativist still being an anti-realist
denies the sophisticated realist position
saying there is no sense of the world beyond the mind
that it makes no sense to speak of it having properties
or being a certain way
because of course in order for something to be discussed
as being a certain way
having certain properties
only ever make sense within a conceptual scheme
it only makes sense if concepts are being applied
and if it is then we aren't actually talking about a mind
independent reality
also it seems to be that part of the ontological relativist point
is to say that if theories can in fact be different
and not reducible and that one theory isn't the most correct one
and what point also is there even mentioning that there is this thing
why bother bringing that up then
now this may seem super frustrating for those of us who are realists
but it's not like we didn't in some sense feel a similar way
when it came to big
remember talking about this cube as if it is big
makes no sense
it can't be called that
that's how we felt
so the ontological relativist may actually be equally frustrated with us
in insisting that reality is a certain way and has certain properties
as we might be with someone else who doesn't understand why this cube
that has nothing else to be compared to
cannot be described as big
since big is relative
the ontological relativist feel that all properties
or description, everything
is relative to a conceptual scheme
comes from a mind
and yet here we are trying to describe mind independent reality
with no conceptual scheme applied
yet still trying to say it has certain properties and is a certain way
that equally doesn't seem to have any meaning or have any sense
in the way that describing a cube as being big
when it's the only thing in existence seems to be meaningless
or like an empty idea
now as an aside note
there's also another reason that works for them in their perspective
not only is there this basis of how our conceptual scheme
is giving shape or constructing
or at least providing the schemata for which things can have meaning in the first place
but they also feel that this in some way helps them defend against skepticism
because one of the big issues in philosophy
is that despite what we claim to know
it's possible that no matter how much justification we have
that a mind independent reality could nevertheless be different
in more of a classic way of phrasing it
I guess we could say we could hold full justified belief
about what the truth is
and yet the truth could still nevertheless be different
hence we would not have knowledge
in fact that possibility is always the case
meaning we could never really know if we actually have knowledge or not
which is pretty skeptical
because a mind independent reality may always turn out different
now Kant thought something like this too
that he had somehow solved this kind of skeptical issue in some way
because when ontology is about this
then the possibility about being wrong of a mind independent reality
isn't really an issue for the anti-realist that drops that concept
but that isn't all that convincing to the realist
who would say dropping this
that we can ever know or understand it
or be in any way shape or form in contact with reality
is exactly skepticism
you haven't defeated it
you just given into it
so that isn't much of a motivator for a realist
but the ontological relativists say back
it's only not convincing because you are applying your unjustified view
about there being this thing
we didn't lose the world
we didn't lose objects
we didn't lose things
we don't deny reality exist
just that all those terms are about this
no words or terms or identifiers or symbols or anything
make sense about anything beyond this
a conceptual scheme or paradigm or language
is required for something to even make sense or have meaning
and so I find this is where most of the battle really is
about the frustration of trying to use terms
that are always nevertheless tied into this area for the ontological relativists
but I'll kind of show you what I mean
first it's important to note here
that for the ontological relativist in this sense
there is no division between epistemology
the study of knowledge
and ontology then
because the ontological relativists deny the division between mind and world
there is no world beyond the mind
and accusing the ontological relativists
of simply conflating the issues
of what we can know and understand
with issues about what exists
well, the ontological relativist points out that
that conflation only makes sense
because you had already presumed an ontological perspective
with a mind-world distinction in the first place
some realists would argue
well, we have a realist conception first
and that thereafter we actually need good reasons
to be able to switch to another ontology
and that there are no good reasons for that
but are we really ontological realists first?
I mean, common-day people aren't exactly philosophers
and also just the idea that it's first would eventually mean anything
as O'Grady says that doesn't actually cut much ice for philosophers
I've never actually heard that expression before
but I think it's super dope
oh, it doesn't cut much ice for philosophers
like, you know, I don't know
do philosophers cut ice?
I don't know what O'Grady is doing on his part-time
anyway, okay, so one of the main issues here
that I'm gonna describe is a big philosophic trouble actually
so please think of it yourself
and really try to grasp what the ontological relativist is saying here
because there is actually problems for both sides
because a problem for the sophisticated realist
is what exactly is coming from here
I mean, we want to say that the world is a certain way, right?
it has to be or have
and this is my phrasing to help explain it in the way I think of it
but it has to have some kind of information then
but the relativist for good reason says
information cannot exist without a language for it to be expressed within
and even the realist wants to recognize this
they want to be able to recognize that without a conceptual scheme
to have any meaning in there can't be information
so it kind of seems impossible to be able to say or describe
what is out here that has any information
or properties or is a certain way
just simply impossible to convey what it's influencing here
what structure or what constraints it gives to what our theories can be
how can we express this inexpressible
how can we talk about information being in the world
when there is no language out there
language comes from us, our minds
but on the other hand, the problem for the ontological relativist
is that they don't really want to say that everything is coming from our mind
that would be a kind of radical idealistic picture that they deny
that the world is just ideas
that we can just literally flippantly change reality with different concepts
that we make up as we go along
O'Grady calls this Promethean Anti-Realism
but it's important to point out that reality there is meant in their sense
this middle thing
reality, the world, stuff, information, things, objects, matter, properties
and all of those only have meaning constrained within the conceptual scheme
so this conversation is really hard because anytime a realist tries to use these words
to describe what they're talking about
they can be pulled into the terms as used by the ontological relativist
and that's super frustrating
but as it seems to me at least
they too, in their own terms, are inconsistent
even in this chapter as O'Grady is describing their position, they are inconsistent
part of this inconsistency which I would argue
and I think clearly is the more damning part is the fact that in order to explain their position
in order to deny that these words are about this thing
and are instead about this thing
to even make that clarification
they are in the process of speaking about this thing
which they say is meaningless or impossible to do
this kind of relates to the lesson Wiccanshine gives in On Certainty
where it's nonsense to respond to nonsense
and yet here they sometimes talk about the realist's position
in order to contrast against it in a meaningful way
again in the process of denying an unconceptualized reality
they employ that concept as if non-relative and as if meaningful
or if it could only actually even possibly be meant in a relative way
which is what they are fine with
then they would not be in a process of denying it
in their process of pulling terms into their relative stance
they sometimes use the terms in a non-relative way
to explain or elucidate the change or meaningful difference
so it seems it is possible then for those words to mean something
other than what the relativists insist that they can only possibly mean
so this move of mine here for this chapter
I'm not really visualizing too much right now
because in part we've already seen it before in other applications for truth
so I hope you kind of still understand what the point is I'm making here
but also it will certainly be given much more detailing in the chapter on rationality
because it will be used by Paul O'Grady
and I promise that detailing will be wonderful
anyway there is another reason for their occasional inconsistency here
in order to deny just being full-blown idealist
they do seem to want a brute force say that it just exists
and don't get me wrong they are consistent that we can't talk about
what this stuff is like that it has any properties or information
but at most that it just is
hence the cosmic porridge or the visual of grey mush that I used
but at the same time and here's a problem that was even for Kant
it exists is a property
to say something exists is also to talk about it
and they actually do seem to need to employ it
other than the mind because they don't want to say the world is just the mind
but at the same time the world isn't beyond the mind
so you can see it seems to lead them in a kind of confused state
it definitely isn't the state that they want to say that something is beyond the mind
they want to say the world is within the mind
and yet they don't want to say that we are actually constructing everything from our own heads
or at least deny that it's possible that we could somehow just flippantly decide
or on a whim decide what concepts we want to use
and change reality as it is actually experienced by us
so because they don't want to say there can be any infinite random tandem amount of theories
they want to apply some restrictions to it
but deny that the restrictions to what the theories can be
come from a mind independent reality
instead they proclaim that the constraints on what theories can exist about the world
come from the mind itself
but that means this restraint which comes from the mind
could nevertheless be the means by which we criticize another
if that is itself universal in some way
and what are those constraints?
well, Paulo Grady is going to give an account of what those restrictions are
in his chapter 5 in rationality
now from here on in O Grady's chapter in ontology
he does have a kind of outline that mainly focuses on two philosophers
that are most well known for ontological relativism
both Quine and Putnam
and really he does go to some detail explaining their positions
because it's not exactly a simple thing to talk about
but I'm just going to skip all of it completely
after explaining both of their positions
he then has seven objections to ontological relativism
three of those objections are specifically targeted to Putnam
one objection is specifically targeted to Quine
and the final three are just general arguments against ontological relativism
some of these arguments work but seem to target just the philosopher
and not the kind of general position of ontological relativism
other arguments just seem to lead to other battlefields
like whether or not IBE inference to the best explanation
is appropriate to making ontological metaphysical arguments about the nature of reality
this is namely the no miracles argument
and like I said I don't want to get into all of this stuff
ultimately when it comes to these arguments
it simply seems that there isn't a kind of final blow
there isn't anything fully restricting the possibility of ontological relativism
so O Grady allows for ontological relativism here
he seems to settle on the idea that relativism does go all the way through to the end
and anything beyond that is meaningless to talk about
and so in some sense he also perhaps on that basis
I'm a little bit unsure but he does accept the kind of differentiation
between truth and ontology
he feels one can absolutely be an absolutist
that is a non-relativist about truth
while still being a relativist about ontology
and certainly that seems to work within the schema of the ontological relativist
since the ontological relativist is denying a mind-independent reality
so all you would have to do is discuss capital T truth
as if it doesn't have to do with a mind-independent reality
and indeed if you do go look back on that chapter
where he does absolutely defend a non-relativist truth
he isn't relying on appeals to a mind-independent reality
which is actually pretty great
but anyway here in this chapter
is actually where I'm kind of really critical of O Grady
well maybe not really critical but kind of critical
and in my final video about this book
I will take a closer look at the chapter to outline the kind of criticism that I have
but to me and I'm just a shadowy character on the internet here
still he seems to be tricked by a technique used by the relativist
and maybe not exactly tricked
because the technique is used in other areas
and he combats against that same technique
so instead I currently feel like
even though he could have actually made a stronger case
against the relativist in ontology
he really is instead merely allowing for relativism in ontology
to a much greater extent
both because he feels it's safer than in epistemology
where it can cause damage to rationality
since rationality actually plays a role in epistemology
but also because he feels he can agree to segregating the areas of truth
from ontology
saving his victory there
not only is it safest to allow it here
I think in part his technique in this book overall
is simply to funnel the relativist away from other areas to this place
where they can cause the least amount of damage to the areas he battles against it
in any case there are still some good battles in this chapter
and he does give much more detail in the dealings with three philosophers in particular
David, Quine and Putnam
if you, my subscribers, really would like a detailed look at this chapter
perhaps I will do it at some point in time
but you gotta let me know
because these videos, they're super hard to make all by myself
I have no editors, no animators, no co-writers
and no funding beyond my one Patreon supporter, Slickpockets
as yet
and like I said, I didn't really come here to the battlefield of metaphysics for this
even though, yeah, this is probably the most metaphysical stuff that I'm talking about
even in this whole series
in other case this issue as I see it and we will see it again
is a problem in different areas
and can be described and visualized in many ways
and this is just one way
the question and issue is
how is information outside
if language can't be
how is that outside
influencing the inside
what of our descriptions of the world
what amount, what way
what properties is from outside
how can we ever know
since we cannot know the outside
I can go on and on for hours rephrasing that
so instead I would try to ask you to phrase the problem yourself
in your own mind
to get a good grip with what the problem really is
because you really do come to grip with the philosophic problem
when you realize due to this new post-continent picture
simply saying we get the outside
by observing, seeing, touching, etc
no longer is sufficient
as even those acts
what we are seeing
what information we are getting when we touch
it is structured by the kind of creatures we are
the kind of interests we have
the kind of minds we have
the influence of the kind of conceptual scheme we have built for ourselves
influenced by our histories
like if we are in the medieval ages
or after Einstein
and many other things
so I do have my own opinion
and my own kind of answer in some sense about some of these things
but it's not my place to say it here
as I said
I will talk about ontology again
after I am done
and giving an evaluation of this book
but I simply do not think I have any right here
at least in this place
to start telling you what I think the proper solution is
in my kind of formal idea and presentation of it
I'm not trying to do that
I was just trying to give you
an outlay of what's going on in ontological...
what's going on in ontological relativism
the kind of issues that are in play
and the kind of position that Paulo Grady settles on
now let's move on to that next area
epistemological relativism
see you there for the battle
oh please subscribe and stuff
that would be like super nice because I think
I really want to be able to prove that a philosopher can exist out here on the internet
and it can provide a place for us
anyway