Θα μπορούσα να δούμε τον Γερματικό Φινένσμι,
ότι είχε εξαναγωγήσει με δυνατές που έφεραν σαν λασσοπίδια.
Και έφεραν το παιδί και είχε πει,
«Αυτή η σημερινή, η σημερινή,
η οποία θα εξαναγωγήσω εσύ».
Οι εξαναγωγήσεις δεν μπορούν να αλλάξουν την οικονομική πολιτισμία.
Οι εξαναγωγήσεις δεν μπορούσαν να εξαναγωγήσουν την οικονομική πολιτισμία.
Έχω εξαναγωγήσει.
Η εξαναγωγήση μου ήταν,
«Αυτή η εξαναγωγήση για την κίνηση της Κίνησης,
γιατί they believed that too».
Και έγιναν με την προποσία,
αυτό είναι το reason why they hated me,
was to be very moderate and said,
«In that case, Wolfgang, let's ban elections,
in bankrupt countries.
Let's come out and declare that in the European Union
you can only have democracy if you are a creditor country.
If you are a debtor country, no democracy,
elections cannot be allowed to change anything,
because we have a loan agreement.
We have a debtor's prison.
Let's put Greece in the workhouse.
I didn't say all these things,
but I did say the thing about the Chinese Communist Party.
«Αν εξαναγωγήσει την κίνηση της Κίνησης,
γιατί they believed that if you are not able
to explain the economy in a language
which young people can understand,
then you are clueless yourself.
This from its author, Yanos Varifakis,
a man not only known not to mince his words,
but one who, in fact, wrote the book in Greek in nine days.
I'm Mary Stath, the director of Cambridge Forum
and tonight to assist us in navigating
the murky waters of capitalism,
and to quote Yanos,
«Come to terms with the beast that dominates our lives.
We are privileged to have the best of teachers,
a philosopher and international economist,
Varis Varifakis.»
I'm very much looking forward to the conversation
that we're going to have.
But I've been asked to give a presentation,
so I will, because sometimes I like to do,
as I'm told, not very often.
The title that has been advertised
and some of you saw it outside and walked in,
so I might as well honour the title,
is a question.
Is Capitalism Devouring Democracy?
Allow me to begin with a slightly different question.
Have you noticed how in the last few decades
the quality of politicians has stumbled?
Not just in this country, everywhere.
For God's sake, even I became a politician in 2015.
No, but seriously,
there is a marked diminution
in the rhetoric, in the capacity of politicians
to inspire and indeed in the power that they have.
Now, I don't believe that this is due to
a degeneration of the DNA of humanity
or of those who are interested in politics.
What we have been observing
is the shrinking of what I shall refer to
as the political sphere.
There used to be a time before capitalism
when there was one sphere, the sphere of power.
It was impossible to separate economic power
from political power.
The king had both military power,
military power, produced political power
and political power and economic power
were one and the same thing.
There is no great mystery really
as to why there was no economics 150 years ago.
The thing about Harvard University
did not have an economics department
in the 19th century, why?
Because there was no need for it
before capitalism came of age.
Before capitalism, the political and economic sphere
were one.
There were closures in Britain
that you had a remarkable transformation of society,
that great transformation.
The shifting from feudalism to capitalism.
Effectively, the peasants were evicted from the land,
replaced by sheep,
because of the international trade routes
that were creating an international market for wool
and some commodities like wool, like steel,
like spices and so on
were emerging as international commodities
with prices that were determined
at the level of the international trade route system.
All the other commodities were goods,
were effectively sidelined.
The lord of the land in Yorkshire
or in Manchester had absolutely no incentive
to retain those peasants
planting idiotic little vegetables
when they could just chuck them out of the land,
replace them with fat sheep,
whose wool suddenly had an international value,
exchange value.
But the enclosures created the working class.
It created the commodification of labour.
Up until then, people worked very hard,
but they didn't sell their labour.
We had a very interesting reversal
of the timing of economic production and distribution.
Under feudalism, we had work, production first.
People actually toiled, they worked the land
and they produced the harvest.
Production came first.
Then came distribution.
The lord of the land or the miner or whatever
would send the sheriff in
and take his cut from the harvest.
How much he would take
and how much he would leave behind
was a political issue.
It had to do with military power.
It had to do even with the benevolence of the lord.
It had to do with the extent to which
the lord needed to keep the peasants on side
in case another lord tried to usurp
his property rights over the land.
It was a political, diplomatic, ethical,
religious, economic process
that determined distribution after production.
Finally, the surplus that the lord amassed
was sold in nearby markets
and that created a financial surplus
for the lord which then he lent out.
We had production, distribution
and then finally finance.
But with the enclosures
and the eviction of the peasantry
we had the exact opposite
because suddenly the lord,
the last thing that the lord wanted to do
is to work or to be entrepreneurial.
So the replacement of the peasants with a sheep
meant that suddenly every acre of land
had an economic value, an exchange value, a price
that did not exist, that was not the case before.
Why did it acquire this price?
Because you knew how many sheep
you could raise on an acre.
You know how much more or less
wool you would produce.
International markets were providing
the equilibrium price of the wool
so you knew how much exchange value
money you could gather per acre of your land.
And of course then once that price was established
that exchange value per acre was established
suddenly land became a commodity
to be rented out, to be sold, to be purchased.
There was no real estate market before that.
Land was either you inherited land
in which case you had it
and if you never inherited land you never got it.
And the only way of effectively getting land
that you didn't have was through war, through conquest.
Or if the king decided to grant you
a plot of land.
There was no such thing as a market for land
and there was no such thing as a market of labor.
The enclosures, the eviction of the peasants
created land as a commodity
and of course labor as a commodity
because the evicted peasants
effectively they were roaming around the country
knocking on doors saying
I will do anything for work, for work,
for a piece of bread.
That's the first labor market.
That had never happened before
in the history of humanity.
People with nothing selling their labor time.
That's the beginning of capitalism.
But with this you have the separation
of the economic from the political sphere
for the first time in our history as a species.
Because suddenly you had merchants
who acquired huge power
through the accumulation of financial surpluses
because the internationalization
of those trade routes,
the emergence of these few commodities
as international commodities
that bestowed substantial financial surplus
upon those who handled them
whether they were the merchants,
the ship owners or the lords of the land
whose land now was used
in order to cultivate inverted commerce wool.
For the first time you had this separation.
You had lords whose political power
and social power
were now becoming increasingly
disproportionate to their economic power.
You had those dirty merchants
as they consider them.
The riffraff, the ugly dirty merchants
acquiring huge quantities of economic power
that had nothing to do with their social status.
They were not allowed in the palace.
They were not allowed in parliament.
They were not allowed in the gentlemen's clubs in London.
Suddenly they had a lot more economic power than the lords.
The economic and the political sphere separated.
With industrialization you throw into this mix
James Watts great invention, the steam engine
and this process just goes berserk.
You have globalization
which Karl Marx and Fritzrich Engels
in the manifesto described
in the most poetic language
when they say that capital must nestle everywhere,
it must settle everywhere,
it must enter into relations everywhere.
It was interesting because when Marx and Engels were writing that
it hadn't happened yet.
But they foresaw the process that we live in.
Globalization.
With globalization now we have, well,
with this process of globalization
you have the establishment of these
completely separate two spheres.
Now interestingly in the 19th century
you recall this.
Well, you live in a very historic town.
Liberalism was a philosophy, a political philosophy
at odds with democracy.
To be a liberal, a genuine liberal
you must have been very skeptical about democracy
if not completely and utterly anti-democratic.
The whole point about liberalism
was how to preserve the right
to track barter and exchange
in Adam Smith's famous expression
which was a right that many of the liberals
including John Stuart Mill,
a very liberal person,
a very progressive person for his age,
he considered the idea of democracy
what is democracy,
is the rule of the many
to be a great impediment
if not a great threat to liberalism.
So when we talk about liberal democracy today
we're talking about something
that in the 19th century
was a contradiction in terms
to be a liberal meant
that you did not believe in democracy.
Now what was it that brought about
a change, a transformation?
Suddenly liberals started
embracing the idea of democracy.
It was economic crisis,
financial and economic crisis
beginning especially in this country
in Europe in the 1840s
because the moment capitalism
started turbocharging itself
with the creation of what I will describe
as networked companies
with the advances in electromagnetism,
electric engines, the telegraph,
all the communication technologies,
electricity grids.
When electricity comes into production
and we move beyond steam
that's the second industrial revolution
to create, when Edison created his empire
he created a networked company.
Remember from the electric bulb
to the power generating station,
to the grid, everything was part of this.
We talk about Google now and Apple
as being mega companies,
well the mega company was invented
with the second industrial revolution.
But think about it,
to set up a company like Edison's
or later Henry Ford's and so on
you needed a lot of financing,
you needed a lot of money.
So suddenly the new reversed order
becomes very significant
because now ever since the peasants
were thrown out of the land,
ever since the enclosures in Britain
the Lord rented out,
leased out an acre or a few acres
to an ex peasant and said
okay, I will charge you a rent,
you raise the sheep here
and you keep the difference,
the residual payments.
So once you pay for the land,
me, once you pay the workers,
the ones that have been expelled
and now are working for a piece of bread,
subsistence wages,
once you pay for the sheep,
for the shearing, scissors,
whatever it is that you are using,
your capital equipment,
what you keep in the end is your profit.
So suddenly these proto-entrepreneurs
were forced, they didn't choose to do it,
they were forced to become entrepreneurs,
but how do you become an entrepreneur?
First you borrow,
and usually you borrow it from the landlord.
The landlord lends you the money
to pay him rent,
with interest.
So you see the reversal?
Instead of finance coming at the end,
we used to have production then exchange
or distribution and then finally finance.
Now we have finance first.
At the beginning there was the loan.
Once the loan comes in,
you hire the workers, you pay the rent,
immediately you have distribution.
So you have finance first, distribution second,
the last thing that happens is production.
So finance suddenly acquires
a very special place in capitalism.
Now the beauty and ugliness
of finance, of banking,
is that it is a magical process.
Because once we move from the landlord
to Edison and Henry Ford,
it is impossible to finance capitalism
simply by the accumulated wealth
of some rich person like the Lord.
There was never enough money
in the hands of any financier
to provide Edison with the capital,
with the money he needed
in order to set up his networked firm.
So you needed banks to conjure up money from nothing.
And this is how finance has been working
ever since the Second Industrial Revolution.
How?
By creating money from thin air.
There is a common fallacy
in the popular culture that we live in,
that banks operate like vaults.
Whereby you and I put our savings in
and somebody else goes to the bank
and borrows money that comes from our savings.
And the banker makes a profit
as a result of the difference
between the interest rate
that he pays us
for depositing our money into his vault
and the interest rate that he charges
the person that has borrowed money
in order to invest in a shop, in a factory, whatever.
That is not what is going on.
If you go to the bank tomorrow morning
and you get a loan from the bank,
the money is going to come out of thin air.
The bank will create it out of nothing.
It's really very simple.
You get $100,000 to buy a house,
to invest in a business.
What will happen is
somebody is going to type $100,000
$100,000 into your bank account.
So it's conjured up.
The ancient Greeks had a word for money,
νόμισμα, or coin,
which comes from the verb νόμισμα,
which means to imagine.
So Aristotle defined the value of money
as a common fiction
since the ancient times.
This is exactly what it is.
So the banker simply types the money in there.
You put your card in the ATM
and suddenly you have $100,000.
Somebody typed $100,000 on the system.
Then what you can do is
you can use web banking, you can wire the money.
If you buy a car or a house,
it goes to the bank account of the vendor.
If you invest in a shop,
it goes to the landlord,
to another bank account with the same banking system.
It doesn't matter whether it's the same bank or not.
So these digits that were typed into your account
simply are transferred to another account.
That's all that happens.
Now, the hope of the banker is
that you are going to use this money productively.
You're going to earn money from that
and then you will give the banker
the money that will effectively tie up
that loose end with interest.
Now, to the extent that this works
and it really works magnificently,
in my book I relate this
in the form of a science fiction metaphor.
It's a bit like a banker
being the specially gifted magician
who has a very long arm
and can push his arm, it's usually he,
so allow me not to say she or he.
Through the timeline,
he pushes his hand into the future,
grabs value that has not been created yet,
snatches it from the future,
brings it into the present
and gives it to you.
Hopefully you do productive things
and you create a value that will repay the future.
This is my preferred metaphor
for what bankers do.
But once they learn the beauty
and the glory of doing this
and they are privileged
in a privileged spot
because they can take value from the future,
bring it to the present, they don't do any work themselves.
Because they are the mediators
between future and present value,
they are ultra-rich
and not only ultra-rich,
but central in societal processes,
political processes.
So if you do this and it works,
why not do more of it?
Keep snatching more value from the future
and bringing it to the present.
At some point, the present can no longer produce
the value that it needs to produce
in order to repay the present.
At that point, suddenly,
those of us who have borrowed money
or some of us
have no capacity to repay it,
a recession begins,
people that work for us lose their jobs,
they cannot repay their own loans
and suddenly, the book of the bank
is full of loans that are non-performing.
At that point, if you and I
or those of us who have some money in the bank
realize that this is happening,
we panic, we rush to the bank,
this is a bank run, we ask for the cash,
the cash is not there.
And then you have the financial crisis
that we had in this country
and in Europe from the 1840s onwards.
Now, to a very large extent,
the United States of America,
the way you understand your own country now,
is the product of this political response
to a sequence of financial crisis
beginning from the 1840s.
Even the creation of the Federal Reserve
in the beginning of the 20th century
was the result of J.P. Morgan saying,
I've had enough of bailing out my mates.
Let's create a Federal Reserve
that is going to be doing the job.
And of course, he created it.
It was all stitched up amongst the bankers.
Think of all the great institutions of this country,
like social security, food stamps,
they are the result of 1929.
It's what brought this nation together,
what created the United States of America,
the way you understand it.
It's a sequence of financial collapses
that puts together nations
and politics and democratic processes.
So, let me go back to the beginning.
We used to have one sphere of power.
It was political, economic, cultural, military.
Power had many different facets,
but it was one sphere in which it emerged from.
Then it separated into two spheres,
the political sphere and the economic sphere.
And as it did,
the political sphere was increasingly democratized.
Why?
Because all the important decisions
were moving to the economic sphere.
So, political legitimacy
and the capacity of the regime,
of the system that we live in,
to maintain itself and to be sustainable
through the common belief amongst the people
that this is a legitimate system,
was based on democratization of giving people the idea
that they had control over their communities,
the nation, their politics.
But this democratization was only accepted
by the proponents of liberalism
to the extent that all the important decisions
were migrating from the political sphere
as the political sphere was democratized.
Women understand that.
It's like the feminization of certain professions.
When women moved into teaching,
teaching lost its power.
When they moved into health,
increased now the majority of judges are women.
And you should see the judicial system collapsing.
So, it's a very similar process that we see.
Power is migrating from the economic sphere
to the political sphere,
and the political sphere is democratized increasingly.
Now, something fundamental happened
beginning in this country in the 1970s.
After the end of Bretton Woods,
which was what? What was Bretton Woods?
Let's not get complicated.
It was the globalization of the New Deal.
Roosevelt's New Deal in 1933,
what was the basic idea?
To put the financial genie,
the banking genie back into its bottle,
to make banking boring,
effectively to ban bankers from doing things
that allowed too much money to be created
and too many bubbles to be built up,
mobilizing idle savings,
the idle savings of the richer members of society,
and putting those idle savings,
turning them into a force in the public interest,
infrastructural works, public works,
education, social security and so on.
That was the New Deal.
But towards the end of the war,
the New Dealers extended that New Deal
internationally,
as Europe was just a pile of ashes.
Japan, you don't need me to explain
what happened to Japan in 1945.
So Bretton Woods, it was a magnificent system.
Think about it, the United States official dome in DC
effectively designed a global capitalist system
that was like a planned economy.
4% interest rates forever,
20 years of 4% interest rates,
no ups and downs, maybe,
plus or minus 0.1%.
So you knew what your mortgage rate
would be in the next 20 years.
You knew if you wanted to change
dollars for British pounds,
you knew how many pounds you would get.
You would get the same quantity year in, year out.
So it was a world which was a nightmare
for finances and of course,
that was by design.
Did you know that in the Bretton Woods
conference in New Hampshire in 1944,
Roosevelt imposed one single rule on his own.
The rest he left to his minions.
They were representatives from
100 different countries.
Most of them already,
they were not even liberated yet.
They were under occupation because it was 1944.
The Second World War had not ended.
Experts, diplomats, politicians and so on.
One species of humanity was banned
from entering the Washington Hotel bankers.
A whole monetary global system was created
on condition that bankers would not be part of it.
Yeah, interesting.
If anybody proposed this today,
they would immediately be branded as
raving communist lunatics.
This was Bretton Woods, 1944.
You know, it's important to think back
about possibilities when we think of what is possible.
Well, what happened in 1944 in Bretton Woods
in 1930, 1931 in this country
would have been completely pie in the sky.
So anyway, but that system collapsed
towards the end of the 1960s,
officially 15th of August 1971
with Nixon's announcement that it's kaput, it's finished.
I'm not going to go into this,
but what happened after that was
a very interesting, fascinating reversal
in the flow of trade and money around the world.
Before the collapse of Bretton Woods,
what was happening was this.
This is how Bretton Woods was designed.
America was a surplus country.
The country was surplus, with profits.
Especially after the Second World War,
was the only credit of the country.
They had the financial surplus, the surplus of goods
and a tax porter.
And what the United States Administration did
as part of Bretton Woods was to say,
okay, the only way of preventing a return
of the Great Depression to this land by 1949,
they were very worried about 1949
because it was 1929 plus 20.
The only way of preventing it is to make sure that,
okay, number one, we convert all the factories
from military production to civilian production,
using white goods instead of tanks and bullets,
producing cars instead of aircraft carriers.
Right, but that's not enough,
because those factories during the war economy
were so productive in this country
that they were capable of producing
so many washing machine tractors and cars
that Americans would simply not have enough use for them.
The only way of preventing the Great Depression from returning
was by selling them to the Europeans.
But the Europeans didn't have money.
So, new dealers, being very practical,
people said, we'll give them the money.
This is what's called the Marshall Aid Plan,
surplus recycling.
For 20 years, the United States was recycling
about 70% of American profits in Japan and in Europe,
because this is what you do if you are a clever hegemon.
What you do is you make sure that the only way
you can continue to have surpluses,
vis-à-vis somebody else, is to finance them.
Because if you don't, then they won't be able
to afford to buy your stuff.
Then you won't be able to have surpluses.
The problem was, however, that those surpluses
disappeared by the late 60s.
America shifted from a surplus position to a deficit position.
Both the government went in deficit
and the American economy developed a trade deficit.
It is fascinating that what happened after
the collapse of Bretton Woods had been imagined
by some smart fellows in this country.
Remember Henry Kissinger?
Yeah.
Exactly my feelings.
But he was a smart cookie, right?
In 1970, a year before the end of Bretton Woods,
he was not yet Secretary of State.
He was still head of the National Security Council.
Of course, he is a Cold Warrior, geopolitical thinker,
things in terms of a bit like Metternich would have
in the 19th century.
He comes from the same part of the world, has the same accent.
He asked all the people that were working for him
that pertinent question.
Now that the United States is shifting into a deficit position,
we used to be a...
Now we are going to become a deficit country.
How can we maintain our global hegemony?
Because it has never happened in the past.
All empires, superpowers fell once they became deficit countries
or economic blocks.
So he was worried about that.
He didn't give a damn about economics,
but he cared about power.
A young man wrote a memo.
Thick waters of a page in reply.
It was the most brilliant reply,
and the one that really explains what happened
between the 1970s and 2008 in the world
and of course in the United States.
His answer was, it doesn't really matter
whose surpluses are being recycled.
What really matters to maintain in control
is the one who is recycling other people's surpluses.
Get it?
We can maintain our superpower status, our hegemony,
as long as we do the recycling of surpluses,
even if the surpluses are not ours.
Think about it.
This is exactly the model that we have been living through
between the 1970s and 2008.
America turned into a deficit country.
The Trump is complaining,
we have a huge trade deficit with China, with Germany,
we need to eliminate it.
Either he is completely unschooled
or he is lying.
Or both.
I added the third option.
Because globalization would not have happened
without the American deficits.
The American trade deficit operated like a gigantic vacuum cleaner
but was sucking into this country
the net exports of Germany, of Holland, of France, of Japan
and later of course of China.
Keeping those factories going at full blast.
And this deficit kept increasing.
It is this increasing American trade deficit
that kept globalized capitalism in rude health.
Of course, the question then is,
how was it being paid for?
Because Greece had a big deficit
and look at what happened to us.
Well, this is the exorbitant privilege
of the United States of America.
At the very same time that the trade deficit was expanding,
the rest of the world was sending to this country
70% of all profits that Germans made,
the Dutch made, the Japanese made
and the Chinese are making.
70% of global profits were coming into Wall Street,
seeking higher returns,
being used to purchase US Treasury bills,
American government debt
and so you had a pure recycling loop.
So recycling was discovered by this young man
whose name by the way is Paul Volcker
who then became the chairman of the Fed
a week before he assumed the position of chairman of the Fed
in a lecture he gave at the University of Oregon, England.
He said, this is the time when a controlled disintegration
of the world economy is in the interest
of the United States of America, verbatim,
I've learned this off by heart because it's so exciting.
The controlled disintegration of the world economy,
so that's what he meant.
So you had this amazing system where
you have increasing imbalances globally
America growing its deficits.
Germany and Japan and then China
growing its surpluses.
When we increase our deficit,
we are creating an imbalance.
When somebody else is increasing their surplus,
that's an imbalance.
And globalization was based on this.
Financialization, what's financialization?
Why did Wall Street,
why was Wall Street allowed to go crazy?
Why were all the checks and balances
the newly dealers introduced
and Bretton Woods introduced?
Why did they go to the dogs?
Why did Larry Summers,
I believe he's got some connection with this place.
Why was he allowed to commit the crime against logic and humanity?
To unleash the Wall Street bankers
from their shackles.
The result being 2008.
The answer is, because without
unleashing the Wall Street bankers,
it was impossible to close that loop.
The only way you could have this model of the world economy
where the United States deficit
was keeping the rest of globalization going
with the rest of the world
sending its surpluses into Wall Street
for Wall Street to close the loop
and pay for the deficit
was to let the Wall Street bankers do as they pleased.
And when you do let the Wall Street bankers do as they please
you know what they do?
With a banker, a few billion every day
for five minutes
just part five billion with a banker
for five minutes every day.
This is to invite them
to create very sophisticated bets
using that five billion every day
that they are always going to win.
If I were to give you five billion every day
for five minutes you would work out ways
of making a load of money
and exponentially increasing load of money.
Anyway, the problem is that they built
so many pyramids of financialized derivatives
on top of this tsunami of capital
that the rest of the world was saying
that it combusted in 2008
and the result was what we're facing.
So, the point I'm making is that
first you had the joint sphere of power
then that bisected into the political
and economic sphere
then after the 1970s the end of Bretton Wood
the economic sphere was also divided
and multiplied between the industrial sphere
and the financial sphere.
And all power ended up with finance
because if you allow bankers to push their hand
into the future so majestically, frequently
and without any kind of control
to bring value that has not been produced yet
into the future and effectively to appropriate themselves
and then you also say to them
that they are too big to fail and when they fail
then austerity for all is combined
with socialism for the bankers
then they have no reason
why not to keep undermining capitalism
again and again and again.
So, remember the question with which I started.
Why do politicians seem to be
so much less talented today
than they were, you know, 40 years ago
20 years ago, 30 years ago?
Well, the answer is because the political sphere
is completely powerless.
The spheres that now have acquired power
are the economic sphere and magnificently the financial sphere.
So, if you're a young, talented person
who wants to change the world, who wants to do things?
Who's not very ideological or historical minded?
Who wants power?
What do you want to be president of the United States
or Goldman Sachs?
CEO of Goldman Sachs.
I remember the one long conversation,
longish conversation I had with Barack Obama
when I was the finance minister of Greece.
The first thing he said to me was
I feel solidarity for the Greek people
and we are behind you
but there's not much I can do to help.
And then he immediately, without me saying anything
he went into a solidarity justifying himself
by saying, you know, when I got elected
I realized there was nothing I could do
because Wall Street had just imploded
and I had to save them
and that was, he said, political poison for me.
Now, I don't know whether he believed it or not
and I can't see how he can explain the fact
that he appointed Larry Summers to sort out the mess
unless of course, you know, you adopt the cynical view
that it takes a murderer to work out
how the criminal justice system should be reformed.
So this is effectively the point I'm making.
So, is capitalism consistent
or sustainable within a democratic polity?
Can it coexist with democracy?
Absolutely not
because capitalism is generating this shift of power
away from the political sphere
and even if you have fantastically scripted constitutions
beautiful congresses with wonderful procedures and so on
power is going to shift away from those processes
they're going to become fig leaves for a system
where power leaves somewhere else.
In my first meeting of finance ministers in Europe
I was exposed to this harsh reality
which I always knew
but it's one thing to know it as a radical lefty
that theorizes
and puts forward various working hypotheses
in an academic environment
it's quite another to be told straight in your face.
The beauty of those few months I spent in government
was exactly that
I didn't have to theorize anymore
I went to my first meeting of the Eurogroup
the Eurogroup is the meeting of the European Union
finance ministers of the countries
that share the same currency the year
So I walked in there and I tried to be as moderate
and as sensible
and as friendly
as anyone who comes from a country that is bankrupt
and whose new government has a title
or the party that won
coalition of the radical left
So there I was the minister of finance
representing the coalition of the radical left
in that cesspool of conservatism
and I tried to be
all I said was
that we are facing a challenge
colleagues
there is the principle I said
of continuity
in democracies
in other words
we are not going to start at year zero
just because we are just elected
we have obligations to you
that previous governments, Greek governments
have assumed
and which of course we were against
our party was against but nevertheless
our state because of the principle of continuity
still has these obligations to you
and therefore I cannot dismiss them
I have to take them seriously
I am obliged by the principle of continuity
at the same time there is another principle
the principle of democracy
I could see that we didn't like that very much
and the principle of democracy is very simple
I have a mandate from the people of Greece
to challenge all these obligations
that we have in this particular fiscal
and monetary policy
that you've been imposing upon my country
which led to a great depression
which led me to be here
because if we didn't have a great depression
the Greeks were not stupid enough to vote for me
they didn't just become left wingers
our party went from 4% to 40%
in two and a half years because of the great depression
I didn't put it in those very words
but you can imagine
but more or less this was my mandate
I was trying to be extremely open to them
and moderate and conciliatory
with Wolfgang Schäuble
the finance minister of Germany
and I said what happens in democracy
when two principles clash
the principle of continuity and the principle of democracy
well we sit around the table like civilized people
and we find a compromise
this is what democracy do
liberal democracy yes
I sit down, the French minister
loved what I said
of course
just complete hot air
yes, yes, yes, yes, yes
I could see Wolfgang Schäuble
the German finance minister
he was looking at me with eyes
that felt like laser beams
and he gets the floor and he said
one sentence, one sentence
which is the one that I'm going to leave you with
elections cannot be allowed
to change economic policy
got it?
my response was
this is excellent news
to the Chinese Communist Party
because they believe that too
and I then came up with a proposal
this is why they hated me
very moderate and said
in that case Wolfgang
let's ban elections
in bankrupt countries
let's come out and declare
that in the European Union
you can only have democracy
if you are a credit or country
if you are a debt or country
no democracy, elections cannot be allowed
to change anything
because we have a loan agreement
we have a debtors prison
let's put Greece in the workhouse
I didn't say all these things
but I did say the thing about the Chinese Communist Party
and also the proposal that we
suspend elections while a country
is in the red
but I'm more honest
so the reason why I'm mentioning this is
that
Shoibley was right
in the capitalist
the globalized
financialized capitalism that we have created
elections cannot be allowed
to change economic policy
because
economic policy simply
springs out of the processes
that I described
and that leave
absolutely no room
for anything beyond a semblance
of a democratic process
that legitimizes
the lack of democracy
we live in pure ironclad
oligarchies
which require for legitimation purposes
and for their reproduction
that we think that we live in democracies
now the tragedy is
that capitalism
is being overthrown
not by the left
we are useless
progressives, left-wingers
are a catastrophe
has anybody seen
the life of Brian, Monty Python's movie
remember the opening scene
when they all hate each other
the Jews of
the liberation front of Judea
whose worst enemy is the liberation
people's front of Judea
that's the left
we are
sectarian, we hate each other
more than we hate anything else
but
and when we did overthrow capitalism
we created the gulag
so we are a disaster
doesn't mean we shouldn't
try again to do it properly and democratically
but
let's face it capitalism is overthrowing itself
with no help from us
and it's doing it in two ways
firstly
think of 2008
this financialization process
that I described
imploded under the weight
of its own hubris
and the result is a never-ending crisis
don't believe anybody who tells you that the 2008 crisis ended
it never ended
it is continuing
it is mutating
it's stating different forms
it migrates, it goes to different parts of the world
it takes, for instance in Germany
it takes the form of negative interest rates
that are eating into the pension funds
of the average middle-class person
who then turns against the political system
and votes for the fascists
of the alternative for Deutschland
they don't have an employment
but they have this sense of deflation
of their hard-earned savings
that creates
the rise of xenophobia, racism
and the ultra-right
in my country we have a Nazi party in parliament
because we have a great depression
because we have an employment rate
of 30%
and we have no interest rates
because nobody is lending to anyone
because everybody is bankrupt
in China
you have
an investment rate
the proportion of GDP
of national income
that goes into investment is gigantic
it's 48%
48 cents to every dollar
earned in China
goes into investment
now investment is a good thing
but our investment simply means
that the Chinese authorities
have given up on the West
because let's face it
the only reason why you don't have a great depression
in this country today
is because in 2008
which was our version
of 1929
two things happened differently
to what happened in 1929
one was that the Federal Reserve started printing money
as if there is no tomorrow
didn't happen in 1929
in order to rebalance global capitalism
they did it very well
but it's not sustainable
so Europe is not sustainable
China is not getting sustainable
and the United States today
which is celebrating growth
what growth? you have 2.5% growth
all the things that shouldn't grow grow
the things that should grow are not growing
you do not have
any serious investment
in good quality jobs in this country
you have wage stagnation
you have a situation
people say oh it's
this idiocy of the democratic party
that put in one the election against Hillary Clinton
come on wake up
you cannot say to Trump voters
that they're idiots
and Putin duped them
you can say that but then that's it
you lose them forever
and it's also not true
people say to me how do you explain that Trump won
I'm an economist so I look at numbers
the number that I think is most spectacular
in this country is that in 2016
more than half of the families
in this country could not afford
the cheapest new car which cost 14000
either they didn't have the money
or they didn't have the money
and they did not have the credit ratings
necessary to borrow 14000
more than half of the families cannot afford the cheapest car
that's why Trump got elected
because Obama failed
spectacularly to shift
the burdens of the crisis of the financial sector
onto the 0.1%
So
I've spoken far too long
let's end on a positive note
Shall we?
Technically
it's really very simple
how to solve the problem
or how to begin a process
we need a new deal
except that this must be an international new deal
exactly as the new deal was
in 1933
but globally
that's not new
Bretton Woods was an international new deal
so we need a new Bretton Woods
we need progressives in this country
progressives in Europe
to get an act together and start collaborating
because you know the bankers are very good
at being internationalists
they love each other
they have very good
only we progressives
fail to get together
and start believing
that it is possible to do that which
has already been done before
it's not buying the sky stuff
now
this in order to ameliorate the effects
of the ongoing crisis after 2008
the fact is that
we need a new deal
to ameliorate the effects of the ongoing crisis
after 2008
then once we stabilize the world
like
Bretton Woods stabilized the world after the Second World War
then we can start
thinking about postcapitalism
because we must
capitalism is over turning itself
not only through its crisis
but also through the technologies that it is creating
3D printing
artificial intelligence
the internet
there will be no need to have a corporation
corporations will lack their zone
the only reason why you have general models
is the economies of scale
economies of scale are dying because of the new technologies
that capitalism is creating
so you are going to have a situation
in which
we are going to have magnificent productivity
magnificent
capacity to produce stuff
but the large majority
will not be able to buy any of it
so that will be a crisis of
not just the poor
but also the haves
but we must never
believe that because there is going to be a crisis of capitalism
because capitalism is going to undermine
and overthrow itself
good things will happen
in the 1930s
capitalism imploded
and Nazism happened
so we can have
one certainty
capitalism cannot maintain itself
something else
another system of organizing
economic and political life is going to follow
and we better make sure
that the way in which we choose
as a species, as a humanity
that different way
of doing things is selected
democratically because even though democracy
takes too long
as Oscar Wilde said socialism
would never happen because it takes too many long evenings
and it's tedious
there's no doubt about that
if you've been to a political meeting
you know how tedious it is
it's the only choice we have
thankfully we are creating the technologies
that will make these debates
both more manageable
and more hopeful in terms of
delivering a future that resembles
as I say in the book
Star Trek and not the Matrix
thank you
You're a very interesting combination
of idealism
and pragmatism
identified the problem
that we have here
which led to somehow
Trump being elected
yet
that terrible inequality
which has gotten way worse
in the last 12 months
and looks like it's going to get worse
even more get worse again
did not produce
enough people to elect Bernie Sanders
and I went to his rallies
and he said great things
do you think that this country
just can't wrap its head around
that word socialist
and that's my question
is does it have to repackage the thinking
Well
I used to think that
until Bernie Sanders called himself a socialist
and won the primary election
they were stolen from him
Bernie Sanders won the election
or he would have won the election
if the National Democratic Committee
did not do its utmost
to perform a coup d'etat against him
and I'm stating this
as an accusation
the Democratic Party
is its own worst enemy
So given that
this is the substrate that we have to work with
how do we change the thinking
if we want the things that that party
is proposing
how do we get
the electorate to change their voting
why did they vote for Trump
why
Well
firstly
the abstention rate was quite high
a lot of good people
could simply not bring themselves
to vote for Hillary
and they didn't vote at all
and many others
but
I wasn't here during your election campaign
but I was in Britain
before the Brexit referendum
and I believe that there are great similarities between the two
and I remember I was campaigning against Brexit
in Britain
in the same way I would have campaigned against Trump here
of course
and I remember asking people
who were
not racist
who were not xenophobic
who were not right-wing
why are you voting for Brexit
and the answer had nothing to do with Europe
the answer was this
if I vote
to remain
in the European Union
those bastards that have been treating me
like a discarded
piece of rag
a discarded rag
are going to be very happy
so I'm going to cast my vote in a manner
that maximizes the discomfort
of those who have been treating me
as if I'm not a human
now
I don't know
you have to tell me whether this is
an appropriate comparison
to what was going on here
a lot of people who voted for Trump
simply wanted to punish the establishment
and they wanted
I think that there is quite a lot of supporting evidence
of course there are racists
and there are Nazis
and there are right-wingers
and bigots and misogynists who voted for Trump
but they made the difference
the ones who made the difference
were the ones who could not afford the car
the ones who had believed in Obama
and who voted for Obama in 2008
from what I'm reading at the data
and there seems to be a very large number of voters
who voted for Obama in 2008
and Trump in 2016
now that cannot be explained
on the basis of racism
it cannot be explained on the basis of
misogyny
it is simply
to hell with you
I am not going to vindicate
yet again
a presidential candidate
who goes into Wall Street
six months before the presidential election
gives
private speeches for hundreds of thousands
of dollars
and
excuse the language
shits on people like me
in front of the bankers calling me names
and promising to them
that they will be allowed to continue doing that
which has put us and our country
in this position
So, trying to be optimistic
from a moment
if we were trying to create
some kind of apparatus
I mean in the 50s
Roosevelt did the very thing that they said was impossible
he put 90% tax
on corporate America
to fund all these great schemes
the social security system
you know Medicare
these things were made possible
but the workers had unions then
quite strong unions
now that's all been taken away
how are people going to
organize and overthrow the system
as you say
I mean it may implode but in the interim
people are just surviving on
ten dollar an hour wages
or not surviving
so where is the impetus for evolution
you do not need punitive tax rates now
you don't need 90%
this was a gimmick anyway
No, but it worked
Yeah, I mean it was more of a political stunt
I don't believe that it is
necessary to have such high tax rates
but what you do need
is you need to change the discourse
in a way that appeals
not only to those who would have joined
trade unions but to people who would never
have imagined themselves to be radical
or even progressive
So let me give you an example, take NAFTA
there is a lot of discussion in this country
now about NAFTA
the liberal establishment says
oh you know free trade is everything
the pie is going to shrink
if you do away with it
but some people in
the Rust Belt say
well that's your pie, that's not my pie
my pie has disappeared a long time ago
so if I can manage to hold on to a few
you know still workers jobs
by means of tariffs
let's do it because it's better
than all of us being thrown into
the dustbin
why not change the narrative
and to say
yes we want to renegotiate NAFTA
along the following lines
if Mexico wants
to continue to have
or Mexican capitalists
want to continue to have
free access to the American market
Mexico is going to have to introduce
a minimum wage in Mexico
but it provides a living wage
by Mexican standards
not by American standards
to the workers who work in the factories
that produces stuff that are then transported
over to the United States
now that is a progressive renegotiation
of NAFTA
not tariffs but minimum living wages
in the poorer countries
ok so that way
not building a wall
of course not building a wall
but then you wouldn't need to bring it to build a wall
so that is one example
take for instance
the question about the health service here
the health system
well you don't have a health system
the absence of a health system
Obamacare was a complete disaster
Obamacare
is an affront against logic
the idea of universal cover
is absolutely essential
but also the idea that
the state is going to be subsidizing
private companies to provide public health
without any controls
regarding the prices of the
services and the pharmaceuticals
is a catastrophe
it's like effectively
subsidizing the private insurance
this is why of course
they contributed massively to Obama's campaign
without the so called public option
it's ludicrous
so how about the following argument
about having
a proper national health service
a public health service system
in the United States
so that we can introduce tax cuts
think about that
that would really throw the Republicans wouldn't it
because your tax
your health system
is the most expensive in the world
you pay twice as much on health
than the rest of the world
and you have far worse outcomes
so imagine that you created a proper public system
you'd save a huge amount of money
public money
and then you could give them
give them away as tax cuts
but why not also say that
those tax cuts will go to the lowest wage
earners not to the top
so that's how you change the debate
you get out of the way
of the stereotype
that the Republicans are trying to create for you
and you subvert the dominant way of thinking
So I would like to hug the questioning
but I don't think it's fair
because I'm sure there are lots of good questions
that are going to come from the audience
so I'm going to open up the questions
and if you could confine it to one
I would be appreciative
It may be one and a half
I thought for a minute your talk was going to be almost entirely about Harvard
Marshall
who announced it at Harvard commencement
Kissinger
and then Larry Summers
I'd say
have this idea that maybe Obama was
put in the White House
to bail out Harvard
that whose endowment went from
losing 11 billion to regaining it
I think many people in this country
are still not convinced
that Obama did have a choice
Now you said
I believe that he did
but can you be a little more specific about
and you sort of writ large
you talk about a new deal
but are you more specific about what
a person in the White House
could have done
what it would have looked like
that would have been more like bailing out Wall Street
more like bailing out Main Street
than bailing out Wall Street
and can you explain
why the social democratic politics
of building a politics
where we control the government
and regulate capitalism
is not the way to go
but some other alternative politics
is what you're implying
but you haven't really I don't think spelled out
Ok, I'll start from the second part
Look
the new deal that I am suggesting
as a first step
is social democratic
but in the good old fashioned sense
of it
so you need social democratic measures
to stabilize the political economy
before we can have a genuine conversation
about what comes next
the more radical part
for instance changing corporate law
I mean corporate law
is a political value judgment
so when some corporation
goes bust
who gets paid first
amongst the creditors
is a political decision
so why not change it
why have the bankers get paid first
and the workers last
why allow people to own shares
in a company in which they don't work
this is very radical I don't know
where you can only have shares in a company
in which you actually provide labor
then you have socialism
but without state control
so that's the second
part of the second question
but let's go back to Obama, did he have a choice
of course he had a choice
he could have appointed as
instead of appointing
team guide there and Larry Summers
he could have appointed Elizabeth Warren
with a mandate
to save the banks
or operate the bankers
which is not a new idea
in 1992
the Swedish banks
actually all the Scandinavian banks went bust
and what the governments did then
was to say to the bankers ok, out
they took over the banks, they nationalized them
put in a new board of directors
and within two years
they had sold them back to the private sector
but cleansed, the original bankers had gone
with new regulations
he didn't do that
he left Jamie Dimon
Goldman Sachs
intact all the structures of power
in 2009
when he moved into the White House
for about six to eight months
I grant you
not more than that
he had a window of opportunity
he had a whole nation behind him
he could have done that
even libertarians would have approved
of expropriating the bankers
he didn't
but it was him
to create the so called
Summers Geithner plan
if you haven't studied that
go and study it
it is a remarkable
ingenious way
of
conjuring up
around nine trillion dollars
and giving it to the bankers without anybody realizing it
you remember the bailout that Hank Paulson came up with
was 700 billion
initially he was defeated
in congress
and then he managed to push it through
700 billion spinnets
Geithner and Summers
created nine trillion
without anybody realizing it
ok
so Obama had a choice to do it
and he did it
now we are paying for it
because Trump is president
I've been very concerned
lately about China
and sort of there
we have transferred so much money
from our economy
over to China
by buying all those things
and supporting their economy over there
so they could make more and more money
they are now all over
Africa
buying things and
investing over there
and getting those countries dependent on them
and supporting
these democratic people
and I'm just wondering
like whom
we are in a country that supports Saudi Arabia
yes that's true
suddenly we have a problem
with
superpowers supporting non-democratic people
yes I mean yes I do
but I also am concerned
that we've sort of created
the economic power that China
sort of has now and they are using it
I fear
I'm going to be using it against us eventually
and against
the better interests of a lot of people
allow me to put your mind to rest
you shouldn't worry about that
ok
very simple
and let me explain why you shouldn't worry about that
but please continue
I mean
you know
they are in Africa
they are making money to countries to build ports
and different infrastructure
and what's wrong with that
countries that need ports
get ports
but they are making people dependent on
I mean I know it's the same thing that we've done
which is affordable around the world
they are far more humanistic
than the United States ever was
really? ok
let me give you an example
of course they are peddling
for influence
but they are non-interventionists
absolutely non-interventionists
in a way that Europeans
the West has never managed to fathom
but I have a feeling
they have a longer term thought process
that is more
but let's judge what we see
let's start at the beginning
the Chinese never asked Apple
to go to Shenzhen
produce all the iPhones
because Steve Jobs have decided that
it was not China
that
went to Washington DC
and demanded
that they buy a third of your national debt
if they hadn't bought it
you would be in serious trouble
number three
I did allude to this
in my talk
in 2008 China had not cranked up
their credit bubble
you would be in a great depression
now
so China
the United States and the European Union
are absolutely
synergistic
and they need one another
in a way that
if we
failed to acknowledge and to nurture
billions of people
including
the majority of the people in this country
are going to suffer
now
I am not going to stand here
and defend China
and the Chinese Communist Party
I already made some negative remarks
about the Chinese Communist Party
in referring to
their attitudes as being
compatible
with those of Wolfgang Schroeble
my concern about China
is the
authoritarian manner
in which the Chinese regime
is treating the Chinese people
as a democrat, I have a problem with this
mind you
I have to tell you that
from my understanding of China
it's a very interesting social experiment
in the sense that
at the local level
the regional level
you now have a boisterous democracy
at the local and regional level
even with
popular
success stories in overthrowing
local
authorities, local
bureaucrats who have been corrupt
who have been this, who have been that, who have been the other
when it comes to the
influence of China outside
its borders, I have to say
firstly, it's quite remarkable that they
don't seem to have any military
ambitions
secondly
Africa
I'll give you an example
a specific example
Ethiopia
2004, because it happened to be there
and I have some
first-person
first-hand experience of it
they went into Ethiopia
I'll tell you why they went into Ethiopia
because they suspected it was oil
because China is
a major industrial power
but it lacks primary resources
now, instead of going
into Africa with troops
colonially destroying the country
killing people like the west has done
for the last 100 years
what they did was, they went to
Adithababa and they said to the government
we would like, we can see
you have problems with your infrastructure
we would like to build some new airports
upgrade your railway system
create a telephone system
and rebuild your roads
and we'll do this all for free
no strings attached, we don't want
anything from you
and they did, why did they do it?
because it's soft power
now, because they knew
that if oil is
discovered, and it was discovered later
then
of course, the Ethiopian government
will be much more open to Chinese
oil companies coming there
they have never combined
their investment
with imperialistic
when I was minister of finance
I had a very interesting
experience with Costco
one of the Chinese national companies
that in the end bought the port of Piraeus
when I moved into the ministry
I found a contract
from the previous government
the port of Piraeus
for a pittance and other ridiculous conditions
to the Chinese
under the guidance
of course of the European Union and International Monetary Fund
as well
and in other ways I was
as a minister I was
bound to a particular
deal that was terrible for Greece
and I went to the Chinese
and discussed it with them
and I was really astonished
I said to them look, you're paying too little
you're not committing to a sufficient
level of investment
and you are treating our workers
as fodder
you are effectively subcontracting labor
to horrible companies
that exploit the workers
and I can't deal with this
effectively
I proposed to them
to renegotiate the contract
so instead of getting 67% of the shares
of the port they would get with the same price
51%
the remaining shares would go into
the Greek pension fund system
in order to bolster
the capitalization of the public pensions
secondly
I want you to commit
to 180 million euros
of investment within 12 months
and thirdly
proper collective bargaining with the trade unions
and no subcontracting of labor
and to my astonishment
they said ok
can you imagine if that was a German company
or an American company
that's what I'm saying, I don't think you should worry
ok, I won't
hi
hi, big fan Janis
nice to see you in person
and I hope you don't mind that I'll struggle
to give you a short question
instead of an essay
so basically
one angle that
was missing from tonight's talk
is the angle of
class formations
so the new deal was born out of
I believe
about easily 50-60 years
of left wing organizing
among the industrial working classes
who basically
as we would always say on our slogans
had their hands on the wheels
when they went on strike they could stop production
stop the flow of profits
and so on and so on
by the time the Great Depression came
there was a crisis
there was a place for labor
and the left at the bargaining table
I guess
what I want to ask is
let's take neoliberalism at a kind of good faith
and say there really was a change
in the class formation
that allowed them to just throw out Bretton Woods
and say we don't want to commit to this deal anymore
you don't have the power
effectively your bargaining terms
oh laborers are not so good anymore
so then
that leaves us today
where are we
who does have their hands on the wheel
I mean
here we are Cambridge, Massachusetts
large portion of the population works in
white collar professions
many of them are homeowners
in traditional
there aren't a lot of traditional industrial workers
in this room
on the other hand the traditional industrial workers
in Ohio or wherever
are losing their jobs quite rapidly
due to mechanization
and offshoring
so
who can put the worker's gun
to the capitalist class's head anymore
good question
but I have to disagree with you on one thing
and sorry to sound a bit tanky on you
no no no you're not tanky
it is the pertinent question
the one you asked
I don't have a
splendid answer to it
but where I want to disagree with you
is that in 1933
or 32
it was the labor movement
that imposed
its will using its power
there was no power
the 1929 great
the great crash and then the depression that followed
completely depleted
trade unions of any bargaining power
when you have a situation
where you've got hordes of people
outside the factory gates
begging to be allowed into work
at any wage
you don't have trade union power
so it was a political process
that led
not a labor process
that led to the new deal
and let's not forget that FDR was not a revolutionary leader
he was a patrician
he was a bourgeois
even Keynes
but Keynes
Keynes hated the workers
trade unions
the reason why he introduced Keynesian economics
his proposals
which included increasing wages
and welfare states
and
fiscal spending
fiscal stimulus and so on
was very simple
he wanted to preserve capitalism
and he understood that capitalism was not very good at preserving itself
that's a very large part
of the motivation of Roosevelt
it was not that he was being pushed
by the industrial might
of the labor unions
so that gives you a bit of hope
since that didn't happen then
maybe we don't need
strong trade unions today
today I think that
from a class formation point of view
what is me
and what I think is the
the
should be the objective
is how to organize
the precariat
those who live precarious existence
the uberized workers
into a political force
because they now are
falling through the cracks of society
they are like the lumpenproletariat used to be
they are disappearing
I mean
a person who works
18 hours a day in an uber
is not a person
it's a lost soul
it's a moving
monument to
to misanthropy
so that for me
is a major question
but
allow me just to be
to shift in towards
something that may sound science fiction
but I don't think it is
we need to think
innovatively about collective action
I do not believe
that the revolution is going to come through trade unions
in industrial sites
but simply because they are fading
unless the robots organize
and they do the revolution on our behalf
you never know
I've read the science fiction novel
where the computer in the end
organized the revolution
but
let me give you an example
today you have
millions of people
who are being exploited
by public utility companies
being privatized
and which are financialized
and they have already
sold to financiers
the next 20 years
of the electricity bills that you will be paying
and as a result
of this financialization
your bill is going up and up and up
completely disproportionately to the cost
of producing electricity, water, whatever
what if
we could work out
which financial derivatives
or CDOs
are packaging
the bills in a particular neighborhood
and another neighborhood
and we organize through the internet
so that we can have
an electricity bill payment strike
that is timed in such a way
as to explode those CDOs
and make them bankrupt
now that's a form of collective action
which is using the financial instruments
of
this kind of network
against it
we need to think beyond
modern times Charlie Chaplin
thank you very much
very interesting stuff
Kelly Spetta
that's all the Greek I know
so
I originally
tried to do a PhD on
the topic you talked
about the separation between
political power and economic power
specifically about the European Union
and how it sort of formalized
this split between the political spheres
no longer has to do anything
with what the people want
with the economic organization
no one wanted to touch that one with the 10 foot pole
so I'm doing something else now
but it made my passion
but to keep the question reasonably short
what is the one change
one of the many changes you'd like to see
in the structure of the European Union
that could address this
right well
I'll be very
brief in my response
we need to federate
because there are only two choices here
either we break it up
which many people want
even on the left
thinking that
recoiling into the bosom of the nation state
is somehow going to allow them
to create socialism in one country
yeah right
yeah
but you have to create
a democratic union
now the problem is
that with this crisis
that we have which is both
economic and political
and moral if you want
we can't have a serious discussion
about federation
because we have centrifugal forces
that are pulling us apart
so this is why our movement
you may have heard of a movement
that I'm part of, DM25
proposing what we call a European New Deal
a new deal
in order to stabilize
and bring hope back so that we can have a discussion
on how to federate
thank you very much
I'm also going to ask
a question about the European Union
and about Greece
and about
the immigration problem
which is all the more
on everyone's mind
because of everyone's
because of what Trump has just done
with wiping out
the
agreement
on
the Iranian
nuclear situation
I
recently read
that on the island of Lesbos
I believe
which is an island that receives
a lot of the
immigrants from the Middle East, Syria
that Greeks
were attacking
the immigrants
and I read
that
I have read
for years now that conditions
in the camps are terrible
and something
that I have wondered about
for years is
why is it
the immigrants from
the Middle East and North Africa
coming to the south
of Europe
the poorest part of Europe
and
why is it that there is not
some common effort
perhaps this is a very naive question
but some common effort
to subsidize
countries like Greece
which is in
terrible economic straits
to deal
more humanely
with these people
that's a fantastic question
ok let's
let me answer in three parts
firstly inform you about what's going on in Lesbos
because Lesbos is very
dear to us
as Greeks to our hearts
and we are
devastated by what's going on
firstly let me be
fair to the people of Lesbos
the vast majority of the people of Lesbos
have been magnificent
for three years now
it's an island that is very depressed
financially economically
it's a bit like Detroit
and you have a million people
it's an island of 17,000 people
and a million people came
and most of them passed through
now we have 50,000 left
and they went on the shore
they picked them up
they opened their houses
they opened their shops and gave them food
of course for no money and so on
but the vast majority
of course when you have a combination
of
the great depression that we have
in Greece you have Nazis
and add to this
the European Union's
attitude
which is effective to turn Lesbos into a concentration camp
and the people of
the Greeks who live there
then become very susceptible
to the toxic narrative of the Greek Nazis
who say to them see
these bastards came here
and now we are
instead of being a beautiful Greek
a Greek island receiving tourists
and doing well
we are ourselves part of a concentration camp
so it's very difficult to fight against this narrative
but
to tell you what I think
so
the situation on the ground
there are three camps
one is called Moria
it is the most notorious one
a camp that can hold
under reasonable conditions
not good but the reasonable
2,000 people there are 10,000 people
so they live in
circumstances that do not
be fit a civilized
part of the world
but that's on purpose
it is run by the European Union
and the United Nations
and it is
accessible of misery
on purpose
from coming
there are another two camps
that local NGOs have created
and they are magnificent
they are absolutely magnificent
if you look at the circumstances
in there
the problem they have
is that they don't have much capacity
so there are 300 families in one
and 110 families in the other
but they live
it's actually quite heartwarming to see
of course the problem is
that none of these people
have any kind of
guarantee
of safety
I was talking to activists in the good camps
who
educate them
teach them English
their own language because they have kids
who speak Farsi
Persian
and they teach them computing
and they put a lot of effort in it
and it's really heartwarming
but they say to me
do you know the tragedy
of not knowing what's going to happen
tomorrow morning because the police may come in
grab one of them
put them in chains throw them on the boat
back to Turkey
so you have no idea is this kid
you have a 12 year old kid there
and his or her parents
are they going to be with us for a week
2 weeks
6 months 2 years
the refugees don't know
their lives
the activists don't know
so what do you teach them
you teach very differently if you teach somebody for 2 weeks
compared to if you know you would be teaching them for 2 years
the curriculum is different
and the local community
doesn't even know
is this camp here going to be permanent
are we going to assimilate them
are we going to live with these people forever
because the local community will react differently
if they knew that
and with some support from them
and the worst part is
that
you know
the reason why I left the ministry
was because my party
and my prime minister capitulated
to the
loan agreement
but immediately after that capitulation
that's what usually happens
if you capitulate on one big thing
then you capitulate on everything
after that he also capitulated and signed
the European Union Treaty with Turkey
and a front
to civilization
because what we are doing is we are effectively
the west
civilized Europe
we are bribing an increasingly
dictatorial president of Turkey
to the tune of some like 7 billion
dollars
so that he allows us
to violate international law on refugees
you know according to international law of refugees
refugees
people coming to your country have the right
by international law
to a hearing
that will determine whether they are political refugees
or not
they don't have that right on lesbos
because
the EU-Turkey treaty has deemed
that Turkey is a safe country
so that
when you arrive on lesbos
you are not granted an interview
as to whether you've been persecuted by the Syrian regime
by the Taliban
by I don't know whom
but if you are kept there
for an indefinite period
you are not allowed to go to the rest of Greece
you can wander around like a lost soul in lesbos
but of course you live in the camp
because there is nowhere else to live
where are you going to live on the beach
so it's
purely horrible but
let's just
take a broader look at that situation
you said the immigration problem
I don't see that why
that immigration is a problem
but it's a great asset
from a European perspective
for a thousand years
we have been populating the earth
we're Europeans
we've been sending our ships
and our caravans
to the Americas
to Australia, to New Zealand
we destroyed all the indigenous people in the world
in Africa we colonized
we created the new world
that's what we did
and we thought it was alright
but we're aging
we're becoming a sad aged lot
yeah
and the demographic dynamics
are reversing
and we need these people
we really need these people
Germany is being depleted
it's becoming another Japan
Greece too, we have an economic crisis as well
you know
we are in a process of desertification
so we need these people
instead of
treating migration
immigration as an asset
that we must collectively
manage
and find ways
of making it work for us Europeans
we are looking at it as a threat
and we are trying to imagine
a huge wall
Trump-like
going through the Mediterranean
the North Pole, I don't know what they are going to do
it's pathetic
it's just a complete failure of the imagination
and the result of course is
that the builder
the taller
and more
impenderable the wall that we create
the only thing that changes
is more deaths
and greater profits for the traffickers
it doesn't stop immigration
all it does it creates insecurity
both in the local population
and in the migrant population
and profits for the traffickers
so
let them in
and impose minimum wages
living wages
in the countries of their origin
and if the countries cannot provide them
help them provide them
that's the solution
not walls
I can't help but notice
that we are talking about the continuum of capitalism
while we overlook a graveyard
my understanding
but one might be wrong
is that we are paying approximately
8 trillion dollars for the wars
in interest
for the wars?
for the wars US
how does an economy
overcome that
and how does that play out
8 trillion in interest
per year
it's not 8 trillion per year
it's not
no
but what is your general concern
that we pay too much for what
for the dead
no, I'm talking about the wars, just the wars
let me tell you
maybe it's 8 billion but not 8 trillion
ok, then my figures are wrong
3 misers is ok
the United States of America
as Eisenhower told you in the 1950s
and warned you
but a very interesting industrial policy
you don't have a formal industrial policy
you have something called the military industrial complex
and the military industrial complex
is essential for American capitalism
in the way that the American capitalism
has been created
so
the reason why
Missouri
and Massachusetts can be in the same union
and you don't have the same problems that we have
between Greece and Germany
it's because you have
what I call a surplus recycling mechanism
you have food stamps
you have social security
and that means that money
that is taxed in the surplus
states is transferred
to the deficit states and that keeps
a degree of balance
but the most important part of your surplus
recycling mechanism
is in the military industrial complex
so when Boeing gets a contract
to build the new generation of fighter jets
quadrillions
the Pentagon says to them
but you're going to have to build the engine
in a new site in Missouri
in the deficit places
the spare parts of this and that
over there and so on
so
to keep this going you need some wars
I'm not proposing that this is how it should be
I'm just describing it
so in 1991
the Pentagon
and the Treasury Department
had a major
major headache
the Cold War had finished
so they could no longer pass through Congress
on the basis of national security
the bills that were necessary
in order to keep replenishing
the cruise and pressing missiles
so they had to clear the stock
so you had the first war in Iraq
and remember
the war had finished
they were going into the middle of the desert
finding all the cruise and pressing missiles
to get rid of them
so that they could order new ones
so capitalism is just
a very rational system
because
it's a very simple reason why it's so irrational
because it has a productive capacity
a capacity to produce
which far exceeds
its capacity to consume
so something has to make up this difference
and war is a result
not just lack of democracy
Hi, thank you for tonight
question for you
if we
theoretically go back to 2015
you're now in charge instead of
Cyprus, in charge of Greece
faced with harsh austerity versus Grexit
what political path would you have chosen?
You know the answer
that's why I'm here, I'm not in the ministry
why am I not in the ministry
why did I resign
we had an agreement
we had a very simple agreement
and this is the only reason why I accepted the finance ministry
and to run in the election
we had an agreement that there were three possible outcomes
I'll put it succinctly
three possible outcomes
one was
continuing debt bondage
in the euro
which is what has been happening since 2010
for me that was the worst possible outcome
another outcome was Grexit
for Greece to be chucked out of the eurozone
or to choose to get out
this came
with substantial costs
and it was never my proposal
but I always considered it to be better
than perpetual debt bondage in the euro
when people say but the euro is a strong currency
I say if you're a pauper
and you live under a bridge in New York
you have one dollar in your pocket
it doesn't mean you have a strong currency
you have one bloody dollar in your pocket
it doesn't help much
and then
the first best
my
ideal solution
would be
debt restructuring within the euro
that would allow us to stay in the euro in a sustainable way
and to end the great depression
so the point I was making was
no bluffing
we say to them we don't want to get out of the euro
but we need a debt restructure
and we need the end of austerity
for Greece to remain
sustainable within the euro
and let's sit down and we'll compromise
I did say to Obama
when he said you have to compromise
I compromised
I dream of compromise
but I'm never going to be
compromised
there is a fundamental difference between the two
ok
and we say to them
we are not going to accept that
we are not putting our signature on another loan agreement
that extends and pretends
our bankruptcy into the future
shoot us, kill us, get us out of the euro
we don't want to get out of the euro
but we consider getting out of the euro to be
a lesser evil
than staying under the conditions of debt
so Cyprus supposedly agreed with me
and not only agreed with me but considered to be more
right-wing than him
and more ready to compromise
and he had some reasons
not that he was right
but
you'll be very
interested to hear that
but one of the people that worked with me
during this period in creating
the plan and the narrative against
the Troika and the International Monetary Fund
was somebody called Larry Summers
who was actually very good
because he understood that what was happening in Greece
reflected
very quickly and immediately in the European
macroeconomic stance
which was detrimental to the interests of the United States
so we worked together
with Larry Summers
and when we met I said
I'm very glad you haven't read my last book
and he said
why? I said because
I referred to it to you
on a number of occasions in the same book
as the prince of darkness
and he said
well at least you called me prince
I've been called worse
so it's clear
the two organizations
I like to follow side by side
the DM25 movement
and six degrees of citizen space
in Canada
with John Rouse and Saul
and I just really enjoyed John Rouse and Saul's book
The Collapse of Globalism
and he describes this idea
of a positive form of nationalism
that we haven't explored
we think of nationalism as negative
and we often only see negative forms
based on exclusion
but our movements like
DM25
imagining
and exploring possibly
hijacking and displacing hate
with positive forms of nationalism
that are centered around
inclusion
and
sort of collective missions
like reducing inequality
that can capture a lot of the people
that are displaced in this country
the Trump voters that might not be racist
that just wanted a better deal
and they really fall in with the flag
when someone waves the flag
they're easy to be manipulated
but they just feel that they must go with it
but now in this country
when you see two American flags
on the back of a pickup truck
that's kind of a hate symbol
the left progressive people
that enjoy inclusion
have maybe allowed
the flag to get stolen from them
but then at the same time
we need to integrate nationalism
possibly a new form
with ideas like a federation
to gain more power
back into
the political sphere
against the financial sphere
Well, let me say that
I get your drift
I grew up in a culture
where the left
answered this question of yours
a long time ago
by making a distinction
not between positive and negative
but between patriotism
a line was always
we're patriots
and the difference between a patriot and a nationalist
the patriot loves his country
and the nationalist thinks that his country
has the right to steamroll over every other country
and I think that is a good way
of resolving it
and also by making this more
contemporary
I think we have to
appropriate the
slogan
we should take this
I want my city back
I want my neighborhood back
I want control over my city
my municipality
my state, my country
but the only way to get my country back
is if others get their country back
as well
and if we all work together
and we understand that to get our country back
we need to resolve problems such as
low quality jobs
low levels of investments
in the green transition
that the planet needs
climate change and so on
that we need to fight poverty
and it is impossible to fight poverty in one country
when it's rising in other countries
if you think that you can do that
you're deluding yourself
so in effect
to embed patriotism
in a narrative which sees
the major problems that society faces
like poverty, low investment
problems with the health service and so on
as we see climate change
what I mean by that
is climate change requires local action
that we do things here
in Boston, that we do things in Massachusetts
in the United States but we have to act globally
as well
and we need to cooperate
because resolving poverty as I said
can only happen at
the Bretton Woods system is a good example
poverty fell everywhere
throughout the global system
inequality shrunk everywhere
it couldn't rise in one place massively
and fall in another
so we have to combine
level of country, of neighborhoods
of community, patriotism
with transnationalism and internationalism
that allows us to claim
our own countries back
a funny multinational question
that I would love to hear answered from you
in the book
John Rouse and Saul describes this concept
where a lot of the trade
we have is fictitious
it is multinationals trading with themselves
yeah of course
and
it's called limit pricing
well now you know we were just
creating these tariffs
that might not really get to the root
of the issue we were punishing multinationals
we weren't punishing another nation
we were punishing multinationals
that straddle to nations
and that not a lot of people in this country
know how to think of these concepts
well I have a better way
of punishing the multinationals
how about making the IRS do its job
because if you
go to
Venezuela, or by the example
if you go to Italy and make some money
you get taxed here
you are taxed by the IRS
on your global income
you cannot say
I made $10,000 in
Napoli and therefore
none of your business
you get taxed on your global income
unless you are a corporation
and then you don't get taxed at all
for the money you stash away
all over the world
how about having the IRS do its job
instead of introducing
tariffs that in the end
have a detrimental effect on all of us
but the IRS can't
yes it can
yes of course it can
they need their marching orders
from congress
they need the politicians to say to them
you are going to treat
look, the supreme court
in its infinite idiocy
decided that corporations and human
beings and individuals will be treated the same
when it comes to super PACs and all that
why not treat
also decide that
corporations and individuals will be treated the same
tax wise
I remember a beautiful
poster I saw in Texas saying that
I like it
I believe that corporations
have human rights
when I see one of them being hanged
that was Texas for you
in the
briefest and broadest of strokes
in the post-capitalistic world
that you envision
what does the credit system look like
and how does it achieve equilibrium
with the sovereignty of states
ok how long do we have
no but
let me put it simply
if we have a system
where private
property
is maintained over
goods and services
and things that give you happiness
but not over
productive processes
and productive processes belong
to those that work them
that are part of it
then you simply
have a credit system
you don't need one at all
your justification for that is
that credit is only necessary
when you've got an asymmetrical distribution
of property rights
over means of production
if you and I have a cooperative
if we own a business together
we have a partnership
then I'm never going to be in your debt
or you admire that
we're producing together
and we're going to be sharing the profits
that we make
what about investors
well there would be no investors
what about the other person
because investors exist only because
you have an asymmetrical distribution
of wealth
if you didn't have asymmetrical distribution
but look this is going to be the topic of my next book
I have not written it yet
so I'll see you in 3 years
ευχαριστώ