Good morning everyone. I stand for the motion that social media makes us
unsocial. We live in an era where we prefer texting than conversations, online
chat than face-to-face meetings. Social media is in effect turning us into one
of the most unsocial generations. My first point to support is that social media
is creating a false friendship and later these are leading to emotional and
psychological problems. When one posts something in social media they're
looking for social acceptance and appreciation. Nowadays research shows
that there is something called Facebook depression. Not getting enough
feedback for one's post is leading to anxiety. The second harm of social
media is that it can become easily addictive, taking away family time and
personal time as well as diminish interpersonal skills. We really need the
comfort of family members when we have to celebrate a birth or when someone is
really sick. Mainly communicating to a person through Facebook or WhatsApp does
not solve the situation. A physical presence is very much required at those
critical stages of life. Lastly, social media has become a tool for criminals.
Many criminals have taken the advantage of social media to hide their
identity and commit several crimes. Several people have committed suicide
for playing games like blue ale etc. To sum up, the more social media we have, the
more we think we are connecting but actually we are disconnecting from each
other. Hence, I believe that social media makes us unsocial. Thank you.
Don't forget to subscribe and like. Bye.