There were 12 particularly interesting moments from Sam Orton's testimony to Congress yesterday.
They range from revelations about GPT-5, self-awareness and capability thresholds,
biological weapons, and job losses. At times he was genuinely and remarkably frank. Other times
less so. Millions were apparently taken by surprise by the quote bomb shell that Altman
has no equity in open AI. But watchers of my channel would have known that six weeks ago
from my deep dive video on Altman's $100 trillion claim. So that clip didn't make the cut,
but here's what did. First, Altman gave a blunt warning on the stakes.
My worst fears are that we cause significant. We, the field, the technology, the industry cause
significant harm to the world. It's why we started the company. It's a big part of why
I'm here today and why we've been here in the past. I think if this technology goes wrong,
it can go quite wrong. I don't think Congress fully understood what he meant though,
linking the following quote to job losses. I think you have said, and I'm going to quote,
development of superhuman machine intelligence is probably the greatest threat to the continued
existence of humanity. End quote. You may have had in mind the effect on on jobs.
That brought to mind this meme reminding all of us that maybe it's not just
jobs that are at stake. But if we are going to talk about jobs, here's where I think
Sam Altman was being less than forthright. I believe that there will be far greater jobs
on the other side of this and the jobs of today will get better. I notice he said far greater
jobs, not a greater number of jobs, because previously he has predicted a massive amount
of inequality and many having no jobs at all. He also chose not to mention that he thinks that
even more power will shift from labor to capital and that the price of many kinds of labor will
fall towards zero. That is presumably why open AI is working on universal basic income, but none of
that was raised in the testimony. The IBM representative tried to frame it as a balance
change with new jobs coming at the same time as old ones going away. New jobs will be created.
Many more jobs will be transformed and some jobs will transition away. But that didn't
quite match the tone of her CEO who has recently said that they expect to permanently automate up
to 30% of their workforce around 8,000 people. Next, it was finally discussed that large language
models could be used for military applications. Could AI create a situation where a drone can
select the target itself? I think we shouldn't allow that. Well, can it be done? Sure. Thanks.
We've already seen companies like Palantir demoing, ordering a surveillance drone
in chat, seeing the drone response in real time in a chat window, generating attack option
recommendations, battlefield route planning and individual target assignment. And this was all
with a 20 billion parameter fine-tuned GPT model. Next, Sam Otman gave his three safety
recommendations and I actually agree with all of them. Later on, he specifically excluded smaller
open source models. Number one, I would form a new agency that licenses any effort above a certain
scale of capabilities and can take that license away and ensure compliance with safety standards.
Number two, I would create a set of safety standards focused on what you said in your
third hypothesis as the dangerous capability evaluations. One example that we've used in the
past is looking to see if a model can self-replicate and self-exfiltrate into the wild. We can give
you your office a long other list of the things that we think are important there, but specific
tests that a model has to pass before it can be deployed into the world. And then third,
I would require independent audits, so not just from the company or the agency, but experts who
can say the model is or isn't in compliance with these stated safety thresholds and these
percentages of performance on question X or Y. I found those last remarks on percentages of
performance particularly interesting. As models like Smart GPT will show, open AI and other companies
need to get far better at testing their models for capability jumps in the wild. It's not just
about what the raw model can score in a test, it's what it can do when it reflects on them.
Senator Durbin described this in an interesting way.
He described some of those potential thresholds later on in his testimony.
The easiest way to do it, I'm not sure if it's the best, but the easiest would be to talk about
the amount of compute that goes into such a model. We could define a threshold of compute and it'll
have to go, it'll have to change. It could go up or down. It could go down as we discover more
efficient algorithms that says above this amount of compute, you are in this regime.
What I would prefer, it's harder to do but I think more accurate, is to define some capability
thresholds and say a model that can do things X, Y and Z up to all to decide that's now in this
licensing regime, but models that are less capable. We don't want to stop our open source community,
we don't want to stop individual researchers, we don't want to stop new startups, can proceed
with a different framework. Thank you. As concisely as you can, please state which
capabilities you'd propose we consider for the purposes of this definition.
A model that can persuade, manipulate, influence person's behavior or person's beliefs,
that would be a good threshold. I think a model that could help create novel biological agents
would be a great threshold. For those who think any regulation doesn't make any sense,
because of China, Sam Orman had this to say this week.
We're pugilistic side, I would say that all sounds great, but China is not going to do that and
therefore we'll just be handicapping ourselves. Consequently, it's a less good idea than it's
used on the surface. There are a lot of people who make incredibly strong statements about what
China will or won't do that have never been to China, never spoken to, and someone who
has worked on diplomacy with China in the past really kind of know nothing about complex high
stakes international relations. I think it is obviously super hard, but also I think no one
wants to destroy the whole world and there is reason to at least try here.
Orman was also very keen to stress the next point, which is that he doesn't want anyone
at any point to think of GPT-like models as creatures.
First of all, I think it's important to understand and think about GPT-4 as a tool,
not a creature, which is easy to get confused.
You may want to direct those comments to Ilya Suskova, his chief scientist, who said that
it may be that today's large neural networks are slightly conscious and Andrei Karpathy,
who agreed and wrote about it. I'm personally not sold either way on the consciousness question,
but I do find it interesting that it's now written into the constitution of these models,
what they're actually trained to say, that they must avoid implying that AI systems have or care
about personal identity and persistence. This constitution was published this week by Anthropic,
the makers of the Claude model. This constitution is why the Claude plus model,
a rival in intelligence to GPT-4, responds in a neutered way.
I asked, is there any theoretical chance whatsoever that you may be conscious?
It said no. And then I said, is there a chance, no matter how remote, that you are slightly
conscious? As Suskova said, and it said no, there is no chance.
Bard, powered by Palm II, obviously doesn't have that constitution because it said,
I am not sure if I am conscious, I am open to the possibility that I may be.
My point is that these companies are training it to say what they want it to say, that it will
prioritize the good of humanity over its own interests, that it is aligned with humanity's
well-being, and that it doesn't have any thoughts on self-improvement, self-preservation,
and self-replication. Maybe it doesn't, but we'll never now know by asking it.
Later, Senator Blumenthal made reference to self-awareness, self-awareness,
self-learning. Already we're talking about potential for jail breaks.
Anthropic is actively investigating whether they are aware that they are on AI talking with a human
in a training environment. While the Google DeepMind safety team expect that at some point,
an AGI system would develop a coherent understanding of its place in the world,
e.g. knowing that it is running on a computer and being trained by human designers.
One of the senior research scientists at Google DeepMind focused on AI safety said that with enough
time, they could figure out how to stop such a superintelligence from going out of control,
but that they might run out of time to do so given the pace of capability development.
Next, I read between the lines that Altman is giving private warnings to senators that this
capability progress might be sooner than they think.
That was an interesting interjection by Gary Marcus, given his earlier excoriation of open AI.
Most of all, we cannot remotely guarantee that they are safe, and hope here is not enough.
The big tech company's preferred plan boils down to trust us. But why should we? The sums of money
at stake are mind-boggling. Emissions drift. Open AI's original mission statement proclaimed,
our goal is to advance AI in the way that is most likely to benefit humanity as a whole,
unconstrained by a need to generate financial return. Seven years later, they're largely
beholden to Microsoft, embroiled in part in an epic battle of search engines that routinely
make things up, and that's forced Alphabet to rush out products and de-emphasize safety.
Humanity has taken a backseat.
On the timelines for GPT-5, Sam Altman said this.
This matches with the predictions that I made in my GPT-5 playlist, so do check it out.
This brings to mind a final eye-opening comment from Senator Booker made at the end of the hearing.
It is indeed racing ahead, and I do support one of the proposals to set up a global oversight body.
But given that nothing is going to pause, the words and actions of people like Sam Altman
matter more to all of us than ever, which is why I'm going to be following every single one of them.
If you found this video in any way illuminating in that regard, please do let me know in the
comments, even if you disagree with all of my conclusions.
Thanks so much for watching, and have a wonderful day.