I have three goals for this video. First, I want to show you a way of using GPT-4 to get smarter
results. Second, I want to argue that the benchmark results we have for GPT-4 do not reflect its full
abilities. And third, I want to show you a system that I am developing, somewhat cheekily called
Smart GPT, that is already showing significant results on official benchmarks. It remains to
be fully optimized, which I think is exciting in itself. I have shown the system to people at Open
AI who have been quite impressed, and I'm going to end with some reflections on where that might
leave us for GPT-5. But before I get into how it works, I just want to show you one example of it
in action to whet your appetite. This example comes from a TED talk that was released this week.
So suppose I left five clothes to dry out in the sun, and it took them five hours to dry completely.
How long would it take to dry 30 clothes? GPT-4, the newest, greatest AI system says 30 hours. Not
good. On the left, you can see GPT-4's original answer, and it gives this answer pretty consistently
whenever you prompt it with the question provided. On the right, you can see the final answer from
the Smart GPT model, which is correct, and it consistently gives that answer. I really like
how it gives context as well, and it provides some of the assumptions that it had in giving this
correct answer. Now, don't you worry, there will be plenty more examples to go through in this video,
including another one from that TED talk. But first, I want to give you an overview of what is
this Smart GPT model, where did I get my inspiration for it from, and how does it work? I'm going to
keep it fairly simple because it's the beginning of the video, and I know a lot of people won't really
care about the inner details that will come later in the video. But the high-level overview is this.
There are at least three things that have been proven to improve the outputs of GPT-4.
What's called chain of thought prompting, sometimes called step-by-step prompting,
reflection, or finding its own errors, and I did an entire video on this called GPT-4
Can Self Improve, and dialoguing with itself, entering into a back and forth on its own
outputs and deciding which one is best. You can see the title of the papers, which contain much
more detailed results, of course, linked above. Now, the first paper only came out a few days ago,
midway through my testing, so my results don't even reflect the full capacity of the model.
And even if there's nothing else you take from this video, the results from this paper can instantly
improve the outputs you get from GPT-4. Many of you might remember that prompting GPT-4 with
let's think step-by-step improves its results. To give you a very quick reference point, just
asking a question to GPT-4 gives you 81% accuracy. With that prompt, let's think step-by-step,
it goes up to 86%. But algorithmically, the paper found an improved prompt that can give you even
better results, 89% accuracy. All we do, and this is the first part of smart GPT, is we add
answer, let's work this out in a step-by-step way to be sure we have the right answer. Now,
I have so much to say about why I think this works, but I know many of you won't be that
interested in my theories, so I'm going to save them to the end for those who are interested.
Some of you just want the results, so I'm going to get to those first. So far, you might be thinking,
well, thanks, Philip, that's a cool prompt. I'm going to use that. But what's this whole smart
GPT about? Is it just a single prompt? No, I believe with evidence, there are ways of leveraging
even better results than just using a great chain of thought prompt. So let's move on to the next
part of the system, these different outputs in the middle. For my tests, I typically did three
outputs, but of course, depending on the context window, it could be far more than that. And I'm
going to talk about ways I could further improve this model, or we could later on in the video.
Just to restate, these outputs are when you take the user input and add the word question at start,
and then at the end add answer, let's work this out in a step-by-step way to make sure we have
the right answer. And at this moment, many of you are thinking, what is the point of multiple
outputs? It's GPT-4, it's just going to give you the answer that thinks is best, and that's it.
Well, actually, it doesn't quite work like that. These models have a temperature between zero and
one. I believe the default for GPT-4 might be around 0.5. And simplifying massively, this determines
how creative or conservative the model is in giving its outputs. So given that GPT-4 tries to be
fairly creative, you don't get the same output every time. The output is randomly sampled according
to an internal probability distribution. So you can get situations, and I face this hundreds of
times, where some of the outputs are correct, and others are incorrect. And this is where reflection
comes in. Sometimes, definitely not always, but sometimes quite often, GPT-4 can detect the errors
in its own output. And many of you will notice at this point that the prompt that I used to elicit
GPT-4 to spot its own errors contains the same step-by-step prompt I used earlier that has been
shown to produce good results. So to summarize, sometimes at this stage, GPT-4 detects the errors
that some of its outputs have made. Definitely not always. There are certain questions, it just simply
can't spot the error. But sometimes it can. And then I get it to engage in a dialogue using a format
similar to one in this paper published last month. It's a short dialogue, and this is the
step I believe that can be most optimized. In the future, I envision an entire council of advisors
made up of GPT-4 imitating mathematicians, judges, etc. At the moment, it's just being a resolver
and printing a final improved output. Anyway, I'm going to get back to the theory later in the video
because I know some of you will be getting bored at this stage and want to see more practical
examples and the results from my benchmark tests. As I don't have the GPT-4 API key, yes, I had to
manually input each of these steps hundreds of times, waiting sometimes three hours between each
go because you can only do 25 messages every three hours. On the left, you can see the three
outputs when you ask it to think step by step. And then you have the researcher step in the middle
and at the top right. And finally, the resolver step. Notice here, I was using the original
let's think step by step because the paper hadn't yet been published on improving that prompt.
It's time for the second example from that TED Talk, and then I definitely will get on to the
benchmarks. A different one. I have 12 liter jug and 6 liter jug, and I want to measure 6 liters.
How do I do it? Just use the 6 liter jug, right? GPT-4 spits out some very elaborate nonsense.
Of course, I tested smart GPT with that question, and you can see the difference between
the original GPT-4, which gives this incredibly convoluted bad answer, and smart GPT, the final
answer output. Now, at this point, I know many of you will be impressed, but you'll be thinking,
I don't have time to input things five times. Well, I'm developing a model where it can all
be done automatically. Here is a preview of how it works. But of course, at the moment, it has to
use GPT 3.5 Turbo because I don't have the API key of GPT-4. But the epic thing is this, you just
ask a single question, I've written, ask smart GPT-A question. And of course, it does take a
little bit longer to respond because it's doing five or six calls via API, but it does output the
final answer from the resolver step. I will be honest and say that GPT 3.5 isn't as good at
reflecting or resolving. But this is an example of a question where the original chat GPT consistently
gets it wrong, and smart GPT 3.5 gets it right using this program. Remember, all you have to do as
a user is type in a question as normal, and it goes through this entire five or six step process
behind the scenes. By the way, this was a question from MMLU, which is a famous benchmark which I'll
get to in a second. Here's one last practical example before I get to that benchmark. I know many
teachers use chat GPT and GPT-4 to create quizzes for their classes. And here is the same question
put through GPT-4 and smart GPT. The question is, create a high school algebra quiz with five
questions and answers and explanations at the end. Now points for spotting the difference,
but if the teacher had handed out the original quiz, look at the answers for question five.
It says the answers are one and 1.5. But then in the explanation, it gives the final answers,
which are correct by the way, of three and zero point five. So that would really confuse some
students at the reflection stage smart GPT spotted that error and resolved it. And as you can see,
the answer for question five has the correct answers straight away. If at any point you're
wondering if I completed the open AI chat GPT prompt engineering course, the answer is yes,
but it didn't inform too much of my thinking. It was more for beginners and I had already
factored in things like giving the model time to think and writing clear instructions. The
benchmark that I chose to test smart GPT on was the famous MMLU, massive multitask language
understanding benchmark. As you can see, the state of the art is indeed GPT for with 86.4%
accuracy. And you know, open AI think it's a big deal because it's the benchmark mentioned on the
front page of their technical report without boring you too much. I extracted the questions
from the test set of the MMLU data file, and I didn't pick the topics at random. I went for
those that I thought GPT for would find the hardest delving into the original MMLU paper.
You can see that GPT three found for more logic the hardest scoring just over 25% which is random
chance. It's a four question multiple choice test. So around 25 or 30% is pretty bad. And notice
they helped out GPT three here. They did it few shot, meaning they gave it five successful examples
before asking it a new question. It's the same thing they did with GPT four. They did it five
shot. But just before I show you the results, there are three things I want to mention here.
First, I was curious how smart GPT would do without any help zero shot. Second, I wanted to do it
zero shot because people using GPT four don't typically give five successful examples before
asking GPT for a question. They just want code or a quiz or a poem or an example. They don't often
provide five brilliant examples of code before asking their question. And third, if I can prove
it works zero shot, then of course, future refinements can be made to push the results even
further. And here are the results from the first 25 questions from the formal logic test set of the
MMLU. I did many more tests after this. But you can see from this set, if you just ask the question,
you get a lower overall accuracy. But of course, 68% for GPT four is still a huge improvement over
GPT threes around 25%. What happens when you add let's think step by step, which as we know now
isn't the fully optimized chain of thought prompt. Well, on average, you get around 74-75%.
That was 75 examples inputted manually. And I still have all the tabs open. I'm keeping them open
because I'm compiling a spreadsheet with the actual outputs. But what did the resolver get
drawing upon GPT four's ability to reflect and engage in dialogue with itself? It got 84%.
Now notice something about that number. GPT four zero short got 32% of the questions wrong. That
was halved to 16% after putting it through the smart GPT system. There was one question where
the resolver model gave both a correct and incorrect answer. But I'm counting that as an
incorrect answer for the purposes of this test. Anyway, from 32% to 16% incorrect,
that is a pattern that stayed consistent throughout all my testing that approximately half of the
errors that GPT four makes can be rectified. If you give it the optimized step by step prompt,
get it to reflect on its results and get it to engage in dialogue and decide on a final answer.
At this point, for those people losing track of all the details, I want to put into context
what resolving half of the errors on MMLU might mean in the context of the big picture.
Here's Lenard Heim, an AI governance researcher, suggesting a score of 95% on the MMLU would be
reflective of AGI like abilities. I do think I have like a 50% chance like within the next 20
years or so, there might be something what we might call an AGI or transformative AI. What
do I mean by this? Well, maybe can measured on benchmarks. There's like this famous MMLU
benchmarks like yet or something which like scores like 95% on this. Going back to the results,
if a smart GPT like system can automatically resolve half of the errors that GPT four makes
on the MMLU, that would increase its score from around 86.4% to around 93%, which is not far off
95%. Remember, his prediction was a 50% chance in 20 years. I'm talking about GPT four now.
For those who are still skeptical, I'm going to show you plenty more results now and then walk
through the papers that give the theory as to why this works. One thing that I forgot to mention
earlier is that the human expert level on the MMLU is 89.8%. And that's taking the 95th percentile
of human test takers. And remember, those are domain experts in each of these subtopics.
What we're doing is testing GPT four or smart GPT on all of the topics simultaneously.
So even if smart GPT like systems can't quite reach 95%, and I think honestly,
they'll get pretty close with all the refinements that I'm going to suggest,
I think they should almost certainly be 89.8%, which is the human expert test taker level.
Intrigued by these results, I then put it through the college math test from the MMLU. And remember,
this was before using the optimized version of the step by step prompt. Obviously, I'm not going to
go through all the questions here, but let's skip to the final results. We have zero shot accuracy,
six out of 15, which is 40%. The average when you add let's think step by step was 53.5%.
And then the final output of the resolver model had a 60% accuracy. So it couldn't quite resolve
half of the errors, but the overall pattern held up. In case anyone is wondering about methodology,
I kept the formatting identical for every question. I always opened a new tab for each question.
It wasn't looking at the context of what it had already put out. Each attempt was fresh,
aside from the resolver model, which looked at the context of the researcher's output. And again,
as you can see from example 14, it wasn't like the researcher could always spot the errors or that
the resolver could always pick the right option. Sometimes the let's think step by step prompt
gave the right output, but the resolver couldn't quite distinguish it. The optimized prompt gets
a slightly better output. And upon reflection, the researcher can sometimes but not always spot
the errors of those outputs. And sometimes but not always the resolver can spot based on those
flaws, which answer is best. These are incremental improvements. Sometimes GPT-4 simply can't get
it right. I have noticed a few themes in those questions. Anytime it comes to division,
multiplication, characters, or counting in general, GPT-4 tends to make mistakes that
neither the researcher nor resolver can spot. Of course, integrating a few tools via API would
likely solve those issues. And I don't want to preempt the conclusion too much, but I believe a
smart GPT-like system with tools integrated could probably score around 95% right now on the MMLU,
especially if it was helped out with a few shot prompting. To add weight to that preliminary
conclusion, I tested it on certain topics and had to stop because it simply got the questions right
every single time. For example, high school psychology from the MMLU. I then tried prehistory,
which it also aced before finding machine learning where I got more interesting results.
Zooming in this time, the raw score was 65%. The chain of thought let's think step by step average
was 71.6% and the resolver model got 80%. Let's now look a little deeper into why all of these
steps might improve the end result. In reply to the original let's think step by step paper,
which was published around a year ago, Andrea Carpathi said this. Adding something like let's
think step by step to the prompt is a way of using the input space for computation that you'd normally
want in the hidden state of the model. Instead of the workings out being done in the activations
of the neural network, it's done in the discrete tokens of that input space. And he adds did not
super see this coming. And here is the paper released three days ago that improves upon
that original prompt. They also did their testing zero shot like me. And they tested many prompts
starting like I did with just direct prompting, just asking the question like 99% of users would
do of GPT four. And then they tried like me the well established let's think step by step
prompt. They also iteratively tested seven original prompts, as well as the prompt that I've now
integrated into smart GPT the let's work this out in a step by step way, etc. They share my opinion
that zero shot prompting setups have the benefit of not requiring such task dependent selection
of exemplars. You don't have to find correct examples. It just does it all for you. Here are
the end results for GPT four that we saw earlier showing the difference between asking directly
your question and using these refined prompts. Notice that this technique is somewhat model
dependent. And it doesn't have the same effect on smaller or weaker models. Before we move on
to the next paper, there is one somewhat failed prompt that I want to pick up on. It's this
self critique prompt where they ask answer the question, then critique the answer based on the
critique, reconsider the other answer options, and give a single final answer. And you might
wonder why didn't that prompt perform best when we know that reflection and dialogue can work?
My theory is because it's trying to do all of it in one prompt. Through my hundreds of experiments,
I've noticed that GPT four can only handle so much in one go. It simply gets overwhelmed or
confused if you ask it to do too much in one prompt. That's why I broke my model into stages to allow
it to show off each of its abilities one by one. And before we get to the other papers, what's my
personal theory as to why this eliminates up to half of the errors that GPT four makes? Well,
my guess is this. Remember that GPT four is drawing on a vast data set of internet text. And let me
ask you what kind of text has things like question, answer, let's work this out. Be sure we have the
right answer. The kind of data that would have that text would be things like tutorials or expert
breakdowns. So I believe you're triggering more of the weights inside GPT four that relate to
things like expert tutorials. And so inevitably you're getting slightly better answers. Next,
I've already explained why you get different outputs when you give the exact same prompt.
That's down to sampling and the temperature of the model. But to simplify massively, sometimes
GPT four will give you an output that it knows isn't the most probable. It introduces some randomness
into its sampling by generating multiple outputs, you're getting a larger sample size,
reflecting the full range of probabilities that GPT four ascribes to its outputs, you're reducing
a little bit some of the randomness that's inherent in GPT four outputs. Next, I believe that GPT
four can sometimes spot its own errors through reflection, because prompting like this triggers
a different set of weights, you could almost think of it as a different mindset, one more focused on
finding errors. Again, if the question is too hard or involves counting characters,
division, multiplication, as I said earlier, this won't help. But a percentage of the time it can
spot its own errors and point them out. Notice this is a separate bit of inference not lumped into
the original prompt. And when it does successfully point out the errors, it can often engage in
this dialogue with itself. Notice in a meta kind of way, I'm using the step by step prompting
to improve the reflection and dialogue. So those are my theories as to why it works,
but at the end of the video, I'm going to show you at least five ways I think the model can be
further refined. Before we do, though, I looked up the paper by Joe, which produced that prompt that
did the best in the previous paper, they came to that special prompt through automatic prompt
engineering. But there's something interesting I want to point out, though, on page seven,
they say we use automatic prompt engineering to find a prompt starting with let's that maximizes
the likelihood of correct reasoning steps. Then they found the best one that I integrated into
smart GPT. Let's work this out in a step by step way to be sure we have the right answer. That's
the one I want you to use. And they ran their own benchmarks. And of course, it did improve
the scores. But the interesting thing to me is they started with let's each time. So even that
first stage for the model might not yet be fully optimized. Maybe there's a prompt that doesn't
begin with let's that improves this initial results still further. Anyway, back to the papers,
I know many people watching this will wonder if I read the paper boosting theory of mind performance
in large language models via prompting. And yes, I did because they tested something similar for a
theory of mind test. Using similar techniques, they were able to get theory of mind accuracy for
GPT four from 80% to 100%. And they conclude that these results demonstrate that appropriate
prompting enhances large language model theory of mind reasoning. And they underscore the context
dependent nature of these models cognitive capacities. They use that original prompt,
let's think step by step, along with some few shot examples. Take a look at the GPT four table. And
you can see how the let's think step by step improved the results dramatically. And as I
theorized earlier, adding few shot examples would push this still further. This is part of why I think
that 95% barrier on the MMLU will be broken probably this year by GPT four, a few other
points from this paper. They admit that there is not currently a theoretical understanding of why
these prompting techniques are beneficial. I've given you my theory and car pathies, but no one
quite knows for sure. Lastly from this paper, and I found this really interesting, giving it generic
few shot prompts that weren't directly theory of mind actually improve the outputs slightly more
than giving it direct theory of mind examples. This opens the door to the first of the five ways
I anticipate smart GPT getting even smarter. It could be possible to come up with generic
few shot prompts that could be automatically integrated into the model that don't necessarily
relate to the topic at hand. This graph shows the impact of adding few shot examples to GPT three.
And if this can be done in a generic way for GPT four, results could be improved still further.
Next, the boosting theory of mind paper speculates that integrating some of these approaches could
boost the performance of weaker models to beyond the levels of GPT four zero shot accuracy. Next,
here is the original DERA paper that inspired me to have the researcher and resolver dialogue at
the end of smart GPT. As they say, the DERA approach shows significant improvement over base GPT
four performance. And these were open ended questions, by the way, not multiple choice. So
this is more generally applicable than you might think. You can see from this table how results
improved after engaging in this dialogue. And that brings me to the second way I anticipate smart
GPT getting smarter in the future, a longer and more rich dialogue. At the moment, we have this
simple researcher and resolver two step dialogue. I can imagine a council of advisors, you can imagine
a mathematician chipping in and a philosopher and a professor, each one tapping into slightly
different weights of GPT four, extracting more hidden expertise. I'm not saying that would
transform the results, but it might edge them another few percent higher. Next, even with longer
dialogues and different experts, we could find ways of optimizing these prompts just like we did
with the original let's think step by step. That's the third avenue of improvement that I envisaged
because I came up with these prompts, I'm sure they could be improved. Next, we could experiment
with different temperatures. Remember, a lower temperature makes the model more conservative,
a higher one towards one makes it more creative. We could experiment with a higher temperature
to produce a more diverse range of outputs at this stage, and then perhaps a more conservative,
deterministic temperature for the final judge or resolver. It might not work, but it's worth
trying. And the fifth improvement I know would work, integrating APIs for character counting,
calculators, code interpreters, etc. Spending these weeks manually sorting through the outputs of GPT
four on these benchmarks, I can really see where it goes wrong. And it's often by getting letters
in the wrong order or making mistakes with division, it gets the high level logic right,
and then makes quite simple errors. Basic tool integration would I am sure push the results
still higher. Now, I know this isn't my usual video. And trust me, I have been following the AI
news and we'll get back to that very soon. I'm determined to make those improvements and push
smart GBT even further. But of course, that will be aided massively by getting access to the plugins
and the GPT four API key. So far, I've had to do all of this manually, which was a lot of work.
Now, as you saw earlier, I have drawn on GPT four to help me develop a program in replete to
automate this process. But at the moment, it's GPT 3.5. And honestly, the context window really
limits the ability. But I do look forward to the day when I can integrate GPT four and put this out
as an automatic model for people to test and play about with. I'm sure that something similar will
ultimately be incorporated by open AI itself, maybe as a thoughtful mode or smart mode, a bit
like Bing has creative, precise balance, etc. Each response does take longer. But as you've seen,
the outputs are noticeably better. If the results of models like this one do officially exceed the
86.4% that open AI talked about in the GPT four technical report, I do think that would reveal
quite a few things. First, the open AI isn't even aware of the full capabilities of its own
model. I don't even know if they anticipated things like auto GPT. I do think it would reveal
that they need to do far more proper testing of their models before they release them. They should
make falsifiable predictions about what their models won't be capable of. That way we would
know just how much they know about their own models. What we're trying to avoid is a situation
where open AI say their model can only achieve X. And then when they release the model in the
wild, someone comes along and achieves Y, where Y is much more impactful than X. So those were the
goals of this video to show you how to get more out of GPT four to run you through some of the
fascinating papers that have been released in the last few days and weeks. The third goal was to
show you what this model could do with some official benchmarks and suggest ways it might get better
in the near term future. Of course, if you have a GPT four API key or are an expert in benchmarking
systems like GPT four, I'd love to hear from you. I guess the final goal was to perhaps suggest to you
that open AI don't know as much about their own models as they might lead you to believe.
Thank you so much for watching to the end and have a wonderful day.