I want to talk today about the scam of modern conservatism and how the right is manipulating
and exploiting people with an ideology that exists only in theory and in reality is completely
different from that which it claims to be. Let me explain. Modern conservatism is a political
ideology that claims to be about limited government, individual liberty and responsibility,
traditional values, freedom, not regulating businesses on and on and on. And there's two
parts of this. The first part is that in theory, all of that sounds really appealing. It's sort of
like, Hey, doesn't paying no taxes sound appealing in some general sense? I mean, yeah, I'd love to
keep every dollar that I gross and not pay any taxes in some general sense. That sounds pretty
good. It sounds appealing in certain contexts. The ideas espoused by conservatism sound beneficial.
But in practice, modern conservatism has become a scam that is used to manipulate and exploit people
and its values are just as quickly abandoned by those espousing them once they are no longer
convenient or productive or helping their costs. Let's talk about some examples. One way that
modern conservatism is being used to manipulate the public is through propaganda and misinformation.
Conservative media outlets and politicians will often spread misleading information
based on their supposed principles in order to win elections. At the end of the day, all they care
about is winning elections. And this includes conspiracy theories when it's convenient,
cherry picking data, using completely loaded language to evoke an emotional response. We're
pro life. Wow, everybody else must be against life. That sounds pretty bad. We're for tax relief.
Wow. Taxes must just simply be oppressive. Taxes must be like slavery, which is quite literally
what some libertarians say. And by using this language and manipulating the public's understanding
of the facts, conservatives shape public opinion and influence policy decisions and voters in their
favor in ways that are completely misleading and don't actually benefit the people that end up voting
for them. And that's a big part of the scam. And we're going to get back to that. Another way that
the public is exploited by the scam of conservatism is through dog whistle politics. So this is when
they use coded language that certain groups of people understand to have a specific meaning. Like
for example, when they say family values, I mean, that sounds pretty good, right? Like families are
good in values that support families. That all sounds good. But it's a signal to conservative
voters. You're supposed to be opposed to same sex marriage. You're supposed to be supposed to
abortion. More recently, you're supposed to be opposed to even fundamental just basic trans rights.
They don't say it outright. And this allows the right wing politicians to appeal to certain groups
of voters without alienating others. It allows them to avoid accountability. And it allows
something that Donald Trump actually did very well, which is you kind of take every position on issues.
And even if you don't overtly do it, you leave enough vagaries that anybody could sort of stumble
across some version of a position that they agree with you or at least don't overtly disagree.
Modern conservatism also exploits the public through policy. And this is maybe the most important
thing. Right wing conservative, whatever word you want to use for it, policy disproportionately
benefits the wealthy, the powerful and those with what we might call like standard or agent
identities in American society. And conservatives will argue lower taxes are good for everybody.
Increases economic growth, increases prosperity, rising tide lifts all boats. They'll say it with
regulation. Reducing regulation is good for everybody. Economic growth, prosperity, it's great.
The truth is it's a scam. Those very policies, they do particularly in the short term increase
profits for corporations and the wealthy, but they externalize the burden of the pollution
that is created or the low wages that are paid, which then we all have our taxes go to social
welfare programs to support people who rightly need those programs because the corporations are
paying low wages. They claim it's good for everybody. Their economic policy is good for
everybody, but it leads to cuts in social services or increased spending on social services,
higher health care costs, lower wages for workers. We all pay for it. We are getting
scammed by it. So modern conservatism is a scam that by scamming the public and exploiting the
public through all of the things I mentioned, disproportionately benefits the elites. They
love to say Democrats are all about this elitist cabal. That's that's all they care about.
It's actually conservatism that is doing that. Couple modern examples. We can look at how right
wingers sought to undermine the legitimate legitimacy of the 2020 presidential election.
There was no evidence of widespread voter fraud that impacted the results. They scammed their
supporters. They raised money. Trump did claiming we're going to use the money to flip the election.
He kept the money, used it to pay off campaign debt, total and complete scam.
We've seen these conspiracies promoted by conservative media outlets
and by politicians, by Trump himself. And that is the prototypical example of how conservatism
is used to make the public think a certain thing and then get them to take an action,
either going to the Capitol, donating money, whatever the case may be.
We have also seen, by the way, this very same rhetoric used in order to get the public to
support ideas that are seemingly completely antithetical to the values of the right.
For example, free speech for all, including for businesses until we no longer like the speech
and moderation rules that are being applied on Twitter or Facebook or whatever. And all of a
sudden freedom, liberty and low regulation goes out the window and it's we must force Facebook
to publish our COVID disinformation. We must force Twitter to publish the pictures of Hunter
Biden's genitalia. They abandoned those principles right away and the voters at the end of the day
are just getting scammed. They don't know up, down, left, right. They don't know what's going on.
Last thing on this, when you wonder what is the end game with any of these supposedly
conservative policy ideas, whether it's the immigration reform ideas, they have taxation,
whatever the case may be, understand that the end goal is to reinforce and perpetuate
the rich and corporations maintaining power and profitability. That is the big scam that they
claim their entire movement is a set of policies that helps everyone and it doesn't. And we've
talked before about how that is that is not completely missing from the Democratic Party,
but the degree to which it exists in the modern right wing movement is completely stunning.
It is a scam. Last week, we spoke about what it is about people who are victimized by scams
that keeps them being victimized and part of it is the cult aspect and part of it is psychological
factors. We looked at the people being scammed. Now we've looked at what the scam is and it would
be great if people would figure this out and stop falling for it. But it actually is a party that
depends on people continuing to fall for it.