A few days ago, Mamba, linear time sequence modelling with selective state spaces, appeared on
archive. It is causing some excitement, partly because it shows strong empirical results,
partly because it has an interesting design, and partly because Mamba is a great name.
In this video, I'll give a high level summary of the paper. To understand the motivation for this
work, it's helpful to go back in time to the distant memories of 2020, and in particular,
the Long Range Arena, a benchmark for efficient transformers. The starting premise was that
transformers do not scale very well to long sequence lengths, largely because of quadratic
self-attention complexity. Given the proliferation of efficient alternatives to transformers that
were emerging at the time, this work proposed a benchmark specifically focused on evaluating
model quality under long context scenarios. There were tasks like long list ops, where the model
is given an input consisting of a long list of nested operators, and needs to calculate an answer,
and fun tasks like pathfinder, where the model gets a flattened image that looks like this,
and needs to determine whether the two circles can be joined. This is a positive example because
they can. This is a negative example because they cannot. Broadly, they found that if you wanted to
maintain performance encapsulated here in this LRA score, it's quite hard to do much better than
the vanilla transformer. Independently, and a little earlier, a creative approach to tackling
the Long Range Dependency problem was introduced in this work on Legend Memory Units, in the context
of recurrent neural networks. As a refresher, Legend polynomials are these beautiful creatures.
You can construct them by making a sequence of polynomials that are orthogonal to each other.
By projecting values onto a basis of these polynomials, you can efficiently store a history
of the inputs to your system. That's the key idea in this funky looking equation.
You can reconstruct the input U by reassembling it from the components of the memory vector,
denoted here by M. This idea can then be baked into a layer where the memory block is implemented
with simple linear operations. Building on that idea, and others, Hippo, recurrent memory with
optimal polynomial projections, had the insight that we can phrase memory as a technical problem
of online function approximation, where a function is summarized by storing its optimal
coefficients in terms of some basis functions. Using this insight, the authors constructed a
simple model based on Legendre polynomials that worked well on tasks like permuted MNIST,
outperforming other sequence model-based baselines like LSTM and dilated RNN. This was
followed by the work, combining recurrent convolutional and continuous time models
with linear state space layers, which proposed a unifying framework for sequence modelling
based on a standard state space representation. This work showed how, starting from an implicit,
continuous time state space model, you could discretize to produce a system that can be
interpreted as a recurrent network with the benefit of efficient inference, or as a convolutional
model which benefits from parallelizable training. Unfortunately, a naive implementation of these
models requires a massive amount of memory. In fact, for reasonably sized models, such as when
the state dimension is 256, the linear state space layer uses orders of magnitude more memory than
comparably sized RNNs or CNNs. That brings us to the S4 model introduced in efficiently modelling
long sequences with structured state spaces. What we'd really like to be able to do is use the
convolutional interpretation we've just seen to efficiently train our state space model.
Now, if we want to train state space models using the convolutional representation, we can do a
little bit of unrolling and a little bit of vectorization to get this L-dimensional kernel,
where L is the sequence length. The scary part here is this A raised to the power of I term.
Harking back to your linear algebra classes, as soon as you see this, you may feel a strong
and appropriate urge to try to diagonalize A. The authors discuss diagonalization.
Unfortunately, it cannot be used directly for the hippo matrix due to numerical issues.
Specifically, it has entries exponentially large in the state size. However, we can address the
hippo matrix with an adjustment. The authors note that although the hippo matrix is not normal,
it can be decomposed as the sum of a normal and low rank matrix. Even this is still not useful
by itself. An additional three new techniques are needed. First, instead of computing the kernel
k-bar directly, they instead compute its spectrum, then determine k-bar by applying an inverse FFT.
Next, we use everyone's favorite low rank trick, the Woodbury identity. That lets us perform an
efficient matrix update. Third, it is shown that the diagonal matrix case is equivalent to the
computation of a Cauchy kernel, a well-studied problem with stable, near-linear algorithms.
All of this comes together in theorem three. It says that given any step size delta, computing
the state space model convolution filter k-bar can be reduced to four Cauchy multiplies,
requiring only big O of n plus l operations, ignoring logarithmic factors, and big O of
n plus l space, where again, l is the sequence length and n is the state size. Empirically,
the proposed S4 architecture does very well on the long-range arena, even doing well on the path
x task, where the model must determine if two points are connected on a fairly large image.
This task is not too hard when the input is arranged as an image, but it's pretty difficult
when it's a flattened sequence, as evidenced by the fact that many other models fail on this task.
If you'd like to gain some intuition for how S4 works, I highly recommend the annotated S4
by Sasha Rush and Sid Karamchetti, just as with the legendary annotated transformer blog post
back in 2018. The annotated S4 takes you step-by-step through the paper and provides snippets of
code that implement the mathematics. It also includes nice visualizations to help you build
intuition for how state-space models work. All of this brings us back to Mamba. This work builds
on the state-space model approach with a few key contributions. First, a selection mechanism. Since
previous state-space models lack the ability to efficiently select data in an input-dependent
manner, they design a simple selection mechanism by parameterizing the state-space model parameters
based on the input. Unfortunately, this change makes it hard for us to use the efficient convolutional
trick we saw in S4, so the second contribution is a hardware-aware algorithm that computes the
model recurrently with a scan instead of convolution. This leads to an implementation that is faster
than previous methods, both in theory, scaling linearly in sequence length compared to pseudo-linear
for all convolution-based SSMs and on modern hardware, up to three times faster on A100 GPUs.
Spicy. The third contribution is to simplify prior deep-sequence model architectures by
combining the design of prior state-space model architectures with the MLP block of transformers
into a single block, leading to a simple and homogenous architecture design called Mamba
that incorporates selective state-spaces. By building on a state-space model foundation,
Mamba is related to many previous state-space model architectures. In addition to the models we
met earlier, there is Linear Attention, which can be viewed as a degenerate linear SSM, the gloriously
named Hungry Hungry Hippos or H3, Hyena, RhettNet, and RWKV. The core motivation behind Mamba is to
use selection as a means of compression. The authors point out that you can view various
sequence models as making different trade-offs when tackling a fundamental problem of sequence
modeling, i.e. compressing context into a smaller state. At one extreme, we have Attention, which
is both effective and inefficient because it explicitly does not compress context at all.
At the other extreme, recurrent models are efficient because they have a finite state,
but their effectiveness is limited by how well this state has compressed the context. To explore
this trade-off, the authors focus on two synthetic tasks. One previously well-studied task is copying.
The job of the model is to copy color sequences in the input into the output, delayed by some
constant offset. Standard convolutional models with fixed kernels can solve this without any
problem. The first of the harder tasks they consider is selective copying. This time, we have
random spaces symbolized by the white blocks in between the input sequence elements. To successfully
copy the color outputs to the output while ignoring the white blocks, we need a mechanism that behaves
differently at different inputs. The second task they look at is induction heads. Here,
in order to predict the appropriate color at the question mark block, the model needs to be able
to perform retrieval back over the input sequence based on the context provided by the black square,
in order to predict that blue is the next color in the sequence. To build a model capable of solving
these tasks, the models start from the S4 state space model, which uses parameters a, b, c, and
delta, which don't depend on the input sequence. Now, for the proposed algorithm, to allow the model
to behave differently on different inputs, b, c, and delta are altered to be time-varying. They now
depend on the input sequence. This gives the model more power, but means we can no longer use the
efficient S4 convolution trick. To get around this, the authors develop a selective scan based on
hardware-aware state expansion. In effect, the two big challenges to be tackled once we give up on
convolution are the sequential nature of recurrence and the large memory usage. There are three
techniques that come into play, kernel fusion, parallel scan, and recomputation. A key idea for
getting around the sequential processing problem comes from simplified state space layers for
sequence modeling, or S5, which highlighted the benefits of using parallel scans to maintain
efficiency while avoiding the use of convolutional tricks used in S4. Mamba uses this parallel scan
idea in combination with efficient use of memory. In particular, instead of preparing the scan input
in GPU high bandwidth memory, they load the state space model parameters directly from the slow high
bandwidth memory to fast SRAM, where they perform the discretization and recurrence. Then they write
the final results back to high bandwidth memory. Last, recomputation is used to reduce the memory
requirements. This allows them to avoid saving the intermediate states, which are necessary for back
propagation. Putting this all together, here is the selective state space model with hardware-aware
state expansion. The first thing we see is that BT, delta T, and CT all depend on the input
XT via the selection mechanism. The second thing we see is that the parameters are loaded into fast
GPU SRAM, indicated in this diagram by the color orange, where the update is performed. Then the
output is ultimately stored back into GPU high bandwidth memory, shown in green. Next, we come to
the simplified state space model architecture. Here, the authors combine the Hungry Hungry Hippos
block with a gated MLP block to produce their Mamba block. The shapes here indicate that the
dimensionality is expanded inside the block. This block is repeated and interleaved with standard
normalization and residual connections to form the Mamba architecture. I'll mention a few other
model details. The authors note that most prior state space models use complex numbers in their
state, but it has been empirically observed that completely real valued state space models seem
to work fine, and possibly even better, in some settings. So, they use real values as the default,
which work well for all but one of their tasks. Next, we come to the empirical evaluation. First,
we have the synthetic tasks described earlier. First, as a bit of notation, the authors abbreviate
selective state space models as S6 models, because they are S4 models with a selection mechanism,
and computed with a scan. That's a lot of S's. On the selective copying task, S6 works well with
every architecture, but S4 and Hyena work comparatively poorly. On the induction heads task,
Mamba, shown in brown, appears up here at the top, where we see it succeeds on test sequence lengths
of up to a million tokens, which is 4,000 times longer than it saw during training,
while none of the other methods compared to generalize to beyond twice their training length.
Next, we have experiments on language modelling, which follow the training recipe described in
the GBT3 work, and train on the pile dataset. Here, the metric on the y-axis is perplexity,
so lower is better. We can see that across a sequence length of 2,048, and a sequence length
of 8,192, that Mamba, shown in purple, outperforms the other baselines, and matches Transformer++,
which is highlighted in orange, and represents the strongest Transformer recipe that the authors
know of, based on the palm and llama architectures. That means rotary embeddings, swigloo MLPs,
rmsnorm instead of leonorm, no linear bias, and higher learning rates. On zero shot downstream
evaluations, there are lots of comparisons, generally we see Mamba achieving an average
of baselines at twice the model size. Next, there are studies on DNA modelling. On human genome
data, Mamba, shown in orange, scales better than Hyena DNA, shown in blue, and Transformer++,
shown in red, when you scale up the number of parameters. It also scales better than Hyena DNA,
when you scale up the sequence length. Mamba models also do well relative to a Hyena DNA baseline,
when fine tuning for a species DNA classification task. Here, the metric on the y-axis is accuracy,
so higher is better, with longer sequences as we move to the right along the x-axis.
We see the orange and green Mamba curves rising. I won't go through them in detail,
but there are other experiments showing that Mamba mostly works well on audio modelling and
generation. However, there is one ablation in the appendix, identifying a case when a naive
application of Mamba with the selection mechanism seems to hurt performance. Here,
lower is better, and the orange line denotes the default Mamba configuration. The authors suggest
that this may be a case where audio waveforms actually benefit from linear time-invariant
models which have a matching inductive bias. Next, we have speed and memory benchmarks.
The authors provide an implementation of the scan operation that is pretty fast.
They compare the scan versus convolution and attention on an A100 GPU. Here, the y-axis measures
time, so lower is better. We see the red line representing their implementation is considerably
below the other mechanisms at longer sequence lengths. In terms of inference throughput,
where higher is better, we find that Mamba, shown in blue and green, can achieve five times higher
throughput than Transformers, benefiting from its recurrent nature. In terms of limitations,
the authors highlight that there is no free lunch on the continuous discrete spectrum.
The selection mechanism overcomes the weaknesses of prior state space models on discrete modalities
such as text and DNA, but this can impede their performance on data that linear time-invariant
state space models excel on, which we saw with the audio ablation. They also note that the empirical
evaluation is limited to small model sizes, below the threshold of most strong open-source
LLMs. Therefore, it remains to assess whether Mamba still compares favourably at larger sizes.
That's it, we've reached the end. If you'd like to try it out, the authors have released code on GitHub.