Imagine you have a weighted coin, so the probability of flipping heads it might not
be 50-50 exactly, it could be 20%, or maybe 90%, or 0%, or 31.41592%.
The point is that you just don't know.
But imagine that you flip this coin ten different times, and seven of those times it comes up
heads.
Do you think that the underlying weight of this coin is such that each flip has a 70%
chance of coming up heads?
If I were to ask you, hey, what's the probability that the true probability of flipping heads
is 0.7, what would you say?
This is a pretty weird question, and for two reasons.
First of all, it's asking about a probability of a probability, as in the value we don't
know is itself some kind of long-run frequency for a random event, which frankly is hard
to think about.
But the more pressing weirdness comes from asking about probabilities in the setting
of continuous values.
Let's give this unknown probability of flipping heads some kind of name, like h.
Keep in mind that h could be any real number from 0 up to 1, ranging from a coin that always
flips tails, up to one that always flips heads, and everything in between.
So if I ask, hey, what's the probability that h is precisely 0.7, as opposed to say
0.7000001, or any other nearby value, well there's going to be a strong possibility for
paradox if we're not careful.
It feels like no matter how small the answer to this question, it just wouldn't be small
enough.
If every specific value within some range, all uncountably infinitely many of them, has
a non-zero probability, well even if that probability was minuscule, adding them all
up to get the total probability of any one of these values will blow up to infinity.
On the other hand though, if all of these probabilities are 0, aside from the fact that
that now gives you no useful information about the coin, the total sum of those probabilities
would be 0 when it should be 1.
After all, this weight of the coin h is something, so the probability of it being any one of
these values should add up to 1.
So if these values can't all be non-zero, and they can't all be 0, what do you do?
Where we're going with this, by the way, is that I'd like to talk about the very practical
question of using data to create meaningful answers to these sorts of probabilities of
probabilities questions.
But for this video, let's take a moment to appreciate how to work with probabilities
over continuous values and resolve this apparent paradox.
The key is not to focus on individual values, but ranges of values.
For example, we might make these buckets to represent the probability that h is between
say 0.8 and 0.85.
Also and this is more important than it might seem, rather than thinking of the height of
each of these bars as representing the probability, think of the area of each one as representing
that probability.
Where exactly those areas come from is something that we'll answer later.
For right now, just know that, in principle, there's some answer to the probability of
h sitting inside one of these ranges.
Our task right now is to take the answers to these very coarse-grained questions, and
to get a more exact understanding of the distribution at the level of each individual input.
The natural thing to do would be to consider finer and finer buckets, and when you do, the
smaller probability of falling into any one of them is accounted for in the thinner width
of each of these bars, while the heights are going to stay roughly the same.
That's important because it means that as you take this process to the limit, you approach
some kind of smooth curve.
So even though all of the individual probabilities of falling into any one particular bucket
will approach zero, the overall shape of the distribution is preserved and even refined
in this limit.
If on the other hand we had let the heights of the bars represent probabilities, everything
would have gone to zero.
So in the limit, we would have just had a flat line giving no information about the overall
shape of the distribution.
So wonderful, letting area represent probability helps solve this problem.
But let me ask you, if the y-axis no longer represents probability, what exactly are the
units here?
Since probability sits in the area of these bars, or width times height, the height represents
a kind of probability per unit in the x direction, what's known in the business as a probability
density.
The other thing to keep in mind is that the total area of all these bars has to equal
one at every level of the process.
That's something that has to be true for any valid probability distribution.
The idea of probability density is actually really clever when you step back to think
about it, as you take things to the limit.
Even if there's all sorts of paradoxes associated with assigning a probability to each of these
uncountably infinitely many values of h between zero and one, there's no problem if we associate
a probability density to each one of them, giving what's known as a probability density
function, or PDF for short.
Any time you see a PDF in the wild, the way to interpret it is that the probability of
your random variable lying between two values equals the area under this curve between those
values.
So for example, what's the probability of getting any one very specific number, like
0.7?
Well, the area of an infinitely thin slice is zero, so it's zero.
What's the probability of all of them put together?
Well, the area under the full curve is one.
You see, paradox sidestepped.
And the way that it's been sidestepped is a bit subtle.
In normal finite settings, like rolling a die or drawing a card, the probability that
a random value falls into a given collection of possibilities is simply the sum of the
probabilities of being any one of them.
This feels very intuitive, it's even true in a countably infinite context, but to deal
with the continuum, the rules themselves have shifted.
The probability of falling into a range of values is no longer the sum of the probabilities
of each individual value.
Instead, probabilities associated with ranges are the fundamental primitive objects, and
the only sense in which it's meaningful to talk about an individual value here is to
think of it as a range of width zero.
If the idea of the rules changing between a finite setting and a continuous one feels
unsettling, well, you'll be happy to know that mathematicians are way ahead of you.
There's a field of math called measure theory, which helps to unite these two settings and
make rigorous the idea of associating numbers like probabilities to various subsets of all
possibilities in a way that combines and distributes nicely.
For example, let's say you're in a setting where you have a random number that equals
zero with 50% probability, and the rest of the time it's some positive number according
to a distribution that looks like half of a bell curve.
This is an awkward middle ground between a finite context, where a single value has
a nonzero probability, and a continuous one, where probabilities are found according to
areas under the appropriate density function.
This is the sort of thing that measure theory handles very smoothly.
I mentioned this mainly for the especially curious viewer, and you can find more reading
material in the description.
It's a pretty common rule of thumb that if you find yourself using a sum in a discrete
context, then use an integral in the continuous context, which is the tool from calculus that
we use to find areas under curves.
In fact, you could argue this video would be way shorter if I just said that at the
front and called it good.
For my part, though, I always found it a little unsatisfying to do this blindly without thinking
through what it really means.
And in fact, if you really dig into the theoretical underpinnings of integrals, what you'd find
is that in addition to the way that it's defined in a typical intro calculus class,
there is a separate, more powerful definition that's based on measure theory, this formal
foundation of probability.
If I look back to when I first learned probability, I definitely remember grappling with this
weird idea that in continuous settings, like random variables that are real numbers or
throwing a dart at a dartboard, you have a bunch of outcomes that are possible, and yet
each one has a probability of zero, and somehow altogether they have a probability of one.
Now, one step of coming to terms with this is to realize that possibility is better tied
to probability density than probability, but just swapping out sums of one for integrals
of the others never quite scratched the itch for me.
I remember that it only really clicked when I realized that the rules for combining probabilities
of different sets were not quite what I thought they were, and there was simply a different
axiom system underlying it all.
But anyway, steering away from the theory somewhere back in the loose direction of application,
look back to our original question about the coin with an unknown weight.
What we've learned here is that the right question to ask is, what's the probability
density function that describes this value h after seeing the outcomes of a few tosses?
If you can find that PDF, you can use it to answer questions like, what's the probability
that the true probability of flipping heads falls between 0.6 and 0.8?
To find that PDF, join me in the next part.