All right. So, math and cats. Enough said, right? A little bit first sight.
So, just kidding. Freya is an independent game developer and educator, and today she's
going to talk about a topic that to some is the stuff of nightmares and to others, like
myself, is perhaps a little bit more the stuff of dreams and all the squiggly lines in between.
So in her talk, she's going to hopefully inspire you all to consider the math underlying
our games a little bit more magical. Thank you.
Okay. Hello, everyone, to probably the most technical talk. I'm going to teach you all
about set theory and quaternions. This talk is called, why can't you multiply vectors?
And so, I've been doing a lot of things within game development and math for a long time
now. I started out as an environment artist, and then I moved into level design, and then
I eventually learned programming, and I got really excited about that, and then I got
into math, like, very heavily the past, like, two years or so. And now I've sort of, like,
dived so deep into math that sometimes the stuff that I talk about, game developers
are like, oh, this just seems like useless abstract nonsense. Like, why are you even
doing this? Like, I just want to make a game. I just want to copy-paste my math from the
internet and just, like, paste it into my game so that it works. I don't care about
the underlying stuff. But today I want to talk about that underlying stuff anyway, so you're
going to have to suffer through that. So, there's a bit of a schism sometimes between math and
programming. So, I sent this tweet at some point on 9-11 of all days, so this is my personal
9-11, because this started a war between programmers and math people, which was really
weird, but, like, all the math people were like, what are those for loops? That makes
no sense. Like, all of these symbols that look so complicated and weird, and then you had all of
these programmers that were like, what are those weird symbols? Like, there's no context for
this. There's nothing describing what that does. You just have to know what that does, right? But
so all I really wanted to do was kind of, like, draw this, like, simple analogy for people who
might not know that much math to just be like, okay, so these summation symbols is just adding
things up in a for loop, and the capital pi is just a product. You're just multiplying
things together. So, those interesting, because it kind of illuminated to me that there's this
big schism, or like, big divide, that I kind of want to merge, and I see that as sort of my job
in a way of trying to bridge that gap. A little bit about me. I probably don't care that much.
Co-founder of the studio called Neat Corp, made a game called Budget Cuts and Budget Cuts 2,
where a studio of like, seven, very awkward size, made some plugins for Unity, one called Shader Forge,
and one called Shapes. I want to say shader, editor, and the other one is a vector graphics
plugin that I'm also working on a spline plugin right now that is not released yet.
I also make YouTube videos, so I made some videos about tech art, math, and tool development,
mostly within Unity, and then I also made some YouTube videos about Bezia curves and splines.
All right. So, I'm a tech artist. That's kind of the center of what I do. It's kind of the
intersection of art, and programming, and math kind of comes in there to do all of these kinds of
weird funky, techy visual solutions to problems in games. So, a lot of the stuff I do is just
like trying to work out things like, how do you render lines in a way that looks nice?
Because, you know, you have like a naive implementation, might look like garbage,
but if you spend some time thinking about it, you can make something that looks much, much prettier.
And so, a lot of the work I'm doing as of late has to do with splines. This is an excerpt from my
video. It's just a lot of splines. I've just had splines in my head for the past three years,
and I can't get them out, and so here I am. Recently, I've been getting into like quaternionic
splines, or just like splines in quaternion space to interpolate orientations,
and some torsion visualizations. I don't know. I have a bunch of things related to this that I do.
That's a dodecahedron. Anyway, so, in this talk, we're going to explore, why can't you multiply
vectors? And I think, as with any other talk, I think you should always start on the second slide
with some common criticisms of the title of the talk. And so, some common criticisms might be,
yes, you can. It's called a dot product. Like, what are you talking about? Or you might say,
well, yes, you can. It's called a cross product. Like, why do you mean you can't multiply vectors?
Or you might say, what do you mean? I multiply vectors all the time. This could be early signs
that you might be a shader programmer, and no, you're actually not really multiplying vectors.
You're going to find out why. So, the anatomy of a vector, just to go through what we're actually
talking about. We usually write it in bold letters, and that's a vector v, and it has three components
if it's a 3D vector. Realizing I'm forgetting to breathe, because I have so much to talk about.
So, we have three components, x component, the y component, and the z component, usually written
in parenthesis, right? And you can also write it as a column matrix if you want to, which can be
useful sometimes, because you can write longer lines for each component. It's kind of useful.
And this kind of presumes a basis, as in the basis vectors of our coordinate system, right?
We have an x-axis, we have a y-axis, and a z-axis, and they're all orthogonal to each other,
and they have a length of one. So, they're orthonormal, is what we call it in the industry.
All right. So, products. We obviously know about the dot product. Everybody's heard about that,
and it's some kind of multiplication, right? You have your vector a, your vector b, and then you
write little dot in between, and then the dot product is basically multiplying each of the
components, and then adding them all up into a single scalar value. So, it's sometimes called
a scalar product. You can also write it using these summation notations. So, it's like dimension
independent. So, if you want to do the dot product in any dimension, you can use that formula.
I hope it's readable and not too small. And then we have the cross products. The cross products
does not return a scalar, it returns a vector. So, the cross products, we have this kind of
complicated formula. We've just taken out very specific components for each of the x, y, and z
components of the final output vector. That's the cross products. And then we have the 2D
cross products, which is illegal. Don't tell your math teacher that you've been using a 2D cross
product, because it doesn't really exist, but it's a very useful thing in games to have. And
that's basically a cross product where you just set z to zero, and then whatever is left is your
2D cross product. It's also sometimes known as the perpendicular dot product, or the exterior
product, or the determinant, or the wedge product, or the anti-symmetric product. It has many names.
It's annoying. And then finally, we have the Hadamard product, which is the shader programmer
product, where you just say, well, just multiply the components. Like, just do that. Like, why not?
Just take every component, multiply them together, that's your new vector. So, that's a component-wise
product. Okay. So, we have the dot product, we have the cross product, and we have the Hadamard
product. But what about the product? Like, just smash them together. No goddamn symbols in between,
just a canonical product, right? Because usually, you don't write anything in between. If you want
to write 5x, you don't have to write a symbol there. In math, you just have no symbol, because
multiplication is kind of the canonical main operation, right? So, I think a lot of people,
me included a few years ago, I was just like, just do it component-wise. Why are you overthinking
this? Like, if you multiply a vector by a scalar, like a vector, like two times a vector A, you just
multiply each component by two, right? So, that's component-wise. If you divide it by two, that's
also component-wise. If you add two vectors, that's also component-wise. We add the x-axis together,
we add the y-components together, and the z-components together, also component-wise.
Subtraction works exactly the same way. So, why would multiply not just be the Hadamard product?
You just take each component and multiply them together, right? Just don't worry about it. Just
go ham. Just multiply all of your vectors and don't care about the rest. It's going to be fine.
But it's not that simple, unfortunately. So, I'm going to take you all back to elementary school.
We're going to talk about the natural numbers. So, the integers starting from zero and up,
so all of the positive integers and usually zero as well. That's when you count things.
So, we're going to count snail cats. So, here's a snail cat. So, let's say you have two snail cats,
and then you add three snail cats. How many do we get? We get five snail cats. Isn't that amazing?
So, two, three, and five are all natural numbers. We can count items using natural numbers, right?
So, let's try multiplying. So, two snail cats multiplied by three snail cats is six snail cats.
Great. That's perfectly fine. Just one more. So, we have two snail cats, minus three snail cats,
and then we get... Well, that's not actually a natural number anymore, right? Like, two minus three.
Now, we get something negative, and that's not within the realm of natural numbers. Like, negative
is not a natural number, right? And so, in a very technical sense in math, we usually say that
natural numbers are closed under addition and multiplication, but it's not closed under subtraction,
because it's possible to leave the realm of natural numbers if you subtract, right? Because two minus
three, not a natural number. Okay. So, we can talk about numbers of different kinds, right?
Natural numbers, we can add them, but it's closed under addition. We get a natural number if we
add two natural numbers, same with multiplication, but not subtraction, because then we need the
integers. The integers, they have these technical symbols, the blackboard bold. So, natural numbers
are n, integers are z, for some German reasons, I think. I don't know what it is. So, then we
need integers, and that includes the negative numbers, right? The negative integers. Okay. So,
integers are closed... Right. So, subtraction of natural numbers gives you integers.
Integers are closed under addition, multiplication, and subtraction, but not under division, right?
Because if you do one divided by three, that's not an integer. Again, we've left the realm of
integers, and we've gone into the realm of rational numbers. So, rational numbers is an integer
divided by another integer. So, with division, with natural numbers and integers, we get a
rational number. We can also do exponentiation. So, if you take like a natural number, like two
to the power of three, that is also a natural number. So, we stay with the natural numbers
there. So, it's also closed under exponentiation. But integers are... Again, if you do integers,
and you do powers on those, so, like three to the power of negative one would also give you a
rational number. All right. Rational numbers, closed under addition, multiplication, subtraction,
division, you get a rational number out of that. You don't change the kind of number.
Exponentiation gets a little bit more complicated. Because you could do to the power of 0.5,
which is a square root, because 0.5 is just one over two. And then we need the real numbers.
So, the square root of five can't be expressed as an integer divided by an integer. But the
real numbers are closed under all of these four operations. But then we might want to go to the
next step. Like, what about exponentiation? And here's where we enter complex numbers. Because
now it's getting a little bit weird here. Because that's just an entirely different type. Because
a real number is just all the usual numbers we're familiar with. But the complex numbers can express
things like the square root of negative five. In real numbers, we usually say that you just
can't do the square root of a real number. But with complex numbers, we have a way to express that.
And complex numbers are algebraically... Sorry. So, complex numbers. How many of you
know what complex numbers are? Raise your hand. Quite a few. Okay. So, I can sort of speed around
this one. Okay. So, let's say we have a thing called i. And if you square i, you get negative one.
It's just an algebraic symbol. It's a variable like any other. But the only thing we know about
it, we don't know its contents or its value. The only thing we know is that it squares to negative
one. In other words, if you multiply it by itself, we get negative one. And this is called the imaginary
unit. And this is just axiomatically true. Which is math speak for, because I told you so, it is true.
And we just have to accept that, right? Okay. So, how do we do math with this? Well, if we have three
i times two i, that would be six i squared. And since i squared is negative one, this is equal,
because we can apply this rule of i squared equals negative one, then this becomes negative six.
Okay. Another example, two i times four i minus three. We just distribute that. And then we get
eight i squared minus six i. Again, i squared is negative one. So, we get negative eight minus six i.
And we can sort of think of these numbers as having two parts to them. The first part here is the real
number. This is just a regularized number that we use all the time. And then we have a coefficient
of i. So, this is called the imaginary part. And you can kind of divide these up into these two
separate categories. And that's what's called a complex number. So, that's when you have a
regular number, a real number, and then some coefficient of i.
Okay. So, let's say we have a complex number z. Then we can interpret it similar to a vector,
because a vector also has two parts, right? If you have a 2D vector, you have an x component
and a y component. Similarly, we can write complex numbers the way we write vectors, just in
parentheses, right? Where we have the real part and the imaginary part. And now, the basis is just
the value one and i. Because those are the things we multiply each of the components by
in order to get the final results, right? So, you can kind of see the similarity between complex
numbers and vectors. Like, they both have two components, well, for 2D vectors. And so, you
can define a coordinate space using vectors. You have an x-axis and a y-axis. You can also just
do the same with imaginary units. So, you can have a real axis for the real numbers and a vertical
axis that's the imaginary axis. And then, for writing coordinates, we just do exactly the same
thing we do for vectors. So, for 2D vectors, we have maybe this coordinate would be one and two.
So, one on the x-axis, two on the y-axis. Can do the same for the complex numbers. So, this is
called a complex plane. And it's just the same. It's just one and two. It's just that we're using
a different basis. The cool thing about complex numbers is that we can actually just write them
as a formula, like the way we did before, just one plus two i. That's what this represents, right?
And so, this is really useful. What's useful about this one is that we can do algebra with this.
We can, if we have this formula, we can just add them together or multiply them and just see what
happens, right? And so, if we wanted to find out, like, okay, what happens when you multiply two
vectors? Well, if complex numbers are vector-like, we can figure out what happens when you multiply
two complex numbers. And maybe that's going to give us, like, some answers along the way for how to
multiply vectors together. So, we can just try to go through that process. So, like, let's say we have
two complex numbers, a complex number a and b. We multiply those together. So, we just write them
out as equations. And as usual, we just distribute or, like, expand the whole thing, and then we
might notice that, oh, this part has two i's in it, right? So, it's i squared, which means that it's
equal to negative one. So, we multiply that whole thing by negative one. And so, now, we can see
that this part, they share a common factor of i, so we can factor that out. And now, we get a complex
number in the end. So, we have two complex numbers. We multiply them together, just regular
multiplying, no dot products or cross products or anything. We're just multiplying them together.
And in the end, we get another complex number, because we can express this as a coefficient of
just a real number and a coefficient of i. So, what we can say is, again, complex numbers are
closed under multiplication, because we give two complex numbers and we get a complex numbers out
of it. So, if you want to implement this in code, like, this is how you would write that. The actual
symbol of i is never in your code. It's just completely not there. The i is only there to, like,
help us define the algebraic operations that we do using this. And so, we had our formula here,
right? So, we're calculating some sort of real part from two complex numbers. And then, we get
the real part here. And then, we calculate the imaginary part. We get the imaginary part. And
then, we'll return a complex number. So, we only ever store the coefficients. We don't ever store,
like, the weird i symbol, right? So, the reason we can do this is because it's closed under
multiplication. That's why it returns a complex number. Okay. So, what does this look like? Because
now, if we interpret this as a vector, we should be able to visualize this, because we can interpret
complex numbers as 2D vectors. And this is what it would look like. So, here we have two vectors,
the red one and the blue one. And we multiply them as complex numbers in the complex plane.
And the green vector is the result. And you might be able to tell that it has something to do with,
like, sort of adding the angles up, right? It's kind of like taking the angle of one of the vectors,
adding it to the other angle. And when it's normalized, you can see that the vectors
have the same length. Like, the green one doesn't get longer or shorter than the red one or the blue
one. And so, this one, while it's not a vector multiplication, it's still complex number
multiplication, we might be able to apply some of the same strategies for figuring out, like,
what happens when you multiply vectors? Okay. So, now, we figured out that complex numbers
are closed under multiplication. And, in fact, they are closed under all of these operations.
And it's the only, I think it's called a complete algebra. I think it's actually the only complete
algebra within math, which I think is kind of cool, that it's closed under all of these operations.
All right. But what we really want to figure out is vectors, right? That was the whole point
of this talk. Like, why can't we multiply vectors? Like, this should be possible. I really want to
try to do it, you know? So, if we go back to this, we could write our complex numbers as a real part
plus an imaginary part times i. So, why can't we do that with vectors? We have an x component,
we multiply it by a symbol representing our x axis, and then we add the y component multiplied by
a symbol representing the y axis. So, now, if we use this, again, we can do algebra with this,
right? Like, now we can actually just do it ourselves. Instead of just listening to
our math teacher or me, you can just, like, actually do it yourself, right?
So, now we have another way of writing vectors. In other words, like this, if we have a 3D vector,
we just take each of the components and multiply them by the symbol representing
each of the three basis vectors of our coordinate system. Okay. So, if we have two vectors, A and B,
these are 3D vectors, we can write them like this. So, these, again, we have the components,
we have the axes, and then we can do some algebra with this. So, let's do something simple, like,
multiplying a scalar by a vector, just a number times a vector. Well, we have a number s, we
multiply that by our vector, and that just distributes to all the terms in there, and we
can see that that's a component-wise multiplication, which is what we would expect, right? Because we've
been told that that's component-wise. And it seems to be, right? All right. Let's try one more. So,
addition. So, we want to add these two vectors together, and we can remove the parentheses,
because they're useless. And then we can find some common factors here. There's a common factor of
the x-axis. Again, the red x is just referring to the abstract concept of the x-axis. And so,
we just factor out those axes, and we end up with this. And now, again, we have a clean, like,
factor of x, y, and z separately. And so, we can say that addition is component-wise, which is what
we were told before, too. So, I guess they were right. So, that's component-wise. Fine. And if we
do this with all of these operations, we can find that both addition and subtraction is component-wise.
But we haven't multiplied two separate vectors yet, right? We've only done a scalar times the
vector, but not a vector times a vector. And so, what's that going to be? Like, are we going to
stay within the realm of 3D vectors? Like, kind of like the cross product. The cross product,
you know, has a stay in there, right? Or maybe we're kind of like the dot product, where we just
get a real number out of it, instead of a vector, right? Okay. So, let's find out. We have the tools,
right? We can just have our two vectors, a and b, multiplying them together. No goddamn symbols
in between. Just a pure multiplication. We write it out. This is the equation we just have to solve
for, right? Like a straight-up multiplication. There's a lot of terms here, because you need to
multiply these together. And you get this, which is ax, bx, xx, which is a little bit abstract.
We don't quite know what that is yet. And then we just keep on doing this. And we end up with
a lot of terms. And so, there we go. There we have it. So, this is what happens when you multiply
two vectors, I guess. But now we have a little bit of a problem. Like, it's like, this is not a
vector anymore. Like, we can't write this as a factor of x plus a factor of y plus a factor of z.
Like, this is just a pile of nonsense, right? And so, we can see that vectors are just not
closed under multiplication. We don't get a vector out of this, it seems. And so, that's why you can't
multiply vectors. And so, thanks for coming to my talk. I hope this was useful. And so, obviously,
that doesn't feel enough, right? Like, okay, we found out that it had this weird solution,
but like, but what is it? Like, I need to find out. Like, we have to solve this. We haven't
solved it yet. Like, it obviously gave us some sort of algebraic structure, and we need to investigate
this and actually, like, decode this whole thing, because there has to be answers in there, right?
Like, I'm willing to go to the ends of the earth to just, like, approach this whole problem and
just figure out everything. And maybe we need to take a little bit of a leap of faith as a treat.
And so, we're going to ask an oracle, a divine being of incomprehensible wisdom.
Oh, great oracle, Salad. His name is Salad. We made a feeble attempt at multiplying vectors,
and we seem to have reached an impasse. Can you illuminate us? The divine being contemplates for
a second and says, I see. A tricky conundrum indeed, but fear not. The answers you seek are
closer than you think. Don't worry. You are safe now, my child. I bestow upon you a key to
understanding. Venture forth, and the answers you seek will be revealed to you. Now, I must nap.
Leave me be. And the divine being turns into a non-Euclidean manifold.
Okay. So, this is some sort of divine axiomatic truth we were given.
And so, what does this say? So, it's a vector. It's in bold. So, if you multiply a vector by
itself, in other words, square it, you get the length squared. Like, the length of that vector
multiplied by itself. But this is not the full answer, right? This is just what happens when
you multiply a vector by itself, but we want to know what happens when you multiply two arbitrary
vectors. Okay. But let's experiment with this. So, let's say we have a vector with the values
one, two, and three, and we want to square this. In other words, multiply it by itself.
According to our divine axiom, it is the length squared. And the length, we can just use the
Pythagorean theorem, right? We've learned that in school. And then we square that. The square root
and the square cancel out. And so, we're left with one squared plus two squared plus three squared.
And we get 14. Okay. So, if we square a vector, we get just a real number. And in this case,
it's 14. Okay. So, let's explore this some more. So, what about our basis vectors? Because we have
an x-axis, a y-axis, and a z-axis. They all have a length of one, right? So, what happens when
you multiply those two together? Well, following our axiom, that should be equal to the length
squared, which is just one squared, right? And so, that's just one. So, if you take our x-axis
and multiply it by the x-axis, we get one out of that. And all of a sudden, we've gotten one key
to the solution here. Because all of these terms that are crossed out, they just evaluate to one.
So, those three terms are just multiplied by one, right? Okay. So, now we've started to unravel
this a little bit. So, now we can separate out those terms. We have, like, that's just a real
number, because those are no longer multiplied by a vector, right? All right. But we still have a
bit of a mess on the lower part. Like, what the heck is yz and xz and yx? That's still nonsense
to us, right? There's actually one more thing that our divine axiomatic rule gives us. So,
if you consider the basis vectors, again, mutually orthogonal, they have a length of one,
if you consider the diagonal between x and y, just x plus y gives you this white vector,
right? And we know that the length of that one is a square root of two, because we can use the
Pythagorean theorem for that, right? And so, then we can actually make use of our axiom to
find out some more about this, because we can plug in the length that is the square root of two.
So, if we take our vector, the white vector is just x plus y, and we square that, we should get
something that is the square root of two squared. So, the left-hand side, we can expand. The right
hand side, we can just cancel out the square root. And so, we get the expanded form of xx plus xy
plus yx plus yy, and that's equal to two. All right, but we know that x times x is one, and y
times y is one, right? We already figured that out. So, now we have this. We can subtract two
from both sides. So, we end up with xy plus yx equals zero. And if we subtract yx from both sides,
we get this. And this might seem kind of innocent. Like, okay, sure. Like, we have xy equals negative
yx. So, the components are swapped and negated. But it means that they're equal. So, we can swap
components at will, because if they're basis vectors, then we can do this. Okay, so, going back
to our equation here, we can see that in the top one, we have yz on the first term, but then we have
zy on the other one. So, what we can do is that we can swap these two terms and then negate that term.
Because we now have this rule of xy equals negative yx. So, we swap them, and now we have
subtraction symbols there instead of addition. And then we can factor those out.
Do any of you recognize these? Do these formulas seem familiar? Like, something seems to have kind
of jumped out at us, right? Like, this is the dot product. And we never set out to define the dot
product. We just followed the divine command we were given of, like, the square of a vector is the
magnitude squared. And somehow we got the dot product out of it as a complete, like, side effect.
And this is the cross product. The cross product somehow also jumped out of us. So, we just somehow
invented both the dot product and the cross product without ever intending to do so. We just
wanted to know what happens when you multiply two vectors, right? And so, everything stems from this
one rule. But we still have a mystery of, like, what the heck are these, anyway? Like, yz, zx, xy
are just kind of confusing constructs. We know nothing about them, right? So, let's explore
those a little further and see what happens with those. So, for example, maybe we can try seeing
what happens if we square them. We take xy squared. That equals xy, xy. And we know that we can swap
two of these and negate, and that's going to be the same thing. So, if we swap the middle two
components, we get negative xxyy. We know what xx is. We know what yy is, right? So, we get negative
one times one. So, we know that that's equal to negative one. So, we have a thing that we can
square that gives us a negative one. That's the imaginary unit. We didn't set out to invent the
imaginary unit either. This is all just still stemming from that one axiomatic rule. And this
actually applies to the other combinations as well of zx and yz. And so, if you mash them together
like this, all of that equals negative one. And you might have seen this in a different form before.
So, i squared equals j squared equals k squared equals ijk equals negative one is the definition
of quaternions. That's the way quaternions are defined right now. And so, what seems to have
happened is that when we multiply two vectors together, two 3D vectors together, we get a
quaternion which is written with an h for Hamilton. And so, that's kind of weird, isn't it?
And so, this thing that we have here has a basis of one, yz, zx and xy. And that has the exact
algebraic behavior of quaternions. And each component, obviously, it's a factor of each of
these. So, it's a multiple of each of those bases. And so, that's our quaternions. And so,
what about 2D? Like, we haven't looked at 2D vectors now. So, we should try 2D as well. That's
just setting z to zero. And if we multiply two 2D vectors together, we get this. And this has a basis
of one and xy, which that's the complex numbers. That still just has the same algebraic behavior
as complex numbers. But so, this is fascinating and kind of weird that we just went through
this algebraic journey and somehow, like, multiplying vectors gives us quaternions and complex
numbers. But again, like, what are these things? Like, what is yz and zx and xy? And like,
we still don't know. Like, we kind of want to find that out, too. So, if we consider the basis
vectors of a coordinate system, our xy axes, or in 3D, our xyz axes, they all have a length of one.
And they're all mutually orthogonal. So, that's our basis vectors. The things we're trying to
figure out now are these, like, yz and zx and all of that, right? And these look suspiciously
similar to the cross product, don't they? And the cross product has this behavior of, if you have
two vectors, a and b, and you do the cross product, you get something that's perpendicular to both of
them. In other words, it's normal to the plane formed by those two vectors. And it also just so
happens that the magnitude, the length of this green vector, is the area formed by the parallelogram
between those two vectors, both in 2D and in 3D. So, maybe this has something to do with planes.
Rather than, like, points in space, right? All right. So, if we have our xy component,
that's the only one we have in 2D. That was the one that was equal to the imaginary unit.
And in 3D, we have yz, zx and xy. So, what if we conceptualize these bases as planes? So, maybe our
xy refers to the plane formed by x and y, and specifically the unit plane, like a plane with
an area of 1. And if we extend this to 3D, there's obviously three planes now that are the basis
planes of our coordinate system. And so, maybe we can call these bases bi-vectors. So, that's what
we're going to name these. They're not quite vectors, but they're sort of like two vectors
forming a plane. So, let's call them bi-vectors. They have an area of 1, and they are mutually
orthogonal. So, the way to think about this is that if you have a regular vector, like a point
in space, then it's kind of like casting a shadow onto each of the axes, right? The three components
of a vector is just how far along each axis is this point. And so, for bi-vectors, it's the same
thing, but instead of points along axes, maybe we can interpret this as an oriented area,
casting shadows on each of those three bases bi-vectors, the three bases planes. And so,
a bi-vector has those three numbers. It looks very similar to a vector if you just look at those
numbers, right? But we interpret it as a bi-vector. So, it's an oriented plane with an area, and
that's it. It has no position or anything like that. And if we manipulate it, you can see that
the numbers change as well. So, this is just me turning it around in unity. And so, again, we get
kind of the shadow on each of those three planes. And it can be negative. So, we get a signed area
on each of those three planes. And obviously, it has an area, so we can scale it up as well. It can
be larger, and it can be smaller, and so forth. And so, this is what a bi-vector would look like
if you just write it in code. You have, like, just three components. It looks awfully similar to a
vector, but algebraically, it's entirely different because the basis is YZ, ZX, and XY. It's not XYZ.
And in fact, these bi-vectors, they represent the minimum information required in any given
dimension to store both a plane and a magnitude. And this is why it shows up quite a lot when
dealing with rotations, because rotations happen in a plane, right? Like, they don't really happen
around an axis. Like, if you have rotations in 2D, there's no third axis to speak of, but there is a
plane you can rotate in, right? And so, if we look back at the cross product, the cross product,
again, gave us a vector. So, it has an XYZ component, which is a regular vector. But the thing about
the cross product is that in math and physics, we talk about something called a pseudo vector,
which is it has, like, these weird transformation rules. Like, if you mirror the result of a cross
product, it doesn't have the expected behavior. And it only works in 3D and 70. Don't ask me why.
It's just the way it is. And it has all of these hidden transformation rules. The thing we were
doing now, where we returned a bi-vector instead, is called a wedge product. And usually, you write it
with this little hat thing. And so, algebraically, it's exactly the same in terms of the coefficients,
but the bases we use are completely different, because we have YZ, ZX, and XY instead. So,
this returns a bi-vector. It generalizes to any dimension. It doesn't have to be only 3D and 70
or whatever. And it's a little harder to understand, though, because we were never really taught about
bi-vectors in school, right? Or at least I wasn't. And so, here we have the 3D and the 2D vector
multiplication. We can write it a little bit more generalized by saying that multiplying two vectors
together is the dot product plus the wedge product of those two vectors together. Because the wedge
product gives us the bi-vector part of that multiplication. Let's see. Does this work? Oh,
shit, it works. Hell yeah. I thought internet wouldn't work. And another place where this
actually shows up that I ran into is when talking about a thing called curvature. So, here you can
see something called the oscillating circle. So, this is kind of the circle that matches the curvature
of this spline that it's moving along. And the radius of that is 1 divided by the curvature.
So, if instead of thinking about the radius, you think about the inverse of the radius,
and that's curvature. So, a curvature of 0 is a straight line, a curvature of 1 turns in one
direction, a curvature of negative 1 turns in the other direction. Anyway, it's a useful concept.
And so, if we want to measure curvature of a parametric function, say, this is how you would
do curvature in 2D. This is straight up from Wikipedia. If you want to see how to measure
curvature. This is a scalar, and it's signed. In other words, it can be both negative and positive.
And then we have curvature in 3D. And here, we have the magnitude of the cross-products
between the velocity and the acceleration divided by the speed cubed. And so, these look very
different if you're not familiar with everything that we just talked about. But this one is always
positive because we're getting the magnitude of a vector. So, all of a sudden, it's no longer
signed. There's no negative curvature or positive curvature. And what about the axis? If curvature
turns kind of around an axis in 3D, right? And so, these two, that's looking a little sus.
Like, now we can kind of recognize these patterns, right? And so, this is just a wedge product. So,
we've kind of been mistaken in thinking about the curvature and thinking of them as either a scalar
or the cross-product or the magnitude of the cross-product. But if we just do the wedge product
instead, that is much more simple. And it generalizes to any dimension again. And so, instead of
returning to the scalar or a vector, we get a bi-vector out of that. Yes, I'm going to go a
little bit over time. Are you all okay with that? Okay. I'm almost done. So, this is kind of a
generalized curvature. Anyway, so, what I think is cool about this is that throughout math, we've
had this thing of, like, mental gymnastics of, like, you can't really multiply vectors, but here's
eight different products. Just use those instead. And also, the cross-product doesn't work at all
in all dimension, but it works in 3D and, like, 5D or 7D, maybe, like, one of those,
one of those. And also, cross-product returns a pseudo-vector with, like, special transformation
rules. So, it's not really a vector. And complex numbers, they're, like, 2D vectors, but also,
not at all, but they can, like, rotate. And quaternions are, like, an extension of complex
numbers with rules i squared equals j squared equals k squared equals ijk equals negative one.
It's just, like, Jesus Christ, right? Or we can just say that if you square a vector, you get the
length squared. That seems a little bit more simple. And then everything else, all of those things we
talked about, just naturally emerge from that definition. What we've been talking about is
called geometric algebra. More specifically, it's a Clifford algebra. And if you take all of these
components and, like, combine them into a big multi-vector, and 2D, they will look like this.
We have a scalar. We have a real number. We have a vector and a bi-vector. Vector has two components.
Bi-vector only has one component. That's a full 2D VGA multi-vector. So, VGA is either vanilla
geometric algebra or vector geometric algebra. People haven't agreed on this. Then the 3D
multi-vector looks like this. So, the vector has three components now, and the bi-vector also has
three components. This is why we probably mixed up vectors, pseudo-vectors together, because they
both have three components in 3D. But it's actually much better to express the results of the cross
product as a bi-vector instead. There's also a thing called a tri-vector, which is the unit
volume formed by the three basis vectors. We're not going to get into that. So, basically, all of
these concepts that we've kind of juggled around with all these special rules, they can actually
generalize in a really clean way using this framework. So, instead of separating complex
numbers and quaternions as separate things, we can just call them rotors, and that's a real number
plus a bi-vector of that given dimension. And so, finally, after this whole journey,
you might be wondering, well, if multiplying two 3D vectors gives us a quaternion
and in games, we use quaternions for rotations. What rotation does that represent? Like, what
happens when we do that? And this is what it represents. So, we're multiplying these two
vectors together, and the orientation that we get, we're orienting this cube based on it,
is twice the angle between those two vectors in the plane formed by those two vectors.
And so, that applies to 3D as well. So, if we, like, separate these two vectors out, you can
see that the cube rotates after that. And it's, like, twice the angle between those two. If you
want to read up more on that, look up quaternions and double cover that talks about why it's twice
the angle. And so, why couldn't you multiply vectors? Well, probably because your teacher
didn't explain geometric algebra to you, right? But, now you can. And that's my talk. Thank you
very much for coming. All right. Thank you so much. So, if anything, your talk was both a question
and an answer to the multiplication of kath, maths, and rainbows. So, there's that. You have
produced at least an answer to that very tricky multiplication. And with that, I would love to
open it up for a couple of questions. Has any? Yeah, there's a really weird cube that they pass
around. It's very strange. I probably should have mentioned that there was going to be questions
at the end. I forgot. What are you exploring next while people think of questions? Sorry,
what? What area are you exploring next that you want to break your brain over? I'm still stuck
in quaternions. So, I've been making a spline library where, like, a spline library for unity
that has, like, quaternionic splines. And I want to, like, implement a bunch of different types of
splines in quaternion space, which is really fascinating and weird. So, that's been kind of a
recent obsession. Yes? Is it working? Yeah. All right. There we go. First of all, I want to say I
love the talk that you've been giving and also your YouTube channel that you have. Oh, can you
talk a little closer? Yeah. That I really like your YouTube channel and the talk that you've just
been giving. Oh, thank you. What type of, what different type of problems could,
do you have that could help with where you would have a benefit for using the wedge
factor or these operations in? So, most of it is useless. Like, this whole talk,
waste of time. But, it's like, again, this is kind of more, like, reframing things you already knew.
Like, if you looked up how quaternions worked or how complex numbers worked,
they would just be separate systems, kind of, but now they're kind of unified in a way that
makes more sense. Like, for example, one thing that, like, I think a lot of people, if you want to
implement quaternions, most people, even engine developers, probably just, like, copy some code,
paste it into their engine and then call it a day, and now you have quaternion for rotations, right?
But, one thing that I learned after, like, reading up on how they actually work is, like,
you can learn all sorts of, like, tricks with them. So, for example, I had a use case of,
I wanted to, like, interpolate and, I don't know which cordon system we should use,
I wanted to interpolate an orientation along a spline, and then I wanted to add a feature of
reversing that spline. So, this should turn 180 degrees in order to reverse that whole spline.
And when I did the math for that, like, did you know that, like, reversing a quaternion
is a swizzle? You just shuffle the components. Like, you can just, and in any of these three axes,
or the world space axes, it's literally just shuffling the components. It's a free operation
in terms of, like, computational power. You don't have to do a full, like, 180-degree angle axis
multiplication, right? And stuff like that is, like, all of these little, like, mathematical
tricks that kind of pop out. But if you don't really care that much about that, you don't have
to learn all of this. It's just a useful framework to me, at least. And also, if you want to make
a game in any other dimension than 2D or 3D, this is also very useful. Then you really need this.
All right. Any other questions?
People are really hungry. I'm sorry I kept you all this long. Oh, over there.
You get a cube. Thank you. And does your math library support geometric algebra?
So, yeah, I do have a math library on GitHub. I have some geometric algebra components. It's not,
like, fully fleshed out. So, I've only been, like, adding things there as I need them. I haven't,
like, made it into a library that has literally everything. But I do have a library on my GitHub
with, like, there's a bi-vector 3 type there. And there's a, like, rotor 3 type, which is just a
quaternion, right? But I do have that in my math library. So, if you do want to look into the code
of, like, how this might look, my website is up there. These days, there are too many social
media. So, just everything's there. Just go there. And then you can find all of the links to that.
Thanks. Oh, actually, I don't think I have a link to my GitHub there. That's the only link I don't
have on my website. You can probably find it if you Google, I think. All right. Any other questions?
And also, you can, if you have other questions, like, later, you can just come up to me and talk
to me. That makes me feel important and happy that I could provide value to all of you. So,
please validate my feelings by talking to me later. Hi. I was just wondering, do you still plan to
do, like, your tools on other engines, too? Like, on Unreal Engine, for example, your Spline
upcoming tool? I've considered it, like, obviously, with all of the Unity disaster.
I've considered it. Although I looked into Godot and I looked into Unreal, but they're just,
they're very different tools. Like, Unreal is, like, it's a level designer and level artist tool
that turned into a game engine. And Godot is, like, it's just engineers making an engine for
engineers, and it's very engineer. And I feel it's not very artist-focused. And then any time I try to
do something that I do in Unity of, like, making, like, quick editor scripts and just, like, have
that really fast iteration, that is just destroyed in Unreal. And Godot, I think it's a bit more
balanced because they have, like, a more, like, easy-to-use scripting language and whatnot.
But I don't know. Like, if I, like, I make, like, 70% of my income is from selling plugins in Unity.
And so, like, could I really support that in Godot, which is, like, very, like, open-source,
free software-driven? And I'm, like, I don't know. I think that community is not, like, quite,
like, big enough yet to, like, support something like the tools that I do. And so, like, if anything,
I might, like, transition to doing, like, standalone tools, just separate EXEs that you open,
rather than, like, tying it to any specific engine. Or I'm just going to go back to making games
again. Because, yeah, I kind of want to do that. But, yeah. Yep. All right. I think we got a sign
that we should cut. Yes. A stoic nod of, like, all right. Thank you all so much for coming.
Or did you want to close out? Or... No, we're good. Oh, okay.
All right. Thank you all. Time for lunch.