We need more fog that leaves us with an escape.
We need more fog that leaves us with an paradise.
I spend all my time working in thisくるくる of a gym for a whole week.
We need more fog like this.
We need more fog, not even 10 million pounds.
Our parking space is big and kayak今路が mile them.
What about bed Seong-dol?
I'm not going to make it.
Mr. McDonald, let's talk chicken.
Are you aware that the public prefers the taste of Kentucky nuggets to your chicken
muck nuggets by almost three to one?
No sir.
And is your muck chicken sandwich made with the Colonel's secret blend of eleven herbs
and spices?
No sir.
So how do you expect to sell chicken?
Toys!
Lots of toys!
It's our best.
A dollar ninety-nine for the Colonel's chicken sandwich and fries, or Kentucky nuggets and
fries.
Comes a time in every guy's life when, well, things begin to change.
You know what I'm talking about, fellas?
Suddenly wheels means cars instead of skateboards.
Look, let's broaden your horizons.
It's time to move on.
Instead of always reaching for that same old bag of potato chips, why not tear into a bag
a nacho cheese Doritos tortilla chips?
Bigger taste!
Bigger crunch!
Here's a snack chip that bites back.
Come on.
Nacho cheese Doritos.
Come in now.
You can handle that.
Come on.
Punch all you want.
We'll make more.
Dave.
If you make a grilled chicken sandwich at Wendy's, they will come.
They will?
If you make it with a chicken breast, they will come.
It has to be boneless.
If you make it with lettuce and tomato.
And honey mustard.
And put it all together on a toasted bomb, they will come.
Call it Wendy's Grilled Chicken Sandwich.
Dave, I told you they will come.
It's Wendy.
I just can't figure out how she's doing it.
For fun around here, me and the boys liked to do something a little bit crazy.
Put two kinds of cheese on a cheeseburger.
For a while, new taste headed the store for two kinds of cheese and lean ground beef.
Cheddar and monster.
Crazy.
Things do go bump in the night.
There are boogeymen.
Fortunately, Silly's exclusive post-hypothetic sleep system is designed to support everyone
differently.
More comfortably to keep your night from becoming your worst nightmare.
For a better night's sleep, better sleep on a Silly.
Wednesday.
This isn't just about sex.
No, no, why not?
There's a little about sex though, isn't it?
It's sort of nice on the phone.
It's a portable upbringing with me.
Things are really heating up.
Anything but love after Tuggy Hussein.
When Reggie and I agreed to meet for breakfast, I didn't think I needed to say where.
It could only be one place.
Where else can you get this delicious bacon egg and cheese biscuit?
So much for him.
Nice move, Jack.
The Prelude SI with four-wheel steering from Honda.
Grandpa, you think you could have a party every time you come out with a new product?
This is really nice.
You don't have a party like this every night.
This is big.
This is really big.
This new light microwave popcorn.
With one-third fewer calories and two-thirds less fat.
Then our regular microwave.
And it pops up more than any other light microwave.
It's going to keep my figure just like it is today.
Well, you're pretty good-looking, Grandpa, you know.
That's what Grandma says, too.
Yeah.
Not all of us can be as good-looking as you, Grandpa.
Well, that's true.
That's true.
Now, at Little Caesars, you can get Picnic Picnic.
Two medium pizzas, two orders of crazy bread,
and two servings of Coke Classic, all for only $7.98.
It's Picnic Picnic.
Two pizzas, two orders of crazy bread,
and two servings of Coke Classic, all for only $7.98.
It's Picnic Picnic.
Two pizzas, two crazy breads, two soft drinks,
all that food for only $7.98.
And it rains at fours.
Picnic Picnic only at Little Caesars.
Pizza, pizza.
Why are beers that go down lightly watered down so heavily?
Why?
Ask.
Turn off the water and turn but dry.
Its smooth draft taste is dry-brood, not watered down.
To drink light, yet satisfied completely.
So why get soaked?
When you can drink but dry.
A baby changes everything.
Safety takes on a whole new meaning when it's somebody you love in that car.
This is our family.
They're the most technically advanced and life-like dummies in the world.
Only GM uses a family like this to develop safety technology
because we know quality cars, safe cars, should help protect everyone.
I look at my family and I want us to be thinking of everything.
GM's safety, it's not one thing, it's everything.
She's everything to me.
Dorothy, you marry me or is my ring a lifesaver?
It's a beginning.
Don't worry.
I'll give it to my mother.
Lifesavers candy isn't life delicious.
Macy's pre-season sale.
The shopping opportunity of the year.
You'll save on fall's newest fashions now.
Before the fall season at our lowest prices of the year.
The best for women, men and kids.
Everything you need for fall.
From the names you really want.
Our biggest sale of the year.
Macy's pre-season sale.
Don't delay.
Prices go up August 5th.
El Torritos Fajitas Fiesta.
Our famous steak or chicken fajita combos.
And a delicious dessert.
All just $7.95 at El Torrito.
Three bites big.
Hey!
Packs of eight.
New snack size stickers and Milky Way.
Three bites big.
A pose in a pack.
One, two, three bites big.
Hey!
Introducing Milky Way Snickers in a brand new size.
A new snack size.
Snack around the house size.
Three bites big.
Packs of eight.
New snack size stickers and Milky Way.
Three bites big.
Packs of eight.
New snack size.
And now, today's weather.
Cold winds out of the north-northwest.
With a 30% chance of snow tonight.
Temperature dropping into low 20.
At last, a weather-proof formula that holds longer
and stronger than the other leading pumps.
Honey, don't forget your food.
Exclusively ours.
New Final Net Ultimate Hold.
The weather-proof hold that lets you laugh at the weather.
Saturday, this June, your 60th anniversary celebration
will continue in a moment.
This is what American Airlines does better
than anyone else.
Arrive on time.
Again and again.
In fact, American has had the best on-time arrival record
of the nine largest domestic airlines
for as long as records have been kept.
American Airlines.
The on-time machine.
It was a big day when the new equipment arrived.
It's big.
The biggest one I've ever seen.
Of course, being a custom job, some assembly was required.
It'll be a few weeks, people.
But finally, it was ready.
One of the world's fastest check-writing systems.
Some insurance companies look for ways
to get your money from you faster.
Here should do 12,000 an hour.
At Ethna, we look for ways to get your money to you faster.
Probe of misconduct by Oakland Housing Police.
On 7 at 11.
So your woman's body is merely a frame.
Homicides were created to release.
Pants are mandatory.
And to pass, you won't see a leg in Paris disappear.
Perfume and infusion.
The short skirt is dead.
My designs...
No matter what the gentleman prefers,
the lady prefers hands.
Carnation instant breakfast.
You gotta love it in an instant.
Wake up to the nutritious, delicious taste
of Carnation instant breakfast.
Carnation instant breakfast.
You gotta love it in an instant.
Hey, dog lovers.
This is ordinary dog food.
Feast your eyes on Grand Gourmet.
25% more protein and less fat than leading brands.
Grand Gourmet.
It now looks better. It is better.
399, golden fried shrimp and grilled chicken breast
with salad and baked potato.
Just 399 for a limited time at Red Lobster for lunch.
To our tribal breakfast cereals.
Total. Kellogg's Just Right.
Both high nutrition cereals.
So what might make one better than the other?
Just Right has vitamin B1.
We have vitamin B1.
Just Right has vitamin B2.
B2. Just Right has iron.
Oh, we have iron.
Just Right has vitamin E.
Oh, plenty of E.
Just Right has vitamin B6.
B6 here.
Just Right has almonds.
Just Right has sweet dates.
Plump raisins plus four different tasty grains.
Just Right has two out of three people
preferring our taste.
Which means Just Right is just better.
Kellogg's Just Right.
It's the taste that makes it just better.
The Mureen earwax removal system
has drops that safely loosen hard
and wax when used as directed.
Plus an ear washer to gently flush wax away.
Mureen.
The complete medically approved system
to safely remove earwax.
The temperature is well below zero this morning.
Perfect to test Chevy's heartbeat.
With the electrical system fully taxed,
Chevy delivers reliable cold starting.
After thousands of tests,
an incredible 99.9% success record.
With 84 models redesigned and engineered,
GM is putting quality on the road.
Every day, 22 million people come into McDonald's.
They count on the same hot, fresh food
at every McDonald's all over the world.
But imagine if there were only one McDonald's,
you could count on.
And 22 million people came in at the same time.
The whole restaurant would fill up.
The city would fill up.
And all those people in one place
would cause the earth to tilt off its axis
and go spinning into space.
And that would make a real mess of everything.
That's why we make every McDonald's
from Poughkeepsie to Pomona
just as good as every other McDonald's,
thereby saving the universe.
While the Daytona Shelby Turbo
may not be quite as plush as the Aston Martin,
and the power plant isn't quite like a Lamborghini,
its new VNT turbo makes it one of the most powerful
front-wheel sports cars built in America.
And while it doesn't quite reach the speed of a Testerosa,
at that speed, you might miss something.
The all-new Dodge Daytona Shelby Turbo,
the hot new spirit of Dodge.
Now get up to $2,000 back at Dodge, guaranteed.
The bravest men.
Ain't no dream.
Are those with something to prove?
They gotta know that nobody's gonna let them fight.
And nothing to lose.
Someday they're gonna let the 54 get into us.
Matthew Broderick.
We'll be ready, sir.
Denzel Washington.
Come on!
Kerry Ellways.
Ready!
Morgan Freeman.
Glory Redditor.
Now playing at a theater near you.
In DeMonte, Washington, when a kid's 18,
he's old enough to drive, old enough to vote,
and old enough to worry about something most adults have,
gingivitis, an early reversible gum disease
that left untreated could get serious.
Just ask your dentist.
Fortunately, many know enough to use Listerine,
the only non-prescription mouthwash accepted
by the American Dental Association
for helping to prevent and reduce plaque in gingivitis.
Yep, if you're old enough to worry about gum disease,
you ought to be smart enough to use Listerine.
I want to try something different.
Can you make me look like that?
Tuesday, it's a brand new job.
Oh, I'm sure you can, Iris.
I'll go get the wand.
But she's the same old Roseanne.
Ben.
I'm not going to spend the rest of my life
spying some wire.
We all got chances, Elvis.
Some of them we just can't take.
In 1954, Vernon Presley wanted his son
to have a steady job with a secure future.
Well, I said, tell me, baby, what's wrong with you?
His dream came true, a special preview of Elvis Tuesday.
Sammy Davis Jr.'s 60th anniversary celebration
will continue in a moment.
You don't want, you don't get.
That's arithmetic.
Joe Kennedy.
He became the father of two senators and a president.
You were a very successful and wealthy man.
Isn't that winning?
No, not yet.
We had an appetite for power.
For the first Irish Catholic ambassador to England.
Wealth and women.
I never made history with anyone I've made love with.
How soon will you be home?
If there's any dirty work to be done, I'll be the one to do it.
The Kennedys of Massachusetts.
Two weeks from tonight.
To the eye, the Lexus LS-400
looks like an elegantly contoured luxury sedan.
To the wind, however.
It doesn't look like much.
The Lexus LS-400,
the most aerodynamic luxury sedan in America.
The Lexus LS-400 says absolutely no cholesterol.
Now what could be better than sunshine?
Have a little sunshine.
Pentagon Waste reaches the billions on 7 at 11.
The producers of the show,
the producers of the show was hoping you'd have a little more feeling,
a little more Mike Tyson.
A little more Mike Tysonisms.
Hello, ladies and gentlemen.
Sammy and I would like...
To be continued...
It was Uchi.
Look, a little pale.
Maybe he needs a doctor or something.
Maybe I do.
What happened?
They hate on me.
You have to drive it to believe it.
The New Accord.
This is delicious, Danny.
What do you call it?
It's new ragu fresh Italian pasta sauce.
So delicate.
What's it called?
Fresh Italian pasta sauce.
Yeah, it's really fresh.
But what's the name of this?
See, ragu uses less heavy tomato paste
and twice the crushed tomatoes.
It's a very fresh tomato paste.
And twice the crushed tomatoes.
But what's the name of the sauce?
New ragu fresh Italian pasta sauce.
More crushed tomatoes, more fresh tomato taste.
Here's a jar.
Look, it has the name on it.
Forget it.
They instantly turn on.
You put that show lead on,
and that spark is right there.
That's the difference between a good dog and a great dog.
These are champions. They deserve the best.
And I recommend pedigree and pedigree meal time.
Pedigree.
Recommended by top breeders.
And now there's a new kind of pedigree.
Pedigree choice cuts.
Tender juicy meaty chunks with the sauce
dogs can't resist.
One look tells you it's choice.
One feeding shows you it's irresistible.
New pedigree choice cuts.
Recommended by top breeders.
My poor brother Tom,
every time he tried to see what he was missing,
he would miss what he was seeing.
Then Tom got this amazing Magnavox TV.
That lets him watch one show
while he checks out all the others
on this remarkable little window.
Hey, that's a smart window, Dick.
That's what they call it, Tom.
They call it Tom?
No, no, no. They call it smart window, Tom.
I don't know. I kind of like Tom.
Magnavox. Smart choice.
Very smart.
Friday.
I am now officially a teenager.
It's DJ's first kiss.
30 candles
to an all-new full house.
I'm the team.
Followed by a new Family Matters Friday.
Christ on New Yorker 5th Avenue.
If the rebate goes up,
Chrysler will pay you the difference.
I think I'm in love.
Who now?
That goddess.
I'm the rap.
Out of your league.
Oh, yeah?
Yeah.
Watch and learn.
May I have a towel?
Richard?
Never underestimate the doctor.
Hi, excuse me, y'all. Are you French?
You look French. I love French food.
This morning, I was following a Sears service truck
when it dawned on me.
I see Sears trucks all the time.
It also dawned on me that I hardly ever see a service truck
from those so-called superstores.
So before you make that next big buying decision,
ask yourself what kind of service you'll get five years from now,
or if they'll even be around to answer the phone.
That's one of the big reasons I feel better
when I buy a major appliance or electronics from Sears.
And that's what they mean by your money's worth
and a whole lot more.
They've been selected because of their visions, their dreams,
and the roles they want to play as leaders in America's future.
And someday they may truly have a place in black history.
Bitesize Ritz-Bitz Peanut Butter Sandwiches
The taste of Ritz-Bitz and real peanut butter in tiny sandwiches
with no assembly required.
Bitesize Ritz-Bitz Peanut Butter Sandwiches
The taste of Ritz-Bitz and real peanut butter in tiny sandwiches
with no assembly required.
Hey, wait for me!
Monday!
Stop raping the forest!
MacGyver goes out on a limb to save the trees.
I don't know what to do.
I can handle it.
MacGyver, then, based on a true story.
Daddy, you're alive!
The father who refused to let his family die.
Mayday, mating. Two children stranded.
Robert Conrad, anything to survive, Monday.
I'm using this other long-distance company.
Try to call Phoenix. I miss style Fiji.
Pull him and knock him inside!
I call the operator. She says she can't give me instant credit.
I say AT&T always did.
She says, you're not dealing with AT&T.
If you miss dealing with AT&T, it's easier than ever to come back.
Just call 1-800-582-1700 right now and we'll switch you back for free.
They kept saying how much money I'd save.
Then I get the first bill.
I'm not kidding. I thought it was a typo.
I mean, where were the big savings?
People who thought they could do better than AT&T are coming back for the real value.
You can't do it simple. Just call now and come back for free.
It takes longer getting through, but I'm saving a ton, right? Wrong.
You gotta read the fine print.
Pull him and knock him inside!
I couldn't believe it.
You're not dealing with AT&T.
Well, I am now.
1-800-582-1700 for dependable crystal clear AT&T long-distance service.
Call now and we'll switch you for free.
You couldn't pick a better time to come back.
If you want an anti-lock braking system like Mercedes,
a driver airbag like BMW,
a rear load-leveling suspension feature similar to Rolls,
and a more advanced transmission than Jaguar,
this is a simple way to get it all.
Introducing the all-new Chrysler Imperial.
There is no luxury without engineering.
The guaranteed rebate has been extended until February 28th.
Get $1,000 now.
There's only one thing I used to hate worse than having to wash out my pantyhose every night.
And that was having to throw him out.
Pantyhose that lasts are no nonsense.
Ladies and gentlemen, Dennis Miller.
I just knew they'd call.
It's almost as if someone once said,
just in case people like sunshine and water,
we'd better make Florida.
And we'd better make miles of beautiful beaches
and places like St. Augustine and Key West,
just in case people want to go to them.
There are over 4 million miles of roads in Alamo territory,
all across America.
And nationwide, only Alamo gives you all those miles for free,
including the ones that run through a state that's named after sunshine.
Knowing how to read and write can really make you feel wanted.
Help someone learn to read.
Volunteer as a tutor in your community.
Tuesday.
Hi.
I've missed you.
You're married.
It's a second chance for love.
What are we doing?
I can't do this.
I wish that you didn't have to go.
I'm in love with you.
30-something Tuesday.
The day may come when every freestanding range
will have a smooth, sealed-in surface that's easy to clean
and heats up this fast.
But Whirlpool has it today.
Hey, Mike, I really like this white sinfin' doll.
Well, good, good.
Now put it down.
We're going to try another one.
He loves to do this.
This one's great.
Yeah, I like it better.
Why?
Can't it just taste better?
Isn't that loud?
Did you know Gallo made a white sinfin' doll?
No, it's terrific, isn't it?
Am I going to get any credit for this?
Oh, yeah.
Ernest and Julio Gallo present a very special white sinfin' doll.
It will change the way you think about Gallo.
Wednesday.
The war is over.
It's the moment they've all been waiting for.
Forget your troubles.
Come on, get happy.
But is it really the end?
Don't you believe it?
When the wheels of my freedom bird lift off,
I'll believe it.
China Beach.
Alpha Beta shoppers are finding
when the new sign went up,
the prices came down.
For the last year I shopped at Alpha Beta,
and now that it's switched over to Lucky's,
I find a significant reduction in my weekly grocery bill.
It's important that I have quality and affordable prices,
and I find that I get both of that
when I shop at Lucky's.
Alpha Beta is now Lucky.
We think you'll like the change.
I want a ten minute breakfast,
so I'm bringing a clock to time.
You don't need a clock.
The waitress has a stopwatch.
If her watch is stopped,
how will I know when ten minutes are up?
Because if breakfast takes longer than ten minutes, it's free.
I get a broken watch for free?
I'm talking about breakfast.
And you've rambled on long enough.
It's time to go eat at Lenny's.
Denny's.
Now you can have your breakfast or lunch served in ten minutes,
or it's free, only at Denny's.
It's where individuals become a family.
It's where they share memories and news and opinions.
It's where parents get to know their children
and their children's children.
Homes will always be an important part of people's lives.
That's why home loans are such a secure investment.
And that's where Home Savings of America
has put its depositors' money for more than a hundred years.
Juice.
Quiet, please.
Oh no, I'm not here.
When allergies come on this strong,
Benadryl comes on stronger.
A change is coming, it's understood.
Happening all over my neighborhood.
Only one place got the taste for me.
Gonna change the pizza hut delivery.
Call Pizza Hut Delivery now for the Double Cheeseburger Pizza.
Get one medium-sized pizza,
and one large pizza, and one large pizza,
get one medium for $8.99 a second for just four bucks more,
or make it to Lux with bacon and onions for just one more buck.
Gonna change the pizza hut delivery.
Pizza Hut Delivery, Bacon and Grape.
It's here.
Trying is believing week,
and here's how people who are trying breakfast with grape nuts feel.
You've got to try it.
I did, and I feel great.
It's a great natural energy source, and it's fat-free.
You won't believe how good you feel.
I do.
I feel great.
Grape nuts cereal is full of complex carbohydrates.
You won't believe how it helps keep you going all morning.
Look for this display in your store.
Post-grape nuts trying is believing week.
You've got to do it.
Um, excuse me.
In a blind test, women compared new advanced formula
Agree shampoo to an expensive salon brand,
Red Can Amino Pond.
Guess which one they like better?
Agree. It's that good.
Aren't Ritz and Ritz-Bitz really the same?
Well, that's a silly question.
One's bigger, one's little.
So they're different.
But they're still the same.
So they're the same.
Don't you get it?
Ritz or Ritz-Bitz, two sizes fits all.
Wednesday.
I took buster to the vet.
And?
Honey, is there something wrong with him?
Well, nothing.
He can't be fixed.
You'll get sympathy pains on the Wonder Years.
Then?
You're playing.
A special episode.
Nobody makes blueberry pancakes like you do, Margaret.
Oh, those aren't blueberry pancakes.
Share memories of grandpa.
On Growing Pains, Wednesday.
To be the one company big enough and innovative enough
to offer plans where you never have to fill out
one single claim form.
Blue Cross of California.
We make the system work for you.
While the competition only offers a three-year warranty plan,
TaylorMade Office Systems offers an exclusive five-year warranty
plan on their Canon NP copiers
with all of the guarantees in writing.
Remember that the next time your copier company feeds you,
the same old line.
And more overall passenger space.
Stop having fun.
It doesn't add up.
The Isuzu Rodeo.
True, it doesn't add up.
Isuzu, there's no comparison.
Now, with factor-to-dealer incentives,
air conditioning comes standard with any 4x2 Rodeo
for a limited time.
Lots of men have heard about Monoxadil.
And lots of men have heard about Rogaine.
But lots of men don't know that only Rogaine has Monoxadil.
And only your doctor can prescribe Rogaine.
For more information, call this number now.
If you're wondering where the Rogaine is for you,
call this number.
And we'll give you an incentive to find out.
A certificate worth $10 toward a consultation visit with your doctor.
Call 1-800-556-4800.
Some men would rather live their lives sheltered in the harbor.
And some would rather sail into life
with the unmistakable scent of Old Spice.
Clean, true, and classic, Old Spice.
One of the legends of the sea.
What are you sitting here doing?
Excuse me.
Aren't you glad you used dials?
To the airport. Let's go.
Are we over the window here?
Don't you wish everybody did?
Right, Rogaine.
Are you going to handle for this window?
So I start watching the Discovery Channel.
Thought maybe I'll learn something.
Then I see they have this guide, you know,
to kind of help you figure out when everything's on.
So I order it. Real easy.
Just 1-800-TDC-8343.
And I charge it.
And now a few weeks later, it's here.
I mean, look at this thing.
It's a magazine.
T-D-C Magazine.
I open it up.
And there's this grid,
which is great because I can see the whole week at a glance.
I just circle the shows I want to see.
And look at this.
It's a complete description of every single show.
And check this out.
These photographs. Gorgeous.
There's even articles by famous authors.
Amazing.
All I expected was a program guide,
and I get all this.
What a bargain.
I wonder if they'll ever be a swimsuit issue.
Call now to order your T-D-C Magazine
and receive 12 monthly issues for only $14.95.
That's more than 50% off the cover price.
Or tell the operator to bill you later.
These and MasterCard accepted.
It's never one food that gives you what you need.
It's the combination and the balance.
And how you balance the combinations.
So at McDonald's, there's lots to choose from.
Lean burgers to low-fat shakes and frozen yogurt.
Salads.
No fat.
No cholesterol.
Apple brand muffins.
And cholesterol free oil for our chicken, potatoes, and fish.
We've got a long list of good foods to choose from.
All you've got to do is just choose the food for you.
Always good food.
Always good value at McDonald's.
It can be downright frustrating
and difficult to get perfect orange juice.
One with that pure fresh squeeze taste
with no water added or taken away.
But if you remember that no other major brand of juice
comes closer to this,
than this Tropicana Pure Premium,
you'll think you'll find everything will just fall into place.
Tropicana Pure Premium.
Also appearing in 96 ounces.
Call me irresponsible.
Just because the other guy is on the road
doesn't mean his mind is.
So the superb traction of the Subaru Legacy
with four-wheel drive and anti-lock brakes
can be quite a comfort.
Since the next guy is capable of almost anything,
shouldn't the same be true of your next car?
Factory to dealer cash could mean great savings to you
during the Subaru Spring Value Days.
Three hours, nine minutes.
May I ask what you're doing?
Timing tiny time pills.
Excuse me?
Well, this morning when I woke up, I talked like this,
and I didn't like that.
So I took a contact.
So, well, contact has 600 tiny time pills at last 12 hours.
Up to three times longer than ordinary cold medicine.
There's a whole day's work in every contact.
Eight hours and 30 seconds.
Look, if you're going to time the tiny time pills all day,
when are you going to do the work?
Right.
You time.
There's a whole day's work in every contact.
Coming to ABC.
I'll give you three and a half in time served.
No way. Two years tops.
Three. Two and a half.
Three or no deal.
Done.
You know something's wrong and you still want to try this case?
You said you took it on the cases nobody else wanted.
How the hell are we supposed to win a case without witnesses?
They'll deny it.
Oh, your honor, we got a big problem here.
Treat Williams.
You mean you're a real lawyer?
Surprise.
Eddie Dodd, premiering this week on ABC TV.
Announcing something you've never seen before
in an inexpensive Macintosh.
Color.
Lifetime.
No wonder many of us seem to always make bell calling card.
You can easily charge calls wherever you are,
whether you're just down the street or somewhere up the coast.
But unlike most calling cards, Pacific Bells is based on your own familiar phone number.
And since it's welcome at most every phone,
it's really the only calling card you need to hang on to.
Pacific Bell, we're making things easier everywhere.
McDonald's explodes another myth.
If it's no fat, it can't be delicious.
Not so.
Introducing McLean Deluxe, made with a 91% fat free beef patty.
Low fat and delicious.
Can't be done.
Can too.
You wanted great burger taste with a lot less fat.
Only McDonald's responded.
New McLean Deluxe will blow you away.
It's terrific.
It can't be low fat.
It's both New McLean Deluxe after billions and billions.
Another first at McDonald's today.
Johnson's Baby Oil.
For skin soft as the day you were born.
See this displayed for colors you can love.
I love where you're not fade away.
Bigoters lurk in small places.
Stick it to them, the snick ups.
Bigoters linger in small places.
Airwick has big news, a new decorative design and a great new scent.
Popery sashay.
Stick it to them.
My friend Carol is so different from me.
She does lunchables all at once.
I do it one by one.
We're total opposites.
But we've been best friends forever.
Oscar Meyer Lunchables lunch combinations.
Because lunch is what you make of it.
McDonald's explodes another myth.
If it's low fat, it can't be delicious.
Not so.
Introducing McLean Deluxe.
Made with a 91% fat free beef patty.
Low fat and delicious.
Can't be done.
Can too.
You wanted great burger taste with a lot less fat.
Only McDonald's responded.
New McLean Deluxe will blow you away.
It's terrific.
It can't be low fat.
It's both New McLean Deluxe after billions and billions.
Another first at McDonald's today.
Make me, make me your baby.
Touch me, touch me and maybe you will see.
How baby soft you can be.
Make me, make me your baby.
Johnson's Baby Oil.
For skin soft as the day you were born.
I'm gonna tell you how it's gonna be.
Are you gonna give your love to me?
I wanna love you night and day.
You know my love and I fade away.
Meet the Kodak Colorkin toys.
Get them free by mail when you buy these Kodak products.
See this display for colors you can love.
I love where you're not fade away.
Bigoters lurk in small places.
Stick it to up the snick ups.
Bigoters linger in small places.
Airwick has big news.
A new decorative design and a great new scent.
Popories as she is.
Stick it to up.
My friend Carol is so different from me.
She does Lunchables all at once.
But I do it one by one.
We're total opposites.
But we've been best friends forever.
Oscar Meyer Lunchables lunch combinations.
Because lunch is what you make of it.
Poor Sam and Samantha.
So young and yet so glum.
Changing time was just no fun.
But old mother Goose waved her wing
and put all the magic of story time
into new Huggies diapers.
Just the thing.
Nursery Rhymes.
Learning Rhymes.
Playful pictures too.
Eleven designs in every package.
Now Sam and Samantha are full of glee
in new story time Huggies.
And changing time is happy as can be.
You may have noticed lately
that lots of people are having considerable trouble
walking and chewing gum at the same time.
Perhaps it's because of the great taste of Trident.
Original fruit and bubble.
Trident. Good for your teeth.
And great taste too.
But I told him.
Well look, maybe the guy wasn't listening.
Oh, here it comes.
When allergies come on this strong,
Benadryl comes on stronger.
Oh boy, you know, Roger,
I haven't seen anything this nasty since Rosie.
What do you want?
A monkey.
It's gonna be a belly-wagger.
Wow, good night.
Turn up the light.
Uh-oh.
Little Caesars.
Cheezer-Cheezer.
Not one, but two pizzas loaded with cheese
and up to five toppings for $8.98.
Cheezer-Cheezer.
Bravely, Fred has faced one too many healthy
but boring breakfast.
Enough!
I want taste, indulgence.
Kellogg's Frosted Mini Wheats.
A friend.
Ooh, naughty frosting.
Freddy, Kellogg's Frosted Mini Wheats
are good for you, there's fiber.
No.
And no salt.
But they taste so good.
And they're fat-free, see?
Fat-free?
Kellogg's Frosted Mini Wheats.
Surprise, they're good for you.
You see it your way?
I see it mine.
We're all going to Italy Tuesday
when Tony and Harrods are vineyard.
Greetings, fellow villagers.
He's welcomed with Christ's freedom.
Who's the boss?
And at a special time,
net-baity guest stars.
That's a chemistry set.
Every boy should have one.
No, you shouldn't have done that, Ed.
We could just turn on the gas and blow ourselves up.
An hour on Roseanne and...
I flew here this morning from Colombia.
A dope smuggler swallows his stage.
If somebody dies, it's not your fault, is it?
No, not totally.
What percentage would you say?
Stat Tuesday.
Johnson's brings out the baby soft shine
born in your hair.
Double fresh, double good.
Come on and double it.
Double meat, double meat.
Gone.
There's no single come light.
It's not so easy to grow beans, you know.
You have to water them,
pull up the weeds,
and tie them up so they can reach the sun.
Then your mother has to help you build a fence
to keep the bunnies out.
Then you have to pick them carefully.
After that, you get to eat them.
And if you're lucky,
your mother will make a ride of golden twirls
to go with them.
Golden twirls are very delicious
and so much fun.
I wonder how they grow these.
The average driver puts 12 to 13,000 miles a year on a car.
At Saturn, we knew this.
Where and how, though, is anyone's guess.
For sure, we knew people would be taking
to new Saturn places.
And using it in ways you'd never figure.
Or even imagine.
So we tested it.
We ran at 6 million miles.
Everywhere.
Sometimes, nowhere.
Wednesday, Kevin's got a big problem
with Paul's little sister.
I'm not taking your sister to the catillion.
I mean, you're gonna have to tell her.
Unpleasant as it might be.
It was time to break a heart.
Would you go with me?
The wonder years.
It's European holiday and Mike's getting a head start.
Party! Party!
It's a tale of two vacations.
Happy anniversary.
I'm stranded in Spain with a crazy woman.
Catch all the fun Wednesday.
With great burger taste and a lot less fat.
But don't fill up on the press.
Taste for yourself.
One bite and you'll be talking about it, too.
The Swallow First.
New Maclean Deluxe.
After billions and billions.
Another first at McDonald's today.
Bradley decided to express his artistic talent
on the living room wall.
A little more covered in one coat.
They're so cute at that age.
You can't get mad at them.
Wanna bet?
Are you sure you have everything?
Yeah.
Turn around.
Hmm.
I got the Fuji film while you were in cosmetics.
I didn't forget.
Oh.
You forgot you married the perfect husband.
You were right, Dad.
Kmart's pretty cool.
You should listen to me more often.
Of all pine cleaners, more people choose pine saw.
Pine saw's got more active ingredients
than the next leading brand.
And pine saw disinfects better.
It even kills staff germs.
It's not really clean until...
It's pine-solved.
Friday on Full House, Joey and Jesse get close to nature.
Woo-hoo!
Mr. Fox!
Maybe even a little too close.
Ooh-la-la!
It's time for a boy to become a man.
Your mother sent out 150 invitations
and we got 10 tons of potato salad downstairs.
Rejoice!
Robbie comes of age on his howling day.
And all new dinosaurs ride up to Full House Friday.
This one for me?
Is this your kid?
And is he drinking the only juice drink
with a full day's vitamin C, four other vitamins,
and all natural flavors?
Well, maybe this isn't your kid.
But this should be your kid.
This is your kid.
All right, all right.
Can I help you, Kim?
Yes, you can help me.
No, we need to handle our灵s.
We need to handle our灵s.
Okay then.
I'll give you this kmäov qu enorm escroad veijo,
It's no good to огромum.
Please take care of it first.
Please take care of it.
Kiss me once and kiss me twice and kiss me once again, it's been a long, long, long time.
Oreo Unlock the Magic.
Now appearing at a Burger King near you, a cool new star, Snickers ice cream bar, rich
milk chocolate, buttery caramel, and fresh roasted peanuts, together with a cool taste
of premium ice cream.
Just the way you like it, so have it your way with the coolest new star, Snickers ice
cream bar at Burger King.
Break the mold, taste the cold, the diet's 7-up, it's a few degrees away from the ice cream
The diet's 7-up with Nutrisweet, break the ice.
The best of Disney 50 years of magic will continue in a moment.
Customs officials harassed for reporting possible corruption in the war on drugs.
ABC News investigation on world news tonight with Peter Jennings tomorrow.
All across the USA, as long as we've been around.
Our passengers are our neighbors, this country's our hometown.
And we know how hard we work, we work that hard for you.
We believe in putting people first, and that shows up in everything we do.
Cause everywhere we go, everyone of us knows.
Everything we do, USA begins with you.
Every time we fly, every mile of sky.
The world's wildest acrobats are doing the wild thing, Green World.
See the incredible acrobats of China, it's one wild show.
And we know how hard we work, we work that hard for you.
We believe in putting people first, and that shows up in everything we do.
Cause everywhere we go, everyone of us knows.
Everything we do, USA begins with you.
Every time we fly, every mile of sky.
Yo from our home studio, it's Ricky and Dee.
My man Rick, a serious burger lover.
Is doing a blind taste test of McDonald's New McLean Deluxe Salad.
Gee, you let the taste is gone.
Boom, McDonald's is the only one with this 91% fat-free lean beef fat.
Wait, hold up, 91% fat-free?
No, man.
Straight up.
The taste is kicking.
And it's a serious value.
The New McLean Deluxe.
100% death.
On taste.
Word up.
McDonald's today.
A thing about a bonbon, it's almost always gone-gone.
Bonbons are bite-sized.
Twenty ice cream bells dipped in chocolatey shells.
A thing about a bonbon, it's almost always gone-gone.
Bonbons.
If your socks are announcing unexpected new breakthroughs,
introduce your feet to ours, Burlington Socks,
for quality at a price you'll like.
Burlington Socks.
The green sea means morsak for the money.
Sunday, they're the first inhabitants of the moon
with a dream of a new life.
There's a solar flare heading for them,
but it becomes a fight for survival.
My brother's out there.
I'm not gonna leave him out there to die.
Incoming flurr alert.
Do you copy?
A world premiere movie, Plymouth Sunday.
Next, John Stossel discovers some of the best-kept secrets in childcare.
Mastering the terrible twos, getting your children to sleep,
how to raise a happy child.
Whether you're a parent or not,
don't miss this special edition of 2020.
Next.
We're out there.
That's all they took from me.
Just to put them on one time.
New Kodak Gold 400 film.
Buy it today and get $5 back with our Nabisco rebate offers.
The Jungle Book.
You can't bear to be without it.
Whoa, Mom, this isn't Kraft cheese and macaroni.
Yeah, I know.
What?
It was cheaper.
I saved a few cents.
Mom, it's not the cheesiest.
What's the difference?
No, no, no.
Sam, come on, pal.
Dinner.
Mom, you never serve anything but Kraft cheese and macaroni, right?
I wouldn't dream of it.
Kids love Kraft cheese and macaroni, and that's worth every penny.
Kraft macaroni and cheese and new dinosaur and teddy bear shapes, too.
Tuesday.
Ugh, you're going to hate L.A.
I will.
Melissa's got a job on a sitcom.
Do you have a real feel for the show?
Loves the star.
It's a pressure cooker.
It really is.
Loves the writer.
Something about you.
Hates the business.
Who do you want us to contact?
Excuse me.
Who represents you?
I do.
30-something Tuesday.
You're not leaving until you eat breakfast, so you might as well do it.
If we've told you once, we've told you a thousand times.
Have you forgotten everything we taught you?
A suggestion for all you grown-ups who think there's no time for a hot breakfast.
Kellogg's Pop Tarts.
They will fruit.
You like fruit, don't you?
An open wide.
Kellogg's Pop Tarts.
A hot breakfast everyone has time for.
You know you like it.
I'm Kate Kelly in New Orleans.
Coming up tonight on Nightcast, the power of voodoo could have determined the outcome of Sunday Super Bowl.
And are the 49ers superstitious?
I have a little ritual I go through before the game and try to get myself as nervous as possible.
I'm just going to stay out of the small towns and stay away from the people working the voodoo.
Voodoo at the Super Bowl.
Live coverage from New Orleans continues tonight on Nightcast.
For years, we've been telling you how the four-wheel drive Subaru helps the U.S. ski team get to their events early.
Yet at the 1989 World Championships, the U.S. team was not the first to arrive.
The Norwegians beat us, the French beat us, as did the Italians and the Swedes.
How'd they do it?
That was the year we lent them all a Subaru.
Imagine a Disneyland as big as the city of San Francisco.
A Disney world with a surprise around every corner.
43 square miles of tropical paradise.
The spectacular new Disney MGM Studios theme park and the incredible Epcot Center.
Imagine yourself here, Walt Disney World in Florida, as big as imagination gets.
Beauty and the Beast will continue.
You never know where history will unfold, but you always know where to turn.
The CBS Even News with Dan Rather. You always know when it's CBS News.
Gary's being pushed too far.
If you love me, you must leave me alone.
His worst nightmare is taking shape.
My children are going to be living under the same roof as a rapist.
His last resort, an act of desperation.
Speak now or else forever holds your peace.
I'm going to yell rapist or rapist.
I'm not slanting. Thursday.
This is CBS.
It's the biggest party in the history of Disneyland.
Disneyland's year-long 35th anniversary celebration with the biggest parade we've ever staged.
Towering four stories over Main Street.
Our biggest giveaway ever. A new GEO every day and over 400,000 other prizes.
Plan now for your biggest vacation ever. Disneyland's 35th anniversary.
Party, party, Disneyland's big.
It's Disneyland's big.
You know where it's at.
At your Northern California Mazda dealer now.
There are very few guarantees in medicine.
But if you have arthritis pain like I do, you should know about Mediprin and the Mediprin guarantee.
If two Mediprin don't relieve minor arthritis pain better than two regular aspirin, you get your money back.
Strong promise?
Strong medicine.
The medicine that concentrates the power of ibuprofen into these potent little caplets.
The medicine that guarantees better relief than regular aspirin.
Better arthritis pain relief. That's the Mediprin guarantee.
They know they want to win. They look at the judge and they ask for it.
The show dog begins with what you feed it.
I mix the pedigree with the pedigree meal time because the dogs enjoy it.
It's the perfect combination.
These are champions. They deserve the best.
Pedigree. Recommended by top breeders.
Right now you're just 90 seconds away from Chef Boyardee with microwave meals.
Chef Boyardee pasta hot and tasty and with no messy cleanup.
Chef Boyardee microwave meals.
Thank goodness in just 90 seconds.
This morning I was following a Sears service truck when it dawned on me.
I see Sears trucks all the time.
It also dawned on me that I hardly ever see a service truck from those so-called superstores.
So before you make that next big buying decision,
ask yourself what kind of service you'll get five years from now
or if they'll even be around to answer the phone.
That's one of the big reasons I feel better when I buy a major appliance or electronics from Sears.
And that's what they mean by your money's worth and a whole lot more.
This looks like something my mom would eat.
It's kind of quiet, conservative.
I don't think I can get into this.
I mean, it's just a bunch of flakes.
Hmm.
It doesn't taste the way it looks.
I like the way it crunches.
Maybe it's good because it's simple.
Wait, wait. Don't tell me. I'm just like my mother.
Kellogg's Corn Flakes.
Corn Flakes?
Taste them again for the first time.
I hope you'll be with us tonight.
Dan Miller will be live from New Orleans inside the Super Bowl
bringing you updates on goodness knows what
along with actress Karen Black and much more.
See you later tonight.
One, two, three.
On tour with Paul McCartney.
There is life after Beatles.
A special edition of 48 Hours Thursday.
Sammy Davis Jr. 60th Anniversary Celebration
Brought to you by
Dr. Pepper and your local Dr. Pepper bottler.
Dr. Pepper is just what the doctor ordered.
The good time, great taste of McDonald's.
AT&T, the right choice.
And Chrysler Corporation and the Chrysler Motorist
Black Dealers Association.
What do you like about your Eagle Premier?
Everything.
You mean the leather interior and the roominess?
I said everything.
So what's Premier got that other cars in his class don't they?
Me.
You test drove the Maxima?
You got it.
The Taurus and the Cressida?
Then you tried the Eagle Premier?
You got it.
What'd you think?
I got it.
All the phone cords that bind,
that hold your small business back.
Now AT&T can set you free with the first cordless phone
specifically designed for business.
The multi-line Merlin cordless.
It works with AT&T's small business phone systems
so you don't have to lose any quality to gain your freedom.
Set your business free.
Call 1-800-MERLIN-ATT for the new Merlin cordless.
Who's weather?
Kate.
Pitch a maroon as due up.
So Burns is going to have to do his pinch.
The only choice is John Kane.
Hey, kid.
Can't be the doc?
Burns has been reluctant.
It's Kane's friend to go with the younger players,
but he may not have a choice here tonight.
Now batting from around.
Kane.
I got into him.
This is Hubert Strohls.
Austrian downhill racer and Olympic gold medalist.
He's not afraid of extreme vertical drops.
He's not afraid of speeds over 90 miles an hour.
He's not afraid of anything except going slow.
But if you think he's tough,
wait till you see the guys at the ticket window
at the Olympics if you don't have your Visa card
because the Olympics don't take American Express.
Asa, it's every way you want to be.
We really missed you, man.
Really.
You were left all night long.
It was your kind of thing.
You made me laugh.
It was so embarrassing.
I haven't seen him in years.
It was great.
He still cracks me out.
I'll tell you one more time because I think I liked it.
I just did that.
We just did that, yeah.
No one helps you share the feelings like AT&T long distance.
I wish you could have been here, too.
AT&T, all you need to reach out.
I love chasing quarterbacks.
When you've got the style of Hanes socks,
who wants to run around and cleats?
Hanes, nothing else feels so right.
Like to try total?
Mom says grape nuts.
Hope you're hungry.
It takes four bowls of grape nuts
to get the vitamins in one bowl of total.
Total has 100% of a day's supply
of 12 vitamins and minerals.
You tell her.
Total, one bowl, 100%.
Red Lobster announces great new trios.
Six delicious trios you're going to love.
Terrific.
Like our large butterfly shrimp.
Lobster alfredo and scallops.
Love it.
Or our crab legs.
Juicy scallops and shrimp.
Let's go.
But hurry, our great new trios won't last long.
Red Lobster for the secret lover.
Try the trio with the unbeatable price.
Our Atlantic trio, just $6.99.
$6.99?
That's incredible.
On One Life to Live, the start of a love affair.
This is going to be a good trip.
Or the beginning of the end.
Oh.
It's an attraction that could be fatal.
You're perfectly safe in the boat.
Trust me.
You'll never forget the incident at Loom Lake
on One Life to Live.
Ford trucks.
The best.
Never a rest.
The first vehicle Henry Ford sold was not a car.
It was a truck.
Our full-size pickups were first with rear anti-lock brakes.
First with electronic overdrive transmission.
First with push-button four-wheel drive.
Now what does all this get you?
It gets you number one.
And if you keep doing it, you stay number one.
More people are driving the best-built,
best-selling American trucks than ever before.
Fresh in breath and taste great.
People who use plain-calamine lotions to relieve itches
or poison ivy are easy to spot.
But new-caladrial clear not only works better to stop the itch,
it dries this clear.
So nobody will ever spot you.
New-caladrial clear.
One man unwilling to forgive.
You break the law, it'll come running back to me.
The other unable to forget.
I swore an oath to my country,
not to what was going on over there.
Charlton Heston, Peter Strauss, Proud Men, Saturday.
China Beach will continue in a moment.
Can life come from lava?
Tomorrow on Good Morning America,
how a lava field blossoms into one of nature's miracles.
Then meet Vi Warshawski.
Kathleen Turner turns private eye in her new role.
We'll bomb back here on Good Morning America tomorrow.
You know, the Channel 7 newsroom is not unlike the community in which we live.
We are an eclectic mix.
Everyone comes from different backgrounds.
We are a boisterous, diversified group.
Everyone has their own ideas in the newsroom about how they think the day should go.
We tend to have loud laughs and loud debates.
I think the newsroom is a microcosm of the community.
We're really a cross-section of the Bay Area.
In a formal life, Sandy can be seen walking in the park,
wearing stirrup pants and stretch denim.
A deep, purple waterproof parka with an attic fleece lining.
And a black rubber backpack.
A line and a climb.
Jodie, who lives on Russian Hill, is talking to her brother Peter, who lives in Eureka.
Remarkably, this call costs 25% less than last month,
because Peter is in Jodie's bonus zone,
and Jodie just got call bonus from Pacific Bell.
Wherever you live in California, call us.
We'll check and see if call bonus can save you money too.
For 1-800-PAC-BELL, we're making things easier.
Another wimpy sandwich.
Not me. I've got vintage farms deli loafing.
It's got real sliced meat chunks.
Still going, nothing outlasts the energizer.
They keep going and going and go.
A better way to catch your zizz is on Sealy's new posturepedic sleep system,
designed to conform to your shape,
distribute your weight evenly, comfortably.
Only Sealy posturepedic has it,
so for a better night's sleep, better sleep on a Sealy.
Someone finally made oatmeal the way I like it.
He doesn't like oatmeal.
Oatmeal crisp is big, crispy flakes with oatmeal.
Little brown sugar, lots of crunchy almonds.
Don't you lie to your mother.
Look Ma, I'm eating my oatmeal.
Oatmeal crisp, oatmeal raisin crisp.
Look Ma, I found something for nothing.
Pop secret popcorn, free and specially marked boxes of oatmeal crisp and oatmeal raisin crisp.
Be sure and write them a nice email.
I'll see you next time.
Please, thank you Lord.
Now there's a new reason to put down those fizzy diet colas.
It's crystal light in a new shade.
Pink grapefruit.
Light and luscious with no carbonation.
Okay, sit down.
Ring side seats.
250 bucks.
This is gonna be great.
These days a good value is hard to come by.
Unless you come by KFC for the amazing double bucket deal.
For a limited time get a 10 piece bucket of chicken for 8 bucks and the seconds just 4 bucks.
Repeat 4 bucks.
The double bucket deal only from KFC.
He was rock's first and only king.
He had the fame, the cash, the women.
And he had the pills, the pains.
One woman saw it all, lived it all.
This is her remarkable story.
Priscilla Presley's devastating account of life and death in the eye of the storm.
Elvis and me, Sunday.
Here is a group of people who were going along doing what they do better than they'd ever done it before.
And someone came along and pulled the rug out.
It was a struggle for survival.
Peter Jennings reporting from the heart of Harlem Thursday.
Only 99 cents each.
McDonald's today.
The breakfast burrito only 99 cents each at McDonald's today.
The Pepsi Summit Chill Out gives us permission to let our hair down.
What is it? Chill out?
I don't know, but what else am I gonna do this summer?
It's games, promotions, fun, and free costs.
It's like Woodstock Man.
People in tight pants moving fast.
For my family, Tartar Control Aquafresh fights Tartar.
Who makes you feel this fresh?
Tartar Control Aquafresh helps remove plaque.
Tartar Control Aquafresh fights cavities.
And makes you feel this fresh.
Only Tartar Control Aquafresh is the fresh way to fight cavities, fight plaque, and fight tartar, all with one great aquafresh taste.
Tartar Control Aquafresh.
It fights tartar.
And makes you feel this fresh.
I've got great news for everyone who uses bleach to clean up the kitchen and bath.
New Clorox Cleanup is a bleach, specially designed for cleaning.
You see, Clorox added a special cleaner to bleach, so it cleans even better.
Now you can clean up stains, clean up germs, and clean up greasy dirt bleach alone leaves behind.
So, when you reach for a bleach to clean up, reach for the one with a special cleaner inside.
New Clorox Cleanup.
Cleans like bleach, only better.
Coming to ABC this fall.
The war is over.
A celebration has begun.
Boys have returned as men to open arms, to laughter, and to love.
Sir, the whole time I was over there, all I thought about was you.
How am I going to tell them?
Is she seeing someone else?
Is she what?
These are their stories of triumph.
This is an impressive record, soldier.
And despair.
They can't pay you less than other men on the line.
They can if I'm a janitor.
Their hope for the future.
Hank has been fighting a war, not dating.
Their dreams left behind.
Americans are wonderful people.
Linda, if you'd made an effort to pretty yourself up, you wouldn't have lost Mike to somebody.
They became wartime heroes.
Now, they've returned to the home front.
China Beach will continue in a moment.
Should government require business to guarantee parental leave?
They tried it in Rhode Island.
On ABC's World News Tonight this week.
This is a Channel 7 Newsbreak.
San Francisco police tonight are investigating why it happened.
A tour bus careened down a street and slammed into a childcare center in San Francisco.
The force was so tremendous, the bus smashed through the walls.
No one was in the childcare center.
The driver of the bus was killed.
One county in the Bay Area is looking at a new source of water to help offset the drought.
Rock stars are telling rock fans about the growing problem of hearing loss.
And what's hot in fashion?
Clothes that change colors all by temperature.
See it on 7 at 11.
Hey, listen to this.
In a blind test, women like new advanced formula agree conditioner as much as a salon brand, Nexisumetris.
So if one cost less, would you switch?
Agree. It's that good.
Tuesday.
I was more wondering about sex.
No reason not to have sex.
Sex is definitely in the mind.
Sex.
Call it what you will, it's still sex.
30 Something Returns Tuesday.
Are you ready?
Yes, I'm ready.
Get ready to feel softer.
Never thought I could ever feel so good.
Caress with its silky touch of bath oil leaves skin softer than soap can.
Are you ready?
Yes, I'm ready.
Get ready to feel your softest.
Never felt so right on a show tonight.
Before you dress, caress.
I won't wear anything without Cross Your Heart.
Because great looks start with Cross Your Heart.
With crisscross shaping, I always look better.
The Cross Your Heart bra.
Great looks start with Cross Your Heart.
From Playtex.
The fit that makes the fashion.
Hey, thanks man. Stay cool.
7-Up.
The Cool Spot.
Let me show you how the educated consumer can tell the difference between my deli meat
and Oscar Maya deli thin slices.
Now you can't go by looks or taste on a con of their both sliced fresh, real thin.
But my deli meat comes in this beautiful white paper.
See how nice you can write?
But Oscar Maya comes in this resealable bag.
You can't write nothing.
Presenting Oscar Maya deli thin slices.
Deli fresh taste without the deli.
Can you believe it when some margarine say buttery taste and there's no butter in them?
Craft touch of butter spread has rich creamy butter in it.
Just a touch.
Craft touch of butter.
A touch of real butter makes a real difference.
Hi, this is Susanne Summers.
All this week I'm hosting the new Into the Night.
I'm having John Schneider Country Singer and my old friend Norman Falkham Threes Company
check out Into the Night.
You