Okay. Hey, everyone. Welcome to the first interview that we're going to post on interconnects.
I'm really trying to bring more scientific voices into the AI discourse as media is covering
a lot these days. I'm happy to be here with Michael Poli and Tree Dow, experts in some
of these non-attention architectures that have been really blowing up in the last few
weeks of December. So, Michael, do you want to introduce yourself first?
Sure. Thank you. Thank you, Nathan, for inviting me. I do research at Together AI and was also
a PhD student at Stanford working with Stefan Orenmann and Chris Rea. That's how I met Tree as well.
If I had to choose, maybe I moved to a few different areas of research. If I had to choose
one, I like to research at the intersection of signal processing, dynamical systems,
and deep learning. Most recently, luckily, there's been more interest in efficient
architectures that use some of these principles to improve scaling along different axes
and to get new trade-offs at inference time.
Great. And Tree?
Hi, everyone. Thanks, Nathan, for hosting us. I'm really excited to be here. I'm Tree. I
finished my PhD at Stanford. I'm an incoming assistant professor at Princeton. Right now,
I'm Chief Scientist at Together AI. This is a startup working on AI infrastructure.
And I've been working at the intersection of machine learning and systems, so designing
algorithms that take advantage of the hardware that they run on. We're interested in long-range
dependencies, how to encode that into model, designing architectures that can
learn long-range dependencies. Yeah, really excited to be here.
Yeah. Okay. I think I'm going to just, I have some questions to dive right into this. I think
you two will kind of both answer them or someone can answer longer, whatever you want. I think to
start with, we should talk about maybe why attention works and what the limitations of
attention are. I think almost every person in tech, broadly, now knows that a transformer
is a model built with attention. And ChatGPT does that, but why is this so good? Even how
much of a transformer is built with attention? Are there other things going on? And what might
be challenges there? Right. So, you know, a transformer, which is this architecture that
powers most of the exciting applications that we're seeing nowadays, as you mentioned,
ChatGPT and so on. Attention is kind of the core layer there. And attention actually
became earlier around 2014, 2015, and then transformer came out, incorporating that focusing
a lot on attention with these MLP, interleaving MLP and attention. And I think the success largely
has been, they seem to be able to scale really well. So you can scale out the models with more
parameters, with more data. And that has been the recipe for success. It sounds obvious now, but
I think five years ago, that wasn't clear. So it seems like transformer architecture is a hugely
successful one. And a couple of reasons why it's successful. I think it's general enough that
it's able to learn a lot from data. And two, it's pretty friendly to hardware. There's no
kind of sequential dependency like previous RNNs. So as a result, you can run it well on GPUs,
TPUs. You can scale it up. It's very hardware efficient. I personally have worked on making it
more hardware efficient as well. So it's just kind of the recipe for success, which is
general architecture that scales well. If you're an NLP person, maybe you'll say to incorporate
some kind of inductive bias for it to protect. Personally, I think it's a very general architecture
that scales well and it's hardware friendly. Yeah, it's remarkable how it seems so obvious now.
And it's like, I think one of the things that studying this work is the context length becomes
a really interesting access to study alternatives to it. And essentially, Michael, do you want to
talk about that? I could babble, but you know more. Sure. Yeah, there are several points. I'll
start by saying that there's still great research trying to understand why, from first principles,
why is it that the transformer can learn these interesting circuits. People can study. They
pick apart the computational combination of different heads and transformers and so on.
So there's work on basically understanding transformers from programming language that is
encoded. But I think, as Trey mentioned, there are some very interesting design choices that
have gone into the transformer. This interleaving of attention in NLP is quite important.
And also, the transformer is essentially successful in the beginning because it encoded
these techniques that have been developed for RNN, Celestium, so these other classical NLP models
gating to modulate which information is absorbed into the model, gating to determine how quickly
something is forgotten in this recurrence of the RNN into a parallel form. It is easily a bunch
of jumps that can be easily, but not very easily, but can be optimized for RNN GPUs.
Yeah, this stuff's all great. I guess the specific thing that I had in mind is how
attention ends up being this kind of quadratic scaling in terms of cost when you have an input
sequence that you have. If you have an input sequence of length L and you want to output a
sequence of length L, essentially, if you zoom into the math and you look at what's happening
in inference in most of these libraries, you have this upper triangular attention matrix where you
say you can only look at the past entries of your text, and as you go through there then,
you end up getting this L squared relationship where the first token you can only look at one,
and then you end up looking at more tokens for each pass. And now we've been talking about
recurrent neural networks, and how does something that isn't attention get around the fact that you
want to look at all of the history of the text in your sequence? So if you write a long prompt to
chat GPT, you really want all that information to be encoded, and how can doing something other than
this dense attention matrix actually make that possible? Yeah. Right. Yeah, so you can go ahead.
Before attention, there was RNNs, right? And then RNNs, they processed text, which is fine.
And maybe they didn't scale as well, but yeah. Can you say briefly what a...
They processed text by encoding text. Can you say briefly what a RNN is and how it works?
Yeah, so these are recurrent neural nets that go back, I think, to the 80s. Maybe some of the
more famous ones are LSDMs, GRU. So they were pretty popular around 2012 to 2016 or so.
They were kind of state-of-the-art for translation, speech recognition,
I think NLP, they were a state-of-the-art, and they processed text kind of sequentially.
They see essentially one token, and then that changes their hidden state, and then they will
update the hidden state, and every time they see a new token. So I think it's kind of, in some sense,
mimicking how, for example, human brain process information, like you read the sentence or a
passage, and maybe it's like you're storing some information in your brain, and by the time you
finish reading the document, maybe you can answer questions about the documents without having to
refer to that document again. So RNNs kind of work that way. They process the text,
and then that changes the hidden state, and their hidden state is the representation that
can be used to either generate new tokens or classify the documents or whatnot.
These work well back in 2016 or so, but they've kind of fallen out of favor, empirically, they don't
do as well as Transformer, I think, and as you touch on Transformer, because of this kind of
quadratic scaling, you compare every token with every other token that comes before it,
it gives you this very kind of easy way to propagate information. And I think that's for a
reason why Transformer and attention does really well. But there's been more recently some of the
new RNN architectures that seem to do pretty well. So RWKV is, I think, one of the earlier ones,
you know, it's one, I really admire that project, you know, it's effort mostly from one person,
really going against the orthodoxy of Transformer, showing that RNNs can be pretty strong.
Who was the lead on that? I think it's this person,
Bo Peng, I think, and you know, it's an entire project, but I think it's pioneered by Bo Peng.
I think it's affiliated with Eluta AI and the Compute Sponsor by Stability and so on.
Yeah, I was reading this earlier. At a technical level, they try to replicate something like the
very key value lookup of attention with two linear RNNs to essentially be able to remove
the specific attention scaling potential problems and with two RNNs, which have this
better, like, long context behavior and different implementation rules.
I think, and they also, the paper, trained up to 14 billion parameters, which kind of leads
into some of the next questions. I was going to ask, I was going to ask Tree about Mamba and then
Michael about Stripe Tahina. I think you could go in either order. I think these came out about
a week apart and were these two language models kind of seen as being way closer than anyone
would expect. Essentially, Stripe Tahina came out and the evaluations were close to models
I've been training on all year, like Lama 2 and Mistral 7B, and I went in and I went to the
Together API and I did like side by side of Mistral versus Stripe Tahina and it's like,
it's a good language model. It answers most questions. There's no obvious failure modes.
I think maybe Michael, do you want to comment on that? I know it's another big project and then
we can go back to Mamba, even though it's slightly out of order in the chronological
the release cycle that happened. Sure. I guess I'll start by saying that
there's an interesting connection between all these new methods. There's this sort of convex set,
which has a center and there's this connection between linear attention,
so attention without the softmax, linear RNNs, and state space models, SSM.
So at some level, the mathematical formulation of this kind of base model here,
I'm not talking about the base architecture, just the fundamental model, is the same.
And then you can go in different directions and each direction has its own trade-offs.
You can go to the feature map direction, the kernel direction. So when you break down the
softmax, you take away the softmax, you can place on queries and keys, kind of the fundamental
the entities that compose your attention matrix, you can compose other kernel-like functions,
other functions that you hope would approximate whatever capability of attention you like.
You can do things like a Taylor approximation, Taylor expansion, for example.
And you have a slightly different perspective, but you get something that, again, is very similar.
You can go to time variance, so you take the RNN and you push this input dependence,
so the way the computation inside the linear RNN is conditioned by the input sequence,
and you can add things like gates. We've seen a lot of work, for example,
modernizing linear attention with additional gates that allow you to make better use of your
fixed state dimension. And then you have the third direction, at least in my mind,
is the one that pushes, that uses the convolutional form, that pushes more towards other types of
linear operators that are still associative, that are still allow you to train in parallel.
So here are things, time invariant systems, I can elaborate on any of these points,
but things that can switch between convolutions and recurrence, like this form model,
with additional gates, again. Striped IEna was born as a project from the IEna architecture,
which belongs to this third category that I just mentioned, and we're really trying to get the best
per-flop architecture that we could. And one principle that was validated over and over again,
and we're trying to understand better now, is that it seems composing, hybridizing different
layers, different blocks of different categories, and even full attention yields something that
is better than the individual components. So there seems to be a compositional aspect
of these models that we're trying to understand better, and this gives you a better
sort of pre-trained model per-flop. And with this model, we ran a whole suite of skating laws,
and so on. Hybridizing also gives you, since we wanted something that would be kind of usable
out of the box, it gives you a way easier time. When you're fine-tuning for longer contexts,
we can apply some of these techniques that have been developed for transformers, and kind of
surprisingly work for hybrids as well. So things like linear scaling for
rotary embeddings and so on, you can go into the details. So it was mostly a project,
what is the best, given the current landscape, what is the best we can do?
Yeah, that's a great description of it. I mean, the sentence in the blog that's like,
start training is optimized using a set of new model grafting techniques, enabling us to change
the model architecture during training, kind of felt like, to me, that there's a ton going on
there. And some of which you probably can't talk about, there's normal data. I don't think all the
data that was quite explained, like what the longer context data was, but it's like,
are you taking this from models, starting point from models that people would know,
and can you say any of that? I think even just the summary that it's a synthesizing recent work
into a strong model is great context for people. Yeah, well, that line, so we've,
given this explosion of primitives that, you know, described, and given sort of the
cost that it would require to evaluate all different combinations, we found ways to essentially
start training with a configuration and then continuing on with another configuration. I
think we'll have, we're going to have more work with paper. Yeah, there's so much cool work in
that area. So one of the, someone at AI2 is working on a project where they're essentially
trying to cut the Lama models in half and keep training them and things. It's just the wild west
out there with people trying to take strong models and make them smaller while still getting the
performance benefits of bigger models. I think that's a whole aside, but I wasn't expecting it to
show up when people, like you follow the social media, I've striped my, you know, people are like,
oh, non-attention models are finally good. And it's like, it covers up a lot of the details
that are very interesting about it, in my opinion. So, okay, it turned back to tree. I think Mamba
actually happened first among these. I did the, his reading back of social media. And it also was
very surprising to me. I think the largest model in the Mamba suite is 2.8 billion parameters,
if I remember correctly. And it was compared to a lot of the common benchmarks in open NLP. So
things like GPTJ, Pythia model suites and the scores on the benchmarks reported were really
strong. And I think if you want to start with the high level summary, and then I'm definitely going
to make you talk about the awesome new CUDA kernels and stuff that you had to write for this project.
Yeah, so this Mamba is a collaboration with, with Albert Gu, who's now, he was,
he's just doing it at Stanford. That's where we met. And he's now a professor at CMU.
And also at a startup. So it's a wonderful collaboration credit goes to him.
Yeah, Albert has been working on this line of work called state space models.
In some sense, as mentioned, it connects to things like linear tension,
linear RNN, convolution, neural nets. And that's what his PhD thesis is about. I've also worked on
state space for the past couple of projects. My, my angle is how to make state space more
hardware efficient and kind of increase their expressiveness. So it's wonderful working with
Albert. And there I think is more of a proof of concept, which is can state space actually do
as well as transformer on language. So we've seen previous papers showing state space could be better
on audio, could be better on some of the tasks on the long range arena. But language has always been
the most difficult to get to do well for state space models. And language is also kind of the
thing that people care about the most right now. So Mamba was more of a proof of concept, which is
hey, we want to show that state space can be competitive, or maybe even be some of the
transformers out there. So we validated that at the scale up to 3B, trained to 300B tokens.
So in absolute terms, you know, these are not very strong models. These are not yet models that you
would actually play with and expect it to do meaningful things. I think it's more of a,
more of an academic comparison in terms of architecture, it's like, hey,
training trained for the same amount of tokens, it does as well, or maybe slightly better than
some of the transformer out there. And that's, in particular, has been very exciting to us.
I think Albert's been pushing on this for a while. I've been pushing on this for a while. And I think
finally, it seems to finally be kind of close to gap or even surpass some of the transformer.
And it just, I think it opens up a bunch of opportunities. So inference could be way faster.
Maybe we would have different ways to understand how in-contact learning happens, etc.
So lots of, lots of future work, I would expect.
Yeah. Can you go into some of the, like, what does it actually take to implement some of these
new CUDA kernels? I just remember when this paper was announced, Sasha Rush, who's also very active
in this space, I recommended me to talk with you too, was tweeting about the types of files or
whatever. And in the paper, there's this discussion about how like the recurrent state needs to be
sufficiently expressive, but doing so in a certain type of memory is a problem.
Translate what this means to people thinking about GPUs and people thinking about these models
being scaled. Like, is it now much easier to scale these models because they work on GPUs?
Which GPUs were you using? Is there a bump that could come just from going to H100s or something?
Any of that? Yeah. So the line of work on state space,
sort of like S4 models kind of pioneered by Albert's work, they are in some sense
recurrent neural network, but they have a much larger state size. So the state size is whatever
kind of buffer that you're going to store information as you traverse or as you process
the sequence. In some sense, you can view Transformers doing that as well, where it's
keep the entire history. It's usually called the KV cache. It keeps the history and keep
referring to it. For RNNs, they have a fixed size state. For Transformers state, you can think of
the state size as increasing. And our intuition is that the larger the state size, the easier it is
for the model to do well. So basically, you have more space to store whatever you need to remember.
And so previous models like S4 and so on, they have an implicitly pretty large state size,
but they use the convolutional view to avoid having to materialize the state. So that was
wonderful. Michael has worked behind architecture, has used some of the same insight focusing on
convolution. Mamba, on the other hand, focuses on the recurrent view. So we wanted to put more
input dependency in the recurrence. We thought the thinking was that it was going to make it
more expressive and the model would do better. But that prevents us from using this convolutional
view that would make things efficient. So we had to figure out a different way to make things
efficient. And so I focused on making that efficient on GPUs. And so our thinking was,
instead of, okay, we're going to have a large state size, but we don't have to write to actual
GPU memory, like the HBM, where you can just keep that large state in a faster memory called S RAM.
You think of it as a cache. So if you're more familiar with CPUs, you just usually get cache and
RAM. So if you have large state, you can keep it in the cache. And by avoiding having to write it
down, you actually don't suffer too much if the state is large. So that's essentially the core
idea. Would this be due to like input, like having to move the data around being really slow?
Yes. Yes. That makes sense. That's a really common constraint in a lot of these things. And it's like,
I think one of the most insightful things I've had now with GPUs versus TPUs and stuff is how
mixtures of expert models doesn't work very well on TPUs just because you have to like,
that essentially add a mixture of expert at a basic level. There's a routing layer that you
learn and then multiple feedforward layers that you can choose from. And when you're distributing
this, the feedforward layers could end up on a different TPU node and TPUs communicate with their
neighbors. So TPUs take a big hit relative to GPUs where within video and video clusters,
everything's connected so much more. And then it's easy to do that sort of distributed training.
That's super interesting. And it's like, do you think there's going to be,
I guess this is really where I want to open the conversation of like, what is this going to
happen in 2024 in this space? Are bigger players going to move in and be exploring this? My take,
seeing how good the long context learning could be and a fundamental limit is that systems like
ChatGPT are going to use a transformer model for most tasks. And then if you need to do
summarization, you might do a long context specialized architecture. And then we could even
see a whole quiver of architectures behind something that you're using. But I think
it's just like, is attention going to be dethroned? Is Sasha Rush somehow going to win this bet that
everyone wants following in the area? What are you thinking about, either of you?
I think it's a very, very strong architecture. And there's a proven recipe, right? You know,
people scaling to a trillion of parameters. Right now, if you want, you say,
well, I just want the best performing model that runs most efficiently on my hardware,
that has the most support on the software side. The transformer is a safe bet. I think it's here
to stay. But I think there are new ideas like state space, China, so the linear attention,
ideas from linear attention, I think they're coming in. We've seen, as Michael mentioned,
that mixing some of these components seem to improve performance. We're validated at, I think,
seven B scale, but maybe it might even work at larger scale. I think people tend to be
conservative and focusing too much on model architecture might not be worth their time.
Like the LIMAR architecture is very, very strong. Most people are doing off of that. They're
focusing on data. They're focusing on infrastructure, which makes sense. I think on
my side personally, the other stuff is just plain interesting. There are more, I would say niche
use cases, niche for now, where some of these alternative architectures are interesting,
things like long contacts, different domains like audio and genomics.
There's just plain interesting scientific questions you can ask, whether it follow
instruction just as well, whether it's fine to interest as well. Does it play well with
quantization and so on? There's just plain interesting research questions we can ask.
Now on the production level, I think transformer is still incredibly strong, very well supported,
both hardware and software. But I think some of these new ideas are coming in and people might
start putting them as part of component in the transformer. Maybe we'll still call them
transformer, but they'll just have more layers and just attention and LPE.
Yeah, I 100% agree with you. So attention as a computational primitive is not going anywhere
anytime soon. It's just a very efficient and a very convenient way to increase
the effective state of your sequence processor. So at some level, if you're working with a model
that only has a fixed state in each of its sequence mixers, you have an assumption and
your assumption is that you only need so much information in the sequence. So there's always
a tradeoff between the ratio of the state dimension, the sequence length, as you push
things to the extreme, either model sizes, so as you make the model bigger, wider, effectively
introduce more states and sequence length. Some of these margins, some of this is speculation,
but some of these margins will disappear, some of the tradeoffs will change, especially 14, 30,
some of these very fat models. But certainly, either whether that's hybridizing or some kind
of new block, we're certainly going to see some more innovation. That's really exciting.
My personal, if I had to make a prediction is that architecture design will get more
interesting or more complex. There's going to be more to do.
Yeah, I mean, this year, it's like, I got some 10 minute clock that's fine for us. I think with
mixture of experts and this being popular as a state-state model, this is all just really within
a few months outside of OpenAI. They've been doing mixture of experts for a lot longer than
everyone, but in terms of open and academic communities, no one's really tried to do RLHF
on mixture of experts. It should just work, but we have to learn all these things. And then the
model grafting is becoming more of a real thing. That's super interesting. And it's just, I agree
that it's just fun to follow. And hopefully, it gives academics and scientists more ways to
influence the conversation where in industry, it's just about scaling and bigger models where we
could maybe do specific things better, which I'm telling open source companies to do with
their language models anyways, like if they want to have a business model, they need to have an edge.
So this all fits into that kind of narrative pretty well with my regards.
Is there anything else you guys are following in ML? It doesn't have to be about state-space
models. What's exciting for you broadly for next year?
Yeah, personally, I think data is still the most important thing. We're thinking a lot about how
data influences the model performance, like really teasing that out, either having some
of the synthetic tasks that correlates very well with model performance has been kind of the
motivating examples in a lot of our papers and work has been focusing on synthetic tasks,
or having maybe smaller data sets that kind of make it easier to really understand what's
really going on. So I think personally, my focus is going to be on data for the next little bit.
All the architecture stuff is fun. Making that hardware efficient is fun, but I think
ultimately it's about data. If you look at the scaling law curve, the different
monarchitectures generally have the same slope. They're just different offset.
Seems like the only thing that changes the slope is the data quality.
I love that point. That does seem true. I have the plot from Mamba in this blog post that I'm
writing, which is just a little bit above. Same slope.
Yeah, maybe add data. Data is really interesting. So miniaturizing architecture design, finding,
breaking down what tasks are involved into, for example, language modeling and trying to
package them into something that can be used to iterate, something that's quite exciting.
That was one of the main techniques that was used for this zoology paper that also looks into
some of these different behaviors. Personally, I'm also really excited about new applications,
scientific applications, the genomics work, but even more engineering-focused.
We're seeing a shift. Right now, language is still the domain that gets most clicks,
most interest, but I think that will evolve over time.
Some of these other applications offer, even just talking about architectures,
they offer completely different design space. I'm excited to look into it.
Yeah, everyone talks about language, but I feel like images and entertainment and videos are the
things that are so obviously going to generate so much value to me. I don't know the ceiling on
language, but when you could access a somewhat local text and video model at your homework
station, that's tailored to your preferences. The amount of value that that creates is totally
astronomical. I'm excited. I started playing around with these where I'd take text of the
blog and convert it to dolly images and convert it to a video with generated audio all with one
Python script. That's really easy to do, so I agree with your more than language. It's fun to
have that view. These things actually do work really well in your experience when you stitch
all of them together. It's not that good. The dolly images are pretty similar, but I'm doing
something really naive where I literally take the text and have a system prompt. It's like,
you're generating a series of images for visualizing a blog post, and it generates various
all the machine learning thumbnails that you see everyone using. There are variations of that.
The fun ones are whether it's about llama or mamba or something, and then they generate
animals in them, which is good. I think I could get much better at it and have a better segmentation
system for the paragraphs and or have chat to BT summarize them or something like that. But I
just know that within a year, it's going to be a text-to-video API, and I'm just going to switch
it, and it's going to be great. I'm laying the groundwork for infrastructure to have a
multimodal content distribution, really, and I just expect it to become very fun. Even the text
of voice is pretty good, I think. I don't have a studio, but once you have a studio, it's going
to be able to generate perfect audio for whatever you want. Another one of my dreams that is bad
for young students is I want to be able to give a slide deck to a script that returns the five-minute
conference video that no one ever watched, just based on a GPT-4 reading the slide deck and voicing
yourself. Those are the silly things that I have time to do because I'm not a professor.
Yeah, I think these advances, these systems, they do generate a lot of economic value,
and we're seeing that already. Lots of companies are now switching to using these things, and I
think it's going to change the way we work, as you mentioned, the way we work, the way we entertain,
so I'm just very exciting future.
Yeah, anything else? Well, thanks for coming. Try to get you guys as much attention as I can
bring. You never know, it'll go viral these days, so I think this was a great conversation.
People are really hungry for basic intuitions in the area, so this is good.
Yeah, thank you, Nathan. It was a pleasure.
Absolutely. Thank you for inviting us, and maybe if there are more questions,
is there a way to collect them to provide readers with listeners with an address or
something, happy to answer anything? Yeah, I'll include contact info in the post in
various ways. This will be out there. You'll get your comments on Substack, YouTube, Twitter. It's
a mess. You've got to pay attention to 10 million streams of information these days, but you'll get
contacted by people. Thankfully, for some reason, people read my stuff, but here we are. So thanks for listening.