One of the most common video formats on YouTube is where a content creator recommends you
other YouTubers to follow other related YouTubers to follow other than his channel.
And this is very common in the Linux space as well where Linux YouTubers will create
a video giving you their top 5, top 10, top 20, whatever, other Linux YouTubers that you
should go and check out and subscribe to and watch their videos.
And I've done these types of videos too in the past, I haven't made one recently, but
one thing that's kind of common with these types of videos is that people typically recommend
the same channels.
It's typically the big channels, the really big channels sometimes, channels that if
you're a Linux enthusiast, you probably already know about, right?
I don't need to tell you guys about channels like Brian Lunduk or Luke Smith or Jupiter
Broadcasting.
You know, I don't need to tell you about Level 1 Tech.
You guys probably know about those big channels, Quidd's Up and Joe Collins and everything
like that.
I don't need to send you to those channels.
If you have been following a little bit of Linux on YouTube, no doubt you've come across
videos of those guys.
So today I wanted to give, really I wanted to shine a spotlight on some of the smaller
channels, some of the channels that I don't think get enough views and subscribers.
I think they put out great content and for whatever reason, maybe it's because their
channel is a little newer or it's because they focus on a really small niche topic for
the most part.
I think these channels, I'm going to discuss 12 channels today that I think are greatly
deserving of far more views and subscribers than they currently get.
That's our topic for the day.
Alright so first things first, if you guys go to my YouTube channel homepage and if you
click on the Channels tab in my page, it will show you every single YouTuber that I'm subscribed
to.
I'm subscribed to probably a hundred different Linux and tech related YouTubers and of course
a lot of these are a lot of the big channels you probably know about and of course some
of these are the smaller channels that I'm going to be discussing today.
Again, many of these you probably already heard of, many of them you haven't though.
So check out the Channels tab here at the DistroTube YouTube page and you'll see everybody
that I'm subscribed to, good channels.
Today though I want to focus on some of the smaller channels that I don't think get enough
attention and part of the reason some of these guys don't get enough attention is the channels
are new and this is one example, old tech bloke, OTB.
His channel just started a month ago, maybe two months ago, he messaged me actually on
Mastodon, he watches some of my videos and he's following me on Mastodon.
I've conferred with old tech bloke a few times and I've watched many of his videos
he's put out in just under two months and this guy is great.
He's very knowledgeable, he has good equipment, good audio equipment, good video equipment,
especially for a beginner YouTuber.
Certainly he's got far more, far better equipment than I started with when I started my channel
and his videos are great, his content's great, solid audio, he's got a good radio kind of
voice and I can't recommend this guy enough.
He's only got 46 subscribers because again his channel is brand new but I can highly
recommend you guys check out old tech bloke, give him a subscribe, watch some of his videos
again, knowledgeable guy and a wide range of topics.
I mean he's got stuff on here about MX and Debian and Slackware and what's the best video
editor on Linux and he does good comparison by the way, I watched that video where he
compared Kaden Live, OpenShot and Shotcut, good content.
So old tech bloke is the first channel I want to recommend to you guys, keep it techy, keep
it techy.
He has 603 subscribers, he's kind of slowed down on his video content creation here lately,
I'm assuming it's probably work and life related, he's only posted one video really
in the last couple of months but hopefully he'll get back on track but keep it techy
is great.
If I go to the about tab I can read a little bit of what keep it techy is about, keep it
techy is a technology channel started by Josh and he helps raise awareness about the Linux
operating system, blah blah blah, I won't read the blurb but basically I can tell you
his videos typically are a little more advanced, I won't say too advanced but he does some
server related stuff, of course some desktop related stuff, again he does stuff about audio,
video and Linux, most YouTubers, most Linux YouTubers are going to cover audio and video
on Linux because that's a big part of what we do.
But again a good mix, good mix of content from this guy because I mean he does everything
from really simple basic like installations and simple terminal commands that you should
know all the way into some more advanced server related topics and once again much like old
tech bloke keep it techy, he's got good equipment, he's got a good microphone, his audio is good
and once again he's got a good speaking voice, a good radio voice and that's so important
on YouTube or on radio but especially what we're talking about today YouTube if you
don't have a good speaking voice combined with pretty decent audio equipment nobody's
really going to listen to you and keep it techy definitely deserves more eyeballs on
his stuff.
And the next YouTuber I want to recommend, Linux related, Red Robo's Workshop, Rob does
some good stuff here, he's again got a perfect radio kind of voice, topics, he focuses pretty
heavily at least here lately on OpenSusa as far as his video content, he does a lot of
stuff about KDE, occasionally he does some off topic stuff, he showed his aquarium with
some shrimp in a recent video but Rob's great, Rob's a good community member too, he comments
on a lot of other Linux related YouTube channels, you guys probably seen Red Robo's Workshop
you know posting and my live streams and many other folks live streams when I do a live
stream or whoever.
But Rob is a great guy, great content and deserves far more subscribers than just 361.
Nicholas Bernstein, now Nicholas here is kind of a newer channel again, he's already got
though 549 subscribers once again, good, good voice, good audio, good video and very knowledgeable,
he's a really good teacher.
Like he explains things very well, he focuses on sysadmin, IT kind of stuff, he focuses on
preparing people for that field and again his explanations are great, you know he doesn't
rush through explanations, kind of like I try to do often times on my tutorial videos,
I kind of take my time talking through stuff, I don't just blow through it talking as fast
as I can, because that is kind of antithetical to trying to cheat somebody that has no idea
about what you're talking to and I think Nicholas is a fantastic teacher, deserves far more
subscribers than the 549 he currently has as of recording this video.
Dark One, Dark One Matt is just a fantastic entertaining guy and the great thing about
Dark One here is he focuses on a wide range of topics which I think is a real benefit,
because I think some of these channels that we're talking about today, they stay small
because they focus on a very tight niche as far as a topic where Dark One covers Linux
related stuff, Linux news, Linux Rants, he covers other tech related stuff not related
to Linux, I mean he covers things like Microsoft Surface Tablets and things like that, he talks
even about Mac I think occasionally, of course Windows and of course he does some gaming
stuff, he's a big gamer, covers Windows gaming and Linux gaming and what I really like about
Matt is he's entertaining his hill, he does a lot of reaction videos where he basically
trashes somebody for being dumb, especially people that make really dumb videos about
Linux which I love, so I really love his reaction videos, he does also music video reactions
which are pretty cool and again he's got 821 subscribers as I'm recording this and I think
he deserves far more attention than he's currently getting.
Colin over at PCTLC, now you guys I know many of you guys like when I do my distro review
type videos and I don't do that many of those type videos anymore because I don't find
them that interesting, they don't interest me as far as that's not the content I really
just want to create, but a lot of people out there do want to create that and Colin over
at PCTLC does a great job with those installation videos and review videos, reviewing various
distros, some of the recent ones are Debbie and Tanny's covered probably for the Big Daddy
Linux challenge and they covered Arch, Open Mandreva, most of these are probably following
the schedule of Big Daddy Linux which we may talk about here in a minute, but Colin over
at PCTLC, great guy, just awesome Linux community member and puts out some fantastic content
again, like, subscribe, share, do whatever you can to help out Colin there.
Sudo Reboot, now Sudo Reboot does nothing but live streams as far as I know of and he
does live streams like almost every day and he typically does long live streams typically
an hour, two hours, three hours or more sometimes and he's not your typical, oh I'm just going
to do a live stream and I have absolutely nothing to talk about, no he's great, he
interacts with the YouTube chat and the community but he also has real content on his live streams
like he does Linux-y stuff during his live streams, you know, reviewing distros and
various software programs and things, talks about the news and Sudo Reboot is one of these
guys, he's been around for a long time too as far as on YouTube and I don't know why
he only has 541 subscribers, I think that's criminal, criminally underrated actually,
you guys please go subscribe to Sudo Reboot, he is absolutely fantastic, great guy as well.
Now this is a bit of a bigger channel but I include it in the list because I still think
it's vastly underrated, Destination Linux, the Destination Linux podcast with Zib, Michael,
Dasgeek and Noah is fantastic, so they put out a weekly podcast and you know typically
about two hours long, they record it live, typically you can watch the live recording
and then they go back and edit it and post it a couple of days after the live recording
as far as the edited podcast version of Destination Linux, but I think it's maybe the premiere
Linux podcast out there and you know they got a pretty good subscriber base, you know
over 4,000 subscribers but I do think that that's very underrated and I think there's
probably a lot of you guys that are watching this video here that probably have not heard
of Destination Linux and if you have not heard of Destination Linux, please check it out,
Big Daddy Linux, we were talking about that a minute ago with PCTLC, how his distro reviews
cover usually the weekly distro review from Big Daddy Linux live, Big Daddy Linux live
is a weekly live show, every Saturday night you get a couple of dozen people joining live
on a video conference, anybody's free to join, anybody from the community can join them live
on camera, plus you've got a couple of hundred people joining them live in the YouTube chat
every Saturday night and it is great, it is one of the great community things going on
as far as Linux YouTube community, Rocco Big Daddy Linux is really one of the leaders
as far as the Linux YouTube community, he really brings people together in a way nobody
else is doing and I really want to commend Rocco, I think he is just, I can't say enough
about how important Rocco Big Daddy Linux is to the Linux YouTube community so definitely
subscribe, check out Big Daddy Linux live every Saturday night and here lately Rocco has been
doing these Linux spotlights where he interviews people from the community, Linux YouTubers,
Linux developers, just Linux personalities, he's been doing that and those shows are
great as well, check out Big Daddy Linux, again another bigger channel but I think is
just woefully underrated is HexDSL, HexDSL has over 5,000 subscribers, definitely the
biggest channel I'm covering today but I think this guy should have 10 times the subscriber
base, great guy, Hex is just fantastic, he's entertaining, fun to watch, does pre-recorded
stuff, does live streaming, good content, good mix of content, focuses heavily on Linux
gaming which is why the subscriber base is not that high so Linux itself is a really
niche topic, if you have a channel that focuses primarily on Linux you're not going to get
that many subscribers, there's just not enough of us Linux users out there, if you focus
on Linux gaming as a topic, wow that's a niche inside a niche and I think that's part
of the problem but don't let the topic of the channel fool you, I mean he is focusing
heavily on Linux gaming but he does a mix of content, he looks at various terminal applications
recently he did a video about Ranger, I know he's covered various tiling window managers
on his show, sometimes he does tutorials, he shows you how to do things like in the
shell and things like that, so there is some tutorial stuff, some nerdy stuff other than
just the gaming stuff and I find his content some of the best out there, I try to catch
as much of Hex DSL's videos as I can, I can't watch everybody, I don't have time to watch
every video from everybody I'm subscribed to but when Hex puts out something I typically
watch it and I think you guys really if you're not subscribed check him out, well that was
the last Linux related channel but I wanted to cover two channels that really aren't
Linux centric but they're pretty close to Linux that I wanted to cover them, first of all Robo
Nuggy, everything free BSD, yes this is a BSD channel and that is why he doesn't have that
many views and subscribers is because think about how niche Linux is, now think about how
niche BSD is, like we probably have a hundred times more Linux users than BSD users and so
just he's fighting an uphill battle as far as getting views and subscribers but if you are
interested in BSD at all please subscribe to Robo Nuggy, even if you're not that interested in BSD
I mean some of what he talks about is applicable to those of us that run Linux on the desktop and
especially Linux as a server so please check out Robo Nuggy and Greg Hurrell, now a bigger
channel he's got over 4,000 subscribers this is not strictly Linux content though, his content is
Vim, he covers the Vim text editor, many of you guys are probably interested in Vim, I know I
cover Vim a lot on my channel you guys ask me about Vim a lot, you're looking for good content
centered around Vim, you know if you're a potential programmer developer and you're looking to harness
the power of Vim please subscribe to Greg Hurrell, a little bit off the beaten path with the Vim
centric channel Greg Hurrell and the free BSD centric channel with Robo Nuggy but I think all
those guys deserve a ton of views but obviously some of the bigger channels that I didn't cover
because they get covered a lot I mean you guys can check out everybody I'm subscribed to there's
always a chance you haven't heard of some of the bigger channels I'm subscribed to I would tell
you I'm often shocked like when I do if I do a colab with somebody even a bigger channel and you
think so much of our content you know I did a colab one time with Luke Smith and you would think
most people that watch my stuff have heard of Luke Smith but no I had people it's like who is Luke
Smith when I announced that I was gonna do that colab with Luke I'm sure Luke had a ton of people
that watch his stuff that had never heard of me so just because they're bigger channels I know some
of you guys probably have never heard of you know Chris Titus Tech and tutorial links and some of
these really big channels just go to my youtube page click the channels tab and anybody that you
haven't heard of that I'm subscribed to please check them out all great channels and I think
because of the community aspect we really want all these people to grow as content creators
because at the end of the day what we really want is more awareness we want to spread more
awareness about this thing we love that is Linux and before I go this show was made possible by
Ansem first Chris second Chris Dylan George Jack Mitchell Natek Philip Rob Robert Tony Sam and
Willie the producers of the show they are my highest tier patrons over on patreon without
these guys this show would not be possible I also want to thank each and every one of those names
you see on the screen that ever growing list of names those are the list of supporters I have over
on patreon these guys they keep the lights on they keep the channel going I want to sincerely
thank each and every one of you guys you'd like to support the channel please consider doing so
you'll find me at distro tube over on patreon okay guys peace