Why all the hate for Ubuntu? Why is it when you talk Linux in Linux forms,
IRC chats, various social media sites, why is it anytime Ubuntu comes up all the haters also show up?
Ubuntu has a ton of shade that is thrown at it and is it deserved? That's the topic for today.
So in my opinion I think that the Ubuntu haters do so mainly for one of two
reasons and I'm talking about broadly speaking one of two reasons. They either hate on Ubuntu
due to elitism you know that superiority complex tribalism or they do it because they see Ubuntu
as going in the wrong direction that Ubuntu as a project canonical as a company the company behind
Ubuntu is misguided and they're going in a direction that is just wrong wrong for Linux wrong
for free and open source software so let me tackle both of those topics. Let's start with the ones
that hate on Ubuntu because of elitism. Ubuntu of course is considered a new user-friendly
distribution certainly many if not most Linux users new to Linux users they start out with Ubuntu.
I did most of you guys did it's the most popular desktop Linux distribution it's certainly one of
the easiest to get installed and working out of the box especially nowadays when I first used it
12 13 years ago you know there was some little bugs and paper cuts in it but nowadays for the most
part Linux has gotten a lot better these things are just so easy to install you click okay three
or four times 10 minutes you're done but when Ubuntu first came on the scene you know there
weren't a lot of these easy to install new user-friendly distros and Ubuntu became very popular
very quickly and I think this really led to some of these haters the the Linux users that are hating
on it maybe because they have this this feeling of superiority to all those Ubuntu noobs especially
once you move to a different distribution right because you start out with Ubuntu and then you
hop a little bit right and you feel like you graduate to the next level because you move to
Demian or Fedora or Arch or Slackware whatever it is you move to and you feel like you're a better
Linux user than that Ubuntu noob you know he's still just a a Linux peasant because he's on that
easy distribution my distribution I had to work a little bit to get this thing installed now it's
certainly easy to be like that to be that elitist arrogant snob that a-hole right especially if you
started on Ubuntu and then you moved away to another distro I can see how you could be tempted to act
that way and because now you see that you've climbed this wrong on a ladder to this next level you
you keep climbing that ladder and you think eventually you're going to achieve elite status
because you're now using more of a quote power users distro you're not on that easy distro you're
not using noob Ubuntu and so now you want to flex a little right you want to tell all those Ubuntu
peasants how much better you are because you're running Arch now or whatever it is you haven't
been running so you guys though don't you got to understand that the elitists out there that are
out there spouting this nonsense just don't listen to them don't give them the time of day don't
respond to them they're just trolls at the end of the day distro choice doesn't matter it doesn't
matter what those guys are running it doesn't matter what you're running their distro of choice
isn't superior to yours and if you're running Ubuntu Ubuntu isn't inferior to those other distros
that those elitists are running now you guys know my mantra for the channel has always been if it's
working for you use it and for millions tens of millions of Linux users out there Ubuntu is working
just fine for them so use it use the right tool for the right job is another one I always say
and certainly for casual desktop computer users Ubuntu is a fantastic choice so the second group
of haters I want to address are the ones that think Ubuntu is going in the wrong direction that
everything Ubuntu does everything canonical does is the wrong thing and it really what really started
it all I think was around 2010 when GNOME 2 reached end of life and GNOME was moving to GNOME 3
and Ubuntu decided to create their own desktop environment called Unity because GNOME 3 was
horrible they didn't want to go that direction most users didn't want to go to GNOME 3 anyway
you couldn't still use GNOME 2 I mean you could but it's no longer being developed no longer being
supported so canonical was like well you know what we'll create our own desktop environment we're
going to create Unity and the first couple of versions of Unity were quite buggy but you know
it got really good really quickly like you know after about a year of development Unity really
became quite stable and to be honest Unity was popular like again millions and millions of
Ubuntu users out there and they many Ubuntu users if you installed Ubuntu past say 2011
all you knew was the Unity desktop environment you never knew the old GNOME 2 desktop anyway
and for many of those users when a Unity went away they were really upset why is because they
loved Unity so Unity really wasn't a hated desktop environment there's a few people that didn't like
it because there's always going to be people out there that resist change there were people that
loved GNOME 2 and once GNOME 2 went away we got to be angry at somebody but being angry at canonical
or being angry at Ubuntu for the death of GNOME 2 is quite frankly retarded right the GNOME project
ended GNOME 2 and moved to GNOME 3 if you want to be angry about the death of GNOME 2
you know direct that anger to the right people and the Ubuntu devs are not the people you should
have been angry at another big controversy that people really hate Ubuntu about was when
during the Unity years they had the Amazon lens and you know there was some telemetry in that
because it's connecting to Amazon Amazon's tracking some of what you're searching because
it's a search feature and people called it spyware which is ridiculous it's not spyware I mean if
that's spyware then every time you use the Google search engine Google spyware every time you fire
up something like Steam or Netflix anything like that I mean they're tracking everything you do too
I mean nobody calls Steam spyware or Netflix spyware but Ubuntu has this Amazon search
lens in Unity and now all of a sudden Ubuntu is spyware I mean how ridiculous is that now the
Amazon lens thing I didn't personally like it and a lot of people complained about it because
it was kind of buggy and it was just kind of clunky anyway and the Ubuntu folks did listen
and they created the ability to turn that thing off and uninstall it but a lot of people years later
way past when they got rid of the Amazon lens and when Unity died people are still talking about
the Amazon spyware in Ubuntu guys check yourselves and then there are the people that love to bring
that canonical and Ubuntu have the NIH syndrome the not invented here syndrome
basically that Ubuntu and canonical they're always trying to reinvent the wheel you know
instead of creating their own desktop environment and a knit system and display server and package
manager and yada yada yada they should just use what's already out there they should just use the
products that these other distributions have created instead of creating their own it's just
duplication of work and the only reason they're doing it is because they're jealous of those
other projects and they don't want to use this superior technology they want to create their
own thing because they can't admit that red hat made something better or susa made something better
or whatever the distro is out there so people love to bring up you know things like upstart
Unity, mirror, snap packages as being a symptom of the not invented here syndrome okay so real
talk here when canonical and Ubuntu created upstart there were no other knit systems out
there other than sysv you know and of course gen2 was I think still using open rc still are
but we didn't have system d back then right and so saying that upstart that canonical created
upstart for a not invented here kind of scenario is ridiculous because they had already been using
sysv and yet initially and then they created upstart to move to upstart and guess what red hat
thought so highly of upstart that they shipped with upstart in those particular versions of
rail back then the red hat enterprise linux and a lot of people don't realize that that rail
actually did ship with upstart until of course red hat created system d but a lot of people were
like well canonical is just inventing a new and a knit system they should have just been using system
d system d didn't exist when they first started creating and developing upstart the unity desktop
environment again gen2 died they had to go a different direction no matter what direction
they went might as well create unity you didn't want to go to genome 3 genome 3 was garbage and
it was going to be a completely foreign interface to everybody as well besides not invented here
i mean every desktop environment project on the planet whether it's genome kde xsce lxq
mate cinnamon i guess they all suffer from not invented here syndrome because why are they
creating new desktop environments just pick one of the ones already out there right i mean
that argument's just stupid the mirror display server weyland was being developed then 10 years
ago but weyland wasn't ready and what canonical created mirror for is because they were doing
the phone they wanted a display server that could work across all devices phone desktop tablet
weyland couldn't do that so they created mirror and then snap packages people love to complain
about snap packages and some people complain maybe ubuntu should just drop snaps and go with flat
pack which okay and you ask them you know why should ubuntu do that is because ubuntu is doing the
not invented here thing they should just go with the standard the standard is flat pack ubuntu
created snaps before flat pack or app images even existed they started working on snaps actually way
back in the ubuntu phone days they were called click packages back then so again this is not a
not invented here type scenario and i think the whole not invented here argument is just stupid
that's why i've never uttered that phrase before making this video you will never see me talk about
not invented here and writing or on video because it's a stupid argument free and open source
software everything we do could be accused of being part of not invented here in recent years
you know people love to bring up the telemetry in ubuntu as far as they're asking for telemetry
information when you first install it they want to know some information about your computer what
hardware you're running you know the resolution of your monitor things like that and they ask you for
permission upfront it's not sneaky or it's not shady in any way they basically tell you exactly
what they want to know from you and you can actually go and read the reports of that telemetry
that they're getting from the users and i hear people compare that kind of telemetry that ubuntu
is upfront asking you about hey we just want to know what what the specs of your hardware are
i hear people comparing that to the spyware that is built into windows 10 now over exaggerate much
i think a lot of this has to do with this tribalism you know it's ubuntu is so popular and you guys
that are not running ubuntu i'm not running ubuntu but you know you're running a less popular
distribution right maybe a really small distribution that most people haven't heard of it doesn't have
that much of a user base and you think maybe by tearing down ubuntu a little bit you can grab
some of those users and bring it over to you know joe bob's distro or whatever it is you happen to be
running and if you're gonna try to steal users you know from another distribution by tearing it down
you're going to go for the most popular one every time that is just common sense that's just human
nature right you want to punch up you don't want to punch down you want to go for the guy on top
you're not going to beat up the guy on bottom nobody i've never seen a thread that somebody
started on how bad something like nitrix linux is or voyage or linux or sparky linux and then have
hundreds of people join that thread and trash it yeah it's so horrible nobody cares right because
those distros they don't have much of a user base why bother right but ubuntu is so much more popular
than all the other linux distributions that's the one you go after me personally i like ubuntu
i started as an ubuntu user i've used ubuntu on many machines over the years i still use ubuntu
on web servers all the time if ubuntu lts server is offered as an option i almost always go with it
when i have family and friends that have windows machines that they want to wipe out and move to
linux because windows is slow and now it's all virus riddled on their their laptops and nothing
is working you know a lot of times i put ubuntu or some ubuntu base distribution on those machines
and every single person i put on ubuntu on a new machine you know never seen linux before they
they just loved it they're blown away even if i told them about all these complaints that people
have they wouldn't care because what do they care about gnometoo going away and unity coming around
you know that that ship is done sealed we're past that chapter the amazon lens and unity like none
of this stuff even matters anymore and it's just strange that people still bring this up
now before i go this show was made possible by chris dj donnie dylan george heplenate lambda
michael michael omri rob shawning willy the producers of the show these guys they're my
highest tiered patrons over on patreon without these guys this episode me addressing why so many
people throw shade on ubuntu this this episode wouldn't have been possible the show is also
brought to you by all these other names you're seeing on the screen right now all those guys
they help support me over on patreon if you'd like to support the channel look for distro tube
over on patreon all right guys peace