This is a question I've been working on for a long time now, and the last few years have
become, I would say, really quite exciting, and the central ideas have become more crystallized
in my mind than they had been before, and it's very much about using life as a guide
to the origin of life, which immediately sounds like it's tautologous in some way, that
it's, I could call it turtles all the way down, it seems as if there's an infinite regress
involved in that, but it begs the question, how can we possibly know what the answer is?
And if you take it almost literally and say, imagine that we had a time machine and we
go back to some time around the origin of life, what would we actually look for?
And the answer is, well, we would have no idea if we found some kind of green slime
or something, we wouldn't really know, was this the origin of life, was this just some
slime, was it on the path towards life, was it a failed experiment?
Actually what we really need to know, what we really need to have is a framework, a rigorous
intellectual framework which shows how a sterile non-living planet can give rise to
a living planet and we need to know what all the predicted steps would be along that
path and then how to test for them to see whether or not they actually have any substance
in them or not.
And so we'll never know how life started on Earth because it's a historical question
and we can't go back and if we did go back, as I say, we still wouldn't actually see what
the answer was.
What we need is this rigorous framework and that's where I think life as a guide comes
in because there is a spectrum and that spectrum starts somewhere almost unknowable, but let's
assume for the sake of argument that it was on the early Earth and that it was in Earth-like
conditions rather than in outer space somewhere or, you know, panspermia may have happened,
however, it tells us nothing about the conditions under which life can start.
So it's an assumption that life started on Earth and we know the other end of the continuum,
the other end of this continuum is life itself, cells like bacterial cells that have a genetic
code that have DNA and RNA and proteins and membranes and everything else we know about
cells.
So we know one end of the continuum and all we need to do is figure out the other end
and how to join it up.
Now what I'll argue very briefly then is that life is an extremely good guide to its own
origin and I'm going to break it into three sections.
One is energy, the second is metabolism, and the third is genetic information.
So I will try and address all three today.
Before I get going, I'm going to just orientate you with a few slides about what I mean by
energy and so on.
So this is, you could imagine it as a bacterial cell or you could see it as the mitochondria
in our own cells, but effectively what we're seeing here inside this lozenge-shaped thing,
if that is a cell, I'm showing it respiring and respiration is effectively taking something
like glucose, breaking it down through the Krebs cycle, and the Krebs cycle, you don't
need to know what it is.
All it's really doing is stripping CO2 and hydrogen out of food, out of any organic molecules.
Now the CO2 is a waste product which we simply breathe out, and the hydrogen is not in the
form of hydrogen, it's in the form of NADH in our own cells, but it's basically two
hydrogen atoms.
They are being split for physicists, we're going to get somewhere in the vicinity of
fundamental particles, so it's basically electrons and protons.
The electrons are passed to oxygen in the membrane, so it has effectively a current
of electrons within an insulating membrane through redox centers in that membrane, and
the current of electrons powers the extrusion of protons across the membrane, which is
what I'm showing, let me just get a pointer up on here.
So we have a charge on the membrane, the protons are positively charged of course,
and so we have a relatively positive charge on the outside of the membrane, relatively
negative inside, and that's known as the proton motive force.
It drives for example ATP synthesis, but it basically drives all work in cells, and that's
all we need to know.
We can put ATP aside for the time being and just think of we have an electrically charged
membrane that drives powers work in cells, and that I think is the fundamental thing
that we need to explain.
Why is it that cells work by having an electrical charge on the membrane that powers work?
That's much easier to understand than something like the ATP synthase as a protein.
This is the next slide, I forgive you if you don't notice any difference whatsoever, but
in fact everything has just been turned on its head here.
The Krebs cycle is now going in the opposite direction, those arrows switched around.
It's deliberately looking the same because the reverse Krebs cycle takes CO2 and hydrogen
from its environment and cobbles them together to make organic molecules.
This happens in various bacteria, it's pretty ancient, and obviously if we get energy out
of burning sugars in the Krebs cycle now, then the missing ingredient there is we have
to put energy in to make these Krebs cycle intermediates from CO2 and hydrogen.
That energy is coming from exactly what I was just talking about, a charge, an electrical
charge on the membrane which is driving the reverse Krebs cycle to make organic molecules
from CO2 and hydrogen, simple gases in the environment.
That Krebs cycle is the center of all of metabolism really.
We make lipids for the membranes, we make amino acids for proteins.
We make sugars and nucleotides from ultimately from Krebs cycle intermediates.
This is the core and the heart of metabolism across all of life.
This is more ancient chemistry than the genes that appear to encode that chemistry.
The genes diverge and differ in bacteria and archaea, but the chemistry underlying it remains
the same.
The third aspect is information.
In this case, I will touch on this at the end and there are patterns in the genetic code
which suggests that there are direct interactions between amino acids and the nucleotides that
code for them in the genetic code.
We don't know exactly what they look like, I'm giving a couple of possible ways of imagining
it here, but I will show you that those patterns are real and they're weak and they're statistical
but they are real and this can explain the origin of information in biology.
In effect, if what we have is a random sequence of RNA, we could say it has no biological
information in it, and that templates in one way or another a non-random peptide which
has function in the context of, say, growing protocells, and I'll come onto that, then
we can select for the sequence which selects for a non-random peptide which has a function
in that context, and so information seamlessly emerges, biological information emerges with
selection on that sequence in that context, and so there is no problem with the origin
of information in biology if we get the context right.
Those are some big claims there and I'll justify them at the end.
Another thing to notice about that is I'm talking about electrical charges on membranes
driving autotrophic biochemistry starting with CO2 and hydrogen to make all the components
of biochemistry which then interact with nucleotides and genetic information comes into existence
in this context.
In other words, I'm saying everything is happening in the same environment and that's another
big ask.
I'm not saying that some stuff happens in the atmosphere over there and some other things
happened in a deep sea hydrothermal vent and some things happen in Darwin's warm pond.
I'm saying it's all happening in one place right now, all at once, and that's a big
ask, but it's experimentally very simplifying because it means that we need one set of conditions
that are capable of driving all this, and so it becomes experimentally very tractable.
The set of conditions that drive it were proposed not by me at all, by Mike Russell,
more than anybody else, but quite a few people have worked on this over 30 years or so now.
The conditions, again, keeping this as simple as possible, the conditions that Mike has
talked about are hydrogen and CO2 in these alkaline hydrothermal vents which are now found
at the bottom of the ocean, but also other environments as well, including on land.
At the right hand side here you can see that these are effectively a labyrinth of interconnected
pores on a micrometer to millimeter scale.
This is modern chemistry in modern oceans, fully oxygenated, and is not reflective of
what we would expect to see four billion years ago in the Haiti, and when there was no oxygen
there was much more, for example, ferrous iron in the oceans back then.
These vents should have had perhaps a similar topology, but the actual chemistry would have
been different and would have included reactive iron-sulfide minerals in there.
The hydrothermal fluids are strongly alkaline, pH 11, the early oceans we think would have
been mildly acidic, perhaps pH 5 or 6, and so there would have been steep proton gradients
across these barriers, and those steep proton gradients in principle can drive work in pretty
much the same way that the proton motive force would drive work in cells.
It's not exactly an electrical charge, but it's very close to being the same kind of
structure.
This is effectively it.
We have at the left hand side here an inorganic pore at the right hand side a cell.
What a cell is doing is pumping protons out across its plasma membrane, so we end up with
this high proton concentration and relatively positive charge on the outside and relatively
alkaline on the inside, and it's about a three to four pH unit difference, equivalent to
a three to four pH unit difference.
In a hydrothermal vent we've got, again, at least arguably a three to four pH unit difference
between the inside of a proto, of a pore, let's call it, and ocean waters percolating
into these vents.
We have a much thicker inorganic barrier surrounding it, and that barrier is likely
to include minerals like iron sulfur minerals that couldn't drive some of this work.
Is there a way, an imaginable way, that we can go from one of those to the other?
This is the hypothesis in a nutshell, and the rest of the talk I'll just give a little
bit of data on trying to test this hypothesis.
What you're seeing here is a pore in a hydrothermal vent is relatively rich in protons outside.
We have this iron sulfide barrier.
I'm imagining protons crossing this barrier and driving the reverse Krebs cycle inside
this proto, a pore, let's just call it a pore at the moment, so we've got hydrogen
reacting with CO2 driven by an influx of protons, pretty much as happens in cells today.
We would expect to see thermodynamically at least fatty acids, so components of lipids
and probably some amino acids from that.
If we look to the right-hand side, what would we expect those to do?
The fatty acids should form some kind of a bilayer membrane, which we can imagine at
least might just sit snugly inside this pore.
Once we've closed down an enclosed proto cell inside here, we might expect that metabolism
will drive further, so not just lipids and amino acids, but perhaps sugars and nucleotides
as well.
This is imaginable.
This is at least a hypothesis.
It's also that for protons to be driving Krebs cycle inside a proto cell, we would
need to have some kind of an iron-sulfur nanocrystal or iron-sulfur clusters, the same kind of thing
that drives this work today, it would need to be sitting in that membrane.
You could label this wishful thinking, but you could also call it a testable hypothesis,
and that's how I've been treating it over the last few years.
I'm going to break it into these three parts, and I'll skip quite lightly over it, and we
can discuss some of the data at more length afterwards.
This idea, though, that proton gradients are fundamental, it's something I've been thinking
about for a long time, and I tended to think of it in terms of driving molecular machinery
rather than as simply phase separations.
Now, Peter Mitchell himself, who put this chemo-osmotic hypothesis forward back in the
1960s, had been thinking about the origin of life before that in the late 1950s, and
there's a lovely quote from a conference in Moscow in 1957 where he said, I cannot consider
the organism without its environment.
From a formal point of view, the two may be regarded as equivalent phases between which
dynamic contact is maintained by the membranes that separate and link them.
When he says organism here, he's thinking of a bacterial cell, but instead of trying
to define life as something different to the environment, he's more or less conflating them.
He's describing them as equivalent phases between which this dynamic contact is maintained.
And if we think before there were any cells, before there was anything living, then the
idea of a membrane that separates and links two equivalent phases is a very productive
way of thinking about the question.
So why would that matter?
Well, in essence, it's this.
The problem with hydrogen is it will not react very readily with CO2.
This is just showing vague thermodynamics for two steps rather than a single step, which
is why I call it vague, through to formaldehyde.
So taking the electrons from hydrogen, pushing them onto CO2 to form formaldehyde.
At pH 7 or any other pH, all I really, for non-chemists, all I really want you to take
away is it's an uphill reaction.
It's not going to happen spontaneously.
But we don't have hydrogen at pH 7 and we don't have CO2 at pH 7 in an alkaline hydrothermal
vent. We've got hydrogen at pH 11 and CO2 at pH 6, say.
And that shifts these equations around.
And the reason for it is very simple, intuitively, to grasp if hydrogen gives up its electrons
in an alkaline environment, what's left behind is protons.
Those protons will react immediately with hydroxide ions to form water.
It's just a neutralization reaction.
It's strongly favored.
And so it will happen immediately.
So hydrogen is more reducing in an alkaline environment.
CO2 needs to pick up electrons.
If there are plenty of protons available, they will balance the charges.
And then you can pick up more electrons and more protons.
So it's easier to reduce CO2 in an acidic environment.
So what we have here, then, is effectively two phases, an alkaline phase and an acid
phase, separated by a semi-permeable, semi-conducting barrier.
And those phases have hydrogen and CO2 and should be more reactive in those phases.
So this is all we effectively need.
It's not clear yet whether it's electrons crossing this barrier or protons coming the
other way.
But this is really just showing visually what I just did.
We've got hydrogen on the alkaline side, passing electrons onto an ion-sulfide barrier.
The protons react with hydroxide ions to form water.
And on the acid side, we've got CO2 picking up protons and electrons from the barrier
itself.
So this, in principle, should work.
It's very easy to set it up.
Well, it's not so easy.
But in principle, it's easy to set it up.
This needs to be done inside a glove box, an anaerobic glove box.
Oxygen, even trace amounts of oxygen, really do play around with this.
We need to have it pretty strictly anoxic.
This is a microfluidic chip with a barrier that's just spontaneously precipitated by laminar
flow with sodium sulfide on one side and, sorry, sodium sulfide on one side, an ion
chloride, ferrous chloride.
On the other side, they spontaneously precipitate this barrier.
And this is just one piece of evidence to show you.
Formates is being formed, acetate also.
So we'll be getting towards the Krebs cycle.
We have seen pyruvate as well, but we've not managed to see it on every occasion yet.
And possibly things like methanol as well.
So this is stuff that I was hoping for when I last presented to you five or six years ago.
But this is now, is being published in PNAS, and this is our own work, which is taking
it a little bit further.
So just to come back to this figure for a moment, if we are able to reduce CO2 to organics,
then we think that they should include amino acids and lipids.
The next step then would be to have some kind of protocell.
We've taken a leap forward rather than, I mean, we are trying to make these lipids as
well.
We've not done so yet.
But if we simply take lipids that other people have successfully synthesized under these
kind of conditions, we're able to form vesicles under these alkaline hydrothermal conditions.
This is another major step, because these vesicles are not supposed to be stable under
these pretty harsh conditions.
And the literature and our experiments as well show that if you have a very simple vesicle
made from decanoic acid, it more or less falls to pieces as soon as you change the pH or
the temperature or anything else.
But if you have mixtures, slightly messy mixtures of fatty acids and long chain fatty alcohols
and so on, especially if you have one-to-one mixtures of these.
Then we get, you can see with cryoAM and you can see with thomphocal microscopy there,
we are seeing vesicles at pH 12, 70 degrees centigrade, modern ocean salinity in the presence
of calcium ions and magnesium ions.
So we really are able to form from the kind of fatty acids that have been formed under
hydrothermal conditions, you can make vesicles under those conditions.
And this was another one I wanted to share with you very briefly.
This is UV-Vis spectroscopy and it's showing a classical shoulder, which was the last thing
we expected to see there, because that shoulder, when we mix the amino acid cysteine with sodium
sulfide and iron chloride, and that's it in water, that shoulder is a 4FE4S cluster,
the same thing that we see in ferrodoxin and which is responsible for a lot of CO2 fixation
in bacteria today.
And we've looked at different concentrations of everything, including the cysteine, we've
used MOSpower spectroscopy to characterize the clusters, and we've used cyclic voltammetry
to show their redox potential, and it's exactly the same as ferrodoxin.
This is the midpoint reduction potential and it's about minus 450 millivolts, which is
right in the region for reducing CO2, though we would not yet use them to reduce CO2.
So it seems to be possible to make this machinery under surprisingly simple sets of conditions.
So I'm going to say a little bit about metabolism, and again I'm going to skip likely over some
data and then I'll finish with the code itself.
So this is the core of metabolism, I've mentioned the Krebs cycle, this is not really the cycle
so much as some of the steps, so acetyl-CoA or some equivalent to it, prebiotic equivalent,
through to pyruvate, we're now into the Krebs cycle, oxaloacetate, alpha ketoglutarate and
so on.
What we really want you to notice here is this is CO2 at the top left, and in a kind
of brownie red color we've got hydrogen, hydrogen, hydrogen, lots of hydrogen in there, in green
we've got CO2, again there's CO2 everywhere that you look pretty much, this is the chemistry
of hydrogen and CO2 and there's not much more to it.
When we get amino acids we're beginning to see ammonia in there as well.
The blue arrows here are basically experiments that have been done successfully under prebiotic
conditions by us and by other people, there are several labs around the world doing this
kind of chemistry and the red boxes are showing the precursors for nucleotide synthesis following
the biological pathways as the starting point.
So much of this chemistry has now been done.
One of the things that has been missing from there is cysteine synthesis and we've recently,
I mean this is about as much as we've got at the moment, it's not very much but this
is a peak for cysteine on NMR, sorry that was on HPLC I beg your pardon, and it looks
like we've managed to do a one pot synthesis of cysteine starting from glycine through
cyrene to cysteine and we're also able to produce spartate and alanine under those kind
of conditions.
This is basically using life as a guide and a lot of these we've used pyrodoxamine which
is a simple cofactor used by life and it's that which is catalyzing these reactions.
So another problem then is can we make pyrodoxamine under these conditions?
So there's always more questions that we've not answered yet but we can make the cysteine.
That's not published yet.
This is also uracil synthesis and again I'll skip very lightly over it but this is following
the biological pathway starting with ammonia, carbonate and a spartate which I just mentioned
we've synthesized and this goes through to uracil which is one of the bases in RNA and
again this is a one pot synthesis starting over here and we've made both oratate and
uracil that way and when we just do these last few steps going from dihydro oratate
to uracil and we try to optimize them so we looked at a panel of different metal ions,
we looked at different pHs, we looked at different temperatures, different salinities
and things like that and worked out what the optimal conditions were.
It turned out those optimal conditions are about 90 degrees centigrade, pH 9, high pressure,
100 bars pressure, modern ocean salinity so that was very gratifying and this at the right
hand side here is showing those optimal conditions, uracil synthesis when we when we matched up
the optimal conditions apart from that's not high pressure that's just atmospheric pressure
so that was an eight-fold increase in yield when we optimized those conditions.
Whoops that just hopped forward this is the last thing I'll say about metabolism but I mentioned
ATP a couple of times it's now produced by this amazing rotating nanomotor the ATP synthase
that's obviously a product of genes and natural selection and must have come later but then the
question is so why did ATP become the universal energy currency and this is
this is some beautiful work from a former PhD student of mine Silvana Pinna who showed that
mildly acidic pH in this case and at 30 or 50 degrees centigrade in water starting with acetyl
phosphate and ferric iron and ADP the acetyl phosphate will phosphorylate ADP to ATP at around
15 to 20 yield just in in water and she tried a whole range of other phosphorylating agents and
none of them really worked carbonyl phosphate worked a little bit, cyclic TMP worked a little bit
but basically acetyl phosphate does that job beautifully and interestingly still does that
job today in bacteria and archaea but the the other beautiful thing about this was it works with ATP
but it doesn't work with any of the other nuclear bases in other words we can make ATP but we can't
make CTP or UTP or ITP or GTP and so on um so why is ATP the universal energy currency the answer
seems to be because you can make it fairly easily with minimum um minimum catalytic requirements
and simply acetyl phosphate which is a two carbon phosphorylating agent in water at reasonable
temperatures and pressures and so on so that's by no means does that say that's why ATP is
the universal energy currency but it's certainly almost uncanny that that we can make that and
nothing else under those conditions so for the last five minutes or so I'd like to touch on
information and this is some of the most beautiful work that I have been involved in in the last few
years and I should say that these ideas came from Stuart Harrison who did his PhD in my lab and is
now doing a postdoc job with me and so this is actually I'm used to thinking and and I'm not
used to my PhD students and postdoc coming up with the best ideas and this is what's happened
on this occasion so it's very pleasing actually in in many respects this is metabolism again
as we've seen it starting with CO2 coming through into pyruvate oxaloacetate and so on
and in the the colors lozenges are the amino acids and they're color coded according to
the first base of the codon that encodes them in DNA or in RNA and so glycine alanine aspartate
and glutamate are all encoded by a gene at the first position as well where it makes sense
yeah get that get that awareness and build that picture yeah I was going to go to the foundry
ones as well though I don't really like it's quite like I'm not going to go to the deep dive I'm
probably going to go to the overview because I feel like that'd be more like able for me I think the
deep dive will be a bit too technical for me it's probably going to be more at the practitioner
I think you'll get a good sense at the high level one from what they've been what they've talked
about so that they did good to get immersed in that yeah
no they're not gone
shall I continue
okay I'll I'll continue so can you hear me okay
yes I think we can yes good so so in gray then it's G at the first position of the codon
and then in yellow it's an A at the first position of the codon and then in blue it's a C
side to dean and in green it's a U at the first position of the codon so there's plainly patterning
there and it seems to link to the distance from co2 fixation and at the bottom right there that's
just showing exactly that distance the number of steps from co2 fixation what exactly this tells us
is not entirely clear but it seems to it seems to suggest that the the organization of the code or
the first letter of the codon is linked in some way to the pattern of metabolism we do have ideas
about why that might be and we can talk about it afterwards but I'll just leave it that there's
clearly a pattern there and that patterns an interesting one if we then so what we're seeing
here is the is is the hydrophobicity of of the amino acid in relation to the second letter of
the anti codon and we're arranging them in boxes with G at the first position of the codon then A
then C then then U as we had before and all I really want you to take away from this is there's a
clear relationship that A is the most hydrophobic amino acid and V is the most hydrophobic base
so this is there is a relationship between the hydrophobicity of the base and the hydrophobicity
of the amino acid that it codes for and at the other end of this one it's spartate and that is
encoded by a U which is the most hydrophilic of the basis so there's a clear patterning there
especially if there's a purine at the first position a gRNA at the first position we see
quite a strong relationship with where there's a pyrimidine at the first position and that's less
of a strong relationship but it's not gone away completely so again all I really want you to take
away from it is there are patterns in the code that depend on the bio on the hydrophobicity
of the amino acids and the bases which suggest direct stereochemical interactions between them
this kind of thing has been known for a long time but the patterning is stronger when we set it out
around an autotrophic protometabolism and this is the third position and again only a couple of
things I really want you to notice here but this is an inverted codon table which is to say
these are the amino acids that are coded in the outermost ring this is the first position
of the codon and the second position of the codon and then the third position of the codon
in the in the most part there so just to give one example here we have glutamate and a spartate
and they both have a g at the first position they both have an a at the second position
but glutamate has a purine at the third position of the codon whereas a spartate has a pyrimidine
at the third position of the codon and what we see if we if we now switch this to the
anticodon not the codon what we find is that if there's effectively a big bulky base a purine
rather than the pyrimidine at the third position then we'll always see the smallest amino acid
so this is the size of the amino acids that could be coded for there and we always see
that the when there's a larger base there's a smaller amino acid so again it just suggests
that there's direct interactions between the chemistry of the amino acids its hydrophobicity
and so on and its size so all of this is very suggestive but there's no doubt various ways
in which it could be interpreted and so this is the last slide then and this is work which is
should be published in the next week or two I hope and this is doing a mixture of molecular
dynamic simulations so all in silico and some NMR work which which is ongoing but these are the
first four that way and what we're seeing here this is basically the proportion of time spent
the amino acid spends in the vicinity of specific bases these are mononutriotides so AMP, CMP,
GMP or UMP and you can this is proline in this particular case and what you're seeing is that
it spends much more time within two angstroms of GMP than anything else there is a direct
predicted interaction between proline and GMP which happens to be the base that codes for it
at the second position of the anticodal we see something a little bit similar underneath for
a spartate but this is much muddier in that case it tends to spend quite a lot of time
with almost everything but in that case it's also I think it's GMP is slightly better.
What we're seeing in effect is we can predict 50% of the of the middle bases of the anticodons that
way we're much better at predicting this is all the amino acids across the bottom here and it's
on a scale going from hydrophobic at the left hand end to hydrophilic at the right hand end
and we can get the hydrophilic interactions pretty well the hydrophobic interactions this
method is much less good at predicting correctly the hydrophobic interactions but still we are
we're better than 99% of random allocations if we simply assume that there were random
interactions our predictions are better than 99% and we also when we do NMR work and we're looking
at the binding constants for these it's again it's easier to work with hydrophilic amino acids
because you can get higher concentrations in water it's it's more fiddly trying to do it with
hydrophobic bases and hydrophobic amino acids in water but we're seeing that essentially the same
patterns so we are I would take this as broad confirmation that there really are weak but
statistically systematic interactions between amino acids and the bases that code for them in
the genetic code and so that picture that I showed you at the beginning suggesting that there can be
some kind of templating or non-random templating that if you've got a random stretch of RNA you will
get a non-random peptide which is interacting with it that seems to be borne out in other words as I
said at the beginning there should be no problem with information at the origin of the code that's
all I'm going to say I just want to have a final call out to the people who've been doing this work
this is over of some years now I just like this picture because they're holding up the
reverse Krebs cycle there this was a birthday present they did a few years ago and I like
it too much too so a few of these people have left the group now but I still keep this image
but they are the people who've really been doing all this experimental work that I've
talked about and that's it so I will stop sharing and I look forward to your questions.
Well thank you Nick that was that that was quite a tour de force so thank you and I'm not sure we
have many questions yet in the chat box so we had a bit of an interruption there in the sound I'm
not sure quite what happened there yeah sorry I apologize for that Alan I had a cup of tea delivered
oh sorry okay anyway okay it's audience's chance to to fire away with some questions from from
for Nick if you'd like to unmute yourself and put your video on and wave your hands we can
some questions don't be shy. Can I maybe start with one Nick you kind of touched on the thermodynamics
so how much of how much of this is a thermodynamic process alongside the chemistry?
I think it's predominantly thermodynamic in the sense that what we're dealing with is an environment
which is continuously out of equilibrium because we have continuous flow of hydrothermal fluids
which are rich in hydrogen in the modern vents that it's up to about 15 millimolar equivalent
hydrogen and CO2 and in the early oceans we don't know what it was exactly but but you know
potentially more than a bar of CO2 back then so the modern systems are somewhat carbon starved
because they're alkaline and it precipitates out carbonate but but in in the older systems there
would have been an overwhelming amount of CO2 there and so thermodynamically it is it's it's
exegonic to be producing pretty much all of all of the biomolecules um it's it's simply an exothermic
reaction. So then it's down to the catalyst. Yeah so and we have a few hands up with a couple of
hands up there's one there from from Victor Victor would you like to unmute yourself and ask your
question okay i'm up can you hear me yeah okay yep i had a question which might not be as knowledgeable
as some of the other people's questions are in in this session um so you've you've looked at the
life that we have and the building blocks that build up that life and kind of working backwards to
some simple conditions where those building blocks might have might have had their origin
um is there another form of life that could have developed rather than the one that we've got or
maybe it did develop at certain stages and then it it it died out for some reason it wasn't as
successful um in terms of the changing conditions on the planet from when life first formed it may
not have had any longevity associated with it is there's some other thing that we could have
and that would have ended up with something completely different potentially yes uh and it
is uh it's a very good question and it's one which keeps me awake at night i think but uh but it's um
there's to my mind there's something a little bit uncanny about all of this metabolic biochemistry
just happening in the absence of genes and information and and some of it i can understand
but the further we get from co2 fixation the more unbelievable it seems to be that's uh
that impure in synthesis or well permadein synthesis as we're working on purine synthesis
and it's well that's a bit hard work um but um we tend that you think there's all these side
reactions that could happen and should happen uh and to a larger extent don't happen what we tend to see
is is small amounts of the intermediates along these known metabolic pathways forming spontaneously
and interchanging between themselves at low low levels um and why why those ones why not other
ones this is the the essence of your question and i think a lot will depend on the starting point
which is to say if we're starting with hydrogen and co2 at a particular temperature
we're likely to get a certain metabolic network if you like and if we change the starting point
to something else or we change the temperature or we change any of those parameters then easily you
could get a different network um so so why this network um it still seems uncanny but if you think
about what the genes would be doing then as soon as we introduce information into this system there
is a serious problem here which has been largely overlooked in my view uh about um how
an RNA world invents metabolism which is the standard view but but but the the RNA world of
people have really got as far as trying to replicate RNA and haven't really worried themselves very
much yet about how how you know as soon as you got something which is capable of self replicating
then you've got a system which is capable of evolution and and and it's easy lazy to put it
aside there and say okay so it'll evolve there is no conceptual problem but there is a conceptual
problem to my mind because if you invent one enzyme that catalyzes one step in a metabolic pathway
and there's 10 steps in that pathway then it's absolutely no use to you you really need all 10
enzymes in that pathway and and so it's beginning to look less probable but and what what use is one
pathway you actually need multiple pathways to have anything that's any use to you so a more
rigorous way of thinking about what's actually what entity is being selected and what are the
reasons it's being selected uh you're left facing quite a large part of proto metabolism needs to
be doing it to produce the required amino acids nucleotide sugars whatever else is is required
to to have a system which is capable of replicating itself um and and again the the problem is still
there's no point in having any one of those pathways by itself um or at least there's no
obvious point that I can see um so there's a there's a serious combinatorial problem there
that's never been seriously addressed and I suspect it's borderline impossibly difficult
but if what actually you see instead is a kind of a spontaneous proto metabolism that happens to
have a particular network structure to it and what the first genes do is increase flux through
that pathway for example by steepening the driving force so increasing the fixation of CO2 to make
the first intermediates in that pathway then you get increased flux through the entire network so
that's not intrinsically very difficult what that says then if you take a step back is that what the
first genes are doing is amplifying the network and so the fact that we get the same network and
the entire thing is amplified is in fact a direct prediction of assuming that network comes first
in which case we should be able to turn that on its head and say okay well if if we can look at the
conditions that give rise to that entire network then we should be able to predict the you know
if we can get the entire network under this set of conditions but not that set then we might be able
to say the conditions under which life arose well that's very good thank you okay thank you for that
Nick we have another question from Chelsea Chen could you unmute yourself please Chelsea and
if you want to put your video on we can see you too perhaps. Hello can I just ask about why ATP
can be spontaneously synthesized in water while other nucleosides can't? Yes you can ask
I'd like to say I could answer we did we did some molecular dynamic simulations on that
and it seems to be in part to do with the with the charge density on ferric iron,
ferric iron was necessary and other other other other metal ions did not work in the same way,
it seems to be partly to do with the actual orientation of the phosphate group of acetyl
phosphates in relation to the ferric iron and the ADP tail I mean we came up with a potential
explanation for the orientation some of it seems to be to do with the way that the ring
nitrogen's interact with ferric iron and I don't understand that very well but they interact very
differently with say guanine compared to adenosine so why I'm not quite sure but the prediction is
that you know molecular dynamic prediction is that you do not have the orientation of the acetyl
phosphate in the right place and and it tends to abstract the catalyst it abstracts the ferric
iron which interacts with the nitrogen on the ring instead so we have some answers but I'm not
persuaded that they're the right answers or that the molecular dynamic simulations are
real I don't know enough of what's going on under the bonnet with them with the atomic forces that
they're predicting I am not a chemist I'm a biochemist and and you know I try to get my hands
dirty with all of this stuff but it's I think we need a proper chemist to look at some of that
okay thank you thanks we have a question from Jim Cunningham on this chat box there
Nick can you see that uh oh he's asking when when when will the book come out about all this
it takes more than 45 minutes to digest at all well I I am trying to put together a proposal
now to write a book on the origin of life specifically covering more or less what I've
said today but it will be some years before it's written I mean we're not I'm neither chemist
nor biochemist so I do have a book that was out last year that touches on some of the actual
chemistry of the Krebs cycle and some of the ideas I've just talked about now so that's out
already but the genetic code stuff is quite new um and I'm I'm quite excited by it but
the path going from a pattern to a predicted set of steps that we can then test that uh
I I want to delay writing the book until we've done some of that and I have something to say about
hmm these these steps you're predicting they seem to depend uh on specifically specific
earth conditions but perhaps earth-like conditions um what they
yes they they I mean what we would get from this metabolic network is a specific set of amino acids
and we would tend to get those amino acids and we would tend to we would predict an order in
which we get them as well um the extent to which we would expect to see exactly the four bases
that we see in RNA compared to a bunch of other possible ones that are and there's a lot of modified
bases around um I'm less sure about that so one thing we want to do is is model metabolism
where we're varying the thermodynamic parameters and kinetic parameters on each of the but
basically it's more the thermodynamics than the kinetics what's the likelihood of each reaction
happening and given that we have no clear idea no clear data under the sets of conditions that
we might be thinking about if we if we model it we can vary across orders of magnitude and obviously
if you make an oxidation reaction more likely then a reduction step is less likely and so on so we
can we can we can vary parameters um in relation to each other and try to see how much of of
metabolism we actually recover and do we recover then the the core of it in which case we would
expect to see exactly the same interaction somewhere else in which case if we discovered life on Mars
and it has exactly the same genetic code then it doesn't prove that it was a contamination
um or it may be that it's much looser than that and that um that if you know if effectively
we would expect to see some but not all or or or it's very contingent on which bases you produce
and which ones get incorporated into RNA or DNA uh then that would come up with a different set
of predictions there's a lot that we don't know or I don't know um but but there's a lot you know
there's a huge amount that can be done here so yeah could could I could I ask a quick supplementary
on that please nick um you've been talking about the the bases you find in in RNA and you mentioned
uracil yes as I recall in in in DNA we've got cytosine, uranine, alanine and thymine have we not
do we know do we know why thymine came along as opposed to uracil in DNA um I mean there are ideas
out there um and it's partly to do with stability um and and and decreasing the risk of mutations
because if I'm probably going to get this wrong I can't quite remember but um if if if there is a
I think an oxidation of uracil then uh you end up with producing something very similar to one
of the other bases uh I need to double check that uh in other words there there's more scope for
um for I suppose confusion replacing the wrong base so so that'd be part of it in part um RNA
does not tend to form structures as stable as DNA and I'm not sure that's to do with the bases
so much as to do with the deoxy versus ribose um but I I don't we've not really started thinking
very much about DNA yet it's plain that as soon as you've got DNA you've got a much larger much
more stable structure which is going to lower the error error error rate um but uh that's another
another reason I want to delay writing a book on this until I until I figure it out how does DNA
how does that fit into this picture right well please don't delay it too long
like to read it um now then Chelsea Chen has had a supplementary right if she's still around
she's welcome to read otherwise I'll read it out are you there Chelsea yes do you want to go ahead
with your supplementary about purely RNA compounds uh sorry this is not no longer Chelsea Chen but
but it's the same question do one yes do we know do we know if there is uh if there are any RNA
purely RNA compounds that are capable of catalyzing reactions such as uh condensing uh condensing
amino acids or or nucleotides um well I mean there there's been a lot of interest over decades in
what's called the RNA world and there are plenty of ribosomes which are basically catalysts a bit
like an enzyme enzymes are made of proteins and ribosomes are made of RNA and RNA will tend to
form into interesting shapes and knots and has quite a wide range of catalytic functions much
less than proteins but but but certainly um you know capable of catalyzing quite complex chemistry
and so this has been the basis for what's being called the RNA world hypothesis
and that really goes back to to people like Leslie Orgel in the 1960s in the late 1960s
and it the ideas are very simple and very appealing which is more or less that
because of complementary base pairing it's it's you know conceptually very easy for an RNA to make
a copy of itself whereas for a peptide to make a copy of itself is much more problematic and complex
and and difficult um so if you were to say which comes first then RNA has to come before
peptides in that sense at least as a hereditary mechanism um but what that has tended to lead
to is a rather purest view of an RNA world where as I said RNA invents everything else it invents
all of metabolism and that view has been I would say receding over the last five to ten years or so
with a kind of recognition that chemistry is dirtier than that and that there will be other
things in there there will be lipids in there there will be amino acids maybe peptides in there
and we've we've got a kind of a dirty RNA world so there's no question that RNA is central to all
of this um and that's that this was almost only the first code and it's interesting that the ribosome
which is the big protein building factories in cells they're basically ribosomes um the the
the RNA content is very high and as far as I'm aware it's the ribosomes that are doing
most of the catalysis of peptide bond formation um so so it's interesting that they have an
absolutely central critical job and this is one thing that we're trying to think our way through
to and do some experiments on as well but this is a highly populated area you may say because it's
it's so central to the question people have been working on it a lot for a long time um
um ironically RNA does not copy itself in cells and this this kind of holy grail of having a
ribosome that will copy itself which was the the essence of the RNA world actually the it's an
enzyme that does that job it's the RNA polymerase it's a magnesium dependent protein um and so
there's this this interesting um RNA effectively copies proteins and proteins copy RNA so we're
back in this strange chicken and egg situation that uh that that is not easily unscrambled um
I've forgotten exactly what your question was but essentially could how much work does RNA do
and the answer is it's very central to a lot of this um but it it's not the only thing that's going
on uh and I think peptides early are are pretty necessary. Nick that's been a very stimulating
afternoon thank you so much um before we go um you you you've clearly got a collection of your
fans here in the audience would you like just to say give a quick a quick commercial for the
other book that you have written very recently the one on trans you call transformers. Oh that's
very kind of you yes why not I'm not sure that I'm not sure I would be intellectually fair of me to
over plug it because it's it's a book on the Krebs cycle uh which is not to everybody's taste
right on it attempts to link the chemistry that I touched on on the origin of life which is which
is making Krebs cycle intermediates from CO2 and hydrogen but I have I have another lab group at
UCL which is working on mitochondrial functions so still and energetics and so on right and it
turned out both groups were measuring Krebs cycle intermediates for most of their lives so
I had to put two and two together um and and you know the the Krebs cycle goes into reverse in
cancer for example and it's it's certainly um and then what's it doing well it's driving cells
copying themselves it's instead of being about energy it's about making the building blocks
required to make a new cancer cell so all of the lipids all of the DNA and and so on that's required
so metabolism the central cycle in metabolism is central right across the whole spectrum of life
from the origin of life up to um to aging and cancer and I there's an epilogue where I have a
go at linking it to consciousness as well which is beyond most people's tolerance for speculation
in science but that's where I finished with the book so that's my plug for the book but if you
don't like metabolic biochemistry then then then you may prefer just to watch a short talk online
or something right okay well thank you so much right well we've had a wonderful afternoon
which I've hugely enjoyed and I'm sure everybody else has so without a do I apart from thanking you
again I'd like to pass over to our chairman uh professor David Southwood if I don't have his
screen up in front of me but uh David over to you if I may thank you Ellen and Nick thank you very
much for an invigorating afternoon um origin of life I think how can how can we not be interested
in it and how can we not feel some of the emotions that you clearly feel the curiosity of it the um
the fact that things have come out of it and yet there we are it's one of the big mysteries that
we live with as human beings in my view so I really think you've taken us on a wonderful voyage
and your enthusiasm is absolutely magnificent I think we'll need to communicate I much admire
and um so I think if I can ask people generally to unmute or to use the symbol for clapping
to give you a sign that we really did appreciate your time this time this afternoon so thank you very much