Welcome to the Future of Life Institute podcast.
My name is Gus Docher,
and I'm here with Samuel Hammond,
who is a senior economist at
the Foundation for American Innovation.
Samuel, welcome to the podcast.
I guess. Thanks for having me.
Fantastic. All right.
I have so much I want to talk to you about,
but I think a natural place to start here would be with
your timelines to AGI.
Why is it that you expect AGI to get here before most people?
Well, I don't really know what most people think.
I think the world divides into people who are paying
attention and people who are basically normies.
In my day job, I work on Capitol Hill and in Washington,
D.C., talking to folks about AGI.
If you think about what people's implicit timelines are,
you can read out people's implicit timelines by their behavior.
I know Paul Cristiano has short timelines
because he's doubled up into the stock market.
He's practicing what he preaches.
But then when you have Sam Altman testifying to work to Congress,
I like to say people are taking him seriously,
but not literally. He's saying,
we're going to develop something like AGI,
potentially this decade,
and superintelligence thereafter.
Then you have folks like Sandra Marshall Blackburn
being like, what will this mean for music royalties?
When the focus of policymakers is things like
music royalties or impact on copyright,
it's not that those are invalid issues.
It's that they belie relatively longer timelines.
Then we also have this definitional confusion
where folks like John Lacoon would say AGI is probably decades away
because he is using AGI to mean something that learns,
like a human learns in the sense that it's born
as a relative blank slate and can acquire language
with very few examples.
People have these moving goalposts of what they mean.
For me, I think we can avoid those definitional conflicts
if we just talk about human level intelligence,
and humans are quite general or generally intelligent.
That's what separates us from animals in a lot of respects.
And when you look at how machine learning models
are being trained today,
like large language models and now multimodal models,
they're being trained on human data,
and they're being trained to reproduce the kinds of behaviors
and tasks and outputs that humans output.
And so they're kind of like an indirect way
of emulating human intelligence.
And then so if you benchmark AI progress to that,
then you can sort of put information theoretic bounds
on what's the likely timeline
to basically an ideal human emulator,
something that can extract the sort of base representations,
the internal representations of our brain
through the indirect path of the data that our brain generates.
Yeah, you have an interesting sentence where you write that
AI can advance by emulating the generator
of human-generated data, which is simply the brain.
Do you think this paradigm holds all the way to AGI?
I think it holds this decade to systems
that in principle can in context learn anything humans do.
Again, this is a semantic question.
Do you want to call that AGI or not?
I think there are still outstanding issues around the limits
of other aggressive models for autonomy
and the question of sort of real-time learning,
the way we train these models,
we sort of are freezing a crystal in place
and humans are continuously learning.
So there still are genuine potential architectural gaps,
but from the practical point of view,
from the economic point of view,
we don't need to debate whether something is conscious
or whether something learns strictly the way humans learn
if it demonstrably can do the things humans do, right?
And that goes to the original insight of the Turing test, right?
It's sometimes presented as a thought experiment,
but what Alan Turing was getting at
was if you can't distinguish between the human and a computer,
in some ways, indistinguishability implies competence, right?
And we can broaden that from just language
because arguably we've surpassed the Turing test,
at least a weaker version of it,
to human performance on tasks in general, right?
If we have a system that can output a scientific manuscript
that experts in the field can't distinguish from a human,
then debating whether this is real AGI or not
is, I feel, academic.
It is surprising in a sense that when you interact with GPT-4,
for example, and it can do all kinds of amazing things
and organize information, present information to you,
but then it can't, or at least at some point,
it couldn't answer questions about the world
after September 2021 or a date like that.
That would be surprising if you presented that fact
to an AI scientist 20 years ago.
For how long do you think we'll remain in this paradigm
of training a foundational model
and then deploying that model?
I mean, it's worse than that.
I think it was surprised people five years ago.
Progress is sort of moving along two tracks.
There's the industry track
and the peer research academic track,
and they're obviously having feedback with one another.
The peer industry track is just looking to create tools
that have practical value
and can improve products and so forth.
And so, Meta has their own GPU cluster
and their training models,
so they can have fun chatbots in their messenger.
And so, those kinds of things are going to progress,
I think, well within the current paradigm
because we know the paradigm works,
basically deep learning and transformers.
And there's lots of marginality on the side,
but that basic framework seems to be quite effective.
And just scaling that up
because we haven't sort of hit the range
of irreducible loss and what transformers can do.
Meanwhile, there's also this parallel peer research track
where people on seemingly a weekly basis
are finding better ways of specifying the loss function,
ways of improving upon power loss scaling
and all these different,
sometimes they're new architectures,
but often they're just like bags of tricks.
And those bags of tricks then,
to the extent that they comport with
the paradigm industries running with,
they can be reintegrated
and end up accelerating progress and industry as well.
So, do you think scale of compute is the main barrier
to getting to human level AI?
Yes, right, I mean, it's not all we need,
but it's the main unlock, right?
To what extent can more compute be used to trade off
for lower quality data or for lower quality algorithms?
Can you just throw more compute
and solve the other factors in that equation?
It depends on the thing you're trying to solve for.
In principle, if we're talking about mapping inputs to outputs,
then transformers are known
to be universal function approximators.
And so the answer is yes.
That doesn't mean that they're necessarily efficient
at approximating everything we want them to approximate.
And sometimes universal function approximation theorems
can be kind of trivial because they'll be like, okay,
if your neural network is infinite width,
then yes, we can approximate everything.
The key fact is both that they're universal approximators
and also that they're relatively sample efficient,
at least relative to things we found in the past.
And so that to me suggests that yes,
they can compensate for things that they're bad at.
On the other hand, the way research is trending
is towards these mixed models,
ensembles of different kinds of architectures,
things like the recent Q transformer
announced from Google DeepMind,
which just sort of uses a combination of transformers
and Q learning to have sort of the associational memory
and sample efficiency of transformers
with the ability to assign policies to do tasks
that you get from reinforcement learning.
So I imagine that there's going to be all kinds
of mixing and matching.
The key point is that in that space of architectures,
it's a relatively sort of finite search space, right?
And as an economist, economists believe
that supply is long run elastic, right?
And so there's this famous bet from the team,
Paul Ehrlich and Julian Simon vis-a-vis the population bomb
and whether population growth would lead
to sort of a mothusian purge.
And Julian Simon being the economist
recognized that if prices rise for these core commodities,
then that will spur research and development
into extracting new resources, right?
So he didn't have to know
that fracking would be a technology.
He understood that if oil prices went too high,
people would find new oil reserves.
And I think there's, I have an analogous instinct
when it comes to progress and deep learning,
meaning you can become too anchored
to sort of the current state of the literature,
but over a tenure horizon, you can say,
well, there's a huge search on a huge gold rush
to find the right way of blending these architectures.
And I don't need to know in advance,
which is the right way to do that
to have high confidence that someone will find it.
Yeah, we can sometimes, if we're too deep in the literature,
we might lose the focus on the forest for the trees
in a sense.
And if we zoom out, we can just see
that there's more investment, there's more talent
pouring into AI, and so we can predict
that something is gonna come out of that.
You have lots of interesting insights
about information theory
and how this can help us predict AI.
What's the most important lessons from information theory?
The reason I start there is because sort of,
within the conceptual realm,
it's sort of like the most general thing
that bounds everything else.
And when you look back at the record of, say,
Ray Kurzweil, I first read The Age of Spiritual Machines
when I was a kid, and in there,
he makes a prediction that we'll have
AIs that pass the Turing test by 2029 or so.
And when was this book written?
1999.
Yeah, that's pretty good.
Right, and so, and people will complain
that he got things wrong,
because he said, well, I'll be wearing AR glasses by 2019,
when in fact, Google Glass came out in 2013,
and now we have Meta Glasses five years later.
So he was wrong on the exact timing,
but sort of right where the technology was wrong,
where the minimal viable product was.
But nonetheless, if you look at his track record,
it's quite good for a methodology
as relatively stupid as just staring at Moore's Law,
and extrapolating it out.
And I think that reveals the power
of these information theoretic methodologies to forecasting
because they set bounds on what will be possible.
The team at epoch.ai have a forecast
called the direct approach where it's sort of,
you can think of it sort of like a way of putting bounds
on when we'll have AIs that can emulate human performance
through an information theoretic lens
where they're looking at sort of how much entropy
does the brain sort of process
and how much compute will we have over time
and what's implied by AI scaling laws.
And you sort of put those three things together
and you can sort of set bounds
on when we'll basically be able to brute force
human level intelligence.
And of course, that's an upper bound
because we're going to do better than brute force.
We're going to also have insights
from cognitive science and neuroscience
and also ways of distilling neural networks and so forth
and better ways of curating data.
So their modal estimate for human level AI is 2029
and their meeting is like 2036.
And I've talked to the authors and they lean towards
the 2029, 2030 for their own personal forecasts.
And so going back to, is this a net liar?
Am I out on a limb here?
I think among our circles probably not,
but among Congress and among the broader public,
I think people are seeing sort of,
they think everything's an asymptote, right?
They're imagining, okay, we have these chatbots
and they're not seeing the next step.
I see a very smooth path from here to systems
that can basically in context learn
any arbitrary human task.
And so what does that look like?
It looks like systems that can basically sit over your shoulder
or can monitor your desktop, your operating system as you work
and watch you for an hour or two and then take over.
And that'll be key to overcoming lack of training data
or why is it important that they can learn in context?
Well, in context learning is sort of the secret source
of the power of transformer models.
They learn these inductive biases and induction heads
and so forth that let them,
a few shot learn different tasks.
So, GPT-4 is very good at zero shot learning
on a variety of different things,
but it's incredibly good at few shot learning.
If you give it a few examples,
it can kind of pick up where you left off.
You know, when I think about myself,
when I wanna learn a new recipe, right?
I can go read a recipe book,
but often what I prefer to do is to go on YouTube
and watch someone make that recipe, right?
And just by watching that person put together the stir fry,
I have enough of a world model
and enough of knowledge of how to cook in general
that I can sort of in context learn
how to pick up from there and do that recipe myself.
LLMs do that already.
Multimodal models are increasingly doing that.
Some of the recent progress in robotics,
like I mentioned, the Q-transformer paper,
it shows that you can basically build robots
as a basic world model
and then have it learn new tasks
with fewer than 100 examples of the human demonstration.
So the human sort of demonstrates the task
and the robot can pick it up and take it from there.
And why that's important is both
for understanding the trajectory of AI,
but also its economic implementation
because we're sort of used to automation
being this thing where you get a contract from IBM
and you spend many millions of dollars with consultants
and they build you some bespoke thing
that doesn't really work very well
and requires lots of maintenance.
And so people have this sort of prior that AI,
even if it's near, will be rate limited by the real world
because of all the complexity of implementation.
But the point is if you have things that can in context learn
and perform sort of as humans perform,
then you don't need to change the process.
You can take human designed processes
and have the AI just fill in for the human.
And so it leads to this paradox
where we're probably going to have AGI
before we get rid of the last fax machine.
Yeah, when we think of say old IT systems
in large institutions, we might think of moving
from analog storage of information to the cloud.
That's still going on in some institutions.
That transformation has taken over a decade now.
And so what exactly is it that makes AI different here?
It is that AI plugs in directly
where the human worker would be?
Yeah, precisely.
You don't need to redesign existing process
to sort of plug into the automation.
And that applies both for sort of the structure of tasks.
So much of a mechanical automation
takes something like the sort of artisanal work
of a shoemaker and has to translate it
into something repetitive that a machine
or an automatic seamstress can do over and over and over
or against our older school kind of automation
requires sort of collapsing a task into a lower dimension
so that simple automations can handle it.
But when you have AGI, the whole point is generality.
It's a flexible intelligence
that can map to existing kinds of processes.
So that's sort of why I think this will catch people
by surprise because it's not just that AGI
could be this decade, but that when it arrives
and sort of crosses some thresholds of reliability,
the implementation frictions could be very low.
And do you expect, would AI have to get all the way there
in order to substitute for a human worker?
I mean, I would expect it to be a bit more gradual
than that, taking over say 20% of tasks
before 40% of tasks, 60% of tasks and so on.
But here we're imagining that the AI kind of plugs in
for the human worker for all tasks
or what do you have in mind?
These things are, yeah, you're right, much more continuous.
It's not an on or off switch in part
because the requisite threshold of reliability
varies by the type of task.
Arguably self-driving cars like Waymo or Tesla
have matched human performance,
but regulators want them to be 100x better than human
before they're loose on the road because of safety.
Codex and coding models are arguably still much worse today
than elite programmers, but everyone is using them
because even if it generates 50% of your code
and you have to go back in and debug,
it's still a huge productivity boost.
So I think it will vary by occupation,
by sort of task category, sort of modulo,
the risks and stakes involved in those tasks.
Yeah, I guess then the question is,
how many of our jobs fall into the,
is more like self-driving cars
and how many of our jobs is more like programming?
Right, I mean, I've been in a manager position before
and I've had research assistants and interns
and I know that they're like a very lossy compression
of the thing I want to do.
And so they require oversight and sort of co-poniting.
We're sort of in that stage now with AIs
in a variety of different kinds of tasks.
I recently read a paper evaluating the use of GPT-4
for peer review and science
and it found that GPT-4 would write reviews of work
that bore some striking correlations
with the points raised by human reviewers,
but also let some things out.
And so it concluded by saying GPT-4
could be an invaluable tool for scientific review,
but it's not about to replace people.
And that's just a case of like, okay, give it five years.
Yeah, this is a phenomena you often see
with some AI models out there
and it has some capabilities, but lacks other capabilities.
And then people might kind of over anchor
on the present capabilities
and not foresee the way the development is going.
I think people are continually surprised
at the advancement of AI.
Yeah, absolutely.
Ramiz Naam, the sci-fi author and futurist
and energy investor, he gives his talk on solar energy
and other renewables and he has this famous graph
where he shows the International Energy Agency, the IEA.
Every year they put out this projection of solar buildout
and every year it's like a flat line,
but it's like a flat line on an exponential,
like the real curve is like going vertical
and every year their projection is that it's just going
flat-toe and I feel like people make that same mistake.
And it sort of has this sort of ironic lesson,
to the extent that we're drawing sort of parallels
with the way our brain works and the way these models work,
it seems like humans have a very strong
autoregressive bias.
So what's going on there?
Is it an institutional problem
or is it a psychological problem?
Why is it that we can't project correctly in many cases?
Well, to what I just said, I think it's probably both,
but largely psychological, right?
Our brains are evolved for, you know,
hunter-gatherer societies that didn't really change
over millennia and, you know, even the last 40, 50 years
have been a period of relative stagnation
where we have a lot of sort of pseudo-innovation.
And so I think people are just a bit sort of disabused.
Okay, you have some super interesting points
about comparing the human brain,
how the human brain works to how neural networks learn.
What is universality in the context of brain learning
and neural network learning?
So universality is a term of our sort of refers to
the fact that different neural networks
independently trained, you know, even on different data
will often converge on very similar representations
in their embedding space of that data.
And you can extend that to striking parallels
or isomorphisms between the representations
that artificial neural networks learn
and that our brain appears to learn.
Probably the area of the brain that's been studied the most
is the visual cortex.
And it seems to me as like a layperson
that the broad consensus in neuroscience
is that the visual cortex is very similar
to a deep convolutional neural network.
It's basically isomorphic to our artificial
deep convolutional neural networks.
And you train CCN on image data
and our brain is trained on our sensory data.
And it turns out they end up learning
strikingly similar representations.
And there are a few reasons for that, right?
So, you know, one is sort of hierarchies of abstraction.
It makes sense that early layers in a neural network
will learn things like edges and simple shapes
and only later in the only deeper in the network
will you learn more subtle features.
So there's that sort of sequencing part of it.
And then there's also just the energy constraint.
You know, gradient descent isn't costless, right?
It requires energy, it requires a lot of energy.
That's, you know, these data centers suck up a lot of energy.
The same is true of our brain.
You know, our brain consumes a lot of energy,
like 25% of our calories.
And especially when it's, and when we're young,
there's a very strong metabolic cost
associated with neural plasticity.
Our brain being something shaped by evolution
was obviously very energy conscious.
And so those energy constraints greatly shrink the landscape
of possible representations from sort of this infinite
landscape of all the ways you could represent certain data
to a much more manageable set of representations.
And that doesn't guarantee that we'll converge
on the same representations.
At least suggestive of a weak universality
where even when we don't have the exact same representations,
they're often a coordinate transformation
that play from each other.
It's actually a bit surprising, so as you mentioned,
when we train neural networks,
we don't have the same energy constraints
as the brain had during our evolution.
And I would expect, again, from evolution,
that the human brains have many more inbuilt biases
and heuristics.
But if we then compare the representations
in a neural network to those in a human brain,
we found that they are quite similar.
Isn't that the whole point of universality?
So does the neural network have the same heuristics
and biases that we have, or what's going on here?
Well, one of the primary biases in stochastic gradient
descent is sometimes called a simplicity preference,
basically an inductive bias for more parsimonious
representations.
Parsimonious in the sense of Occam's razor.
And that's a byproduct of this information
heuristic concept of Kolmogorff complexity,
where Kolmogorff complexity means
is measured by, is there a short program that
can reproduce this longer sequence?
And if you can find a short program that's
sort of a more compact or more compressed way of representing
it, and when you're under energy constraints,
you're looking for those more compressed representations.
And so that simplicity bias seems
to be also the origin of generalization,
of our ability to go beyond merely memorizing data,
overfitting our parameters, to finding a simpler way of
representing those parameters, right?
Where we go from sort of fitting a bunch of data points
to recognizing, oh, these data points are being generated
by a sine function, so I can replace all these data points
by a simple circuit for that sine function
or something like that.
What can we learn about AI progress
when we consider the hard steps that humans
and our ancestors have gone through in evolution?
It's beyond evolution.
This is often comes up in the discussion
of the Fermi Paradox.
Life on Earth to exist at all, let alone intelligent life,
had to pass through many hard steps, right?
We had to have a planet in a habitable zone.
We had to have, you know, the right mix
of organic chemicals in the Earth's crust and so forth.
We had to have the conditions for abiogenesis,
the emergence of the very earliest sort of
non-living replicators, probably, you know,
some kind of polymer type of crystal structure.
Then we had to have, you know,
the transition from single cell to multicellular organisms,
to transition through the Cambrian explosion, right?
Every one of these steps,
you could think of as a very unlikely improbable thing.
All the way up to, you know,
the development of warm-blooded mammals
and sort of social animals that were heavily selected for,
for brain size, to then the sociocultural hard steps
of like moving from small group primates
to sort of settled technological cultures.
Then, you know, technological hard steps,
like the discovery of the printing press
or the discovery of the transistor.
You put those all together and life seems
just incredibly unlikely.
And, you know, this often goes to the point of view
that, you know, creationists or intelligent designers
would put forward.
But then you zoom out and then you recognize,
oh, wait, there are, you know, trillions of galaxies
each with trillions, you know, hundreds of billions
of stars and hundreds of trillions of planets.
There's an awful lot of potential variation out there.
And then meanwhile, every one of these hard steps
seems characterized by a search problem that is very hard.
But then once you find the correct thing,
like the earliest self-replicator,
things kind of take off, right?
So you imagine that before the earliest self-replicator,
there were millions or billions of attempts
to self-replicate, like that didn't succeed.
Yeah, it's just a huge search problem, right?
And, you know, maybe there are more gradual intermediate
stages where you have sort of, you know,
everything in biology ends up looking way more gradual
more you learn about it.
But there are these phase transitions where you tip over
and you get the Cambrian explosion
or you get the printing press and the printing revolution.
And so those hard steps end up looking relatively,
they look more easy in retrospect
because even though the search was hard,
once you've tripped over the correct solution,
there's sort of an autocatalytic self-reinforcing loop
that pulls you into a new regime.
And indeed, when you look at the emergence of life on Earth
relative to the age of the universe,
and Avi Lo with some co-authors have done this,
life on Earth is incredibly early.
Like, you know, the universe is 13.7 billion years old,
but life couldn't emerge really much sooner.
The reason being the universe started out as hot and dense,
it had to cool down, stars had to form,
those stars had to supernovae
so they could produce the heavy elements
that are essential to life.
And then those solar systems had to then take shape
and then had to further cool
so the solar system wasn't being irradiated constantly.
And when you put all those factors together,
human life emerged basically as soon as it was possible
for life to emerge anywhere.
And so this is one way to answer the Fermi paradox
that we're just in the first cohort, right?
But it also should give you strong priors
that passing through those hard steps
isn't as hard as it looks.
And what's the lesson for AI here?
Developing AGI is sort of a hard step.
We're doing this kind of gradient search
for the right algorithms, for the right, what have you.
And we seem to be now in a slow takeoff
where we've figured out the core ingredients
and there's now an autocatalytic process
that's pulling us into a new phase.
And what do you mean by autocatalytic?
Suffering, forcing, once it gets started,
it pulls itself, it sort of has an as if teleology, right?
You see this in nature,
but you also see this in capitalism.
And you would expect us to get to advanced AI
basically as soon as it's computationally possible.
It basically seemed that way, right?
Like, there was a kind of tacit collusion
between Google and other players in the space
to they had transformer models since 2017,
but really, there's some of the precursors
to transformers go back to the early 90s.
But once you have this sort of profit opportunity
that's in the background,
it's hard in the competitive environment
to stop an open AI from being like,
oh, let's chase those profits.
And then once that ball gets rolling,
it's basically impossible to stop.
This is why whatever the merits of the pause letter,
it's virtually impossible to really have a pause
in AI development because everything is sort of structured
by these game theoretic incentives to just keep going faster.
Once you've stumbled on the gold reserve,
it's hard to keep the prospectors from running there.
Samuel, is the US government prepared for advanced AI?
No.
No, I mean, where do I start?
I mean, the US government, if you think of it
from a firmware level, many countries have national IDs.
The US doesn't have a national ID.
We have social security numbers.
There are these like nine digit numbers
that date back to 1935.
We have the core administrative laws
date back to the early 40s.
Much of our sort of technical infrastructure,
like the system the IRS runs on,
date back to the Kennedy administration
and are written in assembly code.
There's also been this general decline
in what you could call state capacity, sort of the ability
for the US government to execute on things.
And you hear about this all the time.
You hear about how the Golden Gate Bridge was built
in four years or something like that.
And now it takes like 10 years to build an access road.
One of the reasons for that goes to what the legal scholar
Nicholas Bagley has called the procedural fetish.
Really, since the 70s, the machinery of the US government
has shifted towards a reliance on explicit process.
And proceduralism has pluses and minuses.
If you have a clear process, government
can kind of run an autopilot to an extent.
But it also means you limit the room for discretion
and you limit the flexibility of government to move quickly.
And moreover, in our adversarial legal system,
you also open up avenues for sort of continuous judicial review
and legal challenge, where famously New York has taken
over three years to approve congestion pricing
on one of their bridges because that's
to undergo environmental review.
And people who don't want to pay the congestion price
keep suing.
Do you think having more procedures
would make it easier for AI to interface with government?
I would say having fewer procedures
would make it easier for government to adapt.
My assumption would be that having something written down,
having a procedure for something would make it easier for AI
to plug AI into that procedure.
If it's less opaque and more kind of almost like an algorithm
step by step.
Yes.
But the analogy I would give is to the Manhattan Project.
The original Manhattan Project was run like a startup.
You had Oppenheimer and General Leslie Groves sort
of being the technical founder and the Type A
get things done founder.
And they broke all the rules.
They pushed as hard as they could.
They were managing at its peak like 100,000 people in secret.
And they built the nuclear bomb in three years.
And so the way we would do that today
under procedural fetish framework
would be to put out a bunch of request for proposals
and have some kind of competitive bid.
And then we'd probably get the lowest cost bid.
And it would be Lockheed Martin.
And they would build half an atom bomb.
And it would take 20 years and five times the budget.
And so that's sort of what I'm getting at.
It's not about process versus discretion per se.
It's about the way process hobbles and straight jackets
are ability to adapt and sort of represents
a kind of sclerosis, a kind of crystallized intelligence.
We lay down the things that worked in the past as process
and sort of freeze those processes in place,
ossifying a particular modality.
And when the motor production shifts
and you need to completely tear up
that process, root and branch, is very difficult.
Because often there's no process for changing the process.
Yeah, I wonder if there are lessons
for how government will respond to AI
and thinking about how governments responded
to, say, historical technical innovations
of a similar magnitude, like the Industrial Revolution
or the printing press or maybe the internet computer.
Do you think we can draw general lessons?
Or is it so specific that we can't really
extract information about the future from them?
I think there are very powerful general lessons.
I think one of the first general lessons
is that every major technological transformation
in human history has preceded a institutional transformation.
Whether it's the shift from nomadic to settled city
states with the agricultural revolution
or the rise of modern nation states
or the end of feudalism with the printing press
to in the New Deal era, the sort of transition
with industrialization from the kind of laissez-faire,
classical liberal phase of 18th century America
to an America with a robust welfare state
and administrative bureaucracies and really
in all new constitutional order.
And so there's sort of better and worse ways
for this transition to happen.
There's sort of the internal regime change model.
And you can think of Abraham Lincoln or FDR
as inaugurating a new republic, a new American republic.
Or there's a scenario where we don't change
because we're too crystallized and sort of like an innovator's
dilemma get displaced by some new upstart.
And there are different countries have different abilities
and different sort of capacities for that internal adaptation.
As a Canadian, I'm a big fan of Westminster-style
parliamentary systems.
And one of the reasons is because it's
very easy for parliamentary systems
to shut down ministries, open up new ministries,
to reorganize the civil service because it's sort
of vertically integrated under the Prime Minister's office
or what have you.
In the US, it's much worse because given
the separation of powers, Congress and the executive
are often not working well together as an understatement.
But then moreover, the different federal agencies
have it sort of a life of their own.
Often they're self-funded and all these other things
that make it very difficult to reform.
Do you think Canada responded better
to the rise of the internet than the US, for example?
Isn't there something wrong with the story
because the US kind of birthed the internet
and Canada adopted the internet from the US?
Let's compare, first of all, the impact of the internet
on weaker states because Canada and the US
are similar or sort of in one quadrant.
They have differences, but the differences
are small compared to other countries.
If you think about internet safety discussions that
would have been taking place in the early 2000s,
people would have been talking about identity theft,
credit card theft, child exploitation, these kind
of direct first order potential harms from the internet.
They didn't foresee that concurrent with the rise of mobile
and social media that the internet would enable tools
for mass mobilization simultaneous
with a kind of legitimacy crisis where
the sort of new transparency and information access
that the internet provided eroded trust and government
and trust in other institutions.
So you have these two forces interacting,
the internet exposing government and exposing corruption
and leading to a decline in trust while also creating
a platform for people to rise up and mobilize against that
corruption.
And it's something that kind of rhymes
with the printing press and the printing revolution
where you had these sort of dormant suppressed minority
groups like the Puritans or the Presbyterians,
the nonconformists, and with the collapse
of the censorship printing licensing regime.
They actually had a licensing regime in the UK parliament
back circa 1630.
That licensing regime collapsed,
there I think 1634 or something around there,
and that was like five years before the English Civil War.
And you see something like this in the Arab Spring
where the internet quite directly led
to mass mobilization in Cairo and Tunisia and elsewhere
and led to actual regime change,
in some cases sort of temporary state collapse.
And that's because those were weaker states
that hadn't democratized,
that hadn't sort of had their own information revolution
earlier in their history the way we did, right?
In some ways like the American Republic
is sort of a founder country built on the backbone
of the printing revolution.
So we were a little bit more robust to that
because it's sort of part of our ethos
to have this open disagreeable society.
But clearly the internet has also affected
the legitimacy of Western democracies.
I think it's clear, clearly one of the major inputs
in sort of rising populism,
the mass mobilizations that we see,
whether in the US context, the 2020 racial awakening
or the January 6th sort of peasant rebellion, right?
These sort of look like the kind of color revolutions
that we see abroad.
And some people want to ascribe conspiracy theories
to that, I think there's a simpler explanation,
which is that people will self-organize
with the right tools.
Our state hasn't collapsed yet,
but there's clearly a lot of cracks in the foundation,
if you will.
Is it, would it be fair to say that the main lesson
for you from history is that technological change
brings institutional change?
Yeah, not necessarily one for one.
I'm not kind of a vulgar Marxist on this, but yes.
And the reason for that is because institutions themselves
exist due to a certain cost structure.
And if you have general purpose technologies
that dramatically change the nature
of that cost structure, then institutional change will follow.
Yeah, and I think we want to get to that.
But before we do, I think we should discuss AI's impact
on the broader economy.
So not just the government, but the economy in general.
Economists have this fallacy they point out often,
the lump of labor fallacy.
Maybe you could explain that.
The lump of labor fallacy is essentially the idea
that there's a fixed amount of work to be done.
If you were thinking about the Industrial Revolution
and what would happen to the 50% of people
who are in agriculture, you couldn't imagine
the new jobs that would be created.
But new jobs were created.
And the reason is because human wants are infinite.
And so demand will always fill supply.
The second reason is because there's a kind of circular flow
in the economy where one person's cost
is another person's income.
Society would collapse if we had true technological
unemployment because there'd be things being produced
but no one to pay for them.
And so that ends up kind of bootstrapping new industries
and new sources of production.
There's still this open question, is this time different?
Yeah, that's exactly what I wanna know.
Because for me, it's in retrospect, let's say.
It's easy to see how workers could move from fields
to factories into offices.
But if we have truly general AI,
it's difficult for me to see where workers would move.
Especially if we have also functional robots
and perhaps AIs that are better at taking care of people
than other people are.
I'm not asking you to predict specific jobs,
but I'm asking you whether you think
this historical trend will hold with the advent
of advanced AI.
You know, the first thing to say is, you know,
when Keynes wrote economic possibilities
for our grandchildren, a famous text where he predicted
that technological progress would lead
to the growth of a leisure society.
And this was in the 1930s, yeah.
You know, people have dismissed him as being wrong,
but actually you look at time use data
and employment data and people are working less.
You know, it's not, it didn't match his,
the optimism of his projection, right?
Because it turns out, you know, maybe if we fixed
living standards at what he expected,
people want more and people will work more for more.
But overall, people are working less.
People do have more leisure.
We've sort of moved to a de facto four-day work week.
So there's one world where rapid technological progress
sort of continues that trend and we all work less.
It's sort of a technological unemployment
that's spread across people and is enabled in part
because in a world of AGI, maybe you only have to work,
you know, a few hours a day to make $100,000 a year.
There's another possibility which is that,
well, AGI could in principle be a perfect emulation
of humans on specific tasks.
It can't emulate the historical formation of that person.
Right?
So what I mean by that is if you had a perfect
Adam by Adam replication of the Mona Lisa,
it wouldn't sell at auction, right?
Because people aren't just buying the physical substrate,
they're also buying the kind of world line of that thing.
And that's clearly the case in humans as well.
Like there are certain, you know, talking heads
that I go and enjoy not because they are the smartest
or would have you because I'm interested
in what that person thinks on this
because they have a particular personality,
a particular world line.
And then the third factor is sort of artificial scarcity.
Right?
And so even in a world with abundance and supply
in services and goods, there are still things
that will be intrinsically scarce,
real estate being probably the canonical thing,
but also energy and commodities and so forth.
And the reason real estate is intrinsically scarce
because people want to live near other people
and people want to live in particular areas of a city.
They want to live in the posh part of town, right?
And those are positional goods.
We can't all live in the trendy loft.
So that builds in a kind of artificial scarcity.
And so people will still be competing over those things.
This is sort of related to artificial scarcity,
but there's also sort of break it out
into a fourth possibility, which are sort of tournaments
and things that are structured as tournaments.
Having chess spots that are strictly better
than humans at chess hasn't killed people playing chess.
If anything, more people play chess today
than they've had in human history.
Yeah, it's more popular than ever.
Yeah.
And the reason is because people like to watch
other humans playing and also they're structured
as sort of zero sum tournaments
where there can only be the best human.
You look at other things that have been created
just in the last 15, 20 years, the X games, right?
I think people will still want to watch other people
do the Olympics or do motocross
and all these other things.
And so maybe more of our life shifts into,
both maybe greater leisure on the one hand,
more competition over positional goods
and more production that is structured as a tournament.
Yeah, yeah, I can see many of those points.
I'm just thinking, again, with fully general AI,
you would be able to generate
a much more interesting person playing chess
or at least a simulation of a very charismatic
and interesting human chess player.
Why wouldn't people watch that chess player
as opposed to the best human?
Maybe they will, sorry to know.
The question is who's producing that video stream
because you still need the human behind it
that had the idea, right?
And you could imagine people being dishonest
about the history of this chess player.
The simulated chess player could be a fully digital,
fully fictional, so to speak,
and just pretending to be human.
Right, so they could fool people.
That's the case too.
No, I can't rule that out,
but I would just say that
however that person is monetizing,
their deep fake chess player,
they're making money, which they're then spending back
into the economy, and so they'll produce jobs somewhere.
Do you think more people will move into,
say, people-focused industries like nursing and teaching?
Is that a possible way for us to maintain jobs?
Maybe nursing, at least in the short run.
I'm not very long on education
being labor-intensive for much longer.
But you don't think education,
at least say, great school education,
is that really about teaching people or conveying knowledge?
Or to what extent is it about conveying knowledge?
And to what extent is it about the social interaction
and specializing your teaching to the individual student?
Well, AI is very good at customization
and sort of mastery tutoring.
Education is a bundle of things.
And for younger ages, it's also daycare.
It is socialization, like you said.
At the very least, it's just a reorganization
of the division of labor,
because the types of teachers that you would select
or hire for may differ if the education component
of that bundle is being done by AI.
Maybe you select for people who are,
maybe don't have any subject matter expertise,
but are just highly conscientious and go to around kids.
Or maybe you one bundle from public education altogether,
and it re-bundles around a jujitsu school
or a chess academy, because you'll have the AI tutor
that will teach you math,
but you'll still want to grapple with the human.
Yeah, yeah.
What about industries with occupational licensings
like law or medicine?
Will they be able to keep up their quite high wages
in the face of AI being able to be a pretty good doctor
and a pretty good lawyer?
It's easy to solve for the long-term equilibrium.
With the rise of the internet,
you can do a comparison of the wage distribution
for lawyers pre and post internet.
And, you know, circa the early 90s,
lawyer incomes were normally distributed
around $60,000 a year.
You know, after in the 2000s, they become bimodal.
And so you have one mode that's still around
that $60,000 range, those are like the family lawyers.
And then you have this other mode
that's into the six figures.
And those are like big law, right?
It's the emergence of these law firms
where you have a few partners on top
and maybe hundreds of associates
who are doing kind of grant work using Westlaw
and Lexus Nexus and these other legal search engines
to accelerate drafting and legal analysis.
So if that pattern repeats,
I could imagine these various high-skill knowledge sectors
to also become bimodal where in the short run,
AI serves as a co-pilot, sort of like Westlaw
or Lexus Nexus was for legal research
and enables the kind of 100x lawyer.
And so there's a kind of averages over dynamic.
The longer run, you know, you start to see the possibility
of doing an end run around existing accreditation
and licensing monopolies
where obviously the American Medical Association
and medical boards will be highly resistant to an AI doctor.
I tend to think that they'll probably end up self cannibalizing
because the value prop is so great
even for doctors to do simple things
like automate insurance paperwork and stuff like that.
But to the extent that there is a resistance,
to the extent that in 10 years there's still a requirement
that you must have the doctor prescribe the treatment
or refer you to a specialist,
even though the AI is doing all the work
and they're just sort of like the elevator person
that's like actually just pushing the button for you.
It'll be very easy to end run that
because AI is both transforming the task itself
but also transforming it's the means of distribution.
And if you can go to GPT-4 and ask for,
put in your blood work and get a diagnosis,
but no regulator's going to stop that, right?
And so, you know, GPT-4 becomes sort of
the ultimate doctor of up orders.
You write a lot about transaction costs
and how changes in transaction costs
change institutional structures.
First of all, what are transaction costs
and how do you think they'll be affected by AI?
So transaction cost is sort of an umbrella term
for different kinds of costs associated with market exchange.
And this goes back to Ronald Coase's famous paper
on the theory of the firm where he asked the question,
why do we have corporations in the first place?
If free markets are so great,
why don't we just go up and spot contract for everything?
And the answer is, well, market exchange itself has a cost.
There's the cost of monitoring.
You know, if you hire a contractor,
you don't know exactly what they're doing.
There's the cost of bargaining.
You know, having to haggle with a taxi cab driver
is a friction.
And there's the cost of searching,
the associate of searching information.
So taking those three things together,
they're not all that companies do,
but they structure the boundary of the corporation.
They explain why some things are done in-house
and some things are done through contracts.
If there's high monitoring costs,
you want to pull that part of the production
into the company so that you can monitor
and manage the people doing the production.
And some of the same effects go for
the existence of governments, right?
Yes, because governments, you know,
with a certain gestalt,
governments and corporations aren't that different.
There are kinds of institutional structures
that pull certain things in-house
and certain things are left for contracting or outsourced.
And, you know, you even see sort of different kinds
of governments having different parallels
with different kinds of corporate governance, right?
Relatively egalitarian democratic societies
like Denmark are kind of like mutual insurers.
Whereas more hierarchical authoritarian countries
are more like, you know, like Singapore, say,
is more of a joint stock corporation.
And indeed, you know, Singapore was founded
as a, as a, uh,
an entrepot for the East India Company.
So there are very deep parallels.
And it's also essential.
Transaction costs are essential
to understand why governments do certain things
and other things.
All Western developed governments
guarantee some amount of basic health care, right?
But, um, most, you know,
outside of, say, the National Health Service in,
in the UK, most of these countries, uh,
guarantee the insurance.
They don't necessarily nationalize the actual providers,
right?
And the reason goes to transaction costs
and sort of an analysis of the market failure
and insurance.
Likewise with roads, uh, you know,
it's possible to build roads through purely private means.
And indeed, um, you know, countries like Sweden,
a lot of the roads are run by private associations.
But, uh, if you have lots of different boundaries,
different micro jurisdictions and so forth,
there can be huge transaction costs
to, uh, negotiating up to a,
to a interstate highway system.
Um, and, and those transaction costs
then necessitate public infrastructure projects.
So the transaction costs in this case
would be being a private road provider.
You'd have to go negotiate with 500 different landowners
about building a highway,
whereas a government can do some expropriation
and simply build the road much, much faster,
or with less transaction costs at least.
Yeah, precisely.
And we're seeing this, this dynamic in the US
with, uh, you know, permitting for,
for great infrastructure and transmission.
You know, we're, we're building all this,
all the solar and renewable energy,
but to build the actual transmission, uh, infrastructure
to get the electrons from where it's sunny to where,
where it's cold requires building, you know,
high voltage, uh, lines across state lines
across different grid regions.
And there are all kinds of NIMBs
and negotiation costs involved, holdouts and so forth.
And so that the more those kind of costs exist,
the more it militates towards a kind of, um,
larger scale intervention that, you know,
federalizes that process.
Yeah, the big question then is how will AI
change these transaction costs?
What, what will the effects be here?
It's easy to say that they will be affected.
And, you know, obviously the internet affected them
to, to an extent.
And we were talking, we talk about sort of the ease
of mobilizing protest movements or the kind of, uh,
the sunlight that was put on government corruption.
Those are, those are reflecting declines
in the cost associated information and coordination.
I think AI takes us to another level.
And I think it's, it's important to, to think through
in part because right now the AI safety debate,
at least in the United States is very polarized
between people who are like, everything's going to be great.
And people who are like, this is like a terminator scenario
or an AI kill us all existential risk.
You know, even if we accept the, you know,
existential risk framing, there's still going to be
many intermediate stages of AI before we flip
on the superintelligence.
And those intermediate stages have enormous implications
for the structure of the very institutions
that we'll need to respond to superintelligence
or what have you.
The ways we can see this is because all these information
and, and monitoring and, and, uh, bargaining costs
are directly implicated by commoditized intelligence.
You know, start with the principal agent problem.
You know, there is no principal agent problem
if your agent does exactly as you ask and works 24 seven
doesn't steal from the till, right?
And so AI agents dramatically collapse agency cost
monitoring.
Now that we have multimodal models in principle,
we could have cameras in every house that are just being
prompted to say, you know, is someone committing a crime
right now?
Whether we wanted to go that direction or not,
it gives you a sense that of how, you know,
the cost of monitoring have basically plummeted
over the last two years and are going to go way lower.
And so you're starting to see this rolled out
in the private sector with, you know,
Activision has announced that they're going to be using
language models for moderating voice chat
and call duty, right?
And, and this, this is a more robust form of monitoring
because in the past you would have to like ban certain words
like certain swear words or things associated with
sexual violence, but then people could always get around
those by using euphemisms, right?
Like on YouTube, you know, the algorithm will ding you
if you talk about coronavirus or if you talk about murder
or suicide, these, these things that throw off at flags.
So what people have taken doing is saying they were
unalived rather than murdered, right?
And that doesn't fool a language model.
If you ask a language model, you know,
if you prompt it in a way to look for sort of broad
semantic categories, not just a narrow, a narrow word,
it's much more robust.
And so what that means, you know,
what you already start to see it, like I said,
with Activision and the use of LLAMS and content moderation,
you're going to start, you're going to see it in the use of
multimodal models for productivity management and tracking.
You know, Microsoft is unveiling their 365 co-pilot
where you're going to have GPT-4 and Word and Excel
and Teams and Outlook, but at the same time,
you're also going to have a manager who is going to be able
to say, you know, to prompt the model,
tell me who is the most productive this week, right?
Something as vague as that.
And so you see this diffusion in the private sector.
The question is, does it diffuse in the public sector?
There's obvious ways that it would be a huge boom, right?
You know, Inspector General GPT could tell you exactly,
you know, how the civil service is working,
whether there's corruption,
whether there's a deep state of conspiracy
or something like that, right?
And at first blush, a lot of what government does
is kind of a fleshy API.
Bureaucracies are nodes that apply a degree of context
between printing out a PDF and scanning it
back into the computer.
It varies.
There's degrees of human judgment that are required,
but on first order, government bureaucracies
seem incredibly exposed to this technology
in a way that could diffuse really rapidly
because, you know, going back to Microsoft 365 Copilot,
Microsoft is the biggest IT vendor in US government, right?
And so you can imagine once everyone has this pre-installed
on their computer that the person at the Bureau
of Labor Statistics who's in charge
of doing the monthly employment situation report,
the jobs report, you know, at some point
he's gonna be walking into work and hitting a button, right?
That, you know, asking Excel to find
the five most interesting trends and generate charts
and the report is done.
And in the private sector, that person would be reallocated
and maybe doing things that the computer's not good at yet,
but these positions are much stickier in government.
To the extent that diffusion is inhibited
on the public sector side,
I worry about the kind of disruption and displacement
of government services by a private sector
that's adopting the technology really fast.
This is something we'll talk about in a moment.
Before that, I just wanna get to your complaints
about isolated thinking about AI.
You've sketched out some complaint about people
thinking about AI only applying to one domain
and then not really seeing the bigger picture.
What are some examples here?
Why do you worry about isolated thinking?
A few dimensions to this.
One is what I've called the horse's carriage fallacy.
Right, the kind of view that, you know,
what automobiles were was just a carriage with the horse.
Right, and so that anchors you to the older paradigm
and it's like you're changing one thing
and everything else stays the same.
And you neglect all the second order ways
that the development of the automobile,
you know, enabled the build out of highway systems,
the total reconfiguration of sort of the economic geography.
Right, and then implications for institutions
at the state where, you know, once you have road networks
or telegraph networks or any of these,
these kind of networks, it suddenly becomes easier
to monitor agents of the state
and other parts of the country.
And so you can, you know, build out
more of a federal bureaucracy.
And so all these things were second order
and were kind of neglected if you just were too focused
on the first order effects of displacing the horses.
And in a sense, the second order effects
turned out to be much more consequential in the end.
Yes, it seemed to always be.
And likewise with the internet and sort of the,
I think this comes up a lot in the,
in how to think about AI use and misuse.
There's lots of valid discussions there,
but they're always very first order.
And when you think about the way the internet
has disrupted legacy institutions,
yes, there's disinformation,
but often the thing that's disrupting is not fake news.
It's real news that's being repeated
with misleading frequency, right?
That's like throwing off our availability heuristic.
Or it's valid things that, you know,
valid complaints, whether, you know,
the protests in Iran, right?
The protests in Iran have this like striking parallel
to the protests following the George Floyd protest
and protesting in other countries
where they even have like a three word chant, right?
Or the case of the Arab Spring in Tunisia
that started with the person self-immolating, right?
There's sort of like the structure that repeats
where you have like a martyr
or like some shocking event.
And because of the way social media is organized,
it synchronizes people around the event
in a way that's kind of stochastic.
Like it's like lightning striking.
You don't know what event it's going to strike on,
but once we're synchronized,
then we start, you know, moving back and forth
in a way that like causes the bridge to buckle.
Nothing about that is a misuse, right?
Those are all valid uses,
but their use is under collective action.
It's sort of solving not just for the partial equilibrium
but the general equilibrium when everyone is doing this.
And I think the person who wrote the best
on this sort of conceptually was Thomas Schelling
and one of his little books,
Micromotives, Macro Behavior,
A Big Influence on Me as a Kid,
where he talks about all these sort of like toy models
where you're at a hockey game or a basketball game
and something is happening,
something exciting is happening in the arena.
And so people in front of you stand up
to get a better view and then you have to stand up
to get a better view of them over them and so on.
And so it cascades and suddenly everyone went from sitting
to everyone went to standing
and no one's view has improved, right?
And so these sort of general equilibria
where you sort of solve for everyone's micro incentives
and the kind of new Nash equilibrium that emerges,
that ends up being the thing that drives
a kind of multiple equilibrium shift
from one regime to another.
And throughout, there may be no actual examples
of misuse involved.
It may just be people following their individual incentives.
I think it's worth the stressing this point you make
about the effects of earlier AI systems
on our institutions,
that they might have effects that deteriorate our institutions
such that we can't handle later and more advanced AI.
And ignoring this would be an example of isolated thinking
and ignoring the second order effects, right?
Yeah.
And they also, it also changes the sort of agenda, right?
The AI safety agenda shouldn't just be
about the first order of things or in alignment,
you know, very important,
but you know, it's led to a discussion of
do we need a new federal agency?
And if so, what kind of agency?
Whereas it may be more appropriate to think
not what new agency do we need,
but how do all the agencies change, right?
And how do we sort of like brace for impact
and enable a degree of co-evolution
rather than displacement?
I don't know whether the question of
how to get our institutions to respond appropriately
is more difficult or less difficult
than the problem of aligning AI.
But it certainly seems very difficult to me.
So is there, are we making it harder on ourselves
if we focus on the effects,
on the second order effects on institutions?
I mean, it's unavoidable.
I mean, we can't pick and choose what kind of problems,
but you know, the alignment problem,
the hard version is yet to be solved,
but we have many examples of governments
building state capacity and having kind of,
you know, shifting from very,
very like clientelistic, sticky corrupt governments
to sort of modernized governments
where you know, state capacity is built
and then that government can sort of break out
of the middle income trap and become rich.
You mentioned Estonia as an example of a country
that's pretty advanced on the IT front,
on the technology side.
Maybe you could talk a bit about Estonia.
Yeah, I would just say in general,
it's hard for any organization to reform itself from within
when there is path dependency,
but I would say at least we have examples of it being done
where we don't have examples of alignment being solved yet.
When it comes to Estonia,
you know, Estonia is an interesting case.
It's sort of an exceptional case
because after the fall of the Soviet Union
and the breakup of the peripheral former Soviet states,
they kind of had a blank slate, right?
They also had a very young population
and people who had a kind of hacker ethic
within their civil service.
And so with that blank slate and with that hacker ethic,
they were very early to adopt and to foresee
the way the internet was going to shape government
through a variety of e-government reforms.
So early in the late 90s and into the 2000s,
they were some of the earliest to digitize
their banking system like e-banking
to build this system called X-Road,
which is kind of like a cryptographically secured
data exchange layer that resembles a blockchain,
but it was about a decade before blockchain was invented.
For exchanging information
between different government entities,
your medical information could be uploaded to the system
and then be available to all systems
that have the right to see that information.
Exactly, in a way that's cryptographically secured
and distributed.
So if a missile hit the Department of Education,
you don't lose your education records
because it's distributed.
And that also enabled an enormous amount of automation
where, for instance, this is my understanding,
a child born in Estonia,
once you file that birth record,
it more or less initiates a clock in the system
that will then enroll your child in school
when they turn four or five automatically
because it knows that your child has aged
and then unless it had a death record to cancel that out.
That also means you can do taxes and transfers
much simpler, you get your benefit within a week.
It can integrate across different parts
of public infrastructure,
like use the same card to ride the bus
as you do to launch a new business.
And it also serves as a kind of platform
for the private sector to do government by API,
to build new services on top of government as a platform
and integrate with government databases.
Yeah, and so the point here for us
is that institutional reform is possible,
modernizing government is possible,
at least under certain circumstances.
We have proofs of concepts of this happening.
The hard thing is the path dependency.
There's always a strong instinct
to wanna start from scratch
and it's normally not advisable
because it's too hard.
And so this is why it's hard in the US.
This is why you have African countries
that leap progress in payment systems and so forth.
The challenge of this decade or century
is how do we solve that path dependency problem
and how do we get to Estonia?
It used to be get to Denmark.
Now let's get to Estonia
and find that sort of that pathway up mountain probable.
Great, let's get to your wonderful series of blog posts
on AI and Leviathan.
In this context, what do we mean by Leviathan?
Well, it's all interrelates.
So Leviathan was the book Hobbes,
Thomas Hobbes wrote at the start of the interregnum
after the English Civil War.
And it was basically his early political science,
early defense of absolutist monarchy
as a way to restore peace and order
after a decade of infighting.
And Hobbes kind of hit on some basic sort of structural
game theoretic properties of why we have governments at all.
He talked about life being nasty British and short
in the state of nature, war of all against all.
And peace is only restored
when people who don't trust each other
offload enforcement and policing responsibilities
to a higher power that can then restore
a degree of peace and order.
AI and Leviathan is talking about,
how does AI change the story?
Does it reinforce the Leviathan?
Does it lead to a digital police state China?
Or is it something that we impose on ourselves?
And we talked about how multimodal models
could in principle be used to put a camera
in everyone's house and have it just continuously monitoring
for people doing any kind of crime.
That's something that North Korea might do.
In the US context, it's something that we're very liable
to just voluntarily do to ourselves
because we want to have ring cameras
and Alexa assistants and so forth.
And so that leads to a kind of bottom up Leviathan
that is potentially no less oppressive
and maybe even more oppressive
because there's no one that we can appeal to
to change the rules.
Yeah, so Leviathan is one way to respond
to technological change, but you mentioned two other ways
we could alternatively respond.
Right, so basically any time a technology
greatly empowers the individual,
it creates a potential negative externality, right?
Hobbes called these our natural liberties.
In the state of nature, I have a natural liberty
to kill you or to strong arm you.
And governments exist to revoke those natural liberties, right?
But for a higher form of freedom, right?
And so there are sort of any time a technology greatly
increases human capabilities,
these are the other humans.
The three canonical ways we can adjust are,
you know, ceding more authority to that higher power,
the Leviathan option.
And then the other two options are,
you know, adaptation and mitigation
and normative evolution.
So the example I give is, you know,
if suddenly we all had X-ray glasses
and you could see through walls and see through clothing.
You know, one option, we have a draconian,
totalitarian crackdown that tries to seize
all those X-ray glasses.
Another option is we adjust normatively, culturally,
that we, our privacy norms wither away
and we stop caring about nudity.
And then the other option is adaptation and mitigation
where we put in, you know, mesh into our walls
and where we're leaded shirts and pants.
Yeah, I guess continuing that analogy a bit
between the smart glasses and AI,
you have this amazing write-up of ways
in which AI can increase the informational resolution
of the universe.
So you give some examples that are,
I think specifically of AI identifying people
by gate, for example.
Right, so gate recognition is nothing new.
China has had advanced forms of gate recognition
for a while now.
So, you know, even if you cover your face,
it turns out we're constantly throwing off
sort of ambient information about ourselves, about everything.
And the way you walk, the particular gate that you have
is a unique identifier.
Another example is galaxy surveys.
There's, we've had from Hubble telescope to now,
the JWST, tons of astronomical surveys
of distant galaxies and so forth.
And all of a sudden, all that old data,
it's like that same data set is now more useful
because applying more modern deep learning techniques,
we can extract entropy that was in that data set,
but we didn't have the tools to extract yet
and discover that, you know, there are new galaxies
or other phenomena that we missed.
Another example you give is listening for keystrokes
on a keyboard and extracting information
about a password being typed in, for example,
which is something that of course humans can do,
but we can do with AI models.
Yeah, so that was a paper showing that
you can reconstruct keystrokes from an audio recording,
including a Zoom conversation.
So I hope you haven't typed in your password
because people in the future, and so this goes to,
you know, the fact that it's sort of retroactive,
that like, even if the technology wasn't diffused yet,
any Zoom conversation, any recording
where someone typed their password in the future
will be like those galaxy surveys
where someone will go backwards in time
and, you know, turn up the information resolution
of that data.
Yeah, this is pure speculation,
but I wonder if, I mean, imagine anonymized people
in interviews, say 10 years ago,
whether they will be able to stay anonymous
or whether AI will be able to extract the data
about their face or their voice
that wasn't technically possible when the interview aired.
Yeah, exactly, there are already systems
for like, depixelating, you probably do something similar
for the voice modulation, and then also sort of, you know,
again, going back to like, this ambient information
we're always shedding, identifiers in the way we write,
you know, the kind, where we place a comma,
the kinds of adverbs we like to use and so forth.
People just dramatically underrate, you know,
how much information we're shedding,
in part because we're blind to it.
Some people who are taking great efforts
to stay anonymous online, people in the cryptography space,
for example, will put their writings
through Google Translate to French
and then back to English to erase subtle clues
to how they, that could identify them personally.
Why is AI so much better at tasks
like the ones we just mentioned, compared to humans?
Well, it goes back to what we were talking about
with sort of putting information theoretic bounds on AGI.
When you minimize the loss function
in a machine learning model,
you're trying to minimize the cross entropy loss.
The cross entropy is, how many bits does it take
to distinguish between two data streams?
And if it takes a lot of bits to distinguish between the two,
that means they're relatively indistinguishable.
So that's going, again, to the Turing test.
Like, if we have a Turing test where I can tell right away
that the AI is different than the human,
that suggests a high cross entropy.
But if I could talk to it for days
and do all kinds of adversarial questioning,
I might still be able to, in the end,
tell the difference between the two,
but we've minimized that cross entropy loss.
And so when you have any arbitrary data distribution
that you're trying to predict,
whether it's trying to predict galaxies
and astronomical data or passwords
from fingerprint data on a phone screen,
all these things embed a kind of physical memory
of the thing in question
and can often be reconstructed
through this kind of loss minimization,
where you have a system that asymptotically
extracts the entropy that was latent in the data.
And this can be done in a way
that is often quite striking,
where we can, with stable diffusion,
make fairly accurate predictions
of what people are imagining in their mind
using fMRI data.
And fMRI data is like blood flow data in the brain.
It's a very lossy representation
of what ever's happening in the brain.
But there's still enough latent entropy in there
that we can kind of reverse engineer
or decompress it into a folder picture.
And this could turn into a form of lie detection.
Yeah, I think it already basically has.
If you have fMRI data or EEGs
or other kinds of like direct brain data,
it's probably a lot easier,
but we already have systems that are over 95% accurate
at detecting deception from just visual video recordings.
We can see how all of this information
that we are continually shedding
gives rise to the possibility of alibiath
than either of the private or of the government's kind.
I wonder what role do you see
open-sourcing AI models playing here?
What are the trade-offs and risks in open-sourcing AI?
Among the people who are most bullish to open-source,
there's often a kind of libertarian ethic undergirding it.
Regardless of whether that's a good idea or not,
one of the things I'm trying to communicate to that group
is to say that be careful what you wish for
because of these kind of paradoxical Hobbesian dynamics.
The fact that in America,
you never know if someone has a gun or not.
On the one hand, the Second Amendment enhances our freedom.
On another hand, you don't get the sort of
like everyone's doors unlocked and people are,
like the police in England don't even have guns.
There's a certain freedom that derives
from us not all being heavily armed.
Likewise, with open-sourcing powerful AI capabilities,
it empowers you as an individual,
but in general equilibrium,
once we all have the capabilities,
the world could look much more oppressive
either because we're all spying on each other all the time
and we can all see through each other's walls
or because there's a backlash and the introduction
of the viathan type solutions
to restrict our ability to spy on each other all the time.
My general sense is that we can only delay
and we can't really prevent things
from being open-source over the long run
because there's a sort of trickle-down
of compute requirements.
But in the interim,
there are definitely things that are valuable to open-source,
having 70 billion parameter language models, not a threat.
In fact, I think it's probably useful for alignment research
for something like that to be open-source.
But if you are a researcher
and you've developed a emotional recognition model
that can tell if, you know, with like 99% accuracy,
whether someone is lying or not lying
and whether your girlfriend loves you or not,
like these things or the ability to see through walls
using, like I talk about the use of Wi-Fi displacement.
There are people who have built pose recognition models
using the displacement of the electromagnetic frequency
of your Wi-Fi and they can see,
they can, there's wall penetrating
so that you can see through walls.
Like, what's the rush to put that on hugging face
and to like make it as democratized as quickly as possible?
I would say that if we value the adaptation
and mitigation pathway as opposed to the Leviathan pathway,
then there's a value in, you know,
slow rolling some of these things.
How do you think government power will be,
or relative government power will be affected by AI?
So you write somewhere in this long series of blog posts
that AI will cause a net weakening of governments
relative to the private sector.
Why is that?
Yeah, specifically Western liberal governments
under constitutional constraints.
So if you imagine society being on this kind of knife edge,
I talked about this in the context of
Theranosso Mogul's book, The Neural Corridor,
where he describes liberal democracy
as sort of being in this corridor
between despotism on the one hand
and anarchy on the other.
And we sort of this day in this saddle path
where society and the state are kept in balance.
If you veer off that path, you can, on the one hand,
you know, the state could become all powerful
and that's the sort of China model
or authoritarian digital surveillance state.
And indeed, you know, China built up
their digital surveillance state
and their internet firewalls and so forth
after watching the Arab Spring
and seeing how the internet was destabilizing
to weaker governments.
And so I fully expect that AI will be very empowering
and self-reinforcing of the power of the Chinese government.
And indeed, there are draft regulations
for large language models stipulate
that you can't use the model
to undermine national unity or challenge the government.
And so they're baking that in.
In liberal democracies, we think of ourselves
as open societies.
And the issue is that we're only open at the meta level.
There's a public sphere, right?
There's freedom of information laws.
We have freedom of speech.
I don't have freedom of speech if I walk into a Walmart.
Wait, right?
The Walmart is private property.
In open societies, it's not that we don't have
social credit scores and forms of,
thicker forms of social regulation.
It's just that we offload those functions
onto competing private actors,
whether it's a church that has very strict doctrines
to be a member or other kinds of social clubs.
The fact that these days,
if you want to go to a comedy club,
they'll often confiscate your phone at the door
because they don't want you recording
the comedian's set and putting it online.
My anticipation is that because of those constitutional
constraints that limit the ability of liberal democracies
to go the China route, right?
Because of our civil laws or bills of rights and so forth.
And also because of a lot of these procedural constraints.
This will naturally shift into the private sector.
And we see that already with the use of AI
for monitoring and employment,
for policing speech in ways that would be illegal
if done by the state,
but are fine if done by Facebook.
To the extent that the AI continues
to increase these kind of negative externalities
and therefore puts more value
on having a sort of vertically integrated experience,
a walled garden that can strip out the negative forms of AI
and reinstate the degree of harmony between people
that more and more of our social life will be mediated
through these sort of private organizations
rather than through a kind of open public sphere.
Or you're imagining that government services
will be gradually replaced by private services
that are better able to respond.
Won't governments fight to uphold individual rights?
In Walmart or on Facebook,
you are regulated in ways
that the government couldn't regulate you,
but you still have the choice to go to a target
instead of Walmart or to go to or X instead of Facebook.
Isn't that the fundamental thing?
So the fundamental thing is the choice between services
and won't governments uphold citizens' rights
to make those kinds of choices?
Yeah, no, I agree.
And so this would be the defense of the liberal model
is that we allow thicker forms of social regulation
because it's moderated by choice and competition.
And the issue with Chinese Confucian integralism
isn't the fact that it's super oppressive.
It's the fact that you only have one choice
and you don't have voice or exit.
So, but it's obviously a matter of degree, right?
When ride hailing first arose,
I remember back in 2013, 2014, it wasn't that long ago.
I think Uber was founded in 2009,
but it really only started taking off in the early 2010s.
No, people thought it was crazy to ride a car
with a stranger.
And then within five years,
it was the dominant mode of ride hailing.
And in that five-year period,
essentially we saw a kind of regime change in micro
where taxis went from being something
that was regulated by the state
through these commissions that were granted,
legal monopolies and used licensing and exams
and other sort of brute force ways of ensuring quality
to competing private platforms
where you have Lyft or Uber to choose from.
And they replaced the explicit governance of legal mandates
with the competing governance of reputation mechanisms
of dispute resolution systems of structured marketplaces
that collapse the bargaining frictions, right?
You never have to haggle with an Uber driver,
you just sort of get in.
And that was obviously a much better way
of doing ride hailing.
So even though there was sort of a violent resistance early on,
literally like in France,
they were throwing rocks off of bridges
and cab drivers in New York were killing themselves.
So for the people affected,
it was a very dramatic sort of regime change,
but for everyone else, it was a huge positive improvement.
And yet it's only made possible
because Uber has a social credit score.
If your Uber rating goes too low,
you'll get kicked off the platform.
And so we're fine with social credit scores.
It's when you only have one and don't have an option
and it can follow you across all these different verticals
that becomes a problem.
Do you imagine that because of rising danger in the world,
you talk about the externalities
from the widespread implementation of AI all across society
because of those dangers, those externalities,
you know, you will either use Uber or whatever service
or you kind of can't participate in society.
Do you imagine increased pressure in that direction?
It does seem to be a longer-term trend.
I don't know if AI will accelerate it.
I have another series of essays that I call separation anxiety.
And it's a reference to the fact that in insurance markets,
there's kind of two equilibria.
There's the pooling equilibria
where we're pooled together into one risk pool
and there's a separating equilibria
where the insurance pool unravels
and we break up into the great power insurance
for senior citizens who'd never had an accident
and stuff like that.
And it turns out that insurance markets
are competitively unstable
that without government regulation or social insurance,
that insurance markets will naturally tend to unravel
because of adverse selection
into, you know, the high-risk people being in one pool
and the low-risk people being in another pool.
And it turns out you can sort of use that as a mental model
to look at other kinds of implicit pooling equilibria, right?
So within company wage distributions,
often there is, you know, 20% of the workers
who are doing 80% of the work,
but they're pooled together under one wage structure.
And that was sort of the dominant structure
of the period of wage compression
in the United States in the 50s and 60s.
And once we had better monitoring technologies
and were able to tell who were the 20%
that were doing 80% of the work,
it suddenly became possible to differentiate pay structure
and a lot of the rise and inequality in the United States
is actually between firm.
So what happens is, you know,
Ezra Klein is like the most productive wiz kid
at the Washington Post and he realizes,
why don't I just go start my own website, right?
And so that dynamics are played out
across a variety of domains,
leads to a world that, you know,
to the extent that these features are correlated,
that does separate, right?
Where you have, you know, the one-star Uber riders
driving the one-star Uber drivers,
the drivers driving the riders.
And, you know, people who have, you know,
the five-star Uber ratings and the perfect credit scores,
self-sort into communities with other people
with perfect driving records and perfect credit scores.
And, you know, we see that to an extent already
with the, you know, enclaves of, you know,
rich zip codes with private schools
and everyone is sort of self-selected.
AI could, it seems to me that AI would exacerbate that.
I mean, at first blush, just because it,
going back to the point about signal extraction,
it can find all these different ways,
you're a high-risk type and I'm a low-risk type and so forth,
that are probably latent in all kinds of data
that we don't even need to get permission
to the insurance company.
They'll just like, the same way that they use,
like smoking or going to a gym as a proxy,
there's all kinds of proxies they could use
and likewise for employers and how they pay people.
Society kind of runs on us not being entirely open
and entirely honest all the time.
Otherwise, you wouldn't be able to have
kind of smooth social interactions and so on.
Won't these norms be inherited by the way we use AI?
Yeah, I think this is a really big issue.
And I'm a big fan of Robin Hansen
and a lot of his writing on social status and signaling
is sort of presenting humans as basically hypocrites,
like we're constantly deceiving other people
and we often deceive ourselves
so it's better to deceive others
as the evolutionary biologist Robert Trivers
has pointed out.
So, all the kinds of polite lies that we tell
are I think critical lubricants to the social interaction
and actually like it's good that there's a gap
between our stated and revealed preference.
I think a world where we all lived
our stated preference could be hellish
because we don't actually mean it.
And AI has a direct implication on that
because if I can have a pair of AR glasses on
that will tell me if you're interested,
if you're bored, if you're over on a date
and are you really attracted to me,
all that sort of polite veneer that social veil
could be lifted in a way that
we'll probably want to coordinate to not do, right?
But again, it's this Nash equilibrium
where it's in my interest to know
whether you're interested or bored.
And so I'll wanna have the glasses on
and my ideal world is where only I have the glasses
and you don't.
And the other way that our hypocrisy is being exposed
and challenged is the need to explicate
the utility function that we want these models
to work under.
We need to formalize human values
if we want to align these models.
And so then we have to be honest and open
about the fact that our stated preferences
probably aren't our true preferences.
And that's a very challenging thing
because it cuts right to the nature of the human condition
and involves topics that are intrinsically things
that we lie to ourselves about.
You have what you call a timeline
of a techno feudalist future,
which I found quite interesting.
Yeah, it's great writing and it's very detailed.
We don't have to go through it in all of its detail,
but maybe you could tell the story of what happens
in what you call the default scenario.
This is the scenario in which Western liberal democracies
are too slow to adapt to AI.
And so we get something like a replacement
of government services with more private services.
What happens in the techno feudalist future?
Right, and it's sort of piggybacks
in everything you've just been discussing, right?
And I don't want techno feudalists
to carry too much of a pejorative.
I'm sort of using it descriptively.
And certainly some people would prefer this world
so the example of Uber and Lyft displacing taxi caps
is sort of a version of this in micro
where we go from this regulated taxi commission
to competing private platforms that use various forms
of artificial intelligence and information technology
to replace the thing that was being done
by explicit regulation.
And as AI progresses and both creates a variety
of new negative externalities,
whether it's like suicide drones
or the ability to spy on each other,
there's going to be a demand for new forms of security
and also kinds of opt-in jurisdictions
that tie our hands in the same way
that we give up our phone before we go into the comedy club.
And so I think this leads to a kind of development
of clubs, the kind of club structure
that may be at the city level
as the vertically integrated walled garden
that will police and build defensive technologies
around the misuse of AI and at the same time
provide a variety of like new AI native public goods
that are only possible once AI unlocks them.
And it's easy to see how this could very quickly displace
and eat away at formal government services
both because we saw it already with Uber,
but also if you map that model
to other areas of regulatory life,
does it make sense to have a USDA farm inspector,
a human person has to go to a commercial farm
and maybe only goes to that farm once every few years
because there's so many farms and only so many people.
And it does a little checklist and says,
oh, you're not abusing the animals
and you get all the process in place
and you get the USDA stamp of approval
or does it make more sense to have multimodal cameras on
in the farm 24-7 that are continuously generating reports
that throw up a red flag anytime someone sneezes
on the conveyor belt.
And to the extent that government is going to be slow
at adopting that, will there be a push
for the kind of Uber model of governance as a platform
where you have the kind of AI underwriter,
the consumer reports that sells these farms,
the camera technology and the monitoring technology
and builds their own set of compliant standards.
And then you want to go to those farms
or would have you that have the stamp of approval
of the underwriter because it's much higher trust.
It's sort of like the end of asymmetric information.
And you can map that from food safety to product safety
to OSHA and workplace safety.
There's other parts of government
that maybe just rendered completely obsolete, right?
Like once we have self-driving cars
that are a thousand next more safe than humans,
do we need a national highway traffic safety administration?
Once we have sensors that are privately owned everywhere
and can model weather patterns better
than the national oceanic administration,
do we need a national weather service
or could we bootstrap that ourselves?
And then once we have AI,
accelerated drug discovery,
do we want to rely on the FDA to be a kind of choke point
to do these sort of frequentist clinical trials
that are inherently slow and don't capture
the kind of idiosyncrasies and heterogeneity
that could be unlocked by personalized medicine?
Or do we move to an alternative drug approval process
that is maybe non-governmental,
but much more rapid and much more personalized?
So that's the overall picture.
I'll just run through the timeline here,
picking up on some of your comments
that I thought were especially interesting.
You write, this is in 2024 to 2027,
you write that the internet will become vulcanized
and it will become more secure and more private in a sense.
Why does that happen?
We're already starting to see this a little bit, right?
Once people realize that the data
that's being generated on Stack Overflow
or Reddit or whatever is valuable
for training these models,
suddenly everyone's closing their API
and consequently Google Search and the Google index
have sort of started to degrade already.
So I think that will continue
for the kind of privatization of data reasons.
Then when you also think about
how websites are going to handle sort of the growth of bots
and catfishes and catfish attacks
and cyber attacks and so forth,
it makes sense that we're going to move
from a sort of open, everything goes kind of Twitter-esque
platform to things that are much more closed
because they require human verification
and identity verification to sort of build the trust
that you're talking to other people and not deepfakes.
And then medium-term, again,
over this sort of 2024 to 2027 horizon,
you could also start to see the emergence
of intelligent malware, sort of modern AI native cyber attacks
that could be devastating to legacy cyber security
infrastructure in a way that I talk about good heart
and back to the famous Moore's worm
that in the late 80s,
basically shut down the early internet.
They literally had to partition the internet
and turn it off so they could read the network at the worm.
So for all those reasons,
I think you start to see the internet balkanize
and then particularly at the international level,
we're already starting to see sort of the semiconductor
supply chain become critical part of national security.
The growth of the Chinese firewall,
the European Union is going to have to have their own
quasi firewall and they kind of already do with GDPR
and the EU AI Act.
And so the kind of nationalization of compute
and telecommunications infrastructure
that will take off once people understand
both the security risks and the value prop
of owning the infrastructure for the AI revolution.
Yeah, in 2028 to 2031,
you write about alignment turning out to be easier
than we thought with the increasing scale of the model.
That was somewhat surprising to me.
Why does alignment turn out to be easier?
And part of this is imagining a scenario
where alignment is easy.
So we can talk about what happens if alignment is easy.
But I think there are reasons to think
that the classic alignment problem
will be easier than people think.
I think that some of the early intuitions
about the hardness of the alignment problem
were rooted in a view of maybe AI turns out
to be a very simple algorithm
rather than like a deep neural network
that achieves its generality because of its depth.
Clearly the kind of value,
I forget what Eliezer Kewski called it,
but there's like a value alignment problem
where how do we teach the model our values?
But that part of the alignment problem seems trivial now
because our large English models aren't like
autistic savants, they're actually incredibly sensitive
to soft human concepts of value and context.
They're not going to have a,
the paperclip maximizer sort of monkey paw
kind of threat models don't really make sense in that world.
But there's a difference between the output of the model
and the weights or what the model has learned.
And so just because a model can say,
it can say the right words that we wanted to say,
but what has it actually learned?
We are not entirely sure.
And so it has learned to satisfy human values to some extent,
but has it learned to want to comply with human value
out of distribution sort of, yeah, in other domains
and in a deep sense, I'm not sure about that.
No, I agree.
So I'm sort of just laying some of my groundwork
for to expand my priors on this.
I agree, like, you know, reinforcement learning
from human feedback is not alignment.
You know, the same way that, you know,
you could argue that like the co-evolution of cats and dogs
with humans led to a kind of reinforcement learning
from human feedback in their, in their short run evolution
that, you know, made them look up, appear as if they,
you know, they experienced guilt and shame
and these human emotions when in fact they're,
they're just sort of a simulacra of those emotions
because it means that we'll give them a treat.
But I've done plenty of episodes on deceptions
in these models and so on.
We don't have to go through that,
but I just wanted to point out that, yeah,
maybe there's some complexities there.
So the first, my first prior is that these models
aren't autistic savants the way they might have been.
The second is going back to universality.
Well, it is true that you, there are, that, you know,
it's possible through reinforcement learning
from human feedback, for example,
that you, you're, you're not selecting for honesty
or selecting for a deep pick up honesty,
but in the bigger picture, the intuition
that these models are converging or convergent
with human representations should give you some confidence
that they're not going to be as alien
as we, as we think they will be.
It's also useful input for thinking about interpretability.
You know, some recent work showing that discussing
sort of representation, interpretability
where, where instead of trying to interpret
individual neurons, you interpret sort of collections
of neurons and, and, and circuitry
through sort of human interpretable representations.
And one of the, one of the lessons of universality
is that like some of these high level human concepts,
like happiness or, or anxiety,
like these seem like vague psychological abstractions
that there's no way they can correspond
to like the micro foundations of the way our brain works.
But in fact, they may actually be very efficient,
low dimensional ways of talking about
what's happening in our brain.
And then the third thing is, I think that I just
have seen, you know, my sense is that the work
on interpretability is actually making some,
some good progress, you know,
whether it can scale is another question,
but I think we'll get there.
In my timeline, I talk about sort of AGI level models
within the human limit, human emulator plus domain.
I do later on talk about like super intelligence
emerging maybe in the 2040s.
And that's another story, right?
And so I think some of this stuff maybe goes out the window
if we have, you know, models that are bigger
than all the brains combined and have like
strong situational awareness.
But I don't think that happens this decade.
Certainly, certainly not with the current way
we're building these models,
with the way we're currently building these models,
I think it's comes much closer to a stimuli
lack of the human brain.
Got it.
In 2036 to 2039, you talk about robotics
being solved to the same extent,
or maybe even in the same way
as we are now solving a language.
That would, I found that super interesting.
Explain to me why, why would robotics
suddenly or quite relatively suddenly become much easier?
Robotics have been fighting for decades
to get these models to walk relatively
unencumbered and it's been an uphill battle.
Yeah, why can we solve robotics in the 2030s?
This may end up happening sooner than I'd project,
but I mean, if you look at LLMs,
what one of the stylized sort of trends
with large language models is that, you know,
that natural language processing went from being this,
you know, the study of how to make machines
understand language went from being, you know,
a dozen different sub-disciplines,
you know, people working on parsing,
people are working on syntax,
people are working on semantics,
people are working on summarization and classification.
And these are all different, you know, directions,
research directions.
And then along comes transformer models
and, you know, it's just supplants everything
and LLMs can do it all.
And I think robotics is sort of still in that ancient regime
where a lot of, you know, what Boston Dynamics does
is ad hoc control models,
analytically solvable, you know, differential equations,
different kinds of object recognition modules
and control action loops and so forth.
And so it's still in that like early NLP phase
where they have 12 different sub-disciplines
and they're sort of mashing them together.
And of course you get something that's not very robust.
I think we're already starting to see that paradigm shift
to, you know, end-to-end neural network trained models,
like, you know, Tesla, for instance,
I think one of the reasons why Tesla cars
had a sort of temporary decline in performance
was because they were undergoing the transition
from these ad hoc lane detectors
and stop sign detectors and stuff like that
to a fully end-to-end neural network transformer-based model.
And that turned out to be much more robust way
to train the model because, you know,
stop signs look different in different countries
and like maybe stop sign isn't the thing you care about,
really, so on and so forth.
And so I think the transformer sort of scale,
deep learning revolution is only now coming to robotics
and people in that field have, are a little bit cynical
because they're used to relatively small RL models
thinking that like the fit with, you know, actuators
and some of the hardware is like a really challenging problem
and also believing that we don't have the data sets
for it, but then you look at, you know,
there's recent RoboDog that you may have seen on Twitter,
fully open source robot model
for a Boston Dynamics style dog.
It was trained on H100s, you know,
10,000 human years of training and simulation
and then some fine-tuning on real-world data
and they have a very robust robot control model
that you could plug into all kinds
of different form factors and have something that can,
you know, hop gaps and climb stairs
and do all the things that Boston Dynamics robots
don't do very well outside of their distribution.
You think we'll have a general purpose algorithm
that we can plug into basically arbitrarily shaped robots
that can then navigate the, navigate our apartments
or our construction sites or maybe our highways.
That's an interesting vision.
Why is it that we achieve this level of generality?
If you look at humans, you know, humans are very good at,
you know, if we've suffered an amputation
or you have to go through physical therapy
and it's not easy necessarily,
but humans are able to adapt to different kinds
of physical layouts of our body.
And I think there will be a trend
towards unified robotic control models
that aren't like super tailored to, you know,
two legs and two arms and so on and so forth.
You know, once you've installed it
through a little bit of in-context learning
or fine-tuning or reinforcement learning,
adapt to that particular form factor.
And this will parallel the kind
of pre-trained foundation model paradigm
that is currently taking place in LLMs
where you have like the really big foundation model
that can sort of do everything reasonably well
and then you can fine-tune it beyond that.
If we get to the 2040s in your timeline,
you talk about massive amounts of compute being available.
You talk about post-scarcity in everything
except for land and capital.
And then you also talk about the development
potentially of superintelligence at that point.
What happens there?
Who is in control of the superintelligence, if anyone?
Yeah, this is sort of where I start
to get a little bit tongue-in-cheek,
but first of all, I talk about how I tend to think
that once we have exascale computing and I think DOE
just built their first exascale computer,
and maybe it was private company,
but we have like one exascale computer in the world.
By the 2040s, they'll be commonplace.
And if we are ever worried about sort of controlling
the supply of GPUs, I don't know exactly
how much compute will be on our smartphones,
but it will definitely be possible to train a GP5 model
from your home computer.
And so any kind of AICT regime that we build today
that doesn't take into account that falling costs of compute
will probably break down.
And therefore, amid this broader sort of fragmentation
of the machinery of government, the state,
I expect more and more government functions
to be offloaded into basically private cities,
HOAs, GATIC communities.
And likewise with the internet, I expect more and more
of our sort of permissioning regime for new AI models
and deployment to shift to the infrastructure layer
where telecommunication providers will be monitoring
network traffic for unvetted AI models and so forth,
and we'll have like Chinese style firewalls
that are specific to a particular local area network.
And at that point, the world looks,
the United States where this takes place
looks more like an archipelago of micro jurisdictions.
I tend to think that like a post scarcity
political economy looks a lot like the Gulf States,
Gulf State monarchies, right?
Because Gulf State monarchies are basically
living post scarcity, right?
They have a spigot of oil they can turn on,
and then they can go build mega projects in the desert,
and they have like infinite labor
because they can just import guest workers.
And so you end up with like this,
but if we can't have a Gulf State monarchy
in the United States, instead we have a bunch
of micro monarchies dotting the country.
So I sort of jokingly say, you know,
who's going to stop the free city of California
that's like home to all the trillionaire ML engineers
and tech founders from the decade prior
from plugging in their humanity sized supercomputer
into a fusion reactor and turning it on.
Yeah, and this is really your kind of end point
of the discussion or your main point
of institutions being eroded,
and then afterwards being unable to respond to strong AI.
Yeah, and leading up to this,
it sounds like a scary dystopian type of thing.
It doesn't have to be, right?
Uber is not dystopian, Airbnb is not dystopian,
private airports in other countries are way better
than the public airports in the United States.
So privatization and the sort of techno feudalist paradigm
doesn't have to be bad,
but what it is is more adversarial, right?
And you know, people have sometimes speculated,
you know, did the crumbling of the Roman Empire
was a kind of prerequisite to a renaissance, right?
Because it allowed for these principalities
to sort of compete and to get the Florentine,
you know, creativity and so forth.
I think, you know, the next couple of decades
could similarly be a renaissance
for science and technology and for understanding the world,
but it's probably a renaissance
because we'll be moving into a much more competitive
adversarial world where, you know,
these city-states and so forth will be hard to coordinate.
And so to the extent that there are still these,
like, meta-risks where we would value some large-scale,
intra- and international coordination,
like peace treaties and so forth,
the disintegration of the United States
where this revolution is occurring
would be bad for that.
You talk about or you hint at an alternative path.
What we've been talking about your timeline here
is the default path.
You hint at a path where we have something
you call constrained leviath.
What is constrained leviath?
It's the limited government, right?
So this is a D'Arnaz and Mogul's word
for it from the narrow corridor.
And if you trace the rise of sort of what we associate
with liberal democracy,
it is part of a particular technological equilibrium,
in particular an equilibrium
that favored centralized governments
with impersonal rule of law
and impersonal tax administration and so on and so forth.
So we associate today with libertarians
with like being anti-government,
but the basic idea of liberalism
is actually associated with strong government,
a strong impersonal government
that can impose the rule of law.
And so if we want to maintain that kind of equilibrium
in a world where AI is diffusing on the society level
faster than it is on the state and elite level,
then we want to accelerate the diffusion
of AI within government.
And there's obviously lots of low hanging fruit.
We talked about how bureaucracies
are basically fleshy APIs.
Even today, I have a friend at the FTC,
the Federal Trade Commission.
They have like a 30 person team
that is part of the healthcare division
and they're in charge of policing
the entire pharmaceutical industry
in the United States for competition.
His day job right now looks like manually
reading through 40,000 emails
that they subpoenaed from a pharmaceutical CEO, right?
And today you could take those emails
and put them into a Claude II or something
like it with a big context window and ask,
find me the five most egregious examples of misconduct.
And it would do that.
It might not be perfect,
but it's a hell of a lot more efficient
than reading through them manually.
And obviously big law is going to be doing that.
And the Pharma CEO and his personal attorneys
will be doing that conversely.
To maintain our state capacity in the face of AI
is to run in this arms race.
And you can kind of liken it to an evolutionary biology
they call the Rig Queen dynamic,
which comes from Alice in Wonderland
where the Rig Queen tells Alice
that sometimes you need to run just to stay in place.
And so I think our government needs to be adopting
this technology as rapidly as possible
so that they can basically tread water.
And that means both diffusing it in existing institutions,
but also being open to radical reconfigurations
of the machinery of government
and addressing some of those firmware level constraints
that we talked about,
whether it's the lack of a national identification system
or the outdated atmoded information technology infrastructure
or the accumulation of old procedural
kinds of methods of governance.
A focused way of doing this is what you've called for
in a political article,
which is a Manhattan project for AI safety.
A first question here,
would it be better to call it an Apollo project
as opposed to a Manhattan project?
I mean, the Manhattan project
created some pretty dangerous weapons,
whereas the Apollo project might have been more benign.
I mean, what the Apollo project
and the Manhattan project have in common
is that they came from an era of US government
where we still dealt things,
where we still had competent state capacity,
where we still had a lot of in-house expertise
and we weren't saddled with all these constraints.
So today, we couldn't go to the moon in 10 years,
NASA couldn't, SpaceX can.
And so our modern Apollo projects
are being done by the private sector
through competitive contracts.
And so one of the messages of my piece
on the Manhattan project is to say,
the reason I make this analogy
is not just because AI is a Oppenheimer like technology,
but also because responding to it
will require a throwback to those kind of institutional forms
where we gave the people at the top a lot of discretion
and sort of gave them an outcome
and let them solve for that outcome
without having much of prescriptive rules
about how to solve for that outcome.
And then the second reason to make the analogy is,
open AI and anthropic,
they both have contingency plans
for developing AGI and having like a runaway market power, right?
And in the case of open AI,
it's their nonprofit structure.
In the case of anthropic, it's their public benefit trust
where they both are envisioning a world
where they could potentially be the first to build AGI
and become basically trillionaires.
And so at that point,
they need to become basically governed by a nonprofit board.
You know, at that point,
and that's not where progress ends, obviously,
like there's going to be continued research.
It would make sense for the US government to step in
and say, let's do this as a joint venture,
or we're no longer competing.
In fact, the basic structures of capitalism
and market competition are starting to break down.
Let's just pull this together into a joint venture,
study the things that require huge amounts of capital
that the private sector doesn't have, but the government can.
The US government spent $26 billion
on the Manhattan Project in today's dollars.
When you think about the financial resources
of nation-state actors to put behind scaling,
it's nothing like what Microsoft or Google have.
What's our first $200 billion training run, right?
What kind of things can come out of that?
I think that's something that you want to do
with the Defense Department's involvement
and working with these companies in a joint way
through secured data centers
and doing gain-of-function-style research
that really is dangerous
and more Manhattan Project than Apollo Project.
What would be the advantages here?
We would be able to slow down capabilities research
and spend more of the resources
on, say, mechanistic interpretability
or evaluations or alignment in general,
because now the top AI corporations
have kind of combined their efforts
on the one government group.
Yeah, and in my vision,
they're still allowed to pursue their commercial verticals.
And I have an extended version of the proposal
where I talk about needing sort of bio-safety-style categories
for high-risk, medium-risk, and low-risk styles of AI
that very closely parallels
what Anthropic recently put out with their recommendations
for sort of a BSL categorization of AI research.
So I'm really talking about that BSL4 lab
and beyond-style stuff.
And some of that stuff,
some of it will be to accelerate alignment
and interpretability research
to sort of do versions of the OpenAI Superalignment Project
where they're dedicating 20% of their compute
to study alignment.
Another part of it will be to forestall
competitive race-to-the-bottom dynamics
so that they can coordinate and not violate antitrust laws.
And then the third thing is sort of the gain-of-function stuff
that we really only want to be doing
with very strict oversight, compartmentalization,
kind of pooling of talent and resources
so we can share knowledge on alignment and safety.
But then also because government has this huge spending power,
relative to the product sector,
anytime you build a supercomputer,
you're basically borrowing from the future.
You're trying to see what like the smartphones
20 years from now will be capable of.
And so if we want to sort of get ahead of the curve
and see where scaling is leading,
then I think governments are really the only actor
that can waste a bunch of money
basically scaling up a system
and seeing what comes out of it.
Yeah, when we talk about gain-of-function research in AI,
it's an analogy to the gain-of-function research
that's done on viruses in biolabs, but done for AI models.
And this could be experimenting
with creating more agent-like models
or inducing deception in a model
and planting it in a simulated environment,
seeing what it does or enticing it to acquire more resources.
But again, perhaps in a safely,
if this is even possible
in a safely constrained, simulated environment.
And this is the type of research that we could do
in this Manhattan project, this government lab,
because we would have excellent cybersecurity
and secure data centers and the combined efforts
of the most capable people in AI research.
If you've watched Oppenheimer, the movie,
a lot of that revolved around suspicions
of coming to spies and so on.
And we really don't have great insight
into the operational security of the major AGI labs.
And that's something that bringing it in house
of the defense department,
they would necessarily have to disclose
everything they're doing, but also hopefully
beef up their operational security.
Yeah, they're kind of stuck with a startup mindset,
but they're not developing a startup product.
They're developing something that, in my opinion,
could be more dangerous than the average startup.
Yeah, and Dari Amade has said as much
that we should just assume that there are Chinese spies
at all the major AI companies
and at Microsoft and Google.
When we think about gain of function research in AI,
how do you think about the value of gaining information
about what the models can do
and what the models can do versus the risk we're running?
It would be a tragic and ironic death for humanity
if we experimented with dangerous AI models
to see whether they would destroy us
and then we hadn't constrained them properly
and they actually destroyed us.
So how do you think of that trade-off
between gaining information and avoiding lab leaks?
Yeah, hopefully lab leaks are less likely
than in the biology context where, you know,
getting a little bit of blood or urine on your shoes
as you walk at the door.
Now, it's a difficult thing to talk about in part
because we just went through a pandemic
that very probably was caused by a BSL4 lab leak.
And so, you know, one saving grace is that AI models
don't get caught in your respiratory system.
And so hopefully there's forms of compartmentalization
that are much more robust than in the biology context.
And to the extent that this research
is going to be done anyway,
you know, it would be much better to move it off-site
and hopefully in a way that facilities are air-gapped
and so forth, rather than, you know,
what Microsoft is doing right now,
that Microsoft just recently announced their AutoGen AI,
which are sort of agent-based models,
very similar to like AutoGPT, but like that work.
And they're doing this through Creative Commons,
totally open source framework.
All this capabilities work is gain a function research,
where we draw the line between doing things
that are intentionally dangerous
or doing things that are dangerous,
but we're kind of pretending that they're not, is hard.
I do think there's, and Paul Cristiano is also agreed
with this sort of threat models
that would be valuable to be running in virtual machines
and to see, you know, if the AI develops awareness,
situational awareness and tries to escape,
but it escapes into a simulated world that we built for it.
Okay, let's end by talking about a recent critique
of expecting AGI to arrive pretty in a short time.
This revolves around interest rates.
And I guess the basic argument is,
or the basic question is, if AGI is imminent,
why are real interest rates low?
I can explain it, but you're the economist,
so maybe you can explain the reason in here.
So it's really a question of how efficient are markets
and how much foresight do markets have.
You know, we're coming out of a world
of very low interest rates, of ultra low interest rates,
near zero interest rates.
And one way to think about that is there's a surplus
of savings relative to investment.
And so one of the reasons interest rates
have been in secular decline
is because populations are aging,
and so all people have a huge amount of savings built up.
And meanwhile, we're going through
the sort of technological stagnation.
So the amount of savings relative
to the amount of profitable investments was out of whack,
and so that pushes interest rates down.
In a world where AGI takes off,
it's a world where we have enormous investment opportunities,
where we'll be building data centers left and right,
and we can't do it fast enough,
where there's new products,
new commercial opportunities left and right.
And so you would expect in that world
where the singularity is near, so to speak,
to be one where the markets begin forecasting
rapidly rising interest rates
because the savings to investment balance
is starting to shift.
And in addition, there's a long run stylized fact
that real interest rates track growth rates.
And so if GDP growth takes off,
you'd also expect at least nominal rates to also take off.
And so some have argued that looking at current interest
rate data, like the five-year, 10-year,
30-year treasury bonds,
that the markets are not predicting AGI.
You know, the two responses to that are,
one, first of all, interest rates are up quite a bit.
Nothing's mono-causal.
There's lots of confounding factors.
Is this, to some extent, the markets anticipating
an investment boom?
You know, maybe they're not anticipating full AGI,
but they're seeing the way LLMs are going to impact
enterprise and sort of picking some of that in.
And then the second piece would be,
okay, to the extent that they're not pricing in AGI,
how much foresight do markets have anyway?
Before we discuss market efficiency,
I just want to just give a couple of intuitions here.
If AGI was imminent and it was unaligned, say,
and it would destroy the world in five years,
well, then it doesn't make a lot of sense to save money.
Similarly, if AGI is about to explode growth rates,
well, then a lot of money will be available in the future.
You're about to become very rich,
so it doesn't make sense to save a lot now.
And the pool of available savings
determine what's available for lending,
which determines interest rates.
But let's discuss whether markets then are efficient
on this issue or to what extent they're efficient.
Right, so this is the efficient market hypothesis,
which comes in strong and weak forms.
So the strong form of the efficient market hypothesis
would say that markets aggregate all of available information
and are our best sort of point estimate
of anything we care about.
The weaker form, which I think is more defensible,
is that markets can be wrong,
but they can be wrong longer than you can be solvent, right?
And so you can try to short a company that, like Herbalife,
famously, there's a big short position on that,
and because Herbalife sort of looks like
it's a multi-level marketing Ponzi scheme,
but yet the hedge fund that did that
lost several billions of dollars before they
ended their position because the markets
stayed irrational longer than they could stay solvent.
The second factor is the weaker versions
of the efficient market hypothesis
are sort of based on a no arbitrage condition, right?
They say markets are efficient only insofar
as you can arbitrage an inefficiency, right?
And so you look at some prediction markets, for example,
they predict it.
They'll often have very clear inconsistencies
across markets that look like they're irrational,
but then you realize, oh, I can only make
like $7,000 total on the website
and there are transaction fees
and there's work involved.
And so if the market isn't very deep or liquid,
there may be inefficiencies that exist
not because the market's inefficient,
but as efficient as it can be under the circumstances.
And when it comes to AI, how do you arbitrage?
I've been thinking for a while now that Shutterstock,
their market cap should be collapsing, right?
Because we have image generation that is proliferating.
And yes, people will make the argument though,
Shutterstock has all this image data
that could build a better image model.
Maybe it seems like it's cannibalizing their business
or turning a moat into a commodity.
And yet Shutterstock's market cap
has basically held constant throughout
this recent rebirth of image generation models.
What if you borrow a lot of money cheaply
and then put it into an index of semiconductor stocks
or just IT companies in general,
even just the general S&P 500 say,
would that be a way of arbitraging this AGI forecast?
Yeah, I would say if you have short timelines,
you should be putting a lot of money into equities.
This is not financial advice, I should say.
Right, and I mentioned earlier that Paul Christiana
has said in interviews that he's twice levered
into the stock market.
He basically owns a bunch of AI exposed companies
and he's borrowed enough money to double his investments.
So that's putting your money where your mouth is.
When you look at market behavior
over the long stretch of time,
markets didn't anticipate the internet very well.
There was a short run bubble
that led to a boom and bust of .com stocks.
But in terms of the real economy,
the internet just kept chugging along
and kept being built out
and eventually a lot of those investments
ended up paying off even if you rode through the bubble.
Markets are made of people.
Some of the biggest capital holders in the markets
are institutional investors, pension funds,
life insurance companies, governments,
like the Saudi Arabia or the Norwegian pension fund.
And often these are making safe bets.
You know, they're not taking very heterodox views
on markets.
And so as a result, markets can be a little bit
autoregressive, they're a little bit biased to the past,
and past this prologue,
and prone to kind of multiple equilibria,
where there's two prices that the shutter stock can be.
The shutter stock could be a $50 stock
or it could be a $0 stock,
and at some point the market will update
and will wander go through like the great repricing
and all these asset prices will flip
in relatively short order.
The efficient market hypothesis has to be false,
or else we wouldn't have Silicon Valley.
Right, we wouldn't have founders
that we wouldn't have Elon Musk, right?
So I would just say the markets are wrong.
And partly they're wrong because to be right
would require having a bunch of relatively bespoke
and kind of esoteric priors about the direction
of technology that are only now just sort of
percolating into the mainstream.
Yeah, and that the big kind of capital allocators
can't really respond to because they're risk averse.
Exactly.
Now that doesn't mean like Renaissance technologies
won't respond to it,
but they're not gonna move the market.
Samuel, thanks for this conversation
and I've learned a lot.
Thank you.