ChatGPT has changed YouTube forever. Despite only being released two months ago,
YouTubers have been using it to get monumental results like this while tripling their productivity.
So I'm going to show you some of my favorite ChatGPT hacks for YouTubers and also talk about
how ChatGPT will change the future of YouTube forever.
Let's start at the beginning. On November 30th, 2022, ChatGPT was launched and in just
five days it had over 11 billion users, including Elon Musk, who said it was quote,
scary good. Seriously, at this stage, there are so many people using this damn software
that 50% of the time I load it up, it just crashes because the servers can't handle the volume.
But what exactly is ChatGPT? Well, if you ask ChatGPT itself, it will say that it's an AI language
model, which is nerd speak that basically means it's kind of like a super smart virtual assistant
with the work ethic of a thousand Dwayne The Rock Johnson's. Let me show you what I mean.
So let's say I'm trying to come up with fun video ideas for my Minecraft YouTube channel.
I could log into ChatGPT and tell it to do something like give me fun video ideas for
my Minecraft YouTube channel. And these ideas are completely unique. They've been created from
scratch by the AI, meaning that they haven't just been scraped and copied and pasted from
somewhere on the internet. Now we've got a bunch of ideas here and you could tell it to continue
generating more and more and more ideas until you find one that clicks with you. But for the sake
of this example, let's just look at number eight on this list, role playing adventures. It sounds
like a cool idea. Let's see if we can flesh it out a little bit. Now I often like to come up with
my titles and thumbnails before I actually create my videos. So what I'm going to do is I'm going
to ask ChatGPT now to give me Minecraft YouTube video titles about me role playing as a potato.
Yes, you heard that right. Wow. So as you can see, we've generated a list of video ideas. We've
picked an idea and now we've told ChatGPT to generate a list of titles for the specific idea
that stood out to it the most. And here they are. Now out of these, I actually find title number
three pretty funny. And now I'm up to the stage where I'd actually start brainstorming a script
or outline for my video. And in the name of laziness, ChatGPT can actually help out with this
as well. I can just tell it to create a script outline for this video. And what it generates is
insane. Look at this. It'll tell me to introduce myself and explain the concept of a role play
series. It'll tell me to set the scene by showing a potato farm where the journey begins. It'll tell
me to preview the goals of the journey and what a viewer can expect from the series, basically
foreshadowing, which is a really powerful storytelling technique. It's then going to give
me the different stages of the video. I should show the initial struggles of the potato character
trying to survive in a Minecraft world through to building a base for my potato character,
through to expanding that base into an empire, and then showcasing the challenges and triumphs
I encounter before finally summarizing my journey so far. And if this is a multi video series,
previewing what is to come in future episodes. And while sure, this is a relatively basic video
structure, honestly, it's probably better than 95% of the Minecraft role play videos out there.
Now, we could tell ChatGPT to actually write a script for a video like this, but because
this video is going to be more of a playthrough style one, it probably wouldn't really work out.
However, what we could do is tell it to write a script for the intro for the hook. Since that's
something we'll probably want to pre-plan so we can grab as many people and rope them into watching
the entire video. So all I have to do is ask ChatGPT and here's what it generates. And if you
don't like what it generates, you can actually tell it to generate something different and kind of
explain to it the way in which you want your script to be written. For example, I could tell
it to write the script in the style of MrBeast. And while it hasn't done a perfect job here,
there are definitely elements of this that we could take and use as inspiration for our intro.
For example, we could start the second paragraph here and intro our video like,
We start our journey as a potato, just like any other potato on a farm. But this isn't just an
ordinary potato, no sir. We have big dreams and even bigger plans, and we're going to take this
blocky world by storm and become the biggest, baddest potato Minecraft has ever seen.
Sure, it's kind of cringy, but again, it's probably better than 90 to 95% of the intro is out
there for this type of content. And finally, now that we've got our script in our structure,
we can tell ChatGPT to write our video description for us because that's incredibly boring and no
one wants to do that. Now this one's decent, descriptions don't matter that much. But let's
say this was a searchable video and descriptions do impact YouTube search. You could tell ChatGPT
to optimize this description for SEO and here's what it will do. And notice it adds in more
keywords and keyword phrases related to our video idea. Now obviously it could be improved,
but this is a pretty good foundation. And last but not least, now we have a description, maybe we
want to generate some tags for our video. Now this is okay, but it's going to be a pain for me to
individually copy and paste all of these tags into my video description. So I can just tell ChatGPT
to separate these tags with commas in between, and it'll create them in a way that I can just
literally copy and paste them straight into my YouTube video. And there we have it. Now obviously
this isn't a perfect video, but notice how long it took us to do all of this. This tool is phenomenally
powerful and it's still in beta. And that begs the question, what will the YouTube ecosystem look like
in three, five or even 10 years time from now when ChatGPT is being used by basically everyone?
How do you prepare? Should you embrace it, fight against it or something else? Why jumped on a call
with Ed from Filmbooth who's been looking into this extensively to ask him just that.
So it's scary and it's exciting at the same time because it's writing scripts better than
people I've hired, not who I'm currently hiring, just in case they're watching. It's not better
than you guys. I'm using it every day for titles. I'm using it every day to tighten up scripts,
research. When I first came across AI of this nature, it was about two months before ChatGPT
and I was like, this is years off. And in two months, it's changed to the point where it's like,
the other day it went down and I felt anxious that I didn't have it. That's how much I'm using it.
It's an amazing tool. It's bad for new YouTubers. If they rely on it too much,
they're not going to learn the skills. I think over this time next year, it's going to have caused
huge amounts of content to flood to YouTube. Don't necessarily know if it's going to be the best.
I think for Search, it's just going to absolutely dominate. I think for Faceless Channels,
people who can find gaps and niches, it's going to be unbelievably good and amazingly profitable.
If it gets to the level, I think it's going to be pretty quick. But I worry that it's going to
make us all too lazy. It's only working off stuff that's already out there. The thing that drives
everything forward and makes being creative so wonderful is new things appear. We're not just
repeating old things. MrBeast created this whole style and a lot of people copied it.
Some people would argue that it ruined the entertainment side because everyone's copying
MrBeast. What we need is new concepts, new ideas, new creative and crazy out-of-the-box
thinking that I don't think AI can bring. But I also think it might bring a level where
maybe people can get by just using it, not pushing themselves. I feel like that could make
the platform very average if that wins. It's scary and exciting. What do you think of it?
It's really interesting. It's completely changing the game. At least a lot of people,
I've heard talk about it, say, oh, it's now we're going to replace human creativity,
but it's pretty damn good. I think to a point, it won't. I think a lot of creativity is just
people being really good at remixing ideas, even if it's just subconscious. At least in my experience,
it's very rare for someone to come with a completely unique original thing that has
no elements of anyone else's stuff involved in it. That's what chatGPT does. Download the
internet, takes lots of bits and pieces and puts it in. When you think about it, at least in my
view, it is very creative, even though it's AI. It isn't the writing side. I think when it comes
to editing, that's going to be a long way off and production. Yes, 100%. I like it. I do think in a
year's time, it's probably going to be the thing that we rely on more than anything else.
What are the skills that you think smart creators should double down on to future proof
themselves? That's a good question. I would lean into storytelling then. The whole point
about storytelling is there's the twists and turns, and there's structures you can follow,
and the whole point is to try and create emotional reactions. So, humor can do that.
There's a lot of views to be had playing it safe with content. Say I make a video about Ryan
Treyham. If I make a video about Ryan Treyham, there are no jokes. Very informative. Harness's
story structure, but it's kind of bland in that it's not about the personality of the presenter.
It's all about the story of the person they're talking about. What that does is it doesn't
put many people off. It doesn't necessarily create a bigger bond with the creator, but I've seen a lot
of these videos do very well that are kind of like people reporting, and I look at them and think
the AI can do that. What they can't do is all the weird stuff. So, I do stuff in my videos that I
know put people off, and I know I would get more views if I stopped dressing up as in weird outfits.
Because it's odd, right? The cold viewers can go, who the hell is this guy? But at the same time,
I look at it and I go, well, for every one of them that hates me, and for everyone that
stops me getting impressions, I have someone out there laughed, and they felt stronger,
and they felt a bond with me because of that. The AI is not going to have that power to be
thinking, how do I create a bond with a viewer? It's just information. So, I actually feel like
if you're relying heavily on matter of fact, that's a problem. You've got to be thinking more
creative, and how do I bond with people, not just report, because AI will just report
significantly faster and easier than you. Well, Ed, thanks so much for jumping on and
talking with us. If you want to check out Ed's channel, it will be linked down below. Also,
he has a new thumbnail course that is out. You can check that out down below as well. Now,
as Ed and I talked about, the AI is really good at generating words. However, it's not so good
at the technical creation process like video editing. And so, if you want to learn one way
to take your editing to the next level, watch the video on screen. It'll show you a really simple
thing that 97% of people aren't doing. It'll help you get more views, watch time, and subscribers.
Check it out.