hello friends this is Moin from curious techie and in this video I'm going to
show you how to resolve multi array error which is going to be occurred in
Python programming language so in this video I'm going to take cues of OpenCB
library and how how the multi array error occurred in OpenCB while importing
OpenCB library so let's get started open up your Python IDE and I'll just
import numpy package importing numpy package this is successfully installed
so we are getting like this so while importing cb2 that means OpenCB I will
get this traceback error called as multi array error and something numpy
version x something so this this usually occurs when one of the libraries and
Python programming language is incompatible with some of the versions of
the libraries so you have to you have to install the compatible version which is
suitable so I'm using Python 2.7.5 version here and let me show you the
numpy version
so my numpy version is 1.9.2 and my numpy path is installed at so this is the path
where I installed this numpy package so I'm using latest version of numpy 1.9.2
and I'm using OpenCB of 3.2 so that is the latest version of OpenCB so here
usually the error occurs because of OpenCB 3.2 it is an incompatible with
Python 2.7.5 so we have to install 2.4 to be compatible with Python 2.7.5 so
let's remove let's remove OpenCB 3.2 from where it is been installed so go to
C drive and go to C drive and delete this OpenCB folder from here
okay so after deleting this go to Python software Python file Python 27 and go
to libraries and site packages so here you will find CB2 file and just delete
that file so it is a 3.2 version file so just download the OpenCB 2.4 version
I'll provide the link in the description below so you can download it from there
just install the OpenCB 2.4 which is compatible with Python 2.7.5 so just
install this package in C drive so after successfully extracting all the files
in C drive just go to just open that folder and go to break and just open
Python and select your desired PC version I'm using 32 bit here so copy this
cb2 file and do as usual paste it in Python 27 folder libraries site
packages and just paste it here now just open here open the Python software
let's take this I'm importing numpy here so numpy is correctly installed so
while importing cb2 let's see what's happened yeah that's a difference it is
compatible and it supports cb2 now so that's why you get an error so you have
to change the versions of your library so that's it friends hope this video
helped you if not please comment your issue in the comment comment bar and
friends don't forget to give a huge thumbs up on our video and please
subscribe to our channel to get latest technical updates and this is Mohin from
Curious Techie signing off