Welcome, welcome, welcome to my stream, hello everybody, our chair over here, we can sit
down, we're not really that visible though, we can maybe tilt it down a little, we're
gonna write on the whiteboard, let's wait for some people to get in here, oh good morning,
we don't subscribe, we're only chat, we don't need to subscribe, we're only chat, thank you for
subscribing. Is this setup working? We have the whiteboard today, no computer, only whiteboard.
I did a lot of thinking about the last stream, I did a lot of thinking about the
techno-peasantism argument for the last one, it was brought up in a few things and we can discuss
crisis of meaning, right, maybe you've heard this phrase, who thinks it's true,
right, can everyone see the board? No one can see the board, I need to write way bigger.
I need to write way bigger, this is not big enough for the board.
Wow, now I understand what you guys always say with the font, right?
We're just gonna write the word meaning, big letters, right?
Everybody suffers from this, right? You think, you think, oh, oh, did I spell it right? Yeah, meaning,
right? It's not a crisis of skill issue, right, and a crisis of meaning is actually incredibly
stupid when you think about it, like, you know, I think about it, I was in New York for the weekend,
I'm thinking about this.
My markers, you don't like my marker, okay, we got lots of markers to choose from, thank you, thank
you, you know what, guys, I'm not gonna wear black anymore, you know, I always dress in black,
I think I'm gonna bleach my hair blonde and I'm gonna wear brightly colored clothes,
not brightly colored, but like white, you know, because it's time, the tides are turning,
it is, it is 2024 and the tides are turning, we thought that marker was bad, this marker is
even worse, someday they will invent good markers, I like big shirts, you know,
no, it's the other way around, bro, the Fs are white, the zeros are black, come on,
um, wear earth colors, no, it's not about the meaning of life, right, but you guys know that
I'm not kidding, when I say what is the meaning of life, right, and there really is only one
answer that makes any sense, and that's to win, right, that's it, win, no one can see anything,
this board doesn't work, it's too shiny, okay, so, um,
how do you win, right, so I just like, like, like here we are, look around, right, you are in an
open world, MMORPG, right, here you are with all these people, now, how do you win at World of
Warcraft, how do you win at Zelda, right, how do you win it, wow, how do you win at Zelda,
right, why do you think it's different, why, and this is what, what just comes to me about
the crisis of meaning being so incredibly stupid, it's like, have you had a crisis of meaning in
Zelda ever, right, what am I even solving these shrines for, you know, okay, I guess it's nice,
I guess it's nice that you can, you can click that button and it says at the top, you know,
destroy Calamity Ganon, right, I'm going to stop saying right, I realize I say right at the end
of things and it's bad, and I'm not going to do that anymore, because it's a new year, it's 2024,
even though you can't see it and it's in green marker, when it felt real,
I understand that, but what do you think feels real anymore, I go to New York every year and the
things that used to feel real don't feel real anymore either, we can't go back, we can only go forward,
only forward, not back,
so you have no problem with this objective in World of Warcraft and Zelda, and there's
lots of different things you can do in these games, you can, you can join a guild, you can go
gather mushrooms in the forests, but you don't have a crisis of meaning in these games and why not,
why do you have a crisis of meaning in this world, but not there, I'm sorry the game is hard,
I'm sorry the game takes a really long time to beat, I can't tell you how to quit procrastination,
just the world, okay, can everybody, Harvard, can everybody read this because we're going to put
a big no sign for it, these people have led us wrong for the last 50 years, for the last 50 years
we've been listening to idiots, we don't have to listen to them anymore, Harvard's over, we're free,
um,
no we don't, we don't, there has been a group of people since, since, we'll put the year up here,
since 1971, that has been, you know, the year the money became fake, this is when everything
seemed to go awry, and we just don't have to listen to them anymore,
can I draw my best integral sign, go, you're the reason we're going to go subscribe only,
uh, no, no, no, no, don't trust me, but this is the problem now, okay, so we destroy Harvard,
right, everyone, everyone, everyone loves being, it was at Robespierre, everyone loves being the guy
who's going to, you know, storm the Bastille and kill the Nobles, but the question is what do we
replace it with, you, you can't replace this with a bunch of Hackney conspiracy theories and
libertarianism and, and, and whatever, you can't do that, you need to come up with a new,
uh, epistemology, sort of, I mean, not really, like, it's, it's been there the whole time,
it's been there the whole time, it brings me back to this point, which is how do we win?
So, you've played, you've played Breath of the Wild, right, some of you have, you know what
you're on, that little island with the four, you get the four shrines and, and, uh,
you get the four shrines and then you get your paraglider and you can leave the little island,
look at the universe, we haven't even left the little island yet, here, here, here is, here is
Earth, Earth, right, and here's a sun over here, right, and like space is like, like we'll make
it a little bigger because it's the sun, right, and like space is like that big, guys,
um, or to be fair, there's not going to be beautiful little quests in every corner of space,
this game is harder than that, reality is a hard game, it's not, not to scale, not to scale, not
to scale, okay, so we're going to talk about a few, uh, its name is Sol, okay fine, fine, fine,
Sol, Sol, Sol, Sol, that's, that's, that's, that's like the, that's like the name, we'll put Alpha
Centauri over here, does that, does that, Alpha, a little Alpha Centauri goes over here, I don't
know how to spell that, but you know, it's like, like, like, isn't that Connie's new girl, Centauri,
Centauri, something like that, um, not to scale, uh,
it's, it's not, it's not, it's not appreciate, so let's talk about a few ways that technology's
actually going to start to improve your life again, um, so for the 2010s,
I just listened to Jim Rott's Corey Doctorow, for the 2010s, tech was synonymous with this group
called fame, okay, most of these companies are not technology companies, and if they do technology,
it is mostly kind of as an aside, right, like there's some interesting stuff happening at Meta,
interesting stuff happening at Apple, interesting stuff happening at Google, Amazon's a logistics
company, Netflix is a stated media company, um, but this is not technology, and you shouldn't
associate that, uh, when you think technology, the best thing to think about is farming,
right, you guys watch, you know what's cool, Clarkson's farm, Clarkson's farm,
farming is the best thing to think about, because humans have been growing food for
many, many, many years, and oh man, if those, if those, if those first agricultural guys who were
trying to get like a mule to pull a plow saw a tractor, oh they flip a shit man, y'all a big tractor
coming through the field, you know, tilling all the soil, planting all the seeds, right, chopping
man, they flip a shit, so can anybody sit right here now and say that things have not gotten better?
And yeah, there's some, there's some great like, like crisis of meaning stuff, all things used to
have meaning, used to have to rely on a neighbor, things used to be better, dude, if you want things
to be better like that, leave America, you can, you can go, you know, I love watching these, this
is, this is YouTube or best documentaries, and you watch Africa documentaries, I love Africa
documentaries, you can see right now, if you want to go live in a world where people still need
each other and food's hard to get, and there's a sense of community and tribalism, you can go to
Africa and live this life, right, if you want to, I said right, I gotta stop doing that, um, but
like, do you want to be, you can opt out, you can opt out at any point, the Luddites can opt out,
but for most people, come on, let's be real here, do you want to be pulling the plow or do you want
the tractor? Um, I don't want to rely on any, yeah, it's true, it's true, like something's lost,
right, I'm no, I'm not a technology guy, I'm not a philosophy guy, you know, and it's a shame that
philosophy guys all came from, you know, terrible institutions like this, there are smart ways to
think about philosophy, you just don't see much of them, there are, there is a real liberal arts
education out there, but unfortunately, we are a lost generation, unfortunately, for the last
50 years, what has been called liberal arts is nothing of the sort, what you will get in a liberal
arts, you know, hey ho, hey ho, western culture's gotta go, come on, right, and it's not, it hasn't
gone anywhere, it's still there, you can still find it, there's people out there, and I love when
I meet them, people out there who are still incredibly educated on the humanities, but
these, these, these, these neo-Marxists, like, you know, I've met some smart Marxists, I've met
some smart Marxists, and you can, you can talk about Marx in, in, in smart ways, and it is true
that they still do produce some decent Marxists, but I don't think Marxism's really the future,
I think that it had some good points a while ago, we tried it, and hey, you know, we got the soviet
union, all right, Marx was a Jew, so what, what, I'm streaming, what's up, what's up,
I got COVID, you got COVID? Yeah. Oh, all right,
uh, I'm streaming, do you want to bring me? Yeah, I'd love to, uh, all right, yeah, uh, yeah,
should, should, should we go? No, I don't, I don't think it's fake COVID, oh yeah, the
flu is just whatever, the flu is just whatever, uh, happens to be the, uh, the, the, the thing,
that goes around, we call it the flu, we call it a cold, we call it whatever,
coronavirus is a cold, uh, okay, I don't have COVID, um,
let's not get distracted by that, we got distracted, let's, let's, let's go back to where we were,
so yeah, there is a real liberal arts education out there, and I hope some of you, you know,
only people who comment, you realize the internet commenters, always remember that the internet
commenters are a very small subset of society, oh, I was commenting about your Marx as a Jew,
so what man, come on, let's move past racism, it's 2024, and we can all agree that racism,
especially, uh, systemic racism, like affirmative action, systematic, systemic,
with the system does it, like affirmative action is evil, and there's no place for racism going
forward, so let's, let's, let's stop doing that, right, um, and if you're not on board with the
no racism, you can maybe go to Harvard, I think they like racism there, so, you know, maybe you'll
fit in, maybe you'll fit in, um, Jews hate white, come on, stop with the racist shit, like it's
still racist, it doesn't matter at all, white power, black power, wokeism, it's all racist,
racism's stupid, okay, you want to win or not, you know, even, even, even, Link had to work with the,
with those fish people, yeah, you had to work with the fish people, all right, all right,
you're imagining it was racist against, but stop being racist, all right, can everyone, can everyone
stop being racist in 2024, that's a good, come in, oh, I know, I know, I know, we're telling everybody
that there's no room for racism in 2024, you mean $135, well help yourself, help yourself to my pile
of money, um, I have some in my wall too, I think, we're on stream right now, do you need
just money right now, but it's like, it's like, Tony's brand, stop and buy, you want to shake his
mouth, all right, I got some 20s here, but it's not that, no, I just, every time I get dollars,
I put them in the pile over there, you want to, you want to show them my dollars, oh, here's some
dollars, what is happening, you want some dollars, I got dollars, um, how upset will you be if I make
it rain right now, wait, I wouldn't be upset, I'll pick it up, you'll pick it up, yeah, I'll make it rain!
I mean, I have to feel bad for the guy, I have to count it all,
he's been, I think, I came on a stripper, I always remember that we're having more fun than the other
side, right, these cells having no fun, accelerationists have fun, uh, no, it's true though, it's true,
I've learned this, I've learned this from, from protests, right, like, you look protests,
you know, like the leftist protest used to have the energy and who's ever got the energy, but can
we have a protest where we, we stop, like, I don't know, you know what, you know what infuriated me
last night, I watched that video about housing in Japan and it turns out we really are just all
getting scammed, like there's no reason housing should be expensive, this is a deliberate policy
made up by people who own real estate to make their real estate bags that are expensive, it's
just a scam, uh, and like, you all are affected by this scam, my rent for this apartment is $4,000,
that's insane, get this in Tokyo for a, a grand,
no, um,
I'm sorry if you're a homeowner, but your bags are gonna tank bro, get out, get out while you can,
no legit, if you are in this scam, get out today, I'm warning you right now, Michael Burry's tweeting
it, yo man, uh, you guys know who Michael Burry is, right, um,
now I'm not saying you gotta do protests, I'm saying you gotta be where the energy is,
who's ever having a good time wins the future and who's ever having a bad time loses the future,
uh,
wait, no, but the housing market's actually gonna crash, it's just a question of when
perception is reality until it's not and the market can remain irrational longer than you
can remain solvent but not me, so, you know, I want to print an mRNA at home too, that's right,
um,
you've heard this shit for decades now, yes, but let me tell you what is different this time,
okay, there is one thing that changes, does anyone know what that one thing is?
Not Bitcoin technology, okay, what does it take to build a house? What if we just had a machine
that could print houses? It's, like, there's a great, I think it's a, it's a Hayek quote at the
end of the, uh, you know, the WTF happened in 1971 page, um, that says the only way that we're ever
gonna make money real again is if we figure out how to make it something that they can't quite see
is money, I'm sorry, they see Bitcoin as money, crypto failed, okay, now that doesn't mean that
technology is going to fail but this, this, this, this, like, oh, we're gonna get crypto in before
they notice, I'm sorry, no, like imagine Uber took the path that Bitcoin took, right, Uber worked,
Uber exists today because it turned out that all the congressmen were taking ubers to go to
Congress, the congressmen are not using Bitcoin to buy coffees and they don't give a shit about
crypto and until crypto people understand this, until crypto people understand how to make normal
people depend on their thing, there's no future in crypto, okay, I say this all the time, like,
you want to succeed in crypto, stop trying to make ZK snark bullshit and make triangle, it's like
square but you can pay decentralized with crypto, right, and you know, you can, there's a lot of,
I think there's actually a lot of energy like this in New York, I love New York, you pay for
everything, the cash, it works, right, and they all have, they all have signs that say 4% fee for
credit cards, I love that, I mean you have to pass it on to the consumer, the consumer has to feel
the pain of those merchant fees, check out DIMO, no, yeah, yeah, this is unfortunate,
but this is what your bags and housing are going to look like if you don't get out,
this is what your money is going to look like if you are a socialist, oh no, this is India,
democracy, yeah, that's what happens if you do democracy,
so when someone was angry at my last video saying I embrace fascists, oh Peter Thiel,
who's the fascist man, I took it crazy to me, that's like, man, you want to like give people
freedom and make things cheap, that's fascist man, you can't just do that, right, like we need like
one world government in surveillance state so we can save democracy, all right,
um, we don't need another war, can we do this without war, come on, World War III is actually
going to suck guys, like you think it's going to be cool and you think it's going to be some
call duty ship, but like it's not, okay, it's just going to suck, everyone's at ist now,
how many houses just like family owned, yo, 100% inheritance tax, who's on board,
you got to build yourself up, a war is kind of essential, I'm not an anti-war, I'm not pro-war,
I think that war is appropriate in certain circumstances,
World War III, I mean, I love cold wars, cold wars are the best, cold wars are the best possible
outcome of wars, nobody dies when technology gets better, I love the US, China cold war,
maybe we can have AI skirmishes where drones destroy each other over the pacific ocean,
now that's my kind of war, right, we can get behind that,
no, warm wars sucked in the kind that, the worst kind of war, like World War II was awful, okay,
and the worst kind of war is a war that wants to get the citizenry involved, right, like a total
war where your citizenry have to contribute to the stupid war effort sucks, okay, none of us want
to live through that, a nice war between US and China where we like fight over some uninhabited
island to just like a tech pissing contest, that sounds sick man, like that's the kind of war we
want in the future, okay, it's not like nice war, right, it's an understanding that both sides could
nuke each other and turn everybody into rubble, right, we sort of do this with proxy wars,
it's a little upsetting that people still have to die, imagine we had proxy wars where we just
sent robots, and we can all agree to some Geneva 2.0 convention where we all just send robots to war
and anyone who sends people to war is a terrorist, how about that, tech bro wants war, no I do,
I do want that kind of war though, I think every year we should have drone combat with China over
to take control of an uninhabited island, rules, you can't send people, and maybe there's a,
no no there's not to be a budget cap, it's like the olympic games but with technology,
I think that'd be sick, that's a huge waste of resources bro, bro what are we gonna do,
help poor people in Somalia, come on, come on, drone war sounds sick, George you can't do that,
that's fascist, okay, well that's like your opinion man, that's my new phrase for like
that's like your opinion man, I think it's from the Big Lebowski, I think it's good, war on the moon,
let's go, right, the thing about the moon is almost everything you do to it improves the place,
you explode a nuclear bomb on the moon, I bet it gets better, have I seen for all mankind,
nah what's that, is that like seven genes, true religion,
space rays, except you can shoot at other spaces, no no no no, let's have the pvp zones of space
and the pve zones of space, I'm not saying that about crypto right, like we like that, that'd be cool,
uh no no no, I did like her to think about it, but you know I think we're gonna we're gonna
compliment Mark Andreessen, I think I think Mark Andreessen does bring up a really good point
about these sort of radical uh radical uh Luddites and if they really believe that this
technology is going to destroy the world, if you are going to destroy the world and you think
you know if you really think that your neighbor is working on a project that's going to destroy the
world, killing your neighbor is the right thing to do right and they're going to become violent,
you know hopefully not, hopefully they see the light before they do, but I think this is one
of the smartest things Andreessen said and it is uh sadly something we have to watch out for,
but the good news is we have drones and they do not, um I am a Christian, uh look guys
yeah, all right, um I can't believe I was duped into atheism, but also evolution is real,
so yeah like Christianity, I can see, I do sort of see a bit of a resurgence of Christianity among
younger people, I'm a Christian, I believe in evolution, uh my belief in evolution does come
above my Christianity right, so so if you say you can't, you know, if you say Jesus didn't
die for your sins if you believe in evolution, well that's like your opinion man, uh so but no
when it comes down to a lot of the, again wokeism really showed me the importance of Christianity
and the importance of forgiveness, wokeism is original sin without forgiveness uh and we can't
have that, we have original sin but we have forgiveness okay, that's Christianity, I like it
everyone should get on board, it's a nice religion, we love everybody, come to a church,
I don't know church is kind of boring, someone's got to make cool churches, actually the churches
in the south are cool, if I lived in the south by like one of them like, I went to like Seacoast
church in South Carolina, and it was good and I'd probably go every sunday, uh you know the the
the low-budget Catholic church doesn't, doesn't, doesn't draw me in every weekend, not not hate and
it just doesn't draw me in every weekend, uh the rock bands are cool right, like I think this is
good, I think that like all right fine, they finally caught up to the 1970s but I would love to see a
resurgence of the church, uh that a church that embraces technology, because if you do not embrace
technology you will lose, how do you, how do these people who say they don't like tech, like do they
have a sustainable plan for the future, do they have like like have they thought about what the
future is going to look like, people who don't like tech are like conservatives, uh conservatives
we're gonna rip on conservatives, everybody knows conservatives suck, uh the kind of conservatives
who like in the 90s really didn't like gay marriage, and today they really don't like trans people,
right, but gay marriage is fine, and then in 20 years, well trans people are fine but we have to
do something about pedophiles, right, like, like, like, like it's gonna be, these conservatives
are always losing because they have no principles, it's just a backlash, a backlash to the backlash
to the thing that's just begun, right, so don't, uh, don't be a conservative, don't be a Luddite,
unless you like losing, who's the worst, who's the worst football team in the NFL, I was saying this,
I was saying this to a friend yesterday, uh, you know, there's some people who just, I gotta stop
saying you know, and I gotta stop saying, right, I'm self-aware about this stuff, right, you know,
uh, the Jets aren't pedos always better, I don't like pedos, but like, again, oh, I don't want to
get into this, come on, let's, let's, let's, uh, let's, let's, let's, let's, let's not get into
this, but I think there is a destination of where this stuff goes, and it can just, culture
or stupid, the culture or stupid, there's only one war that matters, and that's, are you on the side
of technology, or are you against technology, this is the new dividing line, this is the new
dividing line in society, we don't have, uh, conservatives and liberals anymore, we have
excel and desal, okay, desal and excel, and which side are you on, are you on this side,
or are you on this side, now this side is conservative, so we'll give them a C,
all right, and this side is progressive, we'll give them a P, and if you've been listening to the
last five minutes, you realize that the C's always lose and the P's always win, so do you want to root
for the Oakland Raiders, or do you want to root for the Patriots when they still had Tom Brady,
look it's a P, right, so it is kind of still conservatives and liberals, but this is really
the dividing line, now look, embracing technology does not mean embracing every single piece of
every single technology, and it's all good even if there's negative effects, that's not what it means,
that's not what it means, I think the most pure way to distill this down, and every metric can
still be perverted, every metric can be perverted, good heart's law, but I think the most pure way
to look at it is energy use, this is energy use up, and this is energy use minus, do we want to use
more energy in the future, or do we want to use less energy in the future, humans, population,
do we want there to be more humans in the future, more than less humans in the future,
some people might put a plus there and still be conservatives, but really it's all the same thing,
energy use in humans, what's the difference, humans use a lot of energy, well you can't use the
energy for that, no, right, are you a progressive or are you a conservative,
are there people out there who are conservatives, and I don't mean to hate on the individual who's
a conservative, the conservative who wants to be left alone and live their own lifestyle, we need
to totally respect that, I totally respect the person who doesn't want to allow the new technology
into their lives, and that's fine, you can, and you should, you should be left alone, and that's
the moral duty of these people, the moral duty of these people is to people who want to be left
alone, people who don't want the technology to come for them, it absolutely should not come for
them, people should totally be able to opt out of this, otherwise you're just asking for a fight,
and I think that's a real, I think that's a mistake that the current progressives make,
so if you want to opt out you can opt out, what you cannot do is prevent this, if you're on this
side and you want to exist, that's fine, but if you're on this side and you want to try to stop
this, that's where we have a problem, and these are the people who need to be soundly defeated in
every poll, in every ballot, in every democracy, in every war, in every everything, war is the
fundamental decider, we don't, doesn't have to come to war, let's hope it doesn't have to come to
war, let's hope these people realize that if you don't embrace technology you lose, and you don't
even have to fight, now let's give them good surrender terms, let them surrender peacefully,
let them live out life on their farm, let them reproduce, this is animal conservation,
it's the same thing, we like animal conservation, we're progressives, all right, so everybody,
in 2024 welcome to the progressive team, welcome to the accelerationist team, we love technology,
we want to see more humans, we want to see flourishing, we don't want to see deceleration,
we don't want to see housing not being built, we don't want to see power plants being knocked down,
we don't want to see one child policies, we don't see anything that looks like this,
it's negative, it's negative, got got positive energy over here, see I'm not dressing in black
anymore, it's time, it's time the future is ours, wow, is this, is this, is this just me with the
same accelerationist and recent manifesto, come on, so coming back to here, coming back to meaning,
look, what is the existentialism of the 21st century, I don't know, I'm not that great at
liberal arts, I'm not, I'm a good programmer, I'm a good security guy, I'm not, I like the stuff,
I'm a hobbyist, but when I meet people who are genuinely good at this stuff, the people who know
all of the Sart books and the Camus books, the people who've actually read like,
like being in time and who are like, I understand it, what was on my book, Kant's, what's Kant's,
oh, critique of pure reason, like the people who've actually read critique of pure reason,
I just, I can't do it, but there's people out there who have, and this is a, this is a serious
role in the future for this, figure out what the existentialism of the 21st century is,
I don't know, I don't know, but there's answers here, and the closest I can come is thinking about
winning, I don't mean winning over other people, I mean winning over nature, we are in this great
open world universe and, well, do we want to win or lose, let's win, you could stand in the same
place, you could, you could play Zelda, you could just stand there, but why would we do that,
you could play your little, you could play your little minigame, go around, catch horses, buy
that one stable all day, but why would we do that, let's progress, let's get to the end of the game,
we're gonna be tired of winning, we're gonna win so much, we're gonna be tired of winning,
Jesus, Trump 5 in 2024, what a, what a sad, what a sad state, but it doesn't matter, it doesn't
matter, this is the new line, this is the new line,
you're either on this team or you're on this team,
all right, and no racism, okay, I don't see any racism, 2024, if you want to be racist,
go to Harvard, okay, they gotta, they gotta, let them, let them have racism, and you know,
they can, they can be stuck in 1971 and, and you know, let them have racism,
Charlie Schumann's out of his time, Harvard is racist, yes, yes, they are, they are,
they have, they, they, so, so look, let's just come up with a very simple definition of racism,
if you are looking at people's race, if you are making decisions based on people's race,
you are a racist, pretty straightforward, right, so if Harvard looks at people's race,
when they decide who to admit, they are racist, and because Harvard is a powerful corporation,
that's systemic racism, okay, should I, should I teach, should I teach impression studies,
does everyone like this, systemic racism, when a government or a large corporation
uses race to discriminate, systemic racism, is a doctor racist then, a doctor doesn't use that
to discriminate, right, if a doctor were to look at someone's race and charge them a different
amount based on their race, sure, if, if you, you, race affects your medical, yeah, but come on,
we live in a society, we live in a Christian society where we're all equal under God, okay,
everybody has the same moral value to God, now, that doesn't mean that everyone's going to have
the same stuff, that's just, that's just the economy, that's just, we live in a free world,
you make, you make choices, you, you have free will, you also unfortunately are somewhat trapped
to your genetics, but that's just life, sometimes the ball comes up red, sometimes the ball comes up
black, should we make roulette illegal, no, but we should remove the zeros from the wheels,
one zero is plenty, three zeros is really egregious, and someone needs to do something about this,
is all racism bad, I think so, okay, now, I do think race does correlate with certain
things that you may want to discriminate based on, you may want to discriminate based on culture,
you may want to live around people who have similar values to you, this is all very different,
and this is not racism, racism is literally, racism is asking the question, what race are you,
this is not a real category, this is bullshit, it singles out a few pieces of DNA that don't,
this is your color, your skin, come on man, this is, we are progressives here, we have moved past
this, okay, racism is over, it's back at Harvard,
how do we build the protect future, I mean, it's not going to be easy and it's not going to happen
overnight, there's going to be a big struggle, okay, so let's get, let's move fast, racism is a
stupid topic, let's move to a good topic, okay, housing, right, this is Peter Teal's thesis and
I've come to believe that it's very true, if we can fix housing we can fix a lot of other problems
in society, so housing you basically have two groups, you have land owners
and then the renters, I mean I'm in this class, so we have two classes, now let's say rents were to
come down 75%, the renters would be happy but the landowner class, the homeowner class would be
unhappy, their bads would become smaller, look, you got to give them a way out, you got to give
them a way out, I don't know what that's going to be, I hope people smarter than me or at least
thinking about this more than me are working on this because you do have to give them a bag out
that this is what needs to happen, you're going to get continued very strong opposition from this
class, this is why this won't happen but if we figure out how to either satiate, swindle, whatever
it is we do to this class, I don't know, I'm all for diplomatic solutions here but something's
got to be done, this is class warfare, this is Marxism 101, they really try to distract you with
race is bullshit but we are the 99% boys, we are the 99% and something's got to be done about the
damn landowners gouging everybody because they don't just gouge everybody by charging a lot for
their properties, they vote in elections and then they make it illegal to the more housing,
basically, I hope everyone understands this now and hope everyone sees that it doesn't have to be
this way, I think the simplest way to get people out of this and into this is to show them that the
future can be better than the present, if you live in a world where we're in pretty much decline
since 1971, it's hard for them to believe that the future can be better than the present, look up,
look up, trust in the US government, look up trust in the US government, peek to Kennedy and it's
gone downhill since, little spiked Reagan, little spiked Clinton but mostly it's gone downhill since
we need to convince people things can be better and they can, thanks to technology
because everyone can agree that attractor is a lot better than plowing the field yourself
so eat the rich, I love it, I love it, let's team up with AOC, we got to get AOC on this team,
right, we got to, how do we get AOC on this team, we can do it because these are the good guys
I know Uncle Ted wouldn't agree but like
it's not good, it's not good, we got to move past that, we got to move past that ridiculous way
of thinking that somehow meaning is being stripped from the world, all right let's talk about, let's
talk about, let's talk about Ted Kicinski, right, guy love nature, wild nature, guy did not like
uniform housing projects, I don't like uniform housing projects either, the things that we
can build in the future look more like nature, there's a pirate wires article about this,
we can, the reason that houses are boring beige boxes is because the manufacturing technologies
of the last 100 years allow us to build boring beige boxes, as we get control of, as we can use
ad-lib manufacturing technologies, as we can use biotech to build, that's the look at species 8472,
that's the future, like a fusion of biology and the things in the future are going to look more
like nature, not less like nature, we will exist in more harmony with nature, with more technology,
things today are, when you think about, I just want you to imagine an appliance from the 1950s
and how sketchy it looked, the thing was a fire hazard, the thing was, think about like a transformer
and you're putting things through and your coils are vibrating at 60 hertz and it's scraping the
enamel off the coils, now compare that to a MOSFET, think about it, think about a beautiful little
tiny MOSFET, switching a kilowatt, you switch a kilowatt with a MOSFET, you know 50 volts 20 amps
is a kilowatt, with a MOSFET, I don't know, it's the MOSFET symbol, now we'll draw the transistor,
compare this, this is also not to scale, compare this to, oh what I gotta build a relay,
what am I gonna do, build a relay, I'm gonna pull a magnet on here and then have like a little like
electromagnetic coil here, oh, oh, the solid state, the technology gets us closer to like
beautiful pure things, the relay and the transformer last a way shorter amount of time,
I know that's not a MOSFET, what's the MOSFET, what's the MOSFET symbol, well you know what,
I'm gonna label them gate drain and source, so therefore it is a MOSFET, there we go,
take that electrical engineering, actually this is this, right, the drain is the emitter,
the source is the collector, I don't know, is that right, I mean I think yeah because usually
your drain is like, if you have like a, it depends, I think it depends if it's n-type or p-type,
yeah, we could go into, but it's this stuff, I was watching a, you watched a Superbowl
from 1995, you watched like the Superbowl show and you look at these large halogen lamps that
you can't switch on and off quickly, how would you even do that, how would you even switch it on
and off quickly, today we have LEDs switched by MOSFETs, come on, that's cool, so drain,
source and drain, it's gate, source and drain, we have three things, but I forget that one,
that's this n-t-n because I do the arrow that way, p-n-p's the other way, I don't know, I come from
pre-MOSFET, small transistor uses less energy, out arrow is n-type, yeah, okay,
MOSFET and heat sink, yeah, but you need a tinier heat sink today,
you need a tinier heat sink today than you do in the past because your, so MOSFET has a resistance
here, you have, you have some, you have some basic like, like the model is that it's a semiconductor
with some resistance, actually just resistance that matters, so you have some drain source
resistance when your MOSFET's fully saturated and these things are becoming, this like, it's,
I think it's beyond 99% efficient today, meaning that for every, for every, you want to switch
a kilowatt, you only need to sink 10 watts, I bet there are even more, I bet there are even more
than 99% efficient today, if we had computers we could look this stuff up, but the future is so
bright, I agree, so this is a separate problem and we need real liberal arts majors to work on this,
we need people who actually understand what, what was called the liberal arts for many, many years
till it was perverted by a Marxist cult, right, is this controversial, I think, I think everyone
kind of gets it now, um, what can us as engineers do, okay, stop and I say the same thing I always say,
think about what you're working on and what the convergent endpoint of it is,
think about where your technology is going and how your technology is going to change the world,
what group of people is it going to benefit, is it going to benefit, if you are at a physics
research lab researching MOSFET's with lower drain source resistance, you are doing good for the world,
if you are working on a, you know, I don't have a name to have to give examples,
you know the kind of things that I'm talking about, if you are working on,
if you work at TurboTax and you are lobbying the IRS to make the tax code more complicated,
that's my favorite example, but there's many forms of that, if you are working to slow down any of
this technology, if you are the person who made Elon strap a seal to a board, you're the bad guy,
so what can you as engineers do, I mean think about who you work for, do you work for people who
look like this or do you work for people who look like this, a lot of these sort of people still
want technology, the New York Times has somebody making their website, don't do that, the New York
Times actually isn't that bad, but you know the ones who are bad, if they're not, if the ownership
of your company is fundamentally against technology, stop working for them and start working for people
who like technology and want the future to be better than the present,
Yeah, Fang and John Deere are probably on the left side of the board,
I mean I think, I don't look, I don't know that much about John Deere,
for Fang companies, yeah I mean I wouldn't work at Google, I think Google is fairly anti-technology
today, I think that it's less clear for companies like Amazon,
well of course they were lion-tech and look, just like, just like welcome to the, you know,
welcome to the, welcome to the, welcome to the 2020s, the lit 2020s, where we used to, people
used to quit because they're, they're, you know, oh my company doesn't support, like my company
isn't pro-choice, I'm going to quit the company, right, that's right, I respect these people right
to stand up for what they believe in and all the engineers out there, you know, stand up for what
you believe in, right, it's the same thing, but I think, you know, it's, it's, if your, if your
company doesn't share a pro-technology set of values, stop working there, stop helping them with
technology. Meta is, these companies are large, they have many different divisions, they have many
different teams, I think that I can promise that all of my interactions with Elon match up to what
you think Elon is. Elon seems to be complete, like there is no, there actually isn't a filter,
how Elon behaves is what Elon is. I can't say the same thing about Mark Zuckerberg or Jeff Bezos,
I'm not sure, I'm not saying that they're not, but what I'm saying is it's not completely obvious
to me and see if you can find somebody who would vouch for them, you know, someone who's, someone who's,
someone who spent time close with Mark Zuckerberg, does he actually believe the kind of stuff he's
saying now? And then there's also a question of do these people have, you look at someone like
Jack Dorsey on Twitter, it turns out Jack Dorsey was just cut out of everything on Twitter. So
sometimes you might even have, the question is do they have control and do they have good values?
So come on, we all learned, we all learned from the SJWs in the 2010s, some of their tactics are
good, some of their tactics are good, don't announce them because they're SJW tactics,
but always make sure that you are having fun and if you're not having fun, you're going to lose,
right? If you, if you see this all as drudgery and this is what I said on Twitter, I'm like,
if you don't love technology, quit technology, right, it's going to be a party and that's the
kind of energy that was, I loved Occupy Wall Street back in the day, that's the kind of energy
that, that, that, that works, that's sustainable. Everyone here is having a good time building
the future. What's the name of this cult? It's not a cult and it's the future, the progressivism,
it's progressivism, right? Progressivism, we believe in progress.
We're boogieing, right? Electric Boogaloo, I love that, the Boogaloo boys.
See, they're having a good time, man. How is Excel the good side if the doomers are right?
What are the doomers right about? Everybody can say AI and they can say doom, okay?
What exactly, how exactly does AI lead to doom? I was trying to get Yudkowski to explain it and
it's just like convergent endpoint. You know what else a convergent endpoint is? The heat death of
the universe, okay? The heat death of the universe is coming and if we have any chance of answering
the last question, we need AI. So currently, we are on a trajectory to doom. I want everybody to
remember that. You know, some people have those clocks that like, how long you have in your lifespan?
Well, how long do we have before the heat death of the universe?
Right? Right? I gotta stop saying that. I gotta stop saying that. I gotta stop my verbal tics.
It's 2024. So it gets more than a few billion years, but the heat death of the universe is coming
and in order to beat the heat death of the universe, we need AI. Maybe,
maybe you can't beat the heat death of the universe. We don't really know.
AI leads to doom when the government uses autonomous robocops.
With all technology, there's challenges. With every technology in the past, with all this
new surveillance technology that now exists, there are challenges. Is AI a pure unalloyed good?
No. Is technology a pure unalloyed good? When you have a gun pointed at your head,
you do not think technology is a pure unalloyed good, but on balance is technology good.
And the answer is, I think obviously, with things like age back and cheap food and cars,
and look like, I flew here, I just flew here on JetBlue from New York, right? I could talk
shit about JetBlue, but imagine flying in that like right flyer too. At least that was on A321.
I'm against progress of technology. They no longer provide benefits. That's not true.
We are unfortunately, like you've been scammed by a group of people for the last 50 years.
The reason things have gotten worse is largely not because of technology. I also just listened to
Corey Doctorow on Jim Rutt's podcast. And like, we have been scammed largely through
government inaction against these tech companies. I saw someone in the comments like, George,
you don't even know you can download other browsers for iOS. I just, someone says something
like that. I want you to think. I want you to think, do I not know how browsers work on iOS
or are you wrong? When you download Chrome on iOS, it uses a web view, which is actually just Safari,
because nothing else on iOS is allowed to mark pages RWX. RWX is a permission built into the
kernel that only the Jits allowed to bypass. There is a 5% chance I'm out of date on that
information, but I don't think so. Okay, so you'd think who you talking to, right? We went from
a world where Microsoft couldn't bundle Internet Explorer with Windows without getting sued. And
now we live in a world where Apple not only bundles Safari, but doesn't let you install anything else.
So this is not due to technology. This is due to failure of government. This is due to regulatory
capture. Technology itself. When you think of technology, don't think of Fang. Think of a
MOSFET. A very simplistic model of a MOSFET. You put in a little current here and massive
currents flow here. It's a switch. And that has changed. That's why everything's so small and
good now. You have a phone that can charge. I got my phone charger around here. 67 watts.
You're putting 67 watts into something this big. You think you can do that without MOSFET?
You can use a transformer? So everybody, don't think of Fang when you think of technology. Think
of the MOSFET. All right. That's where iOS is now for the Mac. Yeah, for the Mac actually,
you can install it from web browsers. Thank you for watching today's stream. It's the end of 2023.
Make sure you're having a good time. If you're not having a good time, if you're angry, you're
probably over here. And might I consider switching to the, you know what the P stands for? It stands
for party. You're joining, you're joining the party side. Happy 2024. Everybody have a great
New Year's on Alloy. Tech optimism. Someone's got to solve this. Someone's got to solve this.
Let's create an alternative to this that can produce real liberal arts scholars who can
solve the meeting crisis. I'm not smart enough to come up with it, but I'm smart enough to read it
and understand it. So I would appreciate that if you were out there. Happy New Year, everybody.