Hey everyone, this is Purva and I'm really sure you all are wondering what is this audition
doing but a few months ago I had written this small article on how social media is affecting
us especially the youth and a lot of people suggested me that I should video record it
but I was feeling really shy to come in front of the camera and say all that
but I think I gave it a try so let me know if you like it and let's go
okay tell me one thing do you ever stand in front of a mirror and ask yourself who you really are
you know I feel a lot of people make themselves out to be someone they're not and how scary it is
when you pretend to be something you're not and then eventually you start becoming that person
and then have the audacity to say I'm just being myself I mean who are you kidding here
why are we neglecting or rejecting originality the reason why most of us are like this is only us
we are the main culprits here you know in my generation especially in my generation every
single thing is a joke to us we make memes about everything and I know some of you all don't even
know what a meme is it's basically a joke but yeah everything is a joke to us and you know for
example it's funny how we encourage the thought of how people get bored after socializing for two
hours and how they need their space isn't it actually funny how social media is making us
anti-social so a few months back I was having coffee in Starbucks and I saw a group of friends
entering probably of my age they gave their order found a comfortable place to settle down
and nothing they were nicely chit chatting laughing as soon as their order arrived everybody took out
their phones within a second and everybody was taking pictures of their coffee their food they
were not bothered about tasting it you know I just finished my coffee and came outside
and while I was waiting for my driver to pick me up I saw two older men having a small cup of tea
and you know laughing their heart out they were giving each other high fives they were basically
enjoying the moment and they were not bothered about the place the food the environment nothing
they were just in the moment and I just stood there wondering why can't we all be this easy going
well most of them out there go to good-looking places eat good-looking food just because their
instagram story needs to be perfect you know even on birthdays some people are so concerned about
recording the cake cutting part that they forget to actually genuinely sing for the person who is
celebrating his day or you know clap for him nothing they just bothered about taking a video
putting it on social media as soon as possible that's it you know and I really can't blame anyone
here or you know there's no offense to anyone because sometimes somewhere even I have done this
and it makes me so sad that we don't even notice this why is the need of showing off so strong
in our generation why I mean we are forgetting to live in the moment you know all we can think
about is how can I look flawless on social media so that other people won't judge why is the definition
of enjoyment or happiness dependent on such materialistic things why some of you all don't
even know how much effort we have to put in before posting a picture on instagram you know editing it
giving it a good caption so everybody will think how cool I am and then asking others for their
approval posting on weekends so that more people can see it you know not repeating the same clothes
and the list goes on do you ever just think is it really worth it is doing all this stuff
just for one post is it really worth it you know sometimes being just the way you are waking up
and admiring the sunset before checking your phone or you know looking at an old photo album with your
mom and dad having remember when moments with your cousins staring at this guy with your favorite music
you know and hanging out with that one person or that one friend who you really care about
getting a genuine smile from a stranger and a lot of small things which we don't even notice can
make you so happy unknowingly okay I know most of y'all are thinking why is this girl sounding
like a gyanibaba or someone like that but to be honest we are forgetting that we were made to
interact with each other help each other and by interacting I don't mean interact by sending
memes just really interact in person you know and lastly I want to say that happiness doesn't mean
that you have to be happy all the time I mean who is happy 24 7365 that's not possible right
but to find joy and to be alive in the moment and I know it's not as easy as it sounds or
as easy as it looks but is it really that hard to just give it a try