hey so glad you could make it come on in so this is my setup tour it's finally
happening as you see right away there's this dope-ass whiteboard where I keep all
my most important information being a youtuber I have to be organized and make
sure I write down what I have to do wait don't film this this is where I pray
to Odin three times a day please give me more subs Odin it's a trash can oh it
looks like we got a gift
Edgar what were you doing in there you ready for more let's keep the tour going
Michael how's the diamond play button doing looks good what do you think miss a
spot I want that shit polished and clean if you miss a spot you're out Michael is
Romanian follow me don't be shy
hell yeah motherfucker these panels look like a toddler drew them but they were
done by me I think it looks pretty cool it gives that room a bit more
personality instead of a normal wall I don't know I like it all right fuck you
oh yeah baby this is how real men record under goddamn feet can do squatting if
I want how do you think I maintain this great ass it feels like I'm wearing
nothing at all nothing at all nothing got my microphone on a shock mound it's
not it's not the best one but you don't need a great microphone at least if
you're not put a pie so as you can yell in it that's all you need baby the next
alarm so he goes to this goes to this little baby right here I honestly don't
know how it works got my sweet ass glorious mouse pad I managed to find the
tiniest keyboard out there oh wow now I can truly relax oh what should I play
today got my my beauty light the ring light all the beauty gurus use it to look
good I don't need it to look good but my camera it's a Canon with a shotgun mic on
top of it so in case I fuck up and I didn't record my shit this one is a
lifesaver this one is a live see look at the setup though it looks fucking dope
as fuck on camera tell me right now you wish you had this set up baby
alright my headphones they're wireless so in case I'm making videos I can move
around I can do shit I can kick the walls if I want to don't want to though I
can move over here I can move over here I can disappear and you wouldn't even
know now I know what you're thinking this all looks very pretty pills but what
about how does it look behind the scenes oh boy I got a lot to show follow me are
you ready for this I don't think you're ready for this oh oh that
organization oh oh come over here bring come over here look at this they go
out I got all kinds of shit oh my god and it's so neat and tidy bitch that's
right you thought I was a dirty hoe I am the cleanest motherfucker this guy is
clean as a motherfucker Brad what are you doing come on you got to keep up it's
time to check what's inside I know you're curious like a little kid on
Christmas what's inside the package papa parents more pine cones this year
papa parents okay so this is actually a server cabinet I have so many consoles
and computers cables is fucking everywhere but let's get right into that
shit I'm gonna link all my specs in the description because I know a lot of
people care and I know a lot of people have no idea what I'm talking about but
all you need to know is this is a bomb ass computer and it is fast Xbox above
Gamecube I got them all all right I could fit a bunch I could fit as many
consoles in there as I like and I lock it at night so no one touches my shit all
the cables nightly goes into one pop goes right in there it looks nice as
fuck yes right that's right that's right now it was kind of a problem having a
standing desk with the cables being fixed but I think did a pretty good job
you got a clock is that a clock that is a clock that is a huge ass clock so I
can know the fucking time of how long I've been recording and shit what is the
time today it and let's see here it's 15 hey Brad have you seen this shit the
LEDs I can change them what color you what's your favorite color bitch play on
that shit on you ever have a girl over you say that line she'd be dripping whoa
it's Christmas baby I got the cinnamon candle I got the Christmas light
father Christmas comes early in Papa Pimp's house Michael keep polishing what
it what did I tell you keep polishing the diamond play button if I see one
more little smudge on it I'm gonna call YouTube and have you responsible are
you using the bleach now get out because I need to take a nap you forgot to do the
outro I when I started making videos I was really on this tiny fucking table I
couldn't even fit my keyboard on it so tune I made it guys I fucking made it I
got my dream set up now honestly since we got kicked out I really wanted to make
this set up the way I really really wanted and it was really fun to work on
it and I'm just very happy with it so I hope you both enjoyed watching if you
did leave a like and there's always stay awesome
are you playing poker go to catch anything good to drive behind you dude we
see the same Pokemon we found the all the same Pokemon this is so cool this is
if it's real or something it's almost like the Pokemon is there now we just
got hit by a car we're gonna go to the seafront to do some fishing maybe I'll
find some magic comps magic cars