Hey everyone, so in the last couple of years I began to feel this sense of
cynicism and deep pessimism growing in our culture and I'd even say it started
coming into my personal and private life not at a philosophical abstract level
but really in my day-to-day intimate interactions and I started feeling that
viscerally and a part of me was like you got to give the devil his deal you know
I think you can't justify a certain level of cynicism in this world we live in
and that's what inspired this essay you know I write to think and for the
longest time I wrote for myself my private thoughts you know journaling
just taking down notes here and there and I think I finally mastered up the
confidence to start sharing my work publicly you know sharing my writing
publicly even though I tend to ramble a bit so I'm sort of plotting along and
trying to make sense of why I still think despite all the malevolence despite
all the cynicism that is that BCN is justified to a certain level that they
still a case to be made against it a case to be made for living life in the
fullest and deriving meaning out of the world we live in so anyway I hope you
enjoyed this essay it's actually a an essay I wrote for medium and my you know
personal blog and I'm just reading it out because I do know that a lot of people
prefer listening or watching it instead of reading it part of it is obviously
subjective and personal to me but then I also think most of it is really something
that's applicable to all of us that's like an objective truth let's say but
yeah I'm keen to hear your thoughts I hope you enjoy it let's get to it now
against cynicism my case for living life to the fullest
to my partners annoyance I have a running joke I make at social gatherings
about wanting to have 10 kids one day enough to play a 515 basketball game I
tell myself the reason behind the joke is for some engaging befuddling humor to
lighten up the mood in a room even though it mostly leaves me having to
explain the joke awkwardly and even then most people do not find it funny yet
the more I think about it I feel as if this is something my heart truly
desires to have many kids probably not 10 and become a father someday hopefully
a good one as the adage goes there's a grain of truth in every joke but then I
think why would I want to do something that absurdly impractical when evidence
suggests that as people get more educated they tend to have fewer children
why would I want to go against the tide leaving aside the ridiculous number of
kids why even bring a child into this God for second world scourged by climate
change pandemics a lamentable economy and alarming social unrest how selfish
and cruel of us to inflict such inevitable misery onto another human
being by bringing them into this world and even worse what if my posterity
becomes totalitarian and deceitful tyrants who end up exacerbating the
agony of people I've heard people say that loving a child is sacrificial and
such selfless love is the highest of all virtues utter nonsense one could argue
as it looks to me that most people willingly have children leaving aside
the accidents only to overcome the soul sucking banality of their life and don't
get me started on love sheer boredom drives us to find love it is a self
centered facade of intimacy even the unconditional love of God is conditional
as he necessitates for repentance prior to our salvation if God truly loved
his children why couldn't he just forgive us instead of sacrificing his own son
for atonement most people deceive themselves of being in love only when
it's passion and their absolute inability to live with themselves that
prepidatiously hold together their relationship it's why John Baptiste
Clemens recognized in Albert canons the fall of course true love is exceptional
two or three times a century more or less the rest of the time there's vanity
or boredom even if let's say love doesn't have to entail a higher virtue over
mere passion and all love necessitates is just that passion alone is in passion
itself a selfish pursuit supposed a man or woman audaciously follows their
dreams and aspirations in that case it seems like an awfully privileged
position handed to them by society and most people in the world wouldn't have
that fortune some may even say aspiration is for the spoil and ungrateful
desiring something more than being satisfied with the life they're given
as I've demonstrated above being cynical towards life isn't difficult but the
only question really worth asking is what to do after we've rationalized our
sense system that's what I try to deal with in this essay a caveat questioning
the answerable can leave us in a grim place the angst it brings makes us
bitter, misanthropic and implacable hence it's not surprising that we
intentionally repress these gratuitous thoughts and cling to what the rest of
society does with their lives the social zeitgeist protects us from insanity
it's more comforting to distract ourselves with a political or celebrity
scandal rather than looking into the festering wounds in our own lives and
reality itself at least for myself have it to I have been rather fortunate in my
life a lot of unearned good has come my way mostly through those I love and yet
these existential questions haunt me despite my good luck I have spent
countless nights trying to integrate my serendipity with the world's
unjust cruelty how dare I benefit from unmerited happiness it's not gratitude I
feel but a peculiar type of consternation at life I swear you gentlemen
that to be overly conscious is a sickness a real tarot sickness
Voidol Dostoevsky even while I'm writing this piece I question my
privilege and impertinence in asking such nonsensical questions about love
marriage and passion a part of myself is still yelling at me go do some work
hippie these aren't questions one should bother asking last year a friend of mine
unexpectedly passed away she was a beautiful soul her funeral was in
Sri Lanka and I couldn't attend it because I live in Australia but I saw her
wailing parents through the funeral livestream how cruel is the caprice of
life I thought and how arbitrary is the nature of suffering I particularly
remember her mom when I was growing up in Sri Lanka she was a loving and kind
lady what has she done to deserve such so crushing sorrow of losing a child how
could nature be so malignant my friend's death was a clear rebuttal of how life
ought to be as I was told parents aren't supposed to bury their children but it
ought to be the other way around I sit here in my comfortable apartment
typing and philosophizing away on my nifty computer wondering if I dug
myself into a hole too deep how privileged am I to dig this hole of my
own free will when my parents when my friend's parents were pushed into it by
the faded tragedy of life however privilege or misfortune angst or
gratitude aren't justifiable reasons to evade and hide from such questions we
shouldn't give way to the pretense and at times distractions of mundane life
that we all use to cushion ourselves from the existential blows of living nor
should we neolistically succumb to fatalistic resentment both these forms
of living are out of cowardice once a question is asked not as a mere
utterance but as an but as an authentic form of being itself and how we live
through our actions emotions words desires or whatever constitutes an
individual no reason we used to hide from such questions are adequate unless we
confront truth regardless of the consequences these questions will
enduringly haunt us forever every objection I brought up against children
or procreation marriage love passion and even gold salvation can be rebuked
through cogent arguments inferred from numerous intellectual propositions
and syllogisms a few ad hoc examples environmental activists Mike
Schellenberger makes a systematic case in his book apocalypse never as to why we
should be more optimistic about climate change and not capitulate to
anti-human sentiments such as not having children because of the environment
he emphasizes we should focus on humanitarian development and elevating
people from poverty as this has proven to be one of the best remedies for
imminent environmental problems the following tweet thread succinctly
highlights his worry about young people not wanting to have children due to
climate change I should stipulate that my intention behind using Schellenberger's
ideas as an example wasn't me taking a political stance on the matter of
climate change I stand neutral on the complicated subject as I'm grossly
uninformed about its nuances a big lie that pathologize society since the
1960s with the publication of books such as the population bomb is a myth of
dangerous overpopulation that lead to global famine and environmental
catastrophe up till now these radical claims seem unsubstantiated for
instance Lehman Stone from Vox states in his article why he shouldn't obsess
about overpopulation lowering US carbon intensity by about a third to around the
level of manufacturing superpower Germany today has a bigger effect than
preventing 100 million Americans from existing there's only one way to
effectively prevent alleviate or reverse dangerous climate change
technological geographic and social advancement population has little to do
with it especially not in the US despite the terrible consequences of COVID-19
we also made unprecedented progress in epidemiology and vaccination
development while I'm not reducing the suffering people went through due to the
pandemic modern medicines expedition is a scientific miracle we've seen in the
last few months UCLA health reports in a remarkable achievement of medical
science we've gone from identifying a new pathogen discovering an immune
response against it to developing and testing a safe and effective vaccine for
it in less than 12 months previously the fastest vaccination to go from
development to deployment was the mom's vaccine in the 1960s which took about four
years all these developments were obviously done by human beings therefore
using the pandemic as an example we could extrapolate the remedy to every other
problem we face including social unrest unfavorable economic conditions
environmental issues etc the answers lie in people the more talented people who
come to live the most solutions we will find through their skills looking through
a pure utilitarian ethical lens we need a bigger talent pool provided they have
equal opportunity to create more value in this world or crassly stating we need
more people to exploit more good from humanity for the world however pure
talent alone isn't what makes an individual remarkable it's a combination
of exceptional character and innate ability in their respective attitudes
therefore such excellence is rare and the only way to increase our plane of
serendipity is to increase the number of human beings the individual being a
central part of creation is an unbelievably ancient ideal it runs deep
into the mythology and stories that hold our cultures specifically the
Western world together the individual is the correct level of analysis as there
is a fundamental truth that speaks to a human beings sacredness and sublimity it
speaks so deeply that we couldn't even dare to question its validity for the
longest time in human history it would be considered sinful the book of Genesis
explicitly stating Imago day gold created man in his own image is a
proclamation of humanity being endowed by the divine to bring forth a new
reality into being the proposition of Imago day is a metaphysical problem that
philosophers are still trying to comprehend fully yet most modern
societies are undergirded by the concept of human rights which we invariably
cannot violate even the most obtruse and esoteric objections I put forward
earlier about gold salvation has been theologically dealt with by philosophers
such as William Lane Craig and Alvin Pantinger if you're interested in the
subject Dr. Craig recently wrote a whole book on the necessity for the death of
Christ for humanity's sins called atonement and the death of Christ and
exegetical historical and philosophical exploration additionally I could
recommend books like Enlightenment now by Stephen Pinker or the rational
optimist by Matt Ridley where both authors argue that humanity has made
unprecedented progress in the last few centuries they're confident we are on
the right track in almost every available measure for social and
environmental progress in the past two centuries providing ample evidence to
ascertain their findings from various research domains books such as these
delineate that we don't have to look any further for the miracle of human progress
and advancement than our own history notwithstanding the conspicuous
malvalence we see in humanity nevertheless none of these intellectual
arguments will satisfy the burdens of our souls at least it didn't do so for
mine I could find an infinite amount of philosophies from every domain of thought
known to human epistemology but still leave a persisting void of despair in
our hearts I know this to be certain as however much science and philosophy
intellectually stimulated me it was nothing compared to the most intimate
fulfillment that beauty valor and love brought to my soul life is in another
tried philosophical model instead the models are created in trying to
understand life itself we do not lead our lives by making a priori decisions
weighing the pros and cons similar to a machine learning model that runs on a
supervised set of rules for starters this would undeniably drive us insane and
most saliently at the least we do not even have a proper phenomenological
framework to deal with being we patently exist but this existence isn't the end
itself the question lies in what this existence for human beings entails the
telos could life be a set of propositional deductions masqueraded as
choices or is that too simplistic disregarding copious amounts of modern
scientific research research and a an ancient wisdom found across cultures for
a moment simple observation of regular life will show that seldom do we let
PO empiricism logic and cold rationalism guide our lives nor am I sure if we
should necessarily make rationalism the highest of human virtues contrary to
what the Enlightenment think is proclaimed life can be more accurately
portrayed through inspiration romance intuition serendipity synchronicity and
all those bewildering elements of reality that would be dismissed as
superfluous occultism by modernists none of these metaphysical or spiritual
phenomena that still are meaningful occurrences can be explained through the
modern scientific method and rationalism to make sense of those transcendent
realities we need the arts we need to revivify our fading appreciation for
aesthetics as Oscar Wilde wrote paradox though it may seem and paradoxes are
always dangerous things it is nonetheless true that life imitates art far more
than art imitates life for example to elucidate my point I could use a grim
philosophy called antinatalism utilizing the work of its leading advocate in
contemporary times David Beneter the antinatalist position is that humans
should stain from procreation because it's morally wrong to bring more
children to this world and what if and it would have been better for us to never
have been born in the first place
professor Beneter asserts the following presuppositional asymmetry between
pleasure and pain which the whole philosophy rests on number one the
presence of pain is bad number two the presence of pleasure is good number three
the absence of pain is good even if that pain is not enjoyed by anyone number
four the absence of pleasure is not bad unless they somebody for whom this
absence is a deprivation therefore if human beings cease to exist it still
fulfills point number three and four theoretically miss a really David
Beneter may seem like an evil person is evidently anti-human ideas could be the
same worldviews that motivated nihilistic school shooters and ruthless tyrants
publicly unveiling the human hearts innate malevolence I remember my
emotional reaction to coming across his work how in the world could Oxford
University Press even publish such a reprehensible book yet as I delve into
his work and the individual behind those ideas I discovered a person who isn't
much worse than the rest of us fools he did not have an irrational hatred for
humanity and he certainly wasn't stating that people currently living should be
wiped off the face of the planet in fastical irony he dedicated his book
better never to have been to his progenitor stating to my parents even
though they brought me into existence Beneter is simply an academic
philosopher putting forward a set of ideas similar to what socrates all
the stoics have done historically his assertion isn't particularly novel
either it's something human beings always wondered through a discussion that
goes all the way to the book of Ecclesiastes in the Old Testament and
I declared that the dead who had already died are happier than the living who are
still alive but better than both is the one who has never been born who has not
seen the evil that is under the sun I'm not a philosopher nor do I care for the
sort of generative philosophy that acts only in the plane of abstractions there's
nothing more convenient than creating asymmetries and inferring conclusions
within a finite set of ad hoc rules where we define the axioms I've lazily done
that even in parts of this essay it's what Albert Camel understood in the
myth of Sisyphus which in my opinion makes him a true and rare philosopher
there is but one truly serious philosophical problem and that is
suicide judging whether life is or is not worth living amounts to answering
the fundamental question of philosophy all the rest whether or not the world
has three dimensions whether the mind has nine or twelve categories comes
afterwards these are games one must first answer and if it is true as nature
claims that a philosopher to deserve our respect must preach by example you can
appreciate the importance of that reply for it will proceed the definitive act
these are facts the heart can feel yet they call for careful study before they
can become clear to the intellect was Mike Tyson crassly said everybody has a
plan until they get punched in the mouth
nevertheless despite my objections to conceptualizing life as a philosophical
model and prescribing eschatological judgments on living I will engage in
bentis example for expediency's sake but I will not engage as a philosopher as I
don't think the age-old question that was asked in Hamlet Solakway is a
philosophical one to be or not to be that is the question the fundamental
axiom in asymmetry between pain and pleasure presupposes one that the
presence of pain is bad and to the presence of pleasure is good I disagree
with this presupposition it isn't clear that life can be good only if its pain
is entirely eliminated from being and all and all human beings had was
infinite bliss and pleasure nor does it seem like as Dostoevsky understood
human beings will desire such a mode of living one of my childhood heroes was
Lakshman Kadergama okay a Sri Lankan statesman and a lawyer during his time
as the Minister of Foreign Affairs he was a key figure in Sri Lanka civil war
against the LTE a separatist service organization for example the independent
reported on his vitality for global politics Kadergama was not just any
senior minister he was the highest ranking ethnic Tamil in the government
more than that he was the man who was responsible more than anyone for drying
up international support for the Tamil Tigers the LTE it was his
international campaign that has a tiger's name as a banned terrorist
organization in the US UK and other countries similar to similar awards in
any other country Sri Lanka's conflict has a nuanced and complicated history and
yet most Sri Lankans would unequivocally agree LK was a national hero he was
posthumously awarded the highest national honor Sri Lanka Bhimanya a title
shared by Sir Atsi Clark in hindsight I believe my father giving me LK's
biography to read was the impetus behind my interest in studying politics ethics
and philosophy outstanding his profuse security and protection on August 12th
2005 LK was assassinated by an LTE sniper in LK's biography his son Raghi
states when he was assassinated it was of course not a complete surprise part of
me had been expecting it for years his daughter Ajita concludes perhaps fate
intervened on the night of August 12th but chance he allowed it to in the
knowledge that his every move was being watched in the final analysis it is
possible that Lakshman Kaduragama shows to meet his death that night as a sniper
sat there trigger ready target in sight
Lakshman Kaduragama's life was a quintessential hero's journey in a way
he plays an archetypal role in my mind a true patriot that lived a life of
nobility who wrote in a friend's autograph book at the age of 14 how
sweet and honorable is it to die for one's country and still his biography
doesn't depict a life of bliss and pleasure without any pain instead a
life of angst grief strife and the tremendous weight of carrying the
burden of a bloody and ruthless ethnic conflict according to David Bennett's
hypothesis LK's life would be a bad one due to due to its inherent pain but most
people would agree that he'll be good life it'll be philosophically laborious or
probably impossible to reason and delineate this good but the purpose
Lakshman Kaduragama lived for transcended all of his pain for the more
his noble being created more overall good for the world stories like LK's
remind me that hypothetical philosophical models will never explain life and
reality we cannot create arbitrary axioms of good and bad to justify a living
it's impossible ever to know all the consequences of living both good and
bad intended or unintended besides how dare I adjudicate if a potential future
person was to be born after a 30 year old war that took over 100,000 lives what
would it be Trilanka's fate if Lakshman Kaduragama never came into being an
answerable yet deeply moving question it's this impenetrable enigma and
sublime inexplicability of life that mandates are so lived as we'll never
know if life's worth living until we have all together and entirely lived it as
one of Soran Kedricar's journals say it is really true what philosophy tells us
that life must be understood backwards but with this one forgets the second
proposition that it must be lived forwards a proposition which the more it
is subjected to careful thought the more it ends up concluding precisely that
life at any given moment cannot really ever be fully understood exactly
exactly because there is no single moment where time stops completely in
order for me to take the position to do this going backwards often shortened to
life can only be understood backwards but it must be lived forwards I'm a
software engineer and a few weeks ago I was having dinner at a steakhouse with
one of my collegial engineers we had a fascinating conversation that led us all
the way from discussing Roger Penrose's hypothesis on consciousness to me asking
him mate if I may ask what does love mean to you he
unhesitantly replied love gives me a reason for eternity I thought deeply
about this response only love has the metamorphosing ability to turn an
engineer who typically works in the technical realm of logic and cold
abstractions into a port and produce such beautiful statement my fortune to
fall in love with Shannon the most remarkable woman who if my luck prevails
I hope to marry someday has convinced me that love is the most irrational
chaotic and incomprehensible force of being that captivates our life like no
other many have tried but no port or philosopher could ever accurately
portray what love means to a human being I think this may be why the phrase goes
I fell in love not I willed my way into love none of us plan to fall in love it
just happens love is unplanned yet timeless unbidden it's yet yearnful
obtruse yet tangible so real yet meaningful and ultimately we find a
reason to live because of love alone this is why I think even Fitzwilliam
Darcy had to go again societal standards and his own prejudice judgment as love
drove him to profess his feelings towards Elizabeth Bennet in Pride and
Prejudice in vain have I struggled it will not do my feelings will not be
repressed you must allow me to tell you how ardently I admire and love you
however even if love alone gives a reason to live this life still worth
living to the fullest even if the emotions evoked in us by love are good
and absolutely real does love justify doing anything that benefits oneself
like following one's passion marriage or having children firstly unless someone
can prove otherwise doing things that are beneficial and good for ourselves
isn't inherently selfish immoral or unjustifiable due to Eastern
philosophies influence with ideas like impermanence or non-self accentuated by
rampant materialism secularism and growing radical self-criticism within
Western culture Westerners have begun to feel guilty for their own being with the
loss of religion and consequently spirituality being jettisoned from the
cultural ethos Westerners feel their individual lives are a waste of space
on this planet or maybe even a pest brutally exploiting Gaia benevolent
mother nature dr. Carl you in all his brilliance and wisdom understood the
death of spirituality in 1957 and prophetically warned us of the ominous
signs in his essay the undiscovered self just as man as a social being cannot in
the long run exist without a tie to the community so the individual will never
find the real justification for his existence and his own spiritual and
moral autonomy anywhere except in an extra mundane principle capable of
relativizing the overpowering influence of external factors the individual who
is not anchored in God can offer no resistance on his own resources to the
physical and moral blandishments of the world for this he needs the evidence of
inner transcendent experience which alone can protect him from the otherwise
inevitable submersion in the mass therefore with such negation of the
individual self any act not serving the greater good but one self is looked
down upon by contemporary culture but we must ignore scornful societal
condescension and judgment as such nihilistic pessimism is futile and
serves no purpose but only breeds resentment suppose something we find
meaningful is good for us and this minimal harm nothing is entirely innocuous
to society in that case there's no good reason to not do that thing undertaking
such responsibility may even be a divine duty notwithstanding our
consciousness of our own shortcomings and unworthiness secondly a bizarre
realization we eventually come to have about life is that doing things not for
ostensible virtue but genuine goodness that gives us a real sense of meaning
mutual mutually benefits both society and ourselves getting married to a person
we love begins a family one of society's most foundational and imperative
units for it to function even if it were for entirely selfish reasons we
decide to have a child let's say as a remedy for trisinarian odum this act
results in bringing forth a new life and every human being is the epicenter of
untapped potential and creation embarking on an entrepreneurial artistic or
sporting venture merely to live out one's passion creates unforeseeable
value in society and hopefully if done portfully even benefits the planet
symbiotically not just in the cliche capitalist tenor of transactional value
creation but even through those heavenly aspects of life that cannot be
commoditized i.e. inspiration beauty elegance awe and wonder all of this
goodness comes into being despite the inherent suffering and malevolence
inexorably present in life however if we cannot see the divine ethos in this
paradoxical miracle of being alive then nothing could stand up to our nihilistic
and cruel judgment but what if we peel the onion one more layer why be good
why not wreck havoc in society and burn it all to the ground it certainly
creates circular reasoning to assert what must be good for the sake of
goodness fortunately for reasons I can't fathom Abrahamic religions have a
straightforward answer to this dilemma and I'm yet to find a better
explanation or a more truthful narrative than this ancient story as it's an
ultimate divine calling from God beginning with the Old Testament we are
told so God created mankind in his own image and the image of God he created
them male and female he created them Genesis 127 straddling to the cumulative
commandment by Jesus of Nazareth in the Gospels thou shall love thy neighbor as
thyself as many philosophers like Sartor and Dostoevsky understood there's no
God all is permitted the central stipulation of this viewpoint is
without a tangible moral absolute God specifically the monotheistic God
humanity is left in a moral miasma of ethical oblivion and a volatile values
framework it would be like trying to do theoretical physics without mathematics
William Lane Craig recents accordingly in his apologetics book on God to say
that the Holocaust was objectively raw is to say that the Holocaust was raw
even though the Nazis who carried it out thought that it was right and and it
would still have been wrong even if the Nazis had won World War two and succeeded
in brainwashing or exterminating everybody who disagreed with them so that
everyone in the world thought that the Holocaust was right and good to say that
the Holocaust was objectively raw means that it's wrong regardless of the
outcomes of World War two the premise is that if there's no God then moral
values or duties are not objective in that sense and yet my unreasonable and
rebellious heart is still unfulfilled I don't think human divinity can be
reduced to a sentence, catchphrase, proposition, philosophical stipulation,
commandment or law. Tenets could be extrapolated from our understanding of
divinity for pragmatic or applicative sake i.e. Ten Commandments, Magna Carta,
Universal Declaration of Human Rights but instances of divinity don't encompass
all of its truth they only allude to its actuality our limited cognition knowledge
and language gategoal and human divinity the moment it's instantiated for
comprehension the ultimate catch-22 a celestial provocation that's making our
predicament rather comical it's this absurdity of living that makes life both
a tragedy and comedy I see this quandary unfold in my life every day from the
moment I wake up in the morning sometimes I'm an atheistic relativist and
other times I'm a spiritual being piously carrying out my divine duty it's
not that I don't see the logical contradiction in this way of living I
perfectly understand my folly but it's the most accurate way I can portray my
dilemma and I know I'm not the only one maybe human beings created philosophy to
deal with this spontaneous morality driven mainly by emotions that emerge in
life we need coherent providence for cosmic forlorness from a cold and
indifferent universe nevertheless our salvation does not lie in a simple
postulation i.e. I'm a Christian Muslim or Jew I'm a Buddhist or Hindu I'm an
atheist or skeptic etc we are too mercurial to be herald by mere label
I'll observe myself being bizarre by ruining a perfectly good week by doing
something that I hate which makes me miserable and self-loathing the label
I used to define my identity is unavailing and meaningless during these
times so I ask knowing exactly what or what not to do why does my it define my
conscience do otherwise it is naive to think we base our lives on a philosophical
proposition or some arbitrary religious or non-religious label ask yourself how
often do you do things you hate contemporary psychology may call this
self-destructive behavior but identifying its reality doesn't answer the
fundamental question why do human beings act out in this peculiar and
nonsensical way when we observe our lives in retrospect it seems clear that
rationality explains very little about our condition I'm yet to find a
quintessential rationalist even in my highly technical field of computer
science where people mainly deal with logical abstractions people remain true
to their nature I think this is why it's poignant to see modern society reduce
the human experience to pragmatic utilitarianism and carelessly disregard
any sense of the sublime therefore given that life resembles more a symphony or
story over an a priori culturalistic mechanism how do we deal with this
existential volatility at least for now I've concluded what's ultimately left
for us to do is to take a Kierkegaardian leap of faith according to the Sanford
Encyclopedia of Philosophy for Kierkegaard Christian faith is not a
matter of regurgitating church dogma it is a matter of individual subjective
passion which cannot be mediated by the clergy or by human artifacts faith is the
most important task to be achieved by a human being because only on the basis of
faith does an individual have a chance to become a true self this self is a
lifework which God judges for eternity it has taken me years to understand what
faith meant to human beings reading Kierkegaard at least shed some light on
the matter he uses Abraham from the book of Genesis and the modifical night of
faith in his book fear and trembling to expound how he viewed faith people are
unable to bear the martyrdom unintelligently jump off the pile and
choose instead conveniently enough the world's admiration of their proficiency
the true night of faith is a witness never a teacher and in this lies the
deep humanity in him which is more word than this foolish concern for others
wheel and wall which is honored under the name of sympathy but which is
really nothing but vanity the true night of faith is always absolute
isolation the false night is sectarian this sectarianism is an attempt to leap
away from the narrow path of the paradox and become a tragic hero at a cheap
price the tragic hero expresses universal and sacrifices himself for it the
sectarian punch in yellow instead of that has a private theater i.e. several
good friends and comrades who represent the universal just about as well as the
Beatles in the golden snuff box represents justice the individual of faith on
the contrary is the paradox is the individual absolutely nothing but the
individual without connections or pretensions this is the terrible thing
which a sectarian mannequin can't endure for instead of learning from this
terror that he's not capable of performing the great deed and then
plainly admitting it an act which I cannot but approve because it is what I
do the mannequin thinks that by uniting with several other mannequins he will be
able to do it but that is quite out of the question in the world of spirit no
swindling is tolerated the narrow passage to gold is a lonely journey it has to be
or else our faith is mine you can only have faith in our individual pilgrimage
and gold when I first came across as philosophy I became depressed I only
used to term dramatically as an extra word that likes community and enjoys a
good conversation preferably over a fine steak and some whiskey I remember
thinking why does arguably the most important journey of our life the one
to God have to be a lonely endeavor but then I understood living in faith is a
state of being be embodied regardless of our public proclamations it is the only
real identity we incarnate that's unconditionally of our own will because
every other identity gender race sexuality class etc is
inescapably feted by society culture biology and the objective world there's
only a subjective spiritual journey that transcends every other material identity
given to us by simply being alive therefore refusing to accept our
divide divine adventures loneliness and trying to find it through social
institutions or the predominant cultural zeitgeist of our times with only
corrupt its essence and exacerbate our understandable nihilistic cynicism however
we must not misunderstand this journey to be a despondent one around the end of
2017 I experienced a somewhat miracle in life despite all my inadequate season
flaws I made a conscious choice to embody faith I started not to see the
transcendent as a distant deistic reality but rather to see divinity in
mundane life or the Christian parlance treat everyone as God's children and
everything as God's creation I learned that living on faith took courage most
people think it takes courage to face death it doesn't that is inevitable
what requires true courage is the will to live I still face the same trials and
tribulations of life I did in 2017 albeit I found love in 2018 and that's
redemptive to one soul but my choice my lonely leap of faith miraculously rid me
of nihilistic cynicism notwithstanding the malevolence and suffering in being
recognized every day I doubt I can argue against anti-natalism David
Bennett has the verbal virtuosity and it an intellectual prowess that I don't
even remotely possess and yet I know the best case I can make against
anti-natalism is by how I live the faith I choose to embody is the antidote to
cynicism it's at least the best I can do
cynicism is the worst form of existence it doesn't help anybody nor is it a
remedy to anything it's neither pragmatic nor does it answer the deepest
grievances in the human heart a cynic doesn't want to live nor die but only
being a state of resentful non-existence a supercilious refusal to partake in
life being cynical is just cowardly a piece of animus an unheroic reaction to
life yes a lot can and probably will go wrong our passions could be fruitless
and lame every venture we start could end up in failure and possible and
possible ruin friends will disappoint us
unapologetically marriage could end in a better divorce our children might hate
us for a pathetic ineptness as parents love could break our heart we will
witness unjust suffering and we may even be partly responsible for us for its
subsistence during these lamentable moments helpless helplessness will
haunt our souls culture will turn eyes us and society will negate our
individuality nature will try to wipe us out of existence and there will be times
where we feel abandoned and alienated from a cold and dark universe apathetic
and indifferent to our feelings but somehow in spite of everything I said
it about living by faith vindicates all the ghastly anxiety-evoking horrors of
being I can only extrapolate from my journey in the last few years as that's
the only worthy story I can tell I found that faith allows the objective and
subjective to touch by revealing a phenomenological coherence to the
faithful it shows symphony in life and the drama that unfolds as we paradoxically
take part in it as both an audience and cast member faith shows how every
instance of being is meaningful both subjective and objectively faith is the
handmade enough love so we're left with no recalls but to embody faith
undergirded by relentless courage in every moment of life we should not think
of it as a another distant and anachronistic religious ritual being
faithful is an act of bravery for what it's worth I can sincerely say that I
try to consciously exercise faith in every aspect of my life career
relationships family how I treat strangers and even software engineering
I've learned its paramount nature has to be the reason religion is primarily
revealed to us through faith as it amalgamates reality like no other
I've humbled myself to this truth it's what Kerkakar understood about the
crucifixion of Jesus as he writes in the sickness unto death the opposite of sin
is not virtue but faith