Okay, this is really interesting because I was going to ask you before, and I wasn't even sure if I should ask this question because
Initially, I thought you were purely an analytical philosopher and then the more I read your work
I saw you mentioning Foucault. I saw you mentioning psychoanalysis. I was like, oh great. Now I could ask you this
What are your general views on psychoanalysis and
personally, I come more from the
continental psychoanalytic tradition. That's where
I'm most of my reading.
So getting to this conversation and then what's your general view on psychoanalysis and how it pertains to cognitive science
and AI, let's say, and does it have anything to say, anything useful to add to those fields?
So I would say that there's a kind of conventional scientist attitude of like,
isn't this all just nonsense? Like we've come up with better psychological theories since then. We have
science. Like why do we need psychoanalysis? Why are we reading these people from a hundred years ago?
And I think that's a view I used to hold.
I think my, I think partially I've updated because I think a lot of the
I think the overall quality of
Scientific or experimental psychology is lower than I used to think it was and I think in popular discourse
this corresponds to things like the replication crisis of like maybe a lot of these things can't actually
like whatever we're currently doing that we're calling psychological science is not actually producing very reliable results.
And I do have more respect for more like deep thinkers who are more generalists who think about a variety of things using various methodology,
not just scientific methodology. And so I haven't actually read very many of these people, but
broadly it seems like they have important ideas. It seems like it's probably worth people who are into psychology reading them.
I think that,
yeah, I think some of these have like very
like a kind of general psychological concepts that are possible to apply to lots of situations. There's things like the
ids, the ego, the super ego, and like the idea of repressed desires. There's things like
like the Lacanian
trichotomy between the psychotic, the neurotic, and the pervert. And
I think that there, they can be pretty useful models for thinking about a variety of things.
They're not quite at the level of science in the sense that it's like not enough of a theory that you can say like, here's exactly what it predicts. Here's it would falsify it.
But I think it's often fruitful to like think of a situation and apply some of these models to it and then at least be able to come up with something.
Like some interpretation of the situation that's like a starting point,
even if it's not like,
like, therefore, my interpretation is correct. It's like, therefore, I have an interpretation and I can think about like what that implies. Is it at all testable and so on?
Sure, sure. So on the note, Jessica, you know, you had another post called a critical,
agential account of free will and causation or free will causation of physics. And then you use, so the term agent, it's used across all your work, which makes sense, you know, if you're talking about AI and whatnot.
And what are your views? Because in psychoanalysis, we have what we call the subject, right? And the subject is a loaded term, even over from Khan, the German idealist use it, and then subject, it means many things, right?
Whereas the term agent, I think is more apt for conversations around AI and even perhaps cognitive science.
So, in your view, what differentiates a subject as to how it's used, let's say, psychoanalysis from an agent of as to how it's used in, let's say, game theory or even AI or cocci.
Okay, so I would say that I, to be clear, I haven't read a lot of the psychoanalyst, but in my mind, a major distinction is that the subject is primarily something like a world model.
It's a way of ontologizing the world and determining what is in the world and some idea of the self and how the self relates to the world. And I definitely think of Khan's philosophy as specifying what a subject is.
Like the idea of the a priori space and time isn't objective clock time, it's a kind of subjective timeline in which the sensory phenomena are organized and so on.
Whereas I would say that agent is more about, it does include a world model, but it especially focuses on action and values.
So an agent is capable of doing something, not just perceiving the world, and these actions are often for some purpose.
So in game theory, it would be to maximize a utility function.
And it, and I think in my post on critical agential metaphysics, it's, it's not so much about optimizing utility function so much as taking actions so as to do things such as test scientific theories, or operationalize them.
Instead of simply being like more like a passive observer.
Yeah, yeah, that makes sense.
Okay, on the note, you, in fact, I found you through this post you're a post on less room, a short conceptual explainer of Emmanuel Khan's recent.
And at the time I was reading a lot of Khan and I was not that I in any way I'm an expert on this but I couldn't believe how succinctly you've explained all of Khan's concepts because as you may know, the German idealists and the countries in general are notoriously very difficult to read.
So, okay.
Again, general question. What do you think modern cocci and AI can learn from, let's say, can't, and then the post content such as the German idealists, you know, hey girl Victor Schilling, all of them.
Do you think there's anything worthwhile to to get from these philosophers, or are they just, you know, artifacts of the past.
So I would say conch for sure. And I think I can specify that more so like I do think of conch as in some ways an AI and cognitive science person.
Before those were much of a thing.
Because what he's doing is he's saying there's this task of understanding the world in general, which seems like fairly unbounded.
Philosophy specifically, there might be a more bounded thing I can do here, which is determine what what is the cognitive machinery that the human subject uses to conceive of the world.
And if I can complete this task, then perhaps the the general task of understanding the world is mostly just iterations and things following from this rather than then like basically having to work out the foundations and new each time.
And so, when he's thinking about the the the subject.
There's, there's a notion of the a priori, which is which is certainly a concept using cognitive science and AI in terms of Bayesianism and I in the post I give some relationships between those and Bayesian theories.
One of it is like what what do you have to assume at the start before you even take in data and use those two test theories.
Like you, you have to have some machinery already in place for doing things like organizing perceptions into space and time.
You can't learn about time without already having time because time learning takes place in time.
That certainly would if if clarified that would have implications about AI because that would say something about what you have to put into an AI at the start in its mind for it to even be able to learn in the first place.
So in terms of ideas about things like like schemata, or, or like combining a concept, such as the cat with your visual field where you, you kind of see a splotch of orange and then you're like oh it's a cat.
That seems to have a lot in common with computer vision because computer visions about mapping a concept, like the concept of a cat to a visual field.
I wouldn't particularly say that that he's that like he knows how to solve a lot of these problems like computer vision but his work certainly raises a lot of them and like fairly over on early on even before they were computers.
So I think in part it might be useful as a sort of reference point of someone in the past thinking about a lot of the questions of how a mind works, and who's been commented on quite a lot by others.
Even before computers and so on.
I would say even more speculatively there might be things to learn about ontology from Kant in terms of things like like defining ontology in terms of things like space time and sensory fields, a phenomena might have utility if you if you want an AI to have a kind of ontology of
a world that you can talk to it in.
Then you might want it to have something like a 3D model of subjective space time that is somehow related to your 3D model of subjective space time, and have something like a common language for specifying objects I mentioned before the problem of,
if you wanted a paperclip maximizer how would you specify a paperclip and you might want to do it using a sort of Contian method where you think about like, like, like the paperclip in terms of doesn't have a location in space time.
What are its properties in terms of in terms of phenomena and like extension and so on.