So the other bit is and what I love about the book is this is also in a way sort of like a book on
on like social psychology because it's a lot on what laypeople believe and in fact being a layperson
myself I kind of had this belief too for the longest time which is I've always equated what we call
human language to reading and in the the blind story teller you state in page 203
if you don't mind me reading it you say many people think of reading as a process of visual
pattern recognition for example being able to consistently register the contrast between
symmetrical letters such as D and B if that is the case then it stands to reason that when reading
goes ori the culprit is a visual deficit but but in reality visual patterns are just a means to an
end which is language reading is a technology that gets you there so uh professor if you could
delineate what the difference between reading and languages uh that that would be great please
so there are two things we need to explain what is reading and how it differs from language
yes so the true theory what is the true science about and the second is what people think how this
all works so there is the scientific theory and there is the intuitive theory which happens to
be in disagreement and that's where we mess things up so um so there is a sense in which reading is
very different from language um I often start my psychology of language classes uh by working really
hard to disabuse not people of the notion that language and reading are the same thing they aren't
language is natural you take every child they will develop language if you don't expose them to
language they will grow one naturally even they're not exposed to a language um they do it naturally
they don't need language lessons uh reading is not like that so most children if you don't teach
them how to read explicitly they will never read there are tons of societies that they're doing
just well without reading and writing um not so for language so language is universal to all human
societies reading is not so they're divorced in this sense for sure nonetheless there is this
interesting property of human brains that the neuroscientist Danislas de Han has pointed out
which is when human brains come to invent a new system they don't invent it completely a new
but rather what they do is recycle existing systems that are innate and kind of repurpose
them for the new uh for this new purpose and the link between reading and language exactly
follows those lines so when you look at how reading systems are designed they could have been
completely divorced from language they could have been completely arbitrary but that's not the case
because the letters that we use for a system like a phobetic system like English correspond to
linguistic sounds for the most part um even in writing systems as in Mandarin it's true that there
are visual origins of the symbols that they call they also have semantic component but eventually
what they stand up for is also phonological sounds they spend they they stand for syllables
so it turns out that when uh people come to invent language they kind of design it on the
principles of how language works you can think about it in terms of human brains when they start
processing language they start with the phonology and then so when you perceive speech that the
first thing that you get is the sound structure of language and from there you proceed to syntax
and so forth so it's like to go on the linguistic highway so to speak in the brain you need to start
by having some phonological code so if you're trying to hijack the same highway to create
reading you better start by doing by encoding phonology as well and that's how explain the
correspondence between how reading works and how language works reading as a system is taking the
language or or hijacking a component of the language system and repurposing it to for a new
technology and that is why all reading systems that we know encode some phonological units at
some level it doesn't necessarily need to be at the level of phonemes it could be syllables but
there is also some phonological component there is ton of research that shows that when you and I
read well I'm not a native speaker but when I read in my language and you read in your language
even though we read silently we will automatically extract all this phonological component as
integral part of the reading process so you think about reading as a visual affair it's something
that happens only in your eyes of course it begins with the eyes but it looks like it invariably
goes through the phonological system at some point or else reading does not work as it should
so you must get some aspects of the phonology of what you read how do we know that because if
you get two words that have the same phonology such as rose the flower and roses in two rows of
chairs people confuse them all the time even if you'll have ROZE which is not the word people will
also confuse them and using the proper experiments you can show that it's really the phonology that
that confuses them which shows that people have consulted this information or else they would
not have been confused so the point about showing how we stumble is to show how reading actually
works and the fact that it actually works is using phonology it's using this part of language
so that's the real theory of reading and we also know that when you know that the ability to perceive
sounds is so it's not just phonology but also speech when the ability to perceive speech sounds
is impaired this is a characteristic of dyslexia so people with dyslexia have problem with perceiving
speech sounds now that's not that what laypeople think so if you ask a layperson you know johnny
can't read here you know he's a six year old and he can't read what do you think is wrong with him
and invariably people tell you there is something that's wrong with their eyes and if they think
that there is something that's wrong with billy because of jimmy whatever i guess and that if the
problem is congenital which we know that's the case in dyslexia that that um it is a congenital
disorder people invariably think the problem can only be in the eyes it can't be the
abstract phonological thing um this arises from this intuition that people hold that what's
we hold innately so if you know that the problem is congenital that he was born with that then it
must be somewhere in their body the people don't think just genes they think like in the eyes in
the ears it can be something that is abstract that doesn't make sense that the ability to so what
dyslexia really is about is in part the mechanism that allow you to map letters to sound and which
is an abstract kind of cognitive mechanism and people have trouble recognizing that something
like that could possibly be um involved or or or impaired innately so this is unfortunate because
um it's uh first because people misunderstand what dyslexia is all about and and that's a problem
because um if you think that you know if you have a child and you think that the only signal of
dyslexia is switching letters then you will find fail to identify and and and um help these children
with uh early as they need to as you need to um but indirectly it also tells you some something
about how we think about what is innate and what is inateness and um uh and explain some of the
other biases that I've shown in this book uh that show how our misconception about what
about how what what is innate uh lead us to this crazy conclusion that what we know cannot possibly
have an innate basis