Hey everyone, welcome to yet another episode of the interval and podcast and
today I'm gonna read out guiding axiom number five which is a part of this sub
series that I've been doing where I've been reading out these axioms that I
wrote for my newsletter the unhappy man links down below in the description and
as I was writing down these axioms I realized I'm in fact setting up a
framework for sounds like someone just got shot outside that's fine we don't
live in America this is really a people don't get shot here
came back to it when I was laying down these axioms I realized that oh yeah
this is a framework for all of my creative work if it only makes sense to
read them out in this podcast given that this podcast is a part of my creative
work I'm sorry if that sounds pretentious and also it allows me to have a
bit of structured thinking and writing I think is the best way to do that today's
axiom axiom number five is undoubtedly my favorite one it's never fallen love
with your suffering or well I said never fall in love with suffering as a
category and the reason it's important for me is because from all the axioms
I've laid down in many ways these axioms are an antidote to my flaws or things
that I see are shortcomings in my character be it morally spiritually
existentially whatever you want to call it and that's why I'm writing down
these axioms so that I don't let these shortcomings in my character of who am
as a person impact the work I do and falling in love with suffering my god
I am I'm kind of ashamed how how vain it is when I really understood this
concept thanks a lot to Slavoj Zizek I think it's reading his stuff and
listening to his lectures that really influenced me as to why it's a bad idea
to fall in love with suffering and most of us subconsciously or unconsciously do
this therefore it's it's important to be cognizant of this phenomena without
further ado enough of a prelude let's get to the axiom so yes as I said it's
the unhappy man guiding axiom number five never fall in love with suffering and
of course I've got this painting by Goya this is an interesting one of cryos
crucified this is before I think he went through his face of depression but of
course suffering is very much connected to the archetypal story of the western
collective unconscious let's say of the crucifixion that's why I decided to
pick this any kirkard guardian is familiar with the captivating admission
in either or my melancholy is the most faithful mistress I have known what
wonder then that I love her in return most of us of the existentialist elk
have fully bought into the dogma of the depressed yet perspicacious philosopher
for us all great truths lack profundity if not written in a shopenhari and
pessimism about our condition the misery of existence is what those with great
intelligence and deep hearts have come to see to not see this verity is nothing
but naivety at least this is the bullshit we tell ourselves to be depressed or
suffer needlessly as far from the romantic beauty we give to it none of it
makes one so deeper and inspires philosophically penetrating poetry or
the staff skin literature in fact when I read my nonsensical journaling written
during the low points I see it as nothing but vain egotistical pabula which
is why I stopped journaling it's a waste of time and better drinking away your
sorrows this is a joke for them but beyond a stentatious vanity we all dwell
with our misery purely to feel something we often deliberately seek
pathological relationships only because the melodramatic pain of love reminds
us of our humanness better to feel pain than nothing at all
OS Dostoevsky wrote if he human beings does not find means he will contrive
destruction and chaos will contrive suffering of all sorts only to gain
his point notes from underground and of course being willing to suffer through
love particularly romantic tells us of our goodness of our higher virtues in
being authentically self-sacrificial for another such as why Nietzsche wrote
ultimately it is a desire not the desire that we love your granival I must
admit that I am ashamed of how pathetic we are as a species having said that I
see why modern people lust after suffering as they are given the
impossible choice of contrived pseudo happiness in the form of new age self
help which you all know is rife with empty patitudes I bullshit and the
finger wagging pull yourself up by your bootstraps heartless American stoicism
it seems that we're stuck in this binary the modern age is an era of nihilism so
as Nietzsche the man who explored the symptom to his ultimate road read from
a distant planet the majestical script of our earthly existence would perhaps
seduce the reader to the conclusion that the earth was the aesthetic planet
parks alone an outposts of discontented arrogant and nasty creatures who
harbored a deep disgust for themselves for the world for all life and hurt
themselves as much as possible out of pleasure in hurting probably their only
pleasure the passage above is from a skating critique of the aesthetic ideal
the mode of life he pillories has little to do with religious asceticism but
say but rather a cultural zeitgeist despite the characteristic phenomenon
being cross cultural for instance he would be as equally contemptuous of the
contemporary postmodern stoicism of the ryan holy types or neoliberal western
buddhism that turns a blind eye to the problems of the world and decides to
inflict suffering on oneself for the pleasure of it ie cold showers fasting
crossfit etc irrespective of religious connotations all such modes of being
manifest a drive towards the ascetic ideal so his sentiments are apt to any
pseudo suffering we create purely to inject artificial meaning into our barren
desolate veins whether in the form of modern self-help cults with their
unending self-flagellation or a morbid romantic relationship that's conspicuously
making everyone suffer we desire meaning perhaps the intrinsic human reality is
meaninglessness and the incompleteness of life therefore we ought to be cognizant
of how we respond to our predicament and one can only live authentically once
his datum is confronted in my view the only true antidote to meaninglessness
or nihilism of our culture is love but that's a whole other essay or book
listen on suffering on suffering as a psychological phenomenon i find affinity
with the zhezhekyan sentiments on the matter footnote influenced by zhak lakon's concept of
joystones and the Freudian death drive zhezhek made the following point in in his books and
lectures paraphrasing don't fall in love with your suffering never presume that your suffering is
in itself proof of your authenticity renunciation of pleasure can easily turn into pleasure of
renunciation itself back to the essay pleasure never satiates us as there's only so much of it
one can enjoy therefore we seek the pleasure beyond pleasure and willfully suffer for an
ostensibly noble course but in reality this is our yearning to fill the void in life we hope to
overcome the abyss with a deeper spiritual meaning sometimes with a touch of romanticism as we see
in fascism that's elusive for us in the technological age footnote read the question concerning
technology essay by martin heidegger to understand what this age entails when i mean this age i mean
the current age we live in or the technological age to be more specific i'll read that again that's
elusive for us in the technological age where to test have skis this may man has become nothing
but a piano key martyrdom for instance typifies his drive within us despite the words of tomology
a martyr is not a purely religious individual or some fundamentalist fanatic to a certain extent
everyone sees themselves as a martyr from a self-sacrificial parent and a serious employee
working 15 hours a day at a trendy postmodern startup to a nurse working in palliative care
to the martin us the pain of sacrifice and duty gives us that pleasure when the so-called
worldly pleasures generally a derided term but it shouldn't be are inadequate footnote
pleasure which could be misunderstood by how it's colloquially used in the carnal hedonic sense
may not be the aptus term for this instance but i've decided to stick with it since i'm speaking
in Freudian nomenclature i'll reread that sentence because i feel jumping to the footnotes tend to
break the flow of things but i kind of have to read out the footnotes because they are related
to what i'm writing to the martyr in us the pain of sacrifice and duty gives us that pleasure
when the so-called worldly pleasures generally a derided term but it shouldn't be are inadequate
or as G. K. Chesterton wrote pessimism is not in being tired of evil but in being tired of good
despair does not lie in being wary of suffering but in being wary of joy the everlasting man
of course none of this implies we shouldn't take upon actual responsibility in life and
carry the world's burdens nor does it mean above all that love is free of a sword and fire
Alan Burjou observed this is in his book in praise of love by the way it's a great little book
that i've been recommending to many people it's a lovely read reading that again Alan Burjou
observed that our culture is atypically in trying to sell a safety first concept of love
it is love comprehensively ensured against all risks you will have love but will have assessed
the prospective relationship so thoroughly will have selected your partner so carefully by
switching online by obtaining of course a photo details of his or her tastes date of birth
horoscope signs etc and putting it all in the mix you can tell yourself this is a risk-free option
but he fights back against such safetyism i'm convinced that love cannot be a gift given on
the basis of a complete lack of risk the mythic french online dating service approach reminds
me of the propaganda of the american army when promoting the idea of smart bombs and zero dead
wars in praise of love so we ought to pick up battles and be cognizant of the difference
between sacrifice for higher life-sustaining ideals of love justice etc that bring forth
genuine good and on the other hand suffering for the love of suffering itself the latter is
nothing but vanity and exhibitionism any blind renunciation of pleasure and seeking of suffering
becomes a kind of Machiavellian narcissism worse than what you'd see from a typical more explicit
trump-like narcissists as the former is the ultimate wolf in sheep's clothing
ergo as jujek candidly tells us never fall in love with your suffering suffering as a category
but i'd go a step further and assert never fall in love with suffering as a category period firstly
because it's simply un-pragmatic suffering doesn't make anyone's life better and has no
ennobling qualities in itself secondly and more importantly the fixation of suffering has imbued
unspeakable amounts of evil kiss in point i'm disgusted by how post-modern neoliberals that's
most of us fetishize poverty we implicitly believe there's some deepfound wisdom in the suffering
of the poor that those exploited in the mica mines in india for extortionate makeup products
have a profundity to their souls that we degenerate westerners have lost or we would
salivatingly cite an outdated statistic about bangladeshi people being happier
than rich americans footnote who says happiness is the purpose of life or that it's even something
worth measuring it doesn't matter that they're happier if the rapacious fashion industry aloves
for tragedies like the rana plaza collapse in such moments happiness is an unethical category
it's out of the question but isn't all of this romanticization of poverty at a nonsense isn't it
yet another example of the aforementioned suffering fetish this time despicably manifested in the
political domain i doubt any of us unpretentiously listen to a poor person except to an ideological
lens which tells us what to hear over what the person's truly saying personally whenever i've
spoken to someone struggling to survive and barely making ends meet i see nothing but despondency
pain and resentment not the pristine goodness in the souls of poor folk would prescribe on them
not the wisdom of the heart we'd read about in a charles dickens novel of course dickens knew
this better than all of us i partially blame the misappropriation of the crucifixion for the
fetishism of suffering i'm not surprised as someone deeply enamored by christ the crucifixion
is an infinite superhistorical event happening in the eternal now footnote
i borrow this term from poldtelics book eternal now which encapsulate most of his superlative
theology i highly recommend that book he probably gives the best description of god that i've
ever read in my life and i think he's right he's correct to describe god as the ground of all being
actually i say meditating on it has changed my life or more accurately given me a new one
and i shall expand on the matter in later essays in any case crucified christ is only
part of the christian narrative and we replace the whole with a fragment at great peril we ought to
never forget christ also resurrected as bizarre as that sounds notwithstanding one's religious
beliefs be it atheist or spiritual but not religious all of us think of ourselves as a
suffering christ carrying a cross footnote to understand why i recommend starting with
tom holland's dominion and slavojic's fragile absolutes because as don cupid wrote nobody in
the west can be holy non christian you make hold yourself non christian but the dreams you dream
are still christian dreams since we even migrants to the west like myself dream in christianity
we ought to never rush into glamorizing the suffering christ and instead be searingly
skeptical of our underlying humanistic intentions behind the vinnia of self-sacrificial love
perhaps christ was thinking my dad's a malevolent sedomasticistic son of a bitch who's thrown me
into gratuitous suffering because of a twisted cosmic jurisprudential atonement he's conjured
up ex nihilo at least this is what theologians like william lane craig tell us if christ was the
gold man then for him to say ally ally lamar sabustani my god my god why have you forsaken me
is an unsurprising remark for one to make while being crucified and here as jujek points out
momentarily god himself becomes an atheist it's the negation and even hatred of god
e.g. book of job that makes christianity unique from any other religion and makes our culture
outlandish footnote martin scorsese's silence explores this phenomenon well with the modern
flavor of man's helpless frustration at god and gk chesterton's orthodoxy encapsulates his idea
best from any modern theology i've ever read we see in christianity the utmost palpable story
of existence human suffering can be so unbearable that even god once he comes down to us realizes
he can't bear it and loses faith ergo the separation from god is a part of divinity itself
and it's only the christian god that knows the alienation of being human i go on these detours
only to explicate my view that suffering in itself has no higher soul maturing virtue
we don't have to artificially create and fetishize it as pain tragedy and our happiness are already
concomitant with the vicissitudes of life so despite this newsletter being called the unhappy
man i shall never fall in love with unhappiness and suffering if i ever do i will stop writing
thanks for watching as i said the link to this uh essay is down below in the description if you
do prefer reading it please do check it out but i shall see you in the next one cheers