We're talking late 70s over to early 80s. A crucial period actually for computers in many
regards, yes. There was definitely a British's best Britain first purchasing policy, either
for government institutions like radar establishments, like the police, all this kind of stuff,
and particularly for educational establishments. The feeling was computers are expensive,
so if we can spend a lot of money it might as well be fell back into the British economy
by buying British. Certainly applied to universities, one or two were allowed to escape. I think the
University of Newcastle on the computer science front was allowed to have an IBM, so of course
was the University of Cambridge. Can't remember what happened at Oxford.
It was a way for me to find out by the back door about the advantages in a way of sharing a
hardware platform with not just other universities but other government institutions. And in one
of the previous videos I've talked about how we only felt able to use ALGOL 68 as a teaching
language because that well-known government institution blessed them, the Royal Radar
establishment, that actually put a huge amount of effort into setting up a very good ALGOL 68
compiler. And of course it had to be on ICO machinery, they were a government establishment,
so were we, so we benefited from that a lot. How did you get into UNIX? You went over to the
States didn't you? Can you tell me about that? Yes, I was true. I went over to the States in 1978
for the whole calendar year and visited in short order and it was all highly educational, a visit
to Oklahoma State University where they'd written an ALGOL 68 compiler, so given my interest in
those days that was a no-brainer. But I then thought no, no, if I'm going to be away for a year
I want the California experience and so I finagled my way into doing some teaching at UCLA of course
in Los Angeles. But also in the Cal State system, Cal State Northridge is a well-known California
state thing and I did, I lectured all sorts of computer things, I taught FORTRAN in Oklahoma
and so on. It was weird actually that in some ways at Nottingham we were a little bit ahead
of the curve there because before I left we'd taken our first tentative steps into getting this
thing called UNIX which enabled you on a underpowered PDP 11 to sort of run your own programming
experience, multi-user but only on dumb terminals, multi-user multi-tasking operating system,
hopelessly underpowered machinery but it sort of worked and this was, must have been about 76
when we bought, first of all a PDP 1105 just to get used to having our own computer of some sort
could do a similar programming but I think just more or less as I got in the plane from America
my colleagues told me that no we're going to get that upgraded to a PDP 1135 as quickly as possible
and that when we do we will be ready to receive this operating system called UNIX done by Bell Labs
and people said to me Dave you'll find just like why did a radar establishment have to support your
compiler you'll now be saying why does a telephone company have to be the people that provides me
with a little operating system that I feel happy with and it was, it was as Yogi Berrow once said
like deja vu all over again, okay I'm going to say wow you know you're ahead of us we want to go to
UNIX we can't get approval all this kind of stuff so when I came back 1979 very cold winter
all that it really was a liberation to know that while we might have to rely on the computing
centre for a lot of bulk teaching and running programs nevertheless we could start to do
our own thing on PDP 11's with an eye to the future but even so we couldn't on a PDP 1135
give a bulk service to our COMPSI undergrads we continued running ALGOL 68 on ICL machinery
with a huge extended overlap with us getting UNIX because we couldn't become self-hosting on UNIX
or have enough big powerful machines until well after this era we were made very aware
that we were getting this for a few hundred dollars because it came from Bell Labs Bell Labs was a so
called regulated monopoly and that meant they were caught in the crossfire from everywhere
they must not be seen to be using their massive leverage and obscene telephone bills
to squash little startup telcos they must not get in the way of IBM
because there was a suspicion that you know when people said to Bell I was well what are you doing
for the public good they thought it was a nice cool idea to say look we've got basically a
computer science research department we're not a computer company but these researchers
it really was a bit like Malvern's radar defense establishment we are not a computing company
absolutely not but we have developed some software that universities might find interesting
so we're proposing for the public good to virtually give away this software if anybody's
interested and it's a start and IBM won't see it as a threat so we're all right you can get hold
of this so long as you are a bona fide degree giving institution you can get hold of this UNIX
you must have of course a pdp11 got to keep America's balance of payments in the black and it must be
at least a pdp1135 not the most minimal you could get if you do that this UNIX will get you started
in the great world of multi-user on simple terminals you can do your own thing you'll
run out of steam after about four or five users but nevertheless it's all yours so we
cheerfully signed up for this and this as I say it was back in 1979 it's all about to happen
version seven of UNIX I think we did somehow get hold of the previous one version six
but serious usage started with version seven to find out more about this version seven that we
were getting how did you find out let me be boring and oldy and say yet again there was no internet
there were no web pages to tell you about this there was not even email you had to send out posters
to departments you had to use letters you could send faxes right and you had to say
we are the UK UNIX user group principally populated by representatives from computer science
departments in UK universities we are almost all of us absolutely long to have UNIX we have
persuaded the American master UNIX user group and AT&T the ultimate owners of Bell Labs who ran
all the patents and licensing they're going to come over and tell us how to get licensed
for an academic use only licensed for UNIX and what's it all about and it was a superb chat shop
and ideas swap shop as it were enjoyed it hugely the star of the show was a visitor from AT&T
Paterson licensing Frank J. Riffle Jr. I remember his name and oh boy did he have the job from hell
trying to keep everybody happy and he said I want to license you all you're wonderful you know
we love universities and I'm in charge of Paterson licensing but I got to warn you you must not do
any commercial usage with this it is purely for degree giving teaching only right and he kept on
muttering to himself there were a lot of gray areas and it's my job to stamp them out and what a
heck of a job it was he said just remember you must be a bona fide degree giving university
institution then you will be licensed no others a hand goes up from the audience a guy I got to
know quite well later on but he really was the odd man out hand goes up and said well how about me
you've licensed me for version six but I'm not at the university where are you from sir and he said
Marcus Gray this guy's name was he said I'm just a college I'm pre-university you know from
basically we concentrate from 11 to 18 I'm Marlborough College I'm a public school now I
think even the Americans know that there's nothing more badly named than an English public school
it is not available to the poor and the needy as it probably should be or was originally no
some public schools are so expensive you need serious money to attend them principally Eaton
is the most famous but Marlborough College isn't far behind I mean the tuition fees at Marlborough
College will make your eyes water so this guy said no no I'm not I'm pre-university I'm Marlborough
College but sir over here you know most colleges are like universities and Marcus said no it's not
the case with me and riffle was getting more and more ruffled that's a joke and said sir let me
try and summarize are you trying to tell me that you are more or less a very expensive version of
what I would call a high school and Margaret said that's what I'm about to say yeah that's roughly
right he just looked at Margaret and said sir you should not have been licensed and he didn't say
but in parentheses I could hear it going on in the background oh boy somebody's going to be in deep
trouble when I get back to Murray Hill New Jersey he said sir you should not have been licensed but
Frank J riffle is a man of his word I will not take your license away sir truly it did change
everything and I do remember very well we had a lot of conversations at the UK units group saying
those guys at Bellab's are just so good the two of them obviously Dennis and Ken we've
talked about them many a time they've invented the C language for system implementation they've
developed unix and it does things sensibly and this is absolutely great aren't we lucky I thought
as a community to have them being on our side and I did think I wonder if they'll ever get any
recognition from the ACM shall we say about what they've done and I was very pleased it took till
1983 I think but eventually so many academics in the US and all over the world were using unix that
Dennis and Ken were given the ACM Turing Award it was actually awarded to them in 84 it was
won and achieved in 83 so in 1984 they had to give a talk about what their work meant
and normally when you write a paper to go with your presentation you thank everybody which you did
but then you go on to say here's how unix came about here's the nuts and bolts of what it's
like to really run it we didn't get that at all we've got thank yous from Ken in cryptic terms
but very heartfelt to a lot of people so he said I now just want to point out something to you
effectively you've got something here where we you see as a system programming language
so the operating system is written in a high-level language have you any idea the problems that is
going to open up to the potential flaws security holds let me just demonstrate one of these to you
you'll be amazed and amused and I mean you know what standards we have on computer file we don't
swear so I'll allow myself to say that one of the rather celebrated people that we're going to
point you at in the next video just described Ken's contribution as a total effing bombshell
and he wasn't wrong a lot of people couldn't understand why it was a bombshell but it really
really is and I'd like to do my best to explain to you just how what a fundamental earthquake
this caused once people understood what he was trying to say a few seconds or half a second of
time then give him a half and then give her a little bit and just go round and round the people who
wanted to do some kind of computing and because computers were even the signal is moving in so
the speed of those pulses tell us the rate we know which direction it is because we know which
roll is coming from and we can look at those