We're live. Oh, okay. Good. That's fine. All right, everybody. Welcome to another episode of the Break the Rules live stream
I'm your host, Lev Polyakov, and we are here today
again with Dr.
Jason Reza Giorgiani
PhD it is a great honor as always to have you here my friend
We are going to be talking about your latest book Philosophy of the Future as well as talking about what's currently going on within the
political realm and I'm sure that there is a way that we can
Bring those two things together because I personally think that they are very much
Interrelated and of course if you guys have not read the Dr.
Giorgiani's books yet first of all I highly recommend you go into the description right now and
Get yourself a copy of the latest book as well as look at Prometheus and Atlas lovers of Sophia
So so many different books Iranian Leviathan the list goes up Prometheism
So you are going to be
Extremely pleased if this is your first time ever discovering Dr. Giorgiani and his wonderful work and
With that I first want to ask
Dr. Giorgiani about the Prometheus
Titan project however things go in with that
So please let us know and once again like comment subscribe
Super chat ten dollars minimum today and let's go for it. Dr. Giorgiani. You've got the floor
It's a pleasure to be on your show again Lev as always
So last time I think it was the last time that I was on BTR
I introduced the American Colossus project to build a monument to Prometheus on Alcatraz Island in San Francisco Bay and
We talked about the sculpture in general terms and we also went into
What I described as an NFT project at that point really it's not an NFT project
It's more like a digital raffle that will use NFT technology and that's going to involve a nationwide treasure hunt with clues embedded in these in these
Raffles and with very compelling
Aesthetic imagery and so on and so forth
So we discussed that a bit last time. I wanted to give viewers some updates regarding the Colossus project
Some rather significant updates
We are really moving we're working hard and moving at breakneck speed here on this project
It's definitely moving forward. We have found a sculptor
Fantastic sculptor who is an uber Nietzschean
Promethean in the spirit of his work and I think I had mentioned last time I was on that the kind of
Fash wave Greco-Roman type sculptures that you see as 3d renderings that are on the website of americancolossus.org
Right now that they're really placeholders and that the sculpture itself will be more sophisticated in terms of its aesthetics
I think I did touch on that well
You can get a much clearer sense of that now because our sculptor will be a gentleman by the name of fen de Villiers
And you can go to his website a fen de Villiers
and
he
has a fascinating idea of
Retracing the history of Western aesthetics within the context of an overarching style of modernism
So in a lot of the works that he has up on his website right now and his current sculpture portfolio
You can see projects that have a kind of archaic aesthetic
reiterated within the context of modernism
But as I understand it fen is interested in moving now more toward exploring classicism
But again within the context of modernism
So probably the sculpture that winds up being erected on Alcatraz will have somewhat of an art deco feel to it a kind of
classical modernist
Archeo-futuristic hybrid
that you know
One saw some examples of during the zenith of the art deco era
And I think that's very
Consonant with the spirit of Prometheus
Because there's a kind of you know renaissance
fusion of
Art qua craft with craft qua technology in that aesthetic in particular
It's also a very American aesthetic if you ask me
I mean some of the greatest American cities New York included of course
were predominantly built in the art deco style and you know
That was the historical moment when America wound up becoming the leading nation on the planet
So
I think that's a very positive development
And if you're going to listen to some of fen's interviews with various podcasters
You can see that
In terms of his worldview
He is the perfect man for the job. He actually has his own manifesto his own aesthetic manifesto
And I think in a lot of ways it dovetails with
With our own vision with the vision of Prometheus. I'm certainly
It's that's one. Yeah, it's a very interesting that
Fen is being a part of this
I remember first reading about him in men's world magazine
And I do see there being a convergence as well as a divergence
Apart as far as what you're doing and what let's say, you know bronze age pervert and people like that have been up to
Yes, well, look, there is a certain atmosphere which we will we will come around to discussing today, right?
A certain atmosphere that's been created by the left, which has gone full retard
and
that's going to necessitate a reaction to a certain extent and you know, what
What is necessary in order to?
Regain our footing and
Prevent a civilizational collapse
Maybe somewhat different from what I would believe to be ideal
But we're never going to get to any kind of an ideal
Promethean society as I might envision it if our civilization is is taken under by these leftists and social justice warriors
so there is a kind of a degree of reaction that's necessary and
You know for many reasons I think you know fend is certainly the right man for the job and and it's a positive thing that you know his
That he has connections with those circles
Because we are going to need to solicit their support and we need as broad a coalition as possible
to stand a chance in
you know, basically not just saving but but
but
resuscitating our civilization and
Kindling a second renaissance of the west. So that's a very positive development for the classes project, but there's another
Development that in some ways I see as equally positive and that's that
We are going to make a tv series
That traces the making of the colossus
And it's going to involve stunning visuals
initially 3d renderings but ultimately a tracing of the
process that leads to the construction of the colossus itself
And we found the perfect director for this tv series
It's a it's a series that
Through this director and the work that she's done
Will likely also have very significant high-level distribution and while I can't reveal, you know
The name of this person as of yet. I can say that
She is absolutely the perfect director for the project
really strong sharp woman who
shares a lot of our vision and
Who frankly is just a really cool person who I look forward to working with over the coming years
And I also think that it's great to you know, finally have a woman in a prominent place in this project
Do you see her in a way as being your uh,
Promethea if you will
Well, I don't know that, you know, she I don't know that she would want to be put in any such a position, but she's certainly
uh a more than competent director with a
deeply shared
vision and orientation
and
A person who I think it's going to be an absolute pleasure to work with over the coming years
And I will be working closely with her because she's going to basically trace the entire process and make a historical record
So, uh, I was uh reading and I finished your amazing latest book philosophy of the future
And what I noticed is that it did require me to have a certain bits of knowledge from all the other books that you've read
In order to in a way try and complete the puzzle
That is your latest one because you throw a lot of references
Not that people need to specifically read all your other books to enjoy this one
But it definitely helps to be well acquainted with what happened in the past as far as certain questions that I
always had in my mind as far as
in Iranian leviathan, whether it was the
um, uh, the persians, uh, the dynasty that created islam or whether it was these nephilim
Like that is a very interesting thing for me to, uh,
Digest as far as what exactly is the truth where you are playing the role of the trickster
And how exactly that's going to lead to the conclusions that you wanted to lead to
I don't know if that's a good place to start
But uh, let me know like where exactly you would be interested in
In a way, frankly, I'd say it's not a good place to start
I'd say it's kind of getting lost in the weeds and I would want to push back a little bit on your general characterization because
Yeah, you're right that in terms of some very specific questions like what you just articulated
It's helpful to have read some of my other works
but
That's not the main objective of philosophy of the future philosophy of the future has as its aim
a
general introduction of the reader to the fundamental concepts of my philosophical project
Or it can be read as a summary conclusion of my philosophical project
But in any case, what's most important about this book are the central ideas ideas novel ideas that i've developed
Like being bound for freedom spectral revolution world state of emergency phenomenal authorization
Uh and aero sophia. These are you know the the core of the book
In terms of specific
Theses that i've argued in various texts. Yeah, there are brief references to them here
And they're and the reader is also directed to the other books of mine where these
Theses are advanced with more detailed argumentation. So actually the book also functions as a kind of
Uh, like index or lexicon
For my entire corpus where in any given chapter
There are references to other books that i've written if the reader wants more detailed information
Regarding, you know, such and such an argument or thesis
But it's the conceptual structure of my philosophical work as a whole that's being really showcased by this book
Albeit, I also have to add that there is a rather striking conclusion to this book the last chapter
um is a very
dangerously revealing
document which
includes some
lengthy quotations from a
Journal that I wrote around about the age of
23 24
And it shows you the matrix for my entire philosophical project
And what what it is or who it is that really inspired it
As far as a phenomenal authorization goes that is what i'm primarily talking about when it comes to these various references to
You having certain let's say mixes of truths with noble lies
And i'm still trying to understand how exactly this phenomenal authorization would work
Uh, could you possibly guide us through that?
Sure, look the basic idea because I want to stay here with with you know, uh
Large structures and and you know general, you know themes here
Uh, the basic idea behind phenomenal authorization
Develop certain threads from out of the philosophical work of Nietzsche
Heidegger
Wittgenstein
Um, I'd say those are the primary ones also to an extent
Also to an extent it develops certain notions in the work of charles fort fort who was not a philosopher, but who had some very interesting
Epistemological ideas in the course of his study of the paranormal in the early 20th century
And and and to a lesser extent, you know the the philosophy of science of thomas kuhn
And of paul fair robin is also relevant here
But mainly coming from out of Nietzsche
Heidegger and wittgenstein
The idea is this
The and and by the way, heraclitus was incredibly important both to Nietzsche and to uh heidegger
And I would say that the ontology and and uh
And germinal epistemology of heraclitus is also very much in the background here, right?
So the idea is this that
The modern representationalist conception of truth in other words truth as veritas
Where there's an objectively existent structure of reality out there and that
What it means to ascertain knowledge meaning truths about things
Is for us to be able to construct the representational statements in our consciousness
That propositionally refer
To states of affairs in the world and are either accurate representations of those states of affairs or are inaccurate meaning their false propositions
Right, that's the basic conception of truth that began to be developed in the epoch of Descartes
Uh in large part, um as a consequence of the of Descartes dualistic ontology
and it ultimately culminated in uh the representational symbolic logic of like vietnam russell
and the early ludwig vittgenstein
and vittgenstein
Infamously deconstructed that having been the paragon of it himself in the tractatus logical philosophicus
vittgenstein turned on that whole school including his mentor russell
And he deconstructed this representationalist conception of truth in ways that oddly enough
Completely converged with heidegger's
Hermeneutics because these guys had no connection with each other whatsoever
They come from completely different trajectories in the history of philosophy
And yet they converge and how do they converge? Well, they both wind up saying that
Our phenomenological experience of the world in other words the way in which we experience phenomena
And the way in which the world has any meaning for us
Is a function of language
So it's not that there's any objective reality outside our minds and that our minds
ascertain truth by adequately reflecting an objective reality
It's that our subjectivity and what we take to be the objectivity of the world
our relative phenomena
Constructed deconstructed and reconstructed from out of how we use language
And when they're talking about language in this case, they mean it in the ancient greek sense of logos in other words
there is a tapestry of meaning
That is primordial in terms of our experience of phenomena in the world
And it's through this logos that chaos becomes cosmos
so the chaos that that
The chaos that proceeds our consciously processed experience
Becomes a structured array namely a cosmos
through logos
And in this relation between these three terms
chaos and cosmos cosmos coming to be through chaos being processed by logos
There's also a fourth term which is psyche
in other words
Consciousness has integral to that process which we see in quantum physics
and so in an interesting way
What verner heisenberg pointed to in his book physics and philosophy
Which is one of the great, you know texts and I guess what you could call philosophy of physics
What heisenberg
Hitler's nuclear scientist
Points out in that book about quantum theory in terms of the integral role of consciousness
In constituting a structured
World from out of the chaos that is superposition on a quantum scale
and
Which which heisenberg explicitly discusses in that text with reference back to heraclitus and heraclitus is conception of logos
All of that is already implicit
In the ontology and epistemology that heidegger was developing and that bickenstein oddly enough also wound up
Arriving at by a completely different trajectory. And so i'm taking these ideas and synthesizing them and augmenting them
and
using the paranormal
as
an empirical
Let's say raw material
or convenient set of examples
to illustrate
why
The world works this way. I'm being very careful not to say why why reality, you know is this way because the whole point is that
What we take to be reality
objectively
And how we understand ourselves subjectively are co-constructed from out of this interrelationship
between
chaos
logos cosmos and psyche i
describe these four as
ontologically equa primordial
It's a term coming from heidegger equally primordial meaning like the four causes in Aristotle
None of these is more fundamental than the other they represent the kind of fourfold causality
That structures our experience of the world and so okay, so that's the basis
for understanding what phenomenal authorization is because
What that implies
is that
We live in something like a story
We live in a tapestry of meaning in an account a narrative
There is a metanarrative structure to the cosmos itself
And what that suggests is that the world can be written and rewritten
And if you look at some of the more bizarre and distressing
Paranormal phenomena that seem to involve the manipulation of timelines
Or the use of some kind of time travel technology, whether it's
purely mechanical or whether it's actually psychical like remote viewers
Going back to the past and using telekinesis to influence past events to therefore rewrite
Their presence the present that they came from right or to rewrite potential futures
Whether it's entirely mechanical technology or whether it's psychical or whether it's some psychotronic combination thereof
When you look at these kinds of things that are possible
You realize that we live in a revisible world
And it's rewritable the way that the story is rewritable now the thing though is that not everybody's an author
And not all authors have that kind of purchase on
Defining what reality is not just for themselves, but for our whole society
And so I developed this notion of people who are phenomenally authorized meaning
Um
At the diametric opposite pole of what we what we would call these days an npc a non-player character
In a kind of simulacrum in a in a theatrical space in a in a game space
On the opposite pole of of those people who are kind of like part of the
What they're the wallpaper or window dressing
You have people whose agency is such that they are actually
Engaged in defining what reality is for whole society
through their
Creative endeavors whether it's literal writing or whether it's logos in the form of artistic production or
You know cinema or music and and so on and so forth
So you have this idea that there's a relationship between
Authorship again including in all the arts all the modes of of poesis or creative production
Authorship in that sense is related to phenomena
So phenomena are
phenomenally authorized by these author
types
But then there's also a kind of authority that that represents which I argue
Far exceeds political authority or you could say is more fundamental than political authority
Where the political leaders of one or another country are relatively insignificant
Compared to the movers and shakers who define the welton shong the worldview of that
Culture who set the standard for what's even going to count as real or unreal
You know for a given people which as you mentioned in your book
Nowadays unfortunately is uh in the power of all of these social media gossipers
Who back in the day would have just been relegated to gossiping in the back of the church during sunday
And now they're the ones that seem to wheel the power and bring people into the lowest common denominator
So
I don't know if now would be a good time to talk about what that future holds because i'm still very intrigued by
What the possibilities are here of wielding this kind of authority and authorship
So whichever direction you would prefer to go to please let me know
Well, I think that you know, it's fair to say
That my philosophical project as a whole which is reflected in a really condensed and crystallized form in this book philosophy of the future
Uh owes a great deal to nichea and and where nichea did not serve as an explicit inspiration
it's consonant with a lot of what nichea was doing and and um
Uh represents a further development of the same trajectory of thought that nichea was pursuing
And nichea had this vision of what he called frankly artist tyrants or artist philosophers
Uh who would wind up defining
Life on this earth in terms that exceeded the limits of the human condition
these are his uber mention
and
He has this notion that you know, there are these the highest men of history who are great geniuses and that basically
historical development throughout
Throughout time should be seen in terms of these mountain peaks
that are each
The contributions of one or another genius and that these higher men are progenitors of the coming overmen
just as
just as the last men
Uh who are increasingly degenerate
lazy
People who are feckless and without any particular motivation people who become
Ultimately captured by the event horizon of nihilism
that these uh last men are the harbingers of
A race of untermention
Subhumans who are really no longer going to be human and we're going to wind up being integrated into a machinery of
Reduction nichea has this vision as any today when you think in terms of the pace at which
Developments are taking place in artificial intelligence
And I mean, I don't know if you've seen what gpt 4o can do, but it's actually unsettling
uh, so
Even for me who's written about this for years like the rate at which this is happening is astonishing
Well, it was showing your your past as well
Uh possible past. I mean when you were uh using it
Yeah, well, we can come to that too. I mean so
But then when you combine ai with gene editing like for example, there are stories coming out today about how
One of the biggest problems with genetic engineering throughout these years that it's that it's been uh worked on by various companies is that
A lot of genes have secondary and tertiary functions
which if you
tinker with
The primary function of the gene that it is you're trying to manipulate in a person's genome
You wind up shutting off, you know some secondary or tertiary function
You don't understand well and that's going to become a problem for the organism. It could even be potentially lethal
So it requires extremely complex mapping of the multiple functions of any particular gene
It's been very difficult for us to do that which has meant that hitherto genetic engineering has been very dangerous
Well ai has cracked it ai has now mapped all of the secondary tertiary whatever functions of every gene
And it can do an analysis of exactly, you know
What benefit and what risks there are to making a particular edit in the genome using crisper?
So these technologies are becoming increasingly convergent in ways where you could see how
the vast majority of
You know people without any particular will or motivation
aspiration without any
Capacity to think for themselves or to pursue visions in a self-directed way
they're just going to wind up
being integrated into a machinery of production and
At the very best at the very best through cybernetic technology
and
they're going to wind up serving
the purposes of a group of
As Nietzsche put it spiritual aristocrats who are renaissance men in the truest sense
renaissance men and women
who
Are visionaries who are geniuses who who have more ideas than they know what to do with and who will take these emerging technology
First of all, they'll augment themselves biologically, but then also use artificial intelligence
to actualize
astonishing visions that
Have hitherto been deemed impossible. They're going to make the impossible possible
using these singularity level technologies and that's phenomenal authorization
okay, but
You know, if we just look at the state of the world today
I think it's fair to say that that phenomenal phenomenal authorization is not going to extend to the general population. It's it's going to be
A phenomenally authorized group of individuals who fight fight for their autonomy and for their creative power and genius
You don't really see the possibility like you were talking about with zero point energy
Being able to be in anybody's backyard this same kind of AI technology where you could press a button
All of a sudden you're bigger faster smarter
You know, you become the uber mensch even though you start out as the intermensch
You don't really see the npc people as you were calling them
embrace that here's the issue left the issue is
That in some totally
unhistorical abstract hypothetical scenario
Where we didn't have all the ideological baggage that we have in the world that would be entirely possible
However, as we'll get around to discussing by the end of this conversation, you know in terms of what's going on domestically
and geopolitically
The number of retards who are subscribing to
traditionalist
regressive ideologies in the world today or to forms of leftism
That are so nihilistic and cynical that they're actually dialectically
Empowering these various forms of retardation is such that the vast majority of the world population has foreclosed its participation
in such a process
We are 10 to 20 years away
At one point I thought we were 30 years away from the singularity the rate at which AI technology is developing today
I can tell you I I don't think we're more than 10 to 15 years away from the singularity
And we just don't have any time left for these people. We don't have the time left
When you have a vast majority of people
Look, Islam is going to be the dominant religion on this planet by 2075
If current demographic trends continue
Right and then we've got
The russian orthodox
Through people like dugin
aligned with these islamic traditionalists
And then we have china financing both of them and militarily backing them
Right. I mean i'll come to this later. Yeah, it was it was discovered recently by an independent think tank
that the worst of the pro palestine protests in america where they were actually targeting infrastructure blocking roads and
Bridges and taking over university campuses. Those were funded by china through a series of false front organizations
So you've got the chinese behind these muslims and you've got the russian orthodox
Power cabal of putin and dugin also supporting them
Right and then all the leftists in europe and america the socialist parties in europe and the sjw's in the united states
Are also they're literally in some cases converting to islam on these university
Uh, palestine encampments, right? That's that's on the left and on the right
You've got people like andrew tate who's also converting young men into islam because they're very dissatisfied with the way things are going now
In europe and then in america. We have the the retards of the bible belt
Yeah
Well, there is this new movement right now. I'm sure you've heard about you know, like the uh, jesus's uh, jesus's king jesus's lord
it's their way of
reaffirming this much more of a warrior
type christianity as opposed to like the soft christianity that i'm not a big fan of either as far as you know, like the
sjw type christians that i'm sure you've seen a lot of in minhatten
Yeah, well, they're you know, just because there are nods with one another doesn't make either of them our allies
They're both enemies. They're both mortal enemies and look when you have people like steve bannon even steve bannon
Coming out and arguing that server farms should be bombed by the us air force
Then you know, what hope is there that any of these christians in the bible belt are going to
Support our continued advancement toward the technological singularity or availed themselves of the opportunity to use this technology
In order to become ubermanshin, right? I mean no that's not going to happen
They're going to band together with the russian orthodox and in some cases they're even going to band together with the moslems
In order to lead some luddite traditionalist rebellion against the advent of the singularity
well
But uh going back to how exactly this
There's some noise from the outside here. Give me one second. Sure, absolutely
Yes, so that we don't wind up with any disruption. I'll be right back sounds good
And uh while jason is away. I just want to remind everybody here if this is your first time watching break the rules
Be sure to like subscribe comment
But also check out the other videos because I have videos with thinkers like kurdus yarvin mensius moldbug
Uh jason reservoir johnny as you can see over here uber boyo
uh neil nostic informant all kinds of an amazing uh sticks hexan hammer 666
uh britney venti who uh hopefully should be coming back soon as well
So i'm also doing right now these uh
presentations these streams in uh my Manhattan studio in new york city
And what i'm planning on doing is that if you guys become patrons patreon.com slash break the rules
And if you become specifically 20 dollar patrons and you guys happen to live within the new york sydney vicinity
Then you know after making sure everything is kosher, you know
Just so we don't have people from mental institutions coming in then i would definitely love to invite you guys over to these
taped
Uh recordings with uh the various interesting guests including dr.
Giorgiani that i'm going to be having in the coming months
So once again patreon.com slash break the rules go there right now and uh you guys are going to get a lot of good stuff
Even uh if you're not in new york city, you're going to get exclusive episodes including a q&a with georgiorgiani
Which you guys could watch uh right now once again, that's patreon.com slash break the rules
Go there or be square. Anyway, uh jason we are back over here and uh, yeah, let's uh, let's keep uh, let's keep going
So as far as
What exactly are the limitations to changing and i know you don't like using the word reality
But if we're talking about overcoming the situation we're in right now with this philosophy of the future
We still have to know what the certain limitations are obviously right now. I'm not going to be able to just go through a wall
I'm not going to be able to teleport myself back in time
But what are the things that people are able to use?
Right here and right now
In order to change things things that may go beyond just i don't know just being uh
Interesting thinker and philosopher and spreading messages because obviously, you know, we all know that we can do that
But as far as going beyond that what exactly is there?
Well, let me be very practical with you. Okay, um, and also I have to say that
You have to make a caveat there in terms of what you mean by people people can you know, what can people do?
Like most people are utterly oblivious
Uh and or captivated by one of these aforementioned ideologies that are that are responsible for destroying our civilization
And so most people are not going to you know, take the initiative to do to use any
Uh extraordinary abilities to potentially
Make us uh make us uh
Uh to potentially make a better future than the one that we're headed for right now, right?
But what can people with with initiative do? Well
Look, this is a bit of a dangerous game, but remote viewing the future for example is a
Imminently possible thing. It's been done many times
And so there's a case to be made
For training oneself in remote viewing to the point that one could look around the corner
And and see some of the challenges and crises that we're going to be facing in the near future
And grasp what caused them so that we can
address
Those causes before they wind up unfolding into one or another catastrophe that we're headed toward right now
Okay, so precognitive remote viewing is a thing. It's been used for
Oh, I don't know 45 years at this point
effectively by various governments
and now by the corporate sector
and
So that's one thing that people could do is to train that ability
But see that goes back to a point that I've made
Throughout my work from the beginning from Prometheus and out were from Prometheus and Atlas onwards
Is that suppose
you're trying to remote view
The outcome of the second American civil war, which I'm increasingly convinced that we're headed into
or the outcome of the third world war
And your objective is to find out let's say whether, you know
Russia winds up in a favorable position at the end of world war three because let's say France
Leaves NATO or whatever or you're trying to find out
What kind of government exists in the United States in
2028 right
But as part of seeing that future
You also see what happens in terms of your relationship with your wife
Or you see the death of certain of your children
How will that impact your life how capable will you be of dealing with that
What changes will result in your immediate situation?
As a consequence of that so, you know, I think
Many people even those who have the initiative to go and train themselves in the use of such abilities many of those people
Are not prepared for the psychological consequences of say seeing some things in their own personal future
That might be part of
A glimpse into our social or political future
Even if they have the ability to prevent that somewhat from happening if they know about in advance in a way
It's kind of empowering too
Here's the thing about that love is that look just um looking at my own life to give you a very personal answer
If
you were if if let's say 20 years ago
I had pre-cognitively remote viewed certain things that happened
In my life particularly involving relationships with
certain individuals
I might have
At that time with the psychology that I had in the moment
Endeavored to prevent those events from taking place
or let's say certain relationships from
deteriorating in certain ways and so forth, right?
Well by doing so I would also have prevented myself from reaching the place that I'm at today
And I can say that
frankly
Looking at the big picture
and thinking
About this from the deepest level
I have no regrets
And I'm not sure that the Giorgiani of 20 years ago
would have had the insight
Or the wisdom to understand why
It was perhaps important for those things to happen
So it's a very burdensome thing
to see elements of your own future
And to think that you'll be able to handle
The question of whether or not you should act to change certain things, right?
So so it makes it very hard. It makes it very hard
You know to to expect even a small minority of people with great initiative
and motivation
To be able to train themselves in these abilities for the sake of
averting
You know catastrophes on a social or political scale
I see what you mean does it necessarily
need to
Be a cultivation of those future seeing
skills
If one goes down the path of training their concentration
Or could a person decide you know what I don't want to see the future
But I do want to be able to do certain things
That go beyond being a
Regular human being as I was before
Can people choose or is it a matter of once you start going in one direction all of a sudden everything else just opens up like a sponge
I think one. Yeah, you know, I think it's possible to choose but
But I think that
There's only a certain latitude for control there because psi phenomena in general
Are a function of the subconscious
And so and this has been a theme throughout the course of my work
including in my
fiction quote-unquote
The idea that
In order to exercise phenomenal authorization
You need to make the subconscious conscious to a certain extent
And you need to be able to project conscious will into the domain of the subconscious
So there's a certain deconstruction of the barrier between the conscious mind and the subconscious that needs to take place
and and a certain
uh
a certain
capacity to
Will
Processes that are usually subconscious
Like people do in lucid dreams. I mean dream states are subconscious states
But there's a phenomenon of lucid dreaming where people exercise willpower in dreams and it's not coincidental
That remote viewers in certain protocols are first trained in how to
uh become lucid dreamers
Is there a certain timeline that you can give to somebody who is interested in taking the plunge?
And uh acquiring these skills. How long would it usually take for someone who?
Well, would be committed to such a thing
You know, I don't have the personal expertise to to comment on that directly
But I can tell you what some of the best remote viewers have told me. I mean for example, you know
Lynn Buchanan who I had some level of connection with
um, Lynn Buchanan has said repeatedly that
uh, first of all, it's always possible to improve
But that some of the best remote viewers who he's trained, you know
He was the chief trainer for the cia dod remote viewing program for a while
so he trained all the other guys who were the best in the program and
He was of the view that uh, it really takes decades to produce an ace remote viewer
now, you know with things like ai
and neural link type psychotronic technology
And potentially genetic augmentation because actually it's been found that there are certain genetic correlates
Of high aptitude for psi
Right. So ai seems to be an ability that has a genetic basis to some extent just like
aptitude to become a virtuoso musician has genetic basis just like
Becoming an olympic class swimmer has some genetic correlate to it
Some people are going to be more or less genetically predisposed for high level of ability
in in uh in these
Various fields and the same is true with psi. It's very similar to the exercise of sports ability and the trainability of sports ability
Right. Like anyone can be trained to do it to some level
Anyone can, you know, not everyone's going to be a basketball player
No, but everyone can play basketball, but you might suck. Yeah. Yeah
So so the thing is there's a certain degree of genetic, uh, correlation and if now
We bring genetic
Engineering or gene editing into the mix and we combine it with neural link and we combine it with ai protocols
That can develop much more effective ways to learn remote viewing
Maybe you could cut that time down drastically
And it's a question of a few years rather than, you know, a decade or two
But it's it requires a significant investment of time and energy in any case. That's for sure
Do you also a last question regarding this, uh, ascendance? Do you also see a, uh,
usefulness of training the body in conjunction with the mind as far as exercises to make the body stronger
To, uh, you know, do certain tantric exercises as well to, uh,
Work on, you know, the chakras as they refer to, uh, that in the event of a danta and so on and so forth
Absolutely. I think that all of that, you know, should be part of a future Promethean society. No doubt about it. I mean, you know, uh,
I'm a philosopher where I've chosen to, you know,
Place my energy and my time in emphasis thus far at least in my life
is is, uh,
you know
Very much in line with how people like heidegger or jampolsacht or, you know, I don't know, uh
Wittgenstein lived their lives, right? I mean, we philosophers are a certain type, right? Yeah
So and then and then I have a literary dimension to me, which which, you know, gives me an affinity to people like kafka and
Uh, I don't know kamu and and and others
So I I'm that type of person. We're not going to be seeing Dr.
Giorgiani, uh, doing like a deadlifts and squats, uh, you know in the gym, uh,
Or are we or are we? Well, look, I'm at an interesting turning point in my life, frankly, because this book philosophy of the future
Represents a kind of culmination, right?
The fundamental structure of my philosophical project is complete now. That doesn't mean that I won't all of a sudden have a
shift of perspective or, you know, new ideas
Might not dawn on me and revolutionize my work in some way that happened with wittgenstein
You know, heidegger also had some dramatic developments in his later thinking. Uh, so yeah, sure. That's possible
But I am at a point of culmination
And also the colossus project represents in a in a tangible sense a significant development in my life
And probably changes of condition in my life that will afford me the opportunity to maybe spend time and energy doing some
Uh, other types of things how much it in, you know, for example, I certainly would love to go back to skiing
It was my favorite sport uh earlier in my life
And so, yeah, you know, I might I might put my energy in other directions
If I had to guess though, I would say that
If there's going to be a shift of energy and focus to some extent a lot of it will go into art and um art
Most likely in the sense of cinema or a visualization of my
literary work
That's I think very likely
Speaking of which by the way the cover for your book and the design of the book that was all you philosophy of the future
That's true. That's true. But I don't rule out. Let's say learning remote beyond. I don't rule that out at all
And you know, there's some people who I'm sure hope that that never happened
Going around in the ether
That that might be problematic for some of the vested interests in the world
But where exactly we go from here because we were just talking about
psychic abilities, but as far as
Defining reality itself as far as this destructive departure of world review warfare
When it comes to changing what exactly this whole thing we're experiencing is
I'm very fascinated by what that exactly would entail
But also what exactly is currently around us because
I do recall you were talking about how all of these galaxies and galaxy clusters and so and so forth
These are things for us to observe because we're looking out in order to see them that may be what they are
But then the question is well, where exactly does the
Real part end? Well, not real. I know you don't believe in real
But where exactly does the part that we can actually interact with it and there are other life forms there
Where does that end? Does it end on mars? Does it end on, you know, the uh word cloud?
You mean what's the edge of uh
Uh, what's the edge of phenomenal experience in this world? Yes. Yes
Well, I've thought a bit about this and I've discussed it in a couple of my books
to begin with
There are aspects of quantum theory
such as
wave particle duality
And the fact and the fact that a probability distribution on a quantum level
Never actualizes as a particle with a particular location until and unless it's been observed meaning measured by a
sentient
observer
And I I think that the people who push back against that, you know, that was the position of Niles Bohr
and uh, Werner Heisenberg and all the great, uh, quantum physicists in the
Early years and I think that these people reductionist materialists who are trying to push back against that and say that
Wave collapses can take place without sentient observers are trading in a bunch of nonsense
They invent hidden variables and string theories and all this other bullshit to claim that there are deterministic processes that underlie
the
That underlie the probabilistic
Uh quality of quantum phenomena, and I I don't there's no empirical evidence for that all of these are
Uh
purely speculative mathematical formalisms
Okay, that are just intended to give these people a sense of psychological security
There was a sorry to interrupt. There was also a physicist who said that it was the
I getting hit by
Something that caused this change to occur as opposed to observation itself
Yeah, well, that's moronic because the I is a structure made up of quantum particles ultimately just as the brain is
So what's causing the wave collapse, right? I mean quantum particles aren't causing other quantum part
Quantum particles aren't causing wave
Distributions to collapse into particles
An observer is doing that and so you just can't get consciousness from out of the mix there
You cannot you know extricate the psyche from
The cosmos as it's manifesting through logos
Out of chaos psyche is an inextricable element in this process here
But anyway, what I was going to say was that there are aspects of quantum theory like this, you know
Wave article duality or rather the fact that everything is only a probability distribution until it's observed
Which is similar to what we call conditional rendering in
video game
Programming where you don't render something that's not being observed by any one or another player in the game
Because it's just in elegant
And by the way, I have a silent conversation about this the other day
um
Where look
Someone might
Think that the reason for that is that there's a limited amount of energy and processing power
But that's not necessarily the case
If you're designing
a game
You might just
Employ conditional rendering because it would be in elegant not to do so
I mean like when you're building a stage set for a theatrical production, right?
And there's there has to be a house
on the on the set
What moron goes and builds a complete living room?
That the audience is never going to see any of the actors
Enter into right you don't do that. That's not the way it's method acting jason. That's what that is
You know, you got to get full immersion into but yeah, I understand what you're saying
Good method actors wouldn't actually even do that to get into the role. But in any case, yes
So I just think it's a question of elegance
but
features of quantum theory like that or quantum entanglement where you know, if you interact with
You take two particles that have had interaction with one another and you do a measurement on one of them
It actually affects the other one that's now moved to a discrete location
And so these two particles appear to be
Entangled in a way where anything that affects one of them causes a change in the other one. Well, there's also a process like that
in
the
coordinated change of pixels
in the
Rendering of a video game where certain pixels are coded to basically
Change simultaneously change their state simultaneously
And so there are these various features that appear similar to programming code
In the design of simulacra
And then there are other things that are even more bizarre like we've discussed in another episode
That the number 26 keeps popping up at different scales
In the cosmos whether it's in terms of the distance between
You know the or the diameter of the moon or you know the distance between
Our solar system and the center of the galaxy or the time that it takes for our solar system to circumnavigate the galaxy
These are all multiples of the number 26 for some reason. Well, that doesn't make any sense in a in a
physical cosmos the way that
reductionist materialists think about
You know the the universe that they imagine us to be living in nor for that matter does the efficacy of zodiacal astrology
Which is something I've touched on in numerous works of mine
The fact that there's good scientific evidence for example
The work of michelle gaughan showing that people do going to career paths
Influenced by you know the position of the stars at the time of their or position of the at least the planets at the time of their birth
Well, that suggests that we're living in a kind of symbol system that the cosmos is informational rather than physical in nature
That we're in fact
Inside of an information processing system of some kind. So, yeah, you know, you can wonder then
What's the size of the information processing system, you know
Is it are we in something like what's depicted in dark city? Is that what's going on here? You know, how
How uh, what's the scale of the matrix that we're inside of?
Well, the one counter that I can think of giving
To you about that is the idea of the macrocosm and microcosm where
I can imagine there being
Certain processes that are going on that are greater than us and in comparison to which we're like the cells inside of the mind
And I can imagine this going up like some kind of a russian matryoshka doll
Where there could be like certain higher consciousnesses of you know, uh, planets
Or stars or galaxies like it never ends now
I'm not saying that this is something that I'm that attached to
But it is interesting just to see like how certain patterns exist in nature both in the small and in the high end
Like when people observe galaxies, for instance, that makes me think those galaxies can't all be fake, you know
There must be like some bigger process at work here that we're just not aware of
I'll tell you why I disagree with you
I can imagine what you're saying very well
And it's very intriguing
and in some way I would like that to be true because
You know the vast or the cosmos is the more interesting that the evolutionary development possibilities are for all of the
Organisms in it ourselves included. However, the reason why I
First of all, there's no empirical evidence that what you're saying is true
We don't have empirical evidence of that the empirical evidence that we do have of intelligence
That's higher than ours
Suggest that actually
Maybe sadly
We're incredibly important
If you look at the close encounter phenomenon, which I've written an entire book about and which I've mentioned
I've discussed significantly in several other of my books
Including a bit in philosophy of the future. If you look at the close encounter phenomenon
Let's put these Nordics aside for a minute, right these these
People who look like SS officers flying around in their, you know, mercury thorium
Saucers, right muscle down blonde women
Yeah, I mean and they're they're real
There was real as you and I are these are people and you know
They don't I I think they have very deleterious intentions for the near future of our world society
But let's put them aside for the moment
Because I think that actually as I've argued in various books of mine
They're as terrified of this other thing that I'm about to discuss
As some of our government officials are and this other thing this trickster that seems to be able to produce
polymorphous phenomena of all kinds
And that has access to people's bedrooms in the middle of the night
And that sometimes abducts their children
And it takes genetic material from them
And they can shape shift into any number of shamanic forms often drawing from the symbolism of owls and mantids and so forth
Right this entity which I discuss at length
in chapter seven of closer encounters and which I come back to
Contemplating at the end of philosophy of the future
This entity seems awfully interested in human individuals
We are not irrelevant
This thing has tremendous intelligence
It is superior to humanity
It's probably capable of destroying humanity
It certainly has taken apart
human civilizations of global scale before
This is how Atlantis was destroyed ultimately
And
This entity seems incredibly interested in human individuals
We are not at all like
Termites or ants or whatever to this thing every time I hear someone like Michio Kaku say that or any one of these people
Avi Loeb or whatever
It's really aggravating to me because the empirical evidence from close encounters doesn't support that at all
This entity sends emissaries and avatars to interact with us in incredibly intimate ways
And follows human individuals throughout their entire lives gets
Generationally involved with their offspring
It is it is deeply and intimately engaging
The human community and it has an agenda
Which whatever else you want to say about that agenda or speculate about it
Clearly sees the human being as central and of vital importance to its
project for the future
So that's why I I don't really agree with you that
Whatever the forms of intelligence are that are way beyond us and that are operating on a cosmic scale
We actually seem to be incredibly important to them which suggests that we're not actually
All that's separate from them
There's not such a huge gulf between us and them and when you think about the the technological singularity and the transformative potential that it has
That actually makes a lot of sense. We may be very close
to
uh
A transformation and mutation of our form of life that gives us parity with this
entity
I guess the only
Rebutal I would give to that is the idea that this entity
May exist
But there could be also other entities that are beyond that that we don't know and again. I have no proof
For yeah, but there's no evidence for that lab. I mean and look I am as I've said to you before
Uh in our previous conversations and as is abundantly clear from my philosophical work. I'm a radical empiricist
I'm a radical empiricist. I believe in you know, uh developing ontological and epistemological ideas
uh that are
Consonant with phenomena that we can experience and observe and that we can you know
tangibly make some sense out of and and doing so in ways that afford us opportunities for tangible
technological development
And and you know productive artistic
Endeavors so I'm very much a radical empiricist and why do you say it's uh one
Entity though as opposed to a multiplicity of entities
that
Work in a similar fashion
It is a multiplicity of entities
But when you really, you know, the devil is in the details
quite literally
And when you look at the details of some of these close encounters
You have to come away with the conclusion that there is some kind of
Uh, how can I put it?
I don't want to use the term high of mind because it's it's not
Something like the borg that we're dealing with. It is not a
collective intelligence
or a kind of um
Uh organic
Unity that subsumes the individual the way that the borg
Uh assimilates and extinguishes the individuality of the people who are
Assimilated by the collective. That's not what we're dealing with. In fact
This
Super organism appears to want to encourage individuation and differentiation
For the sake of maximizing creative potential
So I don't want to call it a hive mind. Okay, but it appears that these entities
Are operating in tandem in a way that suggests the functioning of some higher
Organizing intelligence
albeit
Very finite
Intelligence is certainly not anything like an omniscient or omnipotent god
Well in the buddhism
The value that you're giving towards human beings is in a way echoed when they talk about human beings
A rebirth within that realm is the best of all
Obviously you disagree with the direction the buddhas end up going to but their reasoning is when you're in the realm of the
Higher end gods or the jealous gods
You're always going to be a lot more raptured in having all this power to deal with
Same thing when you're in the realm of the hell beings or the hungry ghosts
So I don't know if that is a concept that is close to you as well
Like that reason for human beings being so special even if you go in a different direction with it
Actually, yes, I would say so and you know someday we should do an entire show just on
what I think of buddhism because
I've said before, you know the
On an ontological and epistemological level
there's actually a lot of overlap between my work and the thought of gotama and nagarjuna and some of the serious, you know
thinkers in the history of the buddhidharma from the beginning and
you're right that
In a certain way what i'm saying about this entity's interest in humanity is
consonant with
Gotama's valuation
Of the human community over that of both the devas and the ashuras
You know gotama recognized rightly
That I mean, you know just recognized right?
He was he was a reincarnation of someone who had lived in deva realms previously
And he was familiar with the ashura realms the realms of what we call in in a west western tradition the olympians and the titans
and
He knew based on personal memory and amnesis
that
There is more possibility for personal development and the achievement of insight in the human realm than there is in these other
worlds
Uh, and I think this entity feels the same way, but the difference is
that gotama thought that
total enlightenment ultimately meant the extinguishing of individuality
and he has a nihilistic view of suffering as
having no
ultimate
purpose that you know suffering is futile
And that what we should aim at is the extinguishing of suffering
Whereas this entity I think very much
Or rather I should say
Nietzsche very much shares the the outlook of this entity, which is that suffering is
Absolutely indispensable to any creative endeavor
Uh, and that the great creators
need
suffering as part of you know the
Generative process that they act as conduits for in this world
Right, and you can see that very much for example at the core of the myth of prometheus
There's tremendous tragic suffering in the myth of prometheus, which Nietzsche discusses in the birth of tragedy specifically right prometheus as this
Tragic image of human aspiration and as the first uh mask
um in greek theater, so
so
The tragic life affirming view
Of Nietzsche
Is much more in line with how this entity
sees
human evolution
Than gotama's nihilistic will
To end suffering by extinguishing individuality
Before we proceed onwards. There is also the uh roodolph steiner view, which I see as being related
When he talked about how when you would observe a plant or a tree
Or anything in your vicinity in the way you're giving life to it and that reminds me of what you're talking about this
Generating informational computational system that we're in where our
Looking out at something in a way does give more life to it than it may have originally had
Because we're imbuing whatever we're looking at maybe including another person or including whatever we would consider to be a god of sorts
We're imbuing that with the power it did not originally have before we uh looked at it
Or before we thought about it
Yeah, the yeah look steiner has any number of very interesting insights here and there
And and he was a very innovative thinker in some ways and particularly when it comes to like applied fields
He was a polymath, you know who developed innovative educational techniques and
I don't know botany and agricultural methods and all kinds of interesting things
But the uh essential problem with steiner is that he's a strange sort of gnostic
Who has a basically dualistic ontology?
And this is something that i'm trying to deconstruct in my work with my concept of the spectral revolution
This idea that you know, they're for steiner. There's this transcendental realm, which you know is uh
Sort of presided over by lucifer and then there's this purely
materialistic realm which is controlled by ahriman and that the human experience is kind of a
Middle ground between these polarities, right?
I deconstruct that kind of dualism just as niche does
And uh, I think there's only one world. There's the world of our phenomenal experience
And you know what we frame as the spiritual versus the physical is a question again of
Linguistic structures the conditioned consciousness and that's set in place filters for our perception and our processing of our experience
Our experience of a singular world of experience. I mean our experience of a singular world
Which you know, the greeks called fuses going back to our quite as nature as it were
But within that world we would also have let's say
Certain places that people would only be able to observe
During the in-between state of uh, you know the afterlife. I guess you could say so
Similarly, we could have like with the japanese buddhas. They have this conception of pure land buddhism
Which is like this whole other realm that you can go into and like that'll meditate all day or whatever
So i'm not sure exactly as far as the amount of
Real estate that we have to work with here including like going back in time that you were talking about as well
You know, how
How much is there to explore how much is there to uncover or is it pretty much like
The earth and however we keep going, you know expanding beyond that
Look, I think there's a lot of real estate again, though
Let me emphasize the fact that it's it's a question of filters
You know when people die
Filters are removed
Filters that are integral to this particular form this construction that we take to be the physical human body
Filters are removed and other dimensions of experience become perceivable
It's not that there's another world. We don't go into the other side after we die. Okay, this is these are
Dangerous delusions that are being propagated today as part of a discourse that I think ultimately is going to be used to implement
traditionalism and kind of neo feudal subjugation of humanity under a sort of kingdom of heaven
and you know
I think that it's important to acknowledge first of all
That there's a singular realm of experience and that our capacity to perceive various dimensions of it is a question of what filters are operating
Now drugs can remove certain of those filters like for example DMT
Giving us access to these realms where there are apparently these machine elves
But in the same DMT spaces, there are also these reptilians who rape women
Okay, so my issue with what you said about the pure land
Hmm is that so far as I've heard in the contemporary
uh realm of research on altered states of consciousness
Nobody has come back and given us a report about the buddhist pure land as far as I'm aware
Now, of course, there are buddhist writings where these monks claim, you know to have connected with that realm
But you know, there's a lot to psychological projection. I mean you can you can really like really
Imagine yourself in a different milieu
With vivid clarity basically put yourself into a lucid dream while you're meditating. That's one thing
But in terms of uh, you know
Phenomenological realms of experience that could be shared by other people the way that I think the DMT space can be
I don't see anything like the pure land. I don't see any and I'm making this point very deliberately because uh,
I wanted to be impressed upon the listener that there's nowhere to escape to that doesn't involve conflict and suffering
The DMT realm involves terrifying shit
Any, you know, honest authentic account of that makes it very clear that it is not a safe place to be
Okay, so
Uh, I think that again, you know, this whole notion
That we should seek an enlightenment that involves
ultimate peace tranquility and harmony
And eventually also the effacing of our ego and the annihilation of our individuality
Is completely misguided
And it's the most sophisticated form of nihilism
Nietzsche saw this by the way. He said look at least I respect buddhism because its form of nihilism is more sophisticated
Than that of christianity, right? If you're going to be a nihilist be a buddhist not a christian, right? So
Uh, my work very much flies in the face of that kind of nihilism
Well, uh, speaking of effacing the ego
I think now would be a good time to get to the kind of effacing that's going on right now
with the uh, palestine protests going on in the new york city and uh, all over
And the general trend that I mean we talked about this before the convergence in a way that i'm seeing of the ultra left
and uh, certain elements of the uh, further right when it comes to wanting to embrace this kind of
Traditionalism, but this kind of like almost like third worldist type of traditionalism where a lot of those protesters
You know, they have no problem with china. They have no problem with uh, you know, whatever's going on in africa in the middle east
They have a big problem with these, uh, you know, 18th 17th century
Statues and monuments, you know to uh, western civilization. That's what they want to get rid of
So where exactly do you see this going right now?
Uh, jason, you've uh, well got the floor. Yeah
Look, there's so much that I want to say about this
I kind of don't even know where to begin and uh, you know, you know, because we were trying to organize a show some time ago weeks ago
um
That I really didn't want to talk about this subject public
I really tried not to say anything about this publicly
Because we're involved in some very positive optimistic work with the colossus project
and you know, I want to uh
I want to do as much as I can to make sure that that moves forward
Expeditiously and triumphantly that having been said
It's just gone too far. It's gone way too far
So you mentioned pulling down of statues, right back in the summer of of george floyd
The summer of george floyd summer of love
Yes in 2020, right. I love how these fuckers who were, you know, uh
Desecrating our war memorials and want to pull down the statues of our founders also do instagram posts where you know, it's all about love
It's all about love man. That's all it matters and the world is love
And then they go and they burn the american flag or they raise the palestinian flag higher than the american flag on flag polls
Right, and then they go and they desecrate, you know war memorials to uh, you know, uh, world war one heroes in this country
And burn american flags of the but no, it's all about love
right, uh, anyway, um, what I was going to say was that back in the summer of george floyd
We saw them starting to pull down all these statues. So the founders of our country including
This great sculpture of theodore roosevelt that was on the steps of the museum of natural history in new york
There's a place that was dear to my heart from childhood
And um
They didn't even care whether the the founders were slave owners or not they pulled down statues of abraham lincoln
Back in the summer of george. So that summer
With you know, what happened in minneapolis? What happened in portland the whole chas
encampment and so on and so forth, right
That was a watershed moment
And I founded prometheism
In response to that if you look at when prometheism was founded july 4th
2020 what was the context that was the context?
Okay, so that was a watershed moment. We're at another turning point now. Okay. We are at another
uh
Rubicon crossing of the rubicon moment right now
Where
Let me take this angle
where
slogans
That were devised
By ayatollah homini in iran
during
The hostage crisis while american hostages were being held in terron
Ayatollah homini and his fellow molas
Came up with these slogans like death to america
Which are now being chanted on the campuses and the streets of american cities
And in some cases we literally see agents of the islamic republic coming and setting up seminars to teach americans
How to chant not just death to america in english, but marg bar america in persia literally
Teaching them how to pronounce this enchantment
And these same people
Are burning american flags
And they're passing out leaflets saying
The freedom of palestine means death to america
Right
Self-described anarchists self-described communists
Who are supporting an organization namely hamas
Who they characterize as freedom fighters?
But who are actually radical fundamentalist adherents of a religion that endorses slavery
That endorses the enslavement of women
And their total degradation as second or third class citizens
And the religion that violently conquered and genocided
Other cultures in the world and deprived them of any freedom of religion or freedom of conscience or freedom of expression
Self-described communists and anarchists who
Whether or not we agree with their ideology at least were supposedly advocates for freedom and liberation
Right and we're supposedly struggling against capitalism because it was too oppressive
Right and that it was uh too much of a constraint on the human individual and that it didn't go far enough
Let's say in liberating women these same communists and anarchists are now supporting the most regressive
traditionalist ideology on the planet
Which is being spearheaded by hamas
What the fuck is going on here?
Right and meanwhile you have in europe for example, we saw what a week ago. I think it was in germany
Mass protests. I mean math tens of thousands. Where did these people come from?
Who let these people into europe?
Oh anglo-merkel, right? I remember now, right 2013 2014
Yeah, well the the chickens come home to roost at this point tens of thousands of people are marching in germany
demanding an islamic caliphate replace the german government
So that's going on in europe where we literally have muslim armies on the street
demand and then in britain
islamic parties
allied with leftists are winning elections
left and right
And they're using their political power
To completely strip the british citizen of all their fundamental freedoms like we saw happen in scotland in particular
And ireland's having kind of identity crisis where on the one hand ireland traditionally, you know with the ira and such
We're supporting palestine, but now they're also having this influx of these migrants that are coming in
They want to it's straight out of lord of the rings
They want to tear down this beautiful ancient tree in order to build a migrant center
And now there's this war that's going on between the
irish people who live there and the people that want to tear it down
So i don't know what's going on specifically with those people
I mean thankfully a lot of the irish people are standing up for themselves right now
But yeah, they're also supporting palestine. They're also supporting palestine. What kind of sense does that make, you know?
That's very strange order irish. It's a disgrace
I think it's utterly disgraceful
you know like
For fuck's sake, okay israel
was a secular
Progressive country
Which has demonstrated
tremendous capacity in contribution to technological science, which has fostered the arts a society where
women are
Respected to the point where the defense of the nation is also entrusted to them
A society that from the earliest days when the kibbutz movement formed the substrate of israeli society
Was based on radical egalitarianism
okay
And a society that has always enshrined and protected freedom of speech freedom of the press
Right and and yeah, and all the what we consider to be sacred and fundamental rights of the human individual on the one hand
You have that society by the way a society that includes many israeli arabs
Christians drues
drues
at eight at the left
Samaritans first society
Okay, uh one devoted to the protection of the individual one devoted to uh, you know
The equality of women
and one that has
contributed
With tremendous disproportionate power
To the advancement of science and technology
Okay, um, but the problem is that they're like the adult in the room
They're like the logical adult and the kids are like, you know, fuck you dad. I don't have to listen to you
It seems like it's that kind of relationship that's going on where people
Protesters against netanyahu the protesters against him, but in general just the anti-israel feeling
I think a lot of it comes from
Maybe israel is not dianesean enough to put it a certain way because people who are looking at israel are just seeing
You know these very
Logical people who are trying to explain themselves
Meanwhile people want to burn things down and cause all this chaos
I don't know if you've thought about it in that direction
But at least from people who I've spoken with they kind of see israel
I know this is very beneath you, but they see israel as cringe
You know that they don't see that kind of fire in israel's belly that would be a commanding force
And maybe that's why we have all these people online who are also going against israel just from an optics perspective
Well, maybe you're right israel might not be dianesean enough
Dianesis is an incredibly violent symbol. So maybe israel should be a lot more violent
I would be absolutely in favor of that. I think this should be a lot more commanding. There might be something to what you're saying
no, there really might be something to what you're saying, but
Who is holding israel back? Well, now we know who's holding israel back because guess what it just came out
that the united states
The administration of joe biden
Sent the representative to negotiate with the islamic republic of iran in oman
Oh, man
Okay, and the deputy foreign minister of iran was the one present at those negotiations and guess what the subject of discussion was
Bringing an end to the war in gaza
By changing the government in israel
So here's israel since october 7th
rightly aiming for regime change in iran, which would be a tremendous favor to the iranian people
And meanwhile the united states instead of helping israel to foment regime change in iran or at least not standing in the way of israel
The united states is secretly plotting with a regime whose slogan and maxim is death to america
In order to do what to change the government of israel
Before we get deeper into this. I just want to say that about a year ago
I was at a party in the in the hamptons, you know the far far east there of long island
And I met a guy who was introduced to me by a friend as being part of masad
Okay, and I told this guy the what you recommended, which is that israel should go into um
Rather than gaza, you know should go into iran should decimate, uh, you know the government buildings
But leave the nukes alone and the masad guy said
Lev you're absolutely right. We should do this, but we can't because america won't let us
In order to corroborate that let me also tell you what someone very well positioned with a lot of connections to the israeli government told me
Which is that after october 7th like, you know on october 8th. Yeah
You remember how long it took israel to go into gaza, right? Yeah
It was long we were wait for weeks. We were wait. What what is this operation going to take place?
You know why because actually netanyahu didn't want to go into gaza because netanyahu knew
What the optics of this were going to be like netanyahu wanted to bomb iran
He wanted to bomb the islamic republic out of existence rightfully so because
Who's controlling the tentacles of this octopus? That's hamas and that's hezbollah and the houthis of yemen and you know the the various uh
Militias in iraq that are against israel obviously the regime in tehran so israel wanted to go after iran
The united states sent those two aircraft carriers into the Mediterranean
Not to support israel, but to intimidate and threaten israel
I know this for a fact what they told the israelis was here
Here are these two aircraft carriers to help defend you
But if you attack iran, we will publicly withdraw these carriers
Sending a signal to the iranians that we don't have your back anymore
okay, so
This is horrendous
especially when you have masses of leftists on the streets in america
And having taken over tens of our campuses
chanting slogans
That were designed in tehran
When you have masses of people on the streets of america chanting death to america while burning american flags and desecrating american
war memorials and at the same time
you're
doing back room deals
with the islamic republic of iran
There is no higher form of treason than that
That these protests were allowed to continue
For what is it now two months for two months?
We saw these campuses be taken out including by the way the campus of colombia university
Was a sacred place to me. There is a monument to athena there
That to me has always made that place the campus of athena campus in the roman sense
You know the word campus actually comes from the roman term for sacred precincts like the campus of mars
In rome in ancient rome
And to me that place was always the campus of athena. I used to go there
You know in the wee hours of the morning before people showed up and just walk the colonnade there and silently contemplate and
Pay my respects to athena
They desecrated that place they literally held
ceremonies converting american students to islam
Under the banner of the pro-palestine movement on the campus of colombia university in the shadow of athena
They literally put a banner around athena
Renaming that place the people's university of palestine
They excluded jews from the campus at colombia at yale at any number of other universities
They formed human chains
Backed by the security forces on the campus to prevent jewish students and jewish professors from entering the campus
But there are from what i understand also
Leftist jews who are a part of the protest as has always been in history
Like people always love referring to like barbara learner specter or any of these idiots that are talking about you know wanting to destroy
Europe and my whole point is that you're going to have jews
Who are going to have bad ideas as well as good ideas?
And those are going to be the jews that people end up paying attention to and unfortunately right now
I'm sure that there are some jewish students who are so self-hating
And who have this romance having to do with you know freeing palestine and all that that they're also going to join the cause
Well, if I were in mosad right now, I would find a way to start eliminating these people
I mean they represent an existential threat to israel. Well, I've always said I've always said this that israel will never
Be defeated by any foreign enemy
If israel is ever defeated one day, it will be defeated by traders from within
People within israel will defeat israel israel can never be defeated by any foreign enemy
That country has 300 nuclear warheads
And by the way that arsenal stands between islam and its ambition for the conquest of the west
Never forget that never forget those 300 israeli nukes will be used
Before europe is conquered by islam. Okay, so look, but my point is this
that when you have on the one hand these kinds of
rabidly anti-american protests taking place
On these campuses and in the streets of american cities
Desecrating war memorials and so forth burning the american flag raising the flag of palestine higher than the american flag
all the while
chanting death to america
and at the same time
us government officials are doing back room deals with the islamic republic to undercut israel
I don't know what worse form of treason we could see in our country than that
Okay, and so the to me the ultimate red line has already been crossed and as an iranian american
Look, I was born here. Okay, but
I know a lot of other iranian americans foremost my fiance who spent 13 years living in the fucking islamic republic
I can tell you
What it's like for iranian americans who fled that regime
to come here
Looking for a place where individual liberty is honored
And to hear the same slogan that they had to live with in iran
Mark that on recall death to america being chanted by american youth here on the streets of our cities
the iranian youth today
70 percent of iran is under the age of 30 iran
May have many problems, but the natalist problem is not one of them. It's a very youthful vigorous population
70 percent of the country's under the age of 30 and the iranian youth are undoubtedly the most pro-american population
On the planet. Okay out of time when anti-americanism is on the rise
It's undoubtedly the case that the most solid future ally of america
Is the iranian nation? Okay
But what is a travesty is that the average iranian youth today the average
Iranian in their 20s or 30s today
Cares more about american culture and has a better appreciation of america's history
than american youth do
And i'm i'm warning you people right i'm just giving issuing a general warning
This is not going to go to a good place. This is not going to go to a good place. Iran is a country
That has been conquered by greeks, romans, arabs
turks
and mongols
It suffered
genocidal conquests
at the hands of foreign enemies
and it came back
five times
Not just as a country as an empire
Okay, iran will rise again
The people of america
I don't i don't even want to use the term united states anymore because this fucking regime that calls itself the united states government
Is a treasonous criminal mafia
To which no one should pay taxes by the way
It is a treasonous criminal mafia
That does not represent the interests of americans, but the people of america should be very careful
To get this situation under control soon
and to
Eliminate these vermin
Who have stripped themselves of their american citizenship by conducting themselves in this manner that we've seen over the past two months
otherwise
If iran rises again
And we have a population in iran that respects american culture and american history more than
american youth do
Something very bad is going to happen that i hope i never had lived to see
Okay, i'm telling you right now well if we can uh
Europe is fucked europe is fucked
All right, uh look at germany look at britain france
I have some hope for but let me be very frank with you
That right the latest figures that i've seen show 25 of the urban population of france is is living under sharia
There are sharia no-go zones in stance where uh french
The french justice system no longer applies
And and france has the highest birth rate by the way as well in europe of muslims
Yeah, well, yeah, that's of the children of migrants
Okay, and so look the figures in france are are extremely grim. It looks like about 25 of france
is
gone
Okay has been subsumed by basically the the fifth column of the caliphate
Uh, but i actually think there's some hope for france
I think that if national front comes back in 2027 there is some hope for france. However
Let me be clear
There will be no solution in france without concentration camps
Absolutely no solution in france without concentration camps
They are going to have to take french citizens so-called french citizens
Who at this point are citizens of a nascent global caliphate and they're going to have to concentrate them in certain places
And extricate them from france. Maybe they should take algeria
Back and they should use it for this purpose in any case
Because france is constituted differently from britain and i mean that constituted in both senses of the word
I actually think there's some hope in france, but it's going to be extremely brutal
You know to constitute
What what may end up being the sixth french republic? It's doable though and here in this country
The situation is also not far gone
There's still hope to turn things around
But it has to be done very soon and if it doesn't happen during a second term of trump
We're going to be utterly hopeless and a catastrophe will unfold which you know
You know, yes, he's going to come out of the bottle the camp you put back in
Now if we break down some of the players involved here
One of the organizations that's currently funding these uh protests is the open society foundation
You know george saris but more now his son alex who is dating huma abedin
Whose parents from what i understand are involved or we're involved with the muslim brotherhood
So what exactly is going on here and one more thing to add to that from what i understand during obama's administration
When hillary clinton was secretary of state they redid all the manuals having to do with counter terrorism
To completely scrub it of anything related to islam
So i'm curious what you make of this
Look another reason i'm so visibly irate is because i spent a decade in the iranian opposition
And three years in its leadership
We found that the democrat party in the united states
Wanted to secure the continued existence of the islamic republic of iran pretty much at any cost and they undermine any and every effort
Uh of the iranian people to change this regime
So this is an issue in particular with the democrats in this country
And we can see that reflected just uh, you know in the last 48 hours with this letter that blinkin
ordered his people to issue
Expressing condolences for the death of reisi president reisi was a butcher president reisi
presided as a summary execution jurist
over the mass execution of thousands of political dissidents in iran
and you and people
Before it was even confirmed that his helicopter, you know
Cashed and that he had you know that he had met his demise
You had fireworks going off all across iranian cities that night. The iranian people were celebrating
Throughout the night and into the next morning
for the death of this
Butcher and meanwhile the u.s. State department issues its condolences for the death of reisi
Right and the u.s. State department
Allows the american ambassador to the united nations
To stand together with all the other members of the security council in a minute of silence
For reisi's death in the united nations security council
the israeli ambassador
Put on a fantastic spectacle the other day. What was it about a week ago when he walked up
to the podium of the general assembly
And he took the un charter
And he shredded it in a mini shredder right there at the podium of the general assembly after the un general assembly condemned israel
Okay, uh, it's gone too far. It's gone to the international criminal court
issuing a
issuing a request for arrest warrants
For net and yahoo prime minister net and yahoo and defense minister galant
When at the same time this international criminal court
Has completely turned a blind eye to all of the other genocidal
political leaders in afghanistan in iraq during the years of isis in various parts of africa
It's an outrage
And we're fast approaching a situation which i depicted in my novella artemis unveiled
What was it two years ago?
where israel
And a new iran
Are going to wind up a war with the whole world
That day is coming. We are fast approaching
That vision of the future dark vision of the future which i articulated in that novella
And i'm telling you i'm particularly
the american people
need to
change course
and these uh
look
A handful a small group of enthusiastic patriots
Who went to our capital on january 6th?
With american flags see they came with american flags
To storm the capital
And they're branded as insurgents
Patriots who come carrying the american flag
To the people's house
Are branded as insurgents
And they're tried under the insurrection act
You know what insurrection is insurrection is when 40 campuses in our country including all the ivy league and comparable universities
are taken over
by a group
That actually has its orders coming from a chinese front foundation
where a foreign power
is
organizing these takeovers
And doing it in support of an ideology
Whose maxim is death to america
And these people are burning american flags
Right and calling for the destruction of their own country
That is an insurrection
And these people as far as i am concerned
Need to be rounded up
And summarily tried not in civil courts because they have stripped themselves of their american citizenship
They need to be tried in military tribunals under conditions of martial law
That's what has to happen in this country under trump and if it doesn't we're fucked. It's over
It's over for this country and it's frankly going to be over for the west as we know it
So look civil war is a terrible thing
But unfortunately it's going to happen at this point and we need to make sure that we win it
Well
That's going to bring us to super chats right there
I think that you said everything that there is to say about our current situation
And what we're going to be
Expecting one quick note by the way is that the open society foundation and your source and all that
They despite you know, sores being jewish and whatever
Have no love towards israel or the west in general
And that is something that I think a lot of people who are watching this
Tend to forget they tend to lump jewish people into this
Whole pile where a lot of the horrible things that you're talking about right now
They see them as being the cause of
Let me add something there. Let me add something there. George Soros has
Ties in his youth to the romanian iron guard
George Soros has early affiliations to fascist right-wing groups in europe
Otto Scorzani in the 1970s early late 60s early 70s
Was doing some things with mosad in israel as well
Okay, there are complex business
And and military industrial
Connections here all across the world
The point to the fact that certain quote-unquote jews
Look, I know you're of the ukrainian
background and that you're sympathetic to the struggle of ukrainian people
But frankly the same thing can be said of zolinsky in terms of
fascist
Ultimately anti-semitic right-wing groups
using certain jews
In order to accomplish their aims and forward their agenda
And here I would direct people to the research of joseph farrell, which I've quoted and cited at length in some of my books
Now joseph is a dr. Farrell
is a
Russian orthodox adherent, okay, so from
And I you know, I visited ham at his home and we had very nice conversations on so forth
But you know dr. Farrell essentially would consider me a satanist. Okay, so we are we are not aligned
spiritually
And ethically in many ways however
his research on
What he calls di spena
Is impeccable di spena or the spider
Nickname for odessa the the order of former ss officers
Which was basically constituted in 1945
And was part of what what we have been what we have been introduced to as operation paperclip
There was a lot more going on in terms of the importation of nazis
post 1945
They developed a
global
financial control system
And a military industrial network that ultimately has succeeded in capturing the american deep state
And it is these people not the jews
Who are ultimately controlling?
The kind of policy making that's been detrimental to the west
Including in germany where merkel led in all these migrants if you look at the tentacles
Around the let's just let me just say it this way around the 9 11 operation
They go back to institutions like deutschbank
The bank of germany, okay, and you had you know
Martin borman hitler's financial mastermind who supposedly died three different times in three different ways
Still writing checks through chase Manhattan bank in argentina in the 1970s
Go look at joseph arles research the nazi international the european union and the third way
The people who have undermined the west
through
mass migration
Social justice agendas and so on so so forth are not jews
They're nazis
And their ultimate aim
Is to foment a backlash. They want a right-wing reaction that they intend
To ensure is traditionalist in character. This is a sophisticated
Dialectical operation that's taking place. It's what they were always masters at welton shang's creek
worldview warfare
Okay, so
So that's what I have to say about george soros and his ilk is that their pawns their pawns
of
An ss elite that not only survived the end of the war
It went on to ultimately create a hidden power structure in this world and its aim is a traditionalist
neo feudal hierarchical system that's going to crush the human individual
And israel is a bold work against that israel and its 300 nuclear warheads
The only thing I could say is that uh to all the jews who are still
Working in you know the new york crimes or any of these you know new republic all these magazines
I really recommend them to stop being such idiots because I really do think that unfortunately because jews as you know
They live in the city
And you can get all kinds of jobs the jobs you end up getting
The ones that people end up paying the most attention to just because of how information is disseminated would be jobs in the media
So unfortunately you have this weird situation where the people and I wonder I do wonder if what's going on right now
These protests are kind of waking some of these people up to their delusions
That those were the people who ended up rising through the ranks who were disseminating all of this uh, you know
anti-western
bullshit
That uh the unfortunate
Effect of that is that people look up their names and they do all these 4chan infographics saying that you know
Jonah goldberg or whoever you know once white people to go extinct and so on and so forth
So I don't know like as my final question before the super chats
Do you see any way of remedying that because it seems like until that's remedied
We're going to have all these people coming out of the woodwork saying like no, they're secretly against us
They want to overthrow the west. No, I do. I do see a way to remedy it. I do
And that's that I think that the prime minister net and yahoo and and people like defense minister galant and
The people who are you know looking into like how october 7th could possibly have been
Have have happened within mosad and israeli military intelligence
These because you see there were also
But israel has been betrayed
Israel's been betrayed by the kinds of jews in new york that you're talking about
Jews in la and but israel's also been betrayed by certain jews within israel
And right now israel has to win this war. That's this primary objective. It has to be achieved
Without hesitation israel has to win this war
But don't think there's not going to be a reckoning within israel after this war
There's a lot of soul searching that's going to take place and there's a massive purge that's coming within israel
that's what I think I think that
The right kind of leadership learned a really harsh lesson
And they know that they have a lot of traders in their midst
And they're going to clean these people out because these people represent an existential threat to zionism
They they represent an existential threat to the continued existence of a state of israel
All right, and I think they're going to need to be weeded out and what I also think is that
The right kind of zionists
Right people who are just looking to defend a state for people of jewish descent
The right kind of zionists are going to find a tremendous ally in the next regime of iran
A regime that represents the will of the majority of iranian people who love israel
They love america and they love israel
and
I think that
The kind of intelligence and security relationship that could exist again because it existed once between sabaq wasad
Very close relationship to the point where they were developing nuclear weapons together. That's a whole other story
but
There will be an intelligence and security relationship between the future iranian
services
Whether they want to I I'm partial to the idea of calling it sabaq again. I actually think that's a great idea
What does sabaq mean?
Oh, it just means
So I was one am yet of the et alata ke shfar. It means a state
security and intelligence service
But you know, it has a horrific aura to it because you know supposedly they tortured people and
You know engaged in all kinds of repression. Well, who were they who were they interrogating?
They were interrogating
A bunch of islamist cockroaches
Who have turned women into second-class who are beating women right now?
For exposing their hair, right? Islamists who have completely
Abrogated freedom of of the press and freedom of speech for the last 45 years in iran
Those are the people who they were severely interrogating. They were severely interrogating communists
Who wound who apparently were so faithful to their marxist principles their
atheistic humanistic
Universalist marxist principles that all these fucking iranian communists lined up to support a lunatic like ayatollah chomeini
And to bring a bunch of islamic fundamentalists to power those were the communists being interrogated by sabaq
All right sabaq was actually doing its job trying to actually the shah was the one who was too much of a bleak part liberal
Anyway, anyway be that as it may
My point is that the future iranian state security and intelligence apparatus will have an excellent relationship with mosad and shin bet and and you know the israeli
services
So that the iranians i think will be able to help weed out the wrong kind of israelis and the wrong kind of jews even in the united states
Who are undermining the security of israel
You know again to reiterate what i said earlier, you know addressing the american people
understand
That the domestic political situation in america is a vital national security concern of the future iran
The future iran is going to find itself immediately in conflict with china in conflict with russia
Without a europe that it can count on because europe is being taken over by islamists
Right so who is going to be iran's ally well america israel principally and also america
So the future iranian state security apparatus cannot very well allow america
To be a stage for protests
Then mirror the ideology and discourse of the islamic republic
understand
So the domestic political situation in america is going to be a vital national security interest of the future regime of iran
Let me leave it at that
Okay, and and that includes whatever misguided jews
There are who are you know aligning themselves with these apologists for hamas
Yeah, they uh drank the kool-aid just like all these really beautiful girls that i used to have a crush on and now
You see their instagram uh
Story is all like you know pro gaza. Yeah, you know what i mean
It's it's it's a it's a damn shame like like the song goes
One last thing i would say is that you know, believe me i know
Yeah, uh one last thing i would say regarding israel's that i would highly recommend
I'm sure they're doing it already for masa to take a look at people like romana brahmovich and look at all the
immigrants from russia
To israel as far as their effect because netanyahu himself has had too
Chummy of a relationship with uh putin and i think that's one of the things that misguided him keep in mind how often
russia's government including putin himself met with representatives of hamas and iran
Look, um, i i uh
I am certainly not in favor of the conflict in ukraine
spiraling into a potential nuclear confrontation between nato and russia that having been said
As you remember from our previous conversation
Where vlad was also with us vlad davinson. Yeah, yes, and we were discussing october 7th
I i told you that i think that
All these russian jews in the israeli state security apparatus
Who have ties to the kremlin and we know there are a lot of people in mosad who do they are double agents and they work for russian intelligence as well
I think uh
Something went very wrong that day and it did involve the russians
Um, and it was retribution for frankly netanyahu being dragged kicked and screaming by america to support ukraine
Uh, but but be that as it may. Yeah, I you know, there's a case to be made that
Uh, israel was betrayed by russian jews who ultimately were answering to the orders of the kremlin
And now russia's yeah, I can also tell you
I'm sorry to say this to the folks who are my final i have a lot of followers who support russia
But I can tell you that the future regime of iran is going to be an enemy russia. There's no question
There's and they're right across the kast me and c and by the way
By the way for people who don't have a sense of history the russians took a quarter of iran's territory
It's they fought
Two significant wars with iran and they're responsible for taking a quarter of iran's territory
So there's a lot of bad blood there and I can well see that there's going to be a future iranian-israeli alliance
Even just against russia
Well onto uh onto super chats we go so the first super chat is uh from somebody who
Did it last time? Uh, but I unfortunately was not able to get to it. So um, here remind me today
As a reminder my question was of jason has seen the mh 370 videos
That's the hidden tech held by the shadow government and before uh, you respond jason once again
Make sure to like subscribe comment click the bell the bell is very important. Uh, anyway, uh, jason, uh, go ahead
I've seen it. I've heard analyses of it. Uh, I
Have listened to
intelligent people who I really respect
Who have uh, in some cases said they
They think it's legit and in other cases. Um other people who I respect equally
Uh have raised questions about you know, uh, the the legitimacy
And fidelity of that video
Um, whether or not that particular footage is is accurate, you know, it's it's showing these three UFOs
circling around mh 370 and basically creating a vortex which the airplane then disappears into
That's what it shows and supposedly it was leaked by a high level official
Um, and the footage was taken by classified satellites who were looking down at the area that the plane was transiting at the time
Whether or not that particular footage is legit. I think that technology exists
Hmm
Jane Dominic ten dollars
Questions for Jojani. Do you see any room for bacchic mania muse inspiration?
Jungian individuation or some form of serious promethean divinization in the future of philosophical inquiry
The hell do you think i'm doing
I mean, that's the core of my whole philosophical project. Yeah, that's pretty softball
Of course, I do. Yeah
Uh, all right moving on here. Uh, yeah, the ones that we could just answer fast. We could just answer fast
Austin ten bucks
Ethmogens have been administered in traditional cultures to aid in the development of these psychic abilities
Especially for individuals who struggle with the training
Uh, well comment any thoughts on it
It should be some combination thereof, you know, I mean the right drugs properly used as the Greeks called them pharma kea
you know, the right
Pharmacons properly administered
Um, together with various psychical training regiments are probably the way to go
Hmm, but that's drugs as a tool and the craft rather than as an escape
hmm
No, that's true because when it comes psychedelics, you don't want it to become a crutch
right
Or an escape form of escapism. Mm-hmm
Uh, cerulean valley. I don't know if this was a mistake
100 dollars. Thank you so much cerulean valley
Uh, okay. Here we go. They in quotes are more advanced in every field
Um, uh, you speak of ludite ism will be psychologically healthy for most inhabitants on this planet
You can't even astral project. It's not your choice
But just accept their traditionalist dominion over you
You will lose
First of all, I have astral projected second of all, uh
That's perfectly fine if traditionalism is going to be suitable for the majority of the planet in that case
I'm interested in eliminating the majority that are going to subjugate the minority of people who absolutely do not deserve to have their
Individuality subsumed by traditionalism. Okay. I am a radically anti-majoritarian person
I'm the furthest thing from a populist you can ever imagine. I am for the individual. I'm a radical individualist
Who's totally devoted to the defense of liberty and progress
so
Think again, okay, and I can also tell you that as I've had to incessantly repeat every time someone
Asks as if this is a question asks a question like this
That number one
Going back to what you asked me love about buddha, right many of our conversation number one
There's another class of beings opposed to the olympians
Or the devas namely the ashuras or the titans
They're in the mix here and they're very angry people. If you think i'm angry
You see what these people are like. This is why the buddhas depicted them as demons. I mean, they're very angry people very violent people
They've had nuclear wars in the past. You look at the mahabarata and the ramayana
and you look at uh, libyan desert glass
And you know various vitrified stones in south america
You can see the evidence for the nuclear wars between the ashuras and the devas in the distant past
so to begin with the ashuras are in the mix and
Look their policy is that they don't want to have to come in and solve the problem for us
They want to see some kind of human initiative and frankly
It's much better for us if we tried to determine
Our own future course and set the conditions for
You know securing our liberty by ourselves to the greatest extent possible
We don't want to be beholden to some group of titans or ashuras either. Remember prometheus is this rather
ambiguous trickster figure who initially betrays the titans
Decide with the gods and then turns on the gods to defend humanity, right?
So looking at it from a promethean perspective, I don't want us to be beholden to the ashuras
The the titans either
But they're in the mix and they're very powerful. They're very powerful
They're the reason why there's not a biosphere on mars anymore. Okay, so whoever quote, you know made this
Uh
statement is forgetting that and what's more important than that is that quite apart from the ashuras
You have this entity that I spent some time discussing which, you know, I come around to
Uh engaging with at the end of philosophy of the future this trickster this cosmic trickster and its various
avatars and emissaries and that force is so much more powerful than the debuts
And that's why when I talk about phenomenal authorization, I make the point that look
This trickster
Sees the movements of the devas
Not necessarily like movements of chess pieces across a chess board
Because the game is more like backgammon. It involves an element of chance a roll of the die
But it's kind of like a backgammon game except that the trickster
Can win but the trickster is interested in the game and the possibilities opened up by the game
Okay, so frankly the person who posed this who made this statement is utterly clueless
Hmm. Well, he thinks you're a heretic. That's the other thing. Well, I am a yeah. Well, he's right about that
Who I'm a Muslim. Yeah, and you can be born into any religion. I was born muslim
So I'm not just a heretic. I'm an apostate. He gets pretty rude over here
But if you'd like I can read you his five dollar chat right after the one hundred dollar one
Let's spend more time on somebody's
You know, who's
Yeah, yeah, the the cherry on top give other people. Yeah trial size dove
$10 seems to me the birth of humanity is a radically anomalous and finite event
With this entity working to coax as much growth potential from us before that energy dissipates
Say that again one more time sure lower. Okay. Here we go
Um
Seems to me the birth of humanity is radically anomalous and finite event
With this entity working to coax as much growth potential from us before that energy dissipates
It's a question of scale it goes back to when you were talking about we can imagine that there's a macrocosm that's you know
Has you know
Vast in such and such a way and there's all kinds of
intelligences that are potentially so far beyond ours and well, you know, you could imagine a context
That would render humanity
this relatively unexpected
and
anomalous
Phenomenon which this trickster is taking great pains to
Cultivate right and to nurture albeit, you know as a very severe mother
That's you could imagine that but again you're imagining a context for which there's no empirical evidence
And when you look at the literature of close encounters, that's not
Of the picture that we get you know, I don't want to repeat myself like I said earlier
the close encounter phenomenon suggests that actually
humanity
or the evolution of humanity
into a potentially
superhuman species
Is at the center of the cosmos that it's the central phenomenon of existence
Chester ten dollars
Ca, ca, that is uh, that is chester right there. Uh, great friend of the show
Um, next we have ashton milky way 50 dollars
Sorry jason, but how can you look at the Rothschild history of banking and the history of banking in general?
And say that the jews are not the ones controlling the system. I think you're foolish for believing in their propaganda
Read joseph arles books. He also has
Uh texts that are specifically
Dedicated to the history of banking
Like the financial vipers of venice
um, and
When you read his work on the development of the international banking system
In the context of his tracing the genealogy of what you might call the fourth Reich
This occulted Reich, which i've written about
You can see
To what extent various banking families including ones of jewish descent were assimilated and ensconced by this essentially
uh
I don't even want to call it fascist. I don't know
Nazi post-nazi system, right? Um
Joseph's work is is what you should look at if you're interested in actually understanding what's going on here
And so i'll just leave it at that. Hmm. That would be the same author to look at as far as um hitler being funded
Because it's weird like i was watching this uh gentleman on youtube named tick history
and he tries to make well first of all he makes the case that uh, uh,
Nazi germany was very socialist in how it operated
But the second thing is that he tries to say well hitler was not funded by any of these rich people
It was a very grass roots movement, you know, they raised their money from the people
shit
I mean look the thula gazelle shaft consisted of a bunch of barons and aristocrats
And it's the thula gazelle shaft that set up the nsdap as a as a pack as a political action committee
To help fight communism on the streets of germany. So we you know, we know that the
Planning the master mining of the rise of hitler came from very rich people with international banking connections
Though hitler himself was not a big fan of the uh aristocracy at least from what i understand
There was this a lady who i think you met as well at that event that we were at
Who talked about how um her father was this german aristocrat?
He was a general and hitler used to pin medals on him in such a way as to puncture his, uh, skin
And she interpreted that as being his hatred for this upper echelon
He was a rabble rouser who had a very specific purpose and
mission to fulfill
They used him
Okay, and that became abundantly clear to the sad broken man when he was put out to pasture in bariloche argentina
in 1946
Until listen hair hitler just paint your sunsets leave it to us. We've got it all under control
Okay, i think he lived a very sad last 20 years of his life down there in, uh, argentina
And it became abundantly clear to him that he had been played and used by people
Whose machinations he could not even begin to wrap his mind around and those people are still in control of our world today
Damn
Well, uh, we're here. We have fin brown ten dollars
So we have two remaining here unless anybody sends anything else. These would be the last two so fin brown
$10 thoughts on the concept of a live live player
non npc types
Thoughts on npc's no no no the live player so the opposite of what an npc is
What about what thoughts i mean out of the concept like what exactly entails a live player well in your book
you were writing about
consciousness and
Whether you see there being like this great asian of consciousness where people who would be more like the npc's
Would have less of it and people would who would be more of the players to have more of it or is it much more distinct?
individuality
Personal conscience
You know self reflection
critical thinking
Above all creative vision
Right all the things that these protesters we see in the streets today lack
And by the way, I just want to make one point that I neglected to make earlier
Is that because a lot of you know underserting people will say oh, but what about you know
The communists who took over columbia university in 1968 and so forth, you know on behalf of the students for a democratic society sds
Or let's say the activities of the weather underground
Completely different completely different. Look
Uh, you don't have to be a communist or agree with communism to understand why
Dropping napalm on vietnamese children was not a just war. Okay, the vietnam war was an unjust war
Okay, at least at least
One can understand a person who takes that position and protests the war
And also if you look at the doctrine of classic communism going back, you know to marx supposedly
However misguided you may think it is
It's ultimately
an aspiration for
liberation and enlightenment and an egalitarian
world society where you know women have more equal after all look the soviet union sent women into space
Way before we did okay
So there are things that you can respect about classic communism and about the communists who took over columbia university in 1968
The cockroaches and vermin and parasites today who have desecrated those places
Have also hollowed out anything that was respectable about communist ideology
They have in fact imploded communist ideology by aligning themselves to the most traditionalist and retarded
You know religious tradition on the planet namely islam
And by the way, this is a rerun for me
It's a horrific rerun because all of us who have some iranian heritage saw this happen in iran in 1978 1979
We're all the fucking leftists suddenly somehow forgot marx and got behind ayatollah homani and the molas
That's why we have an islamic republic today. It's the leftists in iran who brought the islamic republic to power
They were the firepower behind it. They were the guerrilla fighters who toppled the shah's regime not these turbans molas
It's the leftists who did it. So look, I don't know what that says. I don't I won't blame marx for it though
If you look back in my work, you see I actually you respect marx a great deal
The thing is that his followers have now come to the point where
Evidently, you know, they've become the the epitome of these zombie NPCs
And so I don't see, uh, you know a legitimate future for leftists
And the ussr was also supporting palestine back in the day era fat was an agent of the soviets
No, okay, but that's not there because the ussr was also the first and greatest supporter of the state of israel
That's true. Well, that's before israel
You could say kind of betrayed it
Yes, so is the soviets felt betrayed by israel because actually the soviets were the first supporters of israel
before
France and france became the second strongest supporter of israel and then united states only really started supporting israel after canadi
No, that's true. Yeah, you have a point there. So, uh, over here, although
I
Do remember reading that the soviets were also the ones who coined the term palestinian, but that's like going in a whole
Rabbit hole as far as where these terms originate from, you know, well the woman's going to turn palestinian
No, I mean like palestinian in the context of what happened after israel, you know, as far as like the palestinian people versus the
Yeah, well, no, I wouldn't I wouldn't be shocked that that came out of some soviet propaganda office. So here we have a
Valhulm 10 dollars
How does the world that results out of the niches split of humanity into ubermench and entermench?
Is any
Functionally different than what the davis have constructed with their breakaway civilization
Because what the davis are envisioning is a hierarchical caste society where there are different rungs of human beings in that society
Okay, until you get to the highest rung which is a a priestly class the brahmin whose sole purpose is to serve the davis
It's a caste hierarchy. What niches talking about is essentially the destruction of humanity
through
The under mention becoming a machinery of production. These aren't human beings anymore. We're not talking about human beings anymore
It's it's a completely
It and by the way, niches doesn't describe this a great length because it's right at the margin
Of what he can really what he's really capable of contemplating
In terms of how technological advancement is going to alter the human condition
There are a few notes on this in the will to power mainly
Where you see him describe how the machinery of production as he puts it is going to ensconce and transform
the under mention into a
base upon which
The ubermen pursue their own destinies
But the ubermen are not slave masters
The under mention are not slaves of the ubermen nicha really belabors this point niches
Entire ethical doctrine is a critique of slave morality
Right and an advocacy for a kind of
Morality where the individual sets his own goals and purposes and is not dependent upon
Basically, you know oppressing and manipulating anybody else. Yeah
Okay, so so it's a radically different vision
Actually, it's a much
And I've said this before it's a much harsher vision because to the extent that most people don't want to be free
And most people want to be cattle and most people are sheep
Well, then the dave of vision is much more compassionate because it accommodates that majority inside this pyramid
Nietzsche's vision is saying listen either evolve or you're going to be a machine
Next super chat over here we have uh from uh kalab
Your uh ten dollars your thoughts about the global loss of res publica
And its replacement in the internet where the public ceases to
Check and balance richard senates the fall of public man comes to mind
Look, I think that the republic first of all the republic was a noble idea
Especially if we take care to discern
um, you know
To to make a distinction between a republican constitutional structure and a democracy
The kind of republican constitutional structure that the founding fathers of the united states articulated in our constitution and our bill of rights
was a very noble minded
Uh and progressive endeavor in the proper sense of the word progressive which I entirely embrace
And intend to safeguard against these retarded leftists
But the fact of the matter is that even by the middle of the 20th century with the rise of
you know
instantaneous global banking and military industrial corporations and mega corporations and you know
You know supersonic air travel and so on and so forth
And and the and attendant global business class and
Such developments
Already rendered the republic an antiquated form of political organization. That is the case
Uh, it was already the case in the 1950s, frankly
And certainly as we approach the technological singularity, we're going to have to consider
A new form of political organization that safeguards the liberty and creative potential of the individual
um, and that replaces republics
And that replaces nation states as we've conceived of them thus thus far, right?
Now I don't want that to be any kind of world government
but
We need to come up with a a
A replacement for the republic that at the same time
In spirit safeguards what it is that let's say the bill of rights of our republic was intended to protect
So I don't see the
The obsolescence of the republic of the res publica as a necessarily
negative
Development I see it as an evolutionary
eventuality
And as far as the internet is concerned
I think the problem with the internet is that the worldwide web is increasingly controlled by mega corporations
and that
What we need to do is develop blockchain networks
That use the fundamental substrate technology of the internet in ways that
Are impervious to corporate and other centralized control
Absolutely. So here we have ashton milky way 20 dollars
How can we possibly prepare for the technological singularity and the coming catastrophe in the next 20 years?
Who is we?
One of the point and you've heard me say this yes, yes
one of the points that I I always make is that
Considering that we have maybe 15 maybe 20 years
Between us and the technological singularity at this point. I keep revising my estimate downward
There's no way that the world can prepare
There's no way
Simply impossible the vast majority of people
Who are either adherents of islam by 20 again? I repeat the statistic
Given current demographic trend and by the way people should remember this every time they call what's going on in gaza a genocide
The palestinians are arabs
majority of them arab muslims
There are 22 arab countries in the world all of which by the way refuse to take in these palestinians
okay
And beyond the arab world. There are gigantic countries like malaysia
indonesia pakistan
That are host to huge muslim populations. India has more muslims in it than pakistan
Okay, so we are dealing with a population bomb here
Which is going to result in it and by the way when you think about you know
These people's proposals to turn the united nations into a global democracy
Well, what the fuck would a global democracy be in 2075 when the majority of people on the earth are muslim?
So every time these morons talk about what's going on in gaza as a genocide
they ought to remember that a
muslim majority on this planet by 2075 means the genocide of
Every other culture on earth because we know and especially we who have an iranian heritage know
That what islam does is genocide other cultures the specialty of islam is the genocide of other cultures
And we we see it just recently in iraq with isis what they did to the Kurds
By the way, recently there was a story that made me absolutely incensed
as if you know as if there isn't enough to be incensed about story of a
Kurdish woman
Who was raped and held captive by isis in northern iraq
And she wrote this book and she was supposed to give a presentation about it. I believe it was in canada
And her book event
Was cancelled because they were afraid
It would promote islamophobia
So this poor woman who was tortured and raped by isis
Doesn't get to tell her story about what muslims are like because it might promote fear of islam
Just we we are living already in an orwellian 1984 world. It is as bad as that
Oh, all I could say is as that all I could say is that the people who are afraid of confronting these kind of things
Get what they deserve
Because if you are not afraid and you are willing to accept the consequences and fight for what you believe in
Yes, there's going to be pushback
But at least you could actually sleep at night knowing that you're not going to uh, you know
Be one of these uh yellow bellied cowards who just allow all of this uh to go on
Yeah, but to answer your question, sure, they're gonna get what's coming. So but to answer your question, the problem is this
In the face of the technological singularity
15 to 20 years from now
How do you expect that the world or people at large people writ large when you say that
Are going to prepare for the singularity
when
increasingly, uh, you know, we have a muslim majority on the planet
And uh, the rest of the people are either confusion chinese
Who are ultimately as regressive and uh inimical to change and progress
And we have uh, putin with 3000 nuclear warheads embracing russian orthodoxy
And then we see what's going on in the west
Where there's mass conversion to islam in europe
And there's american university students going around
uh
chanting death to america slogans from a fundamentalist islamic regime and and uh converting to islam
under the palestinian flag
so
What what world what world prepare for the technological singularity? No, no, no, no, no
A small minority
of people with promethean
foresight and forethought
Who care about preserving their own liberty
And maximizing their own creative potential
Are gonna band together as a group of rebels
Like the rebels who set the american revolution in motion
And we are gonna defend our future our future at any cost
Liberty or death
Austin ten dollars is there any chance that iran rid itself of the horrific theocracy now in place?
And restore its traditional empire and dignity as a great culture and civilization between east and west
And that's going to be like the final super chat before that cherry on top that we uh talked about but yeah
Of course it will happen
Of someone who's worked for that for many years of my life
I can tell you it will most certainly happen
but
There is in that process an absolutely
integral and indispensable role to be played by the state of israel
And everyone who wants to see that iran come into being has to understand
That it is inextricable
From support for zionism
Um
Lastly uh speaking of that before the cherry on top
Could you please tell because I know that you said it before I want to make sure that I got this because that's the one thing that I missed
When I was talking about um
Uh humab adin and the muslim brotherhood
What was the connection between what was going on in the obama administration back then
And obviously I think the biden administration is kind of a continuation of that
And what we're seeing right now with these protests and getting rid of the um all references to islam within the counter terrorism manuals
Well, I think I addressed it already
I told you that from my years of working in the iranian opposition where we engaged in significant lobbying activities
At one point I was even sitting with a member of the national security council
But I can tell you that the democrats very clearly have a pro islamist agenda
And they want to keep for example the islamic republican power in iran
So so what do they get for it? What's stated in that direction?
But what do they
What do they obtain by taking that kind of position at the end of the day?
What's their carrot at the end of the stake? Is it just money? Is it power?
Money and power they they get financed and they get to win elections
It's the same reason why they bring, you know millions of migrants into our country
They're trying to demographically re-engineer our country so that they can stay in power staying in power means getting more money
It's just a racket for these people. I mean they're corrupt. They use political office as a way to amass wealth
That's all it is
They're a mafia and they don't give a fuck about the future or our children's future, you know, that's all they are a bunch of looters
Uh now to uh serrillion valley who's been super chatting all of this time
Uh serrillion valley
Now you said before that you are up to hearing a super chats here, but they do get a little bit spicy
Towards you
You know, uh
I don't think that's a good note to end on I think that a better note to end on would be yet again for me to
Direct people to the american colossus not just website american colossus.org
But also to the american colossus substack. We have an american colossus substack
Uh that features a number of very interesting articles
ranging
All the way from commentaries on this catastrophic
domestic political situation
There's a whole piece that I wrote uh against the, you know, woke social justice warriors
All the way to um a new piece that I've written on the close encounter phenomenon. There's an essay called the
airships of prometheus
on the american colossus substack
Where I actually go back and revise
Well, I wouldn't say I revise my thesis. I present an alternative
Uh interpretation and hypothesis
concerning the airship mystery of 1890
Uh 1896 1897, which I know is something that you and I have discussed before and you took the time to try to find
The families of some of the dentists isn't calling back. I gotta try again, but I appreciate you remembering that. Yeah
So folks, go take a look at those articles and uh, please do subscribe to the american colossus substack
there will be a lot of
A lot of good news
Coming
And you can buy dr. Johnny's book
A philosophy of the future
The link is in the description and once again if you want to see the q and a the exclusive q and a in the new york city
Apartment, uh, that uh, dr. Johnny was kind enough to do with uh, me and neil nazik informant
Go to patreon.com slash break the rules become a patron today any tier doesn't matter and you will be able to get that
As well as uh, if you guys become a $20 patron and you're in the new york city area
There's going to be all kinds of events that i'm going to be doing on break the rules
I uh, sincerely hope that uh, jason you will be a part of uh, some of those events if you're interested
Yeah, I look forward to the next q and a we do when I get back to new york
At some point in summer
Yeah, my plan is that I would want to throw certain events where obviously I would vet people first
You know just to get to know like who these people are just that they're not crazy people
But then get them, uh, you know as an audience in this uh
Apartment because everything is set up so wonderfully. They're now jason. There's no more tripods
All the cameras are suspended on the ceiling and on the wall
And it's all wired up and uh, no wires on the floor whatsoever
So it's a completely free space to walk around in I'll be providing white claws. I'll be providing food
So you guys just come in attend. There's a rooftop. We can party on the roof afterwards
So it's going to be a great time. So once again, that's patreon.com slash break the rules
I'll invite you guys to some preliminary events before that later on just like for all the new people
But yeah, go there and also the discord. That's another thing that I don't really talk about that much
But uh, if you guys go to um the discord link that I do have in the description and I'm going to show to you as well
Then uh, you are going to have a good time getting to know some of the other people
From the break the rules universe. Here is the discord link. So guys, thank you so much
Be sure to like comment subscribe click the bell
Dr. Jason Rezger Johnny as always it is a great pleasure speaking with you
The pleasure is always mine levin. I look forward to hanging out with you again in new york