Hi everyone, welcome to the Power Hungry podcast.
I'm Robert Brice on this podcast.
We talk about energy, power, innovation, and politics, and I'm pleased to welcome back
for the third time.
That's right, ladies and gentlemen, the third time, Dr. Judith Curry.
She is the author of a new book called Climate Uncertainty and Risk, Rethinking Our Response.
Judy, welcome back to the Power Hungry podcast.
Well, thank you.
I'm delighted to join you again.
So your book has been out now a couple of months, and it's called, as I said, Climate
Uncertainty and Risk, Rethinking Our Response.
You've been on the podcast before, but guests on this podcast, I think you remember, introduced
themselves.
So you've been on here once, but imagine you've got 30, 60 seconds, you've walked into a room,
you don't know anyone.
Introduce yourself, please.
Okay.
I'm Judith Curry.
I spent most of my career in academia, most recently at the Georgia Institute of Technology,
where I was chair of school of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences for 13 years.
I'm currently president of Climate Forecast Applications Network.
I'm proprietor of the blog Climate Etc. at JudithCurry.com and author of a new book,
Climate Uncertainty and Risk.
Very succinct.
Well done, Attagirl.
And you're also on Twitter, so we get this out of the way, at CurryJA.
At CurryJA.
Okay.
Well, I'm going to just tell me, you know, I've been reading your book, give me your
pitch.
What is this new book about?
We've talked before on the podcast, we've talked about climate science, media, et cetera.
What is this book and what do you hope to achieve with it?
Well the whole climate science issue and the policy response has been squeezed into this
little tiny box, you know, with everybody bouncing around inside the box dotting eyes
and crossing T's and threatening anybody who tries to go outside the box.
Well, I blow the lid off the box.
I look at all the other stuff that people, the inconvenient things that people are trying
to shove under the rug.
I look at the uncertainties.
I look at the controversies.
I look at why we disagree, both in the science and the policy response.
I talk about, you know, how politics of this has really torqued this in a very unfortunate
way.
I talk, the middle part of the book, I look at, speculate about what we can expect in
the 21st century in terms of climate.
I mean, the climate models are deeply flawed in terms of giving us a reliable perspective
on this.
I speculate, you know, on a whole range of possible outcomes, including plausible worst
cases.
And the third part of the book is the most important one really, it's risk and response.
And this is where I talk about how we've fundamentally mischaracterized climate risk and how we've
fundamentally mismanaged our response.
And I use principles from a variety of risk science disciplines to put together a menu
of some other approaches that we can take that make more sense when you're dealing with
a very complex, deeply uncertain problem with conflicts of values and political disagreements
in play.
So, you know, it's a very different approach, and it's a very integrated approach to this
very wicked problem that I think can lead us on a path to doing sensible things and
setting our path towards a prosperous and safe 21st century.
That's a good summary.
Thank you.
Looking at the book, though, and as I've been going through it, and I don't mean this
as a slam, but we talked about it right before we started recording.
You said this was written or published by an academic press, Anthem Press, and it's heavily
footnoted.
And I got to say, I love me some footnotes, right?
I have footnote all my books.
It's a laborious process.
So well, this is a kind of a geeky question.
I could tally them all up here, but about how many footnotes are in this book?
Roughly.
About 1500.
1500 in 239 pages.
So you have your references here, which I think you made clear.
You wanted to publish this book before we started.
You said you wanted it published by an academic press, that it was peer reviewed, and everything
here you've stated is all fully cited.
But still, I mean, the fundamental issue that, and we've talked about this before, is that
we're seeing this lack of robust debate, or even any debate, really, and that most recently
John Clouser, who won the Nobel Prize in physics in just in June and August, had a speech,
a presentation to the International Monetary Fund that he was canceled because he's not
towing the line on the catastrophist orthodoxy.
If I can use that phrase, I mean, it seems rather than getting better, rather than the
debate getting slightly more open, it's getting even yet more constrained, or is that fair?
How have things changed?
Oh, that's correct.
I mean, we'll go back to the little box again.
And the reason it's all been shoved into a box, everybody has to agree, because the
oversimplified analysis that our brilliant policymakers have made is that we need global
collective action on this problem.
And in order to get there, everybody has to agree.
So, you know, so there's huge motivation with that framing of the problem to nuke anybody
who disagrees.
I just want to make sure you said oversimplified analysis.
Is that is that what you the phrase?
Right. So we have to nuke anyone who disagrees.
But that I think that seems to be the right right description as well, that there we will
not brook dissent, right?
But is that so you've talked about this in academic terms, because that's where you
come from this.
And I come at it from as a more, I would say just a more general reporter approach.
But if I were to say, well, what's driving this, I would say it's money, right?
That there is a lot of money at stake here for various subsidies under the Inflation
Reduction Act. This is one of the big drivers, of course, of the renewable energy rollout,
right? There are massive subsidies for wind and solar at hand.
So there must not be any controversy about this.
Otherwise, the sub that you stop the flow of the money is that an oversimplified analysis?
It's an oversimplified analysis.
I think we have to go back to the 1980s and the UN environmental program.
There was a big drive for non-governmental world control through health, environment,
and all these issues, and they keyed on climate change is the issue to get us there.
And we had a climate change treaty in 1992, the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change.
This was before the temperature even started warming in a significant way,
and the US even signed on to that treaty.
So from the very beginning, you've had the policy card way out in front of the scientific horse.
And this is a UN agenda. It's degrowth. It's anti-capitalism. It's anti-democratic.
And in order to enforce this, they amp up the alarm.
I mean, the worst rhetoric, I mean, apart from extinction, rebellion, or something like that,
comes from you and officials, global boiling, code red, all of this kind of stuff over a slow creep
of warming. And the agenda is to kill off the fossil fuel industry. They don't like that.
They don't like nuclear either. So this is a real, it's a clash of values.
And there was a recent survey of university climate scientists, and they asked them a
bunch of questions. And a majority of them were in favor of degrowth, not green growth,
but degrowth. Okay, so you can see the perspectives of these people. I mean, it's not necessarily
about money. There is certainly an element of, you know, follow the money and all this.
But there's a whole worldview and an ideology behind all this.
That's interesting. I guess, so maybe what, I mean, in your reply, I'm not going to argue with it at all.
That is more on the science kind of policy side. I guess what my point about the money and the
subsidies is on the deployment side, right? On the amount of money that's available for the
mitigation side, right? Which was where there's staggering numbers, now hundreds of billions
of dollars, whether it's electric vehicles or solar or wind or hydrogen or carbon capture.
I mean, it's just a staggering amount of money. I think it's the biggest corporate giveaway in
American history, and there's no second place here. But your points are more on the policy side
about this ideology that's driving this alarmism, I guess, to put it, is that a fair way to
characterize it? Yes, yes. Oh, there's definitely money in play. And, you know, Warren Buffett
was very cynical. I mean, he was an early investor in wind power. Sure. He liked wind power, but
he saw it with all these subsidies and whatever, I'm going to make money. He's no dummy.
The only reason to build wind turbines is to collect the tax credits, right? He said that
very clearly, right? That was his famous line. Okay, well, so I live in Texas, and let me tell
you, it feels a little apocalyptic. And let me just tell my climate, what is my view on climate
change? Climate change is a concern. And I think it rhymes with what your book says. Climate change
is a concern. It's not our only concern. So not that I don't favor action on climate change,
is that it's a concern, but we have to balance our action on that against other concerns. And I
think if I were to boil down what I see in your book, you're saying something somewhat similar,
and I'm not trying to put words in your mouth. But it's been stinking hot here in Texas this summer,
Judy. I mean, it's just been, and I'm used to the heat. I lived in Texas, I'm from Oklahoma.
Okay, so here's the question. Is it possible that the Hunga Tonga volcano eruption in January 2022
is in part responsible for the weather or this hot weather that we're seeing now?
Okay, first off, Texas is an anomaly. If you look at the average temperatures over the summer so far
for the US, we're slightly below normal. I mean, you look at the set. I have to move then is what
you're saying. The US has been cool. So you know, Texas is just bad luck. I did my latest blog post
that's up, looks at what is causing all this more on a global level. And it looks Hunga Tonga,
and it looks at the ship fuels, and it looks like the long wave and the radiation budget at the top
of the atmosphere, it looks at the surface energy balance, it looks at the internal modes of climate
variability. It's a very comprehensive discussion of what's going on. To get back to Hunga Tonga,
Hunga Tonga usually volcanoes spew particulates into the atmosphere, which in the stratosphere,
and that has a cooling effect. Well, Hunga Tonga spewed only a little bit of sulfate and a substantial
amount of water vapor into the stratosphere. So right now in the summer hemisphere, it looks
like the effects of Hunga Tonga on the radiation balance are canceling out, you know, the long
wave and the short wave are canceling out. But if you go to the winter hemisphere, the southern
hemisphere, we are seeing the effects of Hunga Tonga because the long wave infrared effects are
dominating. And you see it in a, this is part of the circulation pattern that's giving us an early
ozone hole and is giving us the low extent of the Antarctic sea ice this winter. So Hunga Tonga,
and we may see a bigger effect of Hunga Tonga in the northern hemisphere during our winter.
So that, but if you're interested in that, you know, check out my blog, judithcurry.com,
I've got a whole long post on all this. I see. Well, I just found it. It was posted August 14.
I was looking at your other blog post. It's with Jim Johnstone and Mark Jelenek, I guess,
is that that's the one you're talking about? Right. Yeah. Okay. I didn't have time to look at that
one. I was also looking at the post you did on the hell versus Montana lawsuit, which I want to
talk about as well. Okay. So I just want to read back. So you're saying I can't blame the hot weather
in Texas on Hunga Tonga. No, it's unfortunate circulation patterns. Okay. So well, and that's,
but isn't, I guess, me even asking this question, as I say it, am I, this is part of the issue,
right? Well, why can't we blame this on that? Isn't this, of course, to be due to that, that
there's, like everybody else, I'm like, well, tell me the cause, right? Or is this, you know,
and the Bill McKibbins of the world will gladly say, Oh, well, see, there you go.
You know, you guys in Texas, or in fact, Mark Goodell and the pages of the New York Times,
kind of, he said, in fact, in his piece, that this is, oh, this is like, you're getting payback.
Now, this is you're getting Texas is getting paid back for being a bad guy, right? That this is
like, this is the cause. Is this, is this part of the whole problem? Well, okay, here's the issue.
We're talking about a very complex, chaotic nonlinear system. And not only do we have a
chaotic atmosphere, it's coupled to a chaotic ocean. And it's subject to
changes in external forcing. And the mathematicians, you know, call this
pandemonium, it's even beyond chaos. And trying to unravel causes and effects
is, you know, not impossible, but it's not simple. You know, you can't do this by waving your arms.
Like the analysis in my blog, you know, it unravels a lot of things. And it gives you a sense of how
difficult it is to attribute any specific things to any specific forcing. It's very challenging.
Well, okay, so fair enough. And you have 17 figures in this, in this posting here.
But I guess maybe I'm, my, my desire for that simple solution is reflective of this kind of
broader societal design. Well, of course, this means that, and therefore, we have broad terms,
the way I see a lot of the climate apocalyptic analysis, we've sinned, now we're suffering,
and we're going to pay the price. And therefore, we have to repent, right? That this is,
there's a lot of kind of Christian echoes of what, you know, sin and redemption here, right? And
is that part of the narrative as well, that why this narrative is so strong?
This is the policymakers back in the 1990s, wanting a simple cause and effect and a simple fix.
And it was also the hubris that they can control the climate by, you know, eliminating fossil fuels.
So it's looking for a simple solution and just a total lack of humility and thinking that we can
actually control this. So, you know, it's just, you know, human failing. It's not surprising.
That's why we have scientists to sort all this out. But when the scientists become political
activists and become active in trying to cancel anyone who disagrees with them,
then the whole thing falls apart. And we end up with nonsense, like we're currently facing.
And when you say the nonsense, we're currently facing, so, okay, force rank the nonsense for me,
if you would, then if we're looking at policy responses to climate change, and we've heard
repeatedly from the Biden administration, this is our main concern, right? And, you know,
the president, in fact, at a League of Conservation Voters meeting at a high dollar fundraiser,
I wrote about this on my substack, bragged about the fact that the Export-Import Bank of the United
States was giving a $900 million loan to build a solar project in Angola. Never mind that 60%
of the people who live in Angola don't even have electricity and we're building them a coal,
a solar plant, not a coal plant, not a gas-fired power plant, even though Angola has
all kinds of natural gas. Okay, all this nonsense. So, force rank the nonsense. If you look at this
survey of what our responses, our policy responses have been, what's the silliest of the silly?
Well, this rapid rush to wind and solar, I mean, that's the silliest of the silly. I mean, you know,
I think it makes sense to think, to look forward, you know, into the 21st century and figure out how
we can, you know, improve our energy infrastructure so that we have, you know, more abundant, cheaper,
cleaner energy and let's look forward and try to get there. I mean, that's just going to help
support our progress in the 21st century. That's going to require research and development and
learning curves and different localities and countries experimenting and, you know, at the,
by the end of the 21st century, if the market was left to, you know, take care of all this,
we'd probably have a much better, cleaner energy infrastructure. But now that we're,
you know, tearing what we have down and replacing it with wind and solar, which is totally inadequate,
I know I'm preaching to the choir here, we're setting ourselves up to make ourselves more
vulnerable to whatever weather or climate extremes nature might throw at us. I mean,
electricity helps keep us safe, you know, with desalination plants and air conditioning and on
and on it goes. And it's also electricity is the source of our, you know, innovations across
everything. So I mean, what we're doing is extremely stupid and we've got politicians in
charge of all this wind and solar stuff and nobody's talking to the engineers, you know,
people who, who design transmission lines, the grid operators, you know, they're all sort of
tearing their hair out over all this wind and solar. So what we're doing is just plain stupid.
And if we continue on this path, we're going to end up in a worse place at the end of the 21st
century than if we had just let market forces and our desire for innovation just to take charge
and move forward. So it's just a very bad place to be. Well, you are preaching to the choir,
but amen, sister, keep going. Hallelujah. Past the collection plate. I'd boil that down,
how I distill this is if, if, if we're facing more extreme weather, it's the height of foolishness
or the depth of foolishness to make our most important energy network dependent on the weather.
I mean, we need weather, we need weather resilient systems, not weather dependent systems. And yet
that is in fact what we're doing. And just in the last few days here in Texas has been insanely hot
and the wind is going and the wind doesn't blow when it's really hot. And so there's been a, you
know, wind energy, we have a huge fleet of wind energy turbines. And yet they're only producing
at single digit percentage outputs during times of peak demand. So anyway, I just had to had to
throw that in there. Okay, so let's talk about censorship because you also know a little bit
about this. We talked, I think the last time you were on the podcast, which was in December of 2022,
that in on Twitter, you, you were very pleased that Elon Musk had Elon Musk took over Twitter
because suddenly you got more traction there, you weren't being throttled, your content wasn't
being throttled. Is that still the case now? Do you, have you gotten more followers on Twitter?
Tell me about how you see what's going on just on that platform. And then we'll talk about other
things. Okay, just from my perspective, Twitter's going along great. I know a lot of people don't
like it. Well, they don't like, you know, the climate scientists don't want to have the rabble
questioning them. And they don't like that. And a lot of them are leaving Twitter. Also,
Elon has made a couple of changes to the functionality treat decks. Okay. And a lot of
people are very unhappy with that. So some people are leaving, but this the overall,
you know, from where I sit, I think it's so much improved. And, you know, the quality of my
interactions and the number of my followers has increased very substantially. So I'm happy.
And I have to say that's the only social media platform that I'm happy with.
Well, then let's talk about the others then you were on John Stossel's show. And it was,
was it censored on Facebook? Tell me what this has been several days ago or a couple of weeks
ago, but it was labeled as false information. And this was me talking about my experiences and
my perspective. So I don't know how you label this as false information. So, and that was,
you know, they still left the link where you could click there. But there was this big warning
that this was false information because everybody knows that the consensus exists 97% of climate
scientists agree or whatever. No, there's no debate. I was on a podcast earlier this year
with the Heartland Institute. Right. And this was, it was live. And they, as soon as it started,
they took it down. Facebook did Facebook and they were sensitized to me because like about
two weeks earlier, I, there was a something posted on YouTube. It was an interview by
business news in South Africa. And it went sort of viral. I mean, it got like 500,000 views
in a couple of days. And then YouTube took it down. You couldn't even search for it. Okay,
you couldn't search for it at all. There was no message, no nothing, you couldn't search for it.
So that must have raised some sort of flag to Facebook. So as soon as they saw me being a guest
on the Heartland podcast, they just canceled that live feed. And they, you know, so I'm being
really canceled, you know, by the Mark Zuckerberg type social media. So, you know, and what I say,
if you actually listen to what I say, it's pretty innocuous. I mean, it's not cheerleading, you know,
for the team, but you know, I'm just raising some critical questions. And that's very uncomfortable.
I mean, I'm well outside that little box. And that makes people uncomfortable. And they view me
as a threat. I mean, all those footnotes in my book, you know, it's like evidence sort of supporting
my points. And you know, they view this as sort of dangerous. Well, in the way you speak, in what
you're talking about it, and yes, as I've done, you know, a couple hundred podcasts, and I'm a dad,
and you know, been married a long time. I listen to how people listen to how they say what they're
talking about, right? The words matter, of course, but it's, but there was the tone in your voice
about what I describe it, disappointment, anger, frustration. Here's the, you know, the TV journalist
favorite, how do you feel? How do I say that? I'm just kind of joking about it. But I can sense
of you a kind of an outrage or just a disappointment. How does it make you feel?
Well, you know, I'm a scientist, you know, and reason, dialogue, evidence, debate, and especially
in universities, you know, debate and disagreement is the spice of academic life. And all that's
been canceled. You know, it's the universities which discuss me even more than social media. I mean,
social media is social media, but it's what's going on at the universities to me is the absolute worst.
I'm seeing a few of the universities turn around, but the overall tenor at universities is just
terrible. And, you know, you saw this whole dynamics play out with the COVID situation. It's
just endemic to our society right now. And it's very dangerous and free speech issue, political
freedom, you know, there's a lot of issues here. And unfortunately, a lot of this gets tied up in
what's going on with Donald Trump. And, you know, then it just becomes a big political mess.
But these are very serious issues. And I mean, how I mean, God bless Elon Musk for trying to open up
Twitter. He has his own quirks and whatever. But overall, this is like the one place where people
from across the spectrum still come and, you know, engage and look at, you know, a broad range of
material everywhere else, or most other places. It's in a pretty sad state. How are we going to
get anywhere if we don't think critically and engage in constructive debate and discussion?
You know, what you said about Twitter, I think we talked about this last time,
but Alina Chan and Matt Ridley, who wrote a book called Viral on COVID,
they said the same things about the importance of Twitter in terms of this opening the debate
around origins of COVID. And now, which clearly seems to be, as I think they suspected all along,
a lab leak, right? Or the result of some kind of a lab leak from the Wuhan Institute of Virology.
But they were being censored almost everywhere else, except on Twitter. And this is before Musk took
over. But that lack of critical debate, the free and open debate, I have to agree with you. And
because we're messing with the most important system in our society, which is our energy network,
and we're making it, we're weakening it and spending hundreds of billions of dollars in
the weakening of it, right? Because of the fashion of, and it is fashion, and the way I would talk
about it, I guess, the, I call it climatism and renewable energy fetishism, right? That we have
this combined isms, right there that are, have replaced what has, I would call traditional
conservation, conservation, the traditional conservation ethic. And that's one of the things
that I'm with you exactly on wind and solar. There's this insane headlong rush toward these two
sources of intermittent weather dependent renewables. And with no regard for land use birds,
landscapes, view sheds, it's this, oh, well, this is the, this is the cure. And therefore,
anyone who stands in the way, we're going to run over. And it is almost that bold in terms of,
I mean, some of the states are even saying they're going to override local zoning laws to force
communities to take wind and solar projects they don't want, which just seems the absolute wrong
way to go in terms of democracy and process due, due process and so on. And I know I'm, I'm, I'm
rambling here, but does that ring, ring true to you? Oh, for sure. You summarized it perfectly.
I mean, this is, this whole thing is dangerous in so many different ways. I mean, not just to our
energy infrastructure, but to our freedom and our, the political way that we do things. I mean,
it's, it's a, it's a very slippery slope that we're sliding down. You said, I wrote it down,
you said the universities disgust me. And I reserve my disgust for a few things, lima beans and cauliflower
are two of them, but unpack that just a little bit for me when you say they disgust you. Why is
that? Well, because of the, the cancel, the cancel culture, all of the faculty members, you know,
very talented people can't get hired because they don't know how to write a good DEI essay, diversity,
equity and inclusion. And if you're a chemistry professor or something, what the heck, you know,
when you're talking about molecules, how do you bring that into your teaching? I mean, there's a
lot of stuff that doesn't make sense. They're allowing students to basically lead the charge to
get rid of faculty members that they don't like for some reason. They're interesting and provocative
speakers are getting disinvited because some students feel threatened by their words. And they,
and they pander to this, and they pander to this, people who are sort of skeptical of climate change
or in, in gen, in biology and right, all sorts of other fields. And I thought it was just really
climate change and biology, but people tell me it's rampant in law schools and social psychology
departments and political science departments that the same disease is rampant anywhere that
there is a that's socially relevant. When you're talking about that, it makes me automatically
think now of this held versus Montana lawsuit, which as I read the slump when I brought it up,
you were an expert witness or retained, I guess, as an expert witness in that case, and ultimately
did not testify. But when you're talking about the what's happening on the universities, the line
that comes into my head is grievance culture, right, that everyone's agreed. Everyone is a victim
somehow some way they've been offended or their future has been, been somehow clouded by this,
that or the other. That was in fact the claim, the legal claim that these teenagers made in
Montana that the state was injuring them and their potential, their future. And they won the
court case under the what seemed to be a fairly narrow ruling based on the Montana Constitution.
I know you wrote a blog post about that in June, but now we're here after the held versus Montana
litigation that they won and they Montana Attorney General said he's going to appeal.
How do you read that decision and how important is it?
Well, I don't think it's important. It might stand because the Montana Supreme Court
seems to be equally clueless and sympathetic to these environmental claims as the judge. So
it may not be overruled. If it stands, it's not going to have a big material
impact on what goes on in Montana in terms of changing the statute that they want to change
because Montana and principle, I mean, it just adds a lot of paperwork to everything Montana and
principle can still approve new power plants. It may, it may end up slowing down wind farms
by the same token with all this extra paperwork. I don't know, but it's a symbolic victory for
our Children's Trust, which is the advocacy group behind this case and it's given them fresh steam
because they've been around for 10 years and this is the first case where they got any kind of
attraction. You know, they've been thrown out. Their cases have been thrown out everywhere
until now. They're still pending in a few additional states, but this is the first traction that
they've gotten. And to me, the most dangerous part of this is that like the state legal systems
are ill-prepared, both the judges and the state's attorney's office to deal with an issue like this.
I mean, a technical issue like this. These things should not be decided in the courts.
Okay, they should be decided, you know, by the legislature, you know, elected
legislators and they should have hearings from people across the spectrum and, you know,
wide deliberate deliberations and whatever, not by a single judge who's sympathetic to the defendants
and doesn't have a clue about climate science. And the Montana state's attorney, I mean, I was
brought on the case at the last minute, like the end of last September. And the lawyer that
hired me, he then left a few weeks later. There was a private company who then
took legal firm that then took over and then the lawyer who was eventually in charge of the case
didn't even join it until December. And so he was left, you know, brought in at the last minute.
These weren't witnesses of his choosing. He didn't particularly understand the climate
change issue at all. He wanted, you know, the case to be about something different about
legal nuances. But in spite of my best efforts, I didn't convince him that this was really going
to be about climate change and that you needed to deeply challenge their witnesses and, you know,
the points. And he just didn't know how to evaluate any of that. And I don't blame him. I'm not
surprised. I don't think there'd be very few lawyers in state's attorney's office who are prepared
to handle a case like this. Because of the complexities of the science, because of the
understanding, understanding where the plaintiffs, you know, where their weaknesses are, why is that?
Is the science part of it? Oh, it's both. I mean, and it's, they were claiming psychological
injuries. You know, a few of them, oh, well, my roof was injured by a hailstorm and a barn on
the neighboring property burned down from a fire and the stream dried up. And I couldn't fish in
the stream. And, you know, these were psychological injuries. But a lot of it was pre traumatic
stress syndrome, you know, the Greta Thunberg, we have no future, all of this kind of thing. So
they're very deeply depressed. So I mean, the kids have been fed this insane rhetoric, the rhetoric
targeted at kids and young adults is even worse than what we see, you know, as extinction, rebellion,
all that kind of stuff. So, you know, they just don't have the critical faculties at this point
to evaluate it. And a lot of them are depressed and upset, whatever. But, you know, we blame that on
the education system, on the advocacy groups. I mean, if they were worried about the psychological
injuries of the kids, they should have been suing extinction rebellion and Greta Thunberg and the
National Education Association, which is sort of feeding them all this stuff. But their real agenda
is just to go after the fossil fuel companies. And using kids as a prop. So it's a, you know,
it's a case that made no sense. It's a legal decision that made no sense. But like, it's not
the first thing that makes no sense and all this. So, you know, that this is really, I'm sure our
children's trust the swimming and donations after this little victory, so they can go on and keep suing
everybody. I'm looking at there, I'm looking at one of the rundowns here that they've been,
one of their funders is the Rockefeller Brothers, which is a, I don't know, there's some oil. Yeah,
okay. Well, the air to the Getty fortune is funding extinction rebellion.
You know, you've got all of these oil company fortunes now funding all this craziness, go figure.
I want to reach back to you said that there is a lot of anti-capitalist rhetoric in this,
in these discussions. Talk about that, because I believe I think you're right. And some of these
activists have been very clear about that, right, that capitalism is the problem that's driving
climate change. And therefore, we need some kind of Maoism or socialism or something that would
replace it and have some kind of authoritarian system. I was the only thing I can imagine would
be or the thing that would replace it. But talk about why, how do you see that? How do you see
this? And why do you say that it's an anti-capitalist movement? Well, okay, well, if you look at
the UN environmental program, which is, you know, really behind a lot of this UN stuff,
and you read what they write, and it comes through loud and clear, and not just anti-capitalist,
but anti-democratic, we can't trust the people or the countries to make the right decisions. So
there needs to be, you know, more coercion from the top down at the international level from the
UN. So it's a grab for power. So there's a lot of power grabbing in this, and capitalism and
democracy is inherently against, you know, centralized power. So,
yeah, there are people who've written a lot about this, but the solution is somehow more
coercion, more authoritarianism from presumably the smart people over the dumb people, right,
that they're going to be the ones that are going to make the decisions for us.
Yeah, well, President Biden is talking about declaring a climate emergency,
which would take, and it would be a long-term emergency. I mean, emergencies are for, you
know, something going on two weeks or a month or a year, but not for something that's, you know,
decades. So that would, you know, force people to do this, force people not to do this, that would
take away a lot of freedoms if he declares the climate emergency. And, you know, so there's a
lot of power grabbing going on in the name of this issue. How do you describe your politics, Judy?
Well, when I go to a ballot, I'm looking for the not, you know, a voter's ballot. I'm looking for
the none of the above box to check. Okay, that's my point. I'm not a Republican. I'm not a Democrat.
I'm disgusted, and I am disgusted, but I don't see a disgusted party. So...
Okay, yeah, I'm an independent with a libertarian streak. When I am totally disgusted with the
Republican and Democratic candidates, I'll vote libertarian by default, but I haven't had any great
enthusiasm for any of their recent candidates. But, you know, I'm hoping no party or whatever,
something can come up with something different, because, you know, another Trump Biden election,
you know, the whole country, you know, will just be tearing their hair out. So, yeah,
so I'm an independent. I'm a none of the above. I like to think things through and listen to both
sides. And, you know, a lot of these issues are just not simple, and there's clashes of values.
So, you know, I like the discussion. I like the debate. So I don't pledge allegiance to anybody
or either side, that's for sure. I'm going to go back, jump back to the just stop oil crowd and
the, you know, the climate rebellion people or whatever the extinction rebellion people,
because I find some of these people who are throwing the soup cans and blocking the traffic and the
rest of it. One, for their punishment, I want them to go and live in rural Kenya without any
hydrocarbons and be forced to stay there for two years and just tell us, you know, report back. And
maybe this has changed your mind. That's my idea for punishment. You can't use any modern energy
sources, sorry, none, zero, and then see how you like it. But I also find it somewhat depressing
when I look at them and how they feel the victim. So they feel so aggrieved. I mean, there's something
there's something deeply disgusting about it, right? Because I think I see them also as just
completely spoiled and uneducated about the world around them. But there's something pathetic about
them. Does that ring true to you? And I'm just kind of riffing here, but I see something very
deeply sad in the way they act.
Well, it's part it's a part of the broader victim culture and identity politics, you know, it's
the need to culture victim culture, right? Yeah, that whole thing. So it's it's it's a tribal thing.
And the held lawsuit is part of this, right, that this is an identity, right? This is an identity of
we've been agreed, we've been wronged, and we're going to seek redress for this, this this affront
to us in our, our, then they have somebody in authority who's going to pay the bills for them
to go out and throw, you know, cans of tomato soup. You know, it seems like win win, you know, it
they think they're saving the world. They're part of a tribe. And somebody's paying them and
encourage, you know, somebody in authority who's paying them and encourage them to do this. So
it's, you know, I think all of those things are contributing. But it is very sad that these kids
aren't doing something better with their time, more, more productive, you know, getting educated
and getting jobs. And this is personal for you. You're a grandmother. Am I right? Oh, I'm a grandmother
for sure. How many, how many grandchildren? Well, I have one grandchild and then five step
grandchildren. So we've got a nice crew and they're all of junior high and high school age.
And you talk about these kind of political issues within? Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah. And they, and they
think, you know, I'm cool. I'm a little bit subversive. You know, that's good. Let's see what the real
truth is. So that they seem to all have healthy attitudes, you know, about the situation. And
my granddaughter, who lives in Reno, you know, close to where I live, she's very rational. She
says, Well, I just really need to learn more about this whole issue. You know, I just, I don't think
I should have a big opinion about this right now, because I just really need to learn more about this
issue. You go girl. Yeah. So let me ask you about, we just have a few more minutes. And again,
my guest is Judith Curry. She's the author of this new book, Climate Uncertainty and Risk,
Rethinking Our Response. By the paperback, it's much cheaper than the hardback. It's out by
Anthem Press. It came out in June. I'm going to ask you about the ending of that in just a minute.
But you have your own website, judithcurry.com and climate, et cetera. So you have your own
media outlet. I'm just curious. Can you give me an idea how many visitors you get there? Because
I'm increasingly convinced unless you own your own media outlet, you're not assured of a free press.
You know, I haven't joined Substack or anything else where I might get traffic. When I first
started the blog, it had huge traffic. I get less traffic these days. I think on a big day,
I might get 10,000 visitors. You know, it's and if something gets picked up.
But that's still a respectable number. It's a respectable number. And you know,
I'm not actually looking for influence. I'm just looking to engage in, you know,
in the dialogue and to set up a space where people from across the spectrum can come here
and discuss. And I also host a number of very interesting, intelligent people as guest
authors. And it's even spawned a few books, three books, in fact, you know, that have grown out
from posts on my blog. Yeah. And so, you know, I'm very happy with the blog, even though it's,
you know, not high traffic. And in all honesty, I think my lab that there was a three week period
when I didn't even post something, you know, so it's not like I'm posting four times a day and
really trying to build trap. You know, it's just my personal record of what I'm thinking about and
what I'm investigating. And it really seeded my book. I started the blog in 2010 with a series on
climate science and the uncertainty monster, which was a major theme in my book. So this blog in many
ways documented my journey in writing the book. It's an interesting way to think about it because
I'm talking with other writers and, you know, I've written six books and I don't think I have
another one in them, but that they view the their substack or even their Twitter or other places
of way that they catalog what they know, and then they come come back and use it as a resource.
So I want to we're going to close here in just a few minutes because I know you're on a tight
schedule and so am I. But at the end of the book, you have a section called toward post apocalyptic
climate policies. And you quote the economist Richard toll, who is an interesting character,
I've met him once, he said, politically correct climate change orthodoxy has completely destroyed
our ability to think rationally about the environment. I touched on this before, but I like
that because it speaks to the issues of land use, which I've been reporting on for a very long time.
And met many people in rural America in the course of my travels in Michigan and Wisconsin and all
over the world that you're fighting these encroachment of these wind and solar projects.
But it seems that that to me is the concrete example of this clouded ability to think about
the environment that this climatism has trumping all of these other concerns. I don't know.
Your book is in some ways kind of a technical book, but you also have these quotes that are
really great in each section. So you really, that was the most fun part of the book was
I think, you know, selecting quotes and figuring out where to place them. I mean, it was,
it was, I spent an awful lot of time doing it, but it was the most fun part really of writing the
book. Well, I enjoyed it as well because you have a, somebody, go ahead. From Dirty Harry and May
West, you know, Bruce Lee, you know, popular culture figures, along with philosophers and
scientists and things like that. So, but it breaks up the kind of, it made it less of a
technical way. That gave it some leavening, some, some breathing room, I guess I would say, right?
Because you have a lot of technical things that heavily footnoted and footnoted and the way you
structured it in some ways is more textbook-like. And you said that the publisher is targeting
universities and academic outlets or academic buyers, but I found that part to be good. So
let me read this one section here and then we're going to wrap up. This is in your concluding section,
you say, we need to open up space for dissent, disagreement and discussion about scientific
uncertainty and policy options so that multiple perspectives can be considered and broader support
can be built for a range of policy options. Wicked scientists are willing to become embroiled in
political debates and thorny social problems. To be effective, we need to break the hegemony of
disciplinary researchers, disciplinary researchers, particularly for those who are
strident political activists as being regarded as experts for solutions to the wicked problem of
climate change. I couldn't agree with that more. I thought that was a really good summary of, I
think of what your, your point is, we need, we need more robust debate about the best path forward.
And my thing has always been natural gas and nuclear. If we're serious about this, these are
low carbon scalable, you know, but they're just the lack of policy debate about what the way forward
to me is very, a very dangerous one. So I commend you on the book. I thought, you know, it's really
obviously an enormous amount of effort. So I have to, I wanted to draw part of our discussion to an
end there because I thought that was very well stated. So thank you for that. Last two questions.
And you know, I asked these and I asked you these before. So what are you reading? What's on the,
yeah, I know you're busy with climate forecast actions, climate forecast applications network,
your business, but I know you must be an avid reader. So what's on your bookshelf? What are you
reading on these? What's the top of the pile? Oh, gosh, I wish I could remember the name of this
book, but it's a book by Andy West. It's in the grip of culture. It's about the social psychology
of climate catastrophism, you know, the Greta phenomenon or whatever. And this is another
like scholarly book, but it's very readable. In the grip of culture, it's called? Yeah,
in the grip of culture. Okay. I think and it's about the social psychology of climate catastrophism.
I see. Something like that. So that's like, I highly recommend that. I think that's the main
one I want to recommend at this point. Okay. Last question, what gives you hope?
What gives me hope? Well, that people can be rational. And I think that we are. And I think
this in the grip of culture book explains a lot. And, you know, we just need to get out of that.
And I'm also, I mean, at some point, the weather is going to turn a little bit more favorable.
We've been in a bad place since 2017. You know, the natural climate oscillations will shift at
some point, five years, 10 years into a more favorable state. And hopefully people will calm down.
And about this problem, I think that the apocalyptic rhetoric people are realizing that
they've gone too far. I mean, having a whole generation of kids who are depressed and too
scared to do anything isn't going to help the movement. So they have to figure out how to
make their message a little bit more hopeful, and not just destroy the psyches of all these kids.
So hopefully the catastrophic rhetoric will came down. But, you know, at the end of the day,
things that don't make sense aren't going to have a long lifetime. They can cause us a lot of money,
cause us a lot of pain. But at the end of the day, you know, sense and economics will prevail.
But we're certainly not there right now.
Well, that's a good place to stop. So that's where we will, in fact, stop. My guest has been
Judith Curry. She's the author of a new book called Climate Uncertainty and Risk, Rethinking
Our Response. You can find it, I'm sure, on all the major book selling outlets. She's on Twitter
at CurryJA, and you can find her on the web at JudithCurry.com. Judith, thanks a million for
coming back on The Power Hungry Podcast. A very interesting book and, you know, I applaud you
for your efforts at trying to open up the debate. And with this, if these are the most important
issues of our time, and I think they are important issues, let's have a debate about it. Let's talk
about it. Let's examine it. And your work, I think, is helping that effort. So good on you.
Okay, great. Thanks. It was great to talk to you again.
Okay, so thank you, Judy. And thanks to all of you out there in Podcast Land.
To the next episode of The Power Hungry Podcast, it might be as good as this one,
we will find out. But if you have a chance, also give us a good rating on those podcast outlets
wherever you can give us 4, 5, 6, 12 stars, whatever it is. And until next time, see you.