Welcome to the future you guys happy Friday I'm super pumped up today because
we have people on the show you know contain myself so all you guys that are tuning in you are in
for a real treat I want to tell you a couple things I know about people right off the front here
he's from Wisconsin but now he's currently resides in Charleston South Carolina he produces VJ clips
for concerts and I want to talk to him about that I also found out he's a family man he's got two
kids and he's been doing every day's every day for 10 years some of you guys know him as people
but we now know him as Mike Winkleman and he's going to be on the show doing the math before
10 years an image a day through 365 days a year that equates to more than 3650 images it's so big I
can't even contain it in one slide bananas guys so what we know is he's super consistent and this
is daunting because I just started a challenge myself so hard to do I looked up consistent what
does that mean unchanging in nature standard or effect over time he's also super prolific and
that means producing in large quantities or with great frequency highly productive I'm not sure he
would use those words to describe himself but as an outside observer that's all I can tell you
this is how I see it now if you're not familiar with his work you got to get to know this man
he's producing work all over the place and it's very easy to find check this out now many of us
would be thrilled to be able to produce maybe four five six twelve of these kinds of images
but he's this is just two of 3650 images that he's producing a day here's some other images that
he's produced incredible now I've noticed some themes we're going to get into this with him
about why he chooses certain compositions certain color palates and most oftentimes he'll put a
person in this in the frame too so I want to talk to him about that check out this amazing artwork
Greg and Caleb what do you guys think about this beautiful it's stunning I don't know how you
do this every day well we're gonna find out shortly it's pretty cool and we'll make him
uncomfortable by flattering him a little bit he's got that midwestern modesty thing going so you
know we'll turn it up a little bit but gosh look at these images and for me the hardest thing was
like which image do I put together to encapsulate the volume the prodigious volume of work that
he's been able to produce super cool how do you even get the ideas on how to produce this day in
and day out I'm stuck on day seven of a 30-day challenge right now so this is incredible but
these these images aren't just static he's moving cameras he's animating there's there's walk cycles
that we've seen check this stuff out and the original music to these things are pretty aggro and
let's see let's try to close the music up okay I know that's a little weird
wow
this one feels more appropriate
pretty kind of music
I love this one Greg
all right you guys we're gonna keep this real we're gonna keep this raw Erica please roll the titles
all right Mike welcome to the show and before we have you say anything I just want to warn everybody
there's going to be explicit language on the show today Mike he's got a foul mouth what can we say
what can we say and we want him to be himself so you have sensitive ears or you're easily kind of
insulted by these kinds of things you could tune out right now but you're gonna be missing
something incredible and I just want to let you guys know we'll be monitoring your questions on
Facebook and on YouTube Greg and Caleb will be doing that they're joining us in the in the podcast
or the broadcast today there they are boom you guys look great today you guys oh shucks
you guys get dressed up for people I feel like you did no whatever Greg that was a little short
there Greg all right Mike how you doing man good good how are you I'm good now we understand
you're at home and you have two little ones running around possibly so if they jump into the scene
let's just celebrate the whole fact that you're a family man you're doing this thing I guess the way
I want to kick this off the bat is um how do you find time in the day to do these personal projects
like how are you how's it you can even do this um I mean I get that question a lot but I don't
think there's any like magical answer to it I think it's just one of those things that if you get
into the habit of it you'll keep doing it and it's just something that you have to on some level
just sort of like commit to doing at some point and then I think I've gotten lucky that the momentum
of doing it so long just makes it completely feel like it's not like a choice at all like it's just
something I have to do most days I do not want to do it I'd rather like like today it's definitely
not convenient and I just took a trip it was definitely not convenient any of the days I was
on that trip so I think it's just something that you just kind of um you know once you if you're
lucky enough to be able to get into you know sort of uh routine and have some momentum with it they
kind of carry you forward with it was there a point in in the in the cycle of doing this where
you felt like yeah I can do this now and I can get through that like when you run a marathon when
you hit the wall but you break through and you know you're gonna be able to finish um not really to
be honest I think it was something that uh I just started doing um and I'd seen another artist who
did every day is Tom Judd um and he did drawings a day and that was how I started um and I just
kind of started and then it just kind of like kept going there was no point where it was like
any sort of like epiphany of like oh man I could do this forever and I don't know if I will do it
forever I'm just saying like it just kind of kept going I did not expect it to like keep going this
long so on the days that you don't feel like doing it or there's a lot of stuff going on how
do you find the motivation to to just set aside what you're doing and get something done um that's
again where it's sort of like motivation doesn't really like factor into it because it's sort of
like there's never something that's so important that it's like I'm gonna break this you know 11
year streak yeah because it's like I don't feel like it I want to watch fucking Game of Thrones or
whatever like there's no it's it would have to be a real real good excuse and I mean at this point
it wouldn't really be an excuse it would be like something like physically stops me from like doing
it and which case or I haven't planned ahead and something like that um or just some like stupid
shit because the other thing is it has to be done by midnight and there's times when I've gotten very
close to midnight and if I go over by midnight I will be very very pissed at myself like beyond
pissed at myself so and it'll happen eventually but it hasn't happened do you start stressing out
when it's like 11 50 p.m yeah well I mean by 11 50 p.m yeah I'm definitely like fucking
attention focused and there's been times where it's gone to 11 50 p.m like I'm fucking
left I get pixel fucking whatever it's done with this like it's gone to 11 50 p.m and the power
is going to go out or something and I'm going to be really really fucking pissed yeah all right well
Greg is a person who did like a mythical monday for for a whole year I'm sure you can relate is
there something that you want to ask people I mean I I don't know if relate is even comes close to
imagine the anxiety you feel like mythical monday oh so okay it was a it was an animated gift
project that I did and um this sounds it's not like such a weiner comparing it to your
everyday's but I made one animated gift a week for a year nice and that like stressed me out like
crazy and my my thing was yeah I had to go live um at midnight on on sunday right because it's monday
so sure enough I would always wait until like 11 50 and I'd just be like oh damn it what am I going
to do no sorry what were you saying no that's that's that's the story
really I know that's one thing a lot of people like ask me like well why don't you just do like
one thing like a week like a longer thing but if I was doing that I would just wait till the last
second I wouldn't work on yeah oh it's definitely I would definitely work far less I guarantee that
if I was just doing one thing like a week so I think a lot of designers and creative people can
relate to this part which is I think we need the pressure to make something like no pressure no
diamonds right my wife is always wondering why are you waiting two days before you have to get on
an airplane to write your talk I like I can't produce under any other circumstance it doesn't
the urgency isn't there the fire the the need to make something isn't there so you know I think
there's a whole bunch of people already loving you somebody's like oh no no swearing please like I
think sarcastically and and somebody's like people for president in all caps and they're loving your
accent too so like play it up man just play it up yeah I guess a lot of people the Wisconsin
thing I don't really it doesn't feel like an accent to me but we can hear it though it's lovely I like
it can hear it everybody else can all right um Caleb do you have a question for him or Erica
yeah uh what what is the most time that you've spent on a single daily before oh that's a good
question um there's been times uh I usually try and spend a little more time on the like um
May 1st which is like a anniversary date each year and um and the end of the year
and the beginning of the year so on the 31st and the first I try and spend more time on those
and there's other times where if I have like not often but there's times where I have like an idea
like oh this could be cool if I do you know x y z but it's like a lot to do and I just so happen to
have a bunch of time usually if it's like the weekend um there's been times where I've spent
like probably like 10 hours on one oh my goodness yeah there's definitely been times there's times
where it's like I'll sit down at four o'clock on the weekends and it'll be like I'm just gonna like
spend you know just a little bit of time then we're gonna watch a movie and we'll watch a movie in a
little bit and then I'll fucking spend like eight hours and like go home or something do you find
that there's any correlation between the amount of time you spend on something and the quality or
your satisfaction of the work uh there's a small correlation sometimes there's a correlation there's
times where it's like I'll put in a bunch of time and I'll be like oh that's like decent or like
sucks a little less than the other ones but there's also many times where I'll put in a
shit ton of work and I'm like this fucking blows like that was a goddamn waste of time like or
there's times where I'll do something super quick and it'll just like I'll get lucky and I'll be like
oh fuck it's done and you know uh half hour or something like that so uh that does not happen
very often but well you're you're a living testament to this idea this experiment that was run I think
it was in a book called the fear of art that my business coach had me had me read many many years
ago I mean it they they took a hundred artists they split them in half they told 50 artists in a month
produce as many pieces as you can don't worry about quality or anything and then they set them off on
their way and the other group of 50 artists that make a masterpiece just make one piece that you
think is going to be amazing and the results were quite surprising not to you but maybe to some of
our audience in that the group who was who were directed to just create one masterpiece many of
them didn't produce anything and and there were higher and better quality pieces of work from the
group who were just told just to make stuff all day long and so that that is the testament to
this whole fear of art thing and you've been able to do that wonderfully and and I think you're a
role model for everybody who's just holding on to that precious idea of perfection that your
deadline of midnight like you got to get it done and you got to release it into the world
yeah I don't know I mean that's the thing the that that experiment is interesting but it's
kind of subjective I mean there's definitely people who I see who spend a shit ton of time
on one image and it turns out fucking awesome and it's something that I could look at for like
an insane amount of time because it's got so much detail and it's just fucking framed perfectly and
the color and composition everything so I do think that art in general is a bit of a numbers
game in terms of just if you're putting out more stuff you know there's found a like hit because
I think there's a lot of luck to it I think there's a lot of like you know you just get lucky
times and if you're putting out more stuff there's a lot better chance that you're gonna get lucky
and something might sort of click. Pedro is saying Beeple is the Bill Gates of every day
and he does look a little like Bill Gates right now. There's a lot of people who said I look like
Bill Gates there was a picture that Zed posted with me next to Zed and he's got you know millions
of followers on Instagram or whatever and all the fucking comments Bill Gates Bill Gates Bill Gates
you just need a sweater man get a nice sweater with a collar and you're set
but again you're good to pull up a side by side of Bill Gates.
All right so I have to ask another question as you've been doing this for so long
are you a super organized person do you have all your assets like just super just there it is
everything I want is there come on lie to me lie to me. The people I used to work with well
don't remember this I have on my desktop a crud folder that is like kind of a spill all of like
just general bullshit so no I'm definitely not organized anybody who's like yeah I'm not organized.
So do you find that you spent a lot of your time just digging through your assets like oh I need
that building or that water tower or whatever it is that you're looking for or that that model or
that tree I mean how are you even combing through your stuff. So in terms of that stuff I am I really
didn't start building a like database of stuff because before I hit 10 years like a year ago
I had tried to like model most things because when I started out I didn't know 3D at all I wanted
to learn to model and so I started out I would model everything in the scene every single thing
and over the course of 10 years it kind of slowly I would introduce more and more things where it's
like okay I don't really want to model a tree it doesn't really make sense I'm just going to use a
tree model but then when I hit 10 years I kind of sort of completely took the sort of limitation
off myself and I'll use models from anything now because I want to focus on color and composition
and just like more narrative things and I don't really want to like model a fucking little crate
or whatever. Right. So I just really started building a like true library of assets a year ago
and I would say that is fairly organized actually that I can quickly like pull things in but in
terms of like my things like where to save something or where to like you know directory
structures it's definitely like a bit of a claustrophobic. It's just one giant folder with 3000
images or models. It's not that disorganized but it definitely be more organized I will say not.
So I'm curious because I think I I'm not saying this from my point of view but for people who
are watching or saying well isn't that like cheating like don't you need to make everything
yourself look why have you come to the realization that maybe it's more about the art and the
composition of the idea that you're you want to share with the world versus actually building
every screw and that bolt that's in the scene. Sure I think it's you could consider it cheating
and if your goal is to make everything from scratch then yes this would be like cheating but if
that's not your goal then it's not cheating that's not my goal. So to me I think I would rather use
all the tools available. I think clients are demanding more and more and if you're holding
your back holding yourself back from using things especially on client projects like clients do not
give a fuck how you built it like who wastes all day modeling something they're gonna be like what
the fuck did you do why didn't you buy that from TurboSquid or Adobe stock or Adobe stock.
Why didn't you just buy that you know instead of wasting all day fucking modeling and texturing
and all this shit. So I think it's it's definitely something that it depends on what your goal is.
My goal is not to recreate the wheel if I can you know use something that I can get for you know
much cheaper than I could make it. I mean the most expensive models are only a couple thousand
dollars and that's something that would like take you like months to like make. So it almost never
unless you need something custom it almost never makes sense to like make it yourself. Now
something really stuff wise or weird or whatever then obviously you have to make it or you need a
certain topology or this or that but if you just need a fucking tree don't model that fucking tree
download a goddamn tree like that. Definitely for client work don't fucking model that tree.
Now we're going to get into client work how you make money how you make a living and
your whole financial empire if you will in a second but I do want to share a little story
with you and maybe some other people can relate to this because when I was getting started in
motion design I was painting style frames right using Photoshop and doing photocomping photo
mashing things together but what I was doing was I was creating all my own assets like if there
was something I needed I would run out and shoot it with a camera because I thought the rules were
you had to make everything in your frame and then I go and meet one of my clients and there's a
designer there his name is Ron Padua and Ron is showing me his set of storyboards instead of doing
one set of boards he has seven complete boards with ideas and I was sitting there scratching my
head thinking how is that you are able to create so much in the same amount of time and I just
barely got my first idea out and he's dude I just went in and I grabbed frames from anywhere
and everywhere and I cut things up I just want to get the idea out and if we were to be awarded the
job we'd actually have to hire an art director a production designer we'd have to do casting
and lighting and all this kind of stuff I'm not really worried about that and that was a giant
shift for me I remember getting into my car driving home thinking what a cheating little bastard
like that mother you know how could he do that and I'm sitting here and then I started to think
like what is my hang up with this at the end of the day I want to win the work and I want to
be able to tell stories and I want to learn how to be a director that's what mattered to me the most
so I'm just kind of jumping in on what you're saying there yeah I think it's I think these
tools like I'm interested in using the most advanced tools available like I want to use the
most advanced render I want to use the most advanced plugins because I want to be able to do
like things as quick as possible and get my ideas out there as quick as possible so to me I see like
using stock things is just an extension of that it's another tool like a plugin or like the new
version of octane or something like that that it's like why wouldn't I use that right it's available
to me it's like it's available to everyone so I think it's it's one of those things that it's
just another tool for me okay since we're on the subject of tools and I think there are a
bunch of people wondering what tools you are using can you give us a breakdown of the tools that
using the software um most of the stuff I use is cinema 4d and then um octane I've been using
some redshift lately um but mostly mostly octane still um and then just like after effects and
owner shop okay okay cool I noticed when you were talking about turbo squid and then you
mentioned oh I'm sorry adobe great adobe stock are you sponsored by adobe or something
yeah
no can do right hey uh yeah adobe are you listening we we use adobe stock or is that what it's called
stock loving it love adobe stock number one adobe stock right now hashtag adobe stock you guys
all right we gotta pay the bills I get it I get it we need some adobe love ourselves so we'll get
into that a little bit later so those are the tools hey Greg and Caleb any questions from the
internet that you guys want to throw at people yeah yeah there's a couple from youtube so um
gustav asks on average how long does it take to make one of these every day uh I would say on
average it's probably like two hours two hours okay how much work I have that day in terms of like
client work and how much uh ambition I have or if I have an idea that's like oh this could be like
decent or it could be interesting to explore then I might spend more time or if I don't have
you know that much time than I've spent last time but I would say that average and to to follow that
up like in my mind one of the scariest things is just a blank canvas right so where do where do you
even start like do you have a sketchbook full of crazy ideas that you you know pluck things from
and use every day or what you know you're staring at the screen what happens draw at all so I don't
sketch um I usually will go on like um like Pinterest or I've got like a Pinterest board of like
everyday sort of general ideas um it's not like I've got it like okay Tuesday I'm doing this Wednesday
I got this blah blah blah it's definitely just kind of like what sort of like can get me at all
sort of motivated to just kind of uh just start uh and sometimes it's something very small it's just
like a general shape or a color scheme or a camera angle or something like that um but I find if I have
some sort of like nudge in a certain direction it will turn out better than just like literally
opening up Cinema 40 with no ideas then it will usually kind of uh just turn into more of like a
super abstract pile of crap that I've like done a million times it's not like the other days it's
like insane the original every day but it seems to be uh a little easier if I have some nudge in
a direction right yeah some sort of theme or something to build on yeah do you wait for that
nudge to happen before you sit down and do your every day I wait to a certain extent but I usually
don't I don't have the luxury of just like I'm just gonna wait till I'm inspired because I have like
it's like okay I've got like an hour and a half to do this so I can sit there and
dick around for five minutes but it's like I can't sit here and wait for an hour till the
magical muse comes down and you know kisses my forehead I gotta just fucking sit down and put
some shit out so uh I try to like you know get an idea but sometimes it's just kind of like
okay fuck this I gotta go right right okay I think everybody that watches our channel knows
that we don't just talk about creative things you're a super creative guy but we talk about
business stuff too and we were having a conversation before we went live about this very thing so I
got a lot of questions for you and I and if you feel like I'm throwing a question at you that you
don't want to answer uh because that that whole midwestern modesty thing I get it we'll cover it
up we won't have to talk about it and we'll we'll just say pass okay so I'm gonna throw some things
at you I asked Aaron Draplin this question on the podcast and I want to ask you it's like
where does your money come from like you sell you do freelance work I know that you sell prints and
tell us how what does the financial empire look like from percentages like where does it all come
from the buckets almost entirely freelance um the prince is not very much it's maybe
10% of the money if less than 10% of the money actually far less than 10% of the money that I
make is from France it's definitely almost entirely freelance work do you speak a lot do you get
invited to speak and are you paid to speak um so that's a good question um I have done some
speaking gigs in the last couple years um I've kind of started to do more of them just because
it's I found it's uh you know just a fun way to like meet people and just like because I work from
home to like get out in like I don't know any I would just move to Charleston yeah like six
eight months ago and I don't know anybody here uh so and I just like honestly don't have a ton of
time to like hang out with people on like a day-to-day basis um so you know going to these events I
find is like really great for connecting with people um so yeah I've started to do those more I
haven't gotten paid for any of them so I don't know I should be asking for money for these you
should be thinking about that question for you yeah we'll talk about that I'll help you I mean I
think not not that you're asking for my help or anything but I I think I'm I'm one of those weirdos
where I think I enjoyed math and the idea of running a business as much as I enjoyed doing the creative
aspect some some weird hybrid right I'm just smashing those two worlds together I honestly
enjoyed like the money aspect of it as well uh that's what drew me to like you're looking at your
stuff or you know the the content you guys are putting out is because I think you know like
you're saying a lot of people don't like talking about that or are scared to talk about it whereas
to me that's interesting because it's like that's all these projects happen like if you see like a
big movie or some shit like that like that didn't fucking just come out of nowhere like somebody had
to pay for that like and if it doesn't make money it's not gonna happen again so it's like to me I
find that interesting because it's what facilitates a lot of what we do mm-hmm well we we kind of
actually bumped into it but you you make some money via sponsorship right yeah I there is a
couple things that I've done um that are like sponsorships through um Adobe and then I just
did a thing with Wix um uh with the new website that I have um and I just went and spoke at Wix
actually last week uh so yeah there's been a few things like that just more recently mm-hmm okay
and what percentage of that does that represent your financial empire still small they're small
still yeah it's definitely still mostly just freelance okay and can can I ask that like are
you the uh the sole breadwinner for the family is your wife work yeah my wife stays home she was a
school teacher uh and when we had our first kids we got two kids two and four and um as soon as we
had kids she stays stable mm-hmm and do you ever feel like potentially that that's a lot of pressure
to put on you in terms of like being able to rely on a freelance income that you don't have much of
in terms of passive income set up so if something like if you were to get sick or hit get hit by a
bus and like oh my god uh now what are your what is your wife and your kids going to do um not
really because to be honest I was very fortunate enough to have a dad who was a fucking super tight
ass and he very much instilled in us and this again is maybe you know the midwest thing of saving
money yeah so very much since uh I started working I'm 36 um I was definitely saving at least 10%
of my money the 10% oh good for you and another 401k and then you know I got thrown to side effects
you know yeah my dad does that too but he only did that because he's an accountant and that's how he
do no my dad was not an accountant he was just he was just tight as shit with money and he was
very much so you don't talk to us about investing and you know buying stocks so that's actually
probably the thing I'm more most interested in and I I don't honestly get a chance to talk about it
with any other designers is like stocks and investing um is another thing that I'm like
really interested in so um yeah if something happened and I got you know whatever that we've
got some money that would be fine that's good that's great to hear that's fantastic like you're
you're a responsible adult father and a husband I like that I'm a responsible adult but do you
have life insurance I do not have life insurance that might be something you consider yeah we'd be
fine you don't want to give anybody incentive to like knock off the old man huh no no my uh
yeah it's just I don't have life insurance but um we've got enough money saved that we'd be fine
very good okay well you know I was thinking about this because I noticed when I was downloading
your clips off Vimeo you're like these clips you can download for free these vj clips I was thinking
okay that's super cool we'll be able to use these and I don't have to go through some weird
way to download the videos just for the presentation of your work but I was thinking why aren't you
charging for these vj clips these are awesome they're fantastic yeah to be honest I don't
there's sites where you can buy vj clips yeah um but like adobe stock
to be honest I don't think that revenue model
to me has never been that appealing for one I don't really like trying to like sell stuff
I don't really like I already kind of feel like I'm spamming people with just the like work that
I'm putting out uh just the like every day so like being like buy this thing blah blah blah blah
like I don't know I just I don't like that like a lot of people don't even know that I sell prints
like people are constantly I'll see comments were like oh you got so pretty since like I've been
fucking my selling prints for years like but because I just don't like I'll usually send out one
like tweet per year right before black friday or whatever right like I've got prints other than
that I like pretty much never like sell things so that's one part of it too I feel like vj clips
in general is something where um like if you're a vj I think you need a lot of clips and so
they're kind of like devalued in a sense like on these sites they're really like they don't
do not sell for much so I it would I don't know that personally um at least for me that I think
it makes more sense as a marketing tool than a direct sales tool if that makes sense yeah
because to be honest how I got you know I don't I don't honestly I've never had a demo reel
if you go to my site now you will see none of the like commercial work that I've done
so everything that I've gotten has been from the personal work that I've done
so I look at that as one just shit I want to do and I just happen to be lucky enough that
that is like something that brings in you know freelance okay all right well if you ever change
your mind I know the internet's gonna hate me for this but we could probably talk about how you can
maybe put your images together and put it into a book and launch a Kickstarter campaign and sell
art prints right definitely thought about doing it selling a book um like there's a lot of these
things where it's just like there's not enough like day hours in the day to like you know try and
put this together and monetize this and blah blah blah so I think it's you know I'm not opposed to
making money like you can just fucking make money for this shit that I've already done I'm
certainly fine with that um um but yeah I think it's just been kind of a swamp with the day-to-day
kind of stuff that hasn't pushed me to sort of like like specifically put a book together
do you ever record or film your process in those two hours that you're cranking out a
personal piece oh that's another thing that I should be doing you should easy content for you
that's a layup oh I know I definitely should I definitely to be honest thought of like
different like patreon models I have a couple like I have an idea for one model and I'm not
gonna say it here but I think would be like a really like nobody's doing it and I think it would be uh
I don't know there I I again it just comes down to like hours in the fucking day and like
yeah all right uh Greg and Caleb Erica you guys have any questions for people yeah um so how's
how's your location impacted oh good one your work uh have you been able to get enough freelance work
to support yourself or have you ever had to have an additional job so I actually had a full-time job
up until uh less than four years ago um I worked when I I went to school for computer science and
like halfway through it was like you know fuck this this is boring as hell uh and so I started
doing design shit and then when I got out of school I got a job doing web design and um so I
had a long stretch and well the job was super super easy and I was able to do like a shit like most
of the freelance that I did was at work I would be working on like work for her M&M or like you know
fucking uh a bunch of different like big artists and uh like people would come over and just I kind
of like hide the logos on kind of like this sort of time they're like what do you work on it's like
this is just nothing I don't know so when I quit my job um I was actually making more money about
50% more money doing freelance than the actual day job so I was fairly like I had a good like
kind of ramp up there in terms of like freelance and to be honest like freelance was never something
that I like uh kind of like sought out to do like it was never really like a goal like I want to
like eventually like do freelance I really liked being in an office and the people that I like
worked with were like really good friends so it was like and I actually asked the like place that
I worked was like is there any way I could still like come in here and just like do my own thing
in the corner and they're like no because they were like a software company it was all like
programmers just like what the fuck are you talking about no you can't do that you quit like so anyway
so like I uh and this was back in Wisconsin like all the clients that I worked for were like LA
New York wherever like none of them were in Wisconsin so um yeah I think I've been lucky enough
that there's always kind of been enough work coming in and it the location never made a difference
like I've never gone into a place to work um so yeah well you know you could find the a
co-working space these things exist and you could be around the human beings there was one in
Appleton where I lived because I was in a small town and it was kind of gross to be honest like I
went and looked at it and it was kind of like this is kind of nasty a little bit uh and there is one
in Charleston I just haven't gone there part of the reason is um like I need a lot of like
rendering power so I can work off a laptop but it's really like kind of tying my hands behind
my back to like go sit and work off the laptop uh so that's one reason that I kind of don't love it
I say it's not as established in smaller towns as like we don't have like we works and shit like
or what we work yeah we work very well yeah we don't have those like here like I'm not like
downtown Charleston I'm like way the fuck out in the like suburbs where it's like super cheap like
yeah because that's where you're keeping all the money well that's another honestly that's
another thing that I don't think people like recognize is like these big cities are so fucking
expensive like I you know it's just like like people are like why don't you like move to LA and
it's like I will never move to LA as much as this was back when I was living in Wisconsin
as much as you would never move to Wisconsin that's how much I'll never wait let's get into this
discussion a little bit here now let's not assume I would never move to Wisconsin I know it's cold
there sometimes you wouldn't fucking move to where I live why wouldn't you move to LA
because it's just too expensive it's just way too expensive I just like the the you know
buddies that I have there and I love I like LA the fucking weather is beautiful it's like
never fucking rains like what there's tons of jobs like I I totally get the draw right
there's a lot going on there's tons of work there's tons of cool shit like weather's beautiful
everybody's beautiful like
it's paradise but it comes at a fucking price it does come at a price like to me like you know I
want to have a yard the kids can run around and I can have a you know office and shit and we can
not feel like we're like crammed in you know this and that like when I the amount that you know
I got buddies that are paying for apartments it's just like oh my god gotta be fucking kidding me
never okay okay hold on but if you were uh you landed some big sponsorship deals if you
had printed this book that everybody's saying here like I take my money shut up and take my money
already and somebody's like I'll put it together and then I will buy it from you after I work on it
so there's that if you actually taped or recorded your screen while you're working in and grew your
YouTube channel I'm sure there's a lot of people who would get in on it because I was thinking I
forget the guy's name I want to say his name is Dean but I'm not sure but he's an ultra marathon
runner like he runs marathon like night after night I see you as that guy there's there's only a few
human beings who could do the things that you do so consistently for so long maybe it's going to be a
Guinness world record at some point but there's going to be people who are going to want to get
behind and support you maybe red bull wants to support you you know because you're just jamming
dude or an energizer as the as a battery company or Duracell you know if you can hook those up I'll
hook it up you got my fucking email address all right we will talk after this check look check it
out my LA agent it's going to call your Wisconsin agent or your Charleston agent all right we're
going to get this to happen so it's been an interesting thing so I have a couple other
questions because I hear this a lot I hear this from our community so much do you think your
clients care where you live um my clients specifically yeah no they don't it's never so here the other
thing is I don't like um taking on new clients to be honest I like working with people that uh there's
no drama that it's like um just going to be some like chill thing where it's not like this like
you know I don't want to work with assholes where it turns into this big
you know the fucking bullshit and the clients you know last second expectations like no I don't
want to work I don't want that shit like I would rather work on something boring than with like
people cool people who are like chill like some crazy fucking you know prestigious thing and the
people are assholes and it's super stressful I don't want that like bullshit stress um so I don't
really take on like a huge amount of like new clients um so the people that I've worked with I've
worked with for years super good friends with and you know I'd rather like work with a company that
you know I've worked with uh over a long period of time and like all the companies that I work with
that I have like existing relationships with they don't give a shit like where I live
so there's a lot of people it's not something that's ever like it's never like oh you know are you
going to move to LA it's like they know I'm not moving to LA so it's it's not even on the like
radar I guess well you had mentioned this before that you don't even have a demo reel that you
go to your site it's like this is your personal work you don't put up your commercial work so
most of the people I assume that are finding you are finding you through one of your many social
media outlets and you're just blown away by the work that you do the spam that you put out there
as you call it that's the most artful spam I've ever seen that doesn't ask you for anything it
doesn't want your money your spam is I'll give you this stuff for free that's incredible spam so
they're onboarded and the reason why I want to make a point of this is because there are people
from all over the world that watch our channel and our show and they think oh I need to be in
New York or LA or I need to be in Germany or London or wherever it is and the truth of matter is
it is you don't and and that's a cop out I think it's because if you were people and you lived in
Cairo you could pull this off if you were people and you lived in some remote part of town which
actually you do live in a remote part of town you could still pull this off and it's you have to
start looking inward and saying are you making something that's valuable that's inspiring are you
consistently out there and been and somewhat vulnerable by putting this stuff out there
and that's the problem that a lot of people in our creative community have which is
they they want to get it perfect and so a year goes by two years go by and the site hasn't
launched and the the reel wasn't finished or that personal project was never done and I say this
from experience we've suffered from this too you know we hang on to this be honest like I think
well thank that it's like I'm this you know I just do whatever I've set my mind to and it's like
no I'm like really like strong like I've been working on a short film and I like fucking
struggled if I should have worked on it this morning and I fucking didn't so I there's I think
that every day's are kind of its own little sort of like bubble like I totally get that like oh
fuck I should have done XYZ and I didn't do it because of motivation to be honest and I also
kind of like get the whole like I want to move to like LA or New York or whatever I'm not like
trying to like say that that's like dumb um I think it's I think there's something to be said like
those places have a lot of opportunities and there's a lot of companies where they do want
you to come in and to be honest if you are somebody who is like starting out uh like
right out of school or something like that I would recommend that you do not go freelance
right away that you go to one of those companies because I think you're gonna learn a lot more
I never got that I think I uh took the long way the long path um but I think there's so much to
learn being around people who like no more it's like no no no click on this this morning I just
struggled with something for like fucking hours that I guarantee somebody like a senior level
person who knows this program or been like just click this and it's like I don't have that person
here so I recommend that young people go to like a good studio and like work there for a couple
years before you like do freelance that's what I would good advice I don't know if you know
Joshua Davis but he's saying oh hi there handsome I'm assuming he's not talking about me you must
be talking about you yeah you guys those of you guys that know Mike personally go ahead and give
him a hard time in the chat right now uh bring up some embarrassing stories things that he would
rather sooner forget and we'll discuss that live on air right now please do us a favor
Greg Caleb look out for those comments right now let's get those stories in there the time you
got drunk and did something stupid um Brenda is asking has your wife ever been like this everyday
thing it's enough now no not remotely my my um family is like insanely supportive and they have
been from day one but now even more so like my mom will be like it's time to do it like we're just
sitting around shooting the shit and it's like nine o'clock it's like don't you have to do your
everyday like they're insanely insanely like supportive because they've seen what's come from
it and they've seen they know how important it is to me they know how you know serious I take uh
you know the project as a whole I think it's it's this tough sort of mix between like taking uh
the entire thing like super fucking serious that you're gonna commit to putting in like hours a day
but not taking each sort of day so serious that it paralyzes you from like putting out work
that it's like that's soft tomorrow's another day yeah so this weird kind of like balance between
those two things um but no my wife is insanely insanely supportive um and to be honest I mean
every day is her was put on a table so it's kind of like uh I mean she gets that for sure the like
personal work is what brings in uh you know client work uh so she she kind of sees the whole
sort of picture there right and I think the part about that is not being like a douche lord about
like doing something like this not being like I'm an artist like you need to fuck that like you need
to be like a human and like a fucking person first and like you know if I have to do it at this
on community in community time where I get you know uh interrupted because kids had a
fucking blowout or some shit then it's like okay well then you know I I think trying to like
accommodate your family schedule will give them a lot make it they're buying a lot easier
will make it a lot easier for you to like stick with something like that good advice good advice
and I'm I'm speaking from experience my wife fully supports the endeavor that we do call the
future because there were many years we did this when it was a giant time suck and there was no
return on it at all and now it's starting to pay off and everybody's seeing if you do something
that you love your passion you share openly good things can happen now I do want to tell you
a couple of comments in here because there's there's a funny little dialogue going on in chat
so Catherine Adams is saying hey buy a house in East LA it's still affordable and Joshua Davis
quickly responds no because he's going to want to move to suburbers in New York with me so they're
like fighting for what city you're going to move to right and then Perfect Hue comes back LA is
where it's at so you know uh oh we got a little east coast west coast where do we start all right
what else is going on you guys anything else yeah so there's a question on YouTube from Rowan
who's asking you know Mike how do you balance your time with all these different things with
family um with client projects and freelance and with having to put out every day every day
I would say not well I feel like I wasted a ton of time I feel like I'm like extremely goddamn
distracted all day like just fucking news and dumb Trump bullshit and just I feel like it's
definitely a struggle to like stay focused do the thing like uh so yeah I I I don't really have any
sort of like get up and blah blah blah and do this and then drink a protein shake and like I don't
have like some like like how do you how do you bring your focus back to what you're doing or what
you need to do um bad lines again that's what is sort of like having a deadline by the end of the
day it kind of forces focus because it's sort of like what's got to be done by midnight so
10 o'clock I have to focus like uh so yeah I think if you can get in this like habit that
you've got something that is like a deadline like that like deadlines I feel like are uh just
insanely um insanely good I don't know what the right word is but they really like
help put work out and when I have you have a deadline that's literally every single day
you will produce something right and I tons of other people like who started it every
days and it's like I've seen like a huge amount of growth from like you know a bunch of different
people so it's definitely you know not just you know me right right I think there's a saying
like creativity expands or contracts to meet deadlines so deadlines help you get stuff done
right yeah because it's sort of like there's you know especially with a personal project there's an
infinite amount of choices you have nothing like holding your fucking you know nose to the whatever
then it's sort of like you're just floating around in artists world fucking whatever versus okay I
gotta put some shit down here it's it's 11 o'clock like let's what are we doing today uh you know it
kind of narrows your your focus I'm gonna ask this question because Brendan keeps typing this in and
I want to make sure he gets his question answered here is do you have any particular strategy when
you were first starting out how you were able to get critical mass and grow a following any tips
for people who are trying to do the same thing uh not really come on dig deep dude come on give
us some tips well so here's the thing uh when I started out this was before Facebook the first
probably two years I was just posting a website and literally nobody fucking saw that shit
fucking nobody so uh there's been no sort of like I would say the epiphany is do something for
10 years and just have patience with it um I I think posting on all of the sites um regularly
I think helps um because I think with a lot of these sites you don't really know which um
is gonna be popular you know years from now like I didn't I didn't think Instagram was gonna be as
popular as it is now like back when you know it was like oh here's this cool filter app um you know
I didn't see that coming until like not real popular um so I think kind of not putting all
of your eggs in one basket I would say I guess is some advice um beyond that though I feel like I'm
not very good at sort of like engaging with uh like audience on social media um just because
it takes a lot of time um it's just not something that I've like done that much or feel
uh I don't know I just don't engage as much as I probably should or could to kind of like
grow my audience more I guess so it sounds to me like you're you're saying like you've been doing
this for a long time and it wasn't necessarily uh to to get famous or to grow following you did it
and then when the platforms became available and you you did this more consistently than most artists
which is you post on pretty much every platform you can find which it makes it very easy to find
you every day I post on Facebook all these by hand that I don't have any like aggregator that's one
aggregator that's one other thing that I would recommend is and I asked somebody that actually
at adobe about this and because I always suspected this that if you use like an aggregator it will
kind of like ding uh you'll you'll get dinged a little bit on um on how much it will be shown to
people if they see that you like push it out to all the platforms it wants so I post natively on
each one of the platforms Facebook Twitter Tumblr uh my website Instagram
yeah sorry I didn't mean to interrupt your flow that I was going to give you a bell for every
platform that you mentioned and I'm there with you I really believe in posting natively
well you have to I mean you will definitely get dinged which I always suspected and he was like
yes that's definitely true that if you're not posting natively to the platform if it concedes
you're using some aggregator it will like ding it and show your posts to less people
and you mentioned before when you went to school can you tell us what you studied in school and
where you went to school I went to Purdue University and studied computer science oh wow
Purdue University is not really that like prestigious of a school nothing against people
went to Purdue there goes this uh the sponsorship from the school
I think people have just used Purdue that it's a lot more prestigious than it is because especially
in Wisconsin too it was like oh my gosh wow oh jeez you got into Purdue from UW Madison like it's not
it was not as prestigious as you would think it's not private it's not like it's not really
that prestigious it's got a good computer science uh um and a good engineering like program but
it's not like fucking MIT or one of these things it's definitely like it's pretty good okay Mike I
have to say something I feel like midwesterners make a sport out of self-deprecation you guys
really like let's try to one up each other on that kind of stuff I'm just curious about that mindset
like oh cool you studied computer science you went to Purdue you're like nah it's not that good
they let anybody in it's not really good it's not as good as Madison and I got fucking rejected for
Madison I think they're regretting it now though let me tell you they're regretting it
no no I mean to be honest I was never never gonna be like a programmer it just was immediately like
in school I was immediately just doing little artful shit like and before school too like I
don't know what I was thinking with that so what yeah like why did you study computer science
were you told by your your video games like I want to make video games and then I like realized
that it's like I remember specifically when I was like nope I saw this kid and he was just
so far fucking more advanced than everybody and was just like nope not doing that like that
kid's gonna do that that kid's gonna do whatever the fuck he wants but I'm not gonna do that because
I don't want to compete against that kid I can't compete against that kid and to be honest like he
was spending all of his free time making video games I wasn't doing that I was spending all my
free time doing like design shit so I kind of realized that it's like okay well it seems like
this design shit is what I really want to do uh maybe I should try and do that did you wind up
graduating from Purdue yeah I it was definitely fucking tough I'm not going to say it was not
tough it was definitely very hard but I felt like I would have that to fall back on if the design
thing right yeah I had no portfolio out of school uh luckily the design scene in Wisconsin is not as
uh competitive as you might imagine so I was able to get a job
relatively little experience but again I kind of I mean I say that but I did actually have
a decent amount of experience because I spent a lot of time doing personal work in college so I did
definitely have like some shit to show even though you know I kind of didn't go to a design school
that's interesting I mean I think people are going to be able to jump into your storyline here
in a number of ways because you did what most people do um you you pursue the safe route the
thing that is supposed to make you financially stable you did something respectable and studied
computer science you graduated but you had that burning thing inside of you that said you wanted
to make art you're living kind of in a not exactly the hotbed of whatever it is that you're doing
yet you're able to carve your way through make your own thing get a job figure out that
you're you're more you're destined for more things and so you wind up going freelance you're
like living the dream man congratulations man I don't I don't know about that but yeah I think if
I I don't think it's um yeah I think it's just about fucking persistence like I think uh
not persistent patience I think that it's it's been I'm like me preaching all patients is like
the fucking dumbest most just absolute give me a break thing because I feel like I have very very
little patience but I think it's definitely especially for people starting out uh you know
and it's tough especially with social media I think it would have been I don't know how this
like that this would have happened had this started in the age of social media I would be
I don't know I wonder about that a lot if if I would have stuck with this or if it would have
even like started at all to be honest or how it would have been different had I like started this
in an era of like Instagram and Tumblr and all this other bullshit um because I think those
companies are they're very I think people don't realize how uh like how much they shape a lot of
what we do I mean look at this like future that you guys are building this platform almost entirely
on the backs of Google Facebook like that's a big a piece of what we're like how we like interact
with each other every single day so I don't know I don't know I I don't know how that would have
turned out differently okay um all right uh Matt Kendall and in I think a lot of people on the
internet want to know this because you mentioned this before but what's your rendering rig
like let's see if we can get another sponsor um so I just bought two new computers um because it
was a long time and I kind of put it off for a while because it was this damn crypto bullshit
it was just driving up the fucking price of cards I just bought two new computers um with
four uh 1080 ti's in each of them um so it was a little price for four 1080 ti's that's the video
card yeah who makes the 1080 ti what's up who makes that uh navidia in media or navidia is that you
say it navidia yeah you never heard of navidia I thought you said I thought you say nvidia but
navidia oh maybe yeah okay I'm probably I don't know no I don't know I know probably nvidia yeah
maybe I don't know and did you build your own box or is it uh so yes and no um it's put together I've
got a buddy who um helped me fry baker shout out um you kind of like pick components um and then uh my
dad actually like physically put it together because my hands are dumb uh and I'm like not
remotely like mechanically sort of minded but yeah they're like custom boxes or whatever okay
that wasn't a great sponsorship opportunity right there you could have really just
gotten all specked out on us but okay I'm not gonna push you there yeah I yeah no I'm like
you got the contacts bring them back you have to plant the seeds first before that you can uh
take harvest the fruit if you will it's the same components as like everything else you know an
intel processor and blah blah blah no no that blah blah blah won't sponsor you so I don't know
what the f*** gate is on me I don't know what the f*** and I don't know what the ram is
it's f***ing ram I'm trying to set you up for this and it's not working okay fine now you know
Matt Kendall there's your answer it's uh NVIDIA 4 4 1080 Ti boards that he's got in there and
intel processors and something computers yeah something like that all right um that's here
are you doing anything in AR VR uh yeah I'm doing uh concept work for magically right now
and I've done a couple um VR projects in the past so yeah it's definitely something that I'm
interested in okay I know some people in LA and I told them that after I talked to you today that
I'll introduce you to them because they do a lot of concert stuff and they do 3D stereoscopic
interactive stuff it's super cool um and they do it really well so I'll connect you guys in case
there's an opportunity for you guys to to work together they're big fans of yours what's that
what's the name of the company it's called 3D live I'll connect you later I think I don't
did they reach out to you maybe I can't there's one that's like that uh Nate what's the guy's name
uh Nate Huber and who's the other guy you Ryan Ryan Ryan and Nate
don't worry I'll connect you after the show all right okay let's see what else we got going on
in the chat are you guys monitoring Facebook is anybody asking anything on Facebook yeah yeah
we're showing some love we have a question from Owen and he was wondering how do you keep the
everyday's from causing you stress and anxiety um because you're talking about your mindset a little
bit earlier about not taking it too seriously but how do you keep yourself from taking it so seriously
um again I think it's one of those things where I I feel like I've been lucky that the like sort of
like audience is kind of like ramped up slowly over you know 11 years um because it's one of those
things where I see people like you know push it a couple things on Instagram and it's just blown
off and now suddenly they've got you know 100,000 followers I'm sure that's got to be like a bit
freaky to like uh you know post something like is this good blah blah blah and there again I think
the format of project I don't have any like time to like stress out over it is this good it's like
not socks but 11 o'clock I have to post it so there's it takes that like self doubt out of it
because it's just like there's no choice I have to post it um so you know and after I post something
and it's like oh it's fucking terrible it's definitely like there's some sense of like god
damn it like because it's always like you're you're always gonna fall short when you put two hours
into something you're never gonna be like oh my god fucking crushed it Don you don't even know like
it's it's just it's just a such a short period of time it's just gonna be a sketch um so I think
it's always gonna be tough but there again you've got the next day so it's like okay well
today I'm gonna fucking buckle down and we're gonna fucking crush it today so I think it's
it's one of those things where you can only get so butt hurt about you know two days ago
when you've already made you know it's out of the next thing it's like there's no like
you can't regret the last thing because you have to like be focused on what the fuck am I doing
today like fuck yesterday yesterday sucked whatever what let's try make today not suck
um you can't get too in your head with it I guess
I love that that thinking that's that's so refreshing to hear it's like I don't know that's
really great um I have a question on YouTube it's from Andy and Andy asks what would you
do every day if you didn't have to do every day's if you couldn't do every day's not have to because
one day it was your question yeah I get it if I wasn't doing every day's
you'd be doing every other day's what was what would I be doing I'd just be watching tv or some
shit more I don't know I would just be like lazy or fair enough yeah
okay ask and answer yeah there it is yeah I'm done now you know what else is um so this question
and I'm almost kind of scared to ask this question although I I don't think it'll matter at all
but quite a few people at least on YouTube have asked um do you ever plan on stopping um why would
you be scared to ask that no then other people are like don't don't ask him that because maybe he'll
stop real think like that's never crossed your mind before I don't understand the mentality of like
don't ask me that like it's gonna break me uh no I uh I don't have a plan to stop but I
I can't like I'm gonna do this forever like that sounds like a fucking long time like
I'm gonna do it today pretty sure I'm gonna do it tomorrow you know being like I'm gonna do this
for the next 30 years whatever like that seems a little like daunting so uh I think to be honest
the reason I started doing this was to get better and that need to get better and that
desire and that like looking at other people's work and just feeling that they're absolutely
fucking crushing me and that I really like need to like do whatever I can to get better that has
not changed at all like I still go on the internet and look at people's work and it's like fuck I
can't do that so like uh so the whole reason I started this like nothing's changed I I've gotten
better for sure I've gotten better I've seen improvement but I still look at people's work
and it's like no not they're not even close like so many people's work like not even close
all right people I have a new segment I want to play with you it's called verses but before I get
the verses I want to read something from the internet here they're saying that man won't you
just do a training course or something and how dare they mention some competing network
oh there you guys watch this channel mention somebody else no that's cool what did they mention
no we're not gonna talk about them come on you can read the comments after the show guys
you guys you're about to whoever wrote that comment you're gonna be putting a timeout box
any second right now if you do that again but having said that I want to I want to mention to people
that we actually offer courses and relevant relevant to what we're talking about here
we teach a motion design course style frames and Matthew does a really great job of breaking down
how to do this in case you're not a genius like people who study computer science but can still
make amazing computer art we're trying to help you with what we are the courses that we're offering
you see how I did that so smoothly that's super super smooth see how a pitch man like me does it
people that's how you do it and just just for a couple of like the the guys that are watching on
there when they're like oh what a freaking idiot he doesn't know what the video card is I'm the one
who pronounced it correctly it is Nvidia not the video Nvidia somebody's like I work down the street
from them it's called Nvidia and Christmas right thank you that one's on me boom all right
all right now we're gonna do this thing it's a very short segment it's called versus let me hit play
here boom let me get some let me get some belfry here all right here's what we're gonna do I'm gonna
present you two scenarios oh I need to share this with you don't know who cares you don't need to see
it I'm gonna throw up two words and you just pick one or the other okay see if we can stir up some
controversy pick one or the other pick one or the other or say whatever you want but you have to
say it fast here we go you ready all right PC or Mac PC okay pen or a mouse mouse mm-hmm two wheels
or four wheels four wheels Targaryen or Stark
I don't their names I don't remember all their oh my god I thought you're Game of Thrones fan
oh no I am a Game of Thrones fan but their fucking names are so fucking weird that I can't remember
Targaryen house of blah blah blah okay I'll give you one pass okay Targaryen good all right
good okay next one Marvel or DC Marvel nice good choice last one last one Pepsi or Coke
Coke I guess oh come on you gotta say it more emphatically than that all right there you go
I'm trying to get sponsors here man oh shoot that applause you guys got a little out of control
there easy with the applause you guys easy all right let's see if we start up let's take a couple
more questions and I think we've taken up enough of this good man's time I know he's got an every
day to do a lot of work right he's got children to raise a wife to to talk to and things to do so
a couple more questions and let's wrap this part up but I have one last question I mean
uh one more segment but you guys what do you got for me um yeah I have a question myself um so in
some of your personal work you have actually created your own music um for for some of your videos
and I'm kind of wondering um do you think it's important to take these interests that you have
outside of design and combine them with your work um I think it will be good I feel like I'm I used to
do music I kind of stopped just because I wanted to focus mostly on design and I thought the music
was just pretty shitty and I just wanted to kind of leave that to the experts um I feel like I'm
not very like well-rounded um I'm interested in like investing and I'm interested in the news
and then pretty much like 99 percent just like design shit um so yeah I would say probably being
more well-rounded with other outside interests would be better
was that it is that what you wanted yeah yeah that's great all right Andy Nicholson is saying
thank you and all caps people Mike not just for this but for your attitude and inspiration
I appreciate that we didn't hear any embarrassing stories I'm a little bit disappointed in Mike's
friends right now me too guys you did not come through for us I thought you guys gonna tell
some weird stories and put them on the spot oh you know what okay a couple of people have asked
since you're into investing in technology and uh 1080 what are your thoughts on crypto
oh the show just went to a weird place okay go and answer the question Mike
now I feel like it's I've got a little money uh a tiny amount of money in uh Ethereum just as like I
yeah a kind of super hedge um but I would say overall I would put money I would put money into
Amazon if that but you have one thing you should put money into I would say put money in the Amazon
I think that's all that I think it's very um I would do that or index funds I think are
like BTI or spy I think are good ones but I think Amazon has a lot more room to run
I think they're advertising businesses just getting off the ground and I think they're
too big to fail solid investment advice from Mike boom I have one quick follow-up question
because super interesting too um where do you go to read up on on investments like is there a
subreddit or something you're into or a website um I've got a couple other um bodies that I uh
worked with at the uh in Wisconsin who are super into investing and there's a site um
that we've got a subscription to I think there's no one good place because nobody knows this
that's what like to me makes it interesting is there's no like you can have two fucking harvard
trained people and one's gonna say stock market's about to crash the other one's gonna say oh we're
gonna have a huge run here and nobody knows um but there's a site uh fool dot com motley fool
that has like stock picks and you can get their newsletters and it's maybe I don't even know it's
like a hundred bucks a year or something like that and they've got they've got some ideas but um
that's like hosted by kramer right is that the guy's name kramer on tnn or something like that or ms
nbc he's always yelling out the camera and it's not that guy but I mean my idea is too I mean
that's the thing I think taking a broad range and I think having your money in like a lot of different
things is another thing and I think the biggest thing is just saving your money in the first place
that's the good thing is like uh you know not having a car payment like if you're not into cars
buy a super cheap car like my car that I uh had had three hundred and fifteen thousand miles on it
it was a piece of shit like absolute piece of fucking trash like uh I think that's not a thing
but just like trying to like save as much money as possible because that's what gives you like
the flexibility to say no to projects and to do personal things if you're super fucking like
strapped every last penny is going to something then when that like kind of sketchy job where
you're like this is gonna be a shit show and I know I should not take this but I gotta fucking roll
the dice on it because I really need that fucking like money like you're gonna have to take it um so
I think having that cushion will really like allow you to say no to things and it will give you
more bargaining power too if you're like if you don't need to take a job then when you quote a job
you're gonna be quoting that job from like a position of power and like confidence and you'd
be like fuck this this is so much you I want for the job and they can take it or they cannot take
it and a lot of times they will take it um so I think uh having a cushion and just saving money
in the first place is definitely the biggest piece of that from that putting it into anything in the
stock market as long as it's not crypto I think you'll probably be in a good spot nice all right
I want to say this I think you just wrote the first chapter of the independent artist manifesto
right there don't spend a lot of money save it that way you have the power come on man
all right that's another project that we may or may not wind up doing after this show you guys
we're gonna now enter into lightning round I'm gonna ask you a few questions okay and feel free
to say whatever comes to your mind I only have five prompts for you band your favorite band
apex plan oh nice good one like that I haven't I haven't listened to in a while next up favorite city
uh
Los Angeles I know say it just go ahead I don't I don't know like city yeah I don't I guess
uh Charleston I don't oh you you're sucking up to the local population right there
only been there eight months what about Wisconsin uh well Wisconsin's not a city well I'm sorry
would you grow up in Wisconsin yeah I it's hard to say that that's my favorite place because it's
really like not it's pretty just like that's where I was born
whoo okay yeah all right uh no sponsorship there either okay let's keep going who's your hero
uh I don't really have a hero to be honest somebody is crying right now when you say that
my parents I guess my parents there you go all right excellent you'll sleep well tonight okay a regret
um are you supposed to be like quick these are like
like things like yeah to cry I'm trying um a regret I mean I regret when I'm like
fucking lazy and like don't do the work that I should be doing like I have many regrets throughout
the day of wasting time like that's like wasting time I guess is a regret are you trying to hit
at the quality of this show no no it's just I don't consider this wasting time like it's
been super interesting um I don't consider this wasting time I consider fucking looking at
Donald Trump bullshit or whatever that's wasting goddamn time all right last one last one name a
guilty indulgence guilty indulgence um eating shitty food I guess like what um ice cream
that's not too bad well flavor well what did you expect to say black tar heroin
hold on I know this is not the right sound effect where's my bong hit
fucking math okay ice cream what flavor what brand anything um we were just over in uh
I was over at that off Barcelona and uh anytime we're in Europe there's a lot of gelato
eating it's just you go in the shops and it's just god damn it so good
I don't eat very much ice cream at all
okay we want to let them off the hook with that gray I feel like I mean like brand like
hog and does or like a mint chip or like wires ice cream they eat ice cream and jerry's
I don't really eat ice cream it's something I like but uh yeah I don't I I they're all good I
don't fucking ice cream I feel like it's hard to like like cool like like ice cream is like bad
like it's all fucking good like what do you like I'm not uh-oh those are like fighting words for
people who care about that made in small batches handcrafted locally sourced organic hormone free
ice cream right they're out there somewhere and we just lost another sponsor you guys
he's like who cares about cars Wisconsin sucks I can't even do the review on this show
I'm gonna offend so many people my my mouth is hurting right now from laughing oh all right okay
before we say goodbye to you I want to let everybody know how to get in touch with you your name is
Beeple but your real name is Mike Winkleman and you can be found just about in every social
platform that's out there BeepleCrap.com because you know it's it's keeping in with his self-deprecating
tone and he's on Instagram at Beeple underscore crap I guess you couldn't just get Beeple on Twitter
and Facebook is at Beeple and he's also Beeple.tumblr and just so many other platforms I think
are you also on Pinterest on Pinterest yeah I've got you are everywhere okay art station
yep okay so um is there any last final parting thoughts a a book or sponsorship thing that you
don't want to promote I think you've heard enough bullshit from me
I didn't even get to all my questions for you okay okay I'll let you ask one question before we wrap
let's do this ask that's a hard-hitting question right now you guys this is bonus time you guys
okay let's see the industry in 10 years what's the industry going to be like in 10 years yeah it's
going to be dark for the people who work in advertising and in posts because the margins
are getting smaller and tighter every day we seem to be reading about another VFX company going under
and it's a sad place if you work in the commercial space but if you work in a place where you're able
to work directly with clients and consumers where you've built up a community around the things that
you love I mean Beeple super low-hanging fruit for you to build an audience around what you do put
together a book let people love and celebrate you man you can even call a Beeple crap on the cover
and I think people want to support you they want to see you succeed you are their hero so that's
what I would suggest everybody do the world is shrinking take advantage of it don't run away
from it is that okay got advice it's stay away from all that cryptocurrency oh my god stay away
with that kid don't no black tar heroine and no cryptocurrency and that's it Mike thanks very much
for joining us today guys just give him a big round of applause thank you all right I'm gonna take
us out to the end of the show I think it goes something like this
so
who is that