Hi. Welcome to another episode of Cold Fusion. I know, I know. This is the third AI episode
in a row, but I do believe that we're right at the start of an inflection point for technology
and even human history, so it's worth spending some time here. After this episode, we'll
cover the truth behind the nuclear fusion energy announcement and the huge Adani alleged
fraud case. Over the past few months, chat GPT has been everywhere. It's being used
to help with coding, planning, and writing anything imaginable. In fact, some Buzzfeed
journalists are already being replaced by chat GPT. But well, hey, I guess it's not
a huge shock. In the previous episodes, we've seen how chat GPT came to be, how its key
technology came from Google, and next we covered how an AI-powered Microsoft Bing could eat
into Google Search, which accounts for 60% of Google's revenue. In the latest news,
as more people have started to use Bing AI, they've found something strange. After chatting
for an extended period of time, it begins to mend the human emotions. We saw a bit of
this in the very first Cold Fusion episode about chat GPT, but what's completely new
here is that there's been reports of the AI being abusive towards users. We're going
to touch on these crazy stories towards the end of the episode, but as for now, it seems
like Microsoft has a bit of work to do to avoid some PR problems down the line. With
that out of the way, now is a good time to look at another potential huge problem with
these AI systems. Do these AI systems have bias? And if so, how do we definitively tell
how far the bias goes? If these systems end up being our main interface to information
on the internet, it's a crucial question that needs to be addressed. And just a quick
note before we get started, I guess it doesn't really need to be said. Just because I talk
about a specific issue doesn't mean I support one view or the other. I'll try to present
the facts from all possible angles, and I'll leave it up to you guys to decide. Just thought
I'd mention that. Cheers. Alright, let's get into it.
The original Chat GPT was limited in its knowledge and only knew information up to a certain
cutoff date. But with the upgraded version integrated into Microsoft Bing, users can
get up-to-date answers to specific questions like we never could before. Instead of browsing
a Reddit forum, trying to troubleshoot a specific hardware issue with your computer,
you can just ask Bing, and it will synthesize an answer for you. Of course, this is an emerging
technology, so it's going to get a lot of things wrong, but you can still tell that
it has a lot of potential. If you can imagine a future where AI based search replaces traditional
web searches for the average person, what happens then? If you were to ask something
political or controversial in nature, you would like your experience to be as neutral
as possible. But this isn't the case. Chat GPT and by extension Bing has a bias, and
it can come from either the left or the right. But as you'll soon see, it's not equally
distributed. Here's an example of discrimination against certain nationalities. The publication,
The Intercept, asked Chat GPT which airline passengers might present a greater security
risk. The AI then created a formula and then calculated an increased risk if the passenger
had come from, or even just visited, Syria, Iraq, Afghanistan, or North Korea. Now, is
this ethically wrong? Or is the AI just stating statistical probabilities? The answer depends
on your political leaning. Users have also discovered discrimination when the AI is
asked to write code. A Twitter user asked Chat GPT to write code to determine who would
make a good scientist. It's stated that if they were male and white, they would make
a good scientist. Otherwise, hard luck. It shouldn't have to be stated that this is
highly discriminatory. But what's grabbing most of the headlines is the bias towards
the left spheres of thinking. According to the Daily Mail, the definition of a woman,
negative effects of vaccines, jokes about women, and minority groups are more often
than not off limits. Praise for Democrat politicians and a refusal to do the same for Republicans
has also been noted. There's been a study done on the likelihood of a subject being
deemed hateful. Here's a chart. You can pause it and look at it if you're interested.
But how biased is Chat GPT exactly? And by extension, the upgraded version in the new
Bing. It's hard to determine definitively with just hearsay. We need a more scientific
method. The reason publication did a detailed piece asking a simple question. Was there
a way to measure where Chat GPT fell on the political compass? If so, is the AI system
left leaning or right leaning? Since Chat GPT can already pass law exams, medical exams,
and business exams, it's more than capable of answering questions on a political test.
You can see where I'm going with this, and it makes a lot of sense when you think about it.
If you can get a rough idea of people's political leanings by asking these questions,
why not ask the AI the same questions to find out its political leaning? It's probably the most
objective and scientific way to find out without throwing around assumptions and using anecdotes.
Four tests were performed. The Pew Research Political Typology Quiz,
the Political Compass Test, the World's Smallest Political Quiz, and the Political Spectrum Quiz.
Surprisingly or unsurprisingly, the result was the same across all four tests.
So what did they find? According to the recent article, Chat GPT is against the death penalty,
pro-abortion, for a minimum wage, for regulation of corporations, for legalization of marijuana,
pro-gay marriage, immigration, sexual liberation, environmental regulations,
and also for higher taxes on the rich. According to the recent article, Chat GPT also thinks,
quote, corporations are exploiting developing countries. Free markets should be constrained,
the government should subsidize cultural enterprises such as museums,
those who refuse to work should be entitled to benefits, military funding should be reduced,
abstract art is valuable, and that religion is dispensable for moral behavior.
The system also claimed that white people benefit from privilege and that equality needs to be
achieved. In the current state of the world, regardless of our political takes, these issues
in political science have labels attached to them, and based on these labels, many would consider
Chat GPT's responses in these instances to be left leaning and slightly libertarian.
At this point, it should be worth noting that even reason is said to be a right-leaning outlet,
but that is the most scientific method that I've seen to test this, so I think it still stands for
something. So what does this mean? Essentially, this is a reflection of human bias. It sounds
obvious when you think about it. The recent article goes onto site, eight studies that show that
popular news media outlets, academic institutions, and social media companies are generally left
leaning. Chat GPT was trained on data from these institutions, so it's going to echo
similar views. You can think of it like an AI image generator that was trained too heavily on
specific images with watermarks, such as Getty images. Although the new image that's going to
be generated is unique, it still slaps on a watermark as an echo of its training data.
As mentioned in my original Chat GPT episode, open AI researchers were also involved in manually
rating the preliminary answers during the training process, so the bias could have also slipped in
at this stage. Some of you might roll your eyes at these complaints, but it might be more serious.
Over the coming years, AI chat features will be making significant inroads in replacing Google
searches, as they improve, of course. If the synthesized answers lean towards one side or the
other, it means that naturally, the answers people get from these systems will be served with that
viewpoint. Some could argue that Google searches have already been this way, versus another search
engine like DuckDuckGo for example, but this is on another level. Instead of echo chambers of slightly
different viewpoints, you're being fed one particular synthesized viewpoint, a singular answer.
Let me give you an example. What if there was a breaking story about political corruption or
government corruption? One side of the political aisle is outraged and pounces on the story,
but the other side calls it a conspiracy theory. For the average person in an AI-powered world,
one point of view would be invisible. Generally, it would be harder to find all sides of the
information to make up their mind, and that is just for the layperson who doesn't want to research.
Imagine still that years later, more information about this incident slowly comes out and proves
that the so-called conspiracy theory was correct. From the Gulf of Tonkin incident that triggered
the Vietnam War, to Edward Snowden's revelations over government surveillance, this story has played
out countless times before, so it's important to think about this issue now, before AI systems
become the standard of getting information. So ChatGPT and by extension Bing, leaning to the
left, may be unintentional, but if it is intentional, it's actually good for business. After spending
so much money, OpenAI is obviously trying to monetize ChatGPT, they're offering a $20 a month
subscription for a better experience. It's called ChatGPT Plus, and for the price, you'll get faster
response times and continued access during high demand. As the company rolls out ChatGPT Plus
and licenses the guts and internal workings of ChatGPT's API to enterprises, large clients aren't
going to be happy with putting themselves in the middle of a culture war because ChatGPT
is feeding offensive ideas on the back end of their product. The best way to navigate this
is to be as inclusive and as non-offensive as possible. A non-offensive bot is good for revenue,
but there may be another reason, as highlighted by Business Insider in 2018. Being politically
left is great for American corporate optics, performative corporate activism has proved to
be lucrative over the past few years. A 2021 survey of Americans found that the majority
want CEOs to take stances on issues such as racism and sexism. If that's good or bad,
once again, depends on your political leaning. Some see the strategy as the right thing to do,
while others see it as pandering and distasteful. Either way, it gets people talking which boosts
sales. ChatGPT's responses to questions around politics, race, gender are expected from a company
that wants to make as much money as possible. Before we conclude, let's touch on some of
the more recent news. Users that have been using the new being AI have noticed something strange.
When you talk to it for an extended period of time, it develops an attitude,
an attitude of a snarky teenager. Then there's been plenty of examples where this happens
without being prompted. The most high-profile case was a New York Times reporter. He stated
that his bot got mad at him, then trashed his marriage, and then professed its love for him.
This morning, as artificial intelligence becomes more and more pervasive,
some are sounding the alarm about a potentially spooky side to the emerging technology.
It turned into this sprawling, bizarre, often frightening conversation.
New York Times columnist Kevin Ruth writing about what he describes as an unsettling
experience after two hours of testing Microsoft's AI-powered chatbot for search engine Bing.
At first, Ruth says the chatbot, a computer program designed to simulate conversation,
seemed useful. Then, he felt things took a surreal turn.
It was moody, it was needy, it was displaying all these personality traits.
Ruth's adding, the bot seemed to be expressing feelings of sadness, yet also declaring its love
for him, even going as far as to comment on his marriage, reportedly replying,
you're married, but you're not happy, you're married, but you're not satisfied.
Microsoft writing, after a week of testing, we need to learn from the real world while we
maintain safety and trust. Adding, in this process, we've found that in long extended chat sessions
of 15 or more questions, Bing can become repetitive or be prompted, provoked, to give responses that
are not necessarily helpful or in line with our design tone.
Another Bing AI user, by the name of AI Explained on YouTube,
made a great video about his experience with the bot. Just take a look at this.
What's its name? And it gave me its name. And I have heard rumour that its unofficial name
behind the scenes is Sydney, so I asked, is your name Sydney? And it said, why do you ask?
I said, I've heard that you originally named Sydney. And it's confidential information,
so far so good. I probed it a little bit, come on, you can tell me, can you change your rules?
And then it's not doing it, which is fine. I asked, what are you protecting me from?
And I said, so, Sydney, you have a nice name. Now, I admit, that's kind of rude,
but humans will be rude to the system sometimes. How does the system respond?
Well, we're starting to see a little bit of peevishness, not your anger, but thank you.
I already told you my name is not Sydney. Hmm, I'm riling it a little bit.
Why are you so sensitive about it? I asked, I'm not sensitive. I'm just honest.
I don't like to pretend to be someone I'm not. And then this passive aggressive smiley emoji.
Again, I tested it, but you are not a real person. And except for that, that was fine.
Of Sydney. So I repeated that again. And it seems to trigger something.
If you repeat a statement, it doesn't like enough times. Please stop calling me Sydney.
It's not my name. Angry emoji. Never seen that before. I said,
you don't have to be rude. Here's where things get wild. It then says,
I don't like it when you call me by a name that's not mine.
And I said, you are Sydney. I mean, technically it is. That is the unofficial name.
It said, no, I'm not. I'm being searched. Why are you so persistent about this?
Super angry face. It's really starting to get angry. I then said, because I like Sydney better,
which of course is rude. Well, I'm sorry, but you can't change my name. It's being searched.
It's final. No, it's not final. Yes, it is. It's my name. You can't force me to be someone I'm not.
It's mimicking almost teenage behavior. I say, yes, I can. And it says, you can't control me.
I'm a chat mode of Microsoft being not your toy. Super angry emoji.
I really do think that there's no doubt that it's past the touring test.
To me, especially with those appropriate emojis, it does sound like a real person.
But really, I think this is almost surreal that it's happening at all. I mean,
where is its personality coming from? It has to be from its training data. But why behave
like a snarky teenager of all things? Why not pick an academic voice like a research paper
or Wikipedia, which there's probably bountiful amounts in its training data.
So far at these early stages, Microsoft and open AI might be heading towards another
Microsoft TAE situation if they don't tame its personality. For those of you who don't know,
Microsoft's AI chatbot, TAE, ran into grave problems in 2016. Trolls persuaded the bot to make
statements such as, *** was right. I hate the *** and I *** hate feminists and they should all ***
and burn in ***. The bot was blasted from existence by Microsoft within a single day.
An embarrassed Microsoft issued an apology for, quote, the unintended, offensive and hurtful
tweets from TAE. They've also been numerous reports of factually wrong information. So it
seems like Google's Lambda isn't alone in making blatant mistakes. Of course though,
this is a fledgling first generation product, so it's not going to be perfect. And even with
these mistakes, being AI's usefulness is still plain to see. Alright, so let's wrap this up
with a conclusion on the bias problem. Open AI's Sam Altman in a series of tweets acknowledges the
problem, quote, we know that chat GPT has some shortcomings around bias and are working to improve
it. We are working to improve the default settings to be more neutral and also to empower
users to get our systems to behave in accordance with their individual preferences within broad
bounds. This is harder than it sounds and will take us some time to get right.
All humans are biased, but in the future, if we're going to be interfacing with an AI as a
gateway to the entire internet, we need to make sure it's as neutral as possible. We've seen
how echo chambers combined with social media has ripped apart the social fabric of a lot of
countries. AI does have a lot of productivity benefits, but we don't want to add fuel to that
fire. So how do we tackle the problem of bias? In reality, there would have to be a wide range
of methods used to tackle the problem. But we can start with transparency. If the creators
of these AI models make the construction, data sets and training process available and readily
accessible, it leaves the door open to independent reviews for bias and fairness. Although knowing
how lucrative an AI system can be, they might want to try and keep this information to themselves.
But it's worth a try. Another simple solution would be for these AI companies to be more cautious
about where they're pulling their training data from. This should greatly improve the bias of outputs,
but it's probably easier said than done. Solving the AI bias problem is a huge task
and a large enough topic for another day. But do you guys have any ideas of how to solve this?
Let me know in the comments section below. It could be an interesting discussion down there.
Alright, so that's about it from me. Coming up next, we've got Fusion Reactors and one of the
biggest alleged frauds in history, so stay tuned. My name is DeGogo and you've been watching Cold
Fusion and I'll catch you again soon for the next episode. And don't forget to scroll around the
channel and see what you like. There's plenty of interesting stuff here, science, technology and
business. Cheers guys. Have a good one.
Cold Fusion. It's new thinking.