Hello and welcome to this first episode of The Closure Pills. I'm planning to
make this a weekly thing where we go through the functions in the standard
library, in the closure standard library. There are many of them, this is like worth
a few years of screencasts. I'm not sure if we are gonna go that far and do the
entire thing, but certainly I'm going to enjoy this and I hope you're going to
enjoy this too. The functions and the examples that we're going to see
in these screencasts are mostly coming from a book I'm working on by Manning.
It's available here on the Manning website. So if you enjoy the content of
the screencast you are interested in knowing more about the function in the
standard library. There's a good chance you're also gonna like this book. I hope
you enjoy the screencast and also enjoy the book if you buy it. For this very
first episode we are going to see something that is hopefully not too
complicated. It's a nice little function called f0. It's not very common. You're
not gonna hear this very often, but it's there and it's got a few interesting
use cases that you might be interested in the next time you're working on some
nil input. You might remember about f0 and remember what it can do for you. There
are alternatives. There are different ways of doing things and that's a good
thing. You can also quickly check the sources by doing source or f of f nil
and you can see it's got three arities. It's taking a function as the first
argument is taking then three arguments of any type. So what is the goal of this
function? This is a higher-order function. It takes your function, which is the
thing, your target that you want to patch, so to speak, and it takes up to three
arguments and those arguments are going to be used for the generated function as
defaults if any nil is passed in as an argument. Probably better showing an
example about how this can be used, but basically let's say you have a
pattern matching string of some sort. You want to verify if you can say
hello you in some string that is coming to you and you can use refined for that
and refined is going to return the matching part of the string. If any, if
not, it's going to return nil. If you use refined and you are matching on maybe
external input that is coming from the input, the user input, or third-party
services, and so on, you might receive a nil instead. If you receive a nil you get
this nasty null point or exception. So depending on the application you might
need to take care of that. There are many ways you can take care of that. You can
do a try-catch, you can use a condition, but maybe this is a very
good use case for functional programming. By using higher-order function you can
remove a condition essentially or removing a try-catch. Both of them
are not absolutely bad things to have, but they increase the complexity of the
program. So if you can remove this complexity and remove a condition you
don't need to think about the two branches of a condition. That is a
decrease in the complexity of the program. So fnil can be helpful in this.
How would you use fnil? We said a function generator, so you produce a
different function. So we can call it refined plus just to differentiate the
name, but knowing that we are talking about the good old refined where we are
dealing with nil arguments, with defaults for nil arguments, and you use
fnil. fnil is taking the original function, the one you want to wrap around,
and up to three arguments are the default if you pass nil to that function. Let's
say we pass a nil rejects, so we can use for example the empty rejects as a
default, and we can use the empty string as a target string, as a default if you
pass nil. Once you define this you refined, you can use it in place of your
old refined occurrences, and you just use it as usual. So you would pass any
rejects, and say you pass nil, this time we are getting back a nil, we are now
going null pointer exception, because we are replacing that nil with an empty
string, and we can do the same with rejects. If that is the case for
your application you can do that with all arguments, not just the last or not
just the first. How would it be without fnil? Why do you want to use it? Then you
might have something like this, where you check, let's say string s, and then you
go through your rugged rejects to see if s is matching or not. Of course we
don't have any s, so we define hello, and we try again, and as you can see it's
going as expected, it's matching on a low, but with the when you can of course
also pass in a nil, and that will go through. So essentially with fnil we
are able to replace a condition, this condition specifically, with a non
condition, with something that is not a condition. There is a condition inside
fnil, but you don't see it, that's the important part. So you can use refined
plus, and everything goes without any exception. So you would use fnil if this
kind of rule needs to be applied in multiple places in nana in space, or in
multiple namespaces. So if you need to reuse this, you define the actual
function, and you can reuse it across the application. So we talked about the
arities of fnil, it's got only three, meaning that if you try something more
than three, let's see what happens. So let's say you want to generate an fnil
for plus, where if you pass in any nil arguments, you're going to replace them
with some like neutral number like zero for addition. So you want five of them,
but if you try you'll see that you're passing the wrong number of arguments
of fnil, because fnil only supports three of them, unfortunately. I would say
unfortunately up to certain points. So if you have a function with four, five, six
arguments, you're probably looking at something that needs refactoring in some
other ways, and probably some obstruction is missing, and you need to extract that
obstruction out, and remove or reduce the number of arguments. But let's say you
really need that, we can easily extend fnil to support more arguments. To do that,
we'll define our own fnil, we'll call it fnil plus, and instead of taking like
three arguments, we'll just take a variable number of arguments. Then as a
contract, we'll definitely have to return the generated function, and this
would be a function of any number of arguments, because this is what the
problem we are trying to solve, so to wrap with fnil a function as more than
three arguments, potentially any number. What we need to do then is apply the
target function to these arguments, but when we do apply to the arguments we
need to take care of the potential nil arguments, and replace them with something
that is coming from the options that we are passing to fnil. You need to
take care also of the fact that the number of arguments you're going to apply
f to might be less of the number of arguments that you have defaults for. So
what I'm going to do is to create a sequence that contains nil defaults for
all those defaults that are not given as options. Better showing you what I'm
talking about, so I'm going to map over the sequence, and if I'm in front of
a nil argument, then I'm going to return the default. This is the logic. If not,
then I can just return the argument. I don't need to do anything, and what I'm
mapping on are the arguments, what would be actually passed in during the
invocation, and a sequence that is the concatenation of opts, which are my
options, my defaults, with any number of nils to pad at the end. This makes sure
that I have enough defaults, I have always enough defaults to cover any
possible cases, even if they are not. The right number of arguments is not
passed in. So if we do this, I'm going to show you what this new fnil plus can
do, and for example in the case of plus that we were looking at before, we'll
define a new plus plus function that is using fnil plus instead of the normal
fnil, over plus, which is our target function, and then we say I want like
five potential defaults for nils that are passed in to my plus function, or
double plus function. So what I can do now that I was unable to do
before, and I show you what I'm able to do now, if I do this with the normal plus
I'm getting null pointer exception, but if I use the double plus, that is going
through, and is summing up all the numbers that are available, is
basically removing the nil from the list of arguments, and summing up the
rest, and it's replacing nil with the default I gave, which is a zero. As
potential alternatives, we saw that you can use when, you can use a
condition, you can use a try-catch. There's also another interesting function
in the standard library you could use. If you don't need this behavior to be
reused, and the entire application, and this is the threaded thread first and
thread last sum option, and if I do, for example, if I do pass hello to my
refined, where I'm checking a you hello thing, this is perfectly fine, and this
got also the nice, oh, why is returning nil?
Interesting, and let me just check why this is it, this is the case, I wasn't
expecting that. Oh yeah, I inverted the rejects, sorry for that. So, well anyway,
let's say I'm searching hello, and I'm finding hello, the good thing about some
threaded last is that I can also pass in nil, so let's say my s is still defined
as nil, if I have this input coming through, and I pass it through, this will
have the same effect as f nil, and this is a nice alternative, as I said, this is
not something you would assign to a var in a namespace to reuse, this is
something you use once, and if that is the case for you, this is a good
alternative. Last thing I want to talk about in this first screencast is the
performance profile of nil, so f nil as it is, like in the standard library, let's
have a look again, and the sources is a very simple function, it's not doing
anything particularly bad, it's just basically using nested if statement to obtain the
effect of replacing the nil with the default you give, the performance
profile of this with the limitation that you cannot pass more than three
arguments is a constant time generation of the function, and a constant time
application as well, big O of three basically, with the f nil plus that we
showed before, instead the generation is still remaining a constant time, so
f nil will generate just fine in constant time, but the application of course
will be linear, because we'll have to iterate through the number of arguments
you're passing through, and check if they're nil, and apply the rule to
replace the nil argument with the default. We can see that quite easily if we, for
example, if we take f nil plus, and we create, well, so let's redefine our plus
function with nil plus, where instead of just using like five arguments as we did
before, we give defaults for like a big range of arguments, let's say one billion
or so of arguments, so this generation is just instant, it's a constant time, we
don't need to go, we don't need to iterate through the range at the moment,
everything is lazy, it's going to be iterated as you use it, if you then use
the plus plus function, as usual, yes, oops, I did, I did apply f nil without
specifying the plus, if we do this, this is still, it's not going to, it's not
going through the entire sequence of the range to apply the defaults, because we
are not passing enough arguments, and soon as we go up with that, so let's put a
time on this, as soon, of course, as soon as we go up with this, so we apply
double plus to more arguments, say, 10, 10 millions, and we see that the time to
do this computation go up, and it's roughly linear computation, and it's
coming back now in eight, eight, about eight seconds, so this is it for this
first episode, I hope you enjoyed, if you like this content, have a look at the
book, a few sample chapters are available, and also if you enjoyed this
screencast, I hope you'll enjoy the next one, roughly one week, I hope to keep up
with the weekly thing, the weekly screencast plan, I might miss one or two,
but we'll see how it goes, so thank you for listening, goodbye.