The process specification language is a set of logic terms used to describe processes.
The logic terms are specified in an ontology that provides a formal description of the
components and their relationships that make up a process.
The ontology was developed at the National Institute of Standards and Technology, and
has been approved as an international standard in the document ISO 18629.
The process specification language can be used for the representation of manufacturing,
engineering and business processes, including production scheduling, process planning, workflow
management, business process re-engineering, simulation, process realization, process
modeling, and project management.
In the manufacturing domain, PSLA Euro 1 registered trademark S objective is to serve
as a common representation for integrating several process-related applications throughout
the manufacturing process life cycle.
Ontology, the foundation of the ontology is a set of primitive concepts, constants,
functions, and relations.
This core ontology is then used to describe more complex concepts.
The ontology uses the common logic interchange format to represent the concepts, constants,
functions, and relations.
This ontology provides a vocabulary of classes and relations for concepts at the ground level
of event instances, object instances, and time points.
PSLA Euro 1 registered trademark S top level is built around the following, activity, a
class or type of action, such as install part, which is the class of actions in which parts
are installed, activity occurrence, an event or action that takes place at a specific place
and time, such as a specific instance of install part occurring at a specific time
stump, time point, a point in time, object, anything that is not a time point or an activity.
See also, ISOTC184-SC4, Standards for Industrial Data, Process Ontology, Ontologies for Processes.
References