Can anyone recognize that?
Can you recognize that?
We do like a world's wall though of like things to look for on my back.
Oh, you want to read the quote?
Yep.
Oh, Monty Python, you got it.
The killer rabbit with sharp pointy things like this.
Some call me Tim, Tim.
When I let go of what I am, I become what I might be loud too, loud too, loud too.
That's my wife's, what time is it?
It is, oh my God, we're late.
We're late.
We're kind of late.
I need to start my pomo and all that jazz.
Can I finish my coffee first?
How many have we got here?
I don't even know.
I don't have my counters on the screen like I usually do.
I am so discombobulated because I came back from that run.
Also Hacker Music Yoga is on, I'm going to leave the music on for just a bit more.
When the music goes off, that means we're actually down for Bidnath.
We're going to get ready for Bidnath.
But I'm going to keep my draw diagrams on there because I might be able to use that.
What else?
I've got Anton running, I've got No Albs running, I've got the Discord running.
What else do I need?
Wait, wait.
Website.
Okay, let me grab a new web window and put this over here so I can do stuff.
All right, boosters or whatever we're going to call you.
I don't even know.
RWXers, what should we call you?
What should we call you?
Okay, what's your name?
I don't like skill stackers, that's like weird too, there's like another thing.
We're on the same page.
Boosties.
That should be my swag.
My swag should be boosties, manziers and boosties.
You notice this channel's rated M, right?
For the next four hours I'm going to be trying really, really hard to have you rated M, but
for the most part that mature rating is there for a reason.
You've been warned.
That's all I have to say about it.