So, welcome to Q&A QCA, Questions, Conversations, and Advice with RDBxRob and my absolutely crazy community,
which happens to be international. And so the first question today is, what is the best way to learn foreign languages?
And we've been actually having fun here because somebody asked me to, oh god, what are you sending us?
I'm a little bit afraid. I'm a little afraid of what this is. Somebody's sending us random things.
Yeah, I told you I can speak Russian.
Somebody said, wait, wait, wait, can you speak French with...
You don't speak French like an American. You speak French like a French person.
And I was like, well, thank you. That's very nice.
And then I proceeded to like try every American accent I could.
So this has been like the theme for like the last five minutes.
And then said he says, now do it like a valley girl.
I want to do it very well.