Well Ian, it's great to be here with you on Sky and I suppose how I found my way here
is that for years people have been telling me you must read The Master and his Emissary.
Many people around Dark Mountain have been strongly influenced by it as a book and last
autumn when I had just finished work on At Work in the Ruins I finally sat down with it
and understood why because the question that I'm starting from in At Work in the Ruins is
what's the nature of the trouble that the world is in, not least the part of that trouble that
writes under the name of climate change and early in the book I say whenever we get into
a conversation about climate change that conversation starts inevitably inside the frame of science
because it's science that brings us the news and gives us ways of talking about it. Climate
change is a scientific concept and yet I've been going around for years saying climate change asks
questions that science cannot answer and the example of that that I have sent her on in the
book is how did we find ourselves in this trouble? Is it the result of a piece of bad luck with the
atmospheric chemistry that it turns out seven generations down the line that building industrial
societies around all of these fossil fuels is throwing out of whack the climate system on
which the conditions of possibility of human societies as we've known them have taken place?
So is it bad luck or is it a consequence of a way of approaching the world, a way of seeing and
treating everyone and everything that would anyway have brought us to such a pass even if
the atmospheric chemistry had been different, had been less sensitive to all these carbon dioxide
emissions and I feel like you've given one of the fullest accounts I've come across of that way
of approaching the world. Yes well thank you I suppose when one talks about how we got here
there are a number of different ways you can answer that question so it's not wrong of course to
say that it's a problem to do with use of fossil fuels and so on but that itself
is rooted in something bigger and beyond I believe which is as you say a whole
conception of what we are what the planet is and how the two relate. So how do we begin to
describe that or unpack that in a way that might help us ground the conversations that go on about
climate change differently to the way they often seem to? Yes the difficulty is that there isn't
a very easy way to say well if only you say this or do that it will work it's more a kind of way of
being in the world that we need which we've lost but it can I think encouragingly be recovered and
is you know I see and I'm sure you see this of course that there is a hunger for a way of
thinking about ourselves and what we're doing here that is more sophisticated
and more inclusive than the one that we've we've been taught and we've been sort of
almost without realizing it we've been dragooned into a way of thinking that would have seemed
extremely odd to our ancestors and to most people who are not brought up in the modern western
tradition and it's a very modern thing even in the west I mean I would say perhaps only the last
200 years at the maximum that we have adopted this very harshly reductionist
strictly materialist way of thinking and I think that is at the bottom of what we've got wrong.
And you've used that word modern several times there one of the one of the books that was in
the field of possibility or created the field of possibility for what I've been writing is a book
called Hospicing Modernity by Vanessa Machado de Oliveira who's a Brazilian scholar who's based
in Canada and that image of what is called for in the kind of times we're in being neither to try
and save modernity and make it somehow sustainable nor to try and overthrow it and bring it down or
stage some kind of revolution but being to give it a good ending not least so that it can pass on
the lessons that it has for us that may only be revealed in its in its ending and it feels like
that is part of what this the the hunger or the longing that that you're describing that I think
we both encounter. I like that idea very much because as you say the sort of overthrow he's
always a bad idea to do something peremptory and abrupt but we haven't got a lot of time
and we may not be able to as it were save modernity but as you say it's very important that whatever
we leave is something that is viable and useful to whatever comes after us.
After Paul and I wrote The Dark Mountain Manifesto I found myself increasingly getting invited into
rooms where climate scientists were being brought together with artists and indigenous elders and
people representing different kinds of knowledge or practice and it felt like the the invitation
from the scientists on the one hand there was an assumption that we were going to somehow have a
magic way to help deliver the message get people to listen to what the science was telling so we
were being sort of enlisted as a message delivery system and I say this I don't think this is quite
what we're for but equally where that was coming from there was a sense of helplessness on the part
of the scientists of you know we have the knowledge we can tell people and the kind of knowledge we
produce is what the modern world says is the only kind of knowledge that is reality and yet when we
come with a message that calls into question our ability to just continue and extend these
trajectories of growth and progress and development as they have been understood around here recently
suddenly they're not listening to us any more than they would listen to the protesters who are
outside the gates of the COP meeting and what I've experienced as a paradox is I find myself trying to
say science has to take a humbler role in relation to the other kinds of knowledge and practice that
are showing up here to people who are experiencing a sense of helplessness as scientists or as people
bringing the message from science where to say that more humility might be what's called for
which I think was also in the language that you were using just now at first glance that sounds
like the last thing that is needed and yet there's a deep truth in there and actually a sense of relief
often when we get properly into dialogue with scientists and non-scientists around this at
science not being asked to carry all the weight of knowing the world and telling us what it needs to
what needs to be done absolutely and the the false impression that science can do far more than
science can ever be asked to achieve is one of the reasons for people feeling that science is an
enemy whereas I believe it to be a hugely valuable tool but it is only that and if one can see it as
that and rather over overreaching claims are not made for it then that rift can be reconciled people
can see it for what it is it's when it pretends to be a sort of omnipotent and omniscient or
potentially so you know we're nearly there only a few more experiments and we really understand it
all that is the sort of thing that makes any experience and wise person feel alienated from
the discourse so I think what we want is is to rehabilitate science I find myself in the odd
position that I'm a great believer in both science and reason and I've spent most of my life trying
to practice these these things and it falls to somebody who believes in them passionately
to point out their limitations so another thing that I do is to is to say reason is hugely valuable
but first of all it depends what you mean by reason as it depends what you mean by science
and secondly it depends on what you're asking it to do it can do certain things but beyond that it
can't go so there are certain things that we know are very real but are somehow beyond the reach of
mere reason and the nature of music would be an example we can rationalize about its structure
we can analyze it we can take it apart we can get notes and we can look at them in our electron
microscope and we can say this note is nothing but the music is something very great so it's that
process that needs to be done and so what I'm really saying is the over defensiveness of science
and the over defensiveness of reason are understandable because at the moment they're under attack I think
very wrongly but the reason they may be under attack is because they are misrepresenting themselves
or maybe not even that but there has gone into the popular culture a myth that science can
do everything that reason can answer all our questions but there's absolutely no question
that these claims are unsubstantiated an unsubstantial boom and the analogy that I use is to say you
know how does one be a friend to science yes if your friend is tripping on acid on the roof of a
building and thinks he can fly yes to be a friend to them is not to go yeah man go for it absolutely
it's to put your arm around the shoulder and say why don't we sit down over here and have a little
chat yes which I feel is kind of what you have been been doing in a way that takes it away also
from that the conflictual mode of engagement with the limits of science that doesn't that's a very
good vivid example I like and it's effectively the ancient saying Plato is my friend but a
greater friend is truth and you know so attributed to Aristotle probably wrongly
but it's that that if you are a friend of science and of reason you don't misrepresent it as something
that it isn't because that way you cause a false falling away from it from people who quite rightly
won't accept extreme the extreme positions the very black and white positions that reason
wrongly understood and science wrongly understood can adopt a sort of dogmatic position and dogma
is our enemy in whatever form it comes and in our world now there are far too many dogmas and
are too many things that can't be questioned and when you get to that point as Hannah Arendt said
if things can't be questioned you're in a tyranny so one of the things that I get to in thinking
about this is the relationship between what in my terms is knowledge and knowing
and obviously you know we talked about this last night science as a name for this set of
activities only came in around the 1830s prior to that the people who were doing what we think of
as science would have called themselves natural philosophers and in a sense that shift of name
is reflective of a moment in which a monopoly is being granted where this set of activities are
being seen and seeing themselves as the monopoly on knowing on the work of knowledge because that's
what science means what I found myself um thinking about is the place where maybe these scientists
who I was meeting in these rooms talking about climate change were stark is holding the knowledge
where knowledge is the kind of the fruits of these these activities but it's a kind of it's an arms
length thing and then there's another piece of work which is bringing the knowledge home and if
you think about the way in which the language of knowing I mean if we go to the Hebrew Bible for
example the word to know include can range from you know sexual intercourse to intellectual
apprehension or the fruit of the tree of knowledge in Genesis there is a there's a kind of dance for
me between you know the experience of knowing out of which I distill knowledge that can be shared
which includes the kinds that can be put in books and on shelves and then that dance is completed
at the moment where a reader brings their own experience to the words so as to bring them back
to life in their experience of knowing which will not mirror perfectly the experience of
knowing that led me to write it but it's a bit like two choreographers who use the same set of
choreographic notation the dance that the second choreographer will make from the notations of
the first will be recognizably akin to the first one and so there's this kind of three
three-way move of the experience of knowing the production of knowledge and then the experience
of knowing arising from encountering that which when I then read the master and his emissary felt
to me very close to the dance of the hemispheres that you're describing which was striking because
what I had been saying was I think we've got the a hierarchy where knowledge is held to be the
important bit rather than the experience of knowing that might be part of where we're
getting stuck part of the trouble we ran absolutely that's a very rich vein to mine
and as you know I sometimes contrast and I don't think it's exactly the same but the
difference is that we have in German and French for different kinds of knowledge so there's there's
Canon in German and Konnetto in French which means knowing from experience and there's
Wissen in German and Savoie in French which is to know as it were the facts and another way of
talking is that there is data there is information there is knowledge and there is understanding
and understanding is intelligence and it's what in fact whatever you do with AI but that's
another story you won't achieve that understanding because to have that understanding you have to
have lived an embodied life with emotions and and the body and all the the what we think of
as disadvantages that go with that so yes and the other thing is that what you describe is what has
been amusingly dubbed the McGillchrist manoeuvre which is which is my my theme that in all
understanding there is a three-step process the first take on anything as it were preconceptually
and as a whole is taken by the right hemisphere then at a subsequent stage it is broken down
categorized analyzed it's it's the bare bones of its structure were examined
but then all that knowledge needs to be taken back into the holistic picture of the right
hemisphere and absorbed there and become in a way implicit in that picture the easiest example I can
give is that of learning a piece of music but you're first attracted to it as a whole as you
start to play it you realize you have to practice certain passages and you start thinking intellectually
about the harmonic structure but when you go on stage to perform you must forget all that not
that it was wasted time it was very important time but that now it must be taken up into and become
implicit in the whole so I think that's I hope that something to do with what you were talking
about with knowledge the distinction of knowledge and knowing I mean perhaps interestingly knowledge
is is is a noun knowing is a verbal participle and you're what you're talking about is the
idea of something which is a lived experience yes yes exactly and one of the the things that
worries me about the ways in which we are responding to things like climate change
and actually I wonder if this thought might be extended even to the way in which we responded
to the pandemic is this sense of seeing the world through in your terms the left brain
perspective so that the world comes to be conceived of as a problem to be solved
that if we can just map if we can generate enough knowledge about how the world works
then we can come up with the set of solutions for managing the world as if the world is a thing
that needs to be turned into knowledge for its own good in order for it to continue to
have a chance of existing and I think that people can build very kind of convincing
arguments for what needs to be done that could actually lead us to very dystopian places
indeed and arguably yeah well and the the analogy which I get from my friend Paul Kingsnorth
he talks about all the things that he's learned from keeping a fish tank with a few
freshwater fish in it with his son and how this you know you have to measure the temperature it
can't get too hot can't get too cold you have a whole chemistry set of different things that you
have to drop into it to regulate it and all of this to do what a river or a lake does easily
and for free and my concern is that this left brain approach to the world when it is granted the
kind of dominance that it has had in modernity comes to can't see the difference between a fish
tank and a living world comes to represent the living world as if it were a fish tank and then
attempts to turn the world into a fish tank a thing that requires a total system of human
management and control yes again there's a there's a lot in that I think one being the difference
in scale which shouldn't superficially shouldn't make a difference but it does because what we're
dealing with in nature and what we're dealing with in human society and dealing with with
everything important in this world are complex systems not complicated systems and the distinction
being one which is effectively just like a large mechanical system the complicated system just takes
a bit few more arrows and a few more algorithms but the complex system is one that cannot
intrinsically be modeled in this way it has reentrant loops it has uncertainty involved in it
and so there is a grave danger that complex situations are resolved into a complicated
structure there was a hilarious piece of analysis carried out for the US army in Afghanistan by a
London consultancy firm and who generated a map of all that was going on in Afghanistan and it's
hilarious it's a huge map like this and it's got little centers everywhere and arrows going in every
possible direction and when this was presented to General McChrystal a man of experience an
amount of action he responded when we understand that we will have won the war which you can understand
stand in one of two possible ways and but what intrigues me actually is that at the moment
I've just been approached in the last couple of months quite independently by military intelligence
pooled between the UK the US and France and another approach from military intelligence
in Australia to help them untangle why their sort of systematic abstract ways of working
things out are not actually helpful and that we need to reincorporate into this something which is
less certain less tied down and if you make a structure too rigid and tighten up all the
bolts it's got no movement it will crash down so it needs to have this human intelligence in it
another way of putting it is that it needs to be antifragile in Talib's terms but we need to
reintroduce the much stigmatized concept of human judgment and intuition I love that story of the
map in Afghanistan it makes me think of Borges and the one-to-one map because sometimes it seems
as if that's the sort of the unintentional foolishness of this attempt to turn the world into a thing
that needs to be known in order to exist and the other example that was coming to mind as you were
speaking about it was Dean Bavington who's an environmental historian in Canada who comes from
Newfoundland and has written about the Newfoundland cod fishery and the story that he tells is
of how the Newfoundland cod fishery collapsed not once but twice and after the first collapse it
became the pioneering sort of case study of fisheries management where they were convinced
that they now had mapped and knew this wild fishery well enough to say when the boats could
go back out again how much fish they could take and through the 80s it was the world's leading
sustainable fishery and then in 92 it collapsed again and what he describes in fisheries science
is this kind of retreat then from attempting to know the wild living complex world to saying this
is beyond our capacity and so what we're going to do instead is move to fish farming where we create
deliberately simplified ecosystems that we can know and manage in this way that we failed to do
with the wild fishery and of course that is also failing because those systems are never really cut
off from the wild world they have inputs and outputs going into it but it seems like there's
a sort of spiral there which I see in various areas when we're talking about ecological crisis
which is this desire this feeling that we need to know the world in a way that would allow us to
intervene successfully in that way and then cycling between a despair at the failure to do that
and a sort of desperate optimism of trying to remake the world into something like a fish farm
and I think you know in what we've been talking about in the invitation that you're making in your
work I feel like there are clues for letting people know that you know the world might be
something other than the way it appears through this lens and therefore that the failure that
failing to make the world into something that can be known and managed in that way is not the end of
the world only at the end of a way of seeing it sure yes no that's that's surely right but I
suppose the difficulty would be how people can actually put that into practice that's always
the difficult bit yeah it's how do we have you thoughts about that well I think it starts with
giving up in a sense yeah yeah you know it starts with stopping it starts to stop into what you're
doing which is not working yeah yes and it was Gustavo Estavo who's a Mexican activist and thinker
who can really taught me this because he described how he'd had these three times in his life where
he had walked away from a situation without being able to explain why and the last time was in the
mid 70s when he turned down a job as a cabinet minister in Mexico and he said I couldn't explain
to anyone why or what I was going to do but in the way that he talked about it because he then
got involved with these grassroots networks and the the pueblos and the and the barrios of Mexico
city and it was the until he left that position where he was standing he couldn't see what was
invisible from there he had to actually go somewhere else without being able to give anyone
a justification of this move for things to come into view because the way that the people he was
then working with were seen from above from within the system he'd been working in missed something
important about their ability to make life go on so that's the first step of giving up not as an end
but as a necessary I say in the book you know giving up is always giving up on something
though it may feel like everything until after you've done it so that's the sort of the first
move is to stop um stop trying to save the world as we have known it but also stop assuming that
if you give up on that then you know how the story ends yes well that wouldn't particularly we don't
do as Anne Whitehead said um profits uh we don't know what to do with them perhaps taking them
outside and stoning them in some sort of merciful kind of way which is best but when everyone's
asked to predict the future um I sort of think of Neil Spore saying prediction is a particularly
difficult matter especially when it concerns the future so I don't think we ever know and
keeping that space open about what is going to happen is very important and the failure to do so
is is all part of this we must have certainty we must follow this path we know what will happen
we usually won't be following that path something we didn't know happens like the famous um economic
collapse of 2008-9 um where we thought we had now mapped how these markets work so successfully
that they would never crash again and they promptly crashed too the difficulty is taking
something that works as I mentioned earlier on a small scale and I'm trying to suggest
that this is going to work on a larger one for example if you do have a complex system which
can't be reduced to um mechanistic uh chains of causation you can nonetheless find a very small
isolated part of it where it appears that that's what's happening and you can hone in on that and
you can see a little chain of causation and you can interfere with it and produce a result and the
temptation is for science there to say so we understand that now but what you've understood is
how that little chain of causation there worked but you haven't understood the nature of the
hole in which it inheres and and so when one's zooming out from some small scale experiment
usually the thing is quite different problem when you are looking at um the hole in which
whatever it was you modeled along so the there's a distinction that I use in the book between
which came to me from John Michael Greer and it's the distinction between a problem and a predicament
okay and he says you know a problem has a solution and the thought experiment he gives
is he says so suppose that you can get in a time machine and go back to some a prosperous rural
village in the south of England in 1700 equipped with the knowledge of the industrial revolution
that is coming and everything that that is going to mean for the people there and suppose that you
can actually convince them of all of these things that are going to completely disrupt
their ways of life and for a small number of people going to make them amazingly rich off
things that no one's dreamed of yet and for many others mean life in factories or going off to
fight foreign wars and then they say to you so what should we do and there's no answer to that
because it's not a it's not a problem that can be solved it's a predicament okay which mean doesn't
mean that there aren't responses doesn't mean that there aren't actions worth taking and some of those
will be wiser than others but you know the world that's born out of that which is the world of
industrial modernity of the last couple of hundred years that we've been talking about has been better
at solving problems than any human culture that the world has ever seen but increasingly over time
more and more of the problems it's faced with are the consequences of earlier solutions exactly
and meanwhile it almost can't see that some things might not be problems that there might
be predicaments and that another way of seeing and acting might be called for in the face of a
predicament what would that way of acting involve well suspending the belief that you
can solve this now should be an important part of it so a good example of a predicament that we
almost still recognize as a predicament would be mortality you know when we meet somebody i remember
meeting someone who was a who had his membership card of the cryogenics institute okay with the
instructions on the back if you know if you find me dead then put ice around my head and call this
number yeah and uh i mean i shook his hand and it felt like the coldness was sort of creeping
back into him even while he was alive but most of us kind of at a gut level see that as a category
error we see the fact that we're going to die one day is more more like a predicament than
a problem to be solved and it doesn't cancel out the meaning of the fact that we're sitting here
alive now it doesn't remove there being lots of things we can do with the life that we have
but if our response to the fact that we're going to die one day is to try and throw ourselves
into treating that as a problem to be solved then that may not lead us to make the wisest use of the
time that we have indeed there's a further step we could take which is not only not to see it as a
problem but perhaps not even to see it as a predicament but to see it as an inalienable part
of life and something that has its strength too i mean if you take i was very impressed by
something that mary midgley said when she was 92 and i think she died when she was 96 and she was
extremely sharp until the moment she died and she she said it's very easy to come to terms with death
because one only has to ask the question what would it be like if you literally could live on
this earth forever and i'm sure there may be some people somewhere who say oh marvellous but most
of us begin to feel a sort of craziness and almost a sense of panic that there is no end to this
and if that is the case that it's better that it has its its finite nature it has its finest
then it's only a question of when and nowadays we always think a bigger portion is better but
sometimes there's something quite good about the standard portion of a human life as i find myself
three school years and nine at the moment i feel quite happy with the idea and i think that i really
think that the lack of our awareness of death and what it brings to the picancy of life is is a great
loss and in the past of course people would have had a scholar such as i might have had a
skull on the table that reminded me from my twenties onwards that i was going to die and
that this had meaning and once you once you accept this and you don't see it as the enemy of life
but part of the nature of life as i think the chinese the far eastern tradition chinese and
japanese are much better at saying that the transiency of things is not a problem to be
solved not even a predicament this is in fact something very beautiful and part of their meaning
it's a sentence without a full stop on the end has a problem yes and i'm reminded of the story of
Beethoven before he went deaf hearing somebody in a neighboring room playing a piece as far as the
last note in the scale and not actually going there having to go out to press the note before he could
go back to bed the line when paul and i wrote the dark mountain manifesto the line that has
stayed with me most deeply is right at the end when we found ourselves saying the end of the
world as we know it is not the end of the world full stop and together we will find the hope beyond
hope the path that lead into the unknown world that lies ahead and a year or two after we wrote that
i found myself sitting with the philosopher david abram talking about this and in that
conversation a new turn on that came out which was the end of the world as we know it is also the
end of a way of knowing the world and so i think that's what i'm kind of that's what i'm inquiring
into and and i feel like you're one of the people who's kind of holding that question at the moment
well it is wonderful to to to have that expressed because the the idea of the way in which we know
something affecting what it is is absolutely central to to my philosophy and which is why i pay
so much attention to attention and the importance of how we attend not just whether or not we attend
which is important but how we attend by which of course i don't mean the means by which but the
way in which and that changes the nature of the world and i believe that actually once one starts
looking at the world with a different kind of attention it can change its nature quite quickly
and quite responsibly that has been my experience so we don't have to people often say so what do
we do in a way that's a sort of secondary left hemisphere question now we've got a vision of
how we want to do things what are the steps we need to take to accomplish it
and the left hemisphere servant should say well i will go and do this and you say that's a very
good idea and so forth but really what we're talking about is inhabiting our lives inhabiting the
world inhabiting the cosmos in a different way which depends on the nature of the attention
which means a relationship because attention is never a camera doesn't pay attention
a microphone doesn't pay attention it receives and we don't just receive we pay attention and that
means that we bring something of our own to whatever it is that we encounter but i also
profoundly believe that that's something else responds to our attention i don't never have
believed since i was you know a young adolescent that it was true that the world was a sort of
heap of non responsive material it always seems to me to be vibrantly communicating with me and
and that there is this exchange all the time so it out of that exchange comes what is real because
i do believe and i argue philosophically for those who can't see why on earth i would say that
in in the matter with things that relationships are primary that what actually exists first of all
is relationship and that the things are secondary to the relationships so when there are relationships
bits start to stand out and we go oh there's something a thing and that's what we identify
but it's a web of relationships when you think about how an embryo develops into the animal
it doesn't add a liver and a heart and a spina whatever it these things come out of the hole
and they only are embedded in that context of the hole and then they stand out and you go what's that
over there we'll call that the liver you know so in an organism there are areas of relationship
which become what we then call things and this is quite coherent with um something that means
intuitively something to me but is part of all the great so-called wisdom traditions of the world
that whatever we mean by god that first grounding whatever that encompasses it all
is that its nature is love i mean that is a common theme of all these traditions
and love is nothing if it's not a relationship that's exactly what it is it doesn't exist
but you know you don't have to things first love exists and out of love come the beings and i believe
that the the purpose of this is getting a long way out perhaps but and i think that the purpose of
the cosmos one might say why why if there is this ground of being whatever you like to call it the
Tao or god or whatever else why did it bother to create and i think the answer is that it itself
only becomes fulfilled through this act of creation because there's another and there is a reciprocity
so that reciprocity between the divine and ourselves is usually important not just for us
but also for the divine which means that we also play a crucial role in it we're not just passive
observers once again like the camera or whatever we are making ourselves and we are forging the
reality of the universe by our responsiveness and that helps to explain why things evolve
in the way that they have done why why was the first as we believe in animacy and how did animacy
come about and why was why has this animacy taken the form that it has of developing creatures like
ourselves who are in many ways so much shorter lived and more vulnerable than ancient creatures
way back down this phylogenetic tree and there are examples of actinobacteria in the depths of the
ocean single celled organisms that are themselves over 100 million years old so a 70 year life seems
like what's that achieved i think the whole drive of it is towards differentiation the unfolding
like the bud that unfolds and it's not the negation of the bud that it turns into a flower it's the
fulfillment of the bud that it turns into the flower and the flower eventually to the fruit so
all these things that's an image of course from Hegel but that idea that things are fulfilled
through their unfolding their individuation without that threatening the integrity of the whole is
very important and this process leads through life to two important things one is our greater
responsiveness and the other is a much rapider rate of response as a whole as a species or
or even as an individual to the world both a more rapid ability to respond and a far more
intense and wide ranging response so a vole may well appreciate the things in the garden that
i appreciate at some level but there are certainly things that i can see and appreciate as a human
that that vole can't which is not to say that the vole doesn't have things that it appreciates that
i don't take and that's granted but what we bring to the party is our greater response which includes
things like writing the mass in b minor and and this is an extraordinary response to the creation
people sometimes talk about it as though well yes but it's so tragic you know we're tragically
cast into this pointless meaningless universe and our response is to do this but this is
this is back to front that that thing came out of the universe by willingness to listen to it by
willingness to write what i write vast willingness to write what he wrote all these things come out
of the cosmos they can't come from anywhere else so they're in a sense things that are unpacked
that are potential in it so there is no chasm between us and this cosmos and it only looks
like it has no meaning and no awareness because science at some stage in the last couple of
hundred years decided that it would make a simple principle that it was not going to consider anything
that suggested either purpose or responsiveness and and and anything that couldn't be measured and
wasn't material and so at the end of its elaborate process it solemnly pronounces i can't find any
purpose or or any any evidence that consciousness can be real i mean there really are people tenured
professors in western universities who hold the belief that consciousness is an illusion but you
know consciousness for there to be an illusion there has to be consciousness and it seems like the
invitation that is contained in this end of the world as we know it with all of the
the the harm and damage that is unfolding that is also the end of a way of knowing the world is
an invitation back in an invitation back into relation absolutely back into participating
in the world as we always were anyway rather than pretending that we're standing above it and knowing
it and managing it absolutely that is so true and really what i'm saying is that
something as simple as practicing changing the way in which you attend to things changes the world
and changes you and obviously changes for the better a relationship if you can pay appropriate
kinds of attention and of course everything involves a different kind of attention there's a kind of
attention that is detached and is entirely appropriate that for example the surgeon who's
carrying out a delicate operation and simply has to treat the body as not that person that will
wake up from the operation in order to be able to do his or her job efficiently so different kinds
of attention are important and they bring us back into connection with something surprisingly quickly
and so when people sort of despair about what is happening those who wish to find
can find quite quickly what it is that they're seeking and it may be a problem or predicament
that many people won't survive that that is always going to be a possibility maybe our
civilization won't survive maybe it will maybe it will in a in a in a wiser form in a less arrogant
and hubristic form on a much more local level and a much more coherent and interconnected way
we don't know but this this business of being taken back into relationship and this
receptive this giving and this taking which is so fundamental this can be achieved
i'm thinking of an italian philosopher Federico Campania whose work i got to know while i was
working on this book and he he has a lovely way of putting it he says sometimes you are
born into the ending of a world this is the thing that has happened before exactly and the way that
you diagnose this is that the future no longer works because what we ordinarily are talking
about when we talk about the future is an extension of a story that we were born into
and if you've been born into the ending of that story then attempts to extend it no longer
convince anyone and i think a lot of what we've been witnessing around the world in the last 10
years or so is the political manifestation of the failure of the future and the appeal of the past
is so powerful in politics today attempts to invoke the future don't work in the way they
did in the mid 20th century because this world is in some sense coming to an end so what Campania
says is so if it is your discernment that you have been born into the ending of the world that you
were born into what's worth doing and he says well you can stop trying to make sense according to
the logic of the world that is coming to an end and start trying to create good ruins things that
may turn out to be helpful to the people beyond the end of this world to those who have to make
life work among all of the things that will be left behind and carried forwards but understood
perhaps in very different ways after this particular story that we happened to be born
somewhere late in has come to an end and i feel like maybe that's what we're trying to do
as thinkers as writers as artists right now in networks like dark mountain is to make good
ruins things that may turn out to be fertile and full of possibility after the failure of the
future that we were promised that's wonderful and i suppose what it suggests is that we don't
by any means give up on the future we just give up on the future as a projection of
the way we've been doing things exactly and and that that's um a hopeful idea it's a very
profoundly productive idea if it can be embraced and again one has to accept
limits and mortality is one of them and the civilization has some mortality as well in fact
they tend to thrive for a few hundred years probably 300 400 years and then they tend to
decay wherever they have been and so we have to accept that there is limitation but the left
hemisphere absolutely rejects any idea of boundaries limitations finiteness and the simplest example
is that it will absolutely deny that there is anything wrong with it although it has the person
has a paralyzed left arm perhaps the whole side of their body they'll just deny that it exists
rather than accept that there could be a problem or a limit it's always going for we can do away
with the limits the boundaries and a lot of what is wrong with us now is we knew no limits there
were no limits to what we thought we could do and the world would still carry on being okay
this turned out to be predictably actually um a very stupid thing to believe and i can't really
imagine why people still carry on with a philosophy which is all about trying to
dispense with what they see as the limits on being whatever we want and doing whatever we want
so how do we help the left hemisphere at that point where it's stuck in that limitlessness
what what are the moves i mean i think that's what you're doing as a writer it's as difficult as
how god could have helped satan in paradise lost lucifer the brightest and best of his angels
became this grungy competitive force and this is really an introspective understanding as there
is in so many mythologies of an overseeing power that understands and a part of it that thinks it
knows but doesn't and that tries to use up the power so it's a very difficult thing to do however
there are a couple of things that work in our favor and and the first is that we can we can see what
is happening i believe that the left hemisphere is predominant and that this is damaging for a whole
range of reasons since it is less understanding and less intelligent and it's a way of going can't
be sustained and and that means that we can actively favor what the right hemisphere is
we can make a point of listening to understanding and directing our efforts towards receiving
what is the right hemisphere can can tell us and give to us and the other is that the left
hemisphere is rather like in the emperor with with no clothes on that it sort of believes that
it's marvelous and finest on and suddenly you see how pathetic it is and and that that itself is
wonderfully liberating insight that we don't have to be tyrannized by this this voice that says
we're clever we understand it all it's all mechanical we know it we can just say but actually
that's hilarious it's just there's something about laughter in the middle of all this i hope so
this takes me back to the the way that i've thought about knowledge and knowing
because the example i always use to talk about this sort of threshold between the arm's length
knowledge and the experience of knowing is i say think about the moment when you get a joke
you don't have any information that you didn't have the moment before but you see something
differently and it will affect you emotionally intellectually bodily and it that's the simplest
version of the kinds of encounter the kinds of being pulled across a threshold out of the trap
that that we need holy i agree and and i think that humor and the great humorists are up there in
they're up there in my pantheon along with the great poets because what they're doing is just
that a poet doesn't as you were tell you things you didn't know but it helps you to see things
that you thought you'd seen but you didn't really appreciate understand or feel and that is profoundly
moving and humor is in another way the achievement of this kind of an insight through what they have
in common from a sorry to refer to the brain here but what they have in common is that both of
these things depend very largely on the right frontal cortex which can understand implicit
meaning multiple meaning and tone and all these things that modify meaning which are present
in poetry and are present in humor and you know one of the things we absolutely have got to do
is to liberate humor again and and say no it's not good enough to say people can't make jokes
about things they can make jokes about anything and if you don't like it you know that's for you
to sort out so it's as if the the left hemisphere like applying all of this back to the the predicament
or problem or whatever it is of the trouble that the world is in not least in terms of climate
change left hemisphere wants to design a way out of that to come up with a plan that will somehow
allow us to you know reboot the future to have some extension of the world as we have known it
and the invitation is somehow to stumble into another way of being human together to stumble
into another chapter of the story rather than to design and plan it out on a spreadsheet and
implement it in the world yes and that stumble of course is the way the left hemisphere would
think of it that it's a stumble but actually what it is is quite probably a wise move that
comes from our unconscious and what you're really pointing to is that having everything
consciously planned out is not the way to achieve everything in life it's the way to achieve the
solution to various incredibly circumscribed problems it's been estimated that 99.5% at least
of everything that we know as it were with our body with our with our brain is not in the focus
of our consciousness but because of that it can be much much richer and there's an argument for
saying that it's something damaging about making things explicit and and focus because you limit
them to one single simple idea that has to be pursued whereas in the implicit understanding
of a situation one can with enormous economy bring together a whole lot of different
elements that come out of the field of one's experience out of being alive and bring them
to bear and you know here again I just I often quote this but I think it's so mildless and
Whitehead said two things he said that a civilisation advances according to the number of
actions and thoughts that can be taken care of outside of the glare of experience and the other
was that applying thought is like a cavalry charge in battle it's something that can only
been done occasionally is very expensive and requires fresh horses so you can't just be doing
this all the time in fact in a way what one would say is that when only brings this cumbersome
mechanism of you know focusing on it in the full glare of the spotlight and trying to solve a
problem when there is a problem but when things are running well you shouldn't be bringing that glare
to bear on it because you will freeze it much as if the pianist starts to remember his fingers
while playing then have to stop playing and if the problem is actually the estate of frozenness
then you can't attack it with the with the back kind of cavalry charge
yes but also what I was thinking is that when you are focusing on it then you are likely to
either stumble or march whereas when you are not focused on it it's not so much that you will
stumble but you will be guided by something that if you trusted not uncritically and not
without a dialogue with yourself often not the conscious one about what are you doing but you
will be guided by something which is different from what your immediate analysis at the conscious
level would suggest was the way to do it the stumble becomes a dance becomes more of a dance
a step in a dance or something of the kind that comes out of one naturally and I think we all
have the experience don't we of knowing when that happens that I always think of it in relation to
music that if on occasion one dances well and joyously it's because one's not trying to dance
at all but the dance is happening in you and through you and the music too that music plays
itself through you not you play the music so one more layer as we maybe draw this conversation to
a close that's coming to mind for me is this thing that I've been describing as a sort of left
hemisphere attempt to to map and respond to the trouble that the world is in I think that a lot
of those who in good faith are kind of describing and telling us what we need to do about the situation
in these terms it seems to me that they have a map in which the thing that the left hemisphere sees
or this this way of seeing and describing the world that is kind of through calculative measurement
and that kind of reason that this addresses the deep level of reality and then the things that
we're talking about that we might associate with the right hemisphere you know poetry and
humor music they'll say well all of that stuff is lovely and it's this thing that becomes possible
once the people who think like us have done the hard work of making sure there is a platform
underneath it yes and it's almost as if I've noticed this even amongst novelists there is an
attempt to resolve Snow's two cultures dilemma from the mid 20th century by staging a marriage
between the two cultures in which the you know the scientific side plays the husband and the arts or
other ways of knowing play the wife and so they're they're held to be kind of beautiful
entertaining decorative they make the world a better place we wouldn't want the world without them
but it's a good job we have the practical you see the the stereotypes that this is based on and it
seems to me that that then as things get difficult the people who are who have staged that kind of
way of seeing things go well now it's time to now it's time for the hard serious stuff which
requires us to go into the the left brain mode and of course what you're suggesting and I would
say is that this is quite the opposite it's the upside down story yes and it reminds me of the
image of somebody who after an evening hard work in the city goes to Covent Garden to amuse themselves
watching the magic flute and they see that real life is the hard stuff of working at Goldman Sachs
but all this stuff is in the evening from Mozart it's just a decoration but of course it's entirely
the other way around that that is the only chance this person is going to have that sort of thing
to bring them into touch with reality and what they're doing in that office under strict lighting
he said this is a fantasy and not necessarily a harmless one so I absolutely agree with that
and it's the story the left hemisphere tells that it is doing the hard work and it's the one
that was sold to me as a medical student you know it was almost as though the right hemisphere we
don't really know what it's there for but perhaps it's there to prop up the left hemisphere so it
doesn't fall over but everything important was done by the left hemisphere but this is not the case
and your example of the magic flute for some reason calls to mind for me the most powerful
experience of this inversion of the stories of reality which was you know when my son was born
and beforehand I was working at the Swedish National Theatre at the time and my boss who
was about five years older than me had a couple of young children he said birth is the most animal
experience you'll ever be part of and he was of course completely right about that but the bit
I was less prepared for was it was also the most mythic experience that the temporality of that
journey through birth and the turns within the journey was absolutely something that was familiar
to me from you know the terrain of fairy tale and mythic story and the kinds of journey that's
being staged in the magic flute that oh somehow the the kind of again the linear accountancy
version of time is not the thing that's there underneath not the thing we encounter when we're
there with the blood of birth or death but actually in those moments we're not just we're
simultaneously drawn into the fact that we have always all along been animals and that to be an
animal is to live in dream time and myth time more than to live in the kinds of time that you know
the guys under the strip lighting in the city office or lots of the ways that we do science or
talk about science imply is they the true real there yes I suppose it's that these existential
encounters of birth and death that we realize that time isn't the I think it's very real but it
isn't it's not like science science is very real and important but isn't necessarily the way it's
now conceived and time is other than the way it is now conventionally conceived and that would take
us a long time I have a chapter in the matter of things solely on time and the ways in which the
hemispheres see it but I really like that and this idea of a process struck me very forcibly
because when my third child was born my mother was dying and my mother was at one part of the M3
and my wife was in the labor suite in Winchester and I had to consult with the
obstetrical team and take time to go up the motorway say goodbye to my mother and come back
to see my daughter born so you can imagine the strange experience of that and the emotions and
the sense of being in a non bureaucratic time so yeah well thank you Ian I hope that conversations
like this provide sort of strange little openings or doorways through which people have a chance
of stumbling into another way of seeing where we find ourselves and we're blinding yes dancing
in there another way thank you very much it's been lovely do go talking