The following is a conversation with Charles Isbell and Michael Litman.
Charles is the Dean of the College of Computing at Georgia Tech
and Michael is a computer science professor at Brown University.
I've spoken with each of them individually on this podcast
and since they are good friends in real life we all thought it would be fun
to have a conversation together. Quick mention of each sponsor
followed by some thoughts related to the episode. Thank you to
Athletic Greens, the only one drink that I start every day with
to cover all my nutritional bases. AteSleep, a mattress that cools itself
and gives me yet another reason to enjoy sleep. Masterclass,
online courses from some of the most amazing humans in history
and Cash App, the app I use to send money to friends.
Please check out the sponsors in the description to get a discount
and to support this podcast. As a side note, let me say that
having two guests on the podcast is an experiment that I've been meaning to do
for a while. In particular because down the road I
would like to occasionally be a kind of moderator for debates
between people that may disagree in some interesting ways.
If you have suggestions for who you would like to see debate on this podcast,
let me know. As with all experiments of this kind,
it is a learning process. Both the video and the audio might need improvement.
I realized I think I should probably do three or more cameras next time as
opposed to just two and also try different ways to mount the microphone
for the third person. Also, after recording this intro, I'm
going to have to go figure out the thumbnail for the video version of the
podcast since I usually put the guest's head on the thumbnail
and now there's two heads and two names
to try to fit into the thumbnail. It's a kind of a bin packing problem
which in theoretical computer science happens to be an NP-hard problem.
Whatever I come up with, if you have better ideas for the thumbnail, let me
know as well. And in general, I always welcome ideas
how this thing can be improved. If you enjoy it, subscribe on YouTube,
review it with Five Stars Napa podcast, follow on Spotify,
support on Patreon, or connect with me on Twitter at Lex Friedman.
And now here's my conversation with Charles Isbell
and Michael Littman. You'll probably disagree about this question
but what is your biggest, would you say, disagreement
about either something profound and very important or something completely not
important at all? I don't think you have any disagreements at all.
I'm not sure that's true. We walked into that one, didn't we?
So one thing that you sometimes mention is that, and we did this one on
air too, as it were, whether or not machine learning is
computational statistics. It's not. But it is.
Well, it's not. And in particular, and more importantly, it is not just computational
statistics. So what's missing in the picture?
All the rest of it. What's missing? That which is missing.
Well, you can't be wrong now. Well, it's not just the statistics.
He doesn't even believe this. We've had this conversation before.
If it were just the statistics, then we would be happy with where we are.
But it's not just the statistics. That's why it's computational
statistics. Or if it were just the computational.
I agree that machine learning is not just statistics.
It is not just statistics. We can agree on that.
Nor is it just computational statistics. It's computational statistics.
It is computational. What is the computational and
computational statistics? Does this take us into the realm of computing?
It does. But I think perhaps the way I can get him to admit that he's wrong is that it's about rules.
It's about rules. It's about symbols. It's about all these other things.
But statistics is not about rules? I'm going to say statistics is about rules.
It's not just the statistics. It's not just a random variable that you choose
and you have a probability. I think you have a narrow view of statistics.
Okay. Well, then what would be the broad view of statistics that would still allow it to be
statistics and not say history that would make computational statistics okay?
Well, okay. So I had my first sort of research mentor, a guy named Tom Landauer,
taught me to do some statistics, right? Sure.
And I was annoyed all the time because the statistics would say that what I was doing
was not statistically significant. And I was like, but and basically what he said to me is,
statistics is how you're going to keep from lying to yourself, which I thought was really deep.
It is a way to keep yourself honest in a particular way. I agree with that.
Yeah. And so you're trying to find rules. I'm just going to bring it back to rules.
Wait, wait, wait. Could you possibly try to define rules?
Even regular statisticians, non-computational statisticians,
do spend some of their time evaluating rules, right? Applying statistics to try to understand,
does this rule capture this? Does this not capture that?
You mean like hypothesis testing kind of thing? Sure.
Or like confidence intervals? I think more like hypothesis. I feel like the word
statistic literally means like a summary, like a number that summarizes other numbers.
But I think the field of statistics actually applies that idea to things like rules,
to understand whether or not a rule is valid. Do software engineering statistics?
No. Programming languages statistics?
No. Because I think it's useful to think about a lot of what AI machine learning is,
or certainly should be, as software engineering, as programming languages.
If to put it in language that you might understand, the hyperparameters beyond the problem.
The hyperparameters has too many syllables for me to understand.
The hyperparameters. That's better.
That goes around it, right? It's the decisions you choose to make.
It's the metrics you choose to use. It's the loss function.
You want to say the practice of machine learning is different than the practice of statistics.
Like the things you have to worry about and how you worry about them are different.
Therefore, they're different.
Right. At the very least, it's that much is true.
It doesn't mean that statistics computational and otherwise aren't important.
I think they are. I mean, I do a lot of that, for example.
But I think it goes beyond that. I think we could think about game theory in terms of statistics,
but I don't think it's very as useful to do. I mean, the way I would think about it,
or a way I would think about it, is this way. Chemistry is just physics.
Hmm.
But I don't think it's as useful to think about chemistry as being just physics.
It's useful to think about it as chemistry. The level of abstraction really matters here.
So I think there are contexts in which it is useful.
Yes.
I think it's that way, right?
No, that is.
So finding that connection is actually helpful.
And I think that's when I emphasize the computational statistics thing.
I think I want to befriend statistics and not absorb them.
Here's the a way to think about it beyond what I just said, right?
So what would you say, and I want you to think back to a conversation I had a very
long time ago, what would you say is the difference between, say, the early 2000s,
ICML and what we used to call NIPS, NURPS. Is there a difference?
A lot of it, particularly on the machine learning that was done there?
ICML was around that long.
Oh, yeah.
So I clear as the new conference, new-ish.
Yeah, I guess so.
And ICML was around the 2000.
Oh, ICML predates that.
I think my most cited ICML papers from 94.
Michael knows this better than me because, of course, he's significantly older than I am.
But the point is, what is the difference between ICML and NURPS in the late 90s, early 2000s?
I don't know what everyone else's perspective would be, but I had a particular perspective
at that time, which is I felt like ICML was more of a computer science place and that NURPS,
NURPS was more of an engineering place, like the kind of math that happened at the two places.
As a computer scientist, I felt more comfortable with the ICML math,
and the NURPS people would say that that's because I'm dumb.
And that's such an engineering thing to say.
So I agree with that part of it, but I do a little different.
We actually had a nice conversation with Tom Dietrich about this on Twitter just a couple
days ago. I put it a little differently, which is that ICML was machine learning done by computer
scientists, and NURPS was machine learning done by computer scientists trying to impress statisticians,
which was weird because it was the same people, at least by the time I started paying attention.
But it just felt very, very different. And I think that that perspective of whether you're
trying to impress the statisticians or you're trying to impress the programmers is actually
very different and has real impact on what you choose to worry about and what kind of
outcomes you come to. So I think it really matters.
I think computer statistics is a means to an end. It is not an end in some sense.
And I think that really matters here in the same way that I don't think computer science
is just engineering or just science or just math or whatever.
Okay. So I'd have to now agree that now we agree on everything.
Yes. Yes. The important thing here is that my opinions may have changed,
but not the fact that I'm right, I think is what we just came to.
Right. And my opinions may have changed and not the fact that I'm wrong.
That's right. I lost me. I think I lost myself there too.
But anyway, we're back.
We're back. This happens sometimes. We're sorry.
How does neural networks change this, just to even linger on this topic,
change this idea of statistics, how big of a pie statistics is within the machine learning thing?
Like, because it sounds like hyperparameters and also just the role of data.
You know, this people are starting to use this terminology of software 2.0,
which is like the act of programming as a,
like you're a designer in the hyperparameter space of neural networks,
and you're also the collector and the organizer and the cleaner of the data.
And that's part of the programming.
So how did, on the NeurIPS versus ICML topic,
what's the role of neural networks in redefining the size and the role of machine learning?
I can't wait to hear what Michael thinks about this, but I would add one.
But you will.
That's true. I will force myself to.
I think there's one other thing I would add to your description,
which is the kind of software engineering part of what does it mean to debug, for example.
But this is a difference between the kind of computational statistics view of machine learning
and the computational view of machine learning, which is, I think,
one is worried about the equation as it were. And by the way, this is not a value judgment.
I just think it's about perspective. But the kind of questions you would ask,
when you start asking yourself what does it mean to program and develop and build the system,
is a very computer sciencey view of the problem. I mean, when, if you get on
Data Science Twitter and Econ Twitter, you actually hear this a lot with the economist
and the data scientist complaining about the machine learning people. Well, it's just statistics.
And I don't know why they don't see this, but they're not even asking the same questions.
They're not thinking about it as a kind of programming problem.
And I think that that really matters, just asking this question.
I actually think it's a little different from programming and hyperparameters space and sort
of collecting the data. But I do think that that immersion really matters. So I'll give you a quick
example of the way I think about this. So I teach machine learning. Michael and I have
co-taught a machine learning class, which has now reached, I don't know, 10,000 people at least
over the last several years, or somewhere there's abouts. And my machine learning assignments
are of this form. So the super, the first one is something like implement these five algorithms,
K and N and SVMs and boosting and decision trees and neural networks. And maybe that's it,
I can't remember. And when I say implement, I mean, steal the code. I am completely uninterested.
You get zero points for getting the thing to work. And then once you're spending your time
worrying about getting the corner case right of what happens when you are trying to normalize
distances and the points on the thing. And so you divide by zero. I'm not interested in that,
right? Steal the code. However, you're going to run those algorithms on two data sets. The data
sets have to be interesting. What does it mean to be interesting? Well, data sets interesting if
it reveals differences between algorithms, which presumably are all the same, because they can
represent whatever they can represent. And two data sets are interesting together if they show
different differences as it were. And you have to analyze them. You have to justify their
interestingness and you have to analyze them a whole bunch of ways. But all I care about is the
data in your analysis, not the programming. And I occasionally end up in these long discussions
with students. Well, I don't really, I copy and paste the things that I've said the other 15,000
times it's come up, which is they go, but the only way to learn, really understand is to code them
up, which is a very programmer software engineering view of the world. If you don't program it,
you don't understand it, which is, by the way, I think is wrong in a very specific way. But
it is a way that you come to understand because then you have to wrestle with the algorithm.
But the thing about machine learning is it's not just sorting numbers, where in some sense,
the data doesn't matter. What matters is, well, does the algorithm work on these abstract things
upon the list of the other? In machine learning, the data matters. It matters more than almost
anything. And not everything, but almost anything. And so as a result, you have to live with the data
and don't get distracted by the algorithm per se. And I think that that focus on the data
and what it can tell you and what question it's actually answering for you, as opposed to the
question you thought you were asking, is a key and important thing about machine learning and is
a way that computationalists, as opposed to statisticians, bring a particular view about
how to think about the process. The statisticians, by contrast, bring, I think I'd be willing to say,
a better view about the kind of formal math that's behind it and what an actual number,
ultimately, is saying about the data. And those are both important, but they're also different.
I didn't really think of it this way, is to build intuition about the role of data,
the different characteristics of data by having two data sets that are different,
and they reveal the differences and the differences. That's a really fascinating,
that's a really interesting educational approach. The students love it, but not right away.
No, they love it at the end. They love it at the end. Not at the beginning.
Not even immediately after. I feel like there's a deep, profound lesson about education there.
That you can't listen to students about whether what you're doing is the right or the wrong thing.
Well, as a wise, Michael Lippmann once said to me about children, which I think applies to
teaching, is you have to give them what they need without bending to their will.
And students are like that. You have to figure out what they need. You're a curator. Your whole
job is to curate and to present, because on their own, they're not going to necessarily know where
to search. So you're providing pushes in some direction and learn space. And you have to give
them what they need in a way that keeps them engaged enough so that they eventually discover
what they want, and they get the tools they need to go and learn other things.
What's your view, let me put on my Russian hat, which believes that life is like-
I like Russian hats, by the way. If you have one, I would like this.
Those are ridiculous. Yes.
But in a delightful way, but sure.
What do you think is the role of- we talked about balance a little bit.
What do you think is the role of hardship and education? I think the biggest things I've learned,
like what made me fall in love with math, for example, is by being bad at it until I got good
at it. So like struggling with a problem, which increased the level of joy I felt
when I finally figured it out. And it always felt with me, with teachers, especially modern
discussions of education, how can we make education more fun, more engaging, more all those things?
Well, from my perspective, it's like you may be missing the point that education, that life is
suffering. Education is supposed to be hard, and that actually what increases the joy you feel when
you actually learn something. Is that ridiculous? Do you like to see your students suffer?
Okay, so this may be a point where we differ. I suspect not. I'm going to do go on.
Well, what would your answer be? I want to hear you first.
Okay, well, I was going to not answer the question.
Because you don't want the students to know you and hear them suffer?
No, no, no, no, no. I was going to say that there's, I think there's a distinction that you can make in
the kind of suffering. So, I think you can be in a mode where you're suffering in a hopeless way,
versus you're suffering in a hopeful way, where you're like, you can see
that you still have, you can still imagine getting to the end. And as long as people are
where in that mindset, where they're struggling,
but it's not a hopeless kind of struggling.
That's productive.
I think that's really helpful.
But it's struggling, like if you break their will,
if you leave them hopeless.
No, sure, some people are gonna,
whatever, lift themselves up by their bootstraps,
but like mostly you give up
and certainly it takes the joy out of it.
And you're not gonna spend a lot of time
on something that brings you no joy.
So it is a bit of a delicate balance, right?
You have to thwart people in a way
that they still believe that there's a way through.
Right, so that's a, we strongly agree actually.
So I think, well, first off,
struggling and suffering aren't the same thing, right?
Yeah, it's being poetic.
Oh no, I actually appreciate the poetry.
And one of the reasons I appreciate it
is that they are often the same thing
and often quite different, right?
So you can struggle without suffering.
You can certainly suffer pretty easily.
You don't necessarily have to struggle to suffer.
So I think that you want people to struggle,
but that hope matters.
You have to, they have to understand
that they're gonna get through it on the other side.
And it's very easy to confuse the two.
I actually think Brown University has a very,
just philosophically has a very different take
on the relationship with their students,
particularly undergrads from say,
a place like Georgia Tech, which is-
Which university's better?
Well, I have my opinions on that.
I mean, remember, Charles said,
it doesn't matter what the facts are, I'm always right.
The correct answer-
Is that it doesn't matter, they're different,
but clearly answers to that.
Well, he went to a school like the school
where he is as an undergrad.
I went to a school, specifically the same school,
though it was changed a bit in the intervening years.
Brown or Georgia Tech?
No, I was talking about Georgia Tech.
And I went to an undergrad place
that's a lot like the place where I work now.
And so it does seem like we're more familiar
with these models.
There's a similarity between Brown and Yale?
Yeah, I think they're quite similar.
And Duke?
Duke has some similarities too,
but it's got a little Southern draw.
You've kind of worked at universities
that are like the places where you learned.
And the same would be true for me.
Are you uncomfortable venturing outside the box?
Is that what you're saying?
Journey out?
Is that what I'm saying?
Yeah, Charles is definitely.
He only goes to places that have Institute in the name.
It has worked out that way.
Well, academic places anyway.
Well, no, I was a visiting scientist at U-Pen
or visiting something at U-Pen.
Oh, wow.
I just understood your joke.
Which one?
Five minutes later.
I like to set the sort of time bomb.
The Institute is in the,
that Charles only goes to places that have Institute
in the name.
So I guess Georgia,
I forget that Georgia Tech is Georgia Institute of Technology.
The number of people who refer to it
as Georgia Tech University is large and incredibly ear-to-ear.
It's one of the few things
that genuinely gets under my skin.
But like schools like Georgia Tech and MIT
have as part of the ethos,
like there is,
I wanna say there's an abbreviation that someone taught me,
like IHTFP, something like that.
Like there's an expression,
which is basically,
I hate being here,
which they say so proudly.
And that is definitely not the ethos at Brown.
Like Brown is,
there's a little more pampering and empowerment and stuff.
And it's not like we're gonna crush you
and you're gonna love it.
So yeah, I think there's a,
I think the ethoses are different.
That's interesting, yeah.
We had Drownproofing.
What's that?
Drownproofing.
In order to graduate from Georgia Tech,
this is a true thing,
feel free to look it up.
If you-
A lot of schools have this, by the way.
No.
Actually Georgia Tech was barely the first.
Brandeis has it.
Had it.
I feel like Georgia Tech was the first in a lot of things.
Georgia Tech was the first in a lot of things.
It was the first in a lot of things.
Had the first Master's degree in-
Stop that.
First Masters in Computer Science, actually.
Online Masters.
Well, that too, but way back in the 60s.
NSF, yeah, yeah.
You're the first information
in Computer Science Masters degree in the country.
But the Georgia Tech, it used to be the case
that in order to graduate from Georgia Tech,
you had to take a Drownproofing class,
where effectively they threw you a water to hide you up.
If you didn't drown, you got to graduate.
Hide you up?
I believe so.
No.
Basically, there were certainly versions of it,
but I mean, luckily they ended it
just before I had to graduate
because otherwise I would have never graduated.
It wasn't gonna happen.
I want to say 84, 83, someone around them, they ended it,
but yeah, it used to have to prove you could tread water
for some ridiculous amount of time.
Are you two minutes?
Congratulations.
No, it was more than two minutes.
I bet it was two minutes.
Okay, well, we'll look at it.
And it was in a bathtub.
It was in a pool, but it was a real thing.
But that idea that, you know, push you-
Fully clothed.
Yeah, fully clothed.
I don't think, I bet it was that and not tied up.
Because like, who needs to learn
how to swim when you're tied?
Nobody, but who needs to learn to swim
when you're actually falling into the water dressed.
That's a real thing.
I think your facts are getting in the way
with a good story.
Oh, that's fair.
That's fair.
I didn't mean to.
All right, so they tie you up.
Sometimes the narrative matters.
But whatever it was, you had to,
it was called drown proofing for a reason.
The point of the story, Michael, is-
Struggle.
It's, well, no, but that's good.
It doesn't bring it back to struggle.
That's a part of what Georgia Tech has always been.
And we struggle with that, by the way,
about what we want to be, particularly as things go.
But you sort of, how much can you be pushed
without breaking?
And you come out of the other end stronger, right?
There's this saying we used to have
when I was an undergrad there, which was Georgia Tech,
building tomorrow the night before.
Right?
And it was just kind of, kind of idea
that give me something impossible to do
and I'll do it in a couple of days
because that's what I just spent the last four or five
or six.
That ethos definitely stuck to you.
Having now done a number of projects with you,
you definitely will do it the night before.
That's not entirely true.
There's nothing wrong with waiting until the last minute.
The secret is knowing when the last minute is.
Right, that's brilliantly put.
Yeah, that is a definite Charles statement
that I am trying not to embrace.
Well, I appreciate that
because you helped move my last minute back.
That's the social construct where you converge
together what the definition of last minute is.
And we figure that all together.
In fact, MIT, I'm sure a lot of universities have this,
but MIT has like MIT time
that everyone has always agreed together
that there is such a concept
and everyone just keeps showing up like 10 to 15 to 20
depending on the department late to everything.
So there's like a weird drift that happens.
It's kind of fascinating.
Yeah, we're five minutes.
We're five minutes.
In fact, the classes will say,
well, this is no longer true actually,
but it used to be a class that started eight
but actually started eight or five.
It ends at nine, actually it ends at eight, 55.
Everything's five minutes off
and nobody expects anything to start until five minutes
after the half hour, whatever it is.
It still exists.
That hurts my head.
Well, let's rewind the clock back to the 50s and 60s
when you guys met.
How did you, I'm just kidding, I don't know.
But what, can you tell the story of how you met?
So you've, like the internet and the world kind of
knows you as connected in some ways
in terms of education of teaching the world.
That's like the public facing thing,
but how did you as human beings
and as collaborators meet?
I think there's two stories.
One is how we met
and the other is how we got to know each other.
I'm not gonna say fall, I'm not gonna say fell in love.
I'm gonna say that we came to understand that we...
Had some common something.
Yeah, it's funny, because on the surface
I think we're different in a lot of ways,
but there's something that's just consonant.
There you go.
Afternoon.
So I will tell the story of how we met
and I'll let Michael tell the story of how we met.
Okay, all right.
Okay, so here's how we met.
I was already at that point it was AT&T Labs.
There's a long interesting story there,
but anyway, I was there and Michael was coming to interview.
He was a professor at Duke at the time,
but decided for reasons that he wanted to be in New Jersey.
And so that would mean Bell Labs slash AT&T Labs.
And we were doing interviews,
interviews are very much like academic interviews.
And so I had to be there.
We all had to meet with him afterwards and so on, one-on-one.
But it was obvious to me that he was gonna be hired.
Like no matter what, because everyone loved him.
They were just talking about all the great stuff he did.
Oh, he did this great thing.
And you had just won something at AAAI, I think,
or maybe you got 18 papers in AAAI that year.
I got the best paper award at AAAI for the crossword stuff.
Right, exactly.
So that had all happened and everyone was going on
and on and on about it.
Actually, Satinder was saying incredibly nice things
about you.
Really?
Yes, so.
He can be very grumpy.
Yes.
That's nice to hear.
He was grumpily saying very nice things.
Oh, that makes sense.
Yeah, it does make sense.
So, you know, so it was gonna come.
So why were we, why was I meeting him?
I had something else I had to do.
I can't remember what it was.
Yeah.
Probably involved comic books.
So he remembers meeting me as inconveniencing his afternoon.
So he came, so eventually came to my office.
I was in the middle of trying to do something.
I can't remember what.
And he came and he sat down.
And for reasons that are purely accidental,
despite what Michael thinks,
my desk at the time was set up in such a way
that had sort of an L shape.
And the chair on the outside was always lower
than the chair that I was in.
And, you know, the kind of point was to...
The only reason I think that it was on purpose
is because you told me it was on purpose.
I don't remember that.
Anyway, the thing is that, you know, it kind of gives...
His guest chair was really low
so that he could look down at everybody.
The idea was just to simply create a nice environment
that you were asking for a mortgage.
And I was gonna say, no, that was the point.
It was a very simple idea here.
Anyway, so we sat there and we just talked for a little while.
And I think he got the impression that I didn't like him.
It wasn't true.
He strongly got that impression.
The talk was really good.
The talk, by the way, was terrible.
Right after the talk, I said to my host,
Michael Kearns, who ultimately was my boss.
I'm a friend and a huge fan of Michael, yeah.
Yeah, he is a remarkable person.
After my talk, I went into the...
He would take a little basketball.
I went...
Racquetball, he's good at everything.
No, basketball.
No, but basketball, racquetball too.
Squash.
Squash, squash, squash.
Not racquetball, that's right.
Yeah, squash, which is not...
Racquetball, yes.
Squash, no.
And I hope you hear that, Michael.
Oh, Michael Kearns.
As a game, not his skill level.
Because I'm pretty sure he's...
All right, there's some competitiveness there.
But the point is that it was like the middle of the day.
I had full day of interviews.
Like, I've met with people,
but then in the middle of the day, I gave a job talk.
And then there was gonna be more interviews.
But I pulled Michael aside and I said,
I think it's in both of our best interests
if I just leave now.
Because that was so bad that it'd just be embarrassing
if I have to talk to any more people.
Like, you look bad for having invited me.
Like, it's just, let's just forget this ever happened.
So I don't think the talk went well.
That's one of the most Michael Lippman set of sentences
I think I've ever heard.
He did great.
Or at least everyone knew he was great.
So maybe it didn't matter.
I was there, I remember the talk.
And I remember him being very much
the way I remember him now in any given week.
So it was good.
And we met and we talked about stuff.
He thinks I didn't like him, but...
Because he was so grumpy.
Must've been the chair thing.
The chair thing and the low voice, I think.
Like, he obviously was happy with me.
And that slight skeptical look.
Yes.
I have no idea what you're talking about.
Well, I probably didn't have any idea
what you were talking about.
Anyway, I liked him.
He asked me questions.
I answered questions.
I felt bad about myself.
It was a normal day.
What's a normal day?
And then he left.
And that's how we met.
Can we take a...
And then I got hired and I was in the group.
Can we take a slight tangent on this topic of,
it sounds like, maybe you could speak
through the bigger picture.
It sounds like you're quite self-critical.
Who, Charles?
No, you.
Oh.
I think I can do better.
I can do better.
Try me again.
I'll do better.
I'll be self-critical, I won't, I won't, I won't.
Yeah, that was like a three out of 10 response.
Let's try to work it up to five and six.
I remember Marvin Minsky said, on a video interview,
something that the key to success in academic research
is to hate everything you do.
For some reason...
I think I followed that
because I hate everything he's done.
That's a good line.
That's a six.
Maybe that's a keeper.
But do you find that resonance with you at all
in how you think about talks and so on?
I would say it differently.
It's not that...
No, not really.
That's such an MIT view of the world, though.
So I remember talking about this one as a student.
You were basically told I will clean it up
for the purpose of the podcast.
My work is crap, my work is crap,
my work is crap, my work is crap.
Then you go to a conference or something
and you're like, everybody else's work is crap.
Everybody else's work is crap.
And you feel better and better about it,
relatively speaking.
And then you sort of keep working on it.
I don't hate my work.
That resonates with me.
Yes, I've never hated my work,
but I have been dissatisfied with it.
And I think being dissatisfied,
being okay with the fact
that you've taken a positive step,
the derivative's positive.
Maybe even the second derivative's positive.
That's important because that's a part of the hope, right?
But you have to, but I haven't gotten there yet.
If that's not there, that I haven't gotten there yet,
then it's hard to move forward, I think.
So I buy that, which is a little different
from hating everything that you do.
Yeah, I mean, there's things that I've done
that I like better than I like myself.
So it's separating me from the work, essentially.
So I think I am very critical of myself,
but sometimes the work I'm really excited about.
And sometimes I think it's kind of good.
Does that happen right away?
So I found the work that I've liked, that I've done,
most of it, I liked it in retrospect
more when I was far away from it in time.
I have to be fairly excited about it to get done.
No, excited at the time,
but then happy with the result.
But years later, or even I might go back,
you know what, that actually turned out to matter.
That turned out to matter.
Oh gosh, it turns out I've been thinking about that.
It's actually influenced all the work
that I've done since without realizing it.
But that guy was smart.
Yeah, that guy had a future.
Yeah, yeah.
He's going places.
I think there's, so yeah, so I think there's something to it.
I think there's something to the idea of you gotta,
you know, hate what you do, but it's not quite hate.
It's just being unsatisfied.
And different people motivate themselves differently.
I don't happen to motivate myself with self-loathing.
I happen to motivate myself with something else.
So you're able to sit back and be proud
of in retrospect of the work you've done.
Well, and it's easier when you can connect it
with other people, because then you can be proud of them.
I'm proud of the people, yeah.
And then the question is.
No, you can still safely hate yourself.
Yeah, that's right.
It's win-win, Michael, or at least win-lose,
which is what you're looking for.
Oh wow, there's so many brothers and brothers in this.
There's levels.
So how did you actually meet, meet?
Yeah, Michael.
So the way I think about it is,
because we didn't do much research together at H&T,
but then we all got laid off.
So that was-
By the way, sorry to interrupt,
but that was like one of the most magical places,
historically speaking.
They did not appreciate what they had.
And how do we-
I feel like there's a profile lesson in there too.
How do we get it?
Like, why was it so magical?
Is it just a coincidence of history,
or is there something special about-
There were some really good managers
and people who really believed in machine learning
as this is gonna be important.
Let's get the people who are thinking about this
in creative and insightful ways
and put them in one place and stir.
Yeah, but even beyond that, right?
It was Bell Labs at its heyday.
And even when we were there,
which I think was past its heyday.
And to be clear, he's gotten to be at Bell Labs.
I never got to be at Bell Labs.
I joined after that.
Yeah, I should have been 91 as a grad student.
So I was there for a long time, every summer,
except for two.
So twice I worked for companies
that had just stopped being Bell Labs.
Bell Corps and then AT&T Labs.
So Bell Labs was several locations
or for the researchers, or is it one?
Like, is that- Definitely sevens.
Like, Jersey's involved somehow.
They're all in Jersey.
Yeah, they're all over the place.
But they were in a couple places in Jersey.
Murray Hill was the Bell Labs place.
So you had an office at Murray Hill
at one point in your career?
Yeah, I played Ultimate Frisbee
on the cricket pitch at Bell Labs at Murray Hill.
And then it became AT&T Labs when it split off
with Luce during what we called Trivestiture,
the better than Michael Korn's at Ultimate Frisbee.
Yeah. Oh, yeah.
Okay.
But I think that one's not boasting.
I think that, I think Charles plays a lot of Ultimate.
And I don't think Mike-
No, I was, yes, but that wasn't the point.
The point is yes.
I'm sorry. Oh, yes, yes, sorry, sorry.
Okay, I have played on a championship-winning
Ultimate Frisbee team, or whatever,
Ultimate team with Charles.
So I know how good he is.
He's really good.
How good I was anyway when I was younger.
But the thing is-
I know how young he was when he was younger.
That's true.
So much younger than now.
He's older now.
Michael was a much,
was a much better basketball player than I was.
Michael Korn's.
Yes, no, not Michael Korn.
Let's be very clear about that.
To be clear, I've not played basketball with you.
So you don't know how terrible I am,
but you have a probably pretty good guess.
That you're not as good as Michael Korn.
He's tall and athletic.
And he cared about it.
He's very athletic, very good.
And probably competitive.
I love hanging out with Michael.
Anyway, but we were talking about something else,
although I no longer remember what it was.
What were we talking about?
Honey, that's all Bell Labs.
But also Labs.
So this was kind of cool about what was magical about it.
The first thing you have to know
is that Bell Labs was an arm of the government, right?
Because AT&T was an arm of the government.
It was a monopoly.
And you know, every month you paid a little thing
on your phone bill, which turned out was a tax
for like all the research that Bell Labs was doing.
And you know, they invented transistors and the laser
and whatever else is that they did.
The big bang or whatever the cosmic background radiation.
Yeah, they did all that stuff.
They had some amazing stuff with directional microphones.
By the way, I got to go in this room
where they had all these panels and everything
and we would talk.
And one another and he'd lose some panels around
and then he'd have me step two steps to the left
and I couldn't hear a thing he was saying
because nothing was bouncing off the walls.
And then he would shut it all down
and you could hear your heartbeat.
Which is deeply disturbing to hear your heartbeat.
You can feel it.
I mean, you can feel it now.
So there's so much all this sort of noise around.
Anyway, Bell Labs is about pure research.
It was a university in some sense,
the purest sense of a university, but without students.
So it was all the faculty working with one another
and students would come in to learn.
They would come in for three or four months
during the summer and they would go away.
But it was just this kind of wonderful experience
I could walk out my door.
In fact, I would often have to walk out my door
and deal with Rich Sutton and Michael Kearns yelling
at each other about whatever it is they were yelling
about the proper way to prove something or another.
And I could just do that and Dave McAllister
and Peter Stone and all of these other people
including Satinder and then eventually Michael.
And it was just a place where you could think thoughts
and it was okay because so long as once every 25 years
or so somebody invented a transistor,
it paid for everything else.
You could afford to take the risk.
And then when that all went away,
it became harder and harder and harder to justify it
as far as the folks who were very far away were concerned.
And there was such a fast turnaround
among middle management on the AT&T side
that you never had a chance to really build a relationship.
At least people like us didn't have a chance
to build a relationship.
So when the diaspora happened, it was amazing, right?
Everybody left and I think everybody ended up
at a great place and made a huge,
made a continue to do really good work with machine learning.
But it was a wonderful place and people will ask me,
what's the best job you've ever had?
And as a professor, anyway, the answer that I would give is,
well, probably Bell Labs in some very real sense
and I would never have a job like that again
because Bell Labs doesn't exist anymore.
And Microsoft research is great and Google does good stuff
and you can pick IBM, you can tell everyone to,
but Bell Labs was magical.
It was around for, it was an important time
and it represents a high watermark in basic research
in the US.
Is there something you could say
about the physical proximity and the chance collisions?
Like we live in this time of the pandemic
where everyone is maybe trying to see the silver lining
and accepting the remote nature of things.
Is there one of the things that people like faculty
that I talk to miss is the procrastination.
Like the chance to make everything is about meetings
that are supposed to be,
there's not a chance to just talk about comic book
or whatever, like go into discussion that's totally pointless.
So it's funny you say this
because that's how we met, met is exactly that.
So I'll let Michael say that,
but I'll just add one thing,
which is just that research is a social process
and it helps to have random social interactions
even if they don't feel social at the time.
That's how you get things done.
Have one of the great things about the ad lab
when I was there,
I don't quite know what it looks like now
once they move buildings,
but we had entire walls that were whiteboards
and people would just get up there
and they were just right
and people would walk up and you'd have arguments
and you'd explain things to one another
and you got so much out of the freedom to do that.
You had to be okay with people challenging
every freaking word you said,
which I would sometimes find deeply irritating,
but most of the time it was quite useful,
but the sort of pointlessness and the interaction
was in some sense the point, at least for me.
Yeah, I mean, I think offline yesterday
I mentioned Josh Titanbaum and he's very much,
he's such an inspiration in the child-like way
that he pulls you in on any topic.
He doesn't even have to be about machine learning
or the brain.
He'll just pull you into a closest writable surface,
which is still, you can find whiteboards
at MIT everywhere.
And just like basically cancel all meetings
and talk for a couple hours about some aimless thing
and it feels like the whole world,
the time, space continuum kind of warps
and that becomes the most important thing.
And then it's just, it's definitely something worth
missing in this world where everything's remote.
There's some magic to the physical presence.
Whenever I wonder myself whether MIT really is as great
as I remember it, I just go talk to Josh.
Yeah, you know, that's funny is there's a few people
in this world that carry the best
of what particular institutions stand for, right?
And it's-
It's Josh.
I mean, I don't, my guess is he's unaware of this.
That's the point.
The masters are not aware of their mastery.
So-
How did you meet?
Yes, but first the tangent, no.
How did you meet me?
So I'm not sure what you were thinking,
but when it started to dawn on me that maybe
we had a longer term bond was after we all got laid off
and you had decided at that point that we were still paid.
We were given an opportunity to like do job search
and kind of make a transition,
but it was clear that we were done.
And I would go to my office to work
and you would go to my office to keep me from working.
That was my recollection of it.
You had decided that there was really no point
in working for the company
because our relationship with the company was done.
Yeah, but remember I felt that way beforehand.
It wasn't about the company,
it was about the set of people there doing really cool things
and it always always been that way.
But we were working on something together.
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's right.
So at the very end, we all got laid off,
but then our boss came to, our boss's boss came to us
because our boss was Michael Kearns
and he had jumped ship brilliantly, like perfect timing,
like things like right before the ship was about to sink.
He was like, gotta go.
And landed perfectly because Michael Kearns.
Because Michael Kearns.
And leaving the rest of us to go like, this is fine.
And then it was clear that it wasn't fine
and we were all toast.
So we had this sort of long period of time.
But then our boss figured out, okay, wait,
maybe we can save a couple of these people
if we can have them do something really useful.
And the useful thing was we were gonna make
basically an automated assistant
that could help you with your calendar.
You could like tell it things
and it would respond appropriately.
It would just kind of integrate across
all sorts of your personal information.
And so me and Charles and Peter Stone
were set up as the crack team to actually solve this problem.
Other people maybe were too theoretical that they thought
and but we could actually get something done.
So we sat down to get something done
and there wasn't time and it wouldn't have saved us anyway.
And so it all kind of went downhill.
But the interesting, I think, coda to that
is that our boss's boss is a guy named Ron Brockman.
And when he left AT&T, because we were all laid off,
he went to DARPA, started up a program there
that became KLO, which is the program
from which Siri sprung, which is a digital assistant
that helps you with your calendar
and a bunch of other things.
It really, in some ways got its start
with me and Charles and Peter trying to implement
this vision that Ron Brockman had
that he ultimately got implemented
through his role at DARPA.
So when I'm trying to feel less bad
about having been laid off from what is possibly
the greatest job of all time, I think about,
well, we kind of help birth Siri.
That's something.
And he did other things too.
But we got to spend a lot of time in his office
and talk about-
We got to spend a lot of time in my office, yeah.
And so then we went on our merry way.
Everyone went to different places.
Charles landed at Georgia Tech,
which was what he always dreamed he would do.
And so that worked out well.
I came up with a saying at the time,
which is luck favors the Charles.
It's kind of like luck favors the prepared.
But Charles, he wished something
and then it would basically happen just the way he wanted.
It was inspirational to see things go that way.
Things worked out.
And we stayed in touch
and then I think it really helped
when you were working on,
I mean, you'd kept me in the loop for things like threads
and the work that you were doing at Georgia Tech.
But then when they were starting
their online master's program,
he knew that I was really excited
about MOOCs and online teaching.
And he's like, I have a plan.
And I'm like, tell me your plan.
He's like, I can't tell you the plan yet.
Cause they were deep in negotiations
between Georgia Tech and Udacity to make this happen.
And they didn't want it to leak.
So Charles would kept teasing me about it,
but wouldn't tell me what was actually going on.
And eventually it was announced and he said,
I would like you to teach the machine learning course
with me.
I'm like, that can't possibly work.
But it was a great idea and it was, it was super fun.
It was a lot of work to put together,
but it was, it was really great and...
Was that the first time you thought about,
first of all, was it the first time
you got seriously into teaching?
I mean, you know, I'm trying to get the professor right.
This was already after you jumped to,
so like there's a little bit of jumping around in time.
Yeah, sorry about that.
There's a pretty big jump in time.
So like the MOOCs thing is...
So Charles got to Georgia Tech and he,
I mean, maybe Charles, maybe this is a Charles story.
I got to Georgia Tech in 2002.
He got to Georgia Tech in 2002.
And worked on things like revamping the curriculum,
the undergraduate curriculum,
so that it had some kind of semblance of modular structure
because computer science was at the time moving
from a fairly narrow specific set of topics
to touching a lot of other parts of intellectual life
and the curriculum was supposed to reflect that.
And so Charles played a big role in kind of redesigning that.
And then the...
And for my, my labors, I ended up as associate dean.
Right, he got to become associate dean
of a charge of educational stuff.
Well, that would be a valuable lesson
if you're good at something,
they will give you responsibility to do more of that thing.
Well, don't show competence.
Don't show competence if you...
Well, you know what they say, here's what they say.
The reward for good work is more work.
The reward for bad work is less work,
which I don't know, depending on what you're trying
to do that week, one of those is better than the other.
Well, one of the problems with the word work
sorry to interrupt is that it seems to be an antonym
in this particular language
we have the opposite of happiness.
But it seems like they're,
that's one of, you know, we talked about balance.
It's always like work-life balance.
So it was rubbing me the wrong way as a terminology.
I know it's just words.
Right, the opposite of work is play,
but ideally work is play.
Oh, I can't tell you how much time I'd spend.
Certainly not as a Bell Labs,
except for a few very key moments.
As a professor, I would do this too.
I was just saying, I cannot believe they're
paying me to do this.
Because it's fun.
It's something that I would do for a hobby
if I could anyway.
So that sort of worked out.
Are you sure you want to be saying that
when this is being recorded?
As a dean, that is not true at all.
I need a raise.
But I think here with this, even though a lot of time passed
Michael and I talked almost every, well, we texted
almost every day during the period.
Charles at one point took me, there was the ICML conference
the machine learning conference was in Atlanta.
I was the chair, the general chair of the conference.
Charles was my publicity chair or something like that
or fundraising chair.
Fundraising chair.
Yeah.
But he decided it'd be really funny
if he didn't actually show up for the conference
in his own home city.
So he didn't.
But he did at one point pick me up at the conference
in his Tesla and drove me to the Atlanta mall
and forced me to buy an iPhone
because he didn't like how it was to text with me
and thought it would be better for him if I had an iPhone,
the text would be somehow smoother.
And it was.
And it is, and his life is better.
And my life is better.
And so, yeah.
But it was, yeah, Charles forced me to get an iPhone
so that he could text me more efficiently.
I thought that was an interesting moment.
It works for me.
Anyway, so we kept talking the whole time
and then eventually we did the teaching thing.
And it was great.
And there's a couple of reasons for that, by the way.
One is I really wanted to do something different.
Like you've got this medium here.
People claim it can change things.
What's a thing that you could do in this medium
that you could not do otherwise besides edit?
Right, I mean, what could you do?
And being able to do something
with another person was that kind of thing.
It's very hard.
I mean, you can take turns, but teaching together,
having conversations is very hard, right?
So that was a cool thing.
The second thing, if you'd be excused
to do more stuff with him.
Yeah, I always thought, he makes it sound brilliant.
And it is, I guess.
But at the time, it really felt like
I've got a lot to do, Charles is saying.
And it would be great if Michael could teach the course
and I could just.
Hang out.
Yeah, just kind of coast on that.
Well, that's what the second class was more like that.
Because the second class was explicit.
The first class, it was at least half.
Yeah, but I knew all the stuff.
So the structure that we came up with.
I think you were once again letting the facts
get in the way.
It's a good story.
A good story.
I should just let Charles talk to us.
But that's the facts that he saw,
but so that was kind of true for 72.
Yeah, that was sort of true for 7642,
which is the reinforcement learning class
because that was really his class.
You started with reinforcement learning?
No, we started with, I did the intro machine learning,
7641, which is supervised learning
and reinforcement learning and decision making
and cram all that in there.
Kind of assignments that we talked about earlier.
And then eventually about a year later,
we did a follow on 7642,
which is reinforcement learning and decision making.
The first class was based on something
I'd been teaching at that point for well over a decade.
And the second class was based on something
Michael had been teaching.
Actually, I learned quite a bit
teaching that class with him.
But he drove most of that.
But the first one I drove most of it was all my material.
Although I had stolen that material
originally from slides I found online
from Michael, who had originally stolen that material
from I guess slides he found online,
probably from Andrew Moore,
because the jokes were the same anyway.
At least some of the, at least when I found the slide,
some of the stuff was there.
Yes, every machine learning class
taught an early 2000s stole from Andrew Moore.
A particular joke or two.
At least the structure.
Now I did, and he did actually a lot more
with reinforcement learning and such
and game theory and those kinds of things.
But you know, we all sort of-
You mean in the research world?
No, no, no, in that class.
No, I mean in teaching that class.
The coverage was different than what other people started.
Most people were just doing supervised learning
and maybe a little bit of clustering and whatnot.
But we took it all the way to-
A lot of it just comes from Tom Mitchell's book.
Oh no, yeah, except, well, half of it
comes from Tom Mitchell's book, right?
But the other half doesn't.
This is why it's all readings, right?
Because certain things weren't invented when Tom Mitchell's-
Yeah, okay, that's true.
Right?
But it was quite good.
But there's a reason for that besides, you know,
just I wanted to do it.
I wanted to do something new
and I wanted to do something with him,
which is a realization,
which is despite what you might believe,
he's an introvert and I'm an introvert
or I'm on the edge of being an introvert anyway.
But both of us, I think, enjoy the energy of the crowd,
right?
There's something about talking to people
and bringing them into whatever we find interesting
that is empowering, energizing or whatever.
And I found the idea of staring alone at a computer screen
and then talking off of materials
less inspiring than I wanted it to be.
And I had in fact done a MOOC for Udacity on algorithms
and it was a week in a dark room,
talking at the screen, writing on the little pad.
And I didn't know this was happening,
but they had watched the crew had watched some of the videos
while, you know, like in the middle of this
and they're like, something's wrong.
You're sort of shutting down.
And I think a lot of it was I'll make jokes
and no one would laugh.
And I felt like the crowd hated me.
Now, of course, there was no crowd.
So like it wasn't rational, but it's little.
Each time I tried it and I got no reaction,
it just was taking the energy out of my performance,
out of my presentation.
Such a fantastic metaphor for grad school.
Anyway, by working together,
we could play off each other and have it.
Keep the energy up because you can't let your guard down
for a moment with Charles, he'll just overpower you.
I have no idea what you're talking about.
But we would work really well together.
I thought and we knew each other.
So I knew that we could sort of make it work.
Plus I was the associate dean.
So they had to do what I told them to do.
We had to do that.
We had to make it work.
And so it worked out very well.
I thought well enough that we
with great power comes great power.
That's right.
And we became smooth and curly.
And that's when we did the overfitting thriller video.
Yeah.
That's it.
Can we just like smooth and curly?
What were that?
So it happened.
It was completely spontaneous.
These are nicknames you go by.
Yeah.
So it's what the students call us.
He was lecturing.
So the way that we structured the lectures
is one of us is the lecturer
and one of us is basically the student.
And so he was lecturing on.
The lecturer prepares all the materials,
comes up with the quizzes,
and then the student comes in not knowing anything.
So it was just like being on campus.
And I was doing game theory in particular,
the prisoner's dilemma.
Prisoner's dilemma.
We needed to set up a little prisoner's dilemma grid.
So he drew it and I could see what he was drawing.
And the prisoner's dilemma consists of two players,
two parties.
So he decided he would make little cartoons
of the two of us.
And so there was two criminals, right?
That were deciding whether or not to rat each other out.
One of them, he drew as a circle with a smiley face
and a kind of goatee thing, smooth head.
And the other one with all sorts of curly hair.
And he said, this is smooth and curly.
I said smooth and curly.
He said, no, no, smooth with a V.
It's very important that it have a V.
And then the students really took to that.
Like they found that relatable.
He started singing in smooth criminal by Michael Jackson.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And those names stuck.
So we now have a video series that an episode,
our kind of first actual episode should be coming out today,
smooth and curly on video,
where the two of us discuss episodes of Westworld.
We watch Westworld and we're like,
huh, what does this say about computer science and AI?
And we've never, we did not watch it.
I mean, I know it's on season three or whatever we have.
As of this recording, it's on season three.
And watch now two episodes total.
Yeah, I think I watched three.
What do you think about Westworld?
Two episodes in.
So I can tell you so far,
I'm just guessing what's gonna happen next.
It seems like bad things are gonna happen
with the robots uprising.
It's a lot of.
So I have not, I mean, you know,
I vaguely remember a movie existing.
So I assume it's related to that, but.
That was more my time than your time, Charles.
That's right, cause you're much older than I am.
I think the important thing here is that it's narrative,
right?
It's all about telling a story.
That's the whole driving thing.
But the idea that they would give these reveries,
that they would make people,
they would make them remember the awful things that happened.
How horrible things that happened.
Who could possibly think that was a good, I gotta,
I mean, I don't know.
I've only seen the first two episodes
or maybe the third one.
I think I've only seen the first one.
You know what it was?
Do you know what the problem is?
What?
That the robots were actually designed by Hannibal Lecter.
That's true.
They weren't.
So like, what do you think's gonna happen?
Bad thing.
It's clear that things are happening
and characters being introduced
and we don't yet know anything.
But still, I was just struck by how it's all driven
by narrative and story.
And there's all these implied things like programming hap,
the programming interface is talking to them
about what's going on in their heads,
which is both, I mean, artistically,
it's probably useful to film it that way.
But think about how it would work in real life.
That just seems very great.
But there was, we saw on the second episode,
there's a screen you could see things.
They were wearing like clothes.
It was quite interesting to just kind of ask this question
so far.
I mean, I assume it veers off into Never Never Land
at some point.
So we don't know, we can't answer that question.
I'm also a fan of a guy named Alex Garland.
He's a director of Ex Machina.
And he is the first,
I wonder if Kubrick was like this actually,
is he like studies what would it take
to program in AI systems?
Like he's curious enough to go into that direction.
On the Westworld side,
I felt there was more emphasis on the narratives
than like actually asking like computer science questions.
Like, how would you build this?
How would you, and how would you debug it?
I still, to me, that's the key issue.
They were terrible debuggers.
Yeah.
Well, they said specifically, so we make a change
and we put it out in the world and that's bad
because something terrible could happen.
Like, if you're putting things out of the world
and you're not sure whether something terrible
is going to happen, your process is probably.
I just feel like there should have been someone
who's sole job it was was to walk around
and poke his head at it and say,
what could possibly go wrong?
Just over and over again.
I would have loved if there was an,
and I did watch a lot more and I'm not giving anything away.
I would have loved it if there was like an episode
where like the new intern is like debugging
a new model or something and like it just keeps failing
and they're like, all right.
And then more turns into like a episode of Silicon Valley
or something like that versus like this ominous AI systems
that are constantly like threatening the fabric
of this world that's been created.
Yeah.
And you know, this reminds me of something that,
so I agree with that.
That should be very cool.
At least well, for the small percentage of people
who care about debugging systems.
But the other thing is.
Debugging the series.
It falls into the thing of the sequels, fear of the debugger.
Oh my gosh.
And anyway, so.
It's a nightmare show.
It's a horror movie.
I think that's where we lose people, by the way,
early on as the people who either decide
either figure out debugging or think debugging is terrible.
This is where we lose people in computer science.
This is part of the struggle versus suffering, right?
You get through it and you kind of get the skills of it
or you just like, this is dumb.
This is a dumb way to do anything.
I think that's when we lose people.
But, well, I'll leave it at that.
But I think that there's something really,
really neat about framing it that way.
But what I don't like about all of these things.
And I love Tex Mockingham, by the way.
Although the ending was very depressing.
One of the things I have to talk to Alex about,
he says that the thing that nobody noticed he put in
is at the end, spoiler alert,
the robot turns and looks at the camera and smiles,
very briefly.
And to him, he thought that his definition of passing
the general version of the Torrentiaster,
the consciousness test, is smiling for no one.
It's like the Chinese room kind of experiment.
It's not always trying to act for others,
but just on your own, being able to have a relationship
with the actual experience and just like take it in.
I don't know.
He said like nobody noticed the magic of it.
I have this vague feeling that I remember the smile,
but now you've just put the memory in my head.
So probably not, but I do think that that's interesting.
Although by looking at the camera,
you are smiling for the audience, right?
You're breaking the fourth wall.
It seems, I mean, well, that's a limitation in the medium,
but I like that idea.
But here's the problem I have with all of those movies,
all of them, is that, but I know why it's this way.
And I enjoy those movies.
And Westworld is, it sets up the problem of AI as succeeding
and then having something we cannot control.
But it's not the bad part of AI.
The bad part of AI is the stuff we're living through now,
right?
It's using the data to make decisions that are terrible.
It's not the intelligence that's gonna go out there
and surpass us and take over the world
or lock us into a room to starve to death slowly
over multiple days.
It's instead the tools that we're building
that are allowing us to make the terrible decisions
we would have less efficiently made before, right?
Computers are very good at making us more efficient,
including being more efficient at doing terrible things.
And that's the part of the AI we have to worry about.
It's not the, you know, true intelligence
that we're gonna build sometime in the future,
probably long after we're around.
But, you know, I just, I think that whole framing of it
sort of misses the point, even though it is inspiring.
And I was inspired by those ideas, right?
I got into this in part
because I wanted to build something like that.
Philosophical questions are interesting to me,
but, you know, that's not where the terror comes from.
The terror comes from the everyday.
And you can construct the situation.
It's in the subtlety of the interaction between AI
and the human, like with social networks,
all the stuff you're doing
with interactive artificial intelligence.
But, you know, I feel like how 9,000
came a little bit closer to that
when it's in 2001 Space Odyssey,
because it felt like a personal assistant.
You know, it felt like closer to the AI systems
you have today.
And the real things we might actually encounter,
which is over-relying in some fundamental way
on our, like, DOM assistance or on social networks,
like over-offloading too much of us onto, you know,
onto things that require internet and power and so on.
And thereby becoming powerless as a standalone entity.
And then when that thing starts to misbehave
in some subtle way, it creates a lot of problems.
And those problems are dramatized when you're in space,
because you don't have a way to walk away.
Well, as the man said,
once we started making the decisions for you,
it stopped being your world, right?
That's the matrix, Michael, in case you don't remember.
But on the other hand, I could say,
no, because isn't that what we do with people anyway?
You know, just kind of the shared intelligence
that is humanity is relying on other people constantly.
I mean, we hyper-specialize, right, as individuals.
We're still generally intelligent.
We make our own decisions in a lot of ways,
but we leave most of this up to other people.
And that's perfectly fine.
And by the way, everyone does necessarily share our goals.
Sometimes they seem to be quite against us.
Sometimes we make decisions
that others would see as against our own interests.
And yet we somehow manage it, manage and survive.
I'm not entirely sure why an AI would actually make that worse.
Or even different, really.
You mentioned the matrix.
Do you think we're living in a simulation?
It does feel like a thought game
more than a real scientific question.
Well, I'll tell you why,
like I think it's an interesting thought experiment.
See what you think from a computer science perspective.
It's a good experiment of how difficult would it be
to create a sufficiently realistic world
that us humans would enjoy being in.
That's almost like a competition.
If we're living in a simulation,
then I don't believe that we were put in the simulation.
I believe that it's just physics playing out
and we came out of that.
Like, I don't think.
So you think you have to build the universe
kind of all the time?
I think the universe itself,
we can think of that as a simulation.
And in fact, sometimes I try to think about
to understand what it's like for a computer
to start to think about the world.
I try to think about the world.
Things like quantum mechanics
where it doesn't feel very natural to me at all.
And it really strikes me as,
I don't understand this thing that we're living in.
It has, there's weird things happening in it
that don't feel natural to me at all.
Now, if you want to call that as the result of a simulator.
Okay, I'm fine with that.
But like I don't-
There's the bugs in the simulation.
There's the bugs.
I mean, the interesting thing about simulation
is that it might have bugs.
I mean, that's the thing that I-
But there would be bugs for the people in the simulation.
They're just, that's just reality.
Unless you were hard enough to know that there was a bug.
But I think-
Back to the matrix.
Yeah, the way you put the question-
I don't think that we live in a simulation created for us.
Okay, I would say that.
I think that's interesting.
I've actually never thought about it that way.
I mean, the way you asked the question though is,
could you create a world that is enough for us humans?
It's an interestingly sort of self-referential question
because the beings that created the simulation
probably have not created a simulation
that's realistic for them.
But we're in the simulation and so it's realistic for us.
So we could create a simulation
that is fine for the people in the simulation, as it were.
That would not necessarily be fine for us
as the creators of the simulation.
But, well, you can forget.
I mean, when you go into the,
if you play video games of virtual reality,
you can, if it was some suspension of disbelief or whatever.
It becomes a world.
It becomes a world even like in brief moments.
You forget that another world exists.
I mean, that's what good stories do.
They pull you in.
And the question is, is it possible to pull,
our brains are limited.
Is it possible to pull the brain in
to where we actually stay in that world
longer and longer and longer and longer?
And not only that, but we don't want to leave.
And so, especially, this is the key thing
about the developing brain,
is if we journey into that world early on in life, often.
How would you even know, yeah?
But from a video game design perspective,
from a Westworld perspective,
I think it's an important thing
for even computer scientists to think about,
because it's clear that video games are getting much better.
And virtual reality, although it's been ups and downs,
just like artificial intelligence,
it feels like virtual reality will be here
in a very impressive form
if we were to fast forward 100 years into the future
in a way that might change society fundamentally.
Like, if I were to, I'm very limited
in predicting the future, as all of us are.
But if I were to try to predict,
like, in which way I'd be surprised
to see the world 100 years from now,
it'd be that, or impressed,
it'd be that we're all no longer
living in this physical world,
that we're all living in a virtual world.
You really need to be calculating God by Sawyer.
It's a, he'll read it in a night.
It's a very easy read,
but it's a, I was assuming you were that kind of reader,
but it's a good story, and it's kind of about this,
but not in a way that it appears.
And I really enjoyed the thought experiment.
Yeah, I think it's pretty sure it's Robert Sawyer.
But anyway, he's apparently
Canadian's top science fiction writer,
which is why the story mostly takes place in Toronto.
But it's a very good,
it's a very good sort of story that sort of imagines this.
Very different kind of simulation hypothesis
sort of thing from, say, the egg, for example.
You know, I'm talking about the short story.
By the guy who did the Martian.
Who wrote the Martian?
You know, I'm talking about.
Matt Damon.
No, the book.
So we had this whole discussion
that Michael doesn't partake in this exercise of reading.
Yeah, he doesn't seem to like it,
which seems very strange to me,
considering how much he has to read.
I read all the time.
I used to read 10 books every week
when I was in sixth grade or whatever.
It was a lot of it's science fiction,
a lot of it, a lot of it's history, but I love to read.
But anyway, you should recalculate in God.
I think you'll, it's very easy read, like I said,
and I think you'll enjoy sort of the ideas that it presents.
Yeah, I think the thought experiment is quite interesting.
One thing I've noticed about people growing up now,
I mean, we'll talk about social media,
but video games is a much bigger, bigger and bigger
and bigger part of their lives.
And the video games have become much more realistic.
I think it's possible that the three of us are not,
and maybe the two of you are not familiar
exactly with the numbers we're talking about here.
I think the number of people.
It's bigger than movies, right?
It's huge.
I used to do a lot of the computational narrative stuff.
I understand that economists can actually see
the impact of video games on the labor market.
That there's fewer young men of a certain age
participating in like paying jobs than you'd expect.
And that they trace it back to video games.
I mean, the problem with Star Trek
was not warp drive or teleportation.
It was the holodeck.
Like if you have the holodeck, that's it.
That's it, you go in the holodeck, you never come out.
I mean, it just never made,
once I saw that I thought, okay, well,
so this is the end of humanity, right?
They've been in the holodeck.
Because that feels like the singularity,
not some AGI or whatever.
It's some possibly to go into another world
that can be artificially made better than this one.
And slowing it down so you live forever
or speeding it up so you appear to live forever
or making the decision of when to die.
And then most of us will just be old people on the porch
yelling at the kids these days in their virtual reality.
Worlds.
But they won't hear us because they've got headphones on.
So, I mean, rewinding back to MOOCs,
is there lessons that you've speaking to kids these days?
There you go.
That was a transition.
That was, right there.
I'll fix it in post.
That's Charles' favorite phrase.
Fix it in post.
He said, when we were recording all the time,
whenever the editor didn't like something or whatever,
I would say, we'll fix it in post.
He hated that.
He hated that more than anything.
Because it was Charles' way of saying,
I'm not gonna do it again.
You know, you're on your own for this one.
But it always got fixed in post.
Exactly.
So, is there something you've learned about,
I mean, it's interesting to talk about MOOCs,
is there something you've learned about the process
of education, about thinking about the present?
I think there's two lines of conversation to be had here,
is the future of education in general,
that you've learned about.
And more, pressurantly,
is the education at times of COVID.
The second thing, in some ways,
matters more than the first,
for at least in my head,
not just because it's happening now,
but because I think it's reminded us of a lot of things.
Coincidentally, today,
there's an article out by a good friend of mine,
who's also a professor at Georgia Tech,
but more importantly, a writer and editor
at the Atlantic, kind of Ian Bogos.
And the title is something like,
Americans will sacrifice anything for the college experience.
And it's about why we went back to college,
and why people wanted us to go back to college.
And it's not greedy presidents
trying to get the last dollar from someone.
It's because they want to go to college.
And what they're paying for is not the classes,
what they're paying for is the college experience.
It's not the education, it's being there.
I've believed this for a long time,
that we continually make this mistake
of people want to go back to college
as being people want to go back to class.
They don't, they want to go back to campus.
They want to move away from home.
They want to do all those things that people experience.
It's a rite of passage.
It's an identity, if I can steal some of Ian's words here.
And I think that's right.
And I think what we've learned through COVID is,
it has made it, the disaggregation
was not the disaggregation of the education
from the place, the university place,
and that you can get the best anywhere you want to.
In terms of there's lots of reasons
why that is not necessarily true.
The disaggregation is having it shoved in our faces
that the reason to go, again,
that the reason to go to college
is not necessarily to learn.
It's to have the college experience.
And that's very difficult for us to accept,
even though we behave that way,
most of us, when we were undergrads, you know.
A lot of us didn't go to every single class.
We learned and we got it and we look back on it
and we're happy we had the learning experience as well.
Obviously, particularly us,
because this is the kind of thing that we do.
And my guess is that's true of the vast majority
of your audience.
But that doesn't mean the,
I'm standing in front of you telling you this
is the thing that people are excited about.
And that's why they want to be there,
primarily why they want to be there.
So to me, that's what COVID has forced us to deal with,
even though I think we're still all in deep denial about it
and hoping that it'll go back to that.
And I think about 85% of it will.
We'll be able to pretend that that's really the way it is,
again, and we'll forget the lessons of this.
But technically what will come out of it,
or technologically what will come out of it,
is a way of providing a more dispersed experience
through online education and these kinds of remote things
that we've learned.
And we'll have to come up with new ways to engage them
in the experience of college,
which includes not just the parties
or the whatever kids do,
but the learning part of it so that they actually come out
four or five or six years later
with having actually learned something.
So I think the world will be radically different afterwards.
And I think technology will matter for that,
just not in the way that the people
who were building the technology originally
imagined it would be.
And I think this would have been true even without COVID,
but COVID has accelerated that reality.
So it's happening in two or three years or five years
as opposed to 10 or 15.
That was an amazing answer that I did not understand.
So it was passionate and meaningful.
Shots fired.
But I don't know, I just didn't,
no, I'm not trying to criticize it.
I think I don't think I'm getting it.
So you mentioned disaggregation.
So what's that?
Well, so the power of technology
that if you go on the West Coast and hang out long enough
is all about we're gonna disaggregate these things together,
the books from the bookstore, that kind of a thing.
And then suddenly Amazon controls the universe,
and technology is a disruptor.
And people have been predicting that
for a higher education for a long time,
but certainly in the...
So is this the sort of idea like
students can aggregate on a campus some place
and then take classes over the network anywhere?
Yeah, this is what people thought was gonna happen,
or at least people claimed it was gonna happen, right?
Because my daughter is essentially doing that now.
She's on one campus, but learning in a different campus.
Sure, and COVID makes that possible, right?
Or COVID makes that...
Legal.
All but avoidable, right?
But the idea originally was that,
you and I were gonna create this machine learning class
and it was gonna be great,
and then no one else would be the machine learning class
everyone changed, right?
That was never gonna happen,
but something like that you could see happen.
But I feel like you didn't address that.
So why is it that...
Why Q?
Why?
I don't think that will be the thing that happens.
So the college experience,
maybe I missed what the college experience was.
I thought it was peers, like people hanging around.
A large part of it is peers.
Well, it's peers and independence.
Yeah, but none of that...
You can do classes online for all of that.
No, no, no, no.
Because we're social people, right?
So one would take the classes,
that also has to be part of an experience.
It's in a context, and the context is the university.
And by the way, it actually matters
that Georgia Tech really is different from Brown.
I see, because then students can choose
the kind of experience they think
is gonna be best for them.
Okay, I think we're giving too much agency
to the students in making an informed decision.
Okay.
But yes, they will make choices
and they will have different experiences.
And some of those choices will be made for them.
Some of them will be choices they're making
because they think it's this, that, or the other.
I just don't want to say...
I don't want to give the idea...
It's not homogeneous.
Yes, it's certainly not homogeneous, right?
I mean, Georgia Tech is different from Brown.
Brown is different from pick your favorite
state school in Iowa.
Iowa State, okay?
Which I guess is my favorite state school in Iowa.
But these are all different.
They have different contexts.
And a lot of those contexts are,
they're about history, yes,
but they're also about the location of where you are.
They're about the larger group of people who are around you,
whether you're in Athens, Georgia,
and you're basically the only thing that's there
as a university, you're responsible for all the jobs,
or whether you're at Georgia State University,
which is an urban campus,
where you're surrounded by six million people
in your campus where it ends and begins in the city,
ends and begins, we don't know.
It actually matters whether you're a small campus
or a large campus.
I mean, these things matter.
Why is it that if you go to Georgia Tech,
you're forever proud of that?
And you say that to people at dinner bars and whatever.
And if you get a degree at an online university somewhere,
you don't, that's not a thing that comes up at a bar.
Well, it's funny you say that.
So the students who take our online masters
by several measures are more loyal
than the students who come on campus,
certainly for the master's degree.
The reason for that, I think,
and you'd have to ask them,
but based on my conversations with them,
I feel comfortable saying this,
is because this didn't exist before.
I mean, we talk about this online masters
and that it's reaching 11,000 students
and that's an amazing thing.
And we're admitting everyone we believe we can succeed.
We got a 60% acceptance rate.
It's amazing, right?
It's also a $6,600 degree.
The entire degree costs $6,600 or $7,000,
depending on how long you take.
Dollar degree, as opposed to the $46,000
that cost you to come on campus.
So that feels, and I can do it while I'm working full time
and I've got a family and a mortgage
and all these other things.
So it's an opportunity to do something you wanted to do
but you didn't think was possible
without giving up two years of your life
as well as all the money and everything else,
the life that you had built.
So I think we created something that's had an impact,
but importantly, we gave a set of people opportunities
they otherwise didn't feel they had.
So I think people feel very loyal about that
and my biggest piece of evidence for that
besides the surveys is that we have somewhere
north of 80 students, might be 100 at this point,
who graduated but come back in TA for this class
for basically minimum wage,
even though they're working full time
because they believe in sort of having that opportunity
and they wanna be a part of something.
Now, will generation three feel this way?
15 years from now, will people have that same sense?
I don't know, but right now, they kind of do.
And so it's not the online,
it's a matter of feeling as if you're a part of something.
We're all very tribal.
And I think there's something very tribal
about being a part of something like that.
Being on campus makes that easier.
Going through a shared experience makes that easier.
It's harder to have that shared experience
if you're alone looking at a computer screen.
We can create ways to make that.
Is it possible?
It is possible.
The question is, it still is the intuition to me.
And it was at the beginning when I saw something
like the online master's program
is that this is gonna replace universities.
And I won't replace universities, but it won't.
But like, why is it, why?
Because it's living in a different part of the ecosystem,
right?
The people who are taking it are already adults.
They've gone through their undergrad experience.
I think their goals have shifted from when they were 17.
They have other things that are going.
But it does do something really important,
something very social and very important, right?
You know this whole thing about,
don't build the sidewalks, just leave the grass
and the students or the people will walk
and you put the sidewalks where they create paths.
This is kind of a thing.
That's interesting, yeah.
Their architects apparently believe
that's the right way to do things.
The metaphor here is that we created this environment.
We didn't quite know how to think about the social aspect,
but we didn't have time to solve all,
do all the social engineering, right?
The students did it themselves.
They created these groups, like on Google+,
they were like 30-something groups created in the first year
because somebody had these Google+,
and they created these groups
and they divided up in ways that made sense.
We live in the same state
or we're working on the same things
or we have the same background or whatever,
and they created these social things.
We sent them t-shirts and we have all these great pictures
of students putting on their t-shirts
as they travel around the world.
I climbed to this mountain top,
I'm putting this t-shirt on, I'm a part of this.
They were part of them.
They created the social environment
on top of the social network and the social media
that existed to create this sense of belonging
and being a part of something.
They found a way to do it, right?
And I think they had other,
it scratched an itch that they had,
but they had scratched some of that itch
that might have required to be physically
in the same place long before, right?
So I think, yes, it's possible,
and it's more than possible, it's necessary,
but I don't think it's going to replace the university
as we know it.
The university as we know it will change,
but there's just a lot of power
and a kind of rite of passage
and kind of going off to yourself.
Now, maybe there'll be some other rite of passage
that'll happen that'll drive us somewhere else.
So the university is such a fascinating mess of things.
So just even the faculty position is a fascinating mess.
Like it doesn't make any sense.
It stabilized itself,
but like why are the world-class researchers
spending a huge amount of time,
or their time teaching and service?
Like you're doing like three jobs.
And I mean, it turns out it's maybe an accident of history
or human evolution, I don't know.
It seems like the people who are really good at teaching
are often really good at research.
There seems to be a parallel there,
but like it doesn't make any sense
that you should be doing that.
At the same time, it also doesn't seem to make sense
that your place where you party
is the same place where you go to learn calculus
or whatever, but it's a safe space.
Safe space for everything.
Yeah, relatively speaking, it's a safe space.
No, by the way, I feel the need very strongly
to point out that we are living
in a very particular weird bubble, right?
Most people don't go to college.
And by the way, the ones who do go to college,
they're not 18 years old, right?
They're like 25 or something.
I forget the numbers.
The places where we've been, where we are,
they look like whatever we think
the traditional movie version of universities are,
but for most people, it's not that way at all.
By the way, most people who drop out of college,
it's entirely for financial reasons, right?
So, you know, we were talking about a particular experience.
And so for that set of people, which is very small,
but larger than it was a decade or two or three or four,
certainly, ago, I don't think that will change.
My concern, which I think is kind of implicit
in some of these questions is that
somehow we will divide the world up further.
Into the people who get to have this experience
and get to have the network and they sort of benefit from it
and everyone else while increasingly requiring
that they have more and more credentials
in order to get a job as a barista, right?
You got to have a master's degree
in order to work at Starbucks.
We're gonna force people to do these things,
but they're not gonna get to have that experience.
And there'll be a small group of people who do,
who will continue to, you know, positive feedback,
like, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
I worry a lot about that,
which is why for me, and by the way,
here's an answer to your question about faculty,
which is why to me that you have to focus on
access in the mission.
I think the reason, whether it's good, bad, or strange,
I mean, I agree, it's strange.
But I think it's useful to have the faculty member,
particularly at large R1 universities
where we've all had experiences,
that you tie what they get to do
and with the fundamental mission of the university
and let the mission drive.
What I hear when I talk to faculty is
they love their PhD students
because they're creating, they're reproducing,
basically, right?
Let's them do their research and multiply.
But they understand that the mission is the undergrads,
and so they will do it without complaint, mostly,
because it's a part of the mission and why they're here,
and they have experiences with it themselves.
And it was important to get them where they were going.
The people who tend to get squeezed in that,
by the way, are the master students, right?
Who are neither the PhDs who are like us,
nor the undergrads, we have already bought into the idea
that we have to teach, though.
That's increasingly changing.
Anyway, I think tying that mission in really matters,
and it gives you a way to unify people around
making it an actual higher calling.
Education feels like more of a higher calling to me
than even research.
Because education, you cannot treat it as a hobby
if you're going to do it well.
But that's the pushback on this whole system,
is that you should, education, be a full-time job, right?
And almost like research is a distraction from that.
Although, I think most of our colleagues,
many of our colleagues would say that research is the job
and education is the distraction.
Right, but that's the beautiful dance.
It seems to be that tension in itself seems to work,
seems to bring out the best in the faculty,
or like the ones I've done.
But I will point out two things.
One thing I'm going to point out,
and the other thing I want Michael to point out,
because I think Michael is much closer to the,
to sort of the ideal professor in some sense than I am.
You're the platonic sense of a professor.
I don't know what he meant by that,
but he is a dean, so he has a different experience.
I'm giving him time to think of the profound thing
he's gonna say. That's good.
But let me point this out,
which is that we have lecturers in the college
of computing where I am.
There's 10 or 12 of them, depending on your count,
as opposed to the 90 or so tenure track faculty.
Those 10 lecturers who only teach,
well, they don't only teach, they also do service.
Some of them do research as well, but primarily they teach.
They teach 50%, over 50% of our credit hours,
and we teach everybody.
So they're doing not just,
they're doing more than eight times the work
of the tenure track faculty,
just if you're closer to nine or 10.
And that's including our grad courses, right?
So they're doing this, they're teaching more,
they're touching more than anyone,
and they're beloved for it.
So we recently had a survey, we do these alumni,
everyone does these alumni surveys,
you hire someone from the outside to do whatever,
and I was really struck by something.
I saw all these really cool numbers,
I'm not gonna talk about it,
because it's all internal, confidential stuff.
But one thing I will talk about
is there was a single question we asked our alum,
and these are people who graduated,
born in the 30s and 40s,
all the way up to people who graduated last week, right?
Well, last semester.
Okay, good.
Time flies.
Yeah, time flies.
And it was the question,
name a single person who had a strong,
positive impact on you, something like that.
I think it was special impact?
Yeah, special impact on you.
And then, so they got all the answers from people,
and they created a word cloud.
Those clear word clouds created by people
who don't do word clouds for a living,
because they had one person whose name appeared
like nine different times, like Phillip, Phil,
Dr. Phil, you know, but whatever.
But they got all this.
And I looked at it, and I noticed something really cool.
The five people from the college of computing,
I recognized, were in that cloud.
And four of them were lecturers,
the people who teach.
Two of them, relatively modern.
Both were chairs of our division of computing instruction.
One retired, one is gonna retire soon.
And the other two were lecturers I remembered from the 1980s.
Two of those four actually have-
Despite the way the fifth person was Charles.
That's not important.
The thing is, I don't tell people that.
But the two of those people are teaching awards
are named after.
Thank you, Michael.
Two of those are teaching awards are named after, right?
So when you ask students, alumni,
people who are now 60, 70 years old even,
who touch them?
They say the dean of students.
They say the big teachers who taught
the big introductory classes, they got me into it.
There's a guy named Richard Barker's on there
who's known as a great teacher.
The Phil Adler guy who,
I probably just said his last name wrong,
but I know the first name's Phil
because he kept showing up over and over again.
Famous-
Adler is what it said.
Okay, good.
But different people spelled it differently.
So he appeared multiple times.
Right.
He was a, clearly,
he was a professor in the business school,
but when you read about him,
I went to read about himself,
I was curious who he was.
It's all about his teaching
and the students that he touched, right?
So whatever it is that we're doing,
and we think we're doing that's important,
or why we think the university's function,
the people who go through it,
they remember the people who were kind to them,
the people who taught them something,
and they do remember it.
They remember it later.
I think that's important.
That's what the mission matters.
Not to completely lose track of the fundamental problem
of how do we replace the party aspect of universities.
Before we go to what makes the Platonic professor,
do you think,
what in your sense is the role of MOOCs
in this whole picture during COVID?
Are we, should we desperately be clamoring
to get back on campus?
Or is this a stable place to be for a little while?
I don't know.
I know that it's the online teaching experience
and learning experience has been really rough.
I think that people find it to be a struggle
in a way that's not a happy positive struggle.
That when you got through it,
you just feel like glad that it's over
as opposed to I've achieved something.
So, I worry about that,
but I worry about just even before this happened,
I worry about lecture teaching
as how well is that actually really working
as far as a way to do education,
as a way to inspire people.
I mean, all the data that I'm aware of seems to indicate,
and this kind of fits I think with Charles' story,
is that people respond to connection, right?
They actually feel,
if they feel connected to the person teaching the class,
they're more likely to go along with it.
They're more able to retain information.
They're more motivated to be involved in the class
in some way, and that really matters.
You mean to the human themselves?
Yeah.
Can't you do that?
Actually, perhaps more effectively online,
like you mentioned science communication.
So, I literally, I think,
learned linear algebra from Gilbert Strang
by watching MIT OpenCourseWare when I was in drugs.
And he was a personality,
he was a bit like a tiny,
in this tiny little world of math,
there's a bit of a rock star, right?
So, you kind of look up to that person.
Can't that replace the in-person education?
It can help.
I will point out something.
I can't share the numbers,
but we have surveyed our students,
and even though they have feelings
about what I would interpret as connection,
I like that word, in the different modes of classrooms,
there's no difference between how well
they think they're learning.
For them, the thing that makes them unhappy
is the situation they're in.
And I think the last lack of connection,
it's not whether they're learning anything.
They seem to think they're learning something anyway, right?
In fact, they seem to think
they're learning it equally well,
presumably because the faculty are putting in,
or the instructors, more generally speaking,
are putting in the energy and effort
to try to make certain
what they've curated can be expressed to them
in a useful way.
But the connection is missing,
and so there's huge differences in what they prefer,
and as far as I can tell,
what they prefer is more connection, not less.
That connection just doesn't have to be physically
in a classroom.
I mean, look, I used to teach 348 students
on my machine learning class on campus.
Do you know why?
That was the biggest classroom on campus.
They're sitting in theaters,
they're sitting in theater seats.
I'm literally on a stage looking down on them
and talking to them, right?
I mean, we're not sitting down
having a one-on-one conversation,
reading each other's body language,
trying to communicate,
and going, we're not doing any of that.
So if you're past the third row,
it might as well be online anyway,
is the kind of thing that people have said,
Daphne has actually said some version of this,
that online starts on the third row,
or something like that.
And I think that's not,
yeah, I like it, I think it captures something important.
But people still came, by the way.
Even the people who had access to our material
would still come to class.
I mean, there's a certain element
about looking to the person next to you.
It's just like their presence there,
their boredom, and like when the parts are boring,
and their excitement when the parts are exciting,
like, and sharing in that,
like unspoken kind of, yeah, communication.
In part, the connection is with the other people in the room.
Watching the circus on TV alone is not really,
they've ever been to a movie theater
and been the only one there at a comedy.
It's not as funny as when you're in a room
full of people all laughing.
Well, you need, maybe you need just another person.
It's like, as opposed to many.
Maybe there's some kind of-
Well, there's different kinds of connection, right?
And there's different kinds of comedy.
Well, in the sense that-
As we're learning today.
I wasn't sure if that was gonna land,
but just the idea that different jokes,
I've now done a little bit of stand-up.
And so different jokes work in different sized crowds too.
No, it's true.
Where sometimes if it's a big enough crowd,
then even a really subtle joke can take root someplace,
and then that cues other people,
and it kind of, there's a whole statistics of,
I did this terrible thing to my brother.
So when I was really young,
I decided that my brother was only laughing
as it comes when I laughed.
Like he was taking cues from me.
So I like purposely didn't laugh, just to see if I was right.
And did you laugh at non-funny things?
I really wanted to do both sides.
I did both sides.
And at the end of it, I told him what I did.
He was very upset about this.
And from that day on.
He lost his sense of humor.
No, no, no, no.
Well, yes, but from that day on,
he laughed on his own.
He stopped taking cues from me.
So I wanna say that it was a good thing that I did,
but it was mostly mean.
You saved that man's life.
Yes, but it was mostly mean, but it's true though.
It's true, right?
That people, I think you're right.
But okay, so where does that get us?
That gets us the idea that,
I mean, certainly movie theaters are a thing, right?
Where people like to be watching together,
even though the people on the screen
aren't really co-present with the people in the audience.
The audience is co-present with themselves.
By the way, and that point,
it's an open question that's being raised by this,
whether movies will no longer be a thing
because Netflix's audience is growing.
So that's a very parallel question for education.
Will movie theaters still be a thing in 2021?
I think the argument is that there is a feeling
of being in the crowd that isn't replicated
by being at home watching it,
and that there's value in that.
And then I think just-
But.
It scales better online.
But I feel like we're having a conversation
about whether concerts will still exist
after the invention of the record or the CD
or wherever it is, right?
They won't.
You're right, concerts are dead.
Well, okay, I think the joke is only funny
if you say it before now.
Right, yeah, that's true.
We'll fix it in post.
It's like three years ago.
It's like, well, no, obviously,
concerts are still-
I'll wait to publish this until we have a vaccine.
No, we'll fix it in post.
But I think the important thing is-
Fix the virus first.
Concert's changed, right?
Concert's changed.
First off, movie theaters weren't this way, right?
In like the 60s and 70s, they weren't like this.
Like blockbusters were basically what?
What, Jaws and Star Wars created blockbusters, right?
Before then, there weren't.
The whole shared summer experience didn't exist
in our lifetimes, right?
Certainly, you were well into adulthood
by the time this was true, right?
So it's just a very different, it's very different.
So what we've been experiencing in the last 10 years
is not like the majority of human history,
but more importantly, concerts, right?
Concerts mean something different.
Most people don't go to concerts anymore.
Like there's an age where you care about it.
You sort of stop doing it.
You keep listening to music or whatever
and da, da, da, da, da, da.
So I think that's a painful way of saying
that it will change.
It was not the same thing as it going away.
Replace is too strong of a word, but it will change.
It has to.
I actually, like to push back, I wonder
because I think you're probably just throwing
that you're intuition out.
Oh, absolutely.
And it's possible that concerts,
more people go to concerts now,
but obviously much more people listen to,
dumb, than before there was records.
It's possible to argue that if you look at the data
that it just expanded the pie
of what music listening means.
So it's possible that like universities grow
in the parallel or the theaters grow,
but also more people get to watch movies,
more people get to be educated.
Yeah, I hope that.
Yeah, and to the extent that we can grow the pie
and have education be not just something you do
for four years when you're done with your other education,
but it'd be a more lifelong thing,
that would have tremendous benefits,
especially as the economy and the world change rapidly.
Like people need opportunities to stay abreast
of these changes.
And so, I don't know, that's all part of the ecosystem.
It's all to the good.
I mean, you know, I'm not gonna have an argument
about whether we lost fidelity when we went
from laser discs to DVDs or record players to CDs.
I mean, I'm willing to grant that that is true,
but convenience matters and the ability to do something
that you couldn't do otherwise
because that convenience matters.
And you can tell me I'm only getting 90% of the experience,
but I'm getting the experience.
I wasn't getting it before or wasn't lasting as long
or it wasn't as easy.
I mean, this just seems straightforward to me.
It's gonna, it's going to change.
It is for the good that more people get access.
And it is our job to do two separate things.
One, to educate them and make access available.
That's our mission.
But also for very simple selfish reasons,
we need to figure out how to do it better
so that we individually stay in business.
We can do both of those things at the same time.
They are not in, they may be intention,
but they are not mutually exclusive.
So you've educated some scary number of people.
So you've seen a lot of people succeed,
find their path through life.
Is there a device that you can give to a young person today
about computer science education,
about education in general, about life,
about whatever the journey that one takes in there,
maybe in their teens, in their early 20s,
sort of in those underground years,
as you try to go through the essential process
of partying and not go into classes.
And yet somehow try to get a degree.
If you get to the point where you're far enough up
in the hierarchy of needs
that you can actually make decisions like this,
then find the thing that you're passionate about
and pursue it.
And sometimes it's the thing that drives your life
and sometimes it's secondary.
And you'll do other things because you've got to eat, right?
You've got to family, you've got to feed,
you've got people you have to help or whatever, right?
And I understand that and it's not easy for everyone,
but always take a moment or two to pursue the things
that you love, the things that bring passion
and happiness to your life.
And if you don't, I know that sounds corny,
but I genuinely believe it.
And if you don't have such a thing,
then you're lying to yourself.
You have such a thing, you just have to find it.
And it's okay if it takes you a long time to get there.
Rodney Dangerfield became a comedian in his 50s, I think.
It certainly wasn't his 20s.
And lots of people failed for a very long time
before getting to where they were going.
I try to have hope.
And it wasn't obvious.
I mean, you and I talked about the experience
that I had a long time ago with a particular police officer.
Was it my first one and was it my last one?
But in my view, I wasn't supposed to be here after that
and I'm here, so it's all gravy.
So you might as well go ahead and grab life as you can
because of that.
That's sort of how I see it.
While recognizing, again, the delusion matters, right?
Allow yourself to be deluded.
Allow yourself to believe that it's all gonna work out.
Just don't be so deluded that you missed the obvious.
And you're gonna be fine.
It's gonna be there.
It's gonna work out.
What do you think?
I like to say, choose your parents wisely
because that has a big impact on your life.
It's different.
Yeah, I mean, there's a whole lot of things
that you don't get to pick.
And whether you get to have one kind of life
or a different kind of life can depend a lot
on things out of your control.
But I really do believe in the passion and excitement thing.
I was talking to my mom on the phone the other day
and essentially what came out is that computer science
is really popular right now.
And I get to be a professor teaching something
that's very attractive to people.
And she was like trying to give me some appreciation
for how foresightful I was for choosing this line of work
as if somehow I knew that this is what was gonna happen
in 2020.
But that's not how it went for me at all.
Like I studied computer science
because I was just interested.
It was just so interesting to me.
I didn't think it would be particularly lucrative.
And I've done everything I can to keep it
as un-lucrative as possible.
Some of my friends and colleagues have not done that.
And I pride myself on my ability to remain un-rich.
But I do believe that, like I'm glad,
I mean, I'm glad that it worked out for me.
It could have been like,
oh, what I was really fascinated by
is this particular kind of engraving
that nobody cares about.
But so I got lucky and the thing that I cared about
happened to be a thing that other people
eventually cared about.
But I don't think I would have had a fun time
choosing anything else.
Like this was the thing that kept me interested
and engaged.
Well, one thing that people tell me,
especially around early on the graduate
and the internet is part of the problem here
is they say they're passionate about so many things.
How do I choose a thing?
Which is a harder thing for me to know what to do with.
Is there any?
I mean, don't you know, which, I mean, you know, look.
A long time ago, I walked down a hallway
and I took a left turn.
Yeah.
I could have taken a right turn.
And my world could be better or it could be worse.
I have no idea.
I have no way of knowing.
Is there anything about this particular hallway
that's relevant or are you just in general choices?
Yeah, you were on the left.
It sounds like you regret not taking the right turn.
Oh, no, not at all.
Well, you brought it up.
Well, because it was a turn there.
On the left was Michael Liman's office, right?
I mean, these sorts of things happen, right?
But here's the thing.
On the right, by the way, there was just a blank wall.
It wasn't a huge choice.
It would have really hurt.
He tried first.
No, but it's true, right?
That, you know, I think about Ron Brockman, right?
I went, I took a trip I wasn't supposed to take
and I ended up talking to Ron about this
and I ended up going down this entire path
that allowed me to, I think, get tenure.
But by the way, I decided to say yes to something
that didn't make any sense
and I went down this educational path.
But it would have been, you know, who knows, right?
Maybe if I hadn't done that,
I would be a billionaire right now.
I'd be Elon Musk.
My life could be so much better.
My life could also be so much worse.
You know, you just gotta feel
that sometimes you have decisions you're gonna make.
You cannot know what's gonna do.
You should think about it, right?
Some things are clearly smarter than other things.
You gotta play the odds a little bit.
But in the end, if you've got multiple choices
or lots of things you think you might love,
go with the thing that you actually love,
the thing that jumps out at you
and sort of pursue it for a little while.
The worst thing that'll happen
is you took a left turn instead of a right turn
and you ended up merely happy.
Beautiful.
So accepting, so taking the step and just accepting,
accepting that that don't like question,
question the choice.
I like to think that life is long
and there's time to actually pursue.
Every once in a while,
you have to put on a leather suit
and make a thriller video.
Every once in a while.
If I ever get a chance to put on a leather suit,
I'm doing it.
Yeah.
I was told that you actually danced,
but that part was edited out.
I don't dance.
There was a thing where we did do the zombie thing.
We did do the zombie thing.
That wasn't edited out.
It just wasn't put into the final thing.
I'm quite happy.
There was a reason for that too, right?
Like I wasn't wearing something right.
There was a reason for that.
No leather suit.
Is that what it was?
I can't remember.
Anyway, the right thing happened.
Exactly.
You took the left turn and ended up being the right thing.
So a lot of people ask me that are a little bit
tangential to the programming, the computing world,
and they're interested to learn programming,
like all kinds of disciplines that are outside
of the particular discipline of computer science.
What advice do you have for people
that want to learn how to program
or want to either taste this little skill set
or discipline or try to see if it can be used somehow
in their own life?
What stage of life are they in?
It feels, well, one of the magic things about the internet
of the people that write me is I don't know.
Cause my answer is different for,
my daughter is taking AP computer science right now.
Hi, Johnny.
She's amazing in doing amazing things
and my son's beginning to get interested
and I'll be really curious where he takes it.
I think his mind actually works very well
for this sort of thing and she's doing great.
But one of the things I have to tell her all the time
is she points, well, I want to make a rhythm game.
So I want to go for two weeks and then build a rhythm game,
show me how to build a rhythm game and start small,
learn the building blocks and how to take the time,
have patience, eventually you'll build a rhythm game.
I was in grad school when I suddenly woke up one day
over the Royal East and I thought, wait a minute,
I'm a computer scientist.
I should be able to write Pac-Man in an afternoon.
And I did, not with great graphics.
It was actually a very cool game.
I had to figure out how the ghost moved and everything.
And I did it in an afternoon and Pascal on an old Apple 2GS.
But if I had started out trying to build Pac-Man,
I think it probably would have ended very poorly for me.
Luckily back then there weren't these magical devices
we call phones and software everywhere
to give me this illusion that I could create something
by myself from the basics inside of a weekend like that.
I mean, that was a culmination of years and years and years
before I decided I should be able to write this and I could.
So my advice if you're early on is you've got the internet.
There are lots of people there to give you the information.
Find someone who cares about this.
Remember they've been doing it for a very long time.
Take it slow, learn the little pieces,
get excited about it and then keep the big projects
you want to build in mind.
You'll get there soon enough
because as a wise man once said, life is long.
Sometimes it doesn't seem that long, but it is long
and you'll have enough time to build it all out.
All the information is out there, but start small.
Generative and object numbers.
That's not exciting, but it'll get you a programming language.
Well, there's only one programming language, it's Lisp.
But if you have to pick a programming language,
I guess in today's, what would I do?
I guess I'd do-
Python is basically Lisp, but with better syntax.
Blast for me.
Yeah, with C syntax, how about that?
So you're going to argue that C syntax
is better than anything?
Anyway, I'm going to answer Python despite what he said.
Tell your story about somebody's dissertation
that had a Lisp program in it.
It was so funny.
This is Dave's, Dave's dissertation was like
Dave McAllister who was a professor at MIT for a while
and then he came to our lab and now he's at technology,
technicals to Chicago.
A brilliant guy, such an interesting guy.
Anyway, his thesis, it was a theorem prover
and he decided to have as an appendix his actual code,
which of course was already in Lisp
because of course it was.
And like the last 20 pages are just right parentheses.
It's just wonderful.
It's like, that's programming right there.
Just pages upon pages of right parentheses.
Anyway, Lisp is the only real language,
but I understand that that's not necessarily
the place where you start.
Python is just fine.
Python is good.
If you're of a certain age, if you're really young
and trying to figure out graphical languages
that let you kind of see how the thing works
and that's fine too, they're all fine.
It almost doesn't matter, but there are people
who spend a lot of time thinking about
how to build languages that get people in.
The questions are you trying to get in
and figure out what it is or do you already know
what you want and that's why I asked you
what stage of life people are in
because if you're different stages of life,
you would attack it differently.
The answer to that question of which language
keeps changing, I mean, there's some value
to exploring a lot of people write to me about Julia.
There's these like more modern languages
that keep being invented, Rust and Kotlin.
There's stuff that, for people who love
functional languages like Lisp,
apparently there's echoes of that,
but much better in the modern languages.
It's worthwhile to, especially when you're learning languages,
it feels like it's okay to try one
that's not like the popular one.
Oh yeah, but you want something simple.
And I think you get that way of thinking
almost no matter what language
and if you push far enough, like it can be assembly language,
but you need to push pretty far
before you start to hit the really deep concepts
that you would get sooner in other languages.
But like, I don't know, computation is kind of computation
is kind of touring equivalent is kind of computation.
And so it matters how you express things,
but you have to build out that mental structure
in your mind.
And I don't think it's super matters which language.
I mean, it matters a little
because some things are just at the wrong level
of abstraction.
I think assembly is at the wrong level abstract
for someone coming in new.
I think that if you start it from-
For someone coming in new.
Yes, for frameworks, big frameworks are quite a bit.
You know, you got to get to the point
where I want to learn any language means
I just pick up a reference book
and I think of a project
and I go through it in a weekend.
Right, you got to get there.
You're right though.
The languages that are designed for that
or it almost doesn't matter.
Pick the ones that people have built tutorials
and infrastructure around to help you
get kind of kind of ease into it.
Cause it's hard.
I mean, I did this little experiment with.
I was teaching intro to CS in the summer as a favor.
Which is, anyway.
I was teaching intro to CS as a favor.
And it was very funny cause I'd go in every single time
and I would think to myself,
how am I possibly going to fill up an hour and a half
talking about for loops, right?
And there wasn't enough time.
Took me a while to realize this, right?
There are only three things, right?
There's reading from a variable,
writing to a variable and conditional branching.
Everything else is syntactic sugar, right?
The syntactic sugar matters, but that's it.
And when I say that's it, I don't mean it's simple.
I mean, it's hard.
Like conditional branching, loops, variable.
Those are really hard concepts.
So you shouldn't be discouraged by this.
Here's the simple experiment I'm going to ask you
a question now, you ready?
X equals three.
Okay.
Y equals four.
What is X?
Three.
What is Y?
Four.
Y equals S.
I'm going to mess this up.
Oh, it's easier.
Y equals X.
What is Y?
Three.
That's right.
X equals seven.
What is Y?
That's one of the trickiest things to get
for programmers that there's a memory
and the variables are pointing
to a particular thing in memory.
And sometimes the languages hide that from you
and they bring it closer
to the way you think mathematics works.
Right.
So in fact, Mark Gustav, who worries
about these sorts of things
or used to worry about these sorts of things anyway,
had this kind of belief that actually people
when they see these statements,
X equals something Y equals something Y equals X,
that you have now made a mathematical statement
that Y and X are the same.
Which you can if you just put like
an anchor in front of it.
Yes, but people, that's not what you're doing.
Yeah.
Right.
I thought, and I kind of asked the question
and I think had some evidence for this.
I'm sorry, they study.
Is that most of the people who didn't know the answer
weren't sure about the answer.
They had used spreadsheets.
And so it's by reference or by name really, right?
And so depending upon what you think they are,
you get completely different answers.
The fact that I could go or one could go
two thirds of the way through a semester
and people still hadn't figured out in their heads
when you say Y equals X, what that meant,
tells you it's actually hard
because all those answers are possible.
And in fact, when you said,
oh, if you just put an ampersand in front of it,
I mean, that doesn't make any sense for an intro class.
And of course, a lot of language
don't even give you the ability to think about it
in terms of ampersand.
Do we want to have a 45 minute discussion
about the difference between equal EQ and equal in Lisp?
Yeah.
I know you do.
But you know, you could do that.
It's just actually really hard stuff.
So you shouldn't be, it's not too hard, we all do it,
but you shouldn't be discouraged.
It's why you should start small
so that you can figure out these things
so you have the right model in your head
so that when you write the language,
you can execute it and build the machine
that you want to build, right?
Yeah, the funny thing about programming
on those very basic things is the very basics
are not often made explicit,
which is actually what drives everybody away
from basically any discipline,
but programming is just another one.
Like even a simpler version of the equal sign
that I kind of forget is in mathematics,
equals is not assignment.
Yeah.
Like, I think basically every single programming language
with just a few handful of exceptions equals is assignment.
You have some other operator for equality.
And you know, even that, like everyone kind of knows it.
Once you started doing it,
but like you need to say that explicitly
or you just realize it like yourself.
Otherwise you might be stuck for,
you said like half a semester,
you could be stuck for quite a long time.
And I think also part of the programming is being okay
in that state of confusion for a while.
It's to the debugging point.
It's like, I just wrote two lines of code.
Why doesn't this work?
And staring at that for like hours
and trying to figure out,
and then every once in a while,
you just have to restart your computer
and everything works again.
And then you just kind of stare into the void
with the tears slowly rolling down your eye.
By the way, the fact that they didn't get this
actually had no impact on,
I mean, they were still able to redo their assignments.
Because it turns out their misunderstanding
wasn't being revealed to them
by the problems that we were giving them.
I wrote a program a long time ago,
actually for my master's thesis,
and in C++ I think, or C, I guess it was C.
And it was all memory management and terrible.
And it wouldn't work for a while.
And it was some kind of,
it was clear to me that it was overwriting memory.
And I just couldn't,
I was like, look, I got a paper done, time for this.
So I basically declared a variable
at the front in the main that was like 400K,
just an array, and it worked.
Because wherever I was scribbling over memory,
it would scribble into that space and it didn't matter.
And so I never figured out what the bug was,
but I did create something to sort of deal with it.
To work around it.
And it, you know, that's crazy, that's crazy.
It was okay, because that's what I wanted.
But I knew enough about memory management to go,
you know, management to go, you know,
I'm just gonna create an empty array here
and hope that that deals with the scribbling memory problem.
And it did, that takes a long time to figure out.
And by the way, the language you first learned
probably does garbage collection anyway,
so you're not even gonna come across,
you're not gonna come across that problem.
So we talked about the Minsky idea
of hating everything you do and hating yourself.
So let's end on a question
that's gonna make both of you very uncomfortable.
Okay.
Which is what is your, Charles,
what's your favorite thing that you're grateful for
about Michael and Michael?
What is your favorite thing
that you're grateful for about Charles?
Well, that answer is actually quite easy.
His friendship.
He stole the easy answer.
Yeah, I can tell you what I hate about Charles.
He steals my good answers.
The thing I like most about Charles,
he sees the world in a similar enough but different way
that it's sort of like having another life.
It's sort of like I get to experience things
that I wouldn't otherwise get to experience
because I would not naturally gravitate to them that way.
And so he just shows me a whole other world.
That's awesome.
Yeah, the inner product is not zero for sure.
It's not quite one, 0.7 maybe.
Just enough that you can learn.
That's the definition of friendship.
The inner product is 0.7.
Yeah, I think so.
That's the answer to life really.
Charles sometimes believes in me
when I have not believed in me.
He also sometimes works as an outboard confidence
that he has so much, so much confidence and self,
I don't know, comfortableness.
Okay, let's go with that.
That I feel better a little bit.
If he thinks I'm okay,
then maybe I'm not as bad as I think I am.
At the end of the day, luck favors the Charles.
It's a huge honor to talk with you.
Thank you so much for taking this time,
wasting your time with me.
It was an awesome conversation.
You guys are an inspiration to a huge number of people
and to me, so really enjoyed this.
Thanks for talking to me.
Thank you so much.
And by the way, if luck favors the Charles,
then it's certainly the case
that I've been very lucky to tell you.
I'm gonna end that part out.
Yeah.
Thanks for listening to this conversation
with Charles Isbo and Michael Littman.
And thank you to our sponsors,
Athletic Greens, Super Nutritional Drink,
Aidsleep, Self-Cooling Mattress,
Masterclass Online Courses
from some of the most amazing humans in history,
and Cash App.
The app I use to send money to friends.
Please check out the sponsors in the description
to get a discount and to support this podcast.
If you enjoy this thing, subscribe on YouTube,
review it with Five Stars Napa Podcast,
follow on Spotify, support it on Patreon,
connect with me on Twitter, Alex Freedman.
And now, let me leave you with some words
from Desmond Tutu.
Don't raise your voice.
Improve your argument.
Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.