The following is a conversation with Chris Lattner, his second time in the podcast.
He's one of the most brilliant engineers in modern computing, having created
LLVM compiler infrastructure project, the Clang Compiler, the Swift programming language,
a lot of key contributions to TensorFlow and TPUs as part of Google.
He served as vice president of autopilot software at Tesla, was a software innovator and leader at
and now is at SyFive as senior vice president of platform engineering looking to revolutionize
chip design to make it faster, better, and cheaper. Quick mention of each sponsor,
followed by some thoughts related to the episode. First sponsor is Blinkist,
an app that summarizes key ideas from thousands of books. I use it almost every day to learn new
things or to pick which books I want to read or listen to next. Second is Nero,
the maker of functional sugar-free gum and mints that I use to supercharge my mind
with caffeine, Althianine, and B vitamins. Third is Masterclass, online courses from the best people
in the world on each of the topics covered from rockets to game design to poker to writing and
to guitar. And finally, Cash App, the app I use to send money to friends for food,
drinks, and unfortunately lost bets. Please check out the sponsors in the description
to get a discount and to support this podcast. As a side note, let me say that Chris has been an
inspiration to me on a human level because he is so damn good as an engineer and leader of
engineers and yet he's able to stay humble, especially humble enough to hear the voices
of disagreement and to learn from them. He was supportive of me and this podcast from the early
days and for that, I'm forever grateful. To be honest, most of my life, no one really believed
that I would amount to much. So when another human being looks at me and makes me feel like I might
be someone special, it can be truly inspiring. That's a lesson for educators. The weird kid in
the corner with a dream is someone who might need your love and support in order for that dream to
flourish. If you enjoy this thing, subscribe on YouTube, review it with five stars on Apple
Podcasts, follow on Spotify, support on Patreon, or connect with me on Twitter at Lex Freedman.
And now here's my conversation with Chris Latner.
What are the strongest qualities of Steve Jobs, Elon Musk, and the great and powerful
Jeff Dean since you've gotten the chance to work with each?
You're starting with an easy question there. These are three very different people. I guess
you could do maybe a pairwise comparison between them instead of a group comparison.
So if you look at Steve Jobs and Elon, I worked a lot more with Elon than I did with Steve.
They have a lot of commonality. They're both visionary in their own way. They're both very
demanding in their own way. My sense is Steve is much more human factor focused, where Elon is
more technology focused. What does human factor mean? Steve's trying to build things that feel
good, that people love, that affect people's lives, how they live. He's looking into the future a
little bit in terms of what people want, where I think that Elon focuses more on learning how
exponentials work and predicting the development of those. Steve worked a lot of engineers. That was
one of the things that reading the biography and how can a designer essentially talk to engineers
and get their respect? I did not work very closely with Steve. I'm not an expert at all.
My sense is that he pushed people really hard, but then when he got an explanation that made sense to
him, then he would let go. He did actually have a lot of respect for engineering, but he also knew
when to push. When you can read people well, you can know when they're holding back and when you
can get a little bit more out of them. I think he was very good at that. If you compare the other
folks, Jeff Dean is an amazing guy. He's super smart, as are the other guys. Jeff is a really,
really nice guy, well-meaning. He's a classic Googler. He wants people to be happy. He combines
it with brilliance so he can pull people together in a really great way. He's definitely not a CEO
type. I don't think he would even want to be that. If he still programs. He definitely programs.
Jeff is an amazing engineer today, and that has never changed. It's really hard to compare Jeff
to either of those two. I think that Jeff leads through technology and building it himself and
then pulling people in and inspiring them. I think that that's one of the amazing things about Jeff.
But each of these people, with their pros and cons, all are really inspirational and have achieved
amazing things. I've been very fortunate to get to work with these guys.
For yourself, you've led large teams. You've done so many incredible, difficult technical
challenges. Is there something you've picked up from them about how to lead?
Yeah. I think leadership is really hard. It really depends on what you're looking for there.
I think you really need to know what you're talking about. Being grounded on the product,
on the technology, on the business, on the mission is really important.
Being, understanding what people are looking for, why they're there. One of the most amazing
things about Tesla is the unifying vision. People are there because they believe in
clean energy and electrification and all these kinds of things.
The other is to understand what really motivates people, how to get the best people,
how to build a plan that actually can be executed. There's so many different
aspects of leadership and it really depends on the time, the place, the problems.
There's a lot of issues that don't need to be solved. If you focus on the right things and
prioritize well, that can really help move things.
Two interesting things you mentioned. One is you really have to know what you're talking about.
You've worked on a lot of very challenging technical things.
I assume you were born technically savvy, but I assume that's not the case.
How did you develop technical expertise? Even at Google, you worked on, I don't know,
how many projects, but really challenging, very varied.
Compilers, TPUs, hardware, cloud stuff, a bunch of different things.
The thing that I've become more comfortable with as I've gained experience is being okay
with not knowing. A major part of leadership is actually it's not about having the right answer,
it's about getting the right answer. If you're working in a team of amazing people,
and many of these places, many of these companies all have amazing people,
it's the question of how do you get people together? How do you build trust?
How do you get people to open up? How do you get people to be vulnerable sometimes with an idea
that maybe isn't good enough, but it's the start of something beautiful? How do you
provide an environment where you're not just top-down, don't do the thing that I tell you to
do, but you're encouraging people to be part of the solution, and providing a safe space where
if you're not doing the right thing, they're willing to tell you about it?
So you're asking dumb questions?
Oh yeah, dumb questions are my specialty. So I've been in the hardware realm recently,
and I don't know much at all about how chips are designed. I know a lot about using them.
I know some of the principles and the arse technical level of this, but it turns out that
if you ask a lot of dumb questions, you get smarter really quick. And when you're surrounded by
people that want to teach and learn themselves, it can be a beautiful thing.
So let's talk about programming languages, if it's okay, at the highest absurd philosophical
level. Don't get romantic on me, Lex. I will forever get romantic and torture you. I apologize.
Why do programming languages even matter?
Okay, well, thank you very much. So you're saying why should you care about any one
programming language, or why do we care about programming computers?
No, why do we care about programming language design, creating effective programming languages,
choosing a, you know, one program languages versus another programming language,
why we keep struggling and improving through the evolution of these programming languages?
Sure, sure. Okay, so I mean, I think you have to come back to what are we trying to do here,
right? So we have these these beasts called computers that are very good at specific
kinds of things, and we think it's useful to have them do it for us, right? Now, you have this
question of how best to express that, because you have a human brain still that has an idea in its
head, and you want to achieve something. So, well, there's lots of ways of doing this. You can go
directly to the machine and speak assembly language, and then you can express directly what the
computer understands. That's fine. You can then have higher and higher and higher levels of abstraction
up until machine learning, and you're designing a neural net to do the work for you.
The question is, where, where along this way do you want to stop? And what benefits do you get out
of doing so? And so programming languages in general, you have C, you have Fortran, Java, and
Ada, Pascal, Swift, you have lots of different things. They'll have different tradeoffs, and
they're tackling different parts of the problems. Now, one of the things that most programming
languages do is they're trying to make it so that you have pretty basic things like portability
across different hardware. So you've got, I'm going to run on an Intel PC, I'm going to run on a
RISC-5 PC, I'm going to run on an ARM phone or something like that. Fine. I want to write one
program and have it portable, and this is something the assembly doesn't do. Now, when you start looking
at the space of programming languages, this is where I think it's fun, because programming languages
all have tradeoffs, and most people will walk up to them and they look at the surface level of syntax
and say, oh, I like curly braces, or I like tabs, or I like, you know, semicolons or not,
or whatever, right? Subject, fairly subjective, very shallow things. But programming languages,
when done right, can actually be very powerful. And the, the benefit they bring is expression.
Okay. And if you look at programming languages, there's really kind of two different levels
to them. One is the down-in-the-dirt nuts and bolts of how do you get the computer to be efficient,
stuff like that, how they work, type systems, compiler stuff, things like that. The other is
the UI. And the UI for programming language is really a design problem, and a lot of people don't
think about it that way. And the UI, you mean all that stuff with the braces and... Yeah, all that
stuff's the UI, and what it is, and UI means user interface. And so what, what's really going on is
it's the interface between the guts and the human. And humans are hard, right? Humans have
feelings, they have things they like, they have things they don't like. And a lot of people
treat programming languages as though humans are just kind of abstract creatures that cannot be
predicted. But it turns out that actually there are, there is better and worse. Like, people can
tell when a program language is good or when it was an accident, right? And one of the things
with Swift in particular is that a tremendous amount of time by a tremendous number of people
has been put into really polishing and making it feel good. But it also has really good nuts and
bolts underneath it. You said that Swift makes a lot of people feel good. How do you get to that
point? So how do you predict that, you know, tens of thousands, hundreds of thousands of people
are going to enjoy using this, the user experience of this programming language? Well, you can,
you can look at it in terms of better and worse, right? So if you have to write lots of boiler
plate or something like that, you will feel unproductive. And so that's a bad thing. You can
look at it in terms of safety. If like C, for example, is what's called a memory unsafe language.
And so you get dangling pointers, and you get all these kinds of bugs that then you have spent
tons of time debugging, it's a real pain in the butt. And you feel unproductive. And so by
subtracting these things from the experience, you get, you know, happier people. But again,
keep interrupting. I'm sorry. It's so hard to deal with.
If you look at the people, people that are most productive on Stack Overflow,
they are, they have a set of priorities that may not always correlate perfectly with the
experience of the majority of users. You know, if you look at the most upvoted, quote unquote,
correct answer on Stack Overflow is usually really sort of prioritizes like safe code,
proper code, stable code, you know, that kind of stuff, as opposed to like, if I want to use
go to statements in my basic, right, I want to use go to state, like what if 99% of people want
to use go to statements are used completely improper, you know, unsafe syntax.
I don't think that people actually like if you boil it down, you get below the surface level,
people don't actually care about go tos or if statements or things like this, they care about
achieving a goal. Yeah. Right. So the real question is, I want to set up a web server,
and I want to do a thing, whatever, like how, how quickly can I achieve that? Right. And so the
from programming language perspective, there's really two things that matter there. One is
what libraries exist? And then how quickly can you put it together? And what are the tools around
that look like? Right. And, and when you want to build a library that's missing, what do you do?
Okay. Now, this is where you see huge divergence in the force between worlds. Okay. And so you
look at Python, for example, Python is really good at assembling things, but it's not so great
at building all the libraries. And so you get because of performance reasons, other things like
this, as you get Python layered on top of C, for example, and that means that doing certain
kinds of things, well, it doesn't really make sense to do in Python. Instead, you do it in C,
and then you wrap it and then you have, you're living in two worlds and two worlds never is
really great because tooling and the debugger doesn't work right and like all these kinds of things.
Can you clarify a little bit what, what do you mean by Python is not good at building libraries,
meaning it doesn't make it conducive? Certain kinds of libraries. No, but it's just the actual
meaning of the sentence. Yeah. Meaning like it's not conducive to developers to come in and add
libraries, or it's, it's, or the language, or is it the, the duality of the, it's a dance between
Python and C and... Well, so Python's amazing. Python's a great language. I do not mean to say
that Python is bad for libraries. What I meant to say is, they're Python, they're libraries that
Python's really good at, that you can write in Python. But there are other things like if you
want to build a machine learning framework, you're not going to build a machine learning
framework in Python because of performance, for example, or you want GPU acceleration or
things like this. Instead, what you do is you write a bunch of C or C++ code or something
like that, and then you talk to it from Python. Right. And so this is because of decisions that
were made in the Python design and, and those decisions have other counterbalancing forces.
But, but the trick when you start looking at this from a programming language perspective,
you sort of say, okay, cool, how do I build this catalog of libraries that are really powerful?
And how do I make it so that then they can be assembled into ways that feel good and they
generally work the first time? Because when you're talking about building a thing, you have to
include the debugging, the fixing, the turnaround cycle, the development cycle, all that kind of
stuff in, in, into the process of building the thing. It's not just about pounding out the code.
And so this is where things like, you know, catching bugs at compile time is valuable,
for example. But if you dive into the details in this, Swift, for example, has certain things
like value semantics, which is this fancy way of saying that when you treat a treat a variable
like a value, it acts like a mathematical object would. Okay, so in you have used PyTorch a little
bit. In PyTorch, you have tensors, tensors are any n dimensional grid of numbers. Very simple,
you can do plus and other operators on them. It's all totally fine. But why do you need to clone
a tensor sometimes? Have you ever run into that? Yeah. Okay. And so why is that? Why do you need
to clone a tensor? It's the usual object thing that's in Python. So in Python, and just like with
Java and many other languages, this isn't unique to Python. In Python, it has a thing called
reference semantics, which is the nerdy way of explaining this. And what that means is you
actually have a pointer do a thing instead of the thing. Okay. Now, this is due to a bunch of
implementation details that you don't want to go into. But in Swift, you have this thing called
value semantics. And so when you have a tensor in Swift, it is a value. If you copy it, it looks
like you have a unique copy. And if you go change one of those copies, then it doesn't update the
other one, because you just made a copy of this thing. Right. So that's like highly error prone.
In at least computer science math centric disciplines about Python, that like the
the thing you would expect to behave like math, like math, it doesn't behave like math. And in
fact, quietly, it doesn't behave like math and then can ruin the entirety of your math. Exactly.
Well, and then it puts you in debugging land again. Yeah. Right. Now, now you just want to get
something done. And you're like, wait a second, where do I need, where do I need to put clone?
And what level of the stack, which is very complicated, which I thought I was using somebody's
library. And now I need to understand it to know where to clone a thing. Right. And hard to debug,
by the way. Exactly. Right. And so this is where programming languages really matter. Right. And
so in Swift, having value semantics, so that both you get the benefit of math, working like math,
right. But also the efficiency that comes with certain advantages there,
certain implementation details that really benefit you as a programmer. Right. So
how do you know that a thing should be treated like value? Yeah. So Swift has a pretty strong
culture and good language support for defining values. And so if you have an array, so tensors
are one example that the machine learning folks are very used to. Just think about arrays, same
thing, where you have an array, you put, you create an array, you put two or three or four
things into it, and then you pass it off to another function. What happens if that function
adds some more things to it? Well, you'll see it on the side that you pass it in. Right. This is
called reference semantics. Now, what if you pass an array off to a function? It scrolls it away in
some dictionary or some other data structure somewhere. Right. Well, it thought that you just
handed it that array. Then you return back and that reference to that array still exists in the
caller. And they go and put more stuff in it. Right. The person you handed it off to may have
thought they had the only reference to that. And so they didn't know that this was going to change
underneath the covers. And so this is where you end up having to do clone. So like, I was past a
thing, I'm not sure if I have the only version of it. So now I have to clone it. So what value
semantics does is it allows you to say, hey, I have a, so in Swift, it defaults to value semantics.
Also defaults to value semantics. And then, because most things should be changed, then it makes sense
for that to be the default. And one of the important things about that is that arrays and
dictionaries and all these other collections that are aggregations of other things also have
value semantics. And so when you pass this around to different parts of your program, you don't have
to do these defensive copies. And so this is, this is great for two sides, right? It's great
because you define away the bug, which is a big deal for productivity than the number one thing
most people care about. But it's also good for performance. Because when you're doing a clone,
so you pass the array down to the thing, it was like, I don't know if anybody else has it.
I have to clone it. Well, you just did a copy of a bunch of data. It could be big.
And then it could be that the thing that called you is not keeping track of the old thing. So
you just made a copy of it. And you may not have had to. And so the way the value semantics work
is in Swift is it uses a thing called copy on write, which means that you get, you get the
benefit of safety and performance. And it has another special trick. Because if you think
certain languages like Java, for example, they have immutable strings. And so what they're trying
to do is they provide value semantics by having pure immutability. Functional languages have pure
immutability in lots of different places. And this provides a much safer model and provides
value semantics. The problem with this is if you have immutability, everything is expensive.
Everything requires a copy. For example, in Java, if you have a string x and a string y,
you append them together, we have to allocate a new string to hold x, y.
Oh, if they're immutable.
Strings in Java are immutable. And if there's there's optimizations for short ones,
and it's complicated, but but generally think about them as a separate allocation. And so when
you append them together, you have to go allocate a third thing, because somebody might have a
point or two, either of the other ones, right? And you can't go change them. So you have to go
allocate a third thing. Because of the beauty of how the Swift value semantics system works out,
if you have a string and Swift, you say, hey, put in x, right? And they say, append on y, z, w,
it knows that there's only one reference to that. And so can do an in place update.
And so you're not allocating tons of stuff on the side, you're not, you don't have all these
problems. When you pass it off, you can know you have the only reference. If you pass it off to
multiple different people, but nobody changes it, they can all share the same thing. So you get a
lot of the benefit of purely immutable design. And so you get a really nice sweet spot that I
haven't seen in other languages. Yeah, that's interesting. Like, I thought I thought there
was going to be a philosophical like narrative here that you're going to have to pay a cost for it.
Because it sounds like I think value semantics is beneficial for easing of debugging, or
minimizing the risk of errors, like bringing the errors closer to the source,
bringing the symptom of the error closer to the source of the error, however you say that.
But you're saying there's not a performance cost either, if you implement correctly.
Well, so there's tradeoffs with everything. And so if you are doing very low level stuff,
then sometimes you can notice cost. But then what you're doing is you're saying, what is the right
default. So coming back to user interface, when you talk about programming languages,
one of the major things that Swift does that makes people love it, that is not obvious when it comes
to designing a language is this UI principle of progressive disclosure of complexity. So Swift,
like many languages, is very powerful. The question is, when do you have to learn the power as a user?
So Swift like Python allows you to start with like print hello world,
right, certain other languages, start with like public static void main class,
like all the ceremony, right. And so you go to teach, you teach a new person, hey, welcome,
welcome to this new thing. Let's talk about public access control classes, wait, what's that,
string system dot out, print land like packages, like, right. And so instead, if you take this,
and you say, hey, we need, you need, we need packages, you know, modules, we need, we need
powerful things like classes, we need data structures, we need like all these things.
The question is, how do you factor the complexity? And how do you make it so that
the normal case scenario is you're dealing with things that work the right way in the right way
and give you good performance right by default. But then as a power user, if you want to dive down
to it, you have full cc performance, full control over low level pointers, you can call malloc if
you want to call malloc. This is not recommended on the first page of every tutorial, but it's
actually really important when you want to get work done, right. And so being able to have that
is really the design in programming language design. And design is really, really hard. It's
something that I think a lot of people kind of outside of UI, again, a lot of people just think
is subjective, like there's nothing, you know, it's just like curly braces or whatever, it's just
like somebody's preference. But actually, good design is something that you can feel.
And how many people are involved with good design? So if we look at Swift, but look at historically,
I mean, this might touch like, there's almost like a Steve Jobs question too, like,
how much dictatorial decision making is required versus collaborative? And we'll talk about how
that can go wrong or right. But yeah, we'll Swift. So I can't speak to in general, all design
everywhere. So the way it works with Swift is that there's a core team. And so core team is
six or seven people ish something like that that is people that have been working with Swift since
very early days. And so by early days is not that long ago. Okay, yeah. So it's, it became public
in 2014. So it's been six years public now. But but so that's enough time that there's a story
arc there. Okay. And there's mistakes have been made that then get fixed and you learn something
and then you, you know, and so what the core team does is it provides continuity. And so you want
to have a, okay, well, there's a big hole that we want to fill. We know we want to fill it. So
don't do other things that invade that space until we fill the hole, right? There's a boulder
that's missing here. We want to, we will do that boulder, even though it's not today.
Keep, keep out of that space. And the whole team remembers of the remembers the myth of the boulder
that's there. Yeah, yeah, there's a general sense of what the future looks like in broad strokes
and a shared understanding of that, combined with a shared understanding of what has happened in the
past that worked out well and didn't work out well. The next level out is you have the what's
called the Swift Evolution community. And you've got in that case, hundreds of people that really
care passionately about the ways Swift evolves. And that's like an amazing thing to again,
the core team doesn't necessarily need to come up with all the good ideas. You got hundreds of
people out there that care about something, and they come up with really good ideas too.
And that provides this like tumbling rock tumbler for ideas. And so the, the evolution process is,
you know, a lot of people in a discourse forum, they're like hashing it out and trying to like
talk about, okay, well, should we go left or right? Or if we did this, what would be good?
And, you know, here you're talking about hundreds of people. So you're not going to get consensus,
necessarily. You're not obvious consensus. And so there's a proposal process that then allows
the core team and the community to work this out. And what the core team does is it aims to get
consensus out of the community and provide guardrails, but also provide long term,
make sure we're going the right direction kind of things.
So does that group represent like the how much people will love the user interface?
Like, do you think they're able to capture that?
Well, I mean, it's something we talk about a lot. It's something we care about.
How will we, how will we do that for debate? But I think that we've done pretty well so far.
Is the beginner in mind, like you said, the progressive disclosure?
Yeah, so we care a lot about a lot about that, a lot about power, a lot about efficiency, a lot
about there are many factors to good design. And you have to figure out a way to kind of
work your way through that. And so if you like think about
like a language I love is Lisp, probably still because I use Emacs, but I haven't done anything,
any serious working list, but it has a ridiculous amount of parentheses.
I've also, you know, with Java and C++, the braces,
you know, I, I like, I enjoyed the comfort of being between braces, you know, and then Python
is really excited to interrupt just like, and last thing to me as a design, if I was a language
designer, God forbid, is I would be very surprised that Python with no braces would nevertheless
somehow be comforting also. So like, I can see arguments for all of these.
But look at this, this is evidence that it's not about braces versus tabs.
Right. Exactly. You're good. It's a good point.
Right. So like, you know, there's, there's evidence that
but see, like it's one of the most argued about things.
Oh yeah, of course, just like tabs and spaces, which it doesn't, I mean,
there's one obvious right answer, but it doesn't, it doesn't actually matter.
What's that?
Come on for friends. Like, come on, what are you trying to do to me here?
People are going to, yeah, half the people are going to tune out. Yeah.
So, so these two, you're able to identify things that don't really matter for the experience.
Well, no, no, no, it's always a really hard, so the easy decisions are easy.
Right. I mean, you can, fine. Those are not the interesting ones.
The hard ones are the ones that are most interesting. Right.
The hard ones are the places where, hey, we want to do a thing.
Everybody agrees we should do it. There's one proposal on the table,
but it has all these bad things associated with it. Well,
okay, what are we going to do about that? Do we just take it?
Do we delay it? Do we say, hey, well, maybe there's this other feature
that if we do that first, this will work out better.
How does this, if we do this, are we paying ourselves into a corner?
Right. And so this is where, again, you're having that core team of people that
has some continuity and has perspective, has some of the historical understanding
is really valuable because you get, it's not just like one brain,
you get the power of multiple people coming together to make good decisions,
and then you get the best out of all these people, and you also can harness the community around it.
What about like the decision of whether like in Python having one type
or having, you know, strict typing?
Yeah, okay. Yeah, let's talk about this. So I like how you put that, by the way.
Like, so many people would say that Python doesn't have types.
Doesn't have types, yeah. But you're right.
Well, I've listened to you enough to where I'm a fan of yours,
and I've listened to way too many podcasts and videos of you talking about this.
Oh, yeah. So I would argue that Python has one type. And so,
so like when you import Python and Swift, which by the way works really well,
you have everything comes in as a Python object.
Now, here they're trade-offs because, you know, it depends on what you're optimizing for.
And Python is a super successful language for a really good reason,
because it has one type, you get duck typing for free and things like this.
But also, you're pushing, you're making it very easy to pound out code in one hand,
but you're also making it very easy to introduce complicated bugs, the F2D bug,
and you pass the string into something that expects an integer, and it doesn't immediately die,
it goes all the way down the stack trace, and you find yourself in the middle of some code
that you really didn't want to know anything about, and it blows up, and you're just saying,
well, what did I do wrong, right? And so, types are good and bad, and they have trade-offs,
are good for performance, and certain other things, depending on where you're coming from.
But it's all about trade-offs. And so this is what design is, right?
Design is about weighing trade-offs and trying to understand the ramifications of the things
that you're weighing, like types or not, or one type or many types.
But also, within many types, how powerful do you make that type system is another very complicated
question with lots of trade-offs. It's very interesting, by the way. But that's one dimension,
and there's a bunch of other dimensions. JIT-compiled versus static-compiled,
garbage-collected versus reference-counted versus manual memory management versus,
all these different trade-offs and how you balance them are what make the program language good.
Concurrency, so in all those things, I guess, when you're designing the language,
you also have to think of how that's going to get all compiled down to...
If you care about performance, yeah. Well, and go back to Lisp, right? So Lisp,
also I would say JavaScript is another example of a very simple language, right? And so one of the...
So I also love Lisp. I don't use it as much as maybe you do, or you did.
No, I think we're both everyone who loves Lisp. It's like, I don't know,
I love Frank Sinatra, but how often do I seriously listen to Frank Sinatra?
Sure. But you look at that, or you look at JavaScript, which is another very different,
but relatively simple language. And there are certain things that don't exist in the language,
but there is inherent complexity to the problems that we're trying to model.
And so what happens to the complexity? In the case of both of them, for example,
you say, well, what about large-scale software development? Okay. Well, you need something
like packages. Neither language has a language affordance for packages. And so what you get
is patterns. You get things like NPN. You get things like these ecosystems that get built around.
And I'm a believer that if you don't model at least the most important inherent complexity
in the language, then what ends up happening is that complexity gets pushed elsewhere.
And when it gets pushed elsewhere, sometimes that's great because often building things as
libraries is very flexible and very powerful and allows you to evolve and things like that.
But often it leads to a lot of unnecessary divergence in the force and fragmentation.
And when that happens, you just get kind of a mess. And so the question is, how do you balance that?
Don't put too much stuff in the language because that's really expensive and it makes things
complicated. But how do you model enough of the inherent complexity of the problem that
you provide the framework and the structure for people to think about?
So the key thing to think about with programming languages, and you think about what a programming
language is there for, is it's about making a human more productive. And so there's an old,
I think it's Steve Jobs quote about, it's a bicycle for the mind. You can definitely walk,
but you'll get there a lot faster if you can bicycle on your way.
And a programming language is a bicycle for the mind is basically, wow,
that's a really interesting way to think about it.
But by raising the level of abstraction now, you can fit more things in your head.
By being able to just directly leverage somebody's library,
you can now get something done quickly. In the case of Swift, SwiftUI is this new framework
that Apple has released recently for doing UI programming. And it has this declarative programming
model, which defines away entire classes of bugs. It builds on value semantics and many other nice
Swift things. And what this does is allows you just get way more done with way less code.
And now your productivity as a developer is much higher. And so that's really what
programming languages should be about is it's not about tabs versus spaces or curly braces or
whatever. It's about how productive do you make the person. And you can only see that when you
have libraries that were built with the right intention that the language was designed for.
And with Swift, I think we're still a little bit early. But SwiftUI and many other things
that are coming out now are really showing that. And I think that they're opening people's eyes.
It's kind of interesting to think about like how that, you know, the knowledge of something,
of how good the bicycle is, how people learn about that. You know, so I've used C++. Now,
this is not going to be a trash talking session about C++, but you use C++ for a really long
I can go there if you want. I have the scars. I feel like I spent many years without realizing
like there's languages that could, for my particular life style, brain style, thinking
style, there's languages that could make me a lot more productive in the debugging stage,
in just the development stage, and thinking like the bicycle for the mind that could fit
more stuff into my... Python's a great example of that, right? I mean, a machine learning framework
in Python is a great example of that. It's just very high abstraction level. And so you can be
thinking about things on a like very high level algorithmic level, instead of thinking about,
okay, well, am I copying this tensor to a GPU or not? Right? It's not what you want to be thinking
about. And as I was telling you, I mean, I guess the question I had is, you know, how does a person
like me or general people discover more productive, you know, languages? Like how I was, as I've been
telling you offline, I've been looking for like a project to work on in Swift, so I can really
try it out. I mean, my intuition was like doing a Hello World is not going to get me there,
to get me to experience the power of language. You need a few weeks to change your metabolism.
Exactly. I think it's beautifully put. That's one of the problems with people with diets.
Like I'm actually currently to go in parallel, but in a small tangent is I've been recently
eating only meat. Okay. Okay. And okay. So most people are like, the thing that's horribly unhealthy
or whatever, you have like a million, whatever the science is, it just doesn't sound right.
Well, so back when I was in college, we did the Atkins diet. That was, that was a thing and
similar. And, but if you, you have to always give these things a chance. I mean, with dieting,
always not dieting, but just the things that you like. If I eat personally, if I eat meat,
just everything, I could be super focused or more focused than usual. I just feel great. I've been,
I've been running a lot of, you know, doing push-ups and posts and so on. And your Python
is similar in that sense for me. Where are you going with this? I mean, literally, I just,
I felt ahead like a stupid smile on my face when I first started using Python. I could
code up really quick things. Like I, like I would see the world. I'll be empowered to write a script
to, to, um, you know, to do some basic data processing, to rename files on my computer.
Yeah. Right. And like Perl didn't do that for me, uh, a little bit. Well, and, and again, like
none of these are about which, which is best or something like that, but there's definitely
better and worse here. But it clicks, right? Well, yeah. And if you, if you look at Perl,
for example, you get bogged down in, uh, scalers versus arrays versus hashes versus type globs and
like all that kind of stuff. And, and Python's like, yeah, let's not do this. Right. And some of
it's debugging. Like everyone has different priorities, but for me it's, can I create systems
for myself that empower me to debug quickly? Like I've always been a big fan, even just crewed
like asserts, like always, uh, stating things that should be true, uh, which in Python I found
in myself do more because of type, all these kinds of stuff. Well, you could think of types in a
program language as being kind of assert. Yeah. They could check to compile time. Right.
So how do you learn a new thing? Well, so this, or how do, how do people learn new things? Right.
This, this is hard. Uh, people don't like to change. People generally don't like change around
them either. And so, uh, we're all very slow to adapt and change. And usually there's a catalyst
that's required to, to force yourself over the, over, over this. So for learning a programming
language, it just really comes down to finding an excuse, like build a thing that's, that the
language is actually good for that the ecosystem's ready for. Um, and so, um, and so if you were to
write an iOS app, for example, that'd be the easy case. Obviously you would, you would use Swift
for that. Right. There are Android. So Swift runs on Android. Oh, does it? Oh yeah. Yeah. Swift runs
in lots of places. So, uh, okay. So Swift, Swift, Swift is built on top of LLVM. LLVM runs
everywhere. LLVM, for example, builds the Android kernel. Oh, okay. So yeah. Um, so they realize
this. Yeah. So Swift, Swift is very portable, runs on Windows. There's, it runs on lots of
different things. And, uh, Swift, sorry to interrupt that. Swift UI. And then there's a thing called
UIKit. Can I build an app with Swift? Uh, well, so that, that's the thing is the ecosystem is what
matters there. So Swift UI and UIKit are Apple technologies. Okay. Got it. And so they happen
to, like Swift UI happens to be written in Swift, but it's an Apple proprietary framework that, um,
Apple loves and wants to keep on its platform, which makes total sense. You go, go to Android and
you don't have that library. Yeah. Right. And so Android has a different ecosystem of things that
hasn't been built out and doesn't work as well with Swift. And so you can totally use Swift to do,
like arithmetic and things like this, but building a UI with Swift on Android is not,
not, not a, not a great example right now. So, so if I wanted to, uh, to learn Swift, what's the,
I mean, the one practical different version of that is, um, Swift for TensorFlow, for example.
And one of the inspiring things for me with both TensorFlow and PyTorch is how quickly the community
can like switch from different libraries. Yep. Like you could see some of the communities switching
to PyTorch now, but it could, it's very easy to see and then TensorFlow is really stepping up its
game. And then there's no reason why, I think the way it works is basically it has to be one GitHub
repo, like one paper steps up. It gets people excited. It gets people excited and they're like,
ah, I have to learn this at Swift for what, what's Swift again? And then they learn and they fall
along with it. I mean, that's what happened with PyTorch. There has to be a reason, a catalyst.
Yeah. And so, and, and there, I mean, people don't like change, but it turns out that once you've
worked with one or two programming languages, the, the basics are pretty similar. And so
one of the fun things about learning programming languages, even, even maybe less, but I don't
know if you agree with this, is that when you start doing that, you start learning new things
because you have a new way to do things and you're forced to do them and that forces you to
explore. And it puts you in learning mode. And when you get in learning mode, your mind kind of
opens a little bit and you can, you can see things in a new way, even when you go back to the old
place. Right. Yeah. So it would list with functional stuff. But I wish there was a kind of window.
Maybe you can tell me if there is, there you go. This is a question to ask what is the most beautiful
feature in a programming language. Before I ask, let me say like with Python, I remember I saw
list comprehensions. It was like, when I like really took it in. Yeah. I don't know. I just
loved it. It was like fun to do like, it was fun to do that kind of,
it was something about it to be able to filter through a list and to create a new list on a
single line was elegant. I could all get into my head and it just made me fall in love with the
language. So it's there. Let me ask you a question. Is there what to use the most beautiful feature
in a program languages that you've ever encountered in Swift, maybe, and then outside of Swift?
I think the thing that I like the most from a programming language. So I think the thing you
have to think about with the programming language, again, what is the goal? You're trying to get
people to get things done quickly. And so you need libraries, you need high quality libraries.
And then you need a user base around them that can assemble them and do cool things with them.
Right. And so to me, the question is what enables high quality libraries?
Yeah. Yeah. And there's a huge divide in the world between libraries who enable high quality
libraries versus the ones that put special stuff in the language. So programming languages that
enable high quality libraries. Got it. So what I mean by that is expressive libraries that then
feel like a natural integrated part of the language itself. So an example of this in Swift is that
int and float and also array and string, things like this, these are all part of the library.
Like int is not hard coded into Swift. And so what that means is that because int is just a library
thing defined in the standard library, along with strings and arrays and all the other things that
come with the standard library. Well, hopefully you do like int. But anything that any language
features that you needed to define int, you can also use in your own types. So if you wanted to
find a quaternion or something like this, right? Well, it doesn't come in the standard library.
There's a very special set of people that care a lot about this. But those people are also important.
It's not about classism, right? It's not about the people who care about instant floats are more
important than the people who care about quaternions. And so to me, the beautiful things about programming
languages is when you allow those communities to build high quality libraries that feel native,
that feel like they're built into the compiler without having to be.
What does it mean for the int to be part of not hard coded in? So what is an int?
Int is just an integer. In this case, it's like a 64-bit integer or something like this.
But so the 64-bit is hard coded or no?
No, none of that's hard coded. So int, if you go look at how it's implemented,
it's just a struct in Swift. And so it's a struct. And then how do you add two structs? Well,
you define plus. And so you can define plus on int. Well, you can define plus on your thing, too.
You can define int as an odd method or something like that on it. And so, yeah, you can add methods
on a thing. So you can define operators like how it behaves. That's used beautiful when there's
something about the language which enables others to create libraries which are not hacky.
Yeah, they feel native. And so one of the best examples of this is Lisp.
Because in Lisp, all the libraries are basically part of the language. You write
term rewrite systems and things like this. And so can you, as a counter example, provide
what makes it difficult to write a library that's native? Is it the Python C?
Well, so one example, I'll give you two examples. Java and C++, there's Java and C.
They both allow you to define your own types. But int is hard coded in the language.
Okay. Well, why? Well, in Java, for example, coming back to this whole reference semantic
value semantic thing, int gets passed around by value. But if you make a pair or something like
that, a complex number, it's a class in Java. And now it gets passed around by reference,
by pointer. And so now you lose value semantics. You lost math. Okay. Well, that's not great.
If you can do something with int, why can't I do it with my type?
Right. So that's the negative side of the thing I find beautiful is when you can solve that,
when you can have full expressivity where you as a user of the language have as much or almost
as much power as the people who implemented all the standard built-in stuff. Because what that
enables is that enables truly beautiful libraries. You know, it's kind of weird because I've gotten
used to that. That's one, I guess, other aspect of program language design. You have to think,
you know, the old first principles thinking, like, why are we doing it this way? By the way,
I mean, I remember because I was thinking about the Waller's operator and I'll ask you about it
later. But it hit me that like the equal sign for assignment, like why are we using the equal
sign? It's wrong. And that's not the only solution, right? So if you look at Pascal,
they use colon equals for assignment and equals for equality. And they use like less and greater
than instead of the not equal. Like there are other answers here. So but like, and yeah, like I
ask you all, but how do you then decide to break convention to say, you know what?
That everybody's doing it wrong. We're going to do it right. Yeah. So it's like an ROI,
like return on investment trade off, right? So if you do something weird, let's just say like
not like colon equal instead of equal for assignment, that would be weird with today's
aesthetic, right? And so you'd say, cool, this is theoretically better. But is it better in which
ways? Like, what do I get out of that? Do I define away class of bugs? Well, one of the class of
bugs that C has is that you can use like, you know, if x equals without equals equals fx equals y.
Yeah. Right. Well, turns out you can solve that problem in lots of ways. Clang, for example,
GCC, all these compilers will detect that as a as a likely bug, produce a warning.
Do they? Yeah, I feel like they didn't or clang doesn't GCC didn't. And it's like,
one of the important things about programming language design is like, you're literally
creating suffering in the world. Like, I feel like, I mean, one way to see it is the
bicycle for the mind, but the other way is to like, minimizing suffering.
Well, you have to decide if it's worth it, right? And so let's come back to that.
Okay. But, but if you if you look at this, and again, this is where there's a lot of detail
that goes into each of these things. Equal and C returns a value.
Yep. That's messed up. That allows you to say x equals y equals z, like that works in C.
Yeah. Is it messed up? You know, well, so that most people think it's messed up, I think it is
very by messed up. What I mean is it is very rarely used for good. And it's often used for bugs.
Yeah. Right. And so that's a good definition. You could use, you know, it's a in hindsight,
this was not such a great idea, right? Now, one of the things with Swift that is really powerful
and one of the reasons it's actually good versus it being full of good ideas is that
when we launched Swift 1, we announced that it was public, people could use it, people could
build apps, but it was going to change and break. Okay. When Swift 2 came out, we said,
hey, it's open source, and there's this open process which people can help evolve and direct
the language. So the community at large like Swift users can now help shape the language as it is.
And what happened is that part as part of that process is a lot of really bad mistakes got taken
out. So for example, Swift used to have the C style plus plus and minus minus operators.
Like what does it mean when you put it before versus after? Right? Well, that got cargo-culted
from C into Swift early on. What's cargo-culted? Cargo-culted means brought forward without really
considering it. Okay. This is maybe not the most PC term.
But I have to look it up in Urban Dictionary. Yeah. So it got pulled into C without,
or it got pulled into Swift without very good consideration. And we went through this process
and one of the first things got ripped out was plus plus and minus minus because they lead to
confusion. They have very little value over saying X plus equals one. And X plus equals one is way
more clear. And so when you're optimizing for teachability and clarity and bugs and this
multidimensional space that you're looking at, things like that really matter. And so being
first principles on where you're coming from and what you're trying to achieve and being anchored
on, the objective is really important. Well, let me ask you about the most sort of this podcast
isn't about information, it's about drama. So let me talk to you about some drama. So you mentioned
Pascal and colon equals, there's something that's called the walrus operator. Okay. And Python
Python 3.8 added the walrus operator. And the reason I think it's interesting,
it's not just because of the feature, it does, it's, it has the same kind of expression feature
you can mention to see that it returns the value of the assignment. And maybe you can comment on
that in general. But on the other side of it, it's also the thing that toppled the dictator.
It finally drove Guido to step down from the DFL, the toxicity of the community. So maybe
what do you think about the walrus operator in Python? Is there an equivalent
thing in Swift that really stress tested the community? And then on the flip side,
what do you think about Guido stepping down over it? Yeah, well, like if I look past the details
of the walrus operator, one of the things that makes it most polarizing is that it's syntactic
sugar. Okay, what do you mean by syntactic sugar? It means you can take something that already exists
in language and you can express it in a more concise way. So okay, I'm going to play devil's
advocate. So this is great. Is that objective or subjective statement? Like, can you can you argue
that basically anything is syntactic sugar or not? No, not everything is syntactic sugar. So for
example, the type system, like can you have classes versus versus, like, do you have types or not?
Right. So one type versus many types is not something that affects syntactic sugar. And so
if you say I want to have the ability to define types, I have to have all this like language
mechanics to define classes. And oh, now I have to have inheritance. And I have like, I have all
this stuff that's just making my language more complicated. That's not that's not about sugaring
it. Swift has the sugar. So like Swift has this thing called if let and it has various operators
are used to concisify specific use cases. So the problem with syntactic sugar, when you're talking
about, Hey, I have a thing that takes a lot to write and I have a new way to write it. You have
this like horrible trade off, which becomes almost completely subjective, which is how often does
this happen? And does it matter? And one of the things that is true about human psychology,
particularly when you're talking about introducing a new thing is that people over over estimate the
burden of learning something. And so it looks foreign when you haven't gotten used to it.
But if it was there from the beginning, of course, just part of Python, like unquestionably,
like this is this is just the thing I know. And it's not a new thing that you're worried about
learning is just part of part of the deal. Now with Guido, I don't know Guido well.
Yeah, have you passed cost much? Yeah, I've met him a couple of times, but I don't know Guido
well. But the sense that I got out of that whole dynamic was that he had put the not just the
decision maker weight on his shoulders, but it was so tied to his personal identity that
he took it personally. And he felt the need and he kind of put himself in the situation of being
the person instead of building a base of support around him. I mean, this is probably not quite
literally true. But by too much so there's too much too much concentrated on him, right? And so
and that can wear you down. Well, yeah, particularly because people then say Guido,
you're a horrible person, I hate this thing, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
and sure, it's like, you know, maybe 1% of the community that's doing that. But Python's got a
big community in 1% of millions of people is a lot of hate mail. And that just from human factor
will just wear on you. Well, to clarify, it looked from just what I saw in the messaging for the
let's not look at the million Python users, but at the Python core developers, it feels like the
majority, the big majority on a vote were opposed to it. Okay, I'm not that close to it. So this
okay, so the situation is like literally, yeah, I mean, the majority of the core developers are
against it. So I and they weren't, they weren't even like against it. It was there was a few
while they were against it, but the against it wasn't like, this is a bad idea. They were more
like, we don't see why this is a good idea. And what that results in is there's a stalling feeling
like you just slow things down. Now, from my perspective, that you could argue this. And I
think it's a very, it's very interesting if we look at politics today, and the way Congress works,
it's slowed down everything. It's a dampener. Yeah, it's a dampener. But like, that's a dangerous
thing too, because if it dampens things like, you know, well, dampening results, what are you
talking about? Like, it's a low pass filter. But if you need billions of dollars injected into the
economy or trillions of dollars, then suddenly stuff happens. Right. And so for sure. So you're
talking about I'm not I'm not defending our political situation just to be clear.
But you're talking about like a global pandemic. Well, I was hoping we could fix like the healthcare
system and the education. So like, you know, I'm not I'm not a politics person. I don't I don't
I don't know. When it comes to languages, the community is kind of right in terms of it's a
very high burden to add something to a language. So as soon as you add something, you have a
community of people building on it, and you can't remove it. Okay. And if there's a community of
people that feel really uncomfortable with it, then taking it slow, I think is is is an important
thing to do. And there's no rush, particularly with something that's 25 years old and is very
established. And, you know, it's not like coming coming into its own. What about features?
Well, so I think that the issue with with Guido is that maybe this is a case where he
realized it had outgrown him. And it went from being or the language, the language. So Python,
I mean, Guido is amazing. But but Python isn't about Guido anymore. It's about the users. And to
a certain extent, the users own it. And, you know, Python Guido spent years of his life,
a significant fraction of his career on Python. And from his perspective, I imagine he's like,
well, this is my thing, I should be able to do the thing I think is right. But you can also
understand the users where they feel like, you know, this is my thing, I use this like, and
and I don't know, it's a hard, it's a hard thing. But what if we could talk about leadership in this
because it's so interesting to me, I'm going to, I'm going to make, I'm going to work, hopefully
somebody makes it, if not, I'll make it a water supply shirt, because I think it represents to me,
maybe it's my Russian roots or something. You know, it's the burden of leadership, like,
I feel like to push back, I feel like progress can own like most difficult decisions, just like
you said, there'll be a lot of divisiveness over, especially in the passionate community.
It just feels like leaders need to take those risky decisions that that if you like,
listen, that with some non-zero probability, maybe even a high probability will be the wrong
decision. But they have to use their gut and make that decision.
This is like one of the things where you see amazing founders. The founders understand exactly
what's happened and how the company got there and are willing to say, we have been doing
Thing X the last 20 years. But today, we're going to do Thing Y. And they make a major pivot for
the whole company, the company lines up behind them, they move, and it's the right thing. But
then when the founder dies, the successor doesn't always feel that agency to be able to make those
kinds of decisions. Even though they're a CEO, they could theoretically do whatever. There's two
reasons for that, in my opinion, or in many cases, it's always different. But one of which is they
weren't there for all the decisions that were made. And so they don't know the principles
in which those decisions were made. And once the principles change, you should be obligated
to change what you're doing and change direction. And so if you don't know how you got to where
you are, it just seems like gospel. And you're not going to question it. You may not understand
that it really is the right thing to do. So you just may not see it.
That's so brilliant. I never thought of it that way. It's so much higher burden when as a leader
you step into a thing that's already worked for a long time.
Yeah. And if you change it and it doesn't work out, now you're the person who screwed it up.
People always second guess that. And the second thing is that even if you decide to make a change,
even if you're theoretically in charge, you're just a person that thinks they're in charge.
Meanwhile, you have to motivate the troops. You have to explain it to them in terms of
understanding. You have to get them to buy into and believe in it because if they don't,
then they're not going to be able to make the turn even if you tell them their bonuses are
going to be curtailed. They're just not going to buy into it. And so there's only so much power you
have as a leader and you have to understand what those limitations are. You've been a BDFL of some
stuff. You're very heavy on the B, the benevolent dictated for life. I guess LVM. So I still lead
the LVM world. So then on Swift, you said that there's a group of people.
So if you contrast Python with Swift, one of the reasons... So everybody on the core team takes
the role really seriously. And I think we all really care about where Swift goes. But you're
almost delegating the final decision-making to the wisdom of the group. And so it doesn't become
personal. And also when you're talking with the community, so yeah, some people are very annoyed
at certain decisions that get made. There's a certain faith in the process because it's a very
transparent process. And when a decision gets made, a full rationale is provided, things like this.
These are almost defense mechanisms to help both guide future discussions and provide case lock.
And like Supreme Court does about this decision was made for this reason. And here's the rationale
and what we want to see more of or less of. But it's also a way to provide a defense mechanism
so that when somebody's griping about it, they're not saying that person did the wrong thing.
They're saying, well, this thing sucks. And later they move on and they get over it.
Yeah, the analogy is Supreme Court, I think, is really good. But then, okay, not to get
personal on the Swift team, but is there... It just seems like it's impossible for division
not to emerge. Well, each of the humans on the Swift core team, for example, are different
and the membership of the Swift core team changes slowly over time, which is, I think, a healthy
thing. And so each of these different humans have different opinions. Trust me, it's not a
singular consciousness by any stretch of the imagination. You've got three major organizations,
including Apple, Google and Sci-Fi, all working together. And it's a small group of people,
but you need high trust. Again, it comes back to the principles of what you're trying to achieve
and understanding what you're optimizing for. And I think that starting with strong principles
and working towards decisions is always a good way to both make wise decisions in general,
but then be able to communicate them to people so that they can buy into them. And that is hard.
And so you mentioned LVM. LVM is going to be 20 years old this December. So it's showing its own
age. Do you have a dragon cake plan? No, I should definitely do that. If we can have a pandemic
cake, everybody gets a slice of cake and it gets sent through email. But LVM has had tons of its
own challenges over time too. And one of the challenges that the LVM community has, in my
opinion, is that it has a whole bunch of people that have been working on LVM for 10 years.
Because this happens somehow. And LVM has always been one way, but it needs to be a different way.
And they've worked on it for like 10 years. It's a long time to work on something. And
you suddenly can't see the faults in the thing that you're working on. And LVM has lots of problems
and we need to address them and we need to make it better. And if we don't make it better, then
somebody else will come up with a better idea. And so it's just kind of of that age where the
community is in danger of getting too calcified. And so I'm happy to see new projects joining
and new things mixing it up. Fortran is now a new thing in the LVM community, which is hilarious
and good. I've been trying to find, on a little tangent, find people who program in Cobalt or
Fortran, Fortran especially, to talk to. They're hard to find. Yeah, look to the scientific community.
They still use Fortran quite a bit. Well, interesting thing you kind of mentioned
with LVM or just in general, that if something evolves, you're not able to see the faults.
So do you fall in love with the thing over time or do you start hating everything about the thing
over time? Well, so my personal folly is that I see maybe not all, but many of the faults
and they grate on me and I don't have time to go fix them. Yeah. And they get magnified over time.
Well, and they may not get magnified, but they never get fixed. And it's like sand underneath,
you know, it's just like grating against you and it's like sand underneath your fingernails
or something. It's just like, you know, it's there, you can't get rid of it. And so the problem is
that if other people don't see it, right, nobody ever get like, I can't go, I don't have time to
go write the code and fix it anymore. But then people are resistant to change. And so you say,
hey, we should go fix this thing. Like, oh, yeah, that sounds risky. Well, is it the right thing
or not? Are the challenges the group dynamics or is it also just technical? I mean, some of these
features like, yeah, I think as an observer is almost like a fan in the, you know, as a spectator
of the whole thing. I don't often think about, you know, some things might actually be technically
difficult to implement. An example of this is we built this new compiler framework called MLR.
Yes, MLR is this a whole new framework. It's not many people think it's about machine learning.
The ML stands for multi level because compiler people can't name things very well, I guess.
Can we dig into what MLIR is? Yeah, so when you look at compilers compilers have historically
been solutions for a given space. So LLVM is a it's really good for dealing with CPUs,
let's just say, at a high level, you look at Java. Java has a JVM. The JVM is very good for
garbage collected languages that need dynamic compilation, and it's very optimized for specific
space. And so hotspot is one of the compilers that gets used in that space. And that compiler's really
good at that kind of stuff. Usually, when you build these domain specific compilers,
you end up building whole thing from scratch for each domain.
What's a domain? So what's the scope of a domain?
Well, so here I would say like, if you look at Swift, there's several different parts to the
Swift compiler, one of which is covered by the LLVM part of it. There's also a high level
piece that's specific to Swift. And there's a huge amount of redundancy between those two
different infrastructures and a lot of re implemented stuff that is similar but different.
What is LLVM defined? LLVM is effectively an infrastructure. So you can mix and match it in
different ways. It's built out of libraries. You can use it for different things. But it's
really good at CPUs and GPUs. CPUs and like the tip of the iceberg on GPUs. It's not really great
at GPUs. Okay. But it turns out languages that then use it to talk to CPUs. Got it. And so it turns
out there's a lot of hardware out there that is custom accelerators. So machine learning, for example,
there are a lot of matrix multiply accelerators and things like this. There's a whole world of
hardware synthesis. So we're using MLIR to build circuits. Okay. And so you're compiling for a
domain of transistors. And so what MLIR does is it provides a tremendous amount of compiler
infrastructure that allows you to build these domain specific compilers in a much faster way
and have the result be good. If we're thinking about the future, now we're talking about like
ASICs. So anything. Yeah, yeah. So if we project into the future, it's very possible that the number
of these kinds of ASICs, very specific infrastructure thing, the architecture things,
like multiplies exponentially. I hope so. So that's MLIR. So what MLIR does is it allows you to build
these compilers very efficiently. Now, one of the things that coming back to the LVM thing,
and then we'll go to hardware, is LVM is a specific compiler for specific domain.
MLIR is now this very general, very flexible thing that can solve lots of different kinds of
problems. So LVM is a subset of what MLIR does. So MLIR is, I mean, it's an ambitious project then.
Yeah, it's a very ambitious project. Yeah. And so to make it even more confusing, MLIR has joined
the LVM umbrella project. So it's part of the LVM family. But where this comes full circle is now
folks that work on the LVM part, the classic part that's 20 years old, aren't aware of all the cool
new things that have been done and the new thing that MLIR was built by me and many other people
that knew a lot about LVM. And so we fixed a lot of the mistakes that lived in LVM.
I mean, we have this community dynamic where it's like, well, there's this new thing, but it's not
familiar. Nobody knows it. It feels like it's new. And so let's not trust it. And so it's just really
interesting to see the cultural social dynamic that comes out of that. And, you know, I think it's
super healthy because we're seeing the ideas percolate and we're seeing the technology diffusion
happen as people get more comfortable with it. They start to understand things in their own terms.
And this just gets to the it takes a while for ideas to propagate, even though they may be very
different than what people are used to. Maybe let's talk about that a little bit, the world of
Asics. And yeah, well, actually, you're, you're, you have a new role at SciFive. What's that place
about? What is the vision for their vision for, I would say, the future of computer?
Yeah. So I lead the engineering and product teams at SciFive. SciFive is a company who's
was founded with this architecture called Risk Five. Risk Five is a new instruction set.
Instruction sets are the things inside of your computer that tell it how to run things.
X86 from Intel and ARM from the ARM company and things like this or other instruction sets.
I've talked to, sorry to interrupt, I talked to Dave Patterson, who's super excited about
Risk Five. Dave is awesome. He's brilliant. Yeah. The Risk Five is distinguished by not being
proprietary. And so X86 can only be made by Intel and AMD. ARM can only be made by ARM. They
sell licenses to build ARM chips to other companies, things like this. MIPS is another
instruction set that is owned by the MIPS company, now Wave, and then it gets licensed out, things
like that. And so Risk Five is an open standard that anybody can build chips for. And so SciFive
was founded by three of the founders of Risk Five that designed and built it in Berkeley,
working with Dave. And so that was the genesis of the company. SciFive today has some of the
world's best Risk Five cores and we're selling them and that's really great. They're going to
tons of products. It's very exciting. So they're taking this thing that's open source and just
being trying to be or are the best in the world at building these things. Yeah. So here it's
the specifications open source. It's like saying TCPIP is an open standard or C is an open standard.
But then you have to build an implementation of the standard. And so SciFive, on the one hand,
pushes forward and defined and pushes forward the standard. On the other hand, we have implementations
that are best in class for different points in the space, depending on if you want a really tiny
CPU or if you want a really big beefy one that is faster, but it uses more area and things like
this. What about the actual manufacturer? So where does that all fit? I'm going to ask a bunch
of dumb questions. That's okay. This is how we learn, right? And so the way this works is that
there's generally a separation of the people who design the circuits and then the people who
manufacture them. And so you'll hear about fabs like TSMC and Samsung and things like this that
actually produce the chips, but they take a design coming in and that design specifies how
the, you know, you turn code for the chip into little rectangles that then use photo lithography
to make mask sets and then burn transistors onto a chip or onto silicon. And we're talking about
mass manufacturing. Yeah, they're talking about making hundreds of millions of parts and things
like that. And so the fab handles the volume production, things like that. But when you look
at this problem, the interesting thing about the space when you look at it is that these,
the steps that you go from designing a chip and writing the quote unquote code for it and things
like barrel log and languages like that down to what you hand off to the fab is a really well
studied really old problem. Okay. Tons of people have worked on it. Lots of smart people have built
systems and tools. These tools then have generally gone through acquisitions. And so they've ended
up at three different major companies that build and sell these tools. They're called EDA tools
like for electronic design automation. The problem with this is you have huge amounts of
fragmentation. You have loose standards. And the tools don't really work together. So you have
tons of duct tape, and you have tons of lost productivity. Now, these are, these are tools
for design. So the risk five is a instruction. Like what is risk five? Like how deep does it go?
How much does it touch the hardware? How much does it define how much of the hardware is?
Yeah. So risk five is all about given a CPU. So the processor and your computer,
how does the compiler like Swift compiler, the C compiler, things like this, how does it make it
work? So it's what is the assembly code? And so you write risk five assembly instead of XA6 assembly,
for example. But it's a set of instructions as opposed to instructions. What do you say it tells
you how the compiler works? Sorry, it's what the compiler talks to. Okay. And then the tooling you
mentioned that the disparate tools are for what? For when you're building a specific chip. So risk
five in hardware, in hardware. Yeah. So risk five, you can buy risk five core from sci five and say,
Hey, I want to have a certain number of run a certain number of gigahertz. I want it to be this
big. I want to be have these features. I want have like I want floating point or not, for example.
And then what you get is you get a description of a CPU with those characteristics.
Now, if you want to make a chip, you want to build like an iPhone chip or something like that,
right? You have to take both the CPU, but then you have to talk to memory. You have to have
timers, IOs, a GPU, other components. And so you need to pull all those things together into
what's called an ASIC, an application specific in a grade circuit. So custom chip. And then
you take that design, and then you have to transform it into something that the fabs,
like TSMC, for example, know how to take to production. Got it. So but yeah. And so that
process, I will, I can't help but see it as is a big compiler. It's a whole bunch of compilers
written without thinking about it through that lens. Isn't the universe a compiler?
Yeah. Compilers do two things. They represent things and transform them.
Yeah. And so there's a lot of things that end up being compilers. But this is a space where
we're talking about design and usability. And the way you think about things, the way
things compose correctly, it matters a lot. And so Sci-Fi is investing a lot into that space.
And we think that there's a lot of benefit that can be made by allowing people to design
chips faster, get them to market quicker and scale out. Because at the alleged end of Moore's
Law, you've got this problem of you're not getting free performance just by waiting another year
for a faster CPU. And so you have to find performance in other ways. And one of the
ways to do that is with custom accelerators and other things in hardware.
And so we'll talk a little more about ASICs. But do you see that a lot of people,
a lot of companies will try to have a different sets of requirements that this whole process
to go for. So almost different car companies might use different and different PC manufacturers.
Is risk five in this whole process, is it potentially the future of all computing devices?
Yeah, I think that, so if you look at risk five and step back from the silicon side of things,
risk five is an open standard. And one of the things that has happened over the course of decades,
if you look over the long arc of computing, somehow became decades old.
Yeah.
Because you have companies that come and go and you have instruction sets that come and go.
Like one example of this out of many is Sun with Spark.
Yeah.
Sun one way. Spark still lives on it if you just do. But we have HP had this instruction set called
PA risk. So PA risk was its big server business and had tons of customers. They decided to move
to this architecture called itanium from Intel. Yeah, it didn't work out so well.
Yeah.
Right. And so you have this issue of you're making many billion dollar investments on
instruction sets that are owned by a company. And even companies as big as Intel don't always
execute as well as they could. They have their own issues.
HP for example, decided that it wasn't in their best interest to continue investing in the space
because it was very expensive. And so they make technology decisions or they make their
own business decisions. And this means that as a customer, what do you do?
You've sunk all this time, all this engineering, all this software work, all these,
you've built other products around them and now you're stuck.
Right. What risk five does is provide you more optionality in the space because if you buy
an implementation of risk five from sci-fi, and you should, they're the best ones.
But if something that happens to sci-fi in 20 years, right, well, great, you can turn around
and buy risk five core from somebody else. And there's an ecosystem of people that are all making
different risk five cores with different trade-offs, which means that if you have more than one
requirement, if you have a family of products, you can probably find something in the risk five
space that fits your needs. Whereas with, if you're talking about XA6, for example,
Intel's only going to bother to make certain classes of devices.
Right. I see. So maybe a weird question, but like if sci-fi is infinitely successful
in the next 20, 30 years, what does the world look like? So like, how does the world of computing
change? So too much diversity in hardware instruction sets, I think is bad. We have a
lot of people that are using lots of different instruction sets, particularly in the embedded,
the very tiny microcontroller space, the thing in your toaster, that are just weird and different
for historical reasons. And so the compilers and the tool chains and the languages on top of them,
aren't there. And so the developers for that software have to use really weird tools because
the ecosystem that supports is not big enough. So I expect that will change. People will have
better tools and better languages, better features everywhere that then can serve as many
different points in the space. And I think risk five will progressively eat more of the ecosystem
because it can scale up, it can scale down sideways, left, right. It's very flexible and
very well-considered and well-designed instruction set. I think when you look at sci-fi of tackling
silicon and how people build chips, which is a very different space, that's where you say,
I think we'll see a lot more custom chips. And that means that you get much more battery life,
you get better, better tuned solutions for your IoT thingy. You get people that move faster,
you get the ability to have faster time to market, for example.
So how many custom... So first of all, on the IoT side of things, do you see the number of smart
toasters increasing exponentially? And if you do, how much customization per toaster is there?
Do all toasters in the world run the same silicon, the same design? Or is it different companies
have different designs? How much customization is possible here?
Well, a lot of it comes down to cost. And so the way that chips work is you end up paying by the...
One of the factors is the size of the chip. And so what ends up happening just from an
economic perspective is there's only so many chips that get made in any year of a given design.
And so often what customers end up having to do is they end up having to pick up a chip that exists
that was built for somebody else so that they can then ship their product. And the reason for that
is they don't have the volume of the iPhone. They can't afford to build a custom chip. However,
what that means is they're now buying an off-the-shelf chip that isn't a perfect fit for their needs.
And so they're paying a lot of money for it because they're buying silicon that they're not using.
Well, if you now reduce the cost of designing the chip, now you get a lot more chips. And
the more you reduce it, the easier it is to design chips. The more the world keeps evolving,
and we get more AI accelerators, we get more other things, we get more standards to talk to,
we get 6G, right? You get changes in the world that you want to be able to talk to these different
things. There's more diversity in the cross product of features that people want. And that drives
differentiated chips in another direction. And so nobody really knows what the future looks like.
But I think that there's a lot of silicon in the future.
Speaking of the future, you said Moore's Law allegedly is dead. So do you agree with
Dave Patterson and many folks that Moore's Law is dead? Or do you agree with Jim Keller,
who's standing at the helm of the pirate ship, saying it's still alive?
It's still alive. Well, so I agree with what they're saying, and different people are interpreting
the animal's law in different ways. So Jim would say, there's another 1000X left in physics,
and we can continue to squeeze the stone and make it faster and smaller and smaller geometries and
all that kind of stuff. He's right. So Jim is absolutely right that there's a ton of progress
left. And we're not at the limit of physics yet. That's not really what Moore's Law is, though.
If you look at what Moore's Law is, is that it's a very simple evaluation of, okay, well,
you look at the cost per, I think it was cost per area and the most economic point in that space.
And if you go look at the now quite old paper that describes this, Moore's Law has a specific
economic aspect to it. And I think this is something that Dave and others often point out.
And so on a technicality, that's right. I look at it from, so I can acknowledge both of those
viewpoints. They're both right. They're both right. I'll give you a third wrong viewpoint
that may be right in its own way, which is single threaded performance doesn't improve
like it used to. And it used to be back when you got a, you know, a Pentium 66 or something. And
the year before, you had a Pentium 33. And now it's twice as fast. Right? Well, it was twice as
fast at doing exactly the same thing. Okay. Like literally the same program ran twice as fast.
You just wrote a check and waited a year, year and a half. Well, so that's what a lot of people
think about Moore's Law. And I think that is dead. And so what we're seeing instead is we're pushing,
we're pushing people to write software in different ways. And so we're pushing people to
write CUDA so they can get GPU compute and the thousands of cores on GPU. We're talking about
C programmers having to use P threads because they now have, you know, 100 threads or 50 cores
in a machine or something like that. You're now talking about machine learning accelerators that
are now domain specific. And when you look at these kinds of use cases, you can still get
performance. And Jim will come up with cool things that utilize the silicon in new ways for sure.
But you're also going to change the programming model. Right. And now when you start talking
about changing the programming model, that's when you come back to languages and things like this
too. Because often what you see is like you take the C programming language, right? The C programming
language is designed for CPUs. And so if you want to talk to GPU, now you're talking to its cousin,
CUDA. Okay. CUDA is a different thing with a different set of tools, a different world,
a different way of thinking. And we don't have one world that scales. And I think that we can
get there. We can have one world that scales in a much better way. On a small tangent, then I think
most programming languages are designed for CPUs, for a single core, even just in their spirit,
even if they allow for parallelization. So what does it look like for programming language
to have parallelization or massive parallelization as it's like first principle?
So the canonical example of this is the hardware design world. So Verilog, VHDL,
these kinds of languages, they're what's called a high-level synthesis language. This is the thing
people design chips in. And when you're designing a chip, it's kind of like a brain where you have
infinite parallelism. Like you've got, you're like laying down transistors. Transistors are always
running. And so you're not saying run this transistor, then this transistor, then this
transistor. It's like your brain, like your neurons are always just doing something. They're
not clocked. They're just doing their thing. And so when you design a chip or when you design a CPU,
when you design a GPU, when you design when you're laying down the transistors,
similarly, you're talking about, well, okay, well, how do these things communicate?
And so these languages exist. Verilog is a kind of mixed example of that.
Now, these languages are really great. Yeah, very low level. Yeah.
Yeah, they're very low level. And abstraction is necessary here. And there's different approaches
with that. And it's itself a very complicated world. But it's implicitly parallel. And so
having that as the domain that you program towards makes it so that by default, you get
parallel systems. If you look at CUDA, CUDA is a point halfway in the space where in CUDA,
when you write a CUDA kernel for your GPU, it feels like you're writing a scalar program. So
you're like, you have ifs, you have for loops, stuff like this, you're just writing normal,
normal code. But what happens outside of that in your driver is that it actually is running you on
like 1000 things at once. Right. And so it's, it's parallel, but it has pulled it out of the
programming model. And so now you as a programmer are working in a, in a simpler world, and it's
solved that for you. How do you take the language like Swift?
You know, if we think about GPUs, but also ASICs, maybe if we can dance back and forth
between hardware and software, is, you know, how do you design for these features to be able to
program, make it a first class citizen to be able to do like Swift for TensorFlow,
to be able to do machine learning on current hardware, but also future hardware like
TPUs and all kinds of ASICs that I'm sure will be popping up more and more.
Yeah. Well, so, so a lot of this comes down to this whole idea of having the nuts and bolts
underneath the covers that work really well. So you need, if you're talking to TPUs, you need,
you know, MLIR or XLA or one of these compilers that talks to TPUs to build on top of. Okay.
And if you're talking to circuits, you need to figure out how to lay down the transistors and
how to organize it and how to set up clocking and like all the domain problems that you get with
circuits. Then you have to decide how to explain it to a human. What is EY?
Right. And if, if you do it right, that's a library problem, not a language problem.
And that works if you have a library or a language which allows your library
to write things that feel native in the language by implementing libraries,
because then you can innovate in programming models without having to change your syntax again.
And like you have to invent new code formatting tools and like all the other things that languages
come with. And this, this gets really interesting. And so if you look at this space, the interesting
thing once you separate out syntax becomes what is that programming model? And so do you want the
CUDA style? I write one program and it runs many places. The, do you want the implicitly parallel
model? How do you reason about that? How do you give developers, you know, chip architects the,
the ability to express their intent? And that comes into this whole design question of,
how do you detect bugs quickly? So you don't have to tape out a chip to find out it's wrong,
ideally, right? How do you, and, and, you know, this is a spectrum. How do you make it so that
people feel productive? So their turnaround time is very quick. All these things are really hard
problems. And, and this world, I think that not a lot of effort has been put into that design
problem and thinking about the layering and other pieces. Well, you've, on the topic of concurrency,
you've written the Swift concurrency manifesto. I think it's, it's kind of interesting. Anything
that has the word manifesto in is very interesting. Can you summarize the key ideas of each of the
five parts you've written about? So what is a manifesto? Yes. How about we start there? So in
the Swift community, we have this problem, which is on the one hand, you want to have
relatively small proposals that you can kind of fit in your head. You can understand the details
at a very fine grain level that move the world forward. But then you also have these big arcs.
Okay. And often when you're working on something that is a big arc, but you're tackling it in
small pieces, you have this question of, how do I know I'm not doing a random walk? Where are we
going? Like, how does this add up? Furthermore, when you start that first, the first small step,
what terminology do you use? How do we think about it? What is better and worse in the space?
What are the principles? What are we trying to achieve? And so what a manifesto in the Swift
community does is it starts to say, Hey, well, let's step back from the details of everything.
And let's paint a broad picture to talk about how, what we're trying to achieve. Let's give
an example design point. Let's try to paint the big picture so that then we can zero in on the
individual steps and make sure that we're making good progress. And so the Swift concurrency
manifesto is something I wrote three years ago, it's been a while, maybe, maybe more, trying to
do that for, for Swift in concurrency. It starts with some fairly simple things like making the
observation that when you have multiple different computers or multiple different threads that are
communicating, it's best for them to be asynchronous. And so you need things to be able to run
separately and then communicate with each other. And this means a synchrony. And this means that
you need a way to modeling asynchronous communication. Many languages have features like
this. Async await is a popular one. And so that's what I think is very likely in Swift.
But as you start building this tower of abstractions, it's not just about how do you write this,
you then reach into the, how do you get memory safety? Because you want correctness, you want
debuggability and sanity for developers. And how do you get that memory safety into,
into the language? So if you take a language like Go or C or any of these languages, you get what's
called a race condition when two different threads or Go routines or whatever touch the same point
in memory, right? This is a huge like maddening problem to debug because it's not reproducible
generally. And so there's tools, there's a whole ecosystem of solutions that built up around this,
but it's, it's a huge problem when you're writing concurrent code. And so with Swift, this whole
value semantics thing is really powerful there because it turns out that math and copies actually
work even in concurrent worlds. And so you get a lot of safety just out of the box, but there are
also some hard problems and it talks about some of that. When you start building up to the next
level up and you start talking beyond memory safety, you have to talk about what is the programmer
model? How does a human think about this? So a developer that's trying to build a program,
think about this, and it proposes a really old model with a new spin called actors. Actors are
about saying, we have islands of single threadedness, logically. So you write something that feels
like it's one programming, one program running in a unit, and then it communicates asynchronously
with other other things. And so making that expressive and natural feel good be the first
thing you reach for and being safe by default is a big part of the design of that proposal.
When you start going beyond that, now you start to say, cool, well, these things that communicate
asynchronously, they don't have to share memory. Well, if they don't have to share memory and
they're sending messages to each other, why do they have to be in the same process?
These things should be able to be in different processes on your machine. And why just processes?
Well, why not different machines? And so now you have a very nice gradual transition towards
distributed programming. And of course, when you start talking about the big future,
the manifesto doesn't go into it, but accelerators are things you talk to asynchronously by sending
messages to them. And how do you program those? Well, that gets very interesting. That's not in
the proposal. And how much do you want to make that explicit, like the control of that whole
process explicit to the programmer? Yeah, good question. So when you're designing any of these
kinds of features or language features or even libraries, you have this really hard tradeoff
you have to make, which is how much is it magic or how much is it in the human's control? How much
can they predict and control it? What do you do when the default case is the wrong case?
And so when you're designing a system, I won't name names, but there are systems where
it's really easy to get started. And then you jump it. So let's pick like logo. So something like this.
So it's really easy to get started. It's really designed for teaching kids. But as you get into
it, you hit a ceiling. And then you can't go any higher. And then what do you do? Well, you have
to go switch to a different world and rewrite all your code. And this logo is a silly example here.
This exists in many other languages. With Python, you would say like concurrency, right? So Python
has the global interpreter lock. So threading is challenging in Python. And so if you start writing
a large scale application in Python, and then suddenly you need concurrency, you're kind of
stuck with the series of bad trade-offs, right? There's other ways to go where you say like
foist all the complexity on the user all at once, right? And that's also bad in a different way.
And so what I prefer is building a simple model that you can explain that then has an escape
hatch. So you get in, you have guardrails, you memory safety works like this in Swift where
you can start with, like by default, if you use all the standard things, it's memory safe,
you're not going to shoot your foot off. But if you want to get a C level pointer to something,
you can explicitly do that. But by default, there's guardrails.
There's guardrails. Okay. So, but like, you know,
whose job is it to figure out which part of the code is paralyzable?
So in the case of the proposal, it is the human's job.
So they decide how to architect their application. And then the runtime in the compiler is very
predictable. And so this, this is in contrast to, like, there's a long body of work,
including on Fortran, for auto paralyzing compilers. And this is an example of a bad thing in my,
so as a compiler person, I can rag on compiler people. Often compiler people will say,
cool, since I can't change the code, I'm going to write my compiler that then takes
this unmodified code and makes it go way faster on this machine. Okay. Application development.
And so it does pattern matching, it does like really deep analysis, compiler people are really
smart. And so they like want to like do something really clever and tricky. And you get like 10x
speed up by taking like an array of structures and turn it into a structure of arrays or something,
because it's so much better for memory. Like there's bodies, like tons of tricks.
They love optimization. Yeah, you love optimization. Everyone loves optimization.
Everyone loves it. Well, and it's this promise of build with my compiler and your thing goes fast.
Yeah. Right. But here's the problem. Lex, you write, you write a program,
you run it with my compiler, it goes fast, you're very happy. Wow, it's so much faster than the
other compiler. Then you go and you got a feature to your program or you refactor some code. And
suddenly you got a 10x loss in performance. Well, why? What just happened there? What just happened
there is you, the heuristic, the pattern matching the compiler or whatever analysis
it was doing just got defeated because you didn't inline a function or something, right?
As a user, you don't know, you don't want to know, that was the whole point,
you don't want to know how the compiler works. You don't want to know how the memory hierarchy
works. You don't want to know how it got paralyzed across all these things. You wanted
that abstract away from you. But then the magic is lost as soon as you did something and you fall
off a performance cliff. And now you're in this funny position where what do I do? I don't change
my code. I don't fix that bug. It costs 10x performance. Now what do I do? Well, this is the
problem with unpredictable performance. If you care about performance, predictability is a very
important thing. And so what the proposal does is it provides architectural patterns for being able
to lay out your code, gives you full control over that, makes it really simple so you can explain
it. And then if you want to scale out in different ways, you have full control over that.
So in your sense, the intuition is for compilers too hard to do automated parallelization.
Because the compilers do stuff automatically that's incredibly impressive for other things.
Right.
But for parallelization, we're not even close to there.
Well, it depends on the programming model. So there's many different kinds of compilers.
And so if you talk about like a C compiler or a Swift compiler or something like that where
you're writing imperative code, parallelizing that and reasoning about all the pointers and
stuff like that is a very difficult problem. Now, if you switch domains, so there's this
cool thing called machine learning, right? So machine learning nerds among other endearing
things like solving cat detectors and other things like that have done this amazing breakthrough
of producing a programming model, operations that you compose together that has raised the
levels of abstraction high enough that suddenly you can have auto parallelizing compilers.
You can write a model using TensorFlow and have it run on 1024 nodes of a TPU.
Yeah, that's true. I didn't even think about like, you know, because there's so much flexibility
in the design of architectures that ultimately boil down to a graph that's parallelizable for you,
parallelized for you. And if you think about it, that's pretty cool.
And you think about batching, for example, as a way of being able to exploit more parallelism.
That's a very simple thing that now is very powerful. That didn't come out of the programming
language, nerds, those people. That came out of people that are just looking to solve a problem
and use a few GPUs and organically developed by the community of people focusing on machine
learning as an incredibly powerful abstraction layer that enables the compiler people to go
and exploit that. And now you can drive supercomputers from Python. That's pretty cool.
That's amazing. So just to pause on that, because I'm not sufficiently low level,
I forget to admire the beauty and power of that. But maybe just to linger on it, like what
does it take to run in your network fast? Like how hard is that compilation?
It's really hard. So we just skipped, you said like, it's amazing that that's a thing.
But how hard is that of a thing?
It's hard. And I would say that not all of the systems are really great,
including the ones I helped build. So there's a lot of work left to be done there.
Is it the compiler nerds working on that? Or is it a whole new group of people?
Well, it's a full stack problem, including compiler people, including APIs, like Keras and
the module API and PyTorch and JAX. And there's a bunch of people pushing on all the different
parts of these things. Because when you look at it, it's both, how do I express the computation?
Do I stack up layers? Well, cool. Setting up a linear sequence of layers is great for the
simple case. But how do I do the hard case? How do I do reinforcement learning? Well,
now I need to integrate my application logic in this. Then it's the next level down of,
how do you represent that for the runtime? How do you get hardware abstraction?
And then you get to the next level down of saying, forget about abstraction,
how do I get the peak performance out of my TPU or my iPhone accelerator or whatever,
right? And all these different things. And so this is a layered problem with a lot of really
interesting design and work going on in the space. And a lot of really smart people working on it.
Machine learning is a very well-funded area of investment right now. And so
there's a lot of progress being made. So how much innovation is there on the
lower level, so closer to the ASIC? So redesigning the hardware or redesigning
concurrently compilers with that hardware? If you were to predict the biggest,
you know, the equivalent of Moore's law improvements in the inference and the training
of neural networks and just all of that, where is that going to come from, you think?
Sure. You get scalability, you have different things. And so you get Jim Keller shrinking
process technology, you get three nanometers instead of five or seven or 10 or 28 or whatever.
And so that marches forward and that provides improvements. You get architectural level
performance. And so the, you know, a TPU with a matrix multiply unit in a systolic array is
much more efficient than having a scaler core doing multiplies and ads and things like that.
You then get system level improvements. So how you talk to memory, how you talk across a cluster
of machines, how you scale out, how you have fast interconnects between machines, you then get system
level programming models. So now that you have all this hardware, how do you utilize it? You then
have algorithmic breakthroughs where you say, Hey, wow, cool. Instead of training in, you know,
resident 50 and a week, I'm now training it in, you know, 25 seconds. And it's a combination of,
you know, new, new optimizers and new, new, new just training regimens and different,
different approaches to train. And, and all of these things come together to, to push the world
forward. That was a beautiful exposition. But if you were to force to bet all your money on one of
these, would you? Why do we have to? Unfortunately, we have people working on all this. It's an
exciting time, right? So I mean, you know, open the eye, did this little paper showing the algorithmic
improvement you can get has been, you know, improving exponentially. I haven't quite seen
the same kind of analysis on other layers of the stack. I'm sure it's also improving significantly.
I just, it's a, it's a nice intuition builder. I mean, there's a reason why Moore's law,
that's the beauty of Moore's law is somebody writes a paper that makes a ridiculous prediction.
And it, you know, becomes reality in a sense. There's, there's something about these narratives
when you, when Chris Latner on a silly little podcast makes bets, all his money on a particular
thing, somehow it can have a ripple effect of actually becoming real. That's an interesting
aspect of it. Cause like, it might have been, you know, we focused with Moore's law, most of the
computing industry really, really focused on the hardware. I mean, software innovation, I don't
know how much software innovation there was in terms of
what Intel give a bill takes away.
Yeah. I mean, compilers improved significantly also.
Well, not, not really. So actually, I mean, some, I'm joking about how software's gotten slower
pretty much as fast as Harvard got better, at least through the nineties. There's another joke,
another law in compilers, which is called, I think it's called probestine's law, which is
compilers double the performance of any given code every 18 years.
So they move slowly.
Yeah. Well, so well, yeah, it's exponential also.
Yeah. You're making progress, but there again, it's not about the power of compilers is not
just about how do you make the same thing go faster? It's how do you unlock the new hardware?
A new chip came out. How do you utilize it? You say, oh, the programming model, how do we make
people more productive? How do we, how do we like have better error messages? Even such mundane
things like how do I generate a very specific error message about your code actually makes people
happy because then they know how to fix it, right? And it comes back to how do you help people get
their job done? Yeah. And yeah. And then in this world of exponentially increasing smart toasters,
how do you expand computing to all these kinds of devices? Do you see this world where just
everything's a computing surface? You see that possibility? Just everything's a computer?
Yeah, I don't see any reason that that couldn't be achieved. It turns out that
sand goes into glass and glass is pretty useful too. And, you know, like, why not?
Why not? So a very important question then if, if we're living in a simulation and the simulation
is running a computer, like, what was the architecture of that computer, do you think?
So you're saying is it a quantum system? Is it? Yeah, like this whole quantum
discussion, is it needed? Or can we run it on a, you know, with a risk five architecture,
a bunch of CPUs? I think it comes down to the right tool for the job. Okay. And so.
And what's the compiler? Yeah, exactly. That's, that's my question. Did I get that job?
Feed the universe compiler. And so there, as far as we know, quantum, quantum,
quantum systems are the bottom of the pile of turtles so far. Yeah. And so we don't know
efficient ways to implement quantum systems without using quantum computers.
Yeah. And that's totally outside of everything we've talked about quantum.
But who runs that quantum computer? Yeah. Right. So if we really are living in a simulation,
then is it bigger quantum computers? Is it different ones? Like, how does that work out?
How does that scale? Well, it's the same size. It's the same size. But then,
but then the thought of the simulation is that you don't have to run the whole thing that,
you know, we humans are cognitively very limited. Do you do check points?
Do you do check points? Yeah. And, and if we, the point at which we human, so you basically do
minimal amount of, what is it, the SWIFT does on right, copy on right. So you only,
yeah, you only adjust the simulation and parallel universe theories. Right. And so,
and so every time a decision is made, somebody opens the shorting in your box, then there's a fork.
And then this could happen. And then thank you for considering the possibility. But yeah,
so it may not require, you know, the entirety of the universe to simulate it. But it's
interesting to think about as we create this, this higher and higher fidelity systems. But
I do want to ask on the, on the quantum computer side, because everything we've talked about
with us, with your work with sci-fi, with everything with compilers,
none of that includes quantum computers. Right. That's true. So
if you ever thought about what a, you know, this whole serious engineering work,
how quantum computers looks like of compilers, of architectures, all of that kind of stuff.
So I've looked at it a little bit. I'd know almost nothing about it,
which means that at some point I will have to find an excuse to get involved, because that's
how it works. But do you think, do you think that's the thing to be, like, is, with your little
tingly senses of the timing of when to be involved? Is it not yet?
Well, so the thing I do really well is I jump into messy systems and figure out how to make them
figure out what the truth in the situation is, try to figure out what the unifying theory is,
how to, like, factor the complexity, how to find a beautiful answer to a problem that
has been well studied and lots of people have bashed their heads against it. I don't know that
quantum computers are mature enough and accessible enough to be figured out yet, right? And
the, I think the open question with quantum computers is, is there a useful problem that
gets solved with the quantum computer that makes it worth the economic cost of, like,
having one of these things and having legions of people that set it up? You go back to the 50s,
right? And there's the projections of the world will only need seven computers,
right? Well, and part of that was that people hadn't figured out what they're useful for.
What are the algorithms we want to run? What are the problems that get solved? And this comes back
to how do we make the world better, either economically or making somebody's life better,
or, like, solving a problem that wasn't solved before, things like this. And I think that just
we're a little bit too early in that development cycle because it's still, like, literally a science
project, not a negative connotation, right? It's literally a science project. And the progress
there's amazing. And so I don't know if it's 10 years away, if it's two years away, exactly where
that breakthrough happens. But you look at machine learning, it, we went through a few winters
before the AlexNet transition, and then suddenly had its breakout moment. And that was the catalyst
that then drove the talent flocking into it. That's what drove the economic applications
of it. That's what drove the technology to go faster because you now have more minds thrown
at the problem. This is what caused, like, a serious knee and deep learning and the algorithms
that we're using. And so I think that's what quantum needs to go through. And so right now,
it's in that formidable finding itself, getting the, like, literally the physics figured out.
And then it has to figure out the application that makes that useful.
I'm not skeptical that I think that will happen. I think it's just, you know, 10 years away,
something like that. I forgot to ask, what programming language do you think the simulation
is written in? Probably Lisp. So not Swift. Like, if you were to bet, I'll just leave it at that.
So, I mean, we've mentioned that you worked with all these companies, we've talked about all these
projects. It's kind of, if we just step back and zoom out about the way you did that work,
and we look at COVID times, this pandemic we're living through, that may, if I look at the way
Silicon Valley folks are talking about it, the way MIT is talking about it, this might last for a
long time, not just the virus, but the remote nature. The economic impact. Yeah, it's going to
be a mess. Do you think, what's your prediction? I mean, from sci-fi to Google, to just all the
places you worked in, just Silicon Valley, you're in the middle of it. What do you think is,
how is this whole place going to change? Yeah, so, I mean, I really can only speak to the tech
perspective. I am in that bubble. I think it's going to be really interesting because the, you
know, the zoom culture of being remote and on video chat all the time has really interesting
effects on people. So on the one hand, it's a great normalizer. It's a normalizer that I think
will help communities of people that have traditionally been underrepresented. Because
now you're taking, in some cases, a face off, because you don't have to have a camera going,
right? And so you can have conversations without physical appearance being part of the dynamic,
which is pretty powerful. You're taking remote employees that have already been remote and
you're saying you're now on the same level and footing as everybody else. Nobody gets whiteboards.
You're not going to be the one person that doesn't get to be participating in the whiteboard
conversation. And that's pretty powerful. You've got, you're forcing people to think
asynchronously in some cases, because it's hard to just, just get people physically together and
the bumping into each other forces people to find new ways to solve those problems. And I think
that that leads to more inclusive behavior, which is good. On the other hand, it's also, it just
sucks, right? And so the, the nature, the, the actual communication or it just sucks being
not in, with people like on a daily basis and collaborating with them.
Yeah, all of that. I mean, everything, this whole situation is terrible. What I meant primarily
was the, I think that most humans like working physically with humans. I think this is something
that not everybody, but many people are programmed to do. And I think that we get something out of
that that is very hard to express, at least for me. And so maybe this isn't true of everybody. But
and so the question to me is, you know, when you get through that time of adaptation,
right, you get out of March and April and you get into December and you get into next March,
if it's not changed, right? It's already terrifying. Well, you think about that and you
think about what is the nature of work? And how do, how do we adapt? And humans are very adaptable
species, right? We can, we can learn things. And when we're forced to, and there's a catalyst to
make that happen. And so what is it that comes out of this? And are we better or worse off?
Right? I think that, you know, you look at the Bay Area, housing prices are insane.
Well, why? Well, there's a high incentive to be physically located, because if you don't have
proximity, you end up paying for it and commute, right? And there's, there has been huge social
social pressure in terms of like, you will be there for the meeting, right? Or whatever scenario
it is. And I think that's gonna be way better. I think it's gonna be much more the norm to have
remote employees. And I think this is gonna be really great. Do you, do you have friends or do
you hear of people moving? Yeah, I know one family friend that moved. They moved back to Michigan and
you know, they were a family with three kids living in a small apartment and like, we're going insane.
Right? And they're in tech, husband works for Google. So first of all,
friends of mine have, are in the process of or are have already lost the business. The thing that
represents their passion, their dream, it could be small entrepreneur projects, but it could be large
businesses like people that run gyms, like restaurants, like tons of things. Yeah. So,
but also people like look at themselves in the mirror and ask the question of like,
what do I want to do in life? For some reason, they don't, they haven't done it until COVID.
Like, they really ask that question and that results often in moving or leaving the company
here with starting your business or transitioning to a different company. Do you think we're gonna
see that a lot? Well, I can't speak to that. I mean, we're definitely gonna see it at a higher
frequency than we did before. Just because I think what you're trying to say is there are
decisions that you make yourself and big life decisions that you make yourself. And like,
I'm gonna like quit my job and start a new thing. There's also decisions that get made for you.
Like, I got fired from my job. What am I going to do? Right? And that's not a decision that you
think about, but you're forced to act. Okay. And so I think that those you're forced to act kind
of moments where like, you know, global pandemic comes and wipes out the economy. And now your
business doesn't exist. I think that does lead to more reflection, right? Because you're less
anchored on what you have. And it's not a, what do I have to lose versus what do I have to gain,
AB comparison? It's more of a fresh slate. Cool. I could do anything now. Do I want to do the same
thing I was doing? Did that make me happy? Is this now time to go back to college and take a class
and learn new skill? Is this a time to spend time with family? If you can afford to do that,
is this time to like, you know, literally move into the parents, right? I mean, all these things
that were not normative before suddenly become, I think, very, the value system has changed. And
I think that's actually a good thing in the short term, at least, because it leads to, you know,
there's kind of been an over optimization along one, one set of priorities for the world. And
now maybe we'll get to a more balanced and more interesting world where people are doing different
things. I think it could be good. I think there could be more innovation that comes out of it,
for example. What do you think about all the social chaos in the middle of? It sucks.
Let me ask you, I hope, do you think it's all going to be okay?
Well, I think humanity will survive. From the next extension, we're not all going to kill,
yeah, well. Yeah, I don't think the virus is going to kill all the humans. I don't think all the
humans are going to kill all the humans. I think that's unlikely. But I look at it as
progress requires a catalyst, right? So you need a reason for people to be willing to do
things that are uncomfortable. I think that the US, at least, but I think the world in general,
is a pretty unoptimal place to live in for a lot of people. And I think that what we're
seeing right now is we're seeing a lot of unhappiness. And because of all the pressure,
because of all the badness in the world that's coming together, it's really kind of igniting
some of that debate that should have happened a long time ago, right? I mean, I think that
we'll see more progress. You're asking about offline, you're asking about politics and wouldn't
be great if politics moved faster because there's all these problems in the world and we can move it.
Well, people are intentionally conservative. And so if you're talking about conservative people,
particularly if they have heavy burdens on their shoulders because they represent
literally thousands of people, it makes sense to be conservative. But on the other hand,
when you need change, how do you get it? The global pandemic will probably lead to some change.
And it's not a directed plan, but I think that it leads to people asking really interesting
questions. And some of those questions should have been asked a long time ago.
Well, let me know if you've observed this as well. Something has bothered me
in the machine learning community. I'm guessing it might be prevalent in other places
is something that feels like in 2020, increased level of toxicity. Like people are just
quicker to pile on, they're just harsh on each other to mob, pick a person that screwed up
and make it a big thing. And is there something that we can...
Have you observed that in other places? Is there some way out of this?
I think there's an inherent thing in humanity that's kind of an us versus them thing,
which is that you want to succeed. And how do you succeed? Well, it's relative to somebody else.
And so what's happening, at least in some part, is that with the internet and with online communication,
the world's getting smaller. And so we're having some of the social ties of my town versus your
town's football team turn into much larger and yet shallower problems. And people don't have time,
the incentives, clickbait and all these things really feed into this machine. And I don't know
where that goes. Yeah, I mean, the reason I think about that, I mentioned to you this offline a
little bit, but I have a few difficult conversations scheduled, some of them political-related,
some of them within the community, difficult personalities that went through some stuff.
I mean, one of them I've talked before, I will talk again, is Yann LeCun. He got a little crap on
Twitter for talking about a particular paper and the bias within a data set. And then there's been
a huge in my view, and I'm only comfortable saying it, irrational, over exaggerated pile on
on his comments, because he made pretty basic comments about the fact that if there's bias in
the data, there's going to be bias in the results. So we should not have bias in the data. But people
piled on to him because he said he trivialized the problem of bias. It's a lot more than just
bias in the data. But yes, that's a very good point. That's not what he was saying. And the
response, the implied response that he's basically sexist and racist is something that completely
drives away the possibility of a nuanced discussion. One nice thing about a pocket-long form
conversation is you can talk it out, you can lay your reasoning out, and even if you're wrong,
you can still show that you're a good human being underneath it.
Your point about you can't have a productive discussion, well, how do you get to that point
where people can turn, they can learn, they can listen, they can think, they can engage versus
just being a shallow like, like, and then keep moving, right? And I don't think that
progress really comes from that, right? And I don't think that one should expect that. I think
that you'd see that as reinforcing individual circles and the us versus them thing. And I
think that's fairly divisive. Yeah, I think there's a big role in, like, the people that bother me
most on Twitter when I observe things. It's not the people who get very emotional, angry,
like, over the top. It's the people who, like, prop them up. It's all the, it's that I think what
should be the, we should teach each other is to be sort of empathetic. The thing that it's really
easy to forget, particularly on, like, Twitter or the internet or the email, is that sometimes
people just have a bad day, right? You have a bad day, or you're like, I've been in this situation
where it's like, between meetings, like, fire off a quick response in emails, because I want to, like,
help get something unblocked, phrase it really objectively wrong. I screwed up. And suddenly,
this is now something that sticks with people. And it's not because they're bad. It's not because
you're bad, just psychology of like, you said a thing, it sticks with you, you didn't mean it
that way. But it really impacted somebody because the way they interpreted it, and this is just an
aspect of working together as humans. And I have a lot of optimism in the long term, the very long
term, about what we as humanity can do. But I think that's going to be, it's just always a rough
ride. And you came into this by saying, like, what is COVID and all the social strife that's
happening right now mean? And I think that it's really bad in the short term, but I think it
will lead to progress. And for that, I'm very thankful. Yeah, it's painful in the short term,
though. Well, yeah, I mean, people are out of jobs, like, some people can't eat, like, it's
horrible. And, but, but, you know, it's progress. So we'll see, we'll see what happens. I mean,
the real question is when you look back 10 years, 20 years, 100 years from now, how do we evaluate
the decisions that are being made right now? I think that's really the way you can frame that
and look at it. And you say, you know, you integrate across all the short term horribleness
that's happening. And you look at what that means. And is the, you know, improvement across the world
or the regression across the world significant enough to make it a good or bad thing? I think
that's the question. Yeah. And for that's good to study history. I mean, one of the big problems
for me right now is I'm reading the rise and fall of the third Reich. Light reading. So it's
everything is just, I just see parallels and it means it's, it's, you have to be really careful
not to overstep it, but just the, the thing that worries me the most is the pain that people feel
when, when a few things combined, which is like economic depression, which is quite possible
in this country. And then just being disrespected by in some kind of way, which the German people
were really disrespected by most of the world, like in a way that's over the top, that something
can, it can build up. And then all you need is a charismatic leader just to go either positive
or negative in both work, as long as they're charismatic. And it's taking advantage of,
again, that, that inflection point that the world's in and what they do with it could be good or bad.
And so it's a good way to think about times now, like on an individual level, what we decide to do
is when, when history is written, you know, 30 years from now, what happened in 2020,
probably history is going to remember 2020. Yeah, I think so.
Either for good or bad. And it's like up to us to write it. So it's good.
Well, one of the things I've observed that I find fascinating is most people act as though the world
doesn't change. You make decision knowingly, right, you make a decision where you're predicting
the future based on what you've seen in the recent past. And so if something's always been
had, it's rained every single day, then of course, you expect it to rain today too, right?
On the other hand, the world changes all the time. Yeah, constantly, like for better and for worse.
And so the question is, if you're interested in something that's not right,
what is the inflection point that led to a change? And you can look to history for this,
like what is, what is the catalyst that led to that, that explosion that led to that bill that
led to the, like you can kind of work your way backwards from that. And maybe if you pull together
the right people and you get the right ideas together, you can actually start driving that
change and doing it in a way that's productive and hurts fewer people. Yeah, like a single person,
single event can turn all. Yeah, absolutely. Everything starts somewhere. And often it's
a combination of multiple factors. But, but yeah, this is these, these things can be engineered.
That's actually the optimistic view that I'm a long-term optimist on pretty much everything and
human nature, you know, we can look to all the negative things that the humanity has,
all the pettiness and all the like self self-servingness and the just the the cruelty,
right? The biases, the just humans can be very horrible. But on the other hand,
we're capable of amazing things. And, and the progress across, you know, 100 year chunks is
striking. And even across decades, it's, we've come a long ways and there's so long ways to go,
but that doesn't mean that we've stopped. Yeah, the kind of stuff we've done in the last 100 years
is, is unbelievable. It's kind of scary to think what's going to happen this 100 years. It's scary,
like exciting, like scary in a sense that it's kind of sad that the kind of technology is going to
come out in 10, 20, 30 years will probably too old to really appreciate because you don't grow up
with it. It'll be like kids these days with their virtual reality and their talks and stuff like
this. Like, how does this thing and like, come on, give me my, you know, static photo.
My Commodore 64. Yeah, exactly. Okay. Sorry, we kind of skipped over. Let me ask on,
you know, the machine learning world has been kind of inspired, their imagination captivated
with GPT-3 and these language models. I thought it'd be cool to get your opinion on it. What's
your thoughts on this exciting world of, it connects to computation actually is of language
models that are huge and take multiple, many, many computers, not just to train, but to also
do inference on. Sure. Well, I mean, it depends on what you're speaking to there. But I mean,
I think that there's been a pretty well understood maximum deep learning that if you make the model
bigger and you shove more data into it, assuming you train it right and you have a good model
architecture, that you'll get a better model out. And so on one hand, GPT-3 was not that surprising.
On the other hand, a tremendous amount of engineering went into making it possible.
The implications of it are pretty huge. I think that when GPT-2 came out, there was a very
provocative blog post from OpenAI talking about, we're not going to release it because of the
social damage it could cause if it's misused. I think that's still a concern. I think that we
need to look at how technology is applied and well-meaning tools can be applied in very horrible
ways and they can have very profound impact on that. I think that GPT-3 is a huge technical
achievement. And what will GPT-4 be? Will it probably be bigger, more expensive to train?
Really cool architectural tricks.
What do you think? I don't know how much thought you've done on distributed computing.
Is there some technical challenges that are interesting that you're hopeful about exploring
in terms of a system like a piece of code that GPT-4 might have hundreds of trillions
of parameters which have to run on thousands of computers? Is there some hope that we can
make that happen? Today, you can write a check and get access to a thousand TPU cores and do
really interesting large-scale training and inference and things like that in Google Cloud,
for example. I don't think it's a question about scales, it's a question about utility.
And when I look at the Transformer series of architectures that the GPT series is based on,
it's really interesting to look at that because they're actually very simple designs. They're
not recurrent. The training regimens are pretty simple and so they don't really reflect like
human brains. But they're really good at learning language models and they're unrolled enough that
you can simulate some recurrence. And so the question I think about is, where does this take us?
We can just keep scaling it, have more parameters, more data, more things, we'll get a better result
for sure. But are there architectural techniques that can lead to progressive faster pace?
Right, this is when, you know, how do you get, instead of just like making it a constant time
bigger, how do you get like an algorithmic improvement out of this, right? And whether it
be a new training regimen, if it becomes sparse networks, for example, human brain sparse,
all these networks are dense. The connectivity patterns can be very different. I think this
is where I get very interested and I'm way out of my league on the deep learning side of this.
But I think that could lead to big breakthroughs. When we talk about large scale networks, one of
the things that Jeff Dean likes to talk about and he's given a few talks on is this idea of having
a sparsely gated mixture of experts kind of a model where you have, you know, different nets
that are trained and are really good at certain kinds of tasks. And so you have this distributor
across a cluster. And so you have a lot of different computers that end up being kind of
locally specialized in different demands. And then when a query comes in, you gate it and use
learn techniques to route to different parts of the network. And then you utilize the compute
resources of the entire cluster by having specialization within it. And I don't know
where that goes or if it starts when it starts to work. But I think things like that could be
really interesting as well. And on the data side too, if you can think of data selection as a
kind of programming. Yeah, I mean, at the center, if you look at like Karpathi talked about software
2.0, I mean, in a sense, data is the programming. Yeah, yeah. So I just, so let me try to summarize
Andre's position really quick before I disagree with it. Yeah. So Andre Karpathi is amazing. So
this is nothing personal with him. He's an amazing engineer and also a good blog post writer.
Yeah, well, he's a great communicator. I mean, he's just an amazing person. He's also really
sweet. So his basic premise is that software is suboptimal. I think we can all agree to that.
He also points out that deep learning and other learning based techniques are really great because
you can solve problems in more structured ways with less like ad hoc code that people write
out and don't write test cases for in some cases. And so they don't even know if it works in the
first place. And so if you start replacing systems of imperative code with deep learning models,
then you get better, a better result. Okay. And I think that he argues that software 2.0 is a
pervasively learned set of models. And you get away from writing code. And he's given talks where
he talks about, you know, swapping over more and more and more parts of the code to being learned
and driven that way. I think that works. And if you're pretty predisposed to liking machine
learning, then I think that that's definitely a good thing. I think this is also good for
accessibility in many ways because certain people are not going to write C code or something.
And so having a data driven approach to do this kind of stuff, I think can be very valuable.
On the other hand, they're huge trade offs. And it's not clear to me that software 2.0 is
the answer. And probably Andre wouldn't argue that it's the answer for every problem either.
But I look at machine learning as not a replacement for software 1.0. I look at it as a new programming
paradigm. And so programming paradigms, when you look across, across demands is the structured
programming where you go from go tos to if then else, or functional programming from Lisp. And
you start talking about higher order functions and values and things like this, or you talk about
object oriented programming, you're talking about encapsulation, subclassing inheritance,
you start talking about generic programming, where you start talking about code reuse through
specialization and different type instantiations. When you start talking about differentiable
programming, something that I am very excited about in the context of machine learning,
talking about taking functions and generating variants like the derivative of another function.
Like that's a programming paradigm that's very useful for solving certain classes of problems.
Machine learning is amazing at solving certain classes of problems. Like you're not going to
write a cat detector, or even a language translation system by writing C code. That's not a very
productive way to do things anymore. And so machine learning is absolutely the right way to do that.
In fact, I would say that learned models are really one of the best ways to work with the human
world in general. And so anytime you're talking about sensory input of different modalities,
anytime that you're talking about generating things in a way that makes sense to a human,
I think that learned models are really, really useful. And that's because humans are very difficult
to characterize. And so this is a very powerful paradigm for solving classes of problems.
But on the other hand, imperative code is too, you're not going to write a bootloader for your
computer with a deep learning model. Deep learning models are very hardware intensive,
they're very energy intensive, because you have a lot of parameters. And you can provably
implement any function with a learned model, like this has been shown. But that doesn't make it
efficient. And so if you're talking about caring about a few orders and magnitudes worth of energy
usage, then it's useful to have other tools in the toolbox.
There's also robustness too. I mean, exactly, all the problems of dealing with data and bias in data,
all the problems of, you know, software 2.0. And one of the great things that Andre is
arguing towards, which I completely agree with him, is that when you start implementing things
with deep learning, you need to learn from software 1.0 in terms of testing, continuous
integration, how you deploy, how do you validate all these things and building systems around that,
so that you're not just saying, like, ooh, it seems like it's good, ship it, right? Well,
what happens when I regress something? What happens when I make a classification that's
wrong and now I heard somebody, right? All these things you have to reason about.
Yeah, but at the same time, the bootloader that works for us humans looks awfully a lot like a
neural network, right? It's messy and you can cut out different parts of the brain. There's a lot of
this neuroplasticity work that shows that it's going to adjust. It's a really interesting question,
how much of the world's programming could be replaced by software 2.0?
Well, I mean, it's provably true that you could replace all of it.
Right, so then it's a question of the trade-offs.
So anything that's a function, you can. So it's not a question about if I think it's an
economic question. It's a, what kind of talent can you get? What kind of trade-offs in terms of
maintenance? Those kinds of questions, I think, what kind of data can you collect? I think one
of the reasons that I'm most interested in machine learning is a programming paradigm is that one
of the things that we've seen across computing in general is that being laser focused on one paradigm
often puts you in a box. It's not super great. And so you look at object-oriented programming,
like it was all the rage in the early 80s and like everything has to be objects and people
forgot about functional programming even though came first. And then people rediscovered that,
hey, if you mix functional and object-oriented and structure, like you mix these things together,
you can provide very interesting tools that are good at solving different problems.
And so the question there is, how do you get the best way to solve the problems? It's not about
whose tribe should win, right? It's not about, that shouldn't be the question. The question is,
how do you make it so that people can solve those problems the fastest and they have the right
tools in their box to build good libraries and they can solve these problems? And when you look
at that, that's like, you look at reinforcement learning as one really interesting subdomain
of this. Reinforcement learning, often you have to have the integration of a learned model
combined with your Atari or whatever the other scenario it is that you're working in. You have
to combine that thing with the robot control for the arm, right? And so now it's not just about
that one paradigm, it's about integrating that with all the other systems that you have, including
often legacy systems and things like this, right? And so to me, I think that the interesting thing
to say is like, how do you get the best out of this domain? And how do you enable people to
achieve things that they otherwise couldn't do without excluding all the good things we already
know how to do? Right. But okay, this is a crazy question. But we talked a little about GPT-3,
but do you think it's possible that these language models that in essence, in the language domain,
software 2.0 could replace some aspect of compilation, for example, or do program synthesis
replace some aspect of programming? Yeah, absolutely. So I think that the learned models
in general are extremely powerful. And I think the people underestimate them.
Maybe you can suggest what I should do. So of access to the GPT-3 API,
would I be able to generate Swift code, for example? Do you think that could do something
interesting? So GPT-3 is probably not trained on the right corpus. So it probably has the ability
to generate some Swift, I bet it does. It's probably not going to generate a large enough
body of Swift to be useful. But take it a next step further. If you had the goal of training
something like GPT-3, and you wanted to try to generate source code, it could definitely do that.
Now, the question is, how do you express the intent of what you want filled in? You can
definitely write scaffolding of code and say fill in the hole, and put in some for loops or put in
some classes or whatever. And the power of these models is impressive. But there's an unsolved
question, at least unsolved to me, which is, how do I express the intent of what to fill in?
Right. And kind of what you'd really want to have, and I don't know that these models are up to
the task, is you want to be able to say, here's the scaffolding, and here are the assertions at the end.
And the assertions always pass. And so you want a generative model, on the one hand, yes.
Oh, that's fascinating. Yeah.
Right. But you also want some loopback, some reinforcement learning system or something
where you're actually saying, like, I need to hill climb towards something that is more correct.
And I don't know that we have that. So it would generate not only a bunch of the code, but like
the checks that do the testing. It would generate the tests. I think the humans would generate
the tests, right? Oh, okay. But it would be fascinating if... Well, the tests are the requirements.
Yes, but the... Okay, so... Because you have to express to the model what you want to...
You don't just want gibberish code. Look at how compelling this code looks.
You want a story about four horned unicorns or something.
Well, okay, so exactly. But that's human requirements. But then I thought it's a compelling idea that
the GPT-4 model could generate checks that are more high fidelity, that check for correctness.
Because the code it generates, say I ask it to generate a function that gives me the Fibonacci
sequence. Sure. I don't like... So decompose the problem, right? So you have two things. You have...
You need the ability to generate syntactically corrects with code that's interesting, right?
I think GPT series of model architectures can do that. But then you need the ability to
add the requirements. So generate Fibonacci. The human needs to express that goal. We don't
have that language that I know of. No, I mean, it can generate stuff. Have you seen
what GPT-3 can generate? You can say, I mean, there's interface stuff. It can generate HTML.
It can generate basic for loops that give you... Right, but pick HTML. How do I say I want google.com?
Well, no, you can say... Or not literally google.com. How do I say I want a web page that's got a
shopping cart and this and that? It does that. Okay, so just... I don't know if you've seen these
demonstrations, but you type in, I want a red button with the text that says hello, and you
type that natural language, and it generates the correct HTML. I've done this demo. It's kind
of compelling. So you have to prompt it with similar kinds of mappings. Of course, it's probably
handpicked. I have to experiment that probably... But the fact that you can do that once, even out of
like 20 is quite impressive. Again, that's very basic. Like the HTML is kind of messy and bad.
But yes, the intent is... The idea is the intent is specified in natural language.
So I have not seen that. That's really cool. Yeah, but the question is the correctness of that.
Like visually, you can check, oh, the button is red. But for more complicated functions,
where the intent is harder to check, this goes into like NP completeness kind of things, like
I want to know that this code is correct and generates a giant thing that just some kind
of calculation. It seems to be working. It's interesting to think like should the system also
try to generate checks for itself for correctness? Yeah, I don't know. And this is way beyond my
experience. The thing that I think about is that there doesn't seem to be a lot of
equational reasoning going on. Right. There's a lot of pattern matching and filling in and
kind of propagating patterns that have been seen before into the future and into the
generated result. And so if you want to get correctness, you kind of need their improving
kind of things and like higher level logic. And I don't know that... You could talk to Yon about
that and see what the bright minds are thinking about right now. But I don't think the GPT
is in that vein. It's still really cool. Yeah. And who knows? Maybe reasoning is...
Is overrated. Yeah, it's overrated. I mean, do we reason? How do you tell? Are we just pattern
matching based on what we have and then reverse justifying it to ourselves?
Exactly. So like I think what the neural networks are missing
and I think GPT form might have is to be able to tell stories to itself about what it did.
Well, that's what humans do, right? I mean, you talk about like network explainability, right?
And we give... No, no, that's a hard time about this. But humans don't know why we make decisions.
We have this thing called intuition. And then we try to like say this feels like the right thing,
but why? Right? And you wrestle with that when you're making hard decisions. And
is that science? Not really. Let me ask you about a few high level questions, I guess, is
you've done a million things in your life and been very successful. A bunch of young folks
listen to this, ask for advice from successful people like you. If you were to give advice to
somebody, you know, another graduate student or some high school student about pursuing a
career in computing or just advice about life in general, is there some words of wisdom you can
give them? So I think you come back to change and, you know, profound leaps happen because
people are willing to believe that change is possible and that the world does change and
are willing to do the hard thing that it takes to make change happen. And whether it be implementing
a new programming language or implementing a new system or implementing a new research paper,
designing a new thing, moving the world forward in science and philosophy, whatever,
it really comes down to somebody who's willing to put in the work, right? And you have...
The work is hard for a whole bunch of different reasons. One of which is you...
It's work, right? And so you have to have the space in your life in which you can do that work,
which is why going to grad school can be a beautiful thing for certain people.
But also there's a self-doubt that happens. Like you're two years into a project,
is it going anywhere? Right? Well, what do you do? Do you just give up because it's hard?
Well, no. I mean, some people like suffering. And so you plow through it. The secret to me is
that you have to love what you're doing. And follow that passion because when you get to
the hard times, that's when... If you love what you're doing, you're willing to push through.
This is really hard because it's hard to know what you will love doing until you start doing
a lot of things. And so that's why I think that particularly early in your career,
it's good to experiment. Do a little bit of everything. Go take the survey class on the
first half of every class in your upper division lessons and just get exposure to things because
certain things will resonate with you and you'll find out, wow, I'm really good at this. I'm really
smart at this. Well, it's just because it works with the way your brain. And when something jumps
out, I mean, that's one of the things that people often ask about is like, well, I think there's
a bunch of cool stuff out there. Like, how do I pick the thing? Like, how do you hook in your life?
How did you just hook yourself in and stuck with it? Well, I got lucky, right? I mean,
I think that many people forget that a huge amount of it or most of it is luck, right? So
let's not forget that. So for me, I fell in love with computers early on because they spoke to me,
I guess. What language did they speak? Basic. But then it was just kind of following a set of
logical progressions, but also deciding that something that was hard was worth doing and a
lot of fun, right? And so I think that that is also something that's true for many other
domains, which is if you find something that you love doing that's also hard, if you invest
yourself in it and add value to the world, then it will mean something generally, right? And again,
that can be a research paper, that can be a software system, that can be a new robot,
that can be, there's many things that can be, but a lot of it is like real value comes from
doing things that are hard. And that doesn't mean you have to suffer. But it's hard. I mean,
you don't often hear that message. We talked about it last time a little bit, but it's one of my
not enough people talk about this. It's beautiful to hear a successful person.
Well, in self-doubt and imposter syndrome, and these are all things that successful people suffer
with as well, particularly when they put themselves in a point of being uncomfortable, which I like
to do now and then just because it puts you in learning mode. Like if you want to, if you want
to grow as a person, put yourself in a room with a bunch of people that know way more about whatever
you're talking about than you do and ask dumb questions. And guess what? Smart people love to
teach, often, not always, but often. And if you listen, if you're prepared to listen, if you're
prepared to grow, if you're prepared to make connections, you can do some really interesting
things. And I think a lot of progress is made by people who kind of hop between domains now and
then because they bring a perspective into a field that nobody else has, if people have only
been working in that field themselves. We mentioned that the universe is kind of like a compiler,
you know, the entirety of it, the whole evolution is kind of a kind of a compilation.
Maybe us human beings are kind of compilers. Let me ask the old sort of question that I
didn't ask you last time, which is, what's the meaning of it all? Is there a meaning? Like if
you asked a compiler why, what would a compiler say? What's the meaning of life?
What's the meaning of life? You know, I'm prepared for not to mean anything.
Here we are, all biological things programmed to survive and propagate our DNA. And maybe the
universe is just a computer and you just go until entropy takes over the world or takes
over the universe and then you're done. I don't think that's a very productive way to live your
life, if so. And so I prefer to bias towards the other way, which is saying the universe has a
lot of value. And I take happiness out of other people. And a lot of times part of that's having
kids, but also the relationships you build with other people. And so the way I try to live my
life is like, what can I do that has value? How can I move the world forward? How can I
take what I'm good at and like bring it into the world? And how can I, I'm one of these people
that likes to work really hard and be very focused on the things that I do. And so if I'm going to
do that, how can it be in a domain that actually will matter? Because a lot of things that we do,
we find ourselves in the cycle of like, okay, I'm doing a thing, I'm very familiar with it,
I've done it for a long time, I've never done anything else, but I'm not really learning.
I'm not really, I'm keeping things going, but there's a, there's a younger generation that
can do the same thing, maybe even better than me, right? Maybe if I actually step out of this and
jump into something I'm less comfortable with, it's scary. But on the other hand, it gives somebody
else a new opportunity. It also then puts you back in learning mode. And that can be really
interesting. And one of the things I've learned is that when you go through that, that first you're
deep into imposter syndrome. But when you start working your way out, you start to realize, hey,
well, there's actually a method to this. And, and now I'm able to add new things because I bring
different perspective. And this is one of the, the good things about bringing different kinds of
people together. Diversity of thought is really important. And if you can pull together people
that are coming at things from different directions, you often get innovation. And I love to see that,
that aha moment where you're like, we've like really cracked this, this is something nobody's
ever done before. And then if you can do it in the context where it adds value, other people can
build on it, it helps move the world, then that's what, that's what really excites me.
So that kind of description of the magic of the human experience, do you think we'll ever create
that in like an AGI system, you think we'll be able to create, give, give AI systems a sense of
meaning, where they operate in this kind of world exactly in the way you've described, which is they
interact with each other, they interact with us humans. Sure. Sure. Well, so I mean, I, why, why are
you being so a species, right? All right. So, so AGI versus bionets, you know, what are we about
machines, right? We're just programmed to run our, we have our objective function that we're
optimized for, right? And so we're doing our thing, we think we have purpose, but do we really?
Yeah. Right. I'm not prepared to say that those newfangled AGI's have no soul just because we
don't understand them, right? And I think that would be when they, when they exist, that would be
very premature to look at a new thing through your own lens without fully understanding it.
You might be just saying that because AI systems in the future will be listening to this and then,
Oh yeah, exactly. You don't want to say anything. Please be nice to me, you know, when Skynet,
Skynet kills everybody, please spare me. So why is, why is a look ahead thinking?
Yeah, but I mean, I think that people will spend a lot of time worrying about this kind of stuff.
And I think that what we should be worrying about is how do we make the world better?
And the thing that I'm most scared about with AGI's is not that, that necessarily the Skynet
will start shooting everybody with lasers and stuff like that to, to use us for our calories.
The thing that I'm worried about is that humanity, I think needs a challenge. And if we get into a
mode of not having a personal challenge, not having a personal contribution, whether that be
like, you know, your kids and seeing what they grow into and helping, helping guide them, whether it
be your community that you're engaged in, you're driving forward, whether it be your work and the
things that you're doing and the people you're working with in the product you're building and
the contribution there, if people don't have a objective, I'm afraid what that means. And
and I think that this would lead to a rise of the worst part of people, right? Instead of
people striving together and trying to make the world better, it could degrade into a very
unpleasant world. But, but I don't know. I mean, we hopefully have a long ways to go before we
discover that. And unfortunately, we have pretty on the ground problems with the pandemic right
now. And so I think we should be focused on that as well. Yeah, ultimately, just as you said,
you're optimistic. I think it helps for us to be optimistic. That's faking until you make it.
Yeah, well, and why not? I mean, what's what's the other side? Right? So I mean,
I'm not personally a very religious person. But I've heard people say like, Oh, yeah, of course,
I believe in God. Of course, I go to church because if God's real, I want to be on the right
side of that. And if it's not real, it doesn't matter. Yeah, it doesn't matter. And so, you know,
that's that's a fair way to do it. Yeah, I mean, the same thing with with nuclear deterrence,
all, you know, global warming, all these things, all these threats, natural engineer pandemics,
all these threats we face, I think it's, it's paralyzing to be terrified of all the possible
ways we could destroy ourselves. I think it's much better, or at least productive to be hopeful
and to engineer defenses against these things to engineer a future where like, you know,
see like a positive future and engineer that future. Yeah, well, and I think that's other
another thing to think about as, you know, a human, particularly if you're young and trying
to figure out what it is that you want to be when you grow up, like I am. I'm always looking for that.
The question then is, how do you want to spend your time? And right now, there seems to be a
norm of being a consumption culture, like I'm going to watch the news and, and revel in how
horrible everything is right now, I'm going to go find out about the latest atrocity and find out
all the details of like the terrible thing that happened and be outraged by it. You can spend
a lot of time watching TV and watching the news sitcom or whatever people watch these days, I
don't know. But that's a lot of hours, right? And those are hours that if you're turning to
being productive, learning, growing, experiencing, you know, when the pandemic's over, going exploring,
right, it leads to more growth. And I think it leads to more optimism and happiness because
you're, you're, you're building, right, you're building yourself, you're building your capabilities,
you're building your viewpoints, you're building your perspective. And I think that a lot of the
the consuming of other people's messages leads to kind of a negative viewpoint, which you need to
be aware of what's happening, because that's also important. But there's a balance that I think
focusing on creation is, is a very valuable thing to do. Yeah. So what you're saying is people should
focus on working on the sexiest field of all, which is compiler design. Exactly. Hey, you can
go work on machine learning and be crowded out by the thousands of graduates popping out of school
that all want to do the same thing, or you could work in the place that people overpay you,
because there's not enough smart people working in it. And here at the end of Moore's Law,
according to some people, actually the software is the hard part too.
I mean, optimization is truly, truly beautiful. And also on the YouTube side or education side,
you know, it's, there's a, it'd be nice to have some material that shows the beauty of
compilers. Yeah, yeah. That's, that's something. So that's a call for, for people to create that
kind of content as well. Chris, you're one of my favorite people to talk to. It's such a huge honor
that you would waste your time talking to me. I've always appreciated. Thank you so much for
talking to me. The truth of it is you spent a lot of time talking to me just on, you know,
walks and other things like that. So it's great to catch up with. Thanks, man.
Thanks for listening to this conversation with Chris Latner. And thank you to our sponsors,
Blinkist, an app that summarizes key ideas from thousands of books, Neuro, which is a maker of
functional gum and mints that supercharged my mind, Masterclass, which are online courses from
world experts, and finally, Cash App, which is an app for sending money to friends. Please check
out these sponsors in the description to get a discount and to support this podcast. If you
enjoyed this thing, subscribe on YouTube, review it with five stars on Apple podcast, follow on
Spotify, support on Patreon, connect with me on Twitter, Alex Friedman. And now let me leave you
with some words from Chris Latner. So much of language design is about trade offs. And you
can't see those trade offs unless you have a community of people that really represent those
different points. Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.