The following is a conversation with Daniel Schmacktenberger, a founding member of the
Consilience Project that is aimed at improving public sense-making and dialogue. He is interested
in understanding how we humans can be the best version of ourselves as individuals and as
collectives at all scales. Quick mention of our sponsors, Groud News, Netsuite, FourSigmatic,
Magic Spoon, and BetterHelp. Check them out in the description to support this podcast.
As a side note, let me say that I got a chance to talk to Daniel on and off the
mic for a couple of days. We took a long walk the day before our conversation. I really enjoyed
meeting him just on a basic human level. We talked about the world around us with words that carried
hope for us individual ants actually contributing something of value to the colony. These conversations
are the reasons I love human beings, our insatiable striving to lessen the suffering in the world.
But more than that, there's a simple magic to two strangers meeting for the first time
and sharing ideas, becoming fast friends and creating something that is far greater than
the sum of our parts. I've gotten to experience some of that same magic here in Austin with
a few new friends and in random bars in my travels across this country, where a conversation leaves
me with a big stupid smile on my face and a new appreciation of this too short, too beautiful life.
This is the Lex Friedman podcast and here is my conversation with Daniel Schmacktenberger.
If aliens were observing Earth through the entire history just watching us and we're tasked with
summarizing what happened until now, what do you think they would say? What do you think they
would write up in that summary? Like it has to be pretty short, less than a page. Like in The
Tracker's Guide, there's, I think, like a paragraph or a couple sentences.
How would you summarize, sorry, how would the alien summarize, do you think, all of human
civilization? My first thoughts take more than a page. They'd probably distill it.
Because if they watched, well, I mean, first I have no idea if their senses are even attuned to
similar stuff to what our senses are attuned to or what the nature of their consciousness is like
relative to ours. And so let's assume that they're kind of like us, just technologically more advanced
to get here from wherever they are. That's the first kind of constraint on the thought experiment.
And then if they've watched throughout all of history, they saw the burning of Alexandria. They
saw that 2000 years ago in Greece, we were producing things like clocks, the anti-Catharea
mechanism, and then that technology got lost. They saw that there wasn't just a steady dialectic of
progress. So every once in a while, there's a giant fire that destroys a lot of things.
There's a giant like commotion that destroys a lot of things. Yeah, and it's usually self-induced.
They would have seen that. And so as they're looking at us now as we move past the nuclear
weapons age into the full globalization, Anthropocene, exponential tech age,
still making our decisions relatively similarly to how we did in the Stone Age as far as rivalry
game theory type stuff, I think they would think that this is probably most likely one of the
planets that is not going to make it to being intergalactic because we blow ourselves up in
the technological adolescence. And if we are going to, we're going to need some major progress
rapidly in the social technologies that can guide and bind and direct the physical technologies
so that we are safe vessels for the amount of power we're getting.
Actually, Hitchhiker's Guide has an estimation about how much of a risk this particular thing
poses to the rest of the galaxy. And I think, I forget what it was, I think it was medium or low.
So their estimation would be that this species of ant-like creatures is not going to survive long.
There's ups and downs in terms of technological innovation. The fundamental nature of their
behavior from a game theory perspective hasn't really changed. They have not learned in any
fundamental way how to control and properly incentivize or properly do the mechanism design
of games to ensure long-term survival. And then they move on to another planet. Do you
think there is in a more slightly more serious question, do you think there's
some number or perhaps a very, very large number of intelligent alien civilizations out there?
Yes, it would be hard to think otherwise. I know, I think Postrum had a new article not
that long ago on why that might not be the case, that the Drake equation might not be the
kind of in-story on it. But when I look at the total number of Kepler planets just that we're
aware of just galactically and also like when those life forms were discovered in Mono Lake,
that didn't have the same six primary atoms that I think you had arsenic replacing phosphorus as one
of the primary aspects of its energy metabolism, we get to think about that the building blocks
might be more different. So the physical constraints even that the planets have to have might be more
different. It seems really unlikely not to mention interesting things that we've observed that are
still unexplained as you've had guests on your show discussing tic-tac. Oh, the ones that have visited.
Yeah. Well, let's dive right into that. What do you make sense of the rich human psychology
of there being hundreds of thousands, probably millions of witnesses of UFOs of different kinds
on earth, most of which I presume are conjured up by the human mind through the perception system?
Some number might be true. Some number might be reflective of actual physical objects, whether
it's, you know, drones or testing military technology that's secret or otherworldly technology.
What do you make sense of all of that? Because it's gaining quite a bit of popularity recently.
There is some sense in which that's, that's us humans being hopeful and dreaming of otherworldly
creatures as a way to escape the juroriness of our of the human condition. But in another sense,
it could be, it really could be something truly exciting that science should turn its eye towards.
So what do you, where do you place it? Speaking of turning eye towards, this is one of those
super fascinating, actually super consequential, possibly topics that I wish I had more time to
study and just haven't allocated. So I don't have firm beliefs on this because I haven't
got to study it as much as I want. So what I'm going to say comes from a superficial assessment.
While we know there are plenty of things that people thought of as UFO sightings that we can
fully write off, we have other better explanations for them. What we're interested in is the ones
that we don't have better explanations for, and then not just immediately jumping to
a theory of what it is, but holding it as unidentified and being being curious and earnest.
I think the, the tic-tac one is quite interesting and made it in major media recently, but I don't
know if you ever saw the disclosure project. Guy named Stephen Greer organized a bunch of mostly
U.S. military and some commercial flight. People who had direct observation and classified information
disclosing it at a CNN briefing. And so you saw high-ranking generals, admirals, fighter pilots,
all describing things that they saw on radar with visual, with their own eyes or cameras,
and also describing some phenomena that had some consistency across different people. And
I find this interesting enough that I think it would be silly to just dismiss it.
And specifically, like we can, we can ask the question, how much of it is natural phenomena,
ball lightning or something like that? And this is why I'm more interested in what fighter pilots
and astronauts and people who are trained in being able to identify flying objects and
atmospheric phenomena have to say about it. I think the thing, then you could say, well,
are they more advanced military craft? Is it some kind of human craft? The interesting thing that
a number of them describe is something that's kind of like right angles at speed, or not right
angles, acute angles at speed, but something that looks like a different relationship to inertia
than physics makes sense for us. I don't think that there are any human technologies that are
doing that, even in really deep underground black projects. Now, one could say, okay, well,
could it be a hologram? Well, would it show up on radar if radar is also seeing it? And so,
I don't know. I think there's enough, I mean, and for that to be a massive coordinated psi op,
is it as interesting and ridiculous in a way as the idea that it's UFOs from some extra planetary
source? So, it's up there on the interesting topics. To me, if it is at all alien technology,
it is the dumbest version of alien technology. It's so far away, it's like the old, old crappy VHS
tapes of alien technology. These are like crappy drones that just floated, or even like space,
to the level of like space junk, because it is so close to our human technology. We talk about
it moves in ways that's unlike what we understand about physics, but it still has very similar
kind of geometric notions and something that we humans can perceive with our eyes, all those
kinds of things. I feel like alien technology, most likely, would be something that we would not
be able to perceive, not because they're hiding, but because it's so far advanced that it would be
much, it would be beyond the cognitive capabilities of us humans. Just as you were saying, as per your
answer for aliens summarizing Earth, it's the starting assumption is they have similar perception
systems, they have similar cognitive capabilities, and that very well may not be the case.
Let me ask you about staying in aliens for just a little longer, because I think it's a good
transition talking about governments and human societies. Do you think if a US government or
any government was in possession of an alien spacecraft, or of information related to alien
spacecraft, they would have the capacity, structurally would they have the processes, would
they be able to communicate that to the public effectively, or would they keep it secret in a
room and do nothing with it, both of to try to preserve military secrets, but also because of
the incompetence that's inherent to bureaucracies, or either?
Well, we can certainly see when certain things become declassified 25 or 50 years later that
there were things that the public might have wanted to know that were kept secret for a very
long time, for reasons of at least supposedly national security, which is also a nice source
of plausible deniability for people covering their ass for doing things that would be problematic and
other purposes. There are, there's a scientist at Stanford who supposedly got some material that
was recovered from Area 51 type area did analysis on it using, I believe, electron microscopy and
a couple other methods and came to the idea that it was a nanotech alloy that was something we
didn't currently have the ability to do was not naturally occurring. So there, I've heard some
things and again, like I said, I'm not going to stand behind any of these because I haven't
done the level of study to have high confidence. I think what you said also about would it be
super low tech alien craft? Like would they necessarily move their atoms around in space?
Or might they do something more interesting than that? Might they be able to
have a different relationship to the concept of space or information or consciousness or
one of the things that the craft supposedly do is not only accelerate and turn in a way that looks
not inertial but also disappear. So there's a question as to like the two are not necessarily
mutually exclusive and it could be possible to, some people run a hypothesis that they
create intentional amounts of exposure as an invitation of a particular kind.
Who knows? Interesting field. We tend to assume like SETI that's listening out for aliens out there.
I've just been recently reading more and more about gravitational waves and you have
orbiting black holes that orbit each other. They generate ripples in space time
on my for fun at night when I lay in bed. I think about what it would be like to ride those waves
when they, not the low magnitude they are as when they reach earth but get closer to the black holes
because they'll basically be shrinking and expanding us in all dimensions, including time.
So it's actually ripples through space time that they generate.
Why is it that you couldn't use that? It travels at the speed of light.
It travels at a speed which is a very weird thing to say when you're
morphing space time. You could argue it's faster than the speed of light.
So if you're able to communicate by
to summon enough energy to generate black holes and to force them to orbit each other,
why not travel as the ripples in space time? Whatever the hell that means somehow combined
with wormholes. So if you're able to communicate through like we don't think of gravitational
waves as something you can communicate with because the the radio will be have to be a very
large size of very dense but perhaps that's it. You know perhaps that's one way to communicate.
It's a very effective way and that would explain like we wouldn't even be able to make sense of that
of the physics that results in an alien species that's able to control gravity at that scale.
I think he just jumped up the Kardashev scale so far. You're not just harnessing the power of
a star but harnessing the power of mutually rotating black holes. That's way above my
physics pay grade to think about including even non-rotating black hole versions of
transwarp travel. I think you know you can talk with Eric more about that. I think he has better
ideas on it than I do. My hope for the future of humanity mostly does not rest in the near term
on our ability to get to other habitable planets in time. And even more than that in the list of
possible solutions of how to improve human civilization orbiting black holes is not in
on the first page for you. Not on the first page. Okay I bet you did not expect us to start this
conversation here but I'm glad the places it went. I am excited under my smaller scale of
Mars, Europa, Titan, Venus potentially having very like bacteria like life forms just on a
on a small human level. It's a little bit scary but mostly really exciting that there might be
life elsewhere in the volcanoes and the oceans all around us. Teaming, having little societies
and whether there's properties about that kind of life that's somehow different than ours.
I don't know what would be more exciting if those colonies of single cell type organisms
what would be more exciting if they're different or they're the same. If they're the same that means
through the rest of the universe there's life forms like us something like us
everywhere. If they're different that's also really exciting because there's
life forms everywhere they're not like us. That's a little bit scary. I don't know what's
scarier actually. It's both scary and exciting no matter what right. The idea that they could
be very different is philosophically very interesting for us to open our aperture on
what life and consciousness and self-replicating possibilities could look like. The question
on are they different or the same? Obviously there's lots of life here that is the same in
some ways and different in other ways. When you take the thing that we call an invasive species
is something that's still pretty the same hydrocarbon based thing but co-evolved with
co-selective pressures in a certain environment we move it to another environment it might be
devastating to that whole ecosystem because it's just different enough that it messes up the self
stabilizing dynamics of that ecosystem. The question of would they be different in ways
where we could still figure out a way to inhabit a biosphere together or fundamentally not.
Fundamentally the nature of how they operate and the nature of how we operate would be
incommensurable is a deep question. Well we offline talked about memetic theory. It seems
like if there were sufficiently different where we would not even we can coexist on different
planes it seems like a good thing. If we're close enough together to where we'd be competing then
you're getting into the world of viruses and pathogens and all those kinds of things
to where we would one of us would die off quickly through basically mass murder
without even even accidentally. Even accidentally. If we just had a self replicating single celled
kind of creature that happened to not work well for the hydrocarbon life that was here
they got introduced because either output something that was toxic or utilized up the
same resource too quickly and it just replicated faster and mutated faster. It wouldn't be a
memetic theory conflict theory kind of harm it would just be a von Neumann machine a self
replicating machine that was fundamentally incompatible with these kinds of self replicating
systems with faster ootaloops. For one final time putting your alien lies God had on.
You look at human civilization do you think about the 7.8 billion people on earth as individual
little creatures individual little organisms or do you think of us as one organism with a collective
intelligence? What's the proper framework through which to analyze it again as an alien?
So that I know where you're coming from when you have asked the question the same way
before the industrial revolution before the agricultural revolution when there were half
a billion people and no telecommunications connecting them? I would indeed ask the question
the same way but I would be less confident about about your conclusions. It would be an
actually more interesting way to ask the question at that time but I was nevertheless asked at the
same way yes. Well let's go back further and smaller than rather than just a single human
or the entire human species let's look at a relatively isolated tribe. In the relatively
isolated probably sub Dunbar number sub kind of 150 people tribe do I look at that as one
entity where evolution is selecting for based on group selection or do I think of it as 150
individuals that are interacting in some way? Well could those individuals exist without the group?
No. The evolutionary adaptiveness of humans was involved critically group selection and
individual humans alone trying to figure out stone tools and protection and whatever aren't
what was selected for and so I think the or is the wrong frame. I think it's individuals are
affecting the group that they're a part of they're also dependent upon and being affected by the group
that they're part of and so this now starts to get in deep into political theories also which is
theories that orient towards the collective at different scales whether a tribal scale or an
empire or a nation state or something and ones that orient towards the individual liberalism and
stuff like that and I think there's very obvious failure modes on both sides and so the relationship
between them is more interesting to me than either of them the relationship between the individual
and the collective and the question around how to have a virtuous process between those so a good
social system would be one where the organism of the individual and the organism of the group of
individuals is they're both synergistic to each other so what is best for the individuals and
what's best for the whole is aligned but there is nevertheless an individual they're not it's a
it's a matter of degrees I suppose but what is what defines a human more the the social network
within a which they've been brought up through which they've developed their intelligence or is
it their own sovereign individual self like what's your intuition of how much not just for
evolutionary survival but as intellectual beings how much do we need others for our development
yeah I think we have a weird sense of this today relative to most previous periods of
sapien history I think the vast majority of sapien history is tribal like depending upon your
early human model two or three hundred thousand years of homo sapiens in little tribes where
they depended upon that tribe for survival and excommunication from the tribe was was fatal
I think they and our whole evolutionary genetic history is in that environment and the amount
of time we've been out of it is is relatively so tiny and then we still depended upon extended
families and local communities more and the big kind of giant market complex where I can provide
something to the market to get money to be able to get other things from the market where it
seems like I don't need anyone it's almost like disintermediating our sense of need even though
even though you're my ability to talk to each other using these mics and the phones that we
coordinated on took millions of people over six continents to be able to run the supply chains
that made all the stuff that we depend on but we don't notice that we depend upon them they all
seem fungible um if you take a baby obviously that you didn't even get to a baby without a mom
was it dependent or we depended upon each other right without two two parents at minimum and
they depended upon other people but if we take that baby and we put it out in the wild it obviously
dies so if we let it grow up for a little while the minimum amount of time where it starts to
have some autonomy and then we put it out in the wild and there this has happened a few times
it doesn't learn language and it doesn't learn the artic the small motor articulation
that we learn it doesn't learn the type of consciousness that we end up having that is
socialized so i think i think we take for granted how much conditioning affects us
um it is possible that uh it affects basically 99.9 or maybe the whole thing the whole thing is
the connection between us humans and that we're we're uh no better than apes without our human
connections because that that thinking of it that way forces us to think very differently
about human society and how to progress forward if the connections are fundamental i just have
to object to the no better than apes because better here i think you mean a specific thing which
means have capacities that are fundamentally different than i think apes also depend upon
troops um yes and i i think the idea of humans as better than nature in some kind of
ethical sense ends up having heaps of problems we'll table that we can come back to it but
when we say what is unique about homo sapien capacity relative to the other animals we currently
inhabit the biosphere with and i'm saying it that way because there were other early hominids that
had some of these capacities uh we believe our tool creation and our language creation and our
coordination are all kind of the results of a certain type of capacity for abstraction
and other animals will use tools but they don't evolve the tools they use they keep using the
same types of tools that they basically can find so a chimp will notice that a rock can cut a vine
that it wants to and it'll even notice that a sharper rock will cut it better and experientially
it'll use the sharper rock and if you even give it a knife it'll probably use the knife because
it's experiencing the effectiveness but it doesn't make stone tools because that requires
understanding why one is sharper than the other what is the abstract principle called sharpness
to then be able to invent a sharper thing that same abstraction makes language and the ability
for abstract representation which makes the ability to coordinate in a more advanced set of ways
so i do think our ability to coordinate with each other is pretty fundamental to the selection
of what we are as a species i wonder if that coordination that connection is actually the
thing that gives birth to consciousness that gives birth to well let's start with self-awareness
more like theory of mind theory of mind yeah you know i i suppose there's experiments that show
that there's other mammals that have a very crude theory of mind i'm not sure maybe dogs
something like that but actually dogs probably has to do with that they co-evolved with humans
see it'd be interesting if that theory of mind is what leads to consciousness in the way we think
about it is the richness of the subjective experience that is consciousness i have an
inkling sense that that only exists because we're social creatures that that doesn't come
with this with the hardware and the software in the in the beginning that's like that's learned
as an effective tool for communication almost like we we think we i think we think that consciousness
is fundamental and maybe it's not there's a bunch of folks kind of criticize the idea that the
illusion of consciousness is consciousness that it is just a facade we use to
to help us construct theories of mind you almost put yourself in the world as a subjective being
in that experience you want to reach the experience as an individual person so that i could empathize
with your experience i find that notion compelling mostly because it allows you to then create robots
that become conscious not by being quote-unquote conscious but by just learning to fake it till
they make it is uh creative you know present the facade of consciousness and with it with the task
of uh making that facade very convincing to us humans and thereby it will become conscious
have a sense that in some way that will make them conscious if they're sufficiently convincing to
humans is there some element of that that you uh that you find convincing this is a much harder
set of questions and deep end of the pool than starting with the aliens was um we went from
aliens to consciousness this is not the trajectory i was expecting nor you but let us walk a while
we can walk a while and i don't think we will do it justice so what do we mean by consciousness
versus conscious self-reflective awareness what do we mean by awareness qualia theory of mind
there's a lot of terms that we think of as slightly different things and um subjectivity
first person uh i i don't remember exactly the quote but i remember when reading when sam
harris wrote the book free will and then denet critiqued it and then there was some writing
back and forth between the two because normally they're on the same side of kind of arguing
for critical thinking and logical fallacies and philosophy of science against um supernatural
ideas and here denet believed there is something like free will he is a determinist compatible
list but no consciousness and radical limitivist and sam was saying no there is consciousness
but there's no free will and that's like the most fundamental kinds of axiomatic senses they
disagreed on but neither of them could say it was because the other one didn't understand the
philosophy of science um or logical fallacies and and they kind of spoke past each other and at the
end if i remember correctly sam said something that i thought was quite insightful which was to
the effect of it seems to because they weren't making any progress and shared understanding
it seems that we simply have different intuitions about this and what you could see was that
what the words meant right at the level of symbol grounding might be quite different
one of them might have had deeply different enough life experiences that what is being
referenced and then also different associations of what the words mean this is why when trying to
address these things charles sanders per said the first philosophy has to be semiotics because
if you don't get semiotics right we end up importing different ideas and bad ideas right into the
nature of the language that we're using and then it's very hard to do epistemology or ontology
together uh so i'm saying this to say why i don't think we're going to get very far is i think
we would have to go very slowly in terms of defining what we mean by words and fundamental
concepts um well and also allowing our minds to drift together for a time so there are
definitions of these terms aligned i think there's some there's a beauty that some people
enjoy with sam that he is quite stubborn on his definitions of terms without often clearly revealing
that definition so in his mind he can like he could sense that he can deeply understand what he
means exactly by a term like free will and consciousness and you're right he's very he's
very specific in fascinating ways that not only does he think that free will is an illusion
he thinks he's able not thinks he says he's able to just remove himself from the experience of free
will and just be like for minutes at a time hours at a time like really experiences if he has no
free will like he's a leaf flowing down the river and given that he's very sure that consciousness
is fundamental so here's a this conscious leaf that's subjectively experiencing the floating
and yet there's no ability to control and make any decisions for it for itself it's only a
the decisions have all been made there's some aspect to which the terminology there perhaps
is the problem so that's a particular kind of meditative experience and the people in the
vedantic tradition and some of the buddhist traditions thousands of years ago described
similar experiences and somewhat similar conclusions some slightly different
there are other types of phenomenal experience that are the phenomenal experience of pure agency
and you know like the the catholic theologian but evolutionary theorist ter dishardan describes
this and that rather than a creator agent god in the beginning there's a creative impulse or a
creative process and he was would go into a type of meditation that identified as the pure essence
of that kind of creative process and I think the types of experiences we've had and then
one the types of experiences we've had make a big deal to the nature of how we do symbol grounding
the other thing is the types of experiences we have can't not be interpreted through our existing
interpretive frames and most of the time our interpretive frames are unknown even to us
some of them and so this is a tricky this is a tricky topic so I guess there's a bunch of
directions we could go with it but I want to come back to what the impulse was that was
interesting around what is consciousness and how does it relate to us as social beings and how
does it relate to the possibility of consciousness with it ai's right you're keeping us on track
which is which is wonderful you're a wonderful hiking partner okay yes let's go back to the
initial impulse of what is consciousness and how does the social impulse connect to consciousness
is consciousness a consequence of that social connection I'm gonna state a position and not
argue it because it's honestly like it's a long hard thing to argue and we can totally do it another
time if you want I don't subscribe to consciousness as an emergent property of biology or neural
networks obviously a lot of people do obviously the the philosophy of science orient towards that
in not absolutely but largely I think of the nature of first person the universe of first person
of of qualia as experience sensation desire emotion phenomenology the but the the felt
sense not the we say emotion and we think of a neurochemical pattern or an endocrine pattern
but all of the physical stuff the third person stuff has position and momentum and charge and
stuff like that that is measurable repeatable I think of the nature of first person and third
person as ontologically orthogonal to each other not reducible to each other there are different
kinds of stuff and so I think about the evolution of third person that we're quite used to thinking
about from subatomic particles to atoms to molecules to on and on I think about a similar
kind of and corresponding evolution in the domain of first person from the way whitehead talked about
kind of prehension or proto qualia in earlier phases of self-organization and to higher orders
of it and that there's correspondence but that neither like the like the idealists do we reduce
third person to first person which is what idealists do or neither like the physical lists or do we
reduce first person to third person obviously bone talked about an implicate order that was
deeper than and gave rise to the explicate order of both nagle talks about something like that I
have a slightly different sense of that but again I'll just kind of not argue how that occurs for
a moment and say so rather than say does consciousness emerge from I'll talk about do
higher capacities of consciousness emerge in relationship with so it's not first person as
a category emerging from third person but increased complexity within the nature of first person
and third person co-evolving do I think that it seems relatively likely that more advanced neural
networks have deeper phenomenology more complex where it goes just from basic sensation to
to emotion to social awareness to abstract cognition to self-reflexive abstract cognition
yeah but I wouldn't say that's the emergence of consciousness I would say it's increased
complexity within the domain of first person corresponding to increased complexity and the
correspondence should not automatically be seen as causal we can get into the arguments for why
that often is the case so what I say that obviously the sapien brain is pretty unique
and a single sapien now has that right even if it took sapiens evolving in tribes based on group
selection to make that brain so the group made it now that brain is there now if I take that a
single person with that brain out of the group and try to raise them in a box they'll still not be
very interesting even with the brain but the brain does give hardware capacities that if conditioned
in relationship can have interesting things emerge so do I think that the the human biology
types of human consciousness and types of social interaction all co-emerged and co-evolved yes
as a smaller side as you're talking about the biology let me comment that I spent this is what
I do this is what I do with my life this is why we'll never accomplish anything is I spent much of
the morning trying to calculate trying to do research on how many computations the brain performs
and how many how much energy it uses versus the state of the rcpus and gpus now arriving at
about 20 quadrillion so that's 2 to the 10 to the 16 computations so synaptic firings per second
that the brain does and that's about a million times faster than the uh
the let's say the 20 thread state of the arts intel cpu the the 10th generation and then
there's similar calculation for the for the for the gpu and all ended up also trying to compute
that it takes 10 watts to run the brain about and then what does that mean in terms of calories per
day killer calories that's about two for an average human brain that's
250 to 300 calories a day and so it ended up being a calculation where you're doing about
20 quadrillion calculations that that are fueled by something like depending on your diet three
bananas so three bananas results in uh in a computation that's about a million times more
powerful than the current state of the art computers now let's take that one step further
there's some assumptions built in there the assumption is that one what the brain is doing
is just computation two the the relevant computations are synaptic firings and that there's
nothing other than synaptic firings that we have to to factor so I'm forgetting his name
right now there's a very uh famous neuroscientist at stanford just passed away recently who did a
lot of the pioneering work on glial cells and showed that his assessment glial cells did a huge
amount of the thinking not just neurons and it opened up this entirely different field of like
what the brain is and what consciousness is you look at demasio's work on embodied cognition
and how much of what we would consider consciousness or feeling is happening outside of the nervous
system completely happening in endocrine process involving lots of other cells and
signal communication uh you talk to somebody like penrose who you've had on the show and even
though the penrose hammerhoff conjecture is probably not right is there something like that
that might be the case where we're actually having to look at stuff happening at the level of quantum
computation of microtubules I'm not arguing for any of those I'm arguing that we don't know how big
the unknown unknown set is well at the very least this is this has become like an infomercial for
the human brain at the very but wait there's more at the very least the three bananas buys you a
million times at the very least at the very least and then you could have uh and then the synaptic
firings we're referring to is strictly the electrical signals that could be the mechanical
transmission of information like this chemical transmission of information there's there's all
kinds of other stuff going on and there's memory that's built in that's also all tied in not to
mention which I'm learning more and more about it's not just about the uh the neurons it's also
about the immune system that's somehow helping with the computation so the entirety and the entire
body is helping with the computation so the three bananas they could buy you a lot it could buy you
a lot but on the topic of sort of the greater degrees of complexity emerging in consciousness
I think few things are as beautiful and inspiring as taking a step outside of the human brain
just looking at systems or simple rules create incredible complexity uh not create incredible
complexity emerges so one of the simplest things to do that with is uh cellular automata
and there's I don't know what it is and maybe you can speak to it we can certainly we will
certainly talk about the implications of this but there's so few things that are as awe inspiring to
me as knowing the rules of a system and not being able to predict what the heck it looks like and it
creates incredibly beautiful complexity that when zoomed out on looks like there's actual organisms
doing things that are much uh that operate on a scale much higher than the underlying mechanism
so with cellular automata that's cells that are born and die born or die and they only know about
each other's neighbors and there's simple rules that govern that interaction of birth and death
and then they create at scale organisms that look like they take up hundreds or thousands of cells
and they're moving they're moving around they're communicating they're sending signals to each other
and you forget at moment of time before you remember that the simple rules on cells is all
that it took to create that that's it's sad in that we can't come up with a simple description of that
system that generalizes the behavior of the large organisms we can only come up with
can only hope to come up with the thing the fundamental physics or the fundamental rules
of that system i suppose it's sad that we can't predict everything we know about the mathematics
of those systems it seems like we can't really in a nice way like economics tries to do to predict
how this whole thing will unroll but it's beautiful because how simple it is underneath it all
so what do you make of the emergence of complexity from simple rules what the hell is that about
yeah well we can see that something like flocking behavior the murmuration can can be computer
coded it's not a very hard set of rules to be able to see some of those really amazing types of
complexity and the whole field of complexity science and some of the sub disciplines like
stigmer g are are studying how following fairly simple responses to a pheromone signal do ant
colonies do this amazing thing where the what what you might describe as the organizational
or computational capacity of the colony is so profound relative to what each individual
ants is doing i am not um anywhere near as well versed in the cutting edge of cellular
automatas i would like unfortunately i in terms of topics that i would like to get to and haven't
like uh et's more um all forms a new kind of science i have only skimmed and read reviews of
and not read the whole thing or his newer work since um but his idea of the four basic kind of
categories of uh emergent phenomena that can come from cellular automata and that one of them is
kind of interesting and looks a lot like complexity rather than just chaos or homogeneity or um
self-termination or whatever i think this is very interesting it does not instantly make
me think that uh biology is operating on a similarly small set of rules and or that human
consciousness is i'm i'm not that reductionistly oriented and um so if you look at say santa fe
institute one of the co-founders stewart kaufman um his work he should you should really get him on
your show so a lot of the questions that you like one of kaufman's you know more recent books after
investigations and some of the real fundamental stuff was called reinventing the sacred and it
had to do with some of these exact questions uh in kind of non-reductionist approach but that is not
just silly hippie ism um and he was very interested in highly non-argodic systems where
you couldn't take a lot of behavior over a small period of time and predict what the behavior of
subsets over a longer period of time would do um and then going further someone who spent
some time at santa fe institute and then kind of made a whole new field that you should have on
dave snowden who some people call the father of anthro complexity or what is the complexity
unique to humans uh he says something to the effect of that modeling humans as termites really
doesn't cut it like we we we don't respond exactly identically to the same pheromone stimulus using
stigmer g like it works for flows of traffic and some very simple human behaviors but it really
doesn't work for trying to make sense of the sistine chapel and picasso and general relativity
creation and stuff like that and it's because the the termites are not doing abstraction forecasting
deep into the future and making choices now based on forecasts of the future not just adaptive
signals in the moment and evolutionary code from history that's really different right like making
choices now that can factor deep modeling of the future um and with humans our uniqueness
one to the next in terms of response to similar stimuli is much higher than it is with a termite
um one of the interesting things there is that their uniqueness is extremely low they're basically
fungible within a class right there's different classes but within a class they're basically
fungible and their system uses that very high numbers and lots of um loss right lots of death
the termite feels that way don't you think we humans are deceiving ourselves about our uniqueness
perhaps it doesn't just isn't there some sense in which this emergence just creates different
higher and higher levels of abstraction where every at every layer each organism feels unique
is that possible that we're all equally dumb but at different scales no i think uniqueness is evolving
hmm i think that hydrogen atoms are more similar to each other than cells of the same type are and
i think that cells are more similar to each other than humans are and i think that highly
k selected species are more unique than r selected species so they're different evolutionary
processes the r selected species where you have a whole a lot of death and very high birth rates
you're not looking for as much individuality within or individual possible expression to cover
the evolutionary search space within an individual you're looking at it more in terms of a numbers
game um so yeah i would say there's probably more difference between one orca and the next
than there is between one cape buffalo and the next given that it would be interesting to get
your thoughts about mimetic theory where we're imitating each other
in the context of this idea of uniqueness how much truth is there to that how compelling is
this world view to you of gerardian mimetic theory of desire where maybe you can explain it from
your perspective but it seems like imitating each other is the fundamental property of the
behavior of human civilization well imitation is not unique to humans right monkeys imitate
so a certain amount of learning through observing is not unique to humans humans do more of it
it's actually kind of worth speaking to this for a moment um monkeys can learn new behaviors new
we've even seen teaching an ape sign language and then the ape teaching other apes sign language
so that's a kind of mimesis right kind of learning through imitation and that needs to happen if they
need to learn or develop capacities that are not just coded by their genetics right so within the
same genome they're learning new things based on the environment and so based on someone else learn
something first and so let's pick it up uh how much a creature is the result of just its genetic
programming and how much it's learning is a very interesting question and i think this is a place
where humans really show up radically different than everything else and you can see it in the
in the neoteny how long we're basically fetal um that a the closest ancestors to us if we look at a
chimp a chimp can hold on to its mother's fur while she moves around day one and obviously we see
horses up and walking within 20 minutes the fact that it takes a human a year to be walking and it
takes a horse 20 minutes and you say how many multiples of 20 minutes go into a year like that's
a long period of helplessness that it wouldn't work for a horse right like they or anything else
and and not only could we not hold on to mom in the first day it's three months before we can move
our head volitionally um so it's like why why are we embryonic for so long basically it's like
like it's still fetal on the outside had to be because couldn't keep growing inside and actually
ever get out with big heads and narrower hips from going upright um so here's a place where
there's a coevolution of the pattern of humans specifically here are our neoteny and what that
portends to learning with our being toolmaking and environment modifying creatures which is because
we have the abstraction to make tools we change our environments more than other creatures change
their environments the next most environment modifying creature tusks is like a beaver and then
you wear an la you fly into lax and you look at the just orthogonal grid going on forever in all
directions and you know we we've recently come into the Anthropocene where the surface of the
earth is changing more from human activity than geological activity and then beavers and you're
like okay wow we're really in a class of our own in terms of environment modifying yeah um so as
soon as we started toolmaking we were able to change our environments much more radically we
could put on clothes and go to a cold place right and this is really important because
we actually went and became apex predators in every environment we functioned like apex predators
but polar bear can't leave the Arctic right and the the lion can't leave the savannah and an orca
can't leave the ocean and we went became apex predators in all those environments because of
our tool creation capacity we could become better predators than them adapted to the environment or
at least with our tools adapted to the environment so then every aspect towards any organism in any
environment were incredibly good at becoming apex predators yes and nothing else can do that kind
of thing there there is no other apex predator that you see the other apex predator is only getting
better at being a predator through evolutionary process that's super slow and that super slow
process creates co-selective process with their environment so as the predator becomes a tiny
bit faster it eats more of the slow prey the genes of the fast prey and breed and the prey becomes
faster and so there's this kind of balancing and we in because of our tool making we increased our
predatory capacity faster than anything else could increase its resilience to it as a result we
started out stripping the environment and extincting species following stone tools and going and
becoming apex predator everywhere this is why we can't keep applying apex predator theories because
we're not an apex predator we're an apex predator but we're something much more than that um like
just for an example the the top apex predator in the world in orca an orca can eat one big fish at
a time like one tuna and it'll miss most of the time or one seal and we can put a mile long drift
net out on a single boat and pull up an entire school of them right we can deplete the entire
oceans of them that's not an orca right like that's not an apex predator um and that's not even
including that we can then genetically engineer different creatures we can extinct species we can
devastate whole ecosystems we can make built worlds that have no natural things that are just
human built worlds we can build new types of natural creatures synthetic life so we are much
more like little gods than we are like apex predators now but we're still behaving as apex
predators and little gods that behave as apex predators causes a problem kind of core to my
assessment of the world so what does it mean to be a predator so a predator is uh somebody that
effectively can mine the resources from a place so for their survival or is it also just purely
like higher level objectives of violence and what is can predators be predators towards
the same each other towards the same species like are we think are we using the word predator
sort of generally which then connects to conflict and uh military conflict violent conflict
in the space of uh human species obviously we can say that plants are mining the resources of
their environment in a particular way using photosynthesis to be able to pull minerals
out of the soil and nitrogen and carbon out of the air and like that um and we can say herbivores
are being able to mine and concentrate that so I wouldn't say mining the environment is unique
to predator predator is you know uh
generally being defined as mining other animals right we don't consider herbivores predators
but um animal which requires some type of violence capacity because animals move plants don't move
so requires some capacity to overtake something that can move and try to get away
we'll go back to the juridzing then we'll come back here why are we neoteness why are we embryonic
for so long because are we did we just move from the savannah to the arctic and we need to learn
new stuff if we came genetically programmed we would not be able to do that are we throwing
spears or are we fishing or are we running an industrial supply chain or are we texting what
is the adaptive behavior horses today in the wild and horses 10 000 years ago are doing pretty
much the same stuff and so since we make tools and we evolve our tools and then change our
environment so quickly and other animals are largely the result of their environment but
we're environment modifying so rapidly we need to come without too much programming so we can
learn the environment we're in learn the language right which is uh gonna be very important learn
the tool making learn the um and so we have a very long period of relative helpless of helplessness
because we aren't coded how to behave yet because we're imprinting a lot of software on how to
behave that is useful to that particular time so our mimesis is not it's not unique to humans but
the total amount of it is really unique and this is also where the uniqueness can go up right is
because we are less just the result of the genetics and that means the kind of learning
through history that they got coded in genetics and more the result of it's almost like our hardware
selected for software right like if evolution is kind of doing these think of as a hardware
selection i have problems with computer metaphors for biology but i'll use this one here um that
we have not had hardware changes since the beginning of sapiens but our world is really
really different and that's all changes in software right changes in on the same fundamental genetic
substrate what we're doing with these brains and minds and bodies and social groups and like that
and so um now giord specifically was looking at when we watch other people talking so we
learn language you and i would have a hard time learning mandarin today or it'd take a lot of
work we'd be learning how to conjugate verbs and stuff but a baby learns it instantly without
anyone even really trying to teach it just through mimesis so it's a it's a powerful thing
they're obviously more neuroplastic than we are when they're doing that and all their
attention is allocated to that but they're also learning how to move their bodies and
they're learning all kinds of stuff through mimesis one of the things that giord says is
they're also learning what to want and they learn what to want they learn desire by watching
what other people want and so intrinsic to this people end up wanting what other people want
and if we can't have what other people have without taking it away from them then that
becomes a source of conflict so the mimesis of desire is the fundamental generator of conflict
and then the conflict energy within a group of people will build over time this is a very very
crude interpretation of the theory can we just pause on that for people who are not familiar
and for me who hasn't i'm loosely familiar but haven't internalized it but every time i think
about it's a very compelling view of the world whether it's true or not it's quite
it's like when you take everything Freud says as truth it's a very interesting way to think about
the world and in the same way thinking about the memetic theory of desire that everything we want
is imitation of other people's wants we don't have any original wants we're constantly imitating
others and so and not just others but you know others we're exposed to so there's these like
little local pockets however defined local of people like imitating each other and one that's
super empowering because then you can pick which group you can join like what what do you want to
imitate it's it's uh it's the old like you know whoever your friends are that's what your life
is gonna be like that's really powerful i mean it's depressing that we're so unoriginal but it's
also liberating in that if this holds true that we can choose our life by choosing the people we
hang out with so okay thoughts that are very compelling that seem like they're more absolute
than they actually are end up also being dangerous we want communism i'm i'm gonna discuss here where
i think we need to amend this particular theory but specifically you just said something that
everyone who's paid attention knows is true experientially which is who you're around
affects who you become and as as libertarian and self-determining and sovereign as we'd like to be
everybody i think knows that if you got put in the maximum security prison aspects of your
personality would have to adapt or you wouldn't survive there right you would become different if
you were if if you grew up in dar four versus finland you would be different with your same
genetics like just just no real question about that um and that even today if you hang out in a
place with ultramarathoners as your roommates or um all people who are obese as your roommates
the statistical likelihood of what happens to your fitness is pretty clear right like the
behavioral science of this is pretty clear so uh the whole saying we are the average of the five
people we spend the most time around i think the more self-reflective someone is and the more time
they spend by themselves in self-reflection the less this is true but it's still true so one of the
best things someone can do to become more self-determined is be self-determined about the
environments they want to put themselves in because to the degree that there is some self-determination
and some determination by the environment don't be fighting an environment that is predisposing
you in bad directions try to put yourself in an environment that is predisposing the things
that you want in turn try to affect the environment in ways to predispose positive things for those
around you or perhaps also to there's probably interesting ways to play with this you could
probably put yourself like form connections that have this perfect tension in all directions to
where you're actually free to decide whatever the heck you want because the set of wants
within your circle of interactions is so conflicting that you're free to choose whichever
one so if there's enough tension as opposed to everybody aligned like a flock of birds
yeah i mean you definitely want that all of the dialectics would be balanced
so if you have someone who is extremely oriented to self-empowerment and someone who is extremely
oriented to kind of empathy and compassion both the dialectic of those is better than either of
them on their own if you have both of them inhabiting being inhabited better than you by
the same person spending time around that person will probably do well for you i think the thing
you just mentioned is super important when it comes to cognitive schools which is
i think one of the fastest things people can do to improve their learning and they're not just
cognitive learning but their meaningful problem solving communication and civic capacity capacity
to participate as a citizen with other people and making the world better is to be seeking
dialectical synthesis all the time and so in the hegelian sense if you have a thesis
you have an antithesis so maybe we have libertarianism on one side and marxist kind
of communism on the other side and one is arguing that the individual is the unit of choice and so
we want to increase the freedom and support of individual choice because as they make more
agentic choices it'll produce a better hole for everybody the other side saying well the
individuals are conditioned by their environment who would choose to be born into darfur rather
than finland so we actually need to collectively make environments that are good because that the
environment conditions the individuals so you have a thesis and an antithesis and then hegel's
ideas you have a synthesis which is a kind of higher order truth that understands how those
relate in a way that neither of them do and so it is actually at a higher order of complexity
so the first part would be can i steal man each of these can i argue each one well enough
that the proponents of it are like totally you got that and not just argue it rhetorically but
can i inhabit it where i can try to see and feel the world the way someone seeing and feeling the
world that way would because once i do then i don't want to screw those people because there's
truth in it right and i'm not going to go back to war with them i'm going to go to finding solutions
it could actually work at a higher order if i don't go to a higher order then there's war
and but then the higher order thing would be well it seems like the individual does affect
the commons and the collective and other people it also seems like the collective conditions
individuals at least statistically and i can cherry pick out the one guy who got out of the ghetto
and pulled himself up by his bootstraps but i can also say statistically that most people born
into the ghetto show up differently than most people born into the hamptons and so unless you
want to argue that and have you take your child from the hamptons and put them in the ghetto then
like come on be realistic about this thing so how do we make we don't want social systems that make
weak dependent individuals right the welfare argument but we also don't want no social system
that supports individuals to do better we want we don't want individuals where their self-expression
and agency fucks the environment and everybody else and employs slave labor and whatever so can
we make it to where individuals are creating holes that are better for conditioning other
individuals can we make it to where we have holes that are conditioning increased agency and sovereignty
right that would be the synthesis so the thing that i'm coming to here is if people have that as
a frame and sometimes it's not just thesis nante thesis it's like eight different views right
can i steal man each view this is not just can i take the perspective but am i seeking them am i
actively trying to inhabit other people's perspective then can i really try to essentialize
it and argue the the best points of it both the sense making about reality and the values
why these values actually matter then just like i want to seek those perspectives then i want to
seek is there a higher order set of understandings that could fulfill the values of and synthesize
the sense making of all of them simultaneously maybe i won't get it but i want to be seeking it
and i want to be seeking progressively better ones so this is perspective seeking driving
perspective taking and then seeking synthesis i think that that one cognitive disposition might
be the most helpful thing would you put a title dialectic synthesis on that process because that
seems to be such a part so like this rigorous empathy like like it's not just empathy it's
empathy with rigor like you really want to understand and embody different worldviews and
then try to find a higher order synthesis okay so i remember last night you told me when we first
met uh you said that you looked in somebody's eyes and you felt that you had suffered in some
ways that they had suffered and so you could trust them shared pathos right creates a certain sense
of kind of shared bonding and shared intimacy so empathy is actually feeling the suffering of
somebody else and feeling the the depth of their sentience so i don't want to fuck them anymore
and i mean i hurt them i don't want to behave in a i don't want my proposition to go through
when i go and inhabit the perspective of the other people they feel that's really going to
mess them up right and so the rigorous empathy it's different than just compassion which is i
generally care like i have a generalized care but i don't know what it's like to be them i can
never know what it's like to be them perfectly and that there's a humility you have to have which is
my most rigorous attempt is still not it my most rigorous attempt mine to know what it's like to
be a woman is still not it i have no question that if i was actually a woman it would be different
than my best guesses i have no question if i was actually black it's be different than my best guesses
so there's a humility in that which keeps me listening because i don't think that i know fully
but i want to and i'm going to keep trying better to and then i want to across them and
then i want to say is there a way we can forward together and not have to be in more it has to
be something that could meet the values that everyone holds it could reconcile the partial
sense making that everyone holds and they could offer a way forward that is more agreeable than
the partial perspectives at war with each other but the so the more you succeeded this empathy
with humility the more you're carrying the burden of their of other people's pain essentially
now this goes back to the question of do i see us as one being or 7.8 billion
i think them
if i'm overwhelmed with my own pain i can't empathize that much because i don't have the bandwidth i
don't have the capacity if i don't feel like i can do something about a particular problem
in the world it's hard to feel it because it's just too devastating and so a lot of people go numb
and even go nihilistic because they just don't feel the agency so as i actually become more empowered
as an individual and have more sense of agency i also become more empowered to be more empathetic
for others and be more connected to that shared burden and want to be able to make choices on
behalf of and in and in benefit of so this way of living seems like a way of living that would
solve a lot of problems in society from a cellular automata perspective so if you have a bunch of
little like little agents behaving in this way my intuition there'll be interesting complexities
that emerge but my intuition is it will create a society that's very different and recognizably
better than the one we have today how much um like oh wait hold that question because i want
to come back to it but this brings us back to jarred which we didn't answer the conflict theory
yes because about how to get past the conflict theory yes you know the robert for us poem about
the two paths he never had enough time to return back to the other we're gonna have to do that
quite a lot we're gonna be uh living that poem over and over again but yes how how to uh let's
return back okay so the rest of the argument goes you learn to want what other people want
therefore fundamental conflict based in our desire because we want the thing that somebody else has
and then people are can they're in conflict over trying to get the same stuff power status
attention physical stuff a mate whatever it is and then the we learn the conflict by watching
and so then the conflict becomes a medic so the and you know we become on the palestinian side of
the israeli side of the communist the capitalist side or the left or right politically or whatever
it is and until eventually the conflict energy in the system builds up so much that some type of
violence is needed to get the bad guy whoever it is that we're going to blame and you know jarred
talks about why scapegoating was kind of a mechanism to minimize the amount of violence let's blame
let's blame it a a scapegoat as being more relevant than they really were but if we all
believe it then we can all kind of calm down with the conflict energy it's a really interesting
concept by the way i mean you went you beautifully summarized it but the idea that there's a scapegoat
that there's a this kind of thing naturally still conflict and then they find the other some group
that's the other that's either real artificial as the cause of the conflict well it's always
artificial because the cause of the conflict in jarred is the mimesis of desire itself and how
do we attack that how do we attack that it's our own desire so this now gets to something more like
buddha said right which was desire is the cause of suffering um jarred and buddha would kind of
agree in this way so and so but that's that explains i mean again it's a compelling description
of human history that we do tend to come up with the other and uh okay kind of i just i just had
such a funny experience with someone critiquing jarred the other day in such a elegant and
beautiful and simple way it's a a friend who's uh grew up aboriginal australian uh as a scholar of
aboriginal social technologies and he's like nah man jarred just made shit up about how tribes
worked like we come from a tribe we've got tens of thousands of years and we didn't have increasing
conflict and then scapegoat and kill someone we'd have a little bit of conflict and then we would
dance and then everybody'd be fine like we'd dance around the campfire everyone would like
kind of physically get the energy out we'd look in each other's eyes we'd have positive bonding
and then we're fine and nobody nobody no scapegoats and i think that's called the joe rogan theory of
desire which is uh he's like all all of human problems have to do with the fact that you don't
do enough hard shit in your day uh so maybe maybe just dance it because he says like doing
exercise and running on that treadmill gets gets all the demons out maybe just dance and gets all
the demons out so this is why i say we have to be careful with taking an idea that seems too
explanatory and then taking it as a given and then saying well now that we're stuck with the fact that
conflict is inexorable because human because mimetic desire and therefore how do we deal with
the inexorability of the conflict and how to sublimate violence well no the whole thing might
be actually gibberish meaning it's only true in certain conditions and other conditions it's not
true so the deeper question is under which conditions is that true under which conditions is
it not true what do those other conditions make possible and look like and in general we should
stay away from really compelling models of reality because there's something about about our brains
that these models become sticky and we can't even think outside of them so it's not that we stay away
from them it's that we know that the model of reality is never reality that's the key thing
humility again it goes back to just having the humility that you don't have a perfect model of
reality there's an the model of reality could never be reality the process of modeling is inherently
information reduction and i can never show that the unknown unknown set has been factored
it's back to the cellular automata you can't you can't put the genie back in the bottle like
when you realize it's unfortunately sadly impossible to
to create a model of cellular automata even if you know the basic rules
that predict to even any degree of accuracy what how that system will evolve which is fascinating
mathematically sorry i i think about it quite a lot it's very annoying wolfram has this rule 30
like you should be able to predict it it's so simple but you can't predict what's going to be
like there's a there's a problem he defines like try to predict some aspect of the middle
middle column of the system just anything about it what's going to happen in the future and you
can't you can't it sucks because then we can't make sense of this world you know really in a
reality in a definitive way it's always like in the striving like it we're always striving
yeah i don't think this sucks that so that's a feature not a bug
well that's assuming a designer um i would say i don't think it sucks i think it's
not only beautiful but maybe necessary for beauty the mess so you're uh so you're
you're just a great jordan pierce and you should clean up your room so you like the rooms messy
it's uh it's essential for the for beauty it's not it's not that it's okay i take i have no idea
if it was intended this way and so i'm just interpreting it a way i like the commandment
about having no false idols to me the way i interpret that is meaningful is that reality
sacred to me i have a reverence for reality but i know my best understanding of it is never complete
i know my best model of it is a model where i tried to make some kind of predictive capacity
by reducing the complexity of it to a set of stuff that i could observe and then a subset
of that stuff that i thought was the causal dynamics and then some set of you know mechanisms
that are involved and what we find is that it can be super useful like newtonian gravity can
help us do ballistic curves and all kinds of super useful stuff and then we get to the place where it
doesn't explain what's happening at the cosmological scale or at a quantum scale and at each time what
we're finding is uh we exclude itself and it also doesn't explain the reconciliation of gravity
with quantum mechanics and the other kind of fundamental laws and the so models can be useful
but they're never true with a capital t meaning they're never an actual real full they're never
a complete description of what's happening in real systems they can be a complete description
of what's happening in an artificial system that was the result of applying a model so the model
of a circuit board and the circuit board are the same thing but i would argue that the model of a
cell and the cell are not the same thing and i would say this is key to what we call complexity
versus the complicated which is a distinction davis noden made well in defining the difference
between simple complicated complex and chaotic systems but one of the definers in complex systems
is that no matter how you model the complex system it will still have some emergent behavior
not predicted by the model can you elaborate on the complex versus the complicated complicated
means we can fully explicate the phase space of all the things that it can do we can program it
all human not all for the most part human built things are complicated they don't self organize
they don't self repair they're not self evolving and we can make a blueprint for them
where sorry for human systems for human technologies human technologies sorry it's okay so so
non that are basically the application of models right right and engineering is kind of applied
science science as the modeling process and but with but humans are complex complex stuff with
biological type stuff um and sociological type stuff it more has generator functions
and even those can't be fully explicated then it has or our explication can't prove that it
has closure of what would be in the unknown unknown set where we keep finding like oh it's
just the genome oh well now it's the genome and the epigenome and then a recursive change on the
epigenome because of the proteome and then there's mitochondrial dna and then virus is affected and
fuck right so it's like we get overexcited when we think we found the thing so on facebook you
know how you can list your relationship is complicated it should actually say it's it's
complex that's the more accurate description you uh self terminating is a really interesting idea
that you talk about quite a bit first of all what is a self terminating system and i think you have
a sense correct me if i'm wrong that human civilization as it currently is is a self terminating
system why do you have that intuition combined with the definition of what's of self terminating
means okay so if we look at human societies historically human civilizations uh it's not
that hard to realize that most of the major civilizations and empires of the past don't
exist anymore so they had a life cycle they died for some reason so we don't still have any
the early egyptian empire or inka or maya or aztec or any of those right and so
they they terminated sometimes it seems like they were terminated from the outside in war
sometimes it seems like they self terminate when we look at easter island it was a self
termination um so let's go ahead and take an island situation if i have an island
and we are consuming the resources on that island faster than the resources can replicate
themselves and there's a finite space there that system is going to self terminate it's not
gonna be able to keep doing that thing because you'll get to a place of there's no resources left
and then you get uh so now if i'm utilizing the resources faster than they can replicate
or faster than they can replenish and i'm actually growing our population in the process
so i'm even increasing the rate of the utilization of resources i might get an exponential curve and
then hit a wall and then just collapse the exponential curve rather than do an s curve
or some other kind of thing um so self terminating system is any system that depends upon a substrate
system that is debasing its own substrate that is debasing what it depends upon
so you're right that uh if you look at empires they rise and fall throughout human history
but but not this time bro where this one's gonna last forever that's
i like that idea i think that if we don't understand why all the previous ones failed we
can't ensure that and so i think it's very important to understand it well so that we can
have that be a designed outcome with some what decent probability so we're it's sort of in terms
of consuming the resources on the island we're a clever bunch and we keep coming up
especially when the on the horizon there is a termination point we keep coming up with clever
ways of avoiding disaster of avoiding collapse of constructing this is where technological
innovation this is where growth comes in coming up with different ways to improve productivity and
the way society functions such that we consume less resources or get a lot more from the resources we
have so there's some sense in which there's a human ingenuity is a source for optimism
about the future of this particular system that uh that may not be self terminating if if there's
more innovation than there is consumption so um over consumption of resources just one way I think
can self-terminate we're just kind of starting here but um there are reasons for optimism and
pessimism then they're both worth understanding and there's failure modes on understanding either
without the other um as we mentioned previously there there's what I would call naive techno
optimism naive techno capital optimism that says uh stuff just has been getting better and better
and we wouldn't want to live in the dark ages and tech has done all this awesome stuff and
we know the proponents of those models and that stuff is going to kind of keep getting better
of course there are problems but human ingenuity rises to its apply and demand will solve the
problems whatever would you put rick or as well on that or in that bucket is there some
specific people you have in mind or naive optimism is truly naive to where you're
essentially just have an optimism that's blind to any kind of realities of the way technology
progresses I don't think that anyone who thinks about it and writes about it is perfectly naive
gotcha but there might play time it's a platonic ideal there there might be a bias in the nature
of the assessment I would also say there's kind of naive techno pessimism and there are
um critics of technology I mean you read the unabomber's manifesto on why technology can't
not result in our self termination so we have to take it out before it gets any further um
but also if you read a lot of the ex-risk community you know boss drum and friends uh it's like our
total number of existential risks and the total probability of them is going up
and so I think that there are we have to hold together where our positive possibilities and
our risk possibilities are both increasing and then say for the positive possibilities to be
realized long term all of the catastrophic risks have to not happen any of the catastrophic risks
happening is enough to keep that positive outcome from occurring so how do we ensure that none of
them happen if we want to say let's have a civilization that doesn't collapse so again
collapse theory it's worth looking at books like um the collapse of complex societies by
joseph tainter it does an analysis of that many of the societies fell for internal institutional
decay civilizational decay reasons um baudrillard in simulation in simulacra looks at a very different
way of looking at how institutional decay and the collective intelligence of a system happens and
it becomes kind of more internally parasitic on itself um obviously jarrod diamond made a more
popular book called collapse um and as we were mentioning the anti-catharia mechanism has been
getting attention in the news lately but it's like a 2000 year old clock right like like metal gears
and does that mean we lost like 1500 years of technological progress um and from a society that
was relatively technologically advanced um so what i'm interested in here is being able to say okay
well why did previous societies fail can we understand that abstractly enough that we can
make a civilizational model that isn't just trying to solve one type of failure but solve the
underlying things that generate the failures as a whole are there some underlying generator functions
or patterns that would make a system self-terminating and can we solve those and have that be the
kernel of a new civilizational model that is not self-terminating and can we then be able to actually
look at the categories of extras we're aware of and see that we actually have resilience in the
presence of those not just resilience but anti fragility and i would say for the optimism to
be grounded it has to actually be able to understand the risk space well and have adequate solutions
for it so can we try to dig into some basic intuitions about the underlying sources of catastrophic
failures of the system and overconsumption that's built in into self-terminating systems so both
the overconsumption which is like the slow death and then then there's the fast death of nuclear
war and all those kinds of things a agi biotech bioengineering nanotechnology nano my favorite
nano bots okay nano bots are my favorite because it sounds so cool to me that i could just know
that i would be one of the scientists that would be full steam ahead in building them without
sufficiently thinking about the negative consequence i would definitely be i would be
podcasting all about the negative consequences but when i go back home i'd be i just in my heart
know the amount of excitement is a dumb descendant of ape no offense to apes uh so i want to backtrack
on my previous comments about uh negative comments about apes uh that i have that sense of excitement
that would result in problems so sorry a lot of things said but what's can we start to pull
it a thread because you've also provided kind of a beautiful general approach to this which is this
dialectic synthesis or just rigorous empathy whatever whatever word we want to put to it
that seems to be from the individual perspective is one way to sort of live in the world as we
try to figure out how to construct non-self-terminating systems so what what are some underlying sources
yeah first i have to say uh i i actually really respect Drexler for emphasizing gray goo and
engines of creation back in the day um to make sure the world was paying adequate attention to
the risks of the the nanotech um as someone who was right at the cutting edge of what could be
there's definitely game theoretic advantage to those who focus on the opportunities and
don't focus on the risks or pretend there aren't risks um because they get to market first um and
then they externalize all of the costs through limited liability or whatever it is to the commons
or wherever happen to have it other people are going to have to solve those but now they have
the power and capital associated the person who looked at the risks and tried to do better design
and go slower um is probably not going to move into positions of as much power influence as quickly
so this one of the issues we have to deal with is some of the the bad game theoretic dispositions
in the system relative to its own um stability and the key aspect to that sorry to interrupt is
the externalities generated yes what flavors of catastrophic risk are we talking about here
what's your favorite flavor in terms of ice cream so mine is coconut nobody seems to like
coconut ice cream uh so ice cream aside what's uh what do you most worry about there's a catastrophic
risk that will help us kind of um make concrete the the the discussion we're having about how
to fix this whole thing yeah i think it's worth taking a historical perspective briefly to just
kind of orient everyone to it we don't have to um go all the way back to the aliens who've seen all
of civilization but to just recognize that um for all of human history as far as we're aware
there were existential risks to civilizations and they happened right like there were civilizations
that were killed in war um that tribes that were killed in tribal warfare whatever so
people faced existential risk to the group that they identified with it's just those were local
phenomena right they it wasn't a fully global phenomena so an empire could fall in surrounding
empires didn't fall maybe they came in filled the space um the first time that we were able to
think about catastrophic risk not from like a solar flare or something that we couldn't control but
from something that humans would actually create at a global level was world war two in the bomb
because it was the first time that we had tech big enough that could actually
mess up everything at a global level that could mess up habitability we just weren't
powerful enough to do that before it's it's not that we didn't behave in ways that would have
done it we just only behaved in those ways at the scale we could affect and so it's important to get
that there's the entire world before world war two where we don't have the ability to make a
non-habitable biosphere non-habitable for us and then there's world war two and the beginning
of a completely new phase where global human-induced catastrophic risk is now a real thing
and that was such a big deal that it changed the entire world in a really fundamental way
which is you know when you study history it's amazing how big a percentage of history is
studying war right in the the history of wars you study european history and whatever it's generals
and wars and empire expansions and and so the the major empires near each other never had really
long periods of time where they weren't engaged in war or preparation for war or something like
that was humans don't have a good precedent in the post-tribal phase the civilization phase of
being able to solve conflicts without war for very long world war two was the first time where
we could have a war that no one could win and so the superpowers couldn't fight again they couldn't
do a real kinetic war they could do diplomatic wars and cold war type stuff and they could fight
proxy wars through other countries that didn't have the big weapons and so mutually assured
destruction and like coming out of world war two we actually realized that nation states couldn't
prevent world war and so we needed a new type of of supervening government in addition to nation
states which was the whole bread and woods world the united nations the world bank the imf the
globalization trade type agreements mutually assured destruction that was how do we have
some coordination beyond just nation states between them since we have to stop war between at
least the superpowers and it was pretty successful given that we've had like 75 years of no superpower
on superpower war um we've had lots of proxy wars during that time we've had you know cold war
and i would say we're in a new phase now where the bread and wood solution is basically over
almost over being described the bread was solution yeah so the bread and woods the series of agreements
for how the nations would be able to engage with each other in a solution other than war
was these igos these intergovernmental organizations and was the idea of globalization
since we could have global effects we needed to be able to think about things globally
where we had trade relationships with each other where it would not be profitable
to war with each other it'd be more profitable to actually be able to trade with each other so our own
self-interest was you know going to drive our non-war interest um and so this started to look like
and obviously this this couldn't have happened that much earlier either because industrialization
hadn't gotten far enough to be able to do massive global industrial supply chains and ships stuff
around you know quickly but like we were mentioning earlier almost all the electronics that we
used today just basic cheap stuff for us is made on six continents made in many countries there's
no single country in the world that could actually make many of the things that we have and from the
raw material extraction to the plastics and polymers and the you know etc and so the idea
the idea that we made a world that could do that kind of trade and create massive gdp growth we
could all work together to be able to mine natural resources and grow stuff with the rapid gdp growth
there was the idea that everybody could keep having more without having to take each other stuff
and so that that was part of kind of the the breton woods post world war two model the other was
that we would be so economically interdependent that blowing each other up would never make sense
that worked for a while now it also brought us up into planetary boundaries faster the
unrenovable use of resource and turning those resources into pollution on the other side of
the supply chain so obviously that faster gdp growth meant uh the overfishing of the oceans
and the cutting down of the trees and the climate change and the uh mining toxic mining tailings
going into the water and the mountaintop removal mining and all those types of things that's the
overall consumption side of the of the risk that we're talking about and so the answer of let's do
positive gdp is the answer rapidly and exponentially obviously accelerated the planetary boundary side
and that started to be that that was thought about for a long time but it started to be modeled
with the club of rome and limits of growth um and it but it's just very obvious to say if you
have a linear materials economy where you take stuff out of the earth faster whether it's fish or
trees or or or and you take or oil and you take it out of the earth faster than it can replenish
itself and you turn it into trash after using it for a short period of time you put the trash in
the environment faster than it can process itself and there's toxicity associated with both sides
of this you can't run an exponentially growing linear materials economy on a finite planet forever
that's not a hard thing to figure out and it has to be exponential if there's an exponentiation
the monetary supply because of interest and then fractional reserve banking and to then be able to
keep up with the growing monetary supply you have to have growth of goods and services and so that's
that kind of thing that has happened um but you also see that when you get these supply chains
that are so interconnected across the world you get increased fragility because a a collapse or
problem in one area then affects the whole world in a much bigger area as opposed to the issues
being local right so we got to see with covid and an issue that started in one part of china
affecting the whole world so much more rapidly than would have happened before breton woods right
before international travel supply chains you know that whole kind of thing and with a bunch of
second and third order effects that people wouldn't have predicted okay we have to stop
certain kinds of travel because of viral contaminants but the countries doing agriculture depend upon
fertilizer they don't produce that is shipped into them and depend upon pesticides they don't
produce so we got both crop failures and crops being eaten by locusts in scale in northern
africa and iran and things like that because they couldn't get the supplies of stuff in so then you
get massive starvation or future kind of hunger issues because of supply chain shutdowns so you
get this increased fragility and cascade dynamics where a small problem can end up leading to cascade
effects and also we went from two superpowers with one catastrophe weapon to now that same
catastrophe weapon is there's more countries that have it eight or nine countries that have it and
there's a lot more types of catastrophe weapons we now have catastrophe weapons with
weaponized drones that can hit infrastructure targets with bio with in fact every new type of
tech has created an arms race so we have not with the un or the other kind of intergovernmental
organizations we haven't been able to really do nuclear deproliferation we've actually had more
countries get nukes and keep getting faster nukes the race to hypersonics and things like that
um and every new type of technology that has emerged has created an arms race and so you
can't do mutually assured destruction with multiple agents the way you can with two agents
two agents it's a much easier to create a stable Nash equilibrium that's forced but the ability
to modern say if these guys shoot who do i shoot do i shoot them do i shoot everybody do i and so
you get a three-body problem you get a very complex type of thing when you have multiple agents and
multiple different types of catastrophe weapons including ones that can be much more easily
produced than nukes nukes are really hard to produce there's only uranium in a few areas
uranium enrichment is hard icbm's are hard but weaponized drones hitting smart targets is not
so hard there's a lot of other things where basically the scale at being able to manufacture
them is going way way down to where even non-state actors can have them and so when we talk about
exponential tech and the decentralization of exponential tech what that means is
decentralized catastrophe weapon capacity and especially in a world of increasing numbers of
people feeling disenfranchised frantic whatever for different reasons so uh i would say where the
Bretton Woods world doesn't prepare us to be able to deal with lots of different agents having
lots of different types of catastrophe weapons you can't put mutually assured destruction on
where you can't keep doing growth of the materials economy in the same way because
of hitting planetary boundaries and where the fragility dynamics are actually now their own
source of catastrophic risk so now we're so like there was all the world until world war two and
world war two is just from a from a civilization timescale point of view is just a second ago
it seems like a long time but it is really not we get a short period of relative peace at the
level of superpowers while building up the military capacity for much much much worse
war the entire time and then now we're at this new phase where the things that allowed us to make
it through the nuclear power are not the same systems that will let us make it through the next
stage so what is this next post Bretton Woods how how do we become safe vessels safe stewards
of many different types of exponential technology is uh a key question when we're thinking about
x-risk okay so and i'd like to try to answer the how a few thought a few ways but first
on the mutually assured destruction do you give credit to the idea of two superpowers
not blowing each other up with nuclear weapons to the simple game theoretic model of mutually
assured destruction or something you've said previously this idea of inverse correlation
which i tend to believe between the now you were talking about tech but i think it's
maybe broadly true the inverse correlation between competence and propensity for destruction so
the better the the the bigger your weapons not because you're afraid of mutually assured
self-destruction but because we're human beings and there's a deep moral fortitude there that's
somehow aligned with competence and being good at your job that like it's very hard to be uh
a psychopath and be good at killing at scale is do you share any of that intuition kind of
i think most people would say that alexander the great and gang is con and napoli and were
effective people that were good at their job uh that were actually maybe asymmetrically
good at being able to organize people and do certain kinds of things that were
pretty oriented towards certain types of destruction or pretty willing to
maybe they would say they were oriented towards empire expansion but pretty willing to
commit certain acts of destruction in the name of it what are you worried about the gang is con
or you could argue he's not a psychopath uh that are you worried about gang is con are you
worried about hitler are you worried about a terrorist who is has a very different ethic which
is not even for uh it's not trying to preserve and build and expand my community it's more about
just destruction in itself is the goal i think the thing that you're looking at that i do agree
with is that there's a psychological disposition towards construction right and a psychological
disposition more towards destruction obviously everybody has both and can toggle between both
and oftentimes one is willing to destroy certain things we have this idea of creative destruction
right willing to destroy certain things to create other things and utilitarianism and trolley
problems are all about exploring that space and the idea of war is all about that and i am trying
to create something for our people and it requires destroying some other people um
sociopathy is a funny topic because it's possible to have very high fealty to your in group and work
on perfecting the methods of torture to the out group um at the same time because you can dehumanize
and then remove empathy um and i would also say that there are types so the reason the thing that
gives hope about the orientation towards construction and destruction being a little different in
psychologies is what it takes to build really catastrophic tech even today where it doesn't
take what it took to make a new a small group people could do it takes still some real technical
knowledge that required having studied for a while and some then building capacity and
there's a question of is that psychologically inversely correlated with the desire to
damage civilization meaningfully uh a little bit a little bit i think um i think a lot i think
it's actually i mean this is the conversation i had like what i think offline with dan carlin
which is like it's pretty easy to come up with ways that any competent like i can come up with a
lot of ways to hurt a lot of people and it's pretty easy like i alone could do it and
like there's a lot of people as smarter smarter than me at least in the creation of explosives
why are we not seeing more insane mass murder i i think there's something
fascinating and beautiful about this yes and it does have to do with some deeply pro-social types
of characteristics in humans and um but when you're dealing with very large numbers you don't
need a whole lot of a phenomena and so then you start to say well what's the probability that x
won't happen this year then won't happen in the next two years three years four years and then how
many people are doing destructive things with lower tech and then how many of them can get
access to higher tech that they didn't have to figure out how to build so uh when i can get
commercial tech and maybe i don't understand tech very well but i understand it well enough to
utilize it not to create it and i can repurpose it when we saw that commercial drone with a homemade
thermite bomb hit the ukraine ukrainian munitions factory and do the equivalent of an incendiary
bomb level of damage that's just home tech that's just simple kind of thing and so the question is
not what is does it stay being a small percentage of the population the question is does can you
bind that phenomena nearly completely and especially now when you as you start to get into
bigger things crisper gene drive technologies and various things like that um can you bind it
completely long term over what period of time not perfectly though that's the thing i'm trying i'm
trying to say that there is some let's call it uh let's uh a random word love that's inherent in
that's core to human nature that's preventing destruction at scale and you're saying yeah
but there's a lot of humans there's going to be eight plus billion and then there's a lot of seconds
in the day to come up with stuff there's a lot of pain in the world that can lead to uh distorted
view of the world such that you want to channel that pain into the destruction all those kinds of
things and it's only a matter of time that anyone individual can do large damage especially as we
create uh more and more democratized decentralized ways to deliver that damage even if you don't
know how to build the initial weapon you can but the thing is it seems like it's a race between
the cheapening of destructive weapons and the capacity of humans to express their love
towards each other and it's a race that's so far i know on twitter you it's not popular to say but
love is winning okay so what is the argument that love is going to lose here against nuclear
weapons of biotech and and ai and uh and drones okay i'm gonna comment the end of this to a how
love wins so i just want you to know that that's where i'm oriented that's the end but i'm i'm
gonna argue against why that is a given because it because it's not a given i don't believe and
i think this is like a good romantic comedy so you're gonna create drama right now but it will
end with a happy ending well it's because it's only a happy ending if we actually understand
the issues well enough and take responsibility to shift it do i believe like there's a reason why
there's so much more dystopic sci-fi than protopic sci-fi and the in the summer protopic sci-fi
usually requires magic is because or at least magical tech right dilithium crystals and warp
drives and stuff because it's very hard to imagine people like the people we have been in the history
books with exponential type technology and power that don't eventually blow themselves up they
make good enough choices as stewards of their environment and their comments and and each
other and etc so like it's easier to think of scenarios where we blow ourselves up than it
is to think of scenarios where we avoid every single scenario where we blow ourselves up and
when i say blow ourselves up i also i mean the environmental versions the terrorist versions
the war versions the cumulative externalities versions um can i and i'm sorry if i'm interrupting
your flow of thought but why is it easier is it could it be a weird psychological thing where we
either i was just more capable to visualize explosions and destruction and then the sicker
thought which is like we kind of enjoy for some weird reason thinking about that kind of stuff
even though we wouldn't actually act on it it's almost like some weird uh like i love playing
shooter games you know uh first person shooters and like especially if it's like murdering zombie
and doom you're shooting demons i play one of my favorite games diabolus like slashing through
different monsters and the screaming and pain and the hellfire and then i go out into the real world
to eat my coconut ice cream and i'm all about love so like i
can we trust our ability to visualize how all it all goes to shit as an actual rational way of
thinking i think it's a fair question to say to what degree is there just kind of perverse fantasy
and um morbid exploration and whatever else that happens in our imagination uh
but i don't think that's the whole of it i think there is also a reality to the combinatorial
possibility space and the difference in the probabilities that there's a lot of ways i could
try to put the 70 trillion cells of your body together that don't make you there's not that
many ways i can put them together that make you there's a lot of ways i could try to connect the
organs together that make some weird kind of group of organs on a on a desk but that doesn't
actually make a functioning human and and you can kill an adult human in a second but you
can't get one in a second takes 20 years to grow one and a lot of things to happen right i could
destroy this building in a couple minutes with demolition but it took a year or a couple years
to build it there is uh calm down co this is just an example it's not he doesn't mean it
there's a there's a gradient where entropy is easier and that there's a lot more ways to
put a set of things together that don't work than the few that really do produce higher order
synergies and so when we look at a history of war and then we look at exponentially more powerful
warfare an arms race that drives that in all these directions and when we look at a history
of environmental destruction and exponentially more powerful tech that makes exponential
externalities multiplied by the total number of agents that are doing it in the cumulative
effects there's a lot of ways the whole thing can break like a lot of different ways and for
it to get ahead it has to have none of those happen and so there's just a probability space
where it's easier to imagine that thing so what so to say how do we have a pro-topic future we
have to say well one criteria must be that it avoids all of the catastrophic risks so can we
understand can we inventory all the catastrophic risks can we inventory the patterns of human
behavior that give rise to them and could we try to solve for that and could we have that be the
the essence of the social technology that we're thinking about to be able to guide bind and
direct a new physical technology because so far our physical technology like we were talking about
the Genghis Khan's and like that that obviously use certain kinds of physical technology and armaments
and also social technology and unconventional warfare for a particular set of purposes but
we have things that don't look like warfare like Rockefeller and Standard Oil and it looked like a
constructive mindset to be able to bring this new energy resource to the world and it did and the
second order effects of that are climate change and all of the oil spills that have happened and
will happen and all of the wars in the Middle East over the oil that have been there and the
massive political clusterfuck and human life issues that are associated with it and on and on
right um and so it's also not just the orientation to construct a thing can have a narrow focus on
what I'm trying to construct but be affecting a lot of other things through second and third order
effects I'm not taking responsibility for and you you often another tangent mentioned second
third and fourth order effects and order and cascading which is really fascinating like starting
with the third order plus it gets really interesting because we don't we don't even acknowledge
like the second order effects right but like thinking because those it could get bigger and
bigger and bigger in ways we're not anticipating so how do we make those so it sounds like part of the
part of the thing that you are thinking through in terms of a solution how to create
an anti fragile a resilient society is to make explicit
acknowledge understand the externalities the second order third order fourth order and the
order effects how do we start to think about those effects yeah the war application is harm
we're trying to cause or that we're aware we're causing right um the externality is harm that
at least supposedly we're not aware we're causing or at minimum it's not our intention right maybe
we're either totally unaware of it or we're aware of it but it is a side effect of what our
intention is it's not the intention itself there are catastrophic risks from both types the direct
application of increased technological power to a rival risk intent which is going to cause
harm for some out group for some in group to win but the out group is also working on growing the
tech and if they don't lose completely they reverse engineer the tech upregulated come back
with more capacity so there's the exponential tech arms race side of in group out group rivalry
using exponential tech that is one set of risks and the other set of risks is the application of
exponentially more powerful tech not intentionally to try and beat an out group but to try to achieve
some goal that we have but to produce a second and third order effects that do have harm to
the commons to other people to environment to other groups uh that might actually be bigger
problems than the problem we were originally trying to solve with the thing we were building
when facebook was building a dating app and then building a social app where people could tag pictures
they weren't trying to build a democracy destroying app uh that would maximize time on site
as part of its ad model through ai optimization of a news feed to the thing that made people spend
most time on site which is usually them being limbically hijacked more than something else
which ends up appealing to people's cognitive biases and group identities and creates no
sense of shared reality they weren't trying to do that but it was a second order effect
and it's a pretty fucking powerful second order effect um and a pretty fast one because the rate
of tech is obviously able to get distributed to much larger scale much faster and with a bigger jump
in terms of total vertical capacity then that's what it means to get to the verticalizing part
of an exponential curve so um just like we can see that oil had these second order environmental
effects and also social and political effects war and so much of the whole like the total
amount of oil used is has a proportionality to total global gdp and this way we have this you
know the petrodollar and um and so the the oil thing also had the externalities of a major
aspect of what happened with military industrial complex and things like that so but we can see
the same thing with with more current technologies with facebook and google um and and other things
so i don't think we can run and the more powerful the tech is we build it for
reason x whatever reason x is maybe x is three things maybe it's one thing right we
we're doing the oil thing because we want to make cars because it's a better method of individual
transportation we're building the facebook thing because we're going to connect people
socially in the personal sphere but it it interacts with it interacts with complex systems with
ecologies economies psychologies cultures and so it has effects on other than the thing we're
intending some of those effects can end up being negative effects but because this technology
if if we make it to solve a problem it has to overcome the problem the problem's been around
for a while it's going to overcome in a short period of time so it usually has greater scale
greater rate of magnitude in some way that also means that the externalities that it creates
might be bigger problems and you can say well but then that's the new problem and humanity will
innovate its way out of that well i don't think that's paying attention to the fact that we can't
keep up with exponential curves like that nor do finite spaces allow exponential externalities forever
and this is why a lot of the smartest people thinking about this are thinking well no i think
we're totally screwed and unless we can make a benevolent ai singleton that rules all of us
you know guys like boss drum and and others uh thinking in those directions because they're like
how do humans try to do multi polarity and make it work and i i have a different answer of what
i think it looks like that does have more to do with the love but some applied social
tech aligned aligned with love because i have a bunch of really dumb ideas i'd prefer to uh
i'd like to hear i'd like to hear some of them first i think the idea i would have is uh to be
a bit more rigorous in trying to measure the amount of love you add or subtract from the world
in second third fourth fifth order effects it's actually i think especially in the world of tech
quite doable you know you just might not like you know the the shareholders may not like that
kind of metric but it's pretty easy to measure like that's not even uh i'm perhaps half joking
about love but we could talk about just happiness and well-being long-term well-being
that's pretty easy from facebook for youtube for all these companies to measure that
they do a lot of kinds of surveys they could do i mean there's very simple solutions here
that you could just survey how i mean servers are in some sense use useless because they're um
a subset of the population you're just trying to get a sense it's very loose kind of understanding
but integrated deeply as part of the technology most of our tech is recommender systems most
of the sorry net tech uh online interaction is driven by recommender systems that learn
very little data about you and use that data based on mostly based on traces of your previous
behavior to suggest future things this is how twitter this has facebook works this is how
adsense for google adsense works is how netflix youtube work and so on and and for them to just
track as opposed to engagement how much you spend in a particular video particular site is also
track give you the technology to do self-report of what makes you feel good what makes you grow as
a person of what makes you uh you know the best version of yourself the the the the rogan uh idea
of the hero of your movie and just add that little bit of information if you you have people you
have this like happiness surveys of how you feel about the last five days how would you report
your experience you can lay out the set of videos this is kind of fascinating to me i don't know if
you ever look at youtube the history of videos you've looked at it's fascinating it's very embarrassing
for me like you'll be like a lecture and then like a set of videos that i don't want anyone to know
about which is which is which will be like uh i don't know maybe like five videos in a row where
it looks like i watched the whole thing which i probably did i bought like how to cook a steak
even though or just like the best chefs in the world cooking steaks and i'm just like sitting
there watching it for no purpose whatsoever wasting away my life or like funny cat videos are like
legit that that's that's an that's always a good one and i could look back and rate which videos
made me a better person and not and i mean on a more serious note there's a bunch of conversations
podcasts or lectures i've watched which made me a better person and some of them made me a worse
person uh quite honestly not for stupid reasons like i feel dumber but because i do have a sense
that that started me on a path of um
um
of not being kind to other people for example i'll give you uh for my own and i'm sorry for
rantic but maybe there's some usefulness to this kind of exploration of self when i focus on
creating i'm programming on science i become a much deeper thinker and a kinder person to others
when i listen to too many a little bit is good but too many
podcasts or videos about how how our world is melting down or criticizing ridiculous people
the worst of the quote unquote woke for example all there's all these groups that are misbehaving
in fascinating ways because they've been corrupted by power the more i watch the more i watch criticism
of them the worse i become and i'm aware of this but i'm also aware that for some reason
it's pleasant to watch those sometimes and so for for me to be able to self report that to the youtube
algorithm to the systems around me and they ultimately try to optimize to make me the best
person the best version of myself which i personally believe would make youtube a lot more money
because i'd be much more willing to spend time i need to have been given youtube a lot more a lot
more of my money that's a that's great for business and great for humanity because it'll make me a
kinder person it'll increase the the love quotient the love metric and uh it'll make them a lot of
money i feel like everything's aligned and so you you should do that not just for youtube algorithm
but also for military strategy and for the to go to war or not because one externality you can think
of about going to war which i think we talked about offline is we often go to war with kind of
governments with that with not with the people you have to think about the kids of countries
that see a soldier and because of what they experience the interaction with the soldier
hate is born when you're like eight years old six years old you lose your dad you lose your mom
you lose a friend somebody close to you that want to really powerful externality that could be
reduced to love positive and negative is uh the hate that's born when you make decisions and that's
going to take fruition that that little seed is going to become a tree that then leads to the kind
of destruction that we talk about so but in my sense it's possible to reduce everything to
measure of how much love does this add to the world all that to say do you have ideas of how we
practically build systems that that that create a resilient society there are a lot of good things
that you shared where there's like 15 different ways that we could enter this that are all
interesting so i'm trying to see which one will probably be most useful pick the the one or two
things that are least ridiculous when you're mentioning if we could see some of the second
order effects or externalities that we aren't used to seeing specifically the one of a kid
being radicalized somewhere else which engenders enmity and them towards us which decreases our
own future security even if you don't care about the kid if you care about the kids the whole other
thing um yeah i mean i think when we saw this when jane fonda and others went to vietnam and took
photos and videos of what was happening and you got to see the pictures of the kids with napalm on
them uh that like the anti-war effort was bolstered by that in a way it couldn't have been without
that there's there's a until we can see the images you can't have a mere neuron effect in the same
way and when you can that starts to have a powerful effect i think there's a deep principle that you're
sharing there which is that if we we can have a rival risk intent where our in group whatever it is
maybe it's our political party wanting to win within the u.s maybe it's our nation state wanting to
win in a a war or an economic war over resource or whatever it is that if we don't obliterate the
other people completely they don't go away they're they're not engendered to like us more
they're they didn't become less smart so they have more enmity towards us and whatever technologies
we employed to be successful they will now reverse engineer make iterations on and come back
and so you you drive in arms race which is why you can see that the wars were over history
employing more lethal weaponry and not just the kinetic war um the information war and the narrative
war and the economic war right like it's just increased capacity in all of those fronts um
and so what seems like a win to us on the short term might actually really produce losses in
the long term and what's even in our own best interest in the long term is probably more aligned
with everyone else because we inter-affect each other and I think the thing about globalism
globalization and exponential tech and the rate at which we affect each other and the rate at which
we affect the biosphere that we're all affected by is that this this kind of proverbial spiritual
idea that we're all interconnected and need to think about that in some way that was easy for
tribes to get because everyone in the tribe so clearly saw their interconnection independence
on each other but in terms of a global level the the speed at which we are actually interconnected
the speed at which the harm happening to something in Wuhan affects the rest of the world or a new
technology developed somewhere affects the entire world or an environmental issue or whatever
is making it to where we either actually all get not as a spiritual idea just even as physics
right we all get to the interconnectedness of everything and that we either all consider that
and see how to make it through more effectively together or failures anywhere in that becoming
decreased quality of life and failures and increased risk everywhere don't you think people
are beginning to experience that at the individual level so governments are resisting it they're
trying to make us not empathize with each other feel connected but don't you think people are
beginning to feel more and more connected like isn't that exactly what the technology is enabling
like social networks we tend to criticize them but isn't there a sense which we're
experiencing you know when you watch those videos that are criticizing whether it's
the woke antifa side or the QAnon Trump supporter side does it seem like they
have increased empathy for people that are outside of their ideology camp not at all so I may be
I may be conflating my own experience of the world and that of
that of the populace I I tend to see those videos
as feeding something that's a relic of the past they figured out that drama
fuels clicks but whether I'm right or wrong I don't know but I tend to sense that that is not
that hunger for drama is not fundamental to human beings that we want to actually
that we want to understand antifa and we want to like empathize we want to take radical ideas
and be able to empathize with them and synthesize it all okay let's look at cultural outliers
in terms of violence versus compassion we can see that a lot of cultures have
relatively lower in-group violence bigger out-group violence and there's some variants in
them and variants of different times based on the scarcity or abundance of resource and other things
but you can look at say janes whose whole religion is around non-violence so much
so that they don't even hurt plants they only take fruits that fall off them and stuff
or to go to a larger population you take buddhists where for the most part with a few exceptions
for the most part across three millennia and across lots of different countries and geographies and
whatever you have 10 million people plus or minus who don't hurt bugs the whole spectrum of genetic
variants that is happening within a culture of that many people and head traumas and whatever
and nobody hurts bugs and then you look at a group where the kids grew up as child soldiers
in libiria or darfur were to make it to adulthood pretty much everybody's killed people hand to hand
and killed people who were civilian or innocent type of people and you say okay so we were very
neoteness we can be conditioned by our environment and humans can be conditioned where almost all
the humans show up in these two different bell curves it doesn't mean that the buddhists had no
violence it doesn't mean that these people had no compassion but the they're very different
Gaussian distributions and so I think one of the important things that I like to do is look at
the examples of the populations what buddhism shows regarding compassion or what
Judaism shows around education the average level of education that everybody gets because of a
culture that is really working on conditioning it or various cultures what are the positive deviants
outside of this statistical deviants to see what is actually possible and then say what are the
conditioning factors and can we condition those across a few of them simultaneously and could
we build a civilization like that becomes a very interesting question so there's this kind of real
politic idea that humans are violent large groups of humans become violent they become
irrational specifically those two things rivalrous and violent and irrational and so in order to
minimize the total amount of violence and have some good decisions they need ruled somehow and
that not getting that is some kind of naive utopianism that doesn't understand human nature
yet this gets back to like mimesis of desire as an inexorable thing I think the idea of the masses
is actually a kind of propaganda that is useful for the classes that control
um to popularize the idea that most people are too violent lazy undisciplined and irrational
to make good choices and therefore their choices should be sublimated in some kind of way I think
that if we look back at these conditioning environments we can say okay so the kids
they go to a really fancy school and have a good developmental environment like Exeter Academy
there's still a Gaussian distribution of how well they do on any particular metric
but on average they become senators and the worst ones become high-end lawyers or whatever
and then I look at an inner city school with a totally different set of things and I see a very
very differently displaced Gaussian distribution but a very different set of conditioning factors
so then I say the masses well if all those kids who were one of the parts of the masses got to
go to Exeter and have that family and whatever would they still be the masses um could we actually
condition more social virtue more civic virtue more orientation towards dialectical synthesis
more empathy more rationality widely yes would that lead to better capacity for something like
participatory governance democracy or republic or some kind of participatory governance
yes yes is it necessary for it actually yes and is it good for class interests not not really
by the way when you say class interest this is the powerful leading over the
less powerful that kind of idea anyone that benefits from asymmetries of power
or doesn't necessarily benefit from decreasing those asymmetries of power and kind of increasing
the capacity of people more widely and so when we talk about power we're talking about asymmetries
in agency influence and control you think that hunger for power is fundamental to human nature
I think we should get that straight before we talk about other stuff so like
this this this pickup line that I use at a bar off which is power crops and absolute power crops
absolutely is that true or is that just a fancy thing to say in modern society there's something
to be said have we changed as societies over time in terms of how much we crave power that there is
an impulse towards power that is innate in people and can be conditioned one way or the other yes
but you can see that Buddhist society does a very different thing with it at scale that you don't
end up seeing the emergence of the same types of sociopathic behavior and particularly then
creating sociopathic institutions and so it's like is eating the foods that were rare in our
evolutionary environment to give us more dopamine hit because they were rare and they're not anymore
salt fat sugar is there something pleasurable about those where humans have an orientation
to overeat if they can well the fact that there is that possibility doesn't mean everyone will
obligately be obese and I have obesity right like it's possible to have a particular impulse and to
be able to understand it have other ones and be able to balance them and so to say that power
dynamics are are obligate in humans and we can't do anything about it is very similar to me to saying
like we could everyone is going to be obligately obese yeah so there's some degree to which those
the control those impulses has to do with the conditioning early in life yes and the culture
that creates the environment to be able to do that and then the recursion on that okay so what
if we were to uh bear with me just asking for a friend if we were to kill all humans on earth
and then start over
is their ideas about how to build up okay we don't have to kill let's leave the humans on earth
they're fine and go to mars and start a new society is there ways to construct systems of
conditioning education of how we live with each other that would that would incentivize us properly
to not seek power not to not construct systems that are
of asymmetry of power and to create systems that are resilient to all kinds of terrorist attacks
to the all kinds of destructions I believe so so is there some inklings we get of course you
probably don't have the ant all the answers but you have insights about what that looks like I mean
is it just rigorous practice of dialectic synthesis as essentially conversations with assholes of
various flavors until they're not assholes anymore because you've become a deeply empathetic with
their experience okay so there's a lot of things that we would need to construct to come back to
this like what is the basis of rivalry what how do you bind it how does it relate to tech if you
have a culture that is doing less rivalry does it always lose in war to those who do war better and
how do you make something on the enactment of how to get there from here great great so what's
rivalry why is is rivalry bad or good is so is another word for rivalry competition
yes I think roughly yes I think bad and good are kind of silly concepts here good for some
things bad for other things for some contexts and others even that okay let me give you an example
that relates back to the facebook measuring thing you were mentioning a moment ago first
I think what you're saying is actually aligned with the right direction and what I want to get
to in a moment but it's not the devil is in the details here so I enjoy praise feeds my ego I grow
stronger so I appreciate that I will make sure to include one piece every 15 minutes as we go thank you
so it's easier to measure
there are problems with this argument but there's also utility to it so let's take it
for the utility it has first it's harder to measure happiness than it is to measure comfort
uh we can measure with technology that the shocks in a car are making the car bounce less that the
bed is um softer and you know material science and those types of things and happiness is actually
hard for philosophers to define because some people find that there's certain kinds of overcoming
suffering that are necessary for happiness there's happiness it feels more like contentment and
happiness it feels more like passion does is passion the source of all suffering or the
source of all creativity like that there's deep stuff and it's mostly first person not
measurable third person stuff even if maybe it corresponds to third person stuff to some degree
but we also see examples of some of our favorite examples as people who are in the worst environments
who end up finding happiness right where the third person stuff looks to be less conducive and there's
some victor frankle nelson mendela whatever um but it's pretty easy to measure comfort and it's
pretty universal and i think we can see that the industrial revolution started to replace happiness
with comfort quite heavily as the thing it was optimizing for and we can see that when increased
comfort is given maybe because of the evolutionary disposition that expending extra calories when
for the majority of our history we didn't have extra calories was not a safe thing to do who knows
why um when extra comfort is given it's very easy to take that path even if it's not the
path that supports overall well-being long-term and um so we can see that you know when you when
you look at the techno-optimist idea that we have better lives than egyptian pharaohs and kings and
whatever what they're largely looking at is how comfortable our beds are and how comfortable
the transportation systems are and things like that in which case is massive improvement but
we also see that in some of the nations where people have access to the most comfort suicide
and mental illness are the highest and we also see that some of the happiest cultures are actually
some of the ones that are in materially lame environments and so there's a very interesting
question here and if i understand correctly you do cold showers and joe rogan was talking about how
he needs to do some fairly intensive kind of um struggle that is a non-comfort to actually induce
being better as a person this concept of hormesis that it's actually stressing an adaptive system
that increases its adaptive capacity and that there's something that the happiness of a system has
something to do with its adaptive capacity its overall resilience health well-being which requires
a decent bit of discomfort and yet in the in the presence of the comfort solution it's very hard to
not choose it and then as you're choosing it regularly to actually down regulate your overall
adaptive capacity and so when we start saying can we make tech where we're measuring for the things
that it produces beyond just the measure of gdp or whatever particular measures look like the
revenue generation or profit generation of my business are all the meaningful things measurable
and what are the right measures and what are the externalities of optimizing for that
measurement set what meaningful things aren't included in that measurement set that might
have their own externalities these are some of the questions we actually have to take seriously
yeah and we i think they're answerable questions right progressively better not perfect right so
so first of all let me throw out happiness and comfort out of the discussion those
seem like useless the distinction so i because i said they're useful well-being is useful but
i think i take it back i knew i proposed new metrics in this brainstorm session which is
so one is like personal growth which is intellectual growth i think we're able to
make that concrete for ourselves like you're a better person than you were a week ago or a
worse person than you were a week ago i think we can ourselves report that and and and understand
what that means it's this gray area and we try to define it but i think we humans are pretty
good at that because we have a sense an idealistic sense of the person we might be able to become
we we all dream of becoming a certain kind of person and i think we have a sense of getting
closer and not towards that person maybe this is not a great metric fine the other one is love
actually fuck if you're happy or not or you're comfortable or not how much love do you have
towards your fellow human beings i feel like if you try to optimize that and increasing that that's
going to have that's a good metric how many times a day sorry if i can make quantify how many times
a day have you thought positively of another human being just put that down as a number
and increase that number i think the process of saying okay so let's not take gdp or gdp per
capita is the metric we want to optimize for because gdp goes up during war and it goes up with
more healthcare spending from sicker people and various things that we wouldn't say correlate
to quality of life addiction drives gdp awesomely um by the way when i said growth i wasn't referring
i know i'm give i'm giving an example now of the primary metric we use and why it's not
an adequate metric and because we're exploring other ones so the idea of saying what would the
metrics for a good civilization be if i had to pick a set of metrics what would the best ones be
if i was going to optimize for those and then really try to run the thought experiment more deeply
and say okay so what happens if we optimize for that try to think through the first and second
third order effects of what happens it's positive and then also say what negative things can happen
from optimizing that what actually matters that is not included in that or in that way of defining
it because love versus number of positive thoughts per day i could just make a long list of names
and just think say positive thing about each one it's all very superficial not include animals
with the rest of life have a have a very shallow total amount of it but i'm optimizing the number
if i get some credit for the number so the and this is when i said the model of reality isn't
reality when you make a set of metrics they were going to optimize for this whatever reality is
that is not included in those metrics can be the areas where harm occurs which is why i would say
that wisdom is something like the discernment that leads to right choices beyond what metrics-based
optimization would offer yeah but another way to say that is wisdom is uh constantly expanding
an evolving set of metrics which means that there is something in you that is recognizing a new
metric that's important that isn't part of that metric set so there's a certain kind of connection
discernment awareness and this is an iterative game theory there's a girdles and completeness
theorem right which is if the system if the set of things is consistent it won't be complete so
we're going to keep adding to it which is why we were saying earlier i don't think it's not beautiful
and especially if you were just saying one of the metrics you want to optimize for at the individual
level is becoming right that we're becoming more well that's then becomes true for the civilization
and our metrics as well yeah and our definition of how to think about a meaningful life and a
meaningful civilization i can tell you what some of my favorite metrics are what's that
well love is obviously not a metric it's like you could bench yeah it's a good metric yeah i want
to optimize that across the entire population starting with infants um so in the same way that
love isn't a metric but you could make metrics that look at certain parts of it the thing i'm
about to say isn't a metric but it's a it's a consideration because i thought about this a lot
i don't think there is a metric a right one um i think that every metric by itself without this
thing we talked about of the continuous improvement becomes a paperclip maximizer i think that's why
what the idea of false idle means in terms of the model of reality not being reality then my
sacred relationship is to reality itself which also binds me to the unknown forever to the known
but also to the unknown and there's a sense of sacredness connected to the unknown that creates
an epistemic humility that is always seeking not just to optimize the thing i know but to learn new
stuff and to be open to perceive reality directly so my model never becomes sacred my model is useful
my so the model can't be the false idle correct yeah and this is why the first verse of the
Tao Te Ching is the Tao that is nameable is not the eternal Tao the naming then can become the
source of the ten thousand things that if you get too carried away with it can actually obscure you
from paying attention to reality beyond in the models it sounds a lot a lot like Stephen Wolf
from but in a different language much more poetic i can't imagine that no i'm referring i'm joking
but there's echoes of cellular automata which you can't name you can't construct a good model
cellular automata you can only watch in awe i apologize i'm distracting your train of thought
horribly and miserably making a difference by the way something robots aren't good at
and uh dealing with the uncertainty of uneven ground you've been okay so far you've been doing
wonderfully so what's your favorite metrics okay so i know you're not so i have a fascinating
so one metric and there are problems with this but one metric that i like to just as a thought
experiment to consider is because you're actually asking where i mean i know you ask your guests
about the meaning of life because ultimately when you're deciding when you're saying what is a
desirable civilization you can't answer that without answering what is a meaningful human life and
and to say what is a good civilization because it's going to be in relationship to that right um
and then you have whatever your answer is how do you know what is the what is the
epistemic basis for for postulating that um there's also a whole nother reason for asking
that question i don't i mean but that doesn't even apply to you whatsoever which is it's
interesting how few people have been asked questions like it we we we joke about these
questions is silly right it's it's funny to watch a person and if i was more of an asshole i would
really stick on that question right it's a silly question in some sense but like we haven't really
considered what it means just a more concrete version of that question is what is what is a
better world what is the kind of world we're trying to create really i think well have you
really thought okay i'll give you some kind of simple answers to that that are meaningful to me
but let me do the societal indices first because they're fun yes we should take a note of this
meaningful thing because it's important to come back to um are you reminding me to ask you about
the meaning of life noted i know let me jot that down yeah so um well because i think i stopped
tracking it like 25 open threads um okay let it all burn one index that i find very interesting is
the inverse correlation of addiction within the society the more a society produces addiction
within the people in it the less healthy i think the society is as a pretty fundamental metric
and so the more the individuals feel that there are less compulsive things
in compelling them to behave in ways that are destructive to their own values
and in so far as a civilization is conditioning and influencing the individuals within it
the inverse of addiction um oddly defined addiction what's yeah compulsive behavior that
is destructive towards things that we value
yeah i think that's a very interesting one to think about that's a really interesting one yeah
and this is then also where comfort and addiction start to get very close
and the ability to go in the other direction from addiction is the ability to be exposed
to hypernormal stimuli and not go down the path of desensitizing to other stimuli and needing
that hypernormal stimuli which does involve a kind of hormesis so i do think the civilization
of the future has to create something like ritualized discomfort and um ritualized discomfort
yeah i think that's what the sweat lodge and the vision quest and the solo journey and the
ayahuasca journey and the sundance were i think it's even a big part of what yoga asana was
is to make beings that are resilient and strong they have to overcome some things to make beings
that can control their own mind and fear they have to face some fears but we don't want to
put everybody in war or real trauma and yet we can see that the most fucked up people we know
had childhoods of a lot of trauma but some of the most incredible people we know had childhoods
of a lot of trauma whether or not they happen to make it through and overcome that or not
so how do we get the benefits of the stealing of character and the resilience and the whatever
that happened from the difficulty without traumatizing people a certain kind of ritualized
discomfort that not only has us overcome something by ourselves but overcome it together with
each other where nobody bails when it gets hard because the other people are there so it's both
a resilience of the individuals and a resilience of the bonding so i think we'll keep getting
more and more comfortable stuff but we have to also develop resilience in the presence of that
for the anti-addiction direction and the fullness of character and the trustworthiness to others
so you have to be consistently injecting discomfort into the system ritualize
i mean this sounds like uh you have to imagine sycophus happy you have to
uh imagine sycophus with this rock
optimally resilient from a metrics perspective in society so we want we want to constantly
be throwing rocks at ourselves not constantly uh you didn't have to frequently
periodically periodically and there's different levels of intensity different
period of disease now i do not think this should be imposed by states uh i think it should emerge
from cultures and i think the cultures are developing people that understand the value of
it so the people so there is both a cultural cohesion to it but there's also a voluntarism
because the people value the thing that is being developed they understand it and that's what
condition so it's conditioning it's conditioning some of these some of these values and conditioning
is a bad word because we like our idea of sovereignty but when we recognize the language
that we speak and the words that we think in and the and the patterns of thought built into
that language and the aesthetics that we like and so much is conditioned in us just based on
where we're born you can't not condition people so all you can do is take more responsibility
for what the conditioning factors are and then you have to think about this question of what is a
meaningful human life because we're unlike the other animals born into environment that they're
genetically adapted for we're building new environments that we were not adapted for and
then we're becoming affected by those so then we have to say well what kinds of environments
digital environments physical environments social environments would we want to create
that would develop the healthiest happiest most moral noble meaningful people and what are even
those sets of things that matter so you end up getting deep existential consideration at the
heart of civilization design when you start to rise how powerful we're becoming and how much
what we're building it in service towards matters before I pull it I think three threads you just
lay down is there another metric index a year and I'll tell you one more that I really like
there's a there's a number but the one the next one that comes to mind is
I have to make a very quick model
of healthy human bonding say we were in a tribal type setting my positive emotional states and your
positive emotional states would most of the time be correlated your negative emotional states in
mind and so you start laughing I start laughing you start crying my eyes might tear up and we would
call that the compassion compersion access I would this is a model I find useful so compassion is
when you're feeling something negative I feel some pain I feel some empathy something in relationship
compersion is when you do well I'm stoked for you right like I actually feel happiness right
down I like compersion yeah the fact that it's such an uncommon word in English is actually a
problem culturally um because I feel that often and I think that's a really good feeling to feel
and maximize for actually that's actually the metric I'm gonna say oh is the compassion
compersion at access is the thing I would optimize for now there is a state where my emotional
states and your emotional states are just totally decoupled and that is like sociopathy I don't want
to hurt you but I don't care if I do or for you to do well or whatever but there's a worse state
and it's extremely common which is where they're inversely coupled where my positive emotions
correspond to your negative ones and vice versa and that is the I would call it the jealousy
sadism access the jealousy access is when you're doing really well I feel something bad I feel
taken away from less than upset envious whatever and that's so common but I think of it as kind of
a low-grade psychopathology that we've just normalized the idea that I'm actually upset at
the happiness or fulfillment or success of another is like a profoundly fucked up thing
no we shouldn't shame it and repress it so it gets worse we should study it where does it come
from and it comes from our own insecurities and stuff and but then the next part that everybody
knows is really fucked up is just on the same axis it's the same inverted which is so the jealousy
or the envy is the I feel badly when you're doing well the sadism side is I actually feel good when
you lose or when you're in pain I feel some happiness that's associated and you can see when
someone feels jealous sometimes they feel jealous with a partner and then they feel they want that
partner to get it revenge comes up or something so sadism is really like jealousy is one step on
the path to sadism from the healthy compassion conversion access so I would like to see a
society that is inversely that is conditioning sadism and jealousy inversely right the lower
that amount and the more the compassion conversion and if I had to summarize that very simply I'd
say it would optimize for compersion which is because notice that's not just saying love
for you where I might be self-sacrificing and miserable and I love people but I kill myself
which I don't think anybody thinks a great idea or happiness where I might be sociopathically
happy where I'm causing problems all over the place or even sadistically happy but it's a coupling
right that I'm actually feeling happiness in relationship to yours and even in causal relationship
where I my own agentic desire to get happier wants to support you too that's actually speaking of
another pickup line that's quite honestly what I this is a guy who's single this is going to come
out very ridiculous because it's like oh yeah where's your girlfriend bro but
that's what I look for in a relationship because it's like it's so much it's so it's such an amazing
life where you actually get joy from another person's success and they get joy from your success
and then it becomes like you don't actually need to succeed much for that to have a like a
a loop like a cycle of just like happiness that just increases like exponentially it's weird
so like just be just enjoying the the happiness of others this success of others so this this is
like the let's call this because the first person that drilled this into my head is Rogan Joe Rogan
he was the embodiment of that because I saw somebody who is successful rich and non-stop
true I mean you could tell when somebody's full of shit and somebody's not really genuinely
enjoying the success of his friends that that was weird to me that was interesting and I mean the way
you're kind of speaking to it the reason Joe stood out to me is I guess I haven't witnessed
genuine expression of that often in this culture I've just real joy for others I mean part of
that has to do with there hasn't been many channels where you can watch or listen to people
being their authentic selves so I'm sure there's a bunch of people who live life with compersion
they probably don't seek public attention also but the that that was yeah if there was any word
that could express what what I've learned from Joe why he's been a really inspiring figure is that
compersion and I wish our world was had a lot more of that because then it I mean my own
sorry to go in a small tangent but like you're speaking how society should function but I feel
like if you optimize for that metric in your own personal life you're going to live a truly
fulfilling life I don't know what the right word to use but that's a really good way to live life
you will also learn what gets in the way of it right and how to work with it that if you wanted
to help try to build systems at scale or apply Facebook or exponential technologies to do that
you would have more actual depth of real knowledge of what that takes and this is you know as you
mentioned that there's this virtuous cycle between when you get stoked on other people doing well and
then they have a similar relationship to you and everyone is in the process of building each other
up and this is what I would say the healthy version of competition is versus the unhealthy
version the healthy version right the the root I believe it's a Latin word that means to strive
together and it's that impulse of becoming where I want to become more but I recognize that there's
actually a hormesis there's a challenge that is needed for me to be able to do that but that
means that yes there's an impulse where I'm trying to get ahead maybe I'm even trying to win but I
actually want a good opponent and I want them to get ahead too because that is where my ongoing
becoming happens and the win itself will get boring very quickly the ongoing becoming is
where there's a liveness and for the ongoing becoming they need to have it too and that's
the strive together the so in the healthy competition I'm stoked when they're doing really
well because my becoming is supported by it now this is actually a very nice segue into
a model I like about what a meaningful human life is if you want to go there
let's go there what I have I have three things I'm going elsewhere with but if we were first
let us take a short stroll through the park of the meaning of life Daniel what is a meaningful life
I think the semantics end up mattering because a lot of people will take the word meaning and the
word purpose almost interchangeably and they'll think kind of what is the meaning of my life what
is the meaning of human life what is the meaning of life what's the meaning of the universe and
what is the meaning of existence rather than non-existence so there's a lot of kind of existential
a lot of kind of existential considerations there and I think there's some cognitive mistakes
that are very easy like taking the idea of purpose which is like a goal which is a utilitarian
concept the purpose of one thing is defined in relationship to other things that have assumed
value and to say what is the purpose of everything well it's a purpose is too small of a question
it's fundamentally a relative question within everything what is the purpose of one thing
relative to another what is the purpose of everything and there's nothing outside of it
with which to say it you actually just got to the limits of the utility of the concept of purpose
it doesn't mean it's purposeless in the sense of something inside of it being purposeless it
means the concept is too small which is why you end up getting to you know like in Taoism talking
about the nature of it rather the there's a fundamental what where the why can't go deeper
is the nature of it but I'm gonna try to speak to a much simpler part which is when people
think about what is a meaningful human life and kind of if we were to optimize for something at
the level of individual life but also how does optimizing for this at the level of the individual
life lead to the best society for insofar as people living that way affects others and long
term the world as a whole and how would we then make a civilization that was trying to think about
these things because you can see that there are a lot of dialectics where there's value on two
sides individualism and collectivism or the ability to accept things and the ability to push harder
and whatever and there's failure modes on both sides and so when you were starting to say okay
individual happiness you're like wait fuck say this can be happy while hurting people it's not
individual happiness it's love but wait some people can self-sacrifice out of love in a way
that actually ends up just creating codependency for everybody or okay so so how do we think about
all those things together one like this kind of came to me as a simple way that I kind of relate
to it is that a meaningful life involves the mode of being the mode of doing and the mode of
becoming and it involves a virtuous relationship between those three and that any of those modes
on their own also have failure modes that are not a meaningful life the mode of being the way I
would describe it if if we're talking about the essence of it is about taking in and appreciating
the beauty of life that is now it's a mode that is in the moment and that is largely about being
with what is it's fundamentally grounded in the nature of experience and the meaningfulness of
experience the prima facia meaningfulness of when I'm having this experience I'm not actually asking
what the meaning of life is I'm actually full of it I'm full of experiencing it the momentary
experience yes so taking in the beauty of life doing is adding to the beauty of life I'm going
to produce some art I'm going to produce some technology that will make life easier more
beautiful for somebody else I'm going to do some science that will end up leading to better
insights or others people's ability to appreciate the beauty of life more because they understand
more about it or whatever it is or protect it right I'm going to protect it in some way but
that's adding to or being in service of the beauty of life through our doing and becoming
is getting better at both of those being able to deepen our being which is to be able to take in
the beauty of life more profoundly be more moved by it touched by it and increasing our capacity
with doing to add to the beauty of life more and so I hold that a meaningful life has to be all
three of those and where they're not in conflict with each other ultimately it grounds in being
it grounds in the intrinsic meaningfulness of experience and then my doing is ultimately
something that will be able to increase the possibility of the quality of experience for others
and my becoming is a deepening on those so it grounds an experience and also the evolutionary
possibility of experience and the point is to oscillate between these never getting stuck on
anyone yeah or I suppose in parallel well you can't really attention is a thing you can only allocate
attention I want moments where I am absorbed in the sunset and I'm not thinking about what to do
next yeah and then the fullness of that can make it to where my doing doesn't come from what's in
it for me because I actually feel overwhelmingly full already and then it's like how can I how can
make life better for other people that don't have as much opportunities I had how can I add
something wonderful how can I just be in the creative process and so I think where the doing
comes from matters and if the doing comes from a fullness of being it's inherently going to be
paying attention to externalities or it's more oriented to do that than if it comes from some
emptiness that is trying to get full in some way that is willing to cause sacrifices other places
and where a chunk of its attention is internally focused and so when Buddha said desires the cause
of all suffering then later the vow of the bodhisattva which was to show up for all sentient
beings in universe forever is a pretty intense thing like desire I would say there's a kind of
desire if we think of desire as a basis for movement like a flow or a gradient there's a
kind of desire that comes from something missing inside seeking fulfillment of that in the world
that ends up being the cause of actions that perpetuate suffering but there's also not just
non-desire there's a kind of desire that comes from feeling full at the beauty of life and wanting
to add to it that is a flow this direction and I don't think that is the cause of suffering I think
that is you know and the western traditions right the eastern traditions focused on that
and kind of unconditional happiness outside of them in the moment outside of time western
traditions said no actually desires the source of creativity and we're here to be made in the
image and likeness of the creator we're here to be fundamentally creative but creating from where
and in service of what creating from a sense of connection to everything and wholeness and service
of the well-being of all of it is very different which is back to that compassion compersion axis
being doing becoming it's pretty powerful
also could potentially be algorithmatized into a robot just saying
where does um
where does death come into that
being is forgetting I mean the the the concept of time completely there's a there's a sense to
doing and becoming that has a deadline and built in the urgency built in do you think
death is fundamental to this to a meaningful life uh
acknowledging or um
feeling the terror of death like Ernest Becker or just acknowledging the uncertainty the mystery the
the melancholy nature of the fact that the ride ends is that part of this equation
or not necessary okay look at how it could be related I've experienced fear of death
I've also experienced
times where I thought I was gonna die it felt extremely peaceful and beautiful and
um
it's funny because if we we can be afraid of death because we're afraid of hell or battery
incarnation or the bardo or some kind of idea of the afterlife we have or we're projecting
some kind of sentient suffering but if we're afraid of just non-experience
I noticed that every time I stay up late enough that I'm really tired
I'm longing for deep deep sleep and non-experience right like I'm actually longing for experience
to stop and it's not morbid it's not a bummer it's and and I don't mind falling asleep and I
sometimes when I wake up want to go back into it and then when it's done I'm happy to come out of it
so um
when we think about death and having finite time here and we could talk about if we live for
a thousand years instead of a hundred or something like that it'll still be finite time
the one bummer with the age we die is that I generally find that people mostly start to
emotionally mature just shortly before they die but there's
if I get to live forever I I can just stay focused on what's in it for me forever
and if life continues and consciousness and sentience and people appreciating beauty and
adding to it and becoming continues my life doesn't but my life can have effects that continue
well beyond it then life with a capital L starts mattering more to me than my life my life gets
to be a part of it and in service to and the whole thing about when old men plant trees the
shade of which they'll never get to be in um I remember the first time I read this poem by
Hafez the the Sufi poet written in like 13th century or something like that and he talked about
that if you're lonely to think about him and he was kind of leaning his spirit um into years
across the distance of a millennium and would come for you with these poems and he's thinking
about people millennium from now and caring about their experience and what they'd be suffering if
they'd be lonely and could he offer something that could touch them and it's just fucking beautiful
and so like the most beautiful parts of humans have to do with something that transcends what's
in it for me and death forces you to that so not not only does death create the urgency it uh
urgency of doing it you're very right it does have a sense in which it uh incentivizes the
compersion and the compassion and the widening you remember Einstein had that quote something to
the effect of it's an optical delusion of consciousness to believe there are separate
things there's this one thing we call universe and uh something about us being inside of a
prison of perception that can only you know see a very narrow little bit of it but
but this this might be just some weird disposition of mine but when I think about the future after
I'm dead and I think about consciousness I think about young people falling in love for the first
time in their their experience and I think about people being awed by sunsets and I think about
and I think about all of it right I can't not feel connected to that do you feel some sadness
to the very high likelihood that you will be forgotten completely by all of human history
you Daniel the name that that which cannot be named systems like to self-perpetuate
egos do that the idea that I might do something meaningful that future people appreciate of
course there's like a certain sweetness to that idea but I know how many people did something
did things that I wouldn't be here without and that my life would be less without whose names
I will never know and I feel a gratitude to them I feel a closeness I feel touched by that and I
think to the degree that the future people are conscious enough there is a you know a lot of
traditions had this kind of are we being good ancestors and respect for the ancestors beyond
the names I think that's a very healthy idea but let me return to a much less beautiful
and much less pleasant conversation you mentioned prison back to x-risk okay
and conditioning you mentioned something about the state
so what role let's talk about companies governments parents all the mechanisms that
can be a source of conditioning which flavor of ice cream do you like do you think the state
is the right thing for the future so governments that are elected democratic systems that are
representing representative democracy is there some kind of political system of governance
that you find appealing is it parents meaning a very close knit tribes of conditioning that's
the most essential and then you and michael malice would happily agree that it's anarchy
where the state should be dissolved or destroyed or burned to the ground if you're michael malice
giggling holding the torch as the fire burns so which which is it is the state can the state be good
or is the state bad for the condition of a beautiful world a or b this is like an sd test
you like to give these simplified good or bad things um would i like the state that we live in
currently the united states federal government to stop existing today no i would really not like
that um i think that would be not quite bad for the world in a lot of ways uh do i think that it's a
optimal social system and maximally just and humane and all those things and i wanted to
continue as is no also not that um but i am much more interested in it being able to evolve to a
better thing without going through um the catastrophe phase that i think it's just non-existence would
give so what size of state is good in a sense like do we should be as a human society as this
world becomes more globalized should we be constantly striving to reduce the we can we can
put on a map like right now literally like the the the centers of power in the world some of them
are tech companies some of them are governments should we be trying to as much as possible
decentralize the power to where it's very difficult to point on the map the centers of power and that
means making the state however there's a bunch of different ways to make the government much smaller
that could be reducing in the united states reducing the the funding for the government
all those kinds of things there's a set of responsibilities the the set of powers it could be
i mean this is far out but making more nations or maybe nations not in a space that are
defined by geographic location but rather in the space of ideas which is what anarchy is about
so anarchy is about forming collectives based on their set of ideas and doing so dynamically not
based on where you were born and so on i think we can say that the natural state of humans if we
want to describe such a thing was to live in tribes that were below the dunbar number
meaning that for a few hundred thousand years of human history all of the groups of humans mostly
stayed under that size and whenever we'd get up to that size it would end up cleaving and so it seems
like there's a pretty strong but there weren't individual humans out in the wild doing really
well right so we were a group animal but with groups that had a specific size so we could say
in a way humans were being domesticated by those groups they were learning how to have
certain rules to participate with the group without which you'd get kicked out but that
that's still the wild state of people and and maybe it's useful to do as a side statement
which i've recently looked at a bunch of papers around Dunbar's number where the mean is actually
150 if you actually look at the original paper it's a range it's really a range so it's actually
some somewhere under a thousand so it's a range of like two to five hundred or whatever it is
but like you could argue that the i think it actually is exactly to two the range is two to
five hundred and twenty something like that and this is the mean that's taken crudely it's not a
very good paper the in terms of the actual numerical numerically speaking but it'd be
interesting if there's a bunch of Dunbar numbers that could be computed for particular environments
particular conditions so on it is very true that they're likely to be something small you know
under a million but it'd be interesting if we can expand that number in interesting ways that will
change the fabric of this conversation i just want to kind of throw that in there i don't know
the if the 150 is baked in somehow in the heart into the hardware we can talk about some of the
things that it probably has to do with up to a certain number of people and this is going to
be variable based on the social technologies that mediate it to some degree we can talk about that
in a minute up to a certain number of people everybody can know everybody else pretty intimately
so let's go ahead and just take 150 as a as an average number
everybody can know everyone intimately enough that if your actions made anyone else do poorly
it's your extended family and you're stuck living with them and you know who they are and there's
no anonymous people there's no just them and over there and that's one part of what leads to a
kind of tribal process where it's good for the individual and good for the whole has a coupling
also below that scale everyone is somewhat aware of what everybody else is doing there's not
groups that are very siloed and as a result it's actually very hard to get away with bad behavior
there's a forced kind of transparency and so you don't need kind of like the state
in in that way but lying to people doesn't actually get you ahead sociopathic behavior
doesn't get you ahead because it gets seen and so there's a conditioning environment where the
individuals behaving in a way that is aligned with the interest of the tribe is what gets conditioned
when it gets to be a much larger system it becomes easier to hide certain things from the
group as a whole as well as to be less emotionally bound to a bunch of anonymous people
I would say there's also a communication protocol where up to about that number of people
we could all sit around a tribal council and be part of a conversation around a really big decision
do we migrate do we not migrate do we you know some something like that do we get rid of this person
and why why would I want to agree to be a part of a larger group where everyone can't be part of
that council and so I am going to now be subject to law that I have no say in if I could be part
of a smaller group that could still survive and I get a say in the law that I'm subject to so I
think the cleaving and in a way we can look at it beyond the Dunbar number two is we can look at
that a civilization has binding energy that is holding them together and has cleaving energy and
if the binding energy exceeds the cleaving energy that civilization will last and so there are things
that we can do to decrease the cleaving energy within the society things we can do to increase
the binding energy I think naturally we saw that had certain characteristics up to a certain size
kind of tribalism that ended with a few things it ended with people having migrated enough that
when you started to get resource wars you couldn't just migrate away easily and so tribal warfare
became more obligated it involved the plow in the beginning of real economic surplus there were
so there were a few different kind of um forcing functions but we're talking about what size should
it be right what size should a society be and I think the idea like if we think about your body
for a moment as a self-organizing complex system that is multi-scaled we think about body is a
wonderland our body is a wonderland yeah uh you have you that's a john mayer song I apologize
but yes so if we think about our our body and the billions of cells that are in it well you don't
have like think about how ridiculous it would be to try to have all the tens of trillions of cells
in it with no internal organization structure right just like a sea of protoplasm it would work your
democracy and so you have cells and tissues and then you have tissues and organs and organs and
organ systems and so you have these layers of organization and then obviously the individual
in a tribe in a ecosystem and each of the higher layers are both based on the lower layers but
also influencing them I think the future of civilization will be similar which is there's
a level of governance that happens at the level of the individual my own governance of my own choice
I think there's a level that happens at the level of a family we're making decisions together
we're inter influencing each other and affecting each other taking responsibility for the idea of
an extended family and you can see that like for a lot of human history we had an extended family
we had a local community a local church or whatever it was we had these intermediate structures
whereas right now there's kind of like the individual producer consumer taxpayer voter
and the massive nation state global complex and not that much in the way of intermediate
structures that we relate with and not that much in the way of real personal dynamics all
impersonalized made fungible and so I think that we have to have global governance meaning
I think we have to have governance at the scale we affect stuff and if if anybody is messing up
the oceans that matters for everybody so that that can't only be national or only local
everyone is scared of the idea of global governance because we think about some top
down system of imposition that now has no checks and balances on power I'm scared of that same
version so I'm not talking about that kind of global governance it's why I'm even using the
word governance as a process rather than government as an imposed phenomena and so I think we have to
have global governance but I think we also have to have local governance and there has to be
relationships between them that each where there are both checks and balances and power flows of
information so I think governance at the level of cities will be a bigger deal in the future than
governance at the level of nation states because I think nation states are largely fictitious things
that are defined by wars and agreements to stop wars and like that I think cities are based on
real things will keep being real where the proximity of certain things together the physical
proximity of things together gives increased value of those things so you look at like Jeffrey West's
work on scale and finding that companies and nation states and things that have a kind of
complicated agreement structure get diminishing return of production per capita as the total
number of people increases beyond about the tribal scale but the city actually gets increasing
productivity per capita but it's not designed it's kind of this organic thing right so there
should be governance at the level of cities because people can sense and actually have some
agency there probably neighborhoods and smaller scales within it and also verticals and some of
it won't be geographic it'll be network based right networks of affinities so I don't think the
future is one type of governance now what we can say more broadly is say when we're talking about
groups of people that inter-effect each other the idea of a civilization is that we can figure out
how to coordinate our choice making to not be at war with each other and hopefully increase total
productive capacity in a way that's good for everybody division of labor and specialties
so we all get more better stuff and whatever but it's a it's a coordination of our choice making
I think we can look at civilizations failing on the side of not having enough coordination of
choice making so they fail on the side of chaos and then they cleave and an internal war comes
about or whatever or they can't make smart decisions and they overuse their resources or whatever
it can fail on the side of trying to get order via imposition via force and so it fails on the
side of oppression which ends up being for a while functional ish for the thing as a whole but
miserable for most people in it until it fails either because of revolt or because it can't
innovate enough or something like that and so there's this like toggling between order via
oppression and chaos and I think the idea of democracy not the way we've implemented it but
the idea of it whether we're talking about a representative democracy or a direct digital
democracy liquid democracy republic or whatever the idea of an open society participatory governance
is can we have order that is emergent rather than imposed so that we aren't stuck with chaos
and infighting and inability to coordinate and we're also not stuck with oppression
and what would it take to have emergent order this is the most kind of central question for me
these days because if we look at what different nation states are doing around the world and
we see nation states that are more authoritarian that in some ways are actually coordinating
much more effectively so for instance we can see that China has built high-speed rail not just
through its country but around the world and the US hasn't built any high-speed rail yet
you can see that it brought 300 million people out of poverty in a time where we've had increasing
economic inequality happening you can see like that if there was a single country that could make
all of its own stuff if the global supply chains failed China would be the closest one to being able
to start to go closed loop on fundamental things uh belt and road initiative supply chain on rare
earth metals transistor manufacturing that is like oh they're actually coordinating more effectively
in some important ways in the last call at 30 years and that's imposed order imposed order
and we can see that if in the US if let's look at why real quick
we know why we created term limits so that we wouldn't have forever monarchs that's the thing
we were trying to get away from and that there would be checks and balances on power and that
kind of thing but that also has created a negative second order effect which is nobody
does long-term planning because somebody comes in who's got four years they want re-elected
they don't do anything that doesn't create a return within four years that will end up getting
them elected re-elected and so the 30-year industrial development to build high-speed trains or
the new kind of fusion energy or whatever it is just doesn't get invested in and then if you have
left versus right where whatever someone does for four years then the other guy gets in and
undoes it for four years and most of the energy goes into campaigning against each other this
system is just dissipating as heat right like it's just burning up as heat and the system that
has no term limits and no internal friction in fighting because they got rid of those people
can actually coordinate better but I would argue it has its own fail states eventually and dystopic
properties that are not the thing we want so the goal is to accomplish to create a system that does
long-term planning without the negative effects of a monarch or dictator that stays there for the
long term and accomplish that through not through the imposition of a single leader but through
emergent so doesn't that perhaps first of all the technology in itself seems to maybe
maybe disagree a lot for different possibilities here which is make primary the system not the humans
so the the the basic the medium on which the democracy happens like like a platform
or where people can make decisions do the choice making the coordination of the choice making
where emerges some kind of order to where like something that applies at the scale of the family
the extended family the city the the country the the continent the whole world and then
does that so dynamically constantly changing based on the needs of the people sort of always
evolving and it would all be owned by google like doesn't the doesn't this is there a way to
so first of all you optimistic that you could basically create the technology can save us
technology at creating platforms by technology I mean like software and network platforms
that allows humans to deliberate like make government together dynamically without the need
for a leader that's on a podium screaming stuff that's one and two if you're optimistic about that
are you also optimistic about the CEOs of such platforms the idea that technology is values
neutral values agnostic it and people can use it for constructive or destructive purposes but it
doesn't predispose anything it's just it's just silly naive technology elicits patterns of human
behavior because those who utilize it and get ahead end up behaving differently because of their
utilization of it and then other people then they end up shaping the world or other people race to
also get the power of the technology and so there's whole schools of anthropology that look at the
effect on social systems and the minds of people of the change in our tooling
Marvin Harris's work called cultural materialism looked at this deeply obviously Marshall McLuhan
looked specifically at the way that information technologies change the nature of our beliefs
minds values social systems I will not try to do this rigorously because there are academics will
disagree on the subtle details but I'll do it kind of like illustratively you think about the
emergence of the plow the ox drawn plow in the beginning of agriculture that came with it or
before that you had hunter gather and then you had horticulture kind of a digging stick but not
the plow well that the world changed a lot with that right and and
a few of the changes that at least some theorists believe in is when the ox drawn plow started
to proliferate any culture that utilized it was able to start to actually cultivate grain because
just with a digging stick you couldn't get enough grain for it to matter grain was a
storable caloric surplus they could make it through the famines they could grow their
population so the ones that used it got so much ahead that it became obligate and everybody
used it that corresponding with the use of a plow animism went away everywhere that it existed
because you can't talk about the spirit of the buffalo while beating the cow all day long to
pull a plow so the moment that we do animal husbandry of that kind we have to beat the cow
all day you have to say it's just a dumb animal man has dominion over earth and the nature of even
our religious and spiritual ideas change you went from women primarily using the digging stick to
do the horticulture or gathering before that men doing the hunting stuff to now men had to use the
plow because the upper body strength actually really mattered women would have miscarriages when
they would do it when they were pregnant so all the caloric supply started to come from men where
it had been from both before and the ratio of male female gods changed to being mostly male gods
following that obviously we went from very that particular line of thought then also says that
feminism followed the tractor and that the rise of feminism in the west started to follow women
being able to say we can do what men can because the male upper body strength wasn't differential
once the internal combustion engine was much stronger and we can drive a tractor so I don't
think to try to trace complex things to one cause is a good idea so I think this is a reductionist
view but it has truth in it and so the idea that technology is values agnostic is silly technology
codes patterns of behavior that code rationalizing those patterns of behavior and believing in them
that the plow also is the beginning of the Anthropocene right it was the beginning of us
changing the environment radically to to clear cut areas to just make them useful for people which
also meant the change of the view of where the the web of life were just a part of it etc so
all those types of things um so that's brilliantly put but by the way that was just brilliant but
the question is so it's not agnostic but so we have to look at what the psychological effects of
specific tech applied certain ways are and be able to say it's not just doing the first order thing
you intended it's doing like the effect on patriarchy and animism and the end of tribal
culture in the beginning of empire and the class systems that came with that not like we can go on
and on about what the plow did the beginning of surplus was inheritance which then became the
capital model and like lots of things so we have to say when we're looking at the tech how is what
are the values built into the way the tech is being built that are not obvious right so you
always have to consider externalities yes this is no matter what and the externalities are not
just physical to the environment they're also to how the people are being conditioned and
how the relationality between them is being conditioned question i'm asking you so i personally
would rather be led by a plow and a tractor than stalling okay that's the question i'm asking you
is uh in creating an emergent government where people where there's a democracy that's dynamic
that makes choices that does governance at at like a very kind of liquid like uh there's a
bunch of fine resolution layers of abstraction of governance happening at all scales right and
doing so dynamically where no one person has power at any one time that can dominate and impose rule
okay that's the stalling version i'm saying isn't there the uh the isn't the alternative
that's emergent empowered or made possible by the plow and the tractor which is the modern
version of that is like the internet the the digital space where we can the monetary system
where you have the current currency and so on but you have much more importantly to me at least
is just basic social interaction the mechanisms of human transacting with each other in this
base of ideas isn't so yes it's not agnostic definitely not agnostic you've had a brilliant
rant there the tractor has effects but isn't that the way we achieve an emergent system
of governance yes but i wouldn't say we're on track
you haven't seen anything promising but it's not that i haven't seen anything promising
is that to be on track requires understanding and guiding some of the things differently than
is currently happening and it's possible that's actually what i really care about so
you couldn't have had a stall in without having certain technologies emerge he couldn't have ruled
such a big area without transportation technologies without the train without the uh
communication tech that made it possible so when you say you'd rather have a tractor or a plow than
a stall and there's a relationship between them that is more recursive which is new physical
technologies allow rulers to rule with more power over larger distances historically and
but some things are more responsible for that than others like stalling also eats
stuff for breakfast but the thing he ate for breakfast is less responsible for the starvation
of millions than than the train the train is more responsible for that and then the
weapons of war are more responsible so some technology like let's not throw it all in the
you're saying like technology has a responsibility here but some is better than others i'm saying
that people's use of technology will change their behavior so it has behavioral dispositions built
in the change of the behavior will also change the values in the society it's very complicated
it will also as a result both make people who have different kinds of predispositions with
regard to rulership and different kinds of new capacities and so we have to think about these
things it's kind of well understood that the printing press and then in early industrialism
ended feudalism and created kind of nation states so one thing i would say as a long trend
that we can look at is that whenever there is a step function a major leap in technology physical
technology the the underlying techno industrial base with which we do stuff it ends up coding for
it ends up predisposing a whole bunch of human behavioral patterns that the previous social
system what had not emerged to try to solve and so it usually ends up breaking the previous social
systems the way the plow broke the tribal system the way that the industrial revolution broke the
feudal system and then new social systems have to emerge that can deal with that the new powers the
new dispositions whatever with that tech obviously the nuke broke nation state governance being
adequate and said we can't ever have that again so then it created this in international governance
apparatus world so i guess what i'm saying is that the solution is not exponential tech following
the current path of what the market incentivizes exponential tech to do market being a previous
social tech i would say that exponential tech if we look at different types of social tech so let's
just briefly look at that democracy tried to do the emergent order thing right at least that's
the story and which is and this is why if you look at this important part to build first it's
kind of doing it it's just doing it poorly you're saying i mean that's it is emergent order in some
sense i mean that's the hope of democracy versus other forms of government correct i mean i i said
at least the story because obviously it didn't do it for women and slaves early on it doesn't do it
for all classes equally etc but the the idea of democracy is that is participatory governance
and so you notice that the modern democracies emerged out of the european enlightenment and
specifically because the idea that a lot of people some huge number not a tribal number a huge number
of anonymous people who don't know each other are not bonded to each other who believe different
things who grew up in different ways can all work together to make collective decisions well
that affect everybody and where some of them will make compromises and the thing that matters to
them for what matters to other strangers that's actually wild like it's a wild idea that that
would even be possible and it was kind of the result of this high enlightenment idea that we
could all do the philosophy of science and we could all do the hegelian dialectic those ideas
had emerged right and it was that we we could all so our choice making because we said a society is
trying to coordinate choice making the emergent order is the order of our of the choices that
we're making not just at the level of the individuals but what groups of individuals
corporations nation states whatever do um our choices are based on our choice making is based
on our sense making and our meaning making our sense making is what do we believe is happening
in the world and what do we believe the effects of a particular thing would be our meaning
making is what do we care about right our values generation what do we care about that
we're trying to move the world in the direction of if you ultimately are trying to move the world
in a direction that is really really different than the direction i'm trying to we have very
different values we're gonna have a hard time and if you think the world is a very different world
right if you think that systemic racism is rampant everywhere and one of the worst problems
and i think it's not even a thing if you think climate change is almost existential and i think
it's not even a thing we're gonna have a really hard time coordinating and so we have to be able
to have shared sense making of can we come to understand just what is happening together
and then can we do shared values generation okay maybe i'm emphasizing a particular value
more than you but i can see how i can take your perspective and i can see how the thing that you
value is worth valuing and i can see how it's affected by this thing so can we take all the
values and try to come up with a proposition that benefits all of them better than the proposition
i created just to benefit these ones that harms the ones that you care about which is why you're
opposing my proposition yeah we don't even try in the process of crafting a proposition currently
to see and this is the reason that the proposition when we vote on it gets half the vote almost all
the time it almost never gets 90% of the votes is because it benefits some things and harms other
things we can say all theory of trade-offs but we didn't even try to say could we see what everybody
cares about and see if there is a better solution so how do we fix that try i i wonder is it is it
as simple as the social technology education well no it's that the proposition crafting and
refinement process has to be key to a democracy or part of the government and it's not currently
but it's the isn't that the humans creating that situation so one way there's two ways to fix that
one is to fix the individual humans which is the education early in life
and the second is to create somehow systems that yeah it's both so i understand the education part
but creating systems that's why that's why i mentioned the technologies is creating
yes social networks essentially yes that's actually necessary okay so let's go to the first part and
then we'll come to the second part so democracy emerged as an enlightenment era idea that we
could all do a dialectic and come to understand what other people valued and so that we could
actually come up with a cooperative solution rather than just fuck you we're gonna get our
thing in war right and that we could sense make together we could all apply the philosophy of
science and you weren't gonna stick to your guns on what the speed of sound is if we measured it
and we found out what it was and there's a unifying element to the objectivity in that way
and so this is why i believe jefferson said if you could give me a perfect newspaper and a
broken government or in paraphrasing or broken government perfect newspaper i wouldn't hesitate
to take the perfect newspaper because if the people understand what's going on they can make
build a new government if they don't understand what's going on they can't possibly make good
choices and um washington i'm paraphrasing again first president said the number one aim of the
federal government should be the comprehensive education of every citizen in the science of
government science of government was the term of art think about what that means right science of
government would be game theory coordination theory history it wouldn't call game theory yet
history sociology economics right all the things that lead to how we understand human coordination
i think it's so profound that he didn't say the number one aim of the federal government is rule
of law and he didn't say it's protecting the border from enemies because if the number one
aim was to protect the border from enemies it could do that as military dictatorship
quite effectively and if the goal was rule of law it could do it as a dictatorship as a police
state and so if the number one goal is anything other than the comprehensive education of all
the citizens in the science of government it won't stay democracy long you can see so both
education and the fourth estate the fourth estate being the so education can i make sense of the
world am i trained to make sense of the world the fourth estate is what's actually going on currently
the news do i have good unbiased information about it those are both considered prerequisite
institutions for democracy to even be a possibility and then at the scale it was initially suggested
here the town hall was the key phenomena where there wasn't a special interest group crafted a
proposition and the first thing i ever saw was the proposition to know anything about it and i
got a vote yes or no it was in the town hall we all got to talk about it and the proposition could
get crafted in real time through the conversation which is why there was that founding father's
statement that that voting is the death of democracy voting fundamentally is polarizing the
population in some kind of sublimated war but the and we'll do that as the last step but what we
want to do first is to say how does the thing that you care about that seems damaged by this
proposition how could that turn into a solution to make this proposition better where this proposition
still tends to the thing it's trying to tend to and tends to that better can we work on this together
and that in a town hall we could have that as the scale increased we lost the ability to do that
now as you mentioned the internet could change that the fact that we had representatives that
had to ride a horse from one town hall to the other one to see what the colony would do that we
stopped having this kind of developmental um propositional development process when the town
hall ended the fact that we have not used the internet to recreate this is somewhere between
insane and aligned with class interests i would push back to say that the internet has those things
it just has a lot of other things i feel like the internet has places where that encouraged
synthesis of competing ideas and sense making which is what we're talking about is just that it's
also flooded with a bunch of other systems that perhaps are out competing it under current incentives
perhaps has to do with capitalism in the market is the linux is awesome right and wikipedia and
places where you have and they have problems but places where you have open source sharing of
information vetting of information towards collective building is that building something like
like how much has that affected our court systems or our policing systems or our military systems
first of all i think a lot but not not enough i i think that's something i told you offline yesterday
is uh perhaps there's a whole nother discussion but i i don't think we're quite quantifying the
impact on the world the positive impact of wikipedia you said the policing that i mean i just i just
think the amount of empathy that what could like knowledge i think can't help but lead to empathy
just knowing okay just knowing okay i'll i'll give you some pieces of information
knowing how many people died in various awards that already that delta when you have millions
of people have that knowledge it's like it's a little like slap in the face like oh like
my boyfriend or girlfriend breaking up with me is not such a big deal when millions of people
were tortured you know like just a little bit and when a lot of people know that because of wikipedia
or the effect their second order effect of wikipedia which is it's not that necessarily
people read wikipedia it's like youtubers who don't really know stuff that well will thoroughly
read a wikipedia article and create a compelling video describing that wikipedia article that then
millions of people watch and they understand that holy shit a lot of there was such first of all
there was such a thing as world war two and world war one okay like they can at least like learn about
it they can learn about this was like recent they can learn about slavery they can learn about all
kinds of injustices in the world and that i think has a lot of effects to our to the way
whether you're a police officer a lawyer a judge in the jury or just a regular
civilian citizen the way you approach the every other communication you engage in
even if the system of that communication is very much flawed so i think there's a huge
positive effect on wikipedia that's my case for wikipedia so you should donate to wikipedia
i'm a huge fan but there's very few systems like it which is sad to me so i think it's it would be a
useful exercise for any listener of the show to really try to run the dialectical synthesis process
with regard to a topic like this and take the techno concern perspective with regard to
information tech that folks like tristan harris take and say what are all of the things that
are getting worse and what and are any of them following an exponential curve and how much
worse how quickly could that be and then and do that fully without mitigating it then take
the techno optimist perspective and see what things are getting better in a way that curse well
or diamondus or someone might do and try to take that perspective fully and say are some of those
things exponential what what could that portend and then try to hold all that at the same time
and i think there are ways in which depending upon the metrics we're looking at things are getting
worse on exponential curves and better on exponential curves for different metrics at the
same time which which i hold is the destabilization of previous system and either an emergence to a
better system or collapse to a lower order are both possible and so i want my optimism not to be
about my assessment i want my assessment to be just as fucking clear as it can be i want my
optimism to be what inspires the solution process on that clear assessment so i never i never want
to apply optimism in the sense making right i want to just try to be clear if anything i want to make
sure that the challenges are really well understood but that's in service of an optimism that
there are good potentials even if i don't know what they are that are worth seeking right there's
kind of a there is a some sense of optimism that's required to even try to innovate really hard
problems but then i want to take my pessimism and red team my own optimism to see is that solution
not going to work does it have second order effects and then not get not get upset by that
because i then come back to how to make it better so that just a relationship between optimism and
pessimism and the dialectic of how they how they can work so when i of course we can say that wikipedia
is a pretty awesome example of a thing we can look at the places where it has limits or has failed
where um on a celebrity topic or corporate interest topic you can pay wikipedia editors to
edit more frequently and various things like that but you can also see where there's a lot of
information that was kind of decentralized created that is good information that is more easily
accessible to people than everybody buying their own encyclopedia britannica or walking down to the
library and that can be updated in real time faster and i think you're very right that the
business model is a big difference because wikipedia is not a for-profit corporation it is a
it's tending to the information commons and it doesn't have an agenda other than tending to
the information commons and i think the two master's issue is a tricky one when i'm trying to optimize
for very different kinds of things um where i have to sacrifice one for the other and i can't
find synergistic satisfies which one and if i have a fiduciary responsibility to shareholder
uh profit maximization and you know what what does that end up creating
i think the ad model that silicon valley took um i think jaren laney or i don't know if you've
had him on the show but he has interesting assessment of the nature of the ad model um silicon
valley wanting to support capitalism and entrepreneurs to make things but uh also the
belief that information should be free and also the network dynamics where the more people you
got on you got increased value per user per capita as more people got on so you didn't want to do
anything to slow the rate of adoption um some places actually you know pay pal paying people
money to join the network because the uh value of the network would be there'd be a metcalflike
dynamic proportional to the square of the total number of users so um the ad model made sense of
how do we make it free but also be a business get everybody on but not really thinking about
what it would mean to and this is now the whole idea that if you aren't paying for the product
you are the product um if the if they have a fiduciary responsibility to their shareholder
maximize profit their customer is the advertiser the user who it's being built for is to do behavioral
mod for them for advertisers that's a whole different thing than that same type of tech
could have been if applied with a different business model or a different purpose um
i think there's because facebook and google and other information and communication platforms
end up harvesting data about user behavior that allows them to model who the people are
in a way that gives them more sometimes specific information and behavioral information than
even a therapist or a doctor or a lawyer or a priest might have in a different setting they
basically are accessing privileged information there should be a fiduciary responsibility
and in normal fiduciary law if there's this principal agent thing if you are a
uh principal and i'm an agent on your behalf i don't have a game-theoretic relationship with
you right if you're sharing something with me and i'm the priest or i'm the therapist i'm never
going to use that information to try to sell you a used car or whatever the thing is but facebook is
gathering massive amounts of privileged information and using it to modify people's behavior for a
behavior that they didn't sign up for wanting the behavior but what the corporation did so i think
this is an example of the physical tech evolving in the context of the previous social tech
where it's being shaped in particular ways and here unlike Wikipedia that evolved for the
information commons this evolved for fulfilling particular agentic purpose most people when
they're on facebook think it's just a tool that they're using they don't realize it's an agent
right it is a corporation with a profit motive and and as i'm interacting with it it has a
goal for me different than my goal for myself and i might want to be on for a short period of time
its goal is maximize time on site and so there's a rivalry that is take but where there should be
a fiduciary contract i think that's actually a huge deal and i think if we said could we apply
facebook like technology to develop people's citizenry capacity right to develop their personal
health and well-being and habits as well as their cognitive understanding the complexity
with which they can process the health of their relationships that would be amazing to start
to explore and this is now the thesis that we started to discuss before is every time there is
a major step function in the physical tech it absolutes the previous social tech and the new
social tech has to emerge what i would say is that when we look at the nation state level of the
world today the more top-down authoritarian nation states are as the exponential tech started to
emerge the digital technology started to emerge they were in a position for better long-term
planning and better coordination and so the authoritarian state started applying the exponential
tech intentionally to make more effective authoritarian states and that's everything
from like an internet of things surveillance system going into machine learning systems to
the sesame credit system to all those types of things and so they're upgrading their social
tech using the exponential tech otherwise within a nation state like the us but democratic open
societies the countries the states are not directing the technology in a way that makes
a better open society meaning better emergent order they're saying well the corporations are
doing that and the state is doing the relatively little thing it would do aligned with the previous
corporate law that no longer is relevant because there wasn't fiduciary responsibility for things
like that there wasn't antitrust because this creates functional monopolies because of network
dynamics right where youtube has more users than bimio and every other video player together amazon
has a bigger percentage of market share than all of the other markets together you get one
big dog per vertical because of network effect which is a kind of organic monopoly that the previous
antitrust law didn't even have a place that wasn't a thing anti monopoly was only something that
emerged in the space of government contracts so um so what we see is the new exponential
technology is being directed by authoritarian nation states to make better authoritarian
nation states and by corporations to make more powerful corporations the powerful corporations
when we think about the scottish enlightenment when the idea of markets was being advanced the
modern kind of ideas of markets the biggest corporation was tiny compared to what the biggest
corporation today is so the asymmetry of it relative to people was tiny and the asymmetry now in
terms of the total technology it employs total amount of money total amount of information
processing is so many orders of magnitude and rather than there be demand for an authentic thing
that creates a basis for supply as supply started to get way more coordinated and powerful and the
demand wasn't coordinated because you don't have a labor union of all the customers working together
but you do have a coordination on the supply side supply started to recognize that it could
manufacture demand it could make people want shit that they didn't want before that maybe wouldn't
increase their happiness in a meaningful way might increase addiction addiction is a very good way
to manufacture demand and so as soon as manufactured demand started through this is the cool thing and
you have to have it for status or whatever it is the intelligence of the market was breaking
now it's no longer a collective intelligence system that is up regulating real desire for
things that are really meaningful you're able to hijack the lower angels of our nature rather
than the higher ones the addictive patterns drive those and have people want shit that doesn't
actually make them happier make the world better and so we really also have to we have to update
our theory of markets because a behavioral econ showed that homo economicus the rational actor
is not really a thing but particularly at greater and greater scale can't really be a thing
voluntarism isn't a thing where if my corporate if my company doesn't want to advertise on facebook
i just will lose to the companies that do because that's where all the fucking attention is and so
then i can say it's voluntary but it's not really if there's a functional monopoly
same if i'm going to sell on amazon or things like that so um what i would say is that these
corporations are becoming more powerful than nation states in some ways and
they are also debasing the integrity of the nation states the open societies so the democracies
are getting weaker as a result of exponential tech and the kind of new tech companies that are kind
of a new feudalism tech feudalism because it's not a democracy inside of a tech company or the
supply and demand relationship when you have manufactured demand and kind of monopoly type
functions and so we have basically a new feudalism controlling exponential tech and authoritarian
nation states controlling it and those attractors are both shitty and so i'm interested in the
application of exponential tech to making better social tech that makes emergent order possible
and where then that emergent order can bind and direct the exponential tech in fundamentally
healthy not x-risk oriented directions i think the relationship of social tech and physical tech
can make it i think we can actually use the physical tech to make better social tech but it's not
given that we do if we don't make better social tech then i think the physical tech empowers
really shitty social tech that is not a world that we want i don't know if it's a road we want to go
down but i tend to believe that the market will create exactly the thing you're talking about
which i feel like there's a lot of money to be made in creating a social tech
that creates a better citizen that creates a better human being
this this uh the your description of facebook and so on which is a system that creates addiction
which manufactures demand is not obviously inherently the consequence of the market like i
feel like that's the first stage of us like baby deer trying to figure out how to use the internet
i i feel like there's much more money to be made with something that creates
compersion and love honestly i mean i i really from we can have this i can make the business
case for it i don't know i don't think we want to really have that discussion but don't do you
have some hope that that's the case and i guess if not then how do we fix the system of markets
that work so well for the united states for so long like i said every social tech worked for a
while like tribalism worked well for two or three hundred thousand years i think social tech has to
keep evolving the social technologies with which we organize and coordinate our behavior have to
keep evolving as our physical tech does um so i think the thing that we call markets
of course we can try to say oh even biology runs on markets and but the thing that we call
markets the underlying theory homo economicist demand driving supply that thing broke it broke
with scale in particular um and a few other things so it needs updated in a really fundamental way
um i think there's something even deeper than making money happening
that in some ways will obsolete money making
i think capitalism is not about business
so if you think about business i'm going to produce a good or a service that people want
and bring it to the market so that people get access to that good or service that's the world
of business but that's not capitalism capitalism is the management and allocation of capital
which financial services was a tiny percentage of the total market has become a huge percentage of
the total market it's a different creature so if i was in business and i was producing a good
or service and i was saving up enough money that i started to be able to invest that money and gain
interest or do things like that i could start realizing i'm making more money on my money
than i'm making on producing the goods and services so i stop even paying attention to
goods and services and start paying attention to making money on money and how do i utilize
capital to create more capital and capital gives me more optionality because i can buy anything with
it than a particular good or service that only some people want um capitalism
more capital ended up meaning more control i could put more people under my employment i could buy
larger pieces of land novel access to resource mines and put more technology under my employment
so it meant increased agency and also increased control i think attentionalism is even more powerful
so rather than enslave people where the people kind of always want to get away and put in the
least work they can there's a way in which economic servitude was just more profitable than slavery
right have the people work even harder voluntarily because they want to get ahead
and nobody has to be there to whip them or control them or whatever
this is a cynical take but a meaningful take um so people
so capital is a being a way to influence human behavior right and yet where people still feel
free in some meaningful way they they're not feeling like uh they're going to be punished by
the state if they don't do something it's like punished by the market be a homelessness or
something but the market is this invisible thing i can't put an agent on so it feels like free
and so if if you want to affect people's behavior and still have them feel free
capital ends up being a way to do that but i think affecting their attention is even deeper
because if i can affect their attention i can both affect what they want and what they believe
and what they feel and we statistically know this very clearly facebook has done studies that
based on changing the feed it can change beliefs emotional dispositions etc and so i think there's
a way that the the harvest and directing of attention is even a more powerful system than
capitalism it is effective in capitalism to generate capital but i think it also generates
influence beyond what capital can do and so do we want to have some groups utilizing that type
of tech to direct other people's attention if so um towards what towards what metrics of what a good
civilization and good human life would be what's the oversight process what is the
transparency i can i can i can answer all the things you're mentioning uh i i can build i guarantee
you if i am not such a lazy ass i'll be part of the many people doing this as transparency and
control i'll get to giving control to individual people okay so maybe the corporation has coordination
on its goals that all of its customers or users together don't have so there's some asymmetry
where it's uh asymmetry of its goals but maybe i could actually help all of the customers to
coordinate almost like a labor union or whatever by informing and educating them adequately about
the effects the externalities on them if this is not toxic waste going into the ocean of the
atmosphere it's their their minds their beings their families their relationships um such that
they will in group change their behavior and um i think the i one way of saying what you're
saying i think is that you think that you can rescue homo economicus from uh the the rational
actor that will pursue all the goods and services and choose the best one at the best price the kind
of rand von mises hayek that you can rescue that from dan arielli and behavioral econ that says
that's actually not how people make choices they make it based on status hacking largely
whether it's good for them or not in the long term and the large asymmetric corporation can run
propaganda and narrative warfare that hits people's status buttons and their limbic hijacks and
their lots of other things in ways that they can't even perceive that are happening um they're not
paying attention to that the site is employing psychologists and split testing and whatever
else so you're saying i think we can recover homo economicus and not just through a single
like mechanism technology there's there's the uh not to keep mentioning the guy but platforms like
georogan and so on that that make help make viral the ways that the education of negative
externalities can become viral in this world so interestingly i actually agree with you that
got him that we four and a half hours in that we can tech can do some good all right well see
what you're talking about is the application of tech here broadcast tech where you can speak to a
lot of people and that's not going to be strong enough because the different people need spoken
too differently which means it has to be different voices that get amplified to those audiences more
like facebook's tech but nonetheless we'll start with broadcast tech plants the first seed and then
the word of mouth is a powerful thing you need to do the first broadcast shotgun and then it like
lands a catapult of whatever i don't know what the right weapon is but then it just spreads the word
of mouth through all kinds of tech including facebook so let's come back to the fundamental
thing the fundamental thing is we want to kind of order at various scales from the conflicting
parts of ourselves actually having more harmony than they might have to family extended family
local all the way up to global we want emergent order where our choices
have more alignment right we want that to be emergent rather than imposed or rather than
we want fundamentally different things or make totally different sense of the world where
warfare of some kind becomes the only solution emergent order requires us in our choice making
requires us being able to have related sense making and related meaning making processes
can we apply digital technologies and exponential tech in general to try to increase the capacity
to do that where the technology called a town hall the social tech that we'd all get together and
talk obviously is very scale limited and it's also oriented to geography rather than networks of
aligned interest can we build new better versions of those types of things and going back to the
idea that a democracy or participatory governance depends upon comprehensive education in the
science of government which include being able to understand things like asymmetric information
warfare on the side of governments and how the people can organize adequately can you utilize
some of the technologies now to be able to support increased comprehensive education of the people
and maybe comprehensive informativeness so both fixing the decay in both education and the fourth
estate that have happened so the people can start self-organizing to then influence the corporations
the nation states to do different things and or build new ones themselves yeah fundamentally
that's the thing that has to happen we the exponential tech gives us a novel problem
landscape that the world never had the nuke gave us a novel problem landscape and so that required
this whole breton woods world the exponential tech gives us a novel problem landscape our
existing problem solving processes aren't doing a good job we have had more countries get nukes we
haven't a nuclear deproliferation we haven't achieved any of the un sustainable development goals
we haven't kept any of the new categories of tech for making arms races so our global coordination
is not adequate to the problem landscape so we need fundamentally better problem solving processes a
market or a state is a problem solving process we need better ones that can do the speed and
scale of the current issues right now speed is one of the other big things is that by the time we
regulated ddt out of existence or cigarettes not for people under 18 they'd already killed so many
people and we let the market do the thing but as elon has made the point that won't work for ai by
the time we recognize afterwards that we have an autopoietic ai that's a problem you won't be able
to reverse it that there's a number of things that when you're dealing with tech that is either
self replicating and disintermediate humans to keep going doesn't need humans to keep going
or you have tech that just has exponentially fast effects your regulation has to come early it can't
come after the effects have happened the negative effects have happened if because the negative
effects could be too big too quickly so we basically need new problem solving processes that do
better at being able to internalize externality solve the problems on the right timescale and the
right geographic scale and those new processes to not be imposed have to emerge from people wanting
them and being able to participate in their development which is what i would call kind of a
new cultural enlightenment or renaissance that has to happen where people start understanding
the new power that exponential tech offers the way that it is actually damaging
current governance structures that we care about and creating an extra-risk landscape but could also
be redirected towards more protopic purposes and then saying how do we rebuild new social
institutions what are adequate social institutions where we can do participatory governance at scale
in time and how can the people actually participate to build those things i the the solution that i
see working requires a process like that and the result maximizes love so again elan would be right
that love is the answer let me take it back from the scale of societies to the scale that's far far
more important which is the scale of family you've written a blog post about your dad
we have various flavors of relationships with our fathers what have you learned about life when
your dad well people can read the blog post and see a lot of individual things that i learned that
i really appreciated um if i was to kind of summarize at a high level um i had a really
incredible dad like very very unusually uh positive set of experiences he was committed
we were homeschooled and he was committed to work from home to be available and like prioritize
fathering in a really deep way um and you know as a super gifted super loving very unique man
he also had his unique issues that were part of what crafted the unique brilliance and those
things often go together and i say that because i think i had i had some unusual gifts and also
some unusual difficulties and i think it's useful for everybody to know their path probably has
both of those um but uh if i was to say kind of at the the essence of one of the things my dad
taught me across a lot of lessons was like a the intersection of self-empowerment ideas and practices
that self-empower towards collective good uh towards some virtuous purpose beyond the self
and he both said that a million different ways taught it in a million different ways when we
were doing construction and he was teaching me how to uh build a house we were putting the wires
to the walls before the drywall went on he made sure that the way that we put the wires through
is beautiful like the the that the height of the holes was similar that we twisted the wires in a
particular way that and it's like no one's ever going to see it and he's like if a job's worth
doing it's worth doing well and excellence is its own reward and those types of ideas and if there
was a really shitty job to do he'd say see the job do the job stay out of the misery just don't
indulge any negativity do the things that need done and so there's like a there's an empowerment
and a nobility together um and yeah extraordinarily fortunate is there ways you think you could have
been a better song is there things you regret it's an interesting question let me get first say
just as a bit of a criticism that uh what kind of man do you think you are not wearing a suit and
tie a real man should exactly uh i grew with your dad on that point you mentioned offline that uh he
suggested a real man should wear a suit and tie but outside of that is there ways you could have
been a better son maybe next time on your show i'll wear a suit and tie my dad would be happy about
that um please
i can answer the question later in life not early um i had just a huge amount of respect
and reverence for my dad when i was young so i was asking myself that question a lot so i
learned a lot of things i knew that i wasn't seeking to apply um there was a phase when i went
through my kind of individuation differentiation where i had to make him excessively wrong about
too many things um i don't think i had to but i did and he had a lot of kind of non-standard
model beliefs about things whether early kind of ancient civilizations or ideas on evolutionary
theory or alternate models of physics and and they weren't irrational but they didn't all have the
standard of epistemic proof that i would need and i went through and some of them were kind of
spiritual ideas as well i went through a phase in my early 20s where i kind of had that the
attitude that Dawkins or Christopher Hitchens has that can kind of be um like excessively
certain and sanctimonious uh applying their reductionist philosophy of science to everything and
um i'm kind of brutally dismissive uh i'm embarrassed by that phase um
i'm not to say anything about those men in their path but for myself and so during that time
i was more dismissive of my dad's epistemology than i would have liked to have been
i gotta correct that later apologize for it but that's the first thought that came to mind
you've written the following i've had the experience countless times making love watching
a sunset listening to music feeling the breeze that i would sign up for this whole life and all
of its pains just to experience this exact moment this is a kind of worldless knowing
it's the most important and real truth i know that experience itself is infinitely meaningful
and pain is temporary and seen clearly even the suffering is filled with beauty
i have experienced countless lives worth of moments worthy of life such an unreasonable fortune
a few words of gratitude from you beautifully written is there some beautiful moments now you
have uh experienced countless lives worth of those moments but there's some things that uh
if you could uh in your darker moments you can go to to relive to remind yourself that the whole
ride is worthwhile maybe skip the making love part we don't know about that i mean i i feel
i feel unreasonably fortunate that it is a such a humongous list because i mean i feel fortunate
to have like had exposure to practices and philosophies in a way of seeing things it makes
me see things that way so i can take responsibility for seeing things in that way and not taking for
granted really wonderful things but i can't take credit for being exposed to the philosophies that
even gave me that possibility um you know it's not just with my wife it's with every person who
i really love when we're talking i look at their face i in the context of a conversation feel
overwhelmed by how lucky i am to get to know them and like that there's never been someone like them
in all of history and there never will be again and then they might be gone tomorrow i might be
gone tomorrow and like i get this moment with them and when you take in the uniqueness of that
fully and the beauty of it it's overwhelmingly beautiful
and you know i remember the first time i did a big dose of mushrooms and i was looking at a tree
for a long time and i was just crying with overwhelming how beautiful the tree was and
it was a tree outside the front of my house that i'd walked by a million times and never looked at
like this and it wasn't the dose of mushrooms where i was hallucinating like where the tree was
purple like the tree still looked like if i had to describe it it's green and it has leaves looks
like this but it was way fucking more beautiful like like capturing than it normally was and i'm
like why is it so beautiful if i would describe it the same way and i realized i had no thoughts
taking me anywhere else yeah like what it seemed like the mushrooms were doing was just actually
shutting the narrative off that would have me be distracted so i could really see the tree
and then i'm like fuck when i get off these mushrooms i'm gonna practice seeing the tree
because it's always that beautiful and i just miss it and so i practice being with it and
quieting the rest of the mind and then being like wow and if it's not mushrooms like people have
peak experiences where they'll see life and how incredible it is it's always there it's funny
that i had this exact same experience and the un quite a lot of mushrooms just sitting alone
and looking at a tree and exactly as you described it appreciating the beauty undistorted beauty of
it and it's funny to me that here's two humans very different with very different journeys
where at some moment in time both looking at a tree like idiots for hours
and just in awe and and happy to be alive and yeah and uh even just that moment alone is
is worth living for but you did say humans and we have a moment together as two humans
and you mentioned shots well i have to ask what uh what are we looking at when i went to go
get a smoothie before coming here i got you a keto smoothie that you didn't want because
you're not just keto but fasting but i saw the thing with you and your dad where you did
shots together yeah and this place happened to have shots of um ginger turmeric cayenne
juice of some kind and so i with some Himalayan salt i didn't necessarily plan it for being on the
show but i just brought it wow but we can we can do it that way i think we should we shall uh
we shall toast like heroes daniel it's a huge honor what do we toast to what do we toast to
we toast to this moment this this this unique moment that we get to share together i'm very
grateful to be here in this moment with you and uh yeah i'm grateful that you invited me here
we met for the first time and i will never be the same for the good and the bad
i am
that is really interesting that feels way healthier than the vodka my dad and i were drinking
so i feel like a better man already daniel this is one of the best conversations i've ever had
i can't wait to have many more likewise this has uh it's been an amazing experience thank you for
wasting all your time today i want to say in terms of what you're mentioning about like the
that you work in machine learning and the optimism that wants to look at the issues but
wants to look at how this increased technological power could be applied to solving them and that
even thinking about the broadcast of like can i help people understand the issues better and
help organize them like fundamentally you're you're oriented like wikipedia what i see to
really try to tend to the information commons without another agentic interest distorting it
and for you to be able to get guys like
lee smolen and roger pennrose and like the the the greatest thinkers of that are alive and you
know have them on the show and most people would never be exposed to them and talk about it in a
way that people can understand uh i think it's an incredible service i think you're doing great
work so i was really happy to hear from you thank you daniel thanks for listening to this
conversation with daniel schmockdenberger and thank you to ground news net suite for
sigmatic magic spoon and better help check them out in the description to support this podcast
and now let me leave you with some words from albert einstein i know not with what weapons
world war three will be fought but world war four will be fought with sticks and stones
thank you for listening and hope to see you next time