If you have a democratic style of governance, you are entrusting people with one of the most
awesome and radical of responsibilities. And that's saying that you're going to pick the people
that are going to make some of the hardest decisions in all of human history. If you're
going to trust people to vote correctly, you have to be able to trust them to have open
and honest dialogue with each other. Whether that's Nazis or KKK people or whoever talking,
you have to believe that your people are going to be able to rise above and make the correct
determinations when they hear these types of speeches. And if you're so worried that somebody's
going to hear a certain political figure and they're going to be completely radicalized instantly,
then what that tells me is that you don't have enough faith in humans for democracy to be a
viable institution, which is fine. You can be anti-democratic, but I don't think you can be
pro-democracy and anti-free speech. The following is a conversation with Stephen Bonnell,
also known online as Destiny. He's a video game streamer and political commentator,
one of the early pioneers of both live streaming in general and live streamed political debate and
discourse. Politically, he is a progressive, identifying as either left or far left, depending
on your perspective. There are many reasons I wanted to talk to Stephen. First, I just talked
to Ben Shapiro and many people have told me that Stephen is the Ben Shapiro of the left
in terms of political perspective and exceptional debate skills. Second reason
is he skillfully defends some nuanced, non-standard views, at the same time being pro-establishment,
pro-institutions, and pro-Biden, while also being pro-capitalism and pro-free speech.
Third reason is he has been there at the beginning and throughout the meteoric rise of the video
game live streaming community. In some mainstream circles, this community is not taken seriously,
perhaps because of its demographic distribution skewing young or perhaps because of the sometimes
harsh style of communication. But I think this community should be taken seriously and shown
respect. Millions of young minds tune into live streams like Destiny's to question and to try
to understand what is going on with the world, often exploring challenging, even controversial
ideas. The language is sometimes harsher and the humor is sometimes meaner than I would prefer,
but I, grandpa Lex, put on my rain boots and went into the beautiful chaotic muck of online discourse
and have so far survived to tell the tale with a smile and even more love in my heart than before.
On top of all this, we were lucky to have Malina Goranson, a popular streamer and world traveler,
join us at the end of the conversation. You can check out her channel on twitch.tv
slash malina, and you can check out Stephen's channel on youtube.com slash destiny. This is
the Lex Friedman podcast. To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description. And
now, dear friends, here's destiny. I don't know if you watched me watching your
yay interview. Yeah, thank you so much. I'm so curious. When you're navigating a conversation
like that, are you, how intentional is the thought process between like building rapport and pushing
and giving a little and letting like zero, zero intention? I was watching and thank you so much.
I was very kind for you to review that conversation. It meant a lot that you were
complimentary in parts on the technical aspects of the conversation, but no, zero. And I'm actually
deliberately trying to avoid, I think you've called it debate brain, which is just another
flavor of thinking about like the meta conversation, trying to optimize how should this conversation go.
Because I feel like the more you do that, the better you get at that, the less human connection
you have. Like the less genuinely you're actually sitting there in the moment and listening to the
person, you're more like calculating what's the right thing to say versus like feeling. What is
that person feeling right now? What are they thinking? That's what I'm trying to do is like
putting myself in their mind and thinking, what does the world look like to them? What does the world
feel like to them? And so from that, I truly try to listen. Now I'm also learning, especially because
Rogan and others have been giving me shit for not pushing back. It's good sometimes to say
from a place of care for the other human being to say, stop. What did you just say? I don't think
that represents who you are and what you really mean. Or maybe if it does at that time represents
who they are, I can see a better world if they grow into a different direction and try to point
that direction out to them. There's a really complicated dance between letting somebody
share their full story versus letting somebody like essentially proselytize your audience and
it's like, okay, hold on, let's take a minute here. But yeah, I used to be four or five years ago,
it was attack, attack, attack, attack, attack, whatever you said. And now I'm leaning way more
towards the like, okay, well, tell me how you feel about everything and then we'll go from there.
So a lot of people like my new approach, some older fans will watch and they're like,
why are you letting this guy just ramble on? You know, he said like five or six wrong things and
you're only going to call them out on two of them and it's like, it's different styles of
conversation, but yeah. Do you do a lot of research beforehand too? Depending on the
conversation, yeah. So if we're going to talk like vaccines and stuff, yeah, that's a ton of
reading and stuff that I never thought I'd know going into it. If it's a more personal, like political
philosophy conversation, there's not as much you can prepare for just, it truly depends on the
conversation. How much are you actually listening to the other person? Always listening, you have
to listen because as soon as you stop listening, the quality of everything falls apart, the connection
disappears, the quality of the conversation disappears, but my natural inclination is to
just be way more aggressive than normal. So I have to constantly remind myself, I guess you would
call it a meta conversation when you're like, okay, he's probably saying this because of that or
we'll let him go here and then we'll stop later. But yeah, because my preferred style of conversation
is like, I'm going to talk and the second I say something you disagree with, then let's
iron it out, right? I got like, I think in like syllogisms, like, okay, here's premise A,
good, okay, premise B, okay, and then conclusion. And then as long as we're both deductively
sound, we're not crazy, no psychosis, then we're going to agree on everything. Whereas other people
like to, most people think in stories like narratives, like a whole, there's a whole like
narrative and the individual facts don't matter as much because they'll pick and choose what they
want. And it's really hard because everybody thinks narratives have to function in that world,
but it's frustrating for me sometimes. Well, I've seen, you've had a lot of excellent debates.
One of them I just recently last night watched is on systemic racism. And it's the first time
I've seen you completely lose your shit. Oh, shoot, who was that against? I'm not sure exactly,
but you were just very frustrated and sorry, not lose your shit, but you're frustrated constantly
because of the thing, let's lay out 123. And every time you try to lay it out, it would falter.
I think it had to do with sort of, can you use data to make an argument? Or do you need to use
a study that does an interpretation of that data? And then there's like this tension between,
I think this is a behavioral economist that you were talking to. And the point is, you do this
kind of nice layout that the whole point of behavioral economics, it says there's more
to it than just the data you have to give a context and like do the rich, rigorous interpretation
in the context of the full human story. And then there was like a dance back and forth. Sometimes
you use data, sometimes not, and you're getting really frustrated and shutting down. And so that
felt like a failure mode. I've seen Sam Harris have similar sticking points. Like if we can't
agree on the terminology, we can't go on. To me, I feel like the Wittgenstein perspective is like,
I think if you get stuck on any one thing, you're just not going to make progress. You have to,
part of the conversation has to be about doing a good dance together versus being
dogmatically stuck on the path to truth. I think the true challenge is identifying
what of those sticking points are important versus what is not important. It's like if I'm
having an argument with somebody about Jewish representation and media, it might be like a
big conversation and they might say a couple things. I think Jewish people, they tend to help
their own or whatever and saying, okay. But for the purpose of the conversation, we can keep moving.
But if they casually drop like, yeah, and I think that's why the Holocaust numbers were
blown up from like 100,000 to 6 million. And I was like, okay, hold on, wait,
if you think this, we have to stop here because this is going to be, it's not just a language
game in this part. If you really believe this fact, then the whole rest of the conversation is
going to be informed by that belief. And it has to be something that doesn't bother you personally.
You have to step outside your own ego. So Holocaust denial is somebody that would bother a lot of
people and there's some things just observing you. I feel like when you get really good at
conversation, you can become a stickler to, you might have your favorite terms that really
bothers you. People don't agree on those terms. Beggs the question. You mean racing the question.
Yeah, I usually just want, people say stuff, I just let it slide, yeah. Because if you fight,
when you're having a conversation with somebody and you're talking to their audience at the
same time, because that's really what's happening, you never want to come off as over combative or
over aggressive because it puts people in like, there's like a trigger in your brain and this
is true of relationships or friendships of persuasive rhetoric or whatever. There's a
trigger in the brain and as soon as that defensive trigger gets like flipped on,
everything is over. You've lost the ability to persuade because everything becomes a fight at
that point. Yeah. Well, I wanted to talk to you because I heard somewhere that you were referred
to as the Ben Shapiro of the left and since I'm talking with Ben as well, I wanted to sort of
complete spiritually this platonic political philosophy puzzle in my head. You are a progressive
but a progressive with many nonstandard progressive views and you had a heck of a fascinating
journey through all of that. And like I said, I think you argue with passion sometimes with
excessive amounts of passion. That's a really polite way of saying that. Almost always with
good faith and with rigor, with seriousness. I asked on your subreddit, which is an excellent
subreddit. Shout out to the Destiny subreddit so much, at least for that particular post.
What I really loved is when I asked for questions for you, there were like, holy
shit, there's adults and there's all behave. Like nobody say incest. I was like, what was going on
here? But actually the questions that rose to the top were really good. So somebody said that
Destiny was speaking of your journey was a conservative in his early teens. Then he became
libertarian. Then he became a left-wing social justice warrior. Then he flirted with socialism.
And now he is a social democrat liberal. I've also heard you refer to yourself
as a far left person. So to the degree there's truth to that journey. Can you take me through
your evolution through the landscape of political ideologies that you went through?
So my dad comes from Kentucky and my mom is a Cuban immigrant. Cubans are notorious for being
very conservative in the United States for historical reasons and for other reasons.
But my upbringing was a very Republican one. I grew up listening to Rush Limbaugh, Glenn Beck,
Michael Savage on the radio, Billy Cunningham. I think Sean Hannity a little bit later on,
like that was like my whole upbringing politically. I remember I was writing,
I'd written like articles for the school journal, like in favor of
defending the war in Iraq and defending Bush from all the criticism, etc. So that was my
upbringing. I think once I hit high school college, I had my edgy, like libertarian-esque
high school phase of like reading Ayn Rand, of figuring out that like, oh my god, nothing in life
matters except for class and money. That's actually the answer to everything. And I got to college,
I became a Ron Paul fan, very big Ron Paul fan. And then from there, I kind of work, do life, life
happens at the kind of the lowest point in my life in terms of where I'm working financially.
Everything is like kind of in ruin in my life. There's a whole bunch of dumb stuff that's happened
probably my most conservative point. I don't know what it is about like being poor and thinking like
you can work your way out of it, you can do whatever. It's just my upbringing is always just
like, if you're not, if you're not, if you're not having financial success, just work, work, work,
work, work. And then I got into streaming, very, very lucky break. Everything just lined up at
the right time. And then as I've progressed through streaming, I would say through the years,
I've gradually fallen more and more to the left, especially once my kid turned four, five, six years
old. And I started to see like how much different his life was, just because of the financial
opportunities that I was able to provide for him through no merit of his own. And that started
to radically change how I viewed the world in a lot of ways. So actually, let's like linger on that.
Yeah. Low point. You worked at McDonald's, you worked at a casino, you did carpet cleaning.
What was the lowest point? Definitely the carpet cleaning.
Really? Absolutely. Why? Why was it the lowest point? That's when you were just flirting with
starting streaming. My whole life has been a series of lucky breaks, really, truly. I grew up
playing a lot of video games. But back in my day, our day, you had to read, there was a lot of text
on the screen. Back in my day, we used to play... They didn't all talk to you. Yeah, because nowadays,
everything's voice acting. But back then, you'd have to read a lot. I was a really good reader
and a really good vocabulary. Yeah, I've heard you actually say that. What games are we talking
about? What do you mean just reading? You're talking about like RPGs or what? Yeah, JRPGs. So
like Final Fantasy games, Fantasy Stars, all of these, like any RPG that would have been on the
SNES, Sega, PlayStation, these are the things that I'm... Let's pause on that. Okay. I just talked
to Howard, who's of the Elder Scrolls fame and the Fallout fame and beyond. What's your thoughts
on Elder Scrolls? Why Skyrim the greatest RPG of all time? Man, I really don't like Skyrim or Fallout.
You don't love it. Oh, really? No, not at all. Why do you hate Skyrim?
Yeah, so I really like characters and like compelling stories and narratives around those
characters. And I like to see them kind of like grow and change kind of like a movie or a story.
So in your like Final Fantasy games, you've got characters. There are a lot of like,
like classical tropes of like a character starts off kind of like edgy angsty all on their own.
They develop relationships, friendships, they realize that the life is more about themselves
and they do that. And I like that growth. That's kind of what you see in all of those old role
playing games. I didn't like the open world ones as much because your main character is just like
a blank slate, never talks. It's for you to like project onto. But there's not the same like linear
narrative of like growth for the character. Oh, that's fascinating. There's an actual story arc
to the character that's more crafted in a beautiful way by the designers of the game. Yeah.
I don't think one is better or worse. I tend towards like, I want to hear a compelling story
around like a set of characters that like grow and change just again. Oh, that's beautifully
put then. Yeah, I just really loved being able to leave the town, you go outside the town and you
look outside its nature and the world of possibilities is before you. You can do whatever the fuck you
want. I mean, that immensity of just being lost in the world is really immersive for me. But yeah,
you're right. Whatever attracts you about a world. So you were just starting to play video games.
You go out play to video games. That's one of your lucky breaks.
There's just like a lot of random skills you pick up depending on the type of game you play.
I played a lot of tech space games on the computer. So I was a very fast type or I'm still a very
fast type or read a lot, you know, learn weird kind of math stuff for some of the calculations,
some of the games. I think I'm pretty good at getting information, figuring stuff out, learning
patterns, all of that. And then that plus the reading and everything in the games meant that I
I don't want to say I excelled in school because my grades were pretty bad, but I was on like all
honors, all AP classes or whatever. A lot of dual enrollment, a lot of AP credit going into college.
So I did pretty well in school, probably better than I should have, but it was because I had the
game stuff that was like really powering a lot of my brain there while I was trying to sleep
through class. So you're able to soak in information, integrate it, quickly take notes.
Generally, I think I'm pretty good at that. You do this a lot when you stream your typing stuff.
Is there a system in that note taking? And what note what do you use for note taking?
Does it matter? I use a notepad. Like notepad.exe notepad.exe not the plus plus not.
Is there genius to the madness behind that? Or you just don't give a shit?
No, I mean, it's going to depend on the style of conversation. If I'm with somebody that is
very meticulously organized their thoughts and they're a fine and better word here for Rambler,
you can edit that in, better word for Rambler. Somebody that talks a lot and a lot, I'll start
like taking notes, bullet points like this, this, this, this, this, this, this, because there's a
style of conversation where I say seven or eight different things. And then when you go to respond
to everything I said, I cut you off immediately and we argue that point. But if somebody's going
to do that, he's just like, hold on, you just said these eight things, I'm going to respond to
every single one. I've written them all down and then you can go, if you want to go point by
point, we can, but you just said all this and I wrote it down, so we're going to go.
So what are you actually writing down like a couple of words per point they left?
Honestly, like there are very few unique conversations in politics. Like a lot of them
are kind of retreading old ground. So if we're having a debate on abortion, somebody might say,
like, oh, well, I believe this thing about viability. And I believe this thing about, you
know, when they're a fetus versus a human and I'll just write down like those points so that when
I go to respond, I kind of have like a like note cards, like a guiding thing there to
keep me centered on my response. Political discourse is a kind of tree you're walking
down and I got it and you're like taking just to keep my focus guided. So I'm not like
running off in a weird tangent or responding to something I didn't say or something.
What about like doing research? It's just, is there a system to your note taking? Because
mentally, you seem to be one of the most organized people I've listened to. So is there,
is it in your mind or is there a system that's on paper?
A little of both. I feel like the human mind is a beautiful thing if you have interest in an area.
So like what I'll tell people is, let's say there's like a totally new topic that I'm
researching. I don't know anything. And I'll do a couple of these on stream. I think they're boring
about it. People watch it. I might open a Wikipedia article and I'll read and I hit something I don't
know. And then I open the next Wikipedia article and I'll read into and then I might have like seven
tabs open and I'll read and I'll read and I'll read. And I'll read a ton of stuff maybe for
hour two, three, four hours of stuff. And then by the end, you know, someone in chat will ask me
like, do you even remember like this particular thing? And I'll say, not really. No, not too much.
But what happens is as long as you've seen it once, what'll happen is like the next day of the
day after we'll read something else. And we're like, oh, I remember that thing from this thing.
I remember like vaguely that. And then if you see it like a third time, you're like, oh, this
makes sense because especially when it comes to, oh, here's like a little trick on stuff. If you're
ever reading any news and there's a place that pops up, always look at it on a map because so
much of history is like on a map. It's so important to like know the geography. It makes things make
so much more sense. But yeah, once I once I start to see stuff over and over again, just because
I've like read it a few times, stuff will start to kind of connect to my mind and like, oh, yeah,
well, this makes sense. Of course, these people believe this because of this or of course, like
this happened here, it's because you know, that happened there. So yeah, it's a lot of that if
there's like a topic that I'm doing specific research for. So like vaccine related stuff is a
big one. The Ukrainian Russian conflict is a big one. That I'll break out a note. I'll probably
get like a Google doc and I'll just start like writing like an outline of kind of the rough
points of everything just to organize my thoughts around different topics. Yeah.
We're just going to go on tangent upon a tangent upon a tangent. We'll return to the
low point of your life at some point, always returning from the philosophy to the psychology.
So you did the Ukraine topic. One question is, what role does US play in this war? Could they
have done something to avoid the war? Did they have a role to play in forcing Vladimir Putin's
hand? Do they have a role to play in deescalating the war towards a peace agreement and the opposite?
If it does escalate towards something like the use of a tactical nuclear weapon,
are they to blame? Are we to blame? Oh man, somebody sent me an email a while ago with great
words. There's a specific way to navigate a conversation where you can kind of like contribute
to a negative event, but you're not really the one responsible for it. Like the classic example
is a woman goes out late at night, gets a little bit too drunk, and then something happens. And
it's like, while there might have been steps you could have taken to mitigate the risk,
it's not her fault of what happened because the responsibility rests on the agent making
the choice, right? There's a chooser at some point that is choosing to do wrong or evil.
I don't believe in any of the arguments that say the United States has contributed to Russia's
position on Ukraine or the actions that they've taken on Ukraine. There are several arguments
that some people, some even political scholars are putting out there to say that the United
States is to blame, but I find them completely unconvincing. I think that when you ask the
question of like, what is the United States role or what has our role been? I think it's
really important for us. I don't think we even agree as a country on what our role should be,
which I think is a hard one because you've got this kind of, there's this growing populist
movement in the United States. It might be the far left and the far right. And I think populists
tend to have this kind of isolationist view of the world where the United States should just be
our own thing. We shouldn't be telling anybody what to do. We shouldn't be the world police.
And then kind of more in these like center left, center right positions. And then across a lot of
Europe, you've got, well, okay, the United States is kind of like the big kid on the block.
Like we're looking to them for guidance and leadership on situations like what's going on
in Ukraine. So in so far as the original question is like, what is like the United
States responsibility? I think we have a responsibility to ensure the relative like
freedom, prosperity and stability across Europe. I think that defending Ukraine's sovereignty
and right to their borders is a part of that. And I don't believe that prior to the invasion
in 2022, I don't think the United States was contributing to Russia invading that country.
I know there are arguments given that like the expansion of NATO has something that's been
threatening to Russia, but the Baltics joined and Russia didn't do anything about it. The
invasion to Crimea was very clearly a response to the revolution in 2014. The invasion on the
borders is clearly a response to Ukraine winning that civil war in the Southeast and the Donbass
and Russia becoming more aggressive. I don't think that you can blame any of that on NATO
expansion. There's no NATO countries that are threatening Russia or debating Russia.
Do you think there is a nuclear threat? Do you think about this? Do you worry about this that
there is a threat of a tactical nuclear weapon being dropped? I think that possibility exists
either way. I think the responsibility for that is on Russia because it just can't be the case
that if you have nukes, you're allowed to invade countries and take their land. Because of anything,
I think that that down the road also increases the potential for nuclear problems in the future,
because at that point, either every single country has to acquire their own nuclear weapons,
because if you don't, Russia's going to mess with you, or every single country has to join NATO,
and now what? We're back at square zero, ground zero, square one, where people are like,
oh, well look, all these countries joining NATO is aggressive towards Russia. What are you going
to do? Yeah, you've mentioned that there's a complicated calculus going on with the countries
that have nuclear weapons, and what's our responsibility? Are you allowed to do anything
you want to countries that don't have nuclear weapons? That's a really tricky discussion,
for sure, because what is U.S. supposed to do if Russia drops a tactical nuclear weapon?
There's a set of options, none of which are good, and it's such a tricky moment right now,
because the things that Biden and other public figures say, I feel like has a significant impact
on the way this game turns out, because I think mutually assured destruction is partially a game
of words. I mean, I believe in the power of conversation of leaders talking to each other.
I feel like you have to have a balance between threat and compromise, and empathy for the needs,
the geopolitical, the economic needs of a nation, but also respect and represent your own interests.
It's a tricky one. How do you play the hand? It reminds me of, I don't know if you've ever
heard of evolutionary psychology or evolutionary biology. There are things called tit for tat
strategies. It reminds me of that, where there are a whole bunch of these little biological
mechanisms where creatures will develop, like socializing, like tit for tat. If you do something
bad to me, I'm going to do something bad for you, and then more complicated schemes will come out,
where it'll be like tit, tit for tat, where it's like you can make one mistake, and then I'm going
to get you to do a second one, or it could be tit, tit, tit for tat, or there could be tit for tat,
tat for tat. There's all these back and forths where creatures optimize themselves. I think
something the United States did really well in terms of that kind of conversational strategy,
and I approved of this in the beginning, was Biden was very clear about setting out the exact
level of US involvement for the war. We're not going to do a no-fly zone. There's not going to be
US troops on the ground in Ukraine, but we are going to send a whole bunch of money and a whole
bunch of arms and a whole bunch of intel to them. I thought he did a good job at laying out the
limitation of the US involvement while opening as much as we could in the ways that we could help,
but that looming threat of some sort of tactical nuclear weapon, I think on the table right now
is like it's going to be the annihilation of Russian seaforces and everything, but
what happens if it continues to escalate? That's like a world that nobody wants to
be in. Yeah. So we talked about difficult conversations, and again, thank you so much
for reviewing the Yale conversation. Let me ask you about Putin. Speaking of difficult conversations,
so if you sit down, if I sit down with somebody like Vladimir Putin or Vladimir Zelensky,
what's the right way to have that conversation? Oh man. We can talk about that one or we could talk
about somebody more well understood through history like Stalin or Hitler, something like that.
Maybe that's an easier example to illustrate how to handle extremely difficult conversations.
Yeah. I mean, I can handle really difficult conversations between like two people,
leaders of countries though. There's so much that you are representing in that conversation.
I guess the thing that would be interesting to me would be like, what is Vladimir Putin's
interest? What is the genuine interest that he has in the conflict? Because I think finding out
like what is your buy-in or what is the driving force keeping you here is probably the most
important thing. I think for Zelensky, I think it's quite a bit more simpler because he's
on the defense, so it's defending his country and his people. For Putin, I've heard all sorts of
things. Dugan has his writings on like the East versus the West, the collapse of the West in the
face of all of the liberalism and the weird LGBT stuff that they criticize. You've got the desire
to return to this former Soviet Union-esque thing. You've got Putin's quotes that collapse of the
Soviet Union was the biggest geopolitical disaster of 20th century. I guess figuring out what is
Putin after. I'm not actually sure. I don't know the answer to that question. I know a lot of people
write about it, but yeah. Well, there's a lot of answers to that question. There's a lot of answers
that he can give to that question, so say I sit down with him for three hours and talk about it.
I think this is a really interesting distinction because you do do difficult conversations
in the space of ideas, but also in your stream, there's a bunch of drama going on. There's the
human psychology is laid out in its full richness before you. To me with leaders, I think a part of
the conversation has to be about the human psychology, not like a meta-conversation, but
really understand what they feel, what they fear, who they are as a human being. As a family man,
as a person proud of their country, as a person with an ego, as a person who's been
affected, if not corrupted by powers, all of us can be and likely are. All of that,
that gives context to then the answers about what do you want in this war, because the answers
about what you want in this war will be political answers. It's a game that's being played again
with words, and politicians are incredibly good at playing that game. I think the deeper truth
comes from understanding the human being from which those words come, and I think that's what
you do. I don't know if you do those kinds of conversations where- Never talked to any country
leader, so- No, not a country leader, but say a controversial figure or somebody that represents
a certain idea. Don't just talk in a space of ideas or challenge the ideas, but understand who
is this person, how did you come to those ideas? Oh yeah, when I've had, there have been a couple
of very controversial right-leaning figures. So the two, obviously the mainstream is made by
Lauren Southern and Nick Fuentes. Those types of conversations initially aren't very political at
all. Yeah, it's more like, obviously we believe in very, very, very different things that beliefs
don't happen accidentally, so how did you get to where you are? Those are way more personal
conversations, that's true. Is there things you regret about those conversations where you failed?
Is there things you're proud of or you succeeded? For things that I'm proud of, I feel like I'm
really good at attempting to understand people without judgment, that I think a lot of people
feel like they can have conversations with me where they can share a lot, and I'm not going to jump
down their throat for them having a politically incorrect observation, or for them being judgmental
to somebody else or having a feeling that's maybe not something they should have something they're
embarrassed about. So I think I do a really good job at that, and then by extension of that,
I've gotten the ability to hear perspectives from so many different people that I think I can
understand a lot of different perspectives. For failures of mine, I mean it's always going to be
on stream, it'll be like I didn't push back hard enough or I didn't know a certain fact for a
conversation. These are usually the they're going to be on these like very technical grounds
generally. I'm pretty happy with like the direction my conversations have gone
recently, especially over like the past six months. So your goal is to
de-radicalize the audience of those folks. So that used to be my goal. My goal was de-radicalization.
Now I'm kind of hoping that that's just the byproduct. So the goal I think is to talk to
somebody and to show they believe this because of these reasons, and if you want to change
people's beliefs, we have to talk about the underlying reasons for why they think the things
they think. It's not enough to just say like that belief is bad because it's like, well,
they believe it for a whole bunch of things that are true and real to them at least. So you have
to address all of the underlying things that they believe before you can change the overlying
belief. So if I'm having a conversation with somebody, it'll be like, okay, why do you feel
this about that, that, and that? Okay, I understand that. Maybe like a better way to solve that would
be like this or that instead of this thing. So to what degree do you have to empathize with the
person's worldview versus pushback? That's always the hard one. When I'm talking to other people,
it's almost always me stepping as much inside their bubble as I can. I have to like live and
breathe their worldview and be able to speak their worldview in order to like navigate their thoughts.
Because my worldview is, and I'm not even used as an insult. I don't know if I am a little bit
autistic or something, but when I break apart things, I just want to see like study, study,
study, fact, fact, fact. That's how my mind works for everything. That's what I like to see.
Personal stories don't do much for me. Narratives don't do much for me. Just show me like the
data and the studies or whatever. But for other people, I think most brains are more human than
that and they tend to see things in more kind of like surreal pictures that are kind of painted
and the brush strokes are way broader and they don't care about the itty-bitty tiny fact.
So if I'm talking to somebody else and I'm trying to get into their head and I'm trying
to change their mind on things, I'm going to be stepping into their world and I'm going to try
to be working through that framework. Really good example might be, we'll say like when it comes
to trans issues for minors, okay, 16 or 17-year-old needs to go on puberty blockers. The way that I
want that debate to play out is let's look at all the data, let's see what are the outcomes,
let's see what are the processes for getting a medication, and then we'll evaluate all of that
and then we'll go in whatever like points more favorably. But that's wholly unconvincing to
most people, right? So as a parent, if I'm having that conversation with another parent,
the easiest way for me to have that conversation is like, hey, we both have kids.
Imagine how horrible it would be if we felt like our kids needed help and the government
was trying to get between us and their doctor in that conversation. That might be how that
talk plays out, which I mean, I think that's a really good argument because I think there
probably are times when the government should get in between it, but I'll have that conversation
because now I'm in a world where they understand what I'm saying, I'm resonating with the way
that they feel about things and then I can make progress with the way that they're kind of viewing
the world because I'm talking in a language they understand. So on this particular topic of
trans issues, is that the reason you were banned from Twitch? I'm not sure. I don't know. They just
said hate speech, but I don't use like slurs or anything. So it's hard to know exactly. So I think
you made the claim that trans women shouldn't compete with cis women in the women's athletics.
Can you make this case and can you still man the case against it? I think in your community,
there's a lot of trans folks who love you and there's a lot who hate you. Yeah. And so if you
can walk the tightrope of this conversation to try to steal men both sides. One of the argumentative
strategies I say is that like anytime you have a conversation, you should be able to argue both
sides better than anybody else. So for the my side, the genuine belief side, it feels like
overwhelmingly all of the data is showing that trans women, even after I think three years on
some sort of like HRT or estrogen stuff, they're still maintaining these advantages from their
male puberty over cisgender women. And if that is the case, if we are going to draw these distinctions
around our sports between women and men, it feels unfair to have a category inside the women's
sports that are maintaining advantages that are coming from a male puberty, regardless of the
amount of time they've spent on hormone replacement therapy. So that would be my argument on that side.
So it's unfair from a performance enhancement aspect. So the same way we ban performance
enhancing drugs that involve increasing of testosterone in that same way would be unfair.
Essentially, yeah. So what's the case against? So the case in favor of them competing together is
that realistically, there's not going to be a trans sports category. Realistically, trans women
aren't going to be competitive with cis men because they've gone through these huge,
you know, like hormone changes by the medication they're taking. And that when we look at how
sports are kind of done anyway, there's a whole bunch of biological differences between people
within sports categories that are determining their placement in the professional world.
So for instance, somebody like me is probably never going to go far in the NBA because I'm not
tall enough. I think the average height in the NBA. Don't doubt yourself. Don't doubt myself yet.
I want to say like six or something. They're huge people. Or, you know, you look at like Michael
Phelps is a classic example of a guy whose torso is like so long his body is built for swimming.
And I think there are some trans people that will look at that or somebody advocating for
this position. They'll look at that and go, okay, realistically, the way that Michael Phelps body
processes lactic acid, the shape physiologically of his body is going to put him in a level of
competition that so many men are never going to reach just because of biology. How is it fair
that you can have these biological outliers competing in these categories? But then when we
come to like sports categories with trans and cis women, you're going to take trans women and say
that they can't compete against cis women. Can't you also just say that they have some level of
biological difference there? Like, is it really going to be that great of a difference than what
Michael Phelps has versus the average swimmer or an NBA player has versus like the average height
male? Yeah, do you think we're going to get into some tricky ethical territory as we start to be
able to, through biology and genetics, modify the human body? Absolutely. I feel like those
things are coming sooner than we wanted them to. Oh, man, dude, have you seen the AI art?
Yes, of course. I'm an AI person. Oh, okay, then yeah, yeah. That's always been like,
what's going to happen when robots can do art better than humans, lol? Like, well,
we'll see you in 20 years and 20 years and 20 years. And now you have AI art winning competitions.
And it's funny because robots are essentially... There's a robot behind you, by the way.
A robot behind me. Oh, nice. Robots are really good at... Careful what you say. Yeah. Oh,
god, I'll be careful. That's not like the one of the Chinese ones with a gun on it, right? Oh, okay.
Hopefully not. We'll see, depending on what you say, yeah. Robots are really good at showing
the limitations of the human mind in categories that we didn't believe we were limited before.
I think that humans have this idea, intrinsically, that we have some type of innovative creative
drive that is just outside of the bounds of physical understanding. And with a sophisticated
enough program, we see that maybe that's not actually true. And that's a really scary thing
philosophically to deal with because we feel like we're very special, right? We own the planet,
we make computers, and the idea that you can start to get these robots that can do things that's
like, okay, you can do math, fine. Okay, you can do calculations, fine. But you can't do art.
That's the human stuff. And then when they start to do that, it's like, oh, shoot.
And that terrifies you a little bit, like the human species losing control of our dominance?
I don't think it's necessarily losing control of our dominance. I mean, I guess a Skynet thing
could come in at some point. But I think it brings us to this really fundamental level of like,
what does it mean to be human? What is it that we're good at? What should we be doing with
technology? We never really asked that question in the Western world. It's always the technology is
like normative in that technology equals good, and more technology equals better. That's been
like the default assumption. In fact, if you ask a lot of people, how do you know if civilization
has progressed over the past 100 or 200 years, they don't say we have better relationships,
we, you know, have longer marriages, we blah, blah, blah, they'll say technology has improved.
We've got crazy phones, we've got crazy computers. And the idea that more technology might be bad
has never even crossed somebody's mind, unless it's used for like a really bad thing. So,
well, it's interesting. We kind of think as more and more automation is happening,
we're going to get more and more meaning from things like being artists and doing creative
pursuits. And here's like, oh, shit, if the art, if the creative pursuits are also being automated,
then what are we going to gain meaning from? What are the activities from which we'll gain
meaning? You know, my whole life I've been working on artificial intelligence systems. There's been
different revolutions. One of them is the machine learning revolution. And it's interesting to build
up intuition and destroy that intuition about what is and isn't solvable by machines. I think
for the longest time, I grew up thinking go is not, the game of go is not solvable.
Because my understanding of AI systems is ultimately that it's
fundamentally a search mechanism that is fundamentally going to be brute force. There's
no shortcuts. Sure. Like if it can't solve the traveling salesman problem, it's not even
going to be able to give you an approximation. So most interesting problems are giant travel
salesman problem. And then, so of course, it's not going to be able to solve that. And then you,
then the deep learning revolution made you realize, holy shit, these large neural networks with a
giant number of knobs is able to actually somehow estimate functions that can do a pretty good job
of understanding deep representation of a thing, whether that's a game of go, or whether it's the
human natural language, or if it's images and video or audio and even actions and different
video games and actions of robotics and so on. And then you realize with diffusion models and
different generative models, you start to realize, holy shit, it can actually generate not just
interesting representations or interesting manifestations of the representations and forms,
but it's able to do something that impresses humans in its creativity. It's beautiful in
the way we think of art is beautiful. Like it surprises us and makes us chuckle and makes us
sit back and all and all those kinds of things. And yet the thing that it seems to struggle with
the most is the physical world currently. So that's counterintuitive. We humans think that it's
pretty trivial, being able to pick up a cup, being able to write with a pen in the physical
space, we think that's trivial. We give ourselves respect for being great artists and great
mathematicians and all that kind of stuff. And that seems to be much easier than the physical
space. Our bodies are really cool. There is a, I don't know, it's probably Asimov or something,
there was some science fiction writer that had a short story and it was like an alien that had
landed on earth and it was describing our bodies from a totally alien perspective. And when you
think about all the things we can do, it's pretty cool. We can climb through a whole multitude of
environments. We can exist in a multitude of temperatures. We can manipulate things just
with our hands and the way that we can interact with things around us. And yeah, we're very capable
on a physical level. Even though, like you said, we think about ourselves like, oh, well, human
beings have really big brains and we do. We're really intelligent as well, but our bodies are
pretty cool too. And it's a fascinating hierarchical biological system. We're made up of a bunch of
different living organisms that all don't know about the big picture of our body and it's all
functioning its own little local world and it's doing its thing, but together as it forms a
super resilient system, all of that comes from a very compressed encoding of what makes a human.
You start with the DNA and it builds up from a single cell to a giant organism. And because of
the DNA through the evolution process, you can constantly create new humans and new living
organisms that adapt to the environment. Like that resilience to the physical world,
it seems like running the whole earth over again, the whole evolutionary process over again,
is might be the only way to do it. So to create a robot that actually adapts
is as resilient to the dynamic world might be a really difficult problem.
Possibly. Well, it's going to say like in a programming environment, you can do things on
time scales that are impossible in the real world, right? Like the benefit to AI and computers is
computationally, they can compute so much data so quickly. Whereas on human timetables, we have
to wait. When you talk about evolution, you know, it's generation after generation after
generation, you know, maybe in a virtual environment that could be simulated and then those changes
could happen a lot quicker. Well, that's not a human time scale, but you have to look at earth
as a quantum mechanical system, the computation is happening super fast. This is a giant computer
doing a giant simulation. So just because for us humans, it's slow, there's like trillions of
organisms involved in you, destiny being you. Sure. But the next iteration of like,
from human to human, even if on the quantum level, there's a lot of stuff going on, you talk about
like, like changes in DNA, for instance, right? Like, that's happening from a generation to
generation time scale, like in a virtual environment that could theoretically happen.
Well, it already is, there's like protein folding, like huge cloud computing,
probably ML stuff that's like working on doing all that stuff, and it'll run like
trillions and trillions of simulations, you know, every second and stuff, maybe not every second,
but still slower than the actual protein folding, much slower. That's for the problem
of solving protein folding to estimate the 3D structure, but the actual body does the actual
protein folding way faster. So like we're, the question is, can we shortcut the simulation of
human evolution, try to figure out how to build up an organism without
simulating all the details? Because we have to simulate all the details of biology were
screwed. We don't have- Oh, sure. We'd have to put something in a pond and then watch it for-
That might be the most efficient way to do it. Sure.
That's what the universe most likely is. It's a kind of simulation created by a teenager in
their basement to try to see what happens. It's a computer game. That might be the most
efficient way to create interesting organisms, but within the system is perhaps possible to create
other robots that will be of use and will entertain us in the way that other humans
entertain us. And that's a really interesting, of course, problem, but it's surprising how
difficult it has been to create systems that operate in the physical world and operate in
that physical world in a way that's safe to humans and interesting to humans. Because there's also
the human factor, the human robot interaction. To me, that's like the most interesting problem,
to figure out how to do that well. Elon Musk and others, Boston Dynamics have worked on
legged robots, so I really care about legged robots. Those are super interesting, how to
make them such that they're able to operate successfully in a dynamic environment. It's
super tricky. They're like the dumbest of dogs, speaking of which is a dog barking outside.
It's really tricky to create those kinds of organisms that live in the human world.
Then again, if more and more of us move into the digital world, to you stream a lot,
like part of who you are exists in the digital space. The fact that you have a physical
representation also, maybe more and more will become not important.
I hope that's the case, because I bought a lot of stock in Meta, and man, it's down
a lot. Meta the company. Is there some degree? Can you look at yourself,
like Steven, the physical meat vehicle, and then the destiny of this digital space,
like digital avatar? Do you sense that in a certain way, you're the digital avatar?
I've always tried to keep my on-stream personality as genuine as possible. They're
one and the same to me. I don't really view them as two separate entities, but I mean,
I always view myself as Steven, the real-life person. Destiny's my online name, but...
No, but because so many, your social network has established the digital space. So many people
know you through the digital space. Can we swap out another person that looks like you
in the AI system, and then that entity known as Destiny will continue existing?
There must be some level of sophistication that could emulate a human brain, I would imagine.
Probably tech's not there yet, but... Well, the question is, what's the level of sophistication
of the audience that would recognize that something has changed? Like, it's the Turing test.
How hard is it to trick your audience, your large audience of fans that watch your streams,
that when you swap out an AI that emulates you, that nothing has changed? And the question is,
do you have to really simulate so much of the human brain for that? I don't think so.
Probably not. So, I mean, like you said, a lot of political discourses are just walking down the
tree together, so you can probably emulate a lot of that discussion. Yeah, it would depend on if
you're doing old data sets, and you're training on that, and I'm having conversations about abortion
and your crane and vaccines. I imagine it could do it for quite a while. The only thing that would
be weird is when novel issues pop up, then you probably need a more sophisticated resemblance
of the inner brain, right? You have to keep training on the internet, so how the language
models, and that's the most incredible breakthroughs, is the language models. You just have to keep
retraining the system on Reddit, which is actually what a lot of it is trained on, which is hilarious.
I do think it's really interesting that kind of funny problems, like the trolley problem,
that we can kind of work through our normative ethical systems are now real questions. Like,
if you're driving a Tesla and it's an autopilot and you're going to hit somebody, but a conservative
hit somebody else, what ought the system do? We went very quickly from fun kind of project in
philosophy class to we need to solve this for insurance purposes as quickly as possible. It's
kind of interesting to think about. Actually, I'll bring up the trolley problem with you later.
There's a fascinating version of it that I find hilarious. Okay, let's return to your low point.
You started playing video games. That was a lucky break. You did text-based ones. That was a lucky
break because you got to be pretty good at learning. Then you started thinking about going to college
and so on. What happened next? I went to like a prep school. You kind of have to go to college
after. That's like the point, right? I was also millennial. All of us had to go to college. That's
always what they told us. My life was kind of, it's hard to describe. I didn't really think
much of the future. I was just kind of enjoying the day-to-day because everything in my life was
pretty weird. Both my parents had moved to Florida by the time I was 16, 17. I was living with my
grandma. I was working. I had a girlfriend. Moved out. We got a place. Did college.
By the time I got into college, I had transitioned from working at McDonald's to,
I was like working in a casino restaurant basically. I was really good at that job,
so a high level of patience for drunk people and sane people. I was doing music in school
because I've really grown to love music. My thought process was I can do music as a hobby,
I guess, unless I get really good and maybe I can make money with that. Otherwise,
I love music. I'm okay going to school for music, getting good at it, and then just doing that on
the side. My main job would kind of be this career I was building at the casino. Basically,
the trying to balance personal life plus graveyard shift, six-day hour weeks at a casino,
and then a full-time music degree was not possible for me. Eventually, I had to drop school after,
I think it was like three years. After I dropped school to maintain my casino job,
after a few months, I got fired from my casino job. I'd essentially just thrown away the past
three or four years of my life. Why did you get fired from the casino job? I heard there's a story
behind that. Yeah, there's a story. Basically, I was just really dumb when it came to understanding
corporate politics. This is funny because the same attitude kind of followed me into the streaming
world. My thought process has kind of always been that as long as I'm really good at what I do,
I should be untouchable. If I'm really good, you can't do anything to me. I don't have to play
any dumb games or whatever. At the casino, I think I was the youngest, it was originally
the supervisor position at the casino. When I started to get my own shifts, there were problems
that I would run into on graveyard shift because of carryover from the swing shift. One of these
problems was underneath the soda machine, they weren't cleaning it properly and fruit flies were
showing up. The manager came in one morning and she was like, hey, what's going on with the machine?
I told her, listen, I can't take everything from swing shift and do everything at grave shift.
I can't do this. They need to figure out their stuff better or I need more employees. It's not
possible for me. She's like, what did you tell anybody? I was like, yeah, I complained to the
supervisor on the swing shift all the time. She told me, if you're not getting the answer that
you like, then it's your responsibility to email the next person up. I was like, oh, okay, that's
interesting. Some months went on and I ran into more problems because on graveyard, here's how,
I don't know if it's everywhere, but morning shift is the easiest and that's when you're the
most overstaffed because that's when all the VPs are in and that's when all the managers are there
and everybody blah, blah, blah. Swing shift is the most challenging. It's where your highest
flow of customers is. You're also decently staffed there, but there's a lot of stuff going on.
In graveyard, nobody cares at all about you. They don't give you any employees. You might get swamped.
You might not. Who cares? Make sure it's clean for day shift. That's the only thing that matters.
A quick question for sort of clarification. So this is a 24 hour?
24 hour dyno. Yeah, inside a casino. Yeah. So it's a dyno in a casino. Oh, by the way,
I had an amazing moment at a dyno in a casino recently. It's a special place. A dyno in a casino
is a place of magic. There's a lot of, I don't know if I'd say magic, but there's a lot of other
worldly stuff going on. There's characters. There's, and I had an interaction with the waitress that
was the sweetest waitress in the world. And it was just like, I don't know, made me feel less alone
in this cruel world of ours. So graveyard begins when? For me, my shift was 10 p.m. to 6 a.m.
or sometimes I got called in early, so it'd be 8 p.m. to 6 a.m. That's no love for that shift.
No, especially not trying to do school at the same time. Absolutely not.
But yeah, basically, long story short, I ran into a problem where I didn't have enough employees on
my shift. VPs were coming in in the morning. There's something like, hey, the diner's kind of dirty.
And I'm like, you've cut all my employees past 4 a.m. Like on some nights, I'm literally cooking
and doing front of house, like all on my own. Like I can't do this. And my manager, Pam, told me,
well, you've got to figure it out. And so I remembered her advice. So I emailed the VP of
food and beverage and I CC'd her and I said, I'm not getting the help I need in my restaurant.
Now, I didn't know at the time that I was basically completely throwing her under the bus
because of that email. But retroactively, when I look back on things or retrospectively, I see
that was the moment that I got marked for deletion. And I didn't really understand it,
even though I'd heard terminology for papering somebody out the door. But after that point,
I started to get written up for a lot of little random things. I'd missed one day of work in my
three years at the casino. And I started to get written up for showing up one or two minutes
late. That's kind of weird. That's whatever. Or written up for random ways about filing paperwork.
And then eventually there came a situation with another employee where they were,
it's complicated, it has to be like call out stuff. But basically, they wanted to come or
they wanted to call out. And I told them if they called out, they were going to get fired because
they were at like 10 points, they were at nine points and 10 points is firing, blah, blah, blah.
Pam told me, you can tell her that she's going to get a point, but you can't tell if she's going
to get fired. I don't know what that meant. And then I told her that if you call out, you're going
to get, you know, you're fucked, you're going to get fired, or you're going to be at 10 points.
And then I got called in early, like three days later, and Pam was like, you inappropriately
communicated with an employee because you said the F word and a text message. And I'm like,
really? There's no shot. And she's like, well, you also tried to fire the employee. And I was
like, no, I told her she was going to get 10 points. She's like, well, you use the F word.
I'm like, this is insane. And just because I was such a high performing employee, there's no way
I'm getting fired. And then I did. And I was like, yeah, cash shot my 401k and moped for like three
months because I had thrown away school for this casino job. And then I got fired from this job
that like, yeah, nobody believed I got fired. It was just insane. So if you look back, if you
were allowed to not just look back to your own memory, but actually watch yourself like some
of your court video that whole time, do you think you would be surprised you would notice some things
like potentially of not having a self awareness, not having like social, like a civility and social
etiquette that's played in the human relations? Yeah, absolutely. So is that is that at the core
of it, essentially? Yeah, I think so. I mean, it follows me even to this day, there's a lot of,
I don't know if you're recording or not, but when we spoke early about like meta conversations,
I have to think a lot sometimes about meta conversations because the way that I want to
drive a conversation will sometimes be way different than what is like the best way to
have a conversation. Whereas I just want to like go really hard on like some itty bitty, like
some idiosyncrasy, some factor figure, whatever, but that's not like the human conversation I need
to have, you know? So you got fired slash left that job, and that took you to the job that would
be the lowest point? Yeah, because there was a huge downgrade in pay. I went from getting like,
I think at the casino, because I worked so much overtime, I was like 22.50 an hour on all my
overtime fifth, and this was back in 2008, 2009, as like a college student, like it's amazing pay.
I had benefits, like everything was good. And then the carpet cleaning was like,
I was probably getting my paycheck like every other week was maybe 1500 bucks or $1,000. And
I'm working like 13 day stretches, like I have every other Sunday off, and it's so many hours,
like I have to show up at the shop at like seven or six, and then I go home at like
eight or nine, depending on when my jobs are throughout the day. You doing businesses or
residential or what are you doing? Everything. Everything. Are you working for a company this
company? Yeah. Okay. And so like there's a schedule thing, you have to go to it and so on.
Yeah, but so like, this is why the schedule would suck is sometimes I'd show up at, I think we had
to be in the shop at, I think it was 7am. We show up at the shop at 7am. First job might be at eight
or nine, but that job might be like a one hour job. So I might show up at 7am and have a job from
830 to 930. Then my next job might not be from, until like say 11. So from 830 to 930, I'll do
one job. And then I'm going to drop from like 11 to 12 or something. Then I might have like a decent
job from like five to eight, but like my whole day is destroyed and I'm doing like three smallish
jobs. So I'm getting like 30 bucks maybe for being in the shop or you know, my job for like 10 or 11
hours and it's just like horrible. So you're somebody that seems to be extremely good at
thinking and conversation. And so I have a bit of an ego perhaps in both the negative and the
positive sense of that word. Was there some aspect of working at McDonald's
and then working at the casino and then working for the, as a carpet cleaner that was humbling?
No, never. The ego burned bright through it all. Well, or no, you can pitch back in the ego.
Yeah, no, I understand. I totally get what you mean. I had a really close friend growing up
whose name was Chris. And I think we probably met when he was, we were like four or five,
I think he lived behind me. And I grew up with him and I'd always been kind of an outsider to the
world that I was in once I got to high school for sure. Because all of those kids were incredibly
wealthy, you know, Corvettes and Mustangs when they turned 16, it was a prep school. And I was
doing the, they had like a work study program there where you could stay after school from
two 30 to five every day to kind of like work to pay for your tuition. So I've been working like
throughout all of high school. I got another job at McDonald's when I was 18, worked at the casino.
I'd always been doing that kind of work. I never really viewed it as like beneath me or anything.
It's not like I don't have like a family of doctors or lawyers or anything. And then me and my other
friend, Chris, we'd always make fun of everybody else for being kind of like, you know, like preppy
kids and everything. So there is a, there's some pride to that sort of hard work. Yeah, I guess
a little bit. Yeah. Because, you know, looking especially at my dad, like the solution to every
problem was just throw more hours of work at it basically. So that was always my, yeah, go to.
What was psychologically the low point? I think psychologically the low point was that
as I'm doing this carpet cleaning job, driving around my city, there's like this feeling of,
I guess for a lot of people it's probably college, but there's a feeling when you're in high school
that everything is like so exciting and the whole world is kind of in front of you. And
there are a trillion, trillion different branching paths of possibilities. And you know, even through
high school, you're thinking like, am I going to be a doctor or a lawyer or can I join the
MBA or can I do this or that? There's all these things in front of you. And when I especially
felt it when I was doing these carpet cleaning jobs and I think it was in the fall, I'd be
outside some of these houses and I just kind of look around and I'd recognize a lot of these
neighborhoods that I'd drive around with friends in or I'd, you know, be walking through. I ran
cross country, some of them I'd be running through these neighborhoods. And it was just kind of like
this feeling of looking around. And it was like, when I was here in the past, this was like kind
of like a transitionary phase of my life where I'm doing this and it's so fun and exciting. And
then I'm going to move on to something else and it's going to be fun and exciting and awesome.
And then like, you know, two years later, my whole life has collapsed. Like I'm in a house that I
can't afford anymore. My ex that I hate is pregnant with my kid. And I have no money. I've got no
upward mobility. I failed college. My job is horrible. Like just every single like this is like
all of those, the wave function had collapsed into one thing and that one thing was the worst
thing that could have possibly been at the time for me. Yeah. Like everything was gone and horrible.
So yeah, that was the feeling I had at the time. Do you ever contemplate suicide?
I thought about thinking about it, but I've just never been that kind of person. So
I mean, basically as a way to escape from the hardship, something that I'm so incredibly lucky.
I don't know why or how I'm just going to chalk it up to biology. I've always had really high
mental baseline. I've like depression and all of that. There have been a few short stints of
debt with it past 30 because I did a lot of drugs. But other than that, my mental baseline is just
so high. And even in the carpet cleaning days, like if you, man, the videos might still be there.
I think on my old YouTube channel channel where I'll be like playing Starcraft when I first started
to get into streaming and I'll be calling up customers like this is Steve from guaranteed
clean. We had to move your job back one hour. Is it okay if I show up instead of 230? And then
I hang up and it's like, all right, guys, we got three more games and it's like, let's go.
Like stuff like that. So my, my baseline has always been like really high for mental function.
So even in low point, there's that you had strength. Is there, is there anything you can give
by way of advice from people that for home to wave function collapses as it does for many of us?
Like, holy fuck, the world is not full of opportunity and you're kind of a failure.
Like I've, I've been there. Yeah, I don't know. It's rough because like,
I usually ask for compassion from people that have it better off because like, once you're down
there, like the only reason I say I got lucky, but it wasn't even really lucky. Like, or it was
lucky, but it was more lucky. It wasn't just lucky that I got into streaming. It was lucky that I
was into computers at an early age. It was lucky that I played video games at an early age. It
was lucky that all the tech came up at exactly that right point in time. Like I was a pretty smart
guy, but it was definitely a preparation meets opportunity and that opportunity was like at
the exact precise moment of my life. If anything had gone differently than I would just be cleaning
carpets today. So, so in the many worlds, interpretation of quantum mechanics,
this is like one out of like, there's many, many Stevens, they're just still carpet cleaning
and they're full of pain and resentment. Yeah. The one piece of advice that I give,
I hate that I have to push back against all these crypto bros and everybody online for
decently intelligent people that are successful. I've never heard anybody give a contradiction
to this. Maybe you will. You can tell me if you disagree. I always look at kids in high school
and I'm like, just try a little bit harder. Like 30 minutes a night, if you don't study,
just do 30 minutes, just do a little bit more. It is, you're laying the foundation for the rest
of your life and you can't appreciate it in high school and college. But oh my God, when you get
out, everything in your life is so much easier. You have probably more responsibility over the
direction of your life when you're like 13, 14 years old than you ever will once you're like 25
and older because this is like when you're determining the foundations that everything's
going to be built on. But yeah, 100%. So first of all, it does seem that the liberating aspect
of being young is like anything you learn. So working hard at learning something will pay off
in like nonlinear ways, like you said with video games. I feel like, so like people who are like,
I hate school. All right, well, fine. But find something where you're challenging yourself,
you're growing, you're learning, you're learning a skill, you're learning about a thing.
Of course, you know, you can push back and say, well, there's some trajectories that might not
be productive. Like if you spend the entirety of your teen years playing, I don't know,
League of Legends, a game you have love and hate relationship with.
No, just a hate and hate relationship. Okay. Well, we'll talk about, I think you have a love,
hate relationship with hate in general. We'll just in love. We'll try to de-complexify that one.
I think in general, just investing yourself fully with passion really does pay off. But that said,
also school, I feel like doesn't get enough credit, like high school in particular, middle
school and high school, because it's general education. I think if you're, especially if
you're lucky to have good teachers, but honestly, I haven't mostly the textbooks themselves with
good teachers. It's a one chance in life, you have to really explore a subject. Fuck grades.
Like getting good grades is at tension, I would say, with actual learning. That is true. But
just get a biology textbook and to explore ideas and biology and allowing yourself to be
inspired by the beauty of it. Yeah, I don't know. I think that really, really, really pays off and
you never get a chance to do that again. And maybe not even textbooks, like reading, straight
up reading. I think if you read, this is one time in life, you get a chance to read, really read.
Like read a book a day, read. You can really invest, you can really grow by reading. I mean,
I must, all those guys talk about it. It's very, very rare that you meet like a dumb person who
reads a lot. I don't know if that's ever happened in my life. Yeah. Dumb or not successful. And
the cool thing is, it seems like the reading, it's like investment, the reading you do early
on in high school pays off way more than the reading you do later. So like the really influential
reading is doing those high school years, because you're basically learning from others,
the mistakes they've made, the solutions to problems, you're basically learning the
shortcuts to life. Like whatever the hell you want to do, music, read from the best people
that the music theory, like learn music theory, learn, read biographies about jazz musicians,
blues musicians, see their, like see all the mistakes, see what they did, see the shortcuts.
If you want to do podcast and read about other podcasts, if you want to do streaming,
read about other streamers, physicists, and so on, I feel like you figure out all the mistakes
and get to shortcut through life, because most people show up to college without having done
that. And now you get a chance to shortcut your way past them. Yeah, 100%. But nobody really teaches
you that. They're like, go to school from this time to that time, shut up, this is just what you
do, eat your broccoli. I think I was like, there's two huge problems. One is, now that I'm older,
because you don't know anything as a kid, you can't really criticize as an adult as a kid,
because you're a kid. By the way, you're ageist, if I may say so. I am super ageist. As I get older,
I get even more ageist. There are a lot of people I argue with, I was like, man, dude,
you're really 22, aren't you? I can tell every word you say, just seeps of like 22-year-oldness,
but that's okay. I love that for you. I could just say, because you mentioned this,
your wife is a fellow streamer, Molina. You mentioned that this is a source of fights
for the two of you that, and I could just feel that. There is truth to what you're saying,
which is like, all right, you're saying that because you're 22. Just wait until you're 25,
and you won't be saying that anymore. Sure. No, that is the most annoying thing for people to hear.
Yeah, you can't ever say that, of course. Because it's actually usually true,
because we do go through phases in life, and you can understand that most things are phases.
So just in general, you can say, just wait. Just wait. You won't feel this way. Again,
I could say that to you. You could say that to yourself. Just wait. Whatever you're feeling
like, just wait. In five, 10 years, you'll be a different person, and you will laugh at the
things you take seriously now that are causing you pain now, all that kind of stuff. But people
hate hearing that. Absolutely. I think the joke that I always say is that if I could literally
step into a time machine, and I could come back out and see myself as a 17-year-old, and I could
say, hey, I am literally you from the future. You see the time machine, and I would look at me,
and I would see the time machine, and I would give myself the best advice in the world,
to be the most successful person. I would ignore all of it. Even knowing it came from myself,
I'd be like, this guy sold out. This dude doesn't know what the fuck he's talking about. I'll
figure it out better. He must have made some mistakes. That's what I would think is this
everything. Even I knew it was myself from the future, I would just 100% never believe it,
and knowing that is very frustrating. But I keep that in mind when I deal with younger people.
That's why I always say on stream when I'm talking to, there's been stuff with Sneak-Os,
another girl on my stream called Lab. When I see the mistakes they're making, oftentimes,
because I've made all of these mistakes, sometimes in the most public and horrible
fashion ever. But I'm never like a mentor. I'm not going to sit there and tell you,
oh, do this or that or that or that, because I don't know if you're going to listen to me,
and I don't want to condescend to you. You figure your stuff out, and I'll be here if you want to
talk about it. There was a company that didn't work with me, because I was very adamant on
defending very radical notions about language and racial slurs and everything, when I was like
22 or whatever. There was a company, and they said, well, we don't want to work with this guy
for an event. After they had said that, I had written an article on my website called,
the company was Gigabyte. They make motherboards, and I said, fuck Gigabyte in the ass. That was
the title to my article. And it was like, well, if they don't want to work with me, I'm going to
blow them up and never do anything ever with them again. And it was just like, looking back at it
now, obviously, as an older person, like, hey, you need to pump the brakes and chill. You're
destroying yourself. But as a young person, it's like, yeah, you're 22. Of course, you think that
you can say whatever and do whatever. And as long as you're good at what you're doing, you've got
the whole world behind you. And yeah, geez. Well, let's go there. You have a history of using
offensive language, like the R word, the N word, including the N word with a hard R, calling women
bitches, talking about rape in a nonchalant way. What part of that do you regret? And what part
of that do you not? Language is very complicated. When it comes to stuff relating to slurs,
there's been a whole trajectory of feelings on everything related to language. For you personally
and for the internet as a whole. Yeah, I don't care about the internet, almost for me personally.
In my early 20s, I'll say like 22, 23, I think probably when I first started streaming, my feeling
is that any word is just a word. And if it hurts you, that's your fault. Take responsibility for
yourself. This probably came from my background of being a really independent person. So that's
just kind of like the mind that I had for everything. And there were basically, they were like a
collection of experiences that I had that as I grew, I started to realize like, okay, well,
I feel differently about some of these words depending on the context. And I can see how
they can affect other people depending on the context. So as I've kind of like grown,
I think I've developed a more sophisticated understanding of how different words are used
and how they affect people, whether they like it or not. And more importantly, whether I like it
or not. And that words can, even if I don't want it to be, they can be a vehicle for emboldening
certain types of ideas that I don't want to embolden. And yeah, that's kind of been the whole
like growth. I've been lucky that in the time that I came up on the internet, I was able to learn
these lessons. Because if I was trying to learn those same lessons today, I would have been completely
destroyed because I had insane views on language like 10 years ago. We could talk about the past,
we could talk about the present, let's talk about the past first. So how do you deal with the fact
that there's videos of you in the past saying the N-word, including the N-word with a hard R?
So generally, and what's the context? Can you give me like, what would be the context usually?
When I lay out this defense, it's not because I wouldn't have used the N-word. Generally,
whenever I said the N-word, it was usually in an example of like, this is something that like a
racist person would say, I don't think I've ever, on the internet, I think I've ever called anybody
like the N-word with a hard R. Not because I wouldn't have, but just because it wasn't in
my vocabulary. I played RTS, Real Time Strategy, and we use the F-slur for gay people. That's
what I use that one a ton. I've called people that a ton in the past. So I should actually just
as a small tangent, and this is what I'd like to explore with you. There's a ruthlessness to the
language in the gaming world. And there's different communities. They have different
flavors of language, of hate speech, essentially. And there's also a humor to it,
which really bothers me in a dark way that I haven't been able to really think through,
because humor seems to be a kind of catalyst for hate. It seems to normalize hate. Like you say,
basically, it's like Lucy Kay says a lot of edgy things, but you take something Lucy Kay says
and do it in a non-fine way and do it over and over and over and keep increasing the hatefulness
of it, the vitriol, and somehow you find yourself like Alice in Wonderland in a world full of hate
where there is no good and evil. It's all the same. In fact, the good is to be mocked, and the evil
is to be celebrated for the humor of it, basically not taking the ideas of evil seriously. And I
don't know what it, it reveals something about human nature that you can let go, the moral
relativism that can happen when you do that kind of stuff. At the same time, I'm a fan of dark humor
when done well. Anyway, for people who are not familiar, I just wanted to mention that
some of the worst hate speech that ends in LOL happens in gaming communities.
And that's where you come from in a certain part.
So a lot of people don't remember this or don't know this because they're younger, but
way back in the day, in the late 90s, early mid 2000s of the internet, the way that online kind
of like shit talk worked was you were just trying to ramp up to the most insanely edgy, crazy stuff
you could say to like provoke a reaction. Have you ever heard of something called the aristocrats?
That it's like a joke, the joke? Oh yeah, the joke. Yeah, there's a movie on it. Yeah.
Okay. Basically, every single like shit talk back and forth on the internet was like that.
Like what is the most increasingly depraved and back then you didn't get banned for slurs or
anything on any of these chat rooms. So it was just like insane world to walk into. And I was
fully 100% a part of a product of and a contributor to that world. So that probably still goes on
on the internet in some way and that probably still goes on the internet in a maybe more
pacified way. Only in darker parts of the internet. I'd say for the most part, most,
well, compared to back then compared to 20 years ago, the internet is way cleaned up now.
There are still going to be boards you can go on or parts of the internet where you see that
type of humor, but not nowhere near as mainstream. Like back then you could open your mic on
Xbox Live and hear some insane stuff when that first started nowhere near what you hear today.
Although there are still elements of escalation that happened that just seems to be part of
human nature on the internet. Because we don't get the feedback of actually hurting people
directly. So the trolling, like for the lulls, you'll do like you will still escalate within
the bounds. You're just saying that there's more bounds now. On Reddit, there's more bounds and
so on. There's moderators that kind of yell at you that ban you and so on if you cross those
bounds. But overall, that basic human instinct to escalate, especially under the veil of anonymity
is still there. I don't know. It's dark. It's dark. Yeah, just there's a lot of different ways to
look at it. And there's different ways you can break that art. Like for instance, like you mentioned
dark humor and you say that like sometimes dark humor is funny and sometimes it's not. I think
that it's really important to dig into and figure out like why certain things are funny and why
certain things. Yeah, go. It's from your subreddit. Oh boy. No, that made me laugh and I felt wrong
about it. Oh no. So this is, I already know what this is, yeah. Yeah. So this is a trolley
problem. To me, it connects because I think about the, it keeps, because I worked on autonomous
vehicles, the trolley problem, the philosophical thought experiment keeps brought up a lot.
You know, when AI is part of making the decision, do I kill three people here or five people here?
In AI makes that decision, how do you do that calculus? And this particular, there's a deep
satire that reveals some kind of flaw in society. I feel like that's why- That's what dark humor
does? Successful dark humor does. And I don't know if this- It feels a flaw. Hmm. I feel like
certain, there's a certain brand of dark humor. And I think the reason, I think the reason someone
is why it's good, or why it is good humor, I think is because I don't think it necessarily
reveals a flaw. So sometimes I feel like it reveals like a kind of virtue, I think. Like,
if you look at this particular thing- Yeah, can I explain what we're- Yeah, go for it.
Oh yeah, sure. We're just listening. The title of the Reddit post is, You Know What to Pick.
And it says, five people are going to die either way, but if you flip the lever, the trolley will
do a sick fucking loop first. And also the top comment is a question saying, which I think is
also part of the dark humor that's successful. Can I get the gender and ethnic backgrounds
of the groups first? And the top answer is both groups are each comprised of five white orphaned
cis male heavy meth users who are consistently in and out of drug rehab, all who identify as
right wing extremists. Humor is such a sophisticated thing that we engage in. Humor is like really
complicated. But I would argue that hopefully the humor here shows the virtue of like, this is
obviously horrible, but that's kind of why it's funny. It's funny because it's such a horrible
question to ask. Like, do we kill five people in a boring way or in a really entertaining way? And
it's like, that's really, that's really- And then when you ask even more like, what are the ethnic
backgrounds? Like, that's even worse to say that, you know? So I feel like that's like the type of,
there's a way that you can engage with dark humor where it's like, oof, like, it's funny because
it's so wrong and so taboo. And we all know that it's wrong and taboo. And that's kind of where
the shared laugh comes from. So for me, the question that asking the diversity question
is a sophisticated way of revealing the absurdity of asking about diversity when it's talking about
human life. Oh, interesting. Because the way that I took that was, I think it reveals the absurdity
of how people will weigh different ethnic backgrounds so differently when it comes to value of human
life. Like, I'm actually thinking of that in terms of like a an immigration related question,
where people are really keen and quick to dehumanize like black or brown people. So like,
the question is like, well, if five of them are brown and five are white, well, I know which one
I'm going to, you know, pull the lever for. That's how I read that. But it's satirizing that.
Yeah, exactly. Yes, of course. Yeah. But that's what I mean, that that's the flaw. To me, at least,
it showed that humanity or social networks that are easy to be outraged and love the outrage
and the chaos, that Twitter and social networks will pull that lever. Like, they would,
they would always try to maximize the fun. And there's like a, there's a sick aspect to
all the atrocities, all the tragedies that happen in the world, that we kind of always
lean towards the, the outrageous narrative weaved around it. The, yeah, the, the one that leads
to sort of the most clicks, to the most attention, to the most outrage, to all that,
all that kind of stuff. So that, that's almost like a satire of society. When they are faced with
tragedy, they will maximize, trying to think of a word that's not fun, but entertainment,
maximize the entertainment. Yeah. This is a big criticism I give, especially to conservative
crowds. You know, left-leaning people, everybody doesn't. I don't like when people blame the media
for the state of the media today. I very much believe that everything in society is a feedback
loop and that if you're really unhappy with the state of the media, I think that the media is
a good reflection for what people want to see because there is a room right now in the United
States where somebody could start a company where all they do is completely factual reporting.
They don't have a political slant and they're not giving you these like sensationalist narratives
or stories and that media company would fail in two weeks because people don't want to see that.
Generally, people really want to see the like, show me the guy that really believes in what I
say, that calls the other guy an idiot, the guy that are screaming on TV or on the radio,
like, this is what I really want. And people will engage in that and that feedback loop will
continue for generations. And then all of a sudden people are like, why is the media so bias? Why is
the media driving so many narratives? I was like, well, what do you mean? This is exactly what you
want to see. And that's frustrating for me. That's one of my big kind of when I defend
establishments or when I talk about like the interplay between citizen and all these institutions
we have, that the institutions are very much a reflection of the population, at least in
democratic societies. And I think that people very much try to elude the personal responsibility
or the country's responsibility to why some of them look the way that they do.
But that takes us back to the N word with a hard R. Sure. Why?
For the particular examples that I was giving for the particular conversations that I was having,
if you're going to have challenging conversations around certain words,
I think you should probably be able to say them otherwise it feels really ridiculous to me.
That's like, do you still believe that?
Yes. Not like calling people those words, but in having conversations about those words,
I would say that I still believe that, yeah.
But don't you think, as you said, that using those words
actually gives motivation and strength to people who have hate in their hearts?
I think depending on the context of what's going on, I think that that's going to be a big driver
in terms of how people are going to perceive or take it.
So in a conversation about the N word, I don't think I would normally say the N word,
we would just talk about the word much the same way that like in a movie,
like in Django, people use the N word. Should that be censored in that movie?
Or in the context of that movie, is it being employed in a way where these aren't good people?
You're not supposed to like them. And that's what the audience walks away with.
Yeah, but that context is different than conversation. It feels like in conversation,
you using that word normalizes it. And that normalizing that word is going to make it easier
for people who use that word in a hateful way to use it. Same with the F word, the F slur.
If you use that casually and normalize it in a way that's not hateful, you use it in a way
that's not hateful, but the side effect is that it normalizes it than people who do use it in a
hateful way will be more likely to use it. Therefore, the mathematically looking at the
equation of the number of times the N word or the F word is used throughout the world,
it increases the number of times it's used in a hateful way.
Yeah, I think that human beings-
And you're part of that problem, Steven.
I don't agree. I understand the thought process. But I don't know if using certain words
within different contexts is going to necessarily normalize like the hateful use of that word.
That is an argument that I've heard people use. Somebody will say like, okay, well, hold on.
That should never be used ever because by virtue of you normalizing it, even in an
inoffensive environment, you increase the proclivity for people to use it in a potentially
more offensive environment. And my argument is always like, no, I don't think that crossover
exists. But if you did want to take that argument, and maybe you do feel this way,
I think that you get really problematic when you run into communities that do use certain
words that people would say, well, they should be allowed to do it. So for instance, if you think
that any utterance of the N word at all is highly problematic and might increase hatred,
then like the entire rap industry has to dramatically change the way that they engage
with the N word. And obviously a lot of people that criticize people's use of the N word
aren't going to turn to rappers and say, well, you guys can't say it either.
No, it's who, I mean, it's who uses the N word. That's what it's not. So it's not just the word.
It's the, it is context dependent. But I would say that you as a white person having conversations,
the context there is the kind that would lead to any increase in hate.
Do you think the N word should be censored in the dictionary?
No. And I believe there's a Wikipedia page on it and it's not censored.
Yeah, I don't, I think it should be in the dictionary. I think the context of casual
conversation, like I said, I just believe that on the internet, having humor,
having fun conversations as you have on your streams,
that leads to the normalization of the word without any educational value,
without significant educational value. Yeah, I would agree with that. I think I would,
I think I would agree with that. No, sorry. So there's a difference between
F slur and N word and both I think should not be used in a fun way, but the F word was used
in a fun way for the longest time. For sure. And I'll tell you something that bothers me about
your streams, not your streams and basically every other stream is the casual use of the R word.
Oh, the ableism, yeah. I don't know if it's about the able, I don't even know,
listen, it's complicated. I'm not like virtue signaling here.
No, ableism isn't a virtue signal. I mean, it's a legitimate, yeah. Like I get emails
from fans that say like, Hey, like I deal with this particular issue. Every time you use this
word, it kind of feels like you're attacking me. Like just like, so it's not, it's a valid concept.
It's just something cuts wrong for me. Like for example, I'm not bothered by,
I am bothered by the excessive use of the word fuck, but not in the same way that moderate use of
the word fuck. What is it? I'm curious. And when somebody calls somebody in R word,
what is it that, what is the feeling that you get that makes you feel bad about it?
It signals to me that you don't give a damn about
people who are struggling in ways that you are not struggling. Like that, that signals to me
like, about the experience of others. Do you think that there are other words also that could
convey like a similar feeling to your wife? Cause it feels like you've drawn a pretty special
circle around cause like, I imagine I call, oh, this guy's, you're an uneducated dumb fucker.
You're a nitwicker. Like, do those words probably don't feel it? That circle keeps changing.
Which it can, which is fine. I think that's the whole point with the culture.
So I'm trying to feel my feeling is a kind of, you know, I'm a human being that exists in a
social context that we're all evolving that language together and just feels wrong. Like,
you know, the word bitch, for example, it really bought, like I've heard on your streams and in
general, calling a woman a stupid bitch really bothers me. But it's not just the word bitch,
it's context. Like for example, me personally, I'm speaking to me personally, like badass bitch,
is different than stupid bitch. Sure. Like a bad bitch or something is different. Yeah,
of course. Way different. Sure. I think it speaks to a bigger sense of civility and respect for
human beings that are not like you. That's what, that's, that's the feeling that I'm bothering.
So I guess what I'm trying to say here is just because people speak in this kind of way
in the gaming world and streams doesn't mean that you, like a lot of people look up to you.
It doesn't mean young people especially, doesn't mean that you don't have the responsibility to
sort of stand alone from the crowd. Because you're somebody that values the power of affected discourse.
And to be effective discourse, there's some level of civility. So you can be the sort of
the beacon of civility in that world versus giving in to the derogatory words. Because like
you have to, you have to lift people out of that world, out of the muck of what I would say is
like drama and effective discourse. Like I think that's one of your missions, right, is like to
inspire the world through conversation, through debate, through effective discourse. Yeah.
So I guess I'm just calling you out that I think using our word, for me personally,
as a fan that believes in your mission, it just makes you look ineffective and bad and
uninspiring to young people that look up to you. Because those young people are going to use those
words that you're using and they'll do it much less effectively. That's the problem.
Yeah, I guess the challenge is always just like finding the line. Like my, my book I really shifted
dramatically from, even from like two or three years ago, I think my vocabulary shifted quite a
bit as we've like, we've kind of gotten rid of some words and some things are kind of coming
out. The R word is one that has kind of gone out and come back and gone out and come back,
that one we've definitely gone back and forth on. I know there are different thoughts about it in
different communities on the internet. This is interesting. I mean, I'm just telling you,
for me, it cuts, and I'm not a social justice warrior type, it cuts pretty hard.
So what you're saying is I'm going to lose a subscriber if I'm,
no, it's not a subscriber. I know, I just, I actually have to empathize harder because I'm
like, maybe this is not a very good person. That's what I feel. Like if you're so carelessly using
that word, then maybe you're not actually thinking deeply about the suffering in the world. Like
to be a student of human nature, you really have to think about other humans and other
experiences that are unlike your own. And so that's the sense I get. But at the same time,
you're also like the grandpa, the ages, who's trying to be cool with the young kids. A lot of
the reason young kids look up to you is like, you also know the language of the internet.
Yeah. But I mean, it doesn't, that's not an excuse to use words that we think shouldn't be used.
I guess the question that I would have, because it's always a struggle, and to some extent,
it's kind of happened, is let's say that like three years ago, I would have said I'm no longer
saying the artwork. That's just, I'm just going to get rid of that on my vocabulary. Like,
is there a chance that today we would be having a conversation about like,
why do you call people dumb fucks? Like, is that really appropriate? Like,
does this attack at the core of like somebody's like level of intelligence, education,
opportunities in life? Like, is that a worthy, you don't think so?
I think that's a, as the kids say, cope. You really think so? I think because the words have
definitely moved in a way where it's like, this was okay. Now it's not this. So you're
standing your ground by using, listen, you could, you could, you could, but I think it's better
to use those words. If you want to defend the ground word stand on, to use them rarely and
deliberately versus how you currently use them, which is to express an emotion. Like you,
I'm going to be honest, you use our word, not when you're at your best.
True. And so that's not, that's generally, that could be true for a lot of swearing to that,
but yeah, I know what you mean. No, but like, you know that our word is offensive, you know,
and there's part of it is like the, you tell yourself that like, you're still kind of fighting
political correctness by using it a little bit when you say it. No, I don't think so. I think,
I'm trying to think in terms of like, where is the virtue where, like, there's a whole bunch
of arguments for why some words are okay, some words aren't okay or whatever. And I try to,
like think more along those lines rather than, but like, there's going to be like a lot of
phrases where like, if the our word has come out, the conversation is over. I know that,
like things, my brain is shut down, the person I'm talking to is, but there's like,
there's a lot of words also in terms of like, it like, if you ever hear me say like,
fucking moron in a debate, it's like, it's done, like this conversation is over,
there's no way that anything productive is happening past that point.
I think fucking moron is not, I think it's ineffective, it's not civil, but it's not,
it doesn't bother me in the way. It's basically when you speak in a way that I know there's
a group that's going to be heard by that. Not only do I think about the hurt that group experiences,
I think of you as a lesser intellectual, like as a lesser person who's thinking about the world.
What bothers me the most is just what kind of mindset that inspires in young people,
especially when you're a public figure and a lot of people look up to you.
So I definitely don't think, sort of this idea, the R word is not the battleground of expanding
the Orton window of discourse. Okay. Like I don't think it'll lead to dumb fuck
being canceled two years later, unless that word is hurting people's experience,
which I don't foresee that happening. I think legitimately our word and F slur and calling
women bitches, context matters here too. Of course, but just the way I've heard you use it,
it is not, it's from emotion and it's from frustration and it ultimately is rooted in
disrespect. I don't, I think it's ineffective. And of course, like who gets to say, I don't know,
but I'm saying somebody who would like, I admire effective conversations and I admire great humor,
dark humor, wit. To me, oftentimes the use of the R word in the way you've used in the way I see
the community use it is none of those things. It contributes not at all to the humor and so on.
Now I could see it might contribute to the, to the camaraderie of that particular group,
especially when they normalize the use of that word. You kind of take some of the edge off,
but you forget that there's a large number of other people that don't have the chemistry,
that don't hear the music of the friendship that you have, the relationship you have.
And instead they hear the normalization of a hateful word and it ultimately has an impact
that's hateful. And then people like me who show up, you know, I haven't watched much of your stuff.
It turns me off from like a couple of times your content came before me.
And I listened to it a little bit, it turned me off completely. I didn't understand
how good your heart is. I didn't understand how your mission of actually
deradicalize people, help people like you're, and increase the level of good faith discourse
in the world. I didn't understand any of that because like what I was hearing is pretty rough,
like the R-word type of stuff. And I just feel like the benefit cost analysis is heavy on the cost.
Gotcha. So I just have to sort of call this out. I think, and I straight up think it's wrong,
but that's my own. Why do you think it's wrong? Because it's hurting people without any benefit
to you whatsoever. When you say hurting people, do you mean the person I'm using it at? Or do
you think there's like the third group? It's good feedback, right? I always consider everything,
especially, I respect you a lot, you're a really smart guy. Something that I always kind of like
fight over in terms of like language or like who to attack or what to attack or what to do
is that it's very hard to draw like what boxes are okay to insult people on versus what aren't.
So for instance, if I call somebody like a Nazi with a lot of vitriol, I'm okay with every single
Nazi being negatively affected by that because that category intrinsically calls upon it some
level of more condemnation for me, right? Whereas like if I'm out there, I try not to do like image
related jokes, right? I don't want to call you like, oh, you're a fat fucking loser because there's a
lot of people that are fat that are overweight where I don't want them to feel bad. I don't want
them, I'm not trying to call you out or like insult you. So there's like a lot of, you say cost
benefit, I look at like a lot of collateral damage from a word like that where there's no purpose
in doing that. So certain words are easy to get rid of, they're off the table, right? Epsilon
and word like these are not words you call people because you're there's so much collateral,
it's not worth it. We've got some words where it's like if you have some form of like mental
thing, it is a bad thing, you're not a bad person, but just using that word could feel like a
collateral damage to those people. And then there's other categories of words. So like if I say that
like this person is like there is a stupid fucking Republican, right? There's probably some Republicans
that aren't dumb that I don't want to feel called out by that. Like are those types of phrases that
you think should be completely removed as well? Or I'm kind of curious. So this completely removed
just so we're clear. Yeah. I'm not referring to censorship. Oh no, I'm not even talking about
this. I'm just a person like emotionally like removed is the wrong word though. Like I care about
like I'm not trying to listen to people on the internet saying like you shouldn't say that word,
that's not good. I mean, I'm trying to look to your mind and heart. And the reason we're talking
today is you're betraying your gift. You're better than this. You think it's indicative of like a more
flip of thought process where it's like the only way you can say that word is if you're ignoring
the hurt and suffering of those people. And if you're somebody that says those people, you're
ignoring the state of language. Because I think you're getting to the point because it's not about
a single word. It's about like it's music. And I just feel like there is a very strong note.
It's a strong note that ruins the melody. Gotcha. And I don't think I can say, you know,
you shouldn't use the R word or whatever. I'm just speaking to it. I'm just listening to music
and reviewing the final result. It's not necessarily because maybe one use of the word, the R word
strategically or part of an actual like, or when you've built up a camaraderie that's
sandwiched in like some love, but then you try to reveal there. Because you're talking about
a lot of, there's a bunch of drama. You have friends with whom you're worrying and stuff.
And they're all a little bit beautifully insane. And you've said that you are becoming more and
more insane. It's beautiful to watch. It's the human condition laid before us. Wonderful. And
some of that is swearing and so on. So it's a tricky thing. But the whole skill of discourse,
just like it is with dark humor is walking that line. I just feel like it's overuse of the R
word. And I don't want to die in that grog because I don't think it's that that represent. Like,
there's certain things like that. It feels like it ruins the music. Gotcha. And I don't, you know,
it's just saying like a dumb Republican or dumb Democrat. I don't, yeah, that ruins it too a little
bit. Depends on how you use it. You can be lazy with that. You know, like even overuse of the
word, I think bots is what's used for people who don't think or something. I don't actually know
the definition. I'm offended on behalf of robots. That might be a compliment soon.
Exactly. But I guess bot means you don't think. Yeah, you're like an NPC. You just copy.
Again, I'm a friend on behalf of NPCs. I come myself as one. But there's a sense if you say
bots too much, that you're just dismissing people. Like everything I say is right.
And anyone that disagrees with me needs a bot. That's lazy too. Sometimes it's funny. Sometimes
it's effective. Basically saying a lot of people in the mainstream media or something like that are
bots. Okay, that's a little bit of that is effective. But too much, it becomes ineffective.
And I'm trying to speak to that. And I'm just the reason we're highlighting
clear examples like the N word. Joe Rogan had to contend with that. I think it's
ineffective. It makes you less effective at discourse. But like you've talked about many
times, language is a tricky one. It's always hard because you talk about constructing a melody.
There's not one melody that sounds good to everyone. But there are probably certain notes
that like if you got rid of them, everybody's still going to like it about as much and you
don't really lose anything. There's a whole other part of an audience that might be more
willing to listen. Yeah, of course. And it's not about losing the magic of that melody. Like you
don't want to be vanilla. I just feel like there's stuff that doesn't need to be there.
Yeah, for sure. It's fat. But then again, the other thing that people should understand
that might be listening to this, you're streaming many hours a day for many years. I don't know
11 or 12, I think. Yeah, started in 2010. And so one of the things that people can do is just
clip out anything. You're going through the full human experience of emotion, anger,
fear, frustration, all of it. So of course there's going to be moments when you're not the best
version of yourself. Anything else to say about the language? It's complicated. I'm still always
trying to figure it out. There are opinions that I have that have changed throughout the years.
It's possible that the R word has always been the next one on the chopping block that we're all
kind of looking at, but people are always worried about that treadmill. But it's possible in a year
or two, I'll have a different view on it or all have changed away some of the words I use.
It's always like a work in progress. There's always different communities that feel different
ways about different words. Yeah, but do you acknowledge that there's people out there
that are never going to talk to you? They're never going to think of you as a good man because
you used the N word with the hard R publicly. In the past, I mean, yeah, those people exist.
There are some people that are beyond my reach, which I'm okay with. There's going to be some
people because of things that have been involved or even ideas that I have now that might make them
beyond my reach. Something you said earlier is very true. I think the goal is to identify what
are the elements that you can cut out that aren't integral to your message, but could be alienating
to more people. And those are probably the things that you identify. But I think that you can get
lost in yourself or lost in the internet or lost in the outside of yourself if you're trying to
appeal to every single person. It's just never going to be the case. I like that I've had the
journey that I've had on the internet that you can find me saying and defending a lot of insane
stuff 10 years ago, because I think it shows a level of progress. And I think I do get a lot
of respect and buy into certain communities where it's like, I'm not just some random dude telling
you that, oh, you shouldn't say the F word or the N word. I'm a guy that's been there,
that's done it, that's defended it. And you can see my whole past, my whole history is laid bare
for you to watch every thousands of hours of it. But I can show that there's growth and evolution
and change that can happen in a person. And you're honest about that growth. It's a tricky thing
because people just bring up stuff from your past. I hope we figure out as a civilization,
a mechanism to clearly say, this was me two years ago. This is me five years ago. I'm a
different person. Because Twitter doesn't care about that. These social mechanisms that bring
stuff out doesn't care about that. It's like one stupid thing you say, it becomes like a scarlet
letter. And I don't know how to fight that. It's tricky to fight that. Have you ever seen men in
black? Yes. When K and J are on the bench and he says a person is smart, but people are stupid,
dumb, finicky animals or whatever. There's something that changes for human dynamics when
there is a group of people that make it so hard to control. I think one-on-one, anybody can
sit across on somebody and admit to some horrible stuff. I abused my husband when I was 20 and
35 and I see what's wrong or I did this. I was addicted to whatever and I made these mistakes.
One-on-one, it's always easy. But in group environments that in group, out group, tribalistic
thing of identifying one thing and then coming to destroy a person's life is such a huge impulse
we have. And I think probably when we were hunter-gatherers in the forest, it's probably good
because you really want to push weird people out or anything like that. But now on the internet,
when we can hunt for any dissenting opinion and just with ruthless precision, destroy somebody's
life over it, it's pretty scary dynamic. I think one of the mechanisms that could fix it is make
it super easy for each individual person to analyze all the stupid shit they themselves have said
in the past. Like a full recording because I think people are just honestly paying a very
rosy picture to their own brain of who they have been in the past. If we can have empathy for the
fact that we've said stupid shit or we're drunk, the ridiculous things you say, the offensive
things you might have said, the offensive things you might have done, I just feel like that would
give us the ammunition to have empathy for others that are like, okay, yeah, this guy five years
ago said this, maybe that doesn't represent them, who doesn't represent who they are anymore than
stuff I said five years ago represents who I am today. I feel like technology can actually enable
that. Maybe, although you're talking about more recording and more stuff, which people already
worry about. It's a double edged sword. I think there is going to be more and more recording,
we have to figure out how to do that in a way that respects people's privacy and gives them
ownership of their data and so on. I've looked at the search history I've done on Google,
which for most people is available, like your Google search history, and it's fascinating to
watch the evolution of a human being. It doesn't seem like the same person, like a different person.
For sure. It's weird. It's also hard to with the internet today. I'm going to be agist again,
but like now all of the people are thrown together, whereas like, I don't want a 27-year-old
judging the age of like a 15 or 16-year-old. Obviously, he's in high school. There was that
story that came out of the... There was a kid that saved the recording of... I think it was like
some white girl. I think that she got her driver's license and she's like, I can drive now and words
with the A or whatever. It was dumb. She shouldn't have said it, but I think she was like 15 or 16
when she ticked off this or whatever. He held on to that recording until she applied and got
accepted to college three years later, and then he released it to get her kicked out of college.
And I'm like, damn. Everything that I had ever said as like a 15, 16-year-old was like immortalized
on the internet. My life wouldn't have even begun. And those are insanely high standards to hold
people to. Not that like, obviously you shouldn't be saying those... You shouldn't be saying certain
words or whatever, but you have to be able to make mistakes in adolescence like everybody does.
We all did. Everybody did it growing up, you know?
Why do you think there's so much misogyny in the streaming community? And how can you fight it?
Because you've shown a lot of interest in fighting it. Trying to decrease or eliminate misogyny from
your community. I think it's really difficult. I think that eliminating racism is easier than
eliminating misogyny. On the internet, you mean? On anywhere. Because I think fundamentally,
I don't think there's that much difference between like white people and black people and brown
people and Asian people or whatever. We have different cultures and stuff, but at the end of
the day, we're all people. But I think there are differences between men and women throughout all
of history and time and then even today in every culture. And when real differences do exist,
it's harder to account for them in a way that can we have conversations with each other without it
becoming very gendered in a negative way, right? Negative way of gendering something,
be like a misogynistic way of doing it. Of course, it's unclear to me that it's so difficult to
to avoid the negative gendering versus the positive. Because there's a lot of positive to the
tension, the dance between the different genders and so on. Maybe in this particular moment in
history, it's not. But it's not trivial to me that racism is easier to eliminate. It's an interesting
hypothesis just because there's more biological difference between men and women. That means
it's harder to eliminate. But I don't know if this is true. I hear this a lot. I feel like I read
this somewhere, but I need to get a better source of it. I repeated it everywhere. But I've heard
that in the US military, for instance, they do an exceedingly good job at getting different
people of different races to integrate. And it's not a huge problem once you're through basic
training, all the training, everything. But for a different sex, it still represents a
significant problem that the military hasn't figured out. And as you look to, well, what's the
military doing? Because if something was solvable, can we sleep for four hours a night and be healthy?
If we could, I bet the military would know. So I kind of look sometimes at them to see their
integration. But it might be that there are other issues there that make it ironic.
Yeah, it feels like the military is a very particular kind of thing. The actual task at hand
might bias the difficulty of the process. Potentially, yeah. There's been a lot of interesting
talk about women integrating into male groups. And how do you do this in a way where everybody
is happy with the outcome? And there's not issues. I think Jordan Peterson spoke about this a little
bit and then Workplace Culture speaks about this a bit. Would you happen to remember, I want to say
it was like five or 10 years ago, there was a big tech conference and there were two guys behind a
woman and they made a joke about like a USB dongle, like dongle was a dick. And this woman turned
around, she tweeted pictures of them, spoke about like misogyny and then that blew up into a huge
ordeal that like, yeah. There was this interesting phenomenon that in a less misogynistic and more
inclusive workplace environment, some women might end up feeling worse because in a more
misogynistic environment, you're thinking like, okay, that's a woman. She doesn't get our humor.
I'm going to treat her in a very indifferent, very dispassionate, cold way and whatever. And then
I'm going to have my boys over here. And then you've got like these environments where they're
a little bit more warmer. And it's like, oh, cool, we're going to bring this woman into our environment
and we're going to make all the same types of like crash jokes we did before. And it's actually
worse now. Another woman feels even more otherwise because like, oh my God, why do you talk like
this? I think that internet communities, especially online ones that do like political debate and
video games are very much like big boys clubs. So it's not enough to just say you can't be
misogynistic to get rid of misogyny. There's always going to be an othering effect on women.
There's a lot of like behaviors that are unintuitive that you have to account for and you've
got to try to like push that back. And that's just a very, very, very challenging thing to do.
So like, I like to deal with concrete examples more. So here's a concrete example. And this is
like a recent initiative in my community because I'm trying to like be, because misogyny hasn't
been fixed anywhere on the internet. And I'm curious, well, there are ways that I can push my
community to do this. I don't think you should almost ever make a comment on a woman's appearance
ever if they're appearing in like some political or professional manner. Even if it's a positive
comment, I think it's equally bad to a negative comment. It's just never good to do. And that's
kind of an unintuitive thing because it's like, well, a woman appears, wow, she's really cute.
It seems like a nice comment. You're being nice, you know, she looks cute or whatever. But it's
like, it's not at all the point of why she's there. And just by saying that, you're kind of like
otherizing her as like a person to like think she looks good rather than listening to anything she
has to say, you know? Well, there's a lot of stuff that you're saying and
that is a part of misogyny. It's almost like obvious, like any woman will tell you that.
Woman, well, yeah, but they're not in these spaces and a lot of the guys don't know.
But I think what that requires is just empathy. You don't need, you don't need, you need to
consider the female experience. That's it. Like you have to either read about or talk with women.
You learn like the low hanging food is very easy to learn. It feels like just the level of social
skill oftentimes in internet communities is quite low. I disagree. I don't like to say,
here's the problem with empathy is it's very hard to have empathy for experiences that are so
outside of your own. Well, maybe some people, there might be some people that can do it,
I can't. There's a lot of stuff that I had to learn. Women are half the population.
But they're women. They're totally different. They're totally different.
We'll talk about, they're not totally different. So here's an example, okay? So
especially for me, my archetype makes up a lot of the internet. White man. There's never been a
point. The name of a beautiful woman. Who might be a dancer. What's the backstory from New Orleans
I haven't thought that through yet. It's ambiguous. Like an open world.
Open world. I want you to project wherever you want destiny, the dancer to be from.
That's in your mind. I'll see that for later tonight.
As a white guy, I don't know if there's ever been a spot that I've been in
where I've been made to feel like I don't belong there just by virtue of who I am.
It's impossible for me to empathize that because I don't even have that experience.
If you go back eight, nine years, one of the big issues that came up was harassment and
gaming against women. And I was one of the big debaters against that saying that like,
sure, women might get harassment, but everybody gets harassment. If you're a woman and you're
in gaming and you get harassed, congratulations, you're being treated like a man. What you're
actually asking for is for us to actually treat you differently. You don't want to be insulted.
You don't want to be treated like a man. And that's actually misogyny is women making that
argument. You still stand by that? Is that a problem if I do? No, I'm just kidding.
Okay, hold on. So a little while after. I disagree with it. Sure. Okay. That's good.
You should. A little while later, I had a friend, Jessica, super cool girl. We go to play games.
She was between jobs. She's like, I've got like two months and we're going to grind CS go.
And I'm like, okay, this is awesome. Let's do it. CS go, Counter-Strike,
Global Offensive, Shooter Game, FPS, microphones. First day we start playing. Okay. Hop into our
first game. Obviously she talks. Everybody's making, is that a 12 year old boy? Why aren't
you making sandwiches? Blah, blah, blah. Yeah, okay, whatever. Play our first game.
Play our second game. Same jokes. Third game, fourth game. By like the fourth or fifth game,
I was actually starting to feel triggered. Like every time the game started, I was like,
can you just like talk so we can get over like the stupid fucking jokes? It's so fucking stupid.
And you hear the same fucking joke every single time. And it took one day of that experience
for me to realize it's not about being insulted. It's like this othering feeling that you don't
belong. And I've never felt that because I'm a white guy. Like it's not to be like virtue
singular. So like there's just, there's no places where it's like, you're white, you don't belong
here. You're a guy, you don't belong here. Like I've never felt that not inclusion. And playing
with her, there's a different feeling when it's the same types of jokes coming from a group of
people to make you feel like you don't belong there. Where I was like, damn, this actually
feels really bad. And it feels bad in a different way where it's like, if you call me like NF Slur
or any other type of swear word or insult, like, yeah, you can call me that. But at the end of
the day, like we're all kind of the same, we're all white dudes and we call each other names.
But like this is a woman and this is not her place and she doesn't belong here.
Kind of the analogy that I would make because I after getting these experiences, I would learn
this afterwards. If I tell you that there's another guy in a room and you need to think of the worst
insults ever for that person without ever knowing anything about them or meeting them.
If I tell you that it's like a white straight guy and you have to write insults, you're fucked.
Maybe you can do like school shooter. There's not really much you can say at the end of the day.
But if I tell you it's a woman, whoo, there are so many different jokes you can write.
If it's a black person, so many different racist things we can say.
Are you sure? I can come up with a lot of stuff for a white guy.
In terms of stuff that is just intrinsic to him being a white guy?
Yeah, like there's really?
Wait a minute. What are you talking about? There's a lot. The internet has sharpened that sword.
In terms of like jokes that are targeted at his sex or targets?
Incel, virgin, weak.
Some of the incel, virgin, maybe. Yeah, that's getting there, sure. That's for sure.
That's recent though. Sorry, I'm older on the internet. We didn't have those words way back
then. When I was making these analogies that incel and virgin.
Back in my day, we didn't have gender. There were no incels back then. None of us had sex.
We just accept it. We were all computer gamers. Nobody had sex to play video games back then,
okay? People don't remember that. There wasn't the big bang theory. You were just a loser that
was stuck in zero. You guys didn't even know sex exists as we can use this as an insult.
We had to download sexual pictures and they took two minutes and you didn't even know if
you were going to get the right thing by the time it finished loading. But what I'm saying is that,
okay, I think you agree that if somebody gives you a race, like a black person who's a woman,
we can write very cutting, scathing insults for that person that are very otherizing.
Or words that would really hurt. Yeah, that are very cutting to the person. But for a white guy,
it's kind of hard because that's the default. There's not as much otherizing of those people.
Yeah. So the insults you have from white guy to white guy, the insults are much harsher.
So when you start to apply the same kind of harshness to other groups,
you can make them feel like they really don't belong. And that otherizing effect is something
that's very hard for me. I can't really empathize with it because I never felt it. So I have to
intellectualize it and then sympathize with it. It's like a whole process I have to go through.
And then I try to walk other people through that because if you're a white guy on the internet,
which is a lot of the internet, you really don't know what that feels like. You've never felt
like that before. Well, so you're now in a leadership position, grandpa destiny. So that's
a lot of people look up to you for that. For that sort of pathway to empathy. Yeah.
How not to otherize. I mean, you have felt otherizing. You mentioned high school people
like not being... Yeah, but those are always for things that like it's different to insult somebody
for a non-immutable characteristic. Like, okay, you think poorly about me because I'm like not
enough money or what? I don't have money, but I could get more money and I could change that.
But it's different for somebody to really attack you for like your gender or attack you for like
your race. A lot of the attacks that hit the hardest is not about gender. I do think that
the way women are attacked on the internet, it's the same kind of attacks you would do
towards other guys, but you'd go harsher. I feel like they're fundamentally different.
I feel like when we're attacking guys, I'm not usually attacking you on like the virtue of you
being a guy. But like, if it's a woman and she's typing something like, oh, did your boyfriend
type that for you? Or like, what are you even doing here? Like, shouldn't you be trying to find a
husband? Or like, oh, you're like a stupid kind of like ghost type and only fans? No, but the
stupidity, the intelligence aspect is what's attacked. Yeah, but it's so much different. Like,
you can call a guy stupid, but that's because he's a guy that's being stupid. But when you call
a woman stupid, she's stupid because she's a woman. Yeah, but I honestly think that women
are called stupid more than men on the internet. But it's nothing to do, like the attack
is not gendered. It's the gender inspires an increased level of attack. I feel like it is
gendered. I wish we had data on this. Have you ever heard of the XKCD comics? Yes. It's a really
good comic where, and this is something that I've dealt with a lot in my community, okay? There's
a guy at a board and he fucks up a math equation. And it's like, wow, you suck at math. And then
the next panelist, there's a girl that does it and she fucks it up. And it's like, wow, women
suck at math. And there's like that feeling that happens where when I bring on, I won't use names,
but they're like YouTube people that are brought on that have crazy opinions. And when they're men,
that person is crazy. Oh my God, he said the crazy stuff. He's so dumb. He's so crazy, so stupid.
But when it's a woman, it's like, oh my God, why do you always bring dumb women here? Why do so
many women on the internet have crazy opinions? There's a different like minority character
that has to like stand it and like represent like they're a whole group where like white men
don't typically have to. Speaking of group sources, individuals, yes. But then what I feel happens is
then another person from that group comes, another woman comes and people before she says anything
will already feel like they're ready with that attack. For sure. But they're ready for the attack
because she's a woman. They're going to call her she's stupid because she's not because she says
something to them or just because she's a woman. So like the group in their brain accumulates all
the negative characteristics of the individuals they've met, not the positive, the negative,
and it becomes like this ball of stickiness. And then that becomes the bias for their judgment of
a new person that comes with white men. There's more of a blank slate in terms of bias of how
they analyze the person with any of the minority group, they basically make a judgment based on
the negative characteristics of the individuals they've met in the past. That leads to a system
where you're just harsher towards minority groups and towards women. How do you solve that?
The most important thing for any problem ever is step one is to be aware of it. If you're not aware
of it, then you're hopelessly lost at sea. But yeah, the first thing I like to say is she's like
be aware of it. Like I've had, there's a girl that I've had on recently and she says a lot of,
in my opinion, kind of crazy things, but people will use her as like this is why women shouldn't
be here. This is like she's crazy and she's a woman and blah, blah, blah. But I can bring on a guy
who's has similarly done things and he's evaluated on his own merits because it's a guy. There's never,
ever, ever been a case where I brought a stupid guy on stream and everybody's like,
this guy makes me hate men. This guy makes me hate white people. That has never happened.
But then there's like other women that come on and it's like, now I know why incels exist.
Or I totally understand where red pill ideology comes from. And even if the statements are kind
of true, when you're making these observations over and over and over and over again, it damages
your ability to individually perceive somebody. And then two people that make the same statements,
one can be perceived more harshly just because of that like group bias you've got built up.
I think there's something about streaming that just brings that out of people. Like because
you have to talk for like seven hours. So you're like, all right, well, whatever psychological
issues and complexities I have, I'm going to explore that for some magnified magnified.
And then it's the, as you talked about the memetic theories or Gerardian, like whatever
the things that are very similar and you're going to magnify the conflicts that you have and you're
going to explore the, all the different perspectives on those different conflicts.
And I mean, I don't know if it's just anecdotal, but it's nice to have women on stream. And I think
the dynamic that you guys have is wonderful. It's really interesting. So it's just the female
voice in general. I love having women on the podcast. The female voice, I feel like is under
heard on the internet and I would love the internet to be a place where women feel safe to
speak. All right, given that you're, like we talked about a progressive with non-standard
progressive views. So you're very pro free speech, pro capitalism. So given that it's very
interesting that you're also pro establishment and pro institutions. So right now if you look
at the world, there's a significant distrust of institutions, at least in sort of public
intellectual discourse. What is the nature of your support for government and institutions?
Can you make the case for and against them? Broadly speaking, there is a synergistic effect
when two humans come together. If I can speak very broadly in terms of, we'll say utility,
my happiness with one person might be 10. When they come together, it's like 50
between the two of them. There's like the synergistic effect when humans work together
that the sum is greater than all the individual parts or whatever. There's like an emergent
thing that happens there. There's a capacity, there's a possibility of that. Yeah, a possibility,
sure. Things could go really wrong. There could be a cannibalistic tribe that all eats each other,
but for the purpose of this. There's all their failure modes, but yes.
Okay, sure. Yeah. But I think broadly speaking, are you going to be the well actually guy?
Okay, if you want to well, okay. Well, actually. Sometimes cannibalism is actually good for both.
True. Yeah, sometimes things do go wrong. But I think broadly speaking, the fact that
you're sitting here in clothing that you didn't make and I'm sitting here on an airplane that
I don't know how to fly or build, like right, there's a lot of cool stuff that happens when
people come together and they make civilizations. And part of that civilization building is the
fact that we can specialize. And it's the fact that we can offload a bunch of trust onto third
parties that we delegate the power to make important decisions about our lives, right?
I don't know anything about how to like build like a combustion engine, but I know that when I
push the button in my car, it's going to drive around and the fumes aren't going to kill me
and I can park it in garages and the building's not going to collapse. And the only reason all
of this works is because I've offloaded a lot of trust onto these third party things.
And I would say that the pillars of these third party things that society is built on
are roughly speaking institutions. So that might be the institution of peer review for
scientific articles. It might be the institution of voting for government, right? Or the ability
for us to vote in that whole process. It might, yeah, all the FDA, like all of the institutions
and things that they need to exist because we don't have the time or the capability to
individually sort through all of these things individually. We have to rely on some third
party to do it. Okay. So you believe at scale, when we're together, we're greater than the
sum of our parts. That's the case for institutions. Absolutely. What about the inefficiencies of
bureaucracy? Is there some aspect when at scale, different dynamics come into play than they do
when there's two people together, two people that love each other, the birds and the bees?
Is there some aspect that leads more to cannibalism at scale? So like corruption
inefficiencies that due to bureaucracy and so on. Bureaucracy, which is not, I hate it when people
try to say bureaucracy is government because bureaucracy exists a ton in private environments
as well, right? In businesses and everything. Bureaucracy introduces its own set of problems.
But I mean, a bureaucracy is necessary because it's coordinating all of the underlying things
in order to create something that's greater than the sum of its parts, right? Like all of the
software developers in the world are useless without being paired with good designers in
order to make their products usable by a person. And the coordination of those people and the
coordination of increasingly more and more things necessitates some level of bureaucracy.
I think we always say bureaucracy when it's like a bad, it's like a slur on us. Like you're
a bureaucrat, you're bureaucratic. The bureaucracy is slowing everything down. It's like,
sure, the bureaucracy slows things down, but bureaucracy also gives us things like, you know,
safe medicine and safe water to drink for most of the US or safe buildings to live in or safe
cars to drive. So the managers in institution versus like the software developers and the
designers, the managers is the bureaucracy. The reason bureaucracy is used as a slur is that
something about human nature leads to bureaucracy often growing, growing indefinitely and becoming
less and less efficient. I mean, this is where capitalism can come in, that capitalism puts
a pressure on the bureaucracy not to grow too much because you want the bureaucracy to be useful,
but not large. To be a certain size, of course. To be the minimum size to get the job done.
And so capitalism provides that mechanism. Government does not always. And so that's
the criticism of government of institutions where it can grow without a significant mechanism that says
there's a cost to bureaucracy that's not being accounted for here. We're just paying for the
increasing size of government without the benefit. Yeah, government is a special institution because
it doesn't have to show itself to be financially viable. And we kind of live in a capitalist economy
where that's generally the case. So government gets its powers from votes from the people,
which introduces a whole new set of possible positives and possible negatives. Having something,
for instance, that gives food or shelter to homeless people, maybe you don't want that to
have to run at a profit. But giving an organization that can self-justify its budgets perpetually
and indefinitely growing, maybe that's not the best thing. Yeah, we always have to figure out
how to do the constraints there. What about the corrupting nature of power? That comes with
institutions as well. Absolutely. So then you better pick your style of institution very carefully.
I think that the democratic institution we have in the United States today,
I think works very well. But I mean, there are other styles of government that have been tried
in the past that I think lend themselves more to corruption. Not to say that, by the way,
there's not corruption in the United States. Of course, there's going to be varying levels of
corruption at all levels. But you run into this interesting problem where authoritarian regimes
can act with ruthless precision and swiftness because they don't have to ask any questions.
They just do, do, do, do, do. And that's it. But the problem is, it's an authoritarian regime.
They're prone to missteps. They're slow to respond to changing or evolving needs. There was an
interesting study that was put out a while ago that showed that every single famine that happened
around the world, almost 98% of them happen under authoritarian regimes where freedom of
speech is very limited. It's very rare for a famine to happen under democracy because
press and everything makes the government more responsive to the needs of the people.
Power can corrupt. Their level is of corruption. But you have to have a system of checks and
balances on all of those different levels to make sure it doesn't run off the rails, I guess,
and do a sick loop-de-loop and half the population gets nice callback. There's a lot of people that
will listen to you say that the democracy in the United States is working pretty damn well
and they will spit out the drink if they're drinking a drink and be very upset. Can you make the case
that they're right and you're wrong? Can I make the case that- Can you steal man?
They're right. Yeah. Well, the steal man for them is that people have a lot of problems on the day
to day. And when they look and they see what government is doing, they might see potholes
outside their house, homeless people all over their downtown, and the United States just approved
another X billion amount of dollars for Ukraine. Or they might be living in a city where half
the factors are shut down. A lot of their people are out of work, but the president is on the TV
talking about how to find jobs for immigrants coming in from Mexico. And for these people,
they have problems that exist in their lives. Some of them are paying taxes to alleviate these
problems. And then when they listen to the government talk, it feels like the government is
not responding to the needs that they have. And then that's one problem. Then on top of that,
you've got all of these people working in alternative media that can show you, well,
look at this politician wasting this much money. Or look at him double speaking here or there.
Look at Hillary Clinton saying she's got a private position and a public position. Look at how
all of these politicians have family members that are getting rich because of their relationships
with people in Congress. Look at the revolving door between capitalist companies and the government.
How can you look at all of that, take into account that the government's not responding
to your needs and then really feel like it's a government by the people and for the people?
Yeah, this was a very good, good steelman and good question. How can you, how can you,
how can you tell that they're not just politicians that care more about
continuously winning the elections versus being running government effectively?
They should care about winning the elections. That's the first misconception. A lot of people
say this guy only cares about getting voted in. This guy, like, he doesn't even believe in fracking
or abortion. He just changed his opinion to get voted in. Anytime somebody says that,
you say, that's really good. You want them to change their opinions so they get voted in.
That's the whole point of the democracy. You don't want them to remain obstinate. You don't
want them to say, I'm not changing my opinion no matter what the people want. You want them to
evolve and adopt new opinions based on what the population, their constituents are voting for.
Yeah, but the cynical take is that on the surface they're changing their opinion,
but that there's a boys club or boys means the elite that under in the smoke filled rooms
in secret, they're actually have their own agenda and they're following that agenda and they're
just saying anything publicly to placate the public based on whatever the new trends are.
So here's the cynical take a poll.
Yeah, I understand. Somebody asked me this question and it flipped. I won 80 completely.
I was a Bernie Sanders supporter in 2016 and my single issue voting thing was lobbying.
I thought that lobbying, the government was corrupt, they weren't responding to these people.
It was completely destroyed my faith in government and everything. And I had one question post me
by a conservative that used to come on my stream and shout at me and he said, I think he asked me,
can you think of any popular opinion that the American public has that the government is
unresponsive to? Is there some big piece of legislation or policy or whatever that people
want that the government isn't doing? They asked me that. I couldn't think of a single good answer.
And I'm like, oh, geez, there's good. There's drugs. There's not. Legalization or drug. Hold on.
Yeah, go for it. Oh, shoot. You're doing the Joe Rogan thing. You're pushing back because I brought
up weed. Go ahead. I'm sorry. I have become meme. I don't even, I don't want to interrupt your quote
because there's memes upon memes upon memes I can go with here. But no, because people bring up,
okay, there's no issues. There's no issues that the government is not representing of the public.
So here's the issue. So somebody will bring up like, well, what about the legalization of drugs?
Okay. The first issue people have is one, they look at national polling. Very few things are
decided on a national level. So that's the first huge mistake. Arguably, a lot of BLM made mistakes
in this arena where they're saying like, why isn't the government doing anything about policing?
Federal government can't do anything about policing. That's going to be your, sometimes
not even your state government, sometimes your local city government, the people that like elect
like your chief of police, your police commissioner, that's coming from your mayor, right? So you've
got people looking, one, at the wrong parts of the government to even figure out the solutions to
the problem. Two, oftentimes for polling, the questions are vague enough that you can pull
very high. But when you get into the weeds on things, no pun intended, you start to realize
like, oh, shoot, this is more complicated than I thought. I don't know the numbers in particular
for legalization of marijuana, but this is what I'm going to guess is the case. If you poll and you
say, should we legalize marijuana, that number might pull at like 65, 70%. But that's including
people that are in favor of medical marijuana. If you were to poll, like, should we legalize,
should we decriminalize recreational use of marijuana, that number might drop to like
52%. And then if you poll, like, should we completely legalize, not just decriminalize,
but completely legalize recreational use of marijuana, that number might drop to like 40%.
There's like all these different ways you can pull around issues where people are like, oh,
no, we broadly agree on this topic. But when you really figure out, well, do you,
do we really agree? Or is it just like broad consensus around a thing that's never going
to show up like in a piece of legislation? A really good example, one example I do know is
socialized health care. I think if you poll, there was a time a few years ago where if you
poll America, do you think every American citizen should have access to like free health care?
I think that answer, that poll like 74% yes. But when you asked, should the government be the sole
provider of health care, it dropped to like 26%, dropped 50 points. And you could see it was both
asking questions about single payer, but the way that it was asked was so different that even if
you all, it looks like there's consensus, there's not nearly as much consensus as people think
around certain ideas. Yeah, go. You're right. You're right. You're right. You're right.
That polls, the way you ask the polls really matters. But when you ask, should the government
be in charge of a thing, that also biases the answer, right? Like, because there's such a negative
experience with government creating a dog gov site that runs the thing. But sometimes,
sometimes, I think if you dig in, if you have a one hour conversation with each individual
citizen, I think you will understand that, yes, there is support for socialized medicine.
The argument has to be made though, yeah. What do you mean with the argument has to be made?
Like, if you just ask a conservative, like what about single payer, they're going to tell you,
no, you might be able to build up to an argument for it, but you're going to have to make the case
for it. No, but I thought we're talking about the feeling deep inside your mind and heart.
Does the government represent that? Oh. So it's not like some shallow surface layer
public opinion. Does the government effectively represent what the people want? Not a shallow
survey, but deeply what they want. I'm not actually that familiar with the debates over
healthcare, but let's maybe look at an easier one. Sure. Maybe you'll say it's harder. War.
War is a really good example where the government was very responsive, I think, to the people.
You think so. So, Iraq, Afghanistan, the government didn't manipulate public opinion.
There is an argument to be made that they did in terms of like WMD and everything,
but after 9-11, were you in the United States after 9-11? After 9-11, I legit.
That seems accusatory. Like, where were you in 9-11?
Just checking, okay. All right, cool. I have evidence and witnesses. No, okay,
I'm very defensive right now. That's very strange. Look into it.
I think after 9-11, we could have gone to war with any country in the world.
We were ready because all of America was like, oh my God. And they pointed to Iraq and, you know,
the reasons for the WMDs was kind of dumb, but I don't think we even needed WMDs to go to Iraq.
We could have just said, you know, Saddam Hussein was giving medical aid to Taliban,
al-Qaeda, Iraq, let's go, and we would have gone for it. But post Iraq, Iraq was for a while
popular and then became obviously deeply unpopular, Iraq and Afghanistan. And I think you could see
that influence other foreign policy that the United States had. For instance, we opted more
towards like drone warfare than troops on the ground for places like Yemen. We opted more
towards like kind of like sending money and help instead of boots on the ground for places like
Syria. And I think that a lot of that was kind of in response to how unpopular the Iraq stuff
had become. And when you looked at a lot of elections afterwards, even for Obama, like one
of the defining characteristics of a lot of campaigns were like, I'm going to close Guantanamo
Bay. I'm going to get us out of foreign wars. Even up to Trump, I'm going to, you know, I'm not
going to stop doing all this weird stuff in the Middle East. But they didn't still withdraw from
Afghanistan. They didn't withdraw, but they definitely like tapered off and weren't like as
aggressively pushing those types of conflicts because they knew it was unpopular. But I think
if you also consider perfect information or good information, if you ask a lot of people,
are you okay spending this amount of money for this purpose? So military conflict in
Iraq and Afghanistan, I think almost from the very beginning, they would say no.
After 9-11? I feel like maybe like a few days after 9-11, like,
I remember Freedom Prize.
What was the nature? Well, there's some memes and so on, yes. But the nature of the public support
for the war, was there public support in 2003, which is when the invasion happened?
I feel like initially there was a lot, I remember seeing it on, but then I also lived in a republican
household and I was not very like media savvy at that. And I don't know if the nature of that
public support had to do with WMDs or with 9-11. Because the weird-
It came about WMDs.
But I wonder what is the, if you were to poll people and let's say hypothetically,
there was above 50% support for the war, what would be the nature of that support?
And to what degrees the government actually representing the will of the people versus
some complex mechanism like the military industrial complex is manipulating the narrative
that's controlling public opinion. And then there's the media that gets a lot of attention
by being divided and how they're shaping the narrative through the mechanism of division.
There's a lot of complicated things out there. It's not just like the people and then the
government. And that's, yeah, for sure, I agree that there are going to be different
elements at play.
And how much of those elements that lead us astray can be attributed to the
largeness of the different systems and the different institutions, like the media institutions
and government, the institutions that have a monopoly on violence. Let's put it this way,
which is one way to define government.
Sure. It's complicated. There's definitely going to be different institutions at play.
But I think that like, all I would say is like in reference to my original point,
when there becomes like broad consensus around a thing, I think the government will usually
follow. It's not going to fight. It's going to follow more often than not.
But I think that a lot of times I think Americans think that there's more consensus
around certain issues than there actually are. So like a really good example, we're on that war
point too. What caused like the lowest dip in Biden's approval rating? I'm pretty sure it was
right after we pulled out of Afghanistan, which I think if I would have asked people like a year
before, like, let's assume that we could pull out of Afghanistan, the government's probably
going to collapse after we leave because they just don't have the will to fight, they don't have
the support, whatever, it's just not going to work. But like no Americans are going to die.
There might be a couple other people who are like, no Americans are going to die,
we're going to get out of Afghanistan. Would you support that? I think broadly speaking,
I think more than 60 or 70% of Americans are like, yeah, that would be fine.
But then when it actually plays on TV, when we see the people hanging onto the planes,
when we see like helicopter embassies, some of the courts and politicians,
well now it's like, oh my God, this was horrible and it was so botched.
And it could have gone so much better. It's like, well, could it have gone better?
Maybe, maybe not. But I mean, it seems like you can have consensus around a certain opinion.
But the way that things play out and the way that people actually feel,
it's actually way, way, way more complicated. And there's not usually this broad consensus
opinion. All right, yeah, go ahead. I'd like to believe that. I mean, just to lay my cards on the
table, I have faith in the power of effective government. I just have a lot of concern about
what happens as institutions grow in size. For sure. And I just have a lot of worry about the
natural corrupting influence on the individuals and on the system as a whole, like the boys' club
nature of it. I don't know, there must be a better term. But basically, they, they agree to the game
and they play the game and there's a generational aspect momentum to the game. And they more and
more stop being responsive to the people that they represent. I just feel like there is that
mechanism. And I think the nice thing, democracy elections are a resistance to that natural human
mechanism. Also, the balances of power is a resistance to that mechanism. In some ways,
the media that reveals the bullshit of politicians is also a resistance to that mechanism. It's hard
to be full of shit as a politician because people will try to catch you on it. So there's a honesty
method there that keeps you honest. It's to some degree, but it still feels like
it still feels like politicians are going to politician. Yeah, they definitely play their
games. That is true. There's probably always going to be that meta narrative over like
governance that just develops as like, you have to form relationships and play games to
like get legislation passed and everything. The only, the only reason why I don't like it when
people attack institutions is because one, institutions are incredibly important, arguably
paramount. No, they are to keeping society running. And two, I think sometimes when we shift the
blame onto institutions too much, I think that we lose sight of what the real problems are.
So for instance, in the United States today, people might be very critical of the government not
getting much done, but then everybody turns their eyes to the government for being ineffective.
What I would argue is I would say the government is actually incredibly effective and it's
showcasing the will of the American people really well right now, which is we are historically
more divided than we have ever been. And if I were to just look at the people and I would say
we have a historic divide that is getting like rapidly blown apart by things like the internet
and the media, right? If that exists, well, what would I expect that government to look like?
I wouldn't expect the government to be governing very effective. I would expect that government
to show that legitimate divide in people. Do you think that divide, we have a perception of a
large divide between left and right. Do you think that's a real divide that's in this country?
Narrow the language. What do you mean by real divide? Do you think there is that divide in
ideology, that there's a large number of people that believe a certain set of policies and the
different set of policies? Or is it just the perception on Twitter? No, I think there is a
large divide in terms of belief. I don't think there's very much divide between any people
in terms of like what they like on the most fundamental levels want in terms of like human
beings. But in terms of like Democrat versus Republican right now, I think there is a huge
divide in terms of the direction they want to see the country go and what they believe
really and what they even believe is reality, right? Unfortunately, that's who we've gotten to.
Can I just speak about the mechanism of the left and right here, maybe on the
memetic-roverly aspect? Is there some aspect to the left on which you're a part of that attacks
their own for ideological impurity more than the right does? Is it the bigotry of small differences?
There's a concept where when you're near somebody who is very slightly different than you,
you want to destroy it, but when you're with somebody that's way different than you, you don't.
I think the left does it, but I think the right does it too. I didn't realize it until
I started dipping more into conservative communities, but oh my god, the people from the
Daily Wire and the people from Turning Point and the America First, all these different groups
of people hate each other and they fight each other so much. They hire and fire sometimes,
employs, they talk smack about each other. I think there's a lot of political division between
both sides. I think that the left just kind of gets highlighted more because it's like the
internet and a lot of the internet spaces have a lot of left-leaning people, so you see like
the crazy communists and the crazy progressives and the crazy center-left liberals and the crazy
blah blah blah, whereas a lot of the right-leaning people have kind of been pushed off of the main
areas of the internet now. Interesting. My sense was that it's hard to exist on the center-left,
but maybe because I just don't have the full spectrum view of the political divide. It felt
like center-left is a difficult position to occupy. Yeah, I would definitely say so, yeah.
I don't know if it's that difficult to be center-right. It's very difficult to be center-right.
I think actually maybe even more difficult, because a center-right person might be somebody
who's like conservative, but not a fan of Trump and you're like over, like looking like Liz Cheney,
right? You've had politicians that are just like, they didn't back the Trump stuff and now they're
gone, or you might be like center-right, but like you don't think the election was stolen
and now you're like half the Republican party is looking at you like you're crazy, you know?
That's true. That's true. I think there's a Ben Shapiro I'm talking with. I think he publicly
spoke against Trump, right? He did initially, but I feel like he softened his language up on
him pretty significantly, but... So there's a significant pressure to kind of count how to
a certain kind of messaging. Which the whole Republican party is feeling right now. Geez,
that two years from now, that election is going to be insane.
It's just hard. Okay. So to generalize, it's hard to be in the center, it feels like.
For sure.
To center and then like do like a random walk among the policies around that. I don't know
what that mechanism is. I mean, it makes people like me not feel good being in the center. It
seems like people are just not nice to people in the center. Like the public, the Twitter machine
is not nice to people who are open-minded in the center. Is there some truth to that?
Two reasons for that. One is because I think a lot of people that market themselves as center
are legitimately spineless cowards and deserve to be called out. I've never killed the man,
but today might be my first. Oh no. Like I told you, I'll take over your stream with the AI.
Yeah, we'll see. Is that guy going to be streaming in the background?
Hey fellas. Okay, gotcha, gotcha, gotcha. Lots of gotchas, lots of gotchas. Okay, gotcha.
And decrease them up, which already is a pretty low level of emotion. Just decrease it completely.
When people are screaming at you and accusing stuff, just remain calm.
Absolutely. Emotionless. The gaslighter strategy.
Okay, so what we're talking about. So I don't. I don't even, I don't ever identify a center
anything because it's got such a bad reputation because so many.
Fuck that. I stand center with a spine. It's called being open-minded and it's not
center left and right, those are just labels. Here's a really good quote my mom said to me
when I was really young. She said, Stevie, don't ever let your mind be so open that your brain
falls out. And that's what I find that a lot of center people do. That's not what she told me
last night. Why are you like this? I'm sorry. Okay, I'm glad I can, glad I can bring that. I'm glad
you feel like this is safe space. Like I said, people, not judgmental. If you want to talk about
fucking my mom, you know what? You're totally within your rights. I didn't say that. You said
that. I didn't say that. I support that. She's a beautiful woman. Her husband probably wouldn't
be too happy about it, but you know, I didn't say those any sexual relations. It was just that
having a conversation with her, you projected that that says more by you than me. Anyway,
go ahead about spineless center. There is some aspect to that, which is like amorphous. To me,
center means you think freely about each individual policy without being stuck to a king.
Some ideal, yeah, but a lot of people don't do that. They call them so centrist, but then they
just, they're anti-establishment essentially on everything. I don't know your position on
like the vaccines or anything, but like, I've met a lot of like free and open thinkers who are like,
you know what? I'm open to everything and it's an experimental vaccine and I'm going to eat hydroxy
chloroquine and ivermectin because that's what the institutions are telling me not to take. And I
think Fauci got too much money from that company and these are, but I'm an open thinker. And they,
what open thinker becomes- I'm an MIT. What do you think my position of vaccines is exactly?
I hear a lot of crazy things from a lot of people. Okay. You might be from MIT,
but I know you're from the internet. Okay. And people from the internet are weird and crazy.
So yeah. Well, I- Who knows? I don't like arrogance. And I have criticized scientists during COVID,
a lot of people, but scientists included having arrogance. Which is fair. But- And that's, and I
think there's a lot of good criticism to be made of different scientific and medical establishments
over a lot of stuff. But nobody can make those good criticisms because they're too like obsessed
over like just trying to have the anti-establishment answer. And that is what is upsetting me the most.
Like I think there are good conversations to be had about a lot of stuff related to how we handled
the coronavirus. You know, were lockdowns effective? Was there enough data to support the
huge measures we took? You know, why didn't we have the option to show I was infected a month ago?
Why do I need to be vaccinated? Why did, why wasn't that option ever a thing in the United
States? I don't think it was. There are really good questions to be asked there. But all the people
asking the questions are also trying to tell you that ivermectin and monoclonal antibodies are the
way to go for everything. And the vaccine is evil. And they're just going to turn you gay like the
frogs. And it's like, Jesus, like you get, there's like no place to reasonably criticize from
because all of the people that are criticizing aren't doing it with an open mind or, you know,
they're not reading studies or do anything. They're saying like, I do my own research, which means
they listen to whatever the last guy on Joe Rogan said and now they're parroting that opinion 100%.
Easy no. Easy no, gross. The last guy on Joe Rogan, not Joe Rogan. Okay. That Robert Malone
guy on Joe Rogan got me real fired up. That's one guest. People see him as like the father of
mRNA technology. He published one paper. Okay. What do you mean people? Which people think that?
Joe Rogan fans. I get like, I run into these people. I start arguing with people and they
start studying me. But what about- I'm a Joe Rogan fan and I appreciate the vaccine.
That's good. I'm glad you do. But there's definitely-
Sorry, but you said there's a type. There's a type. What's the type of Joe Rogan fan?
Anti-establishment. I think that's not Joe Rogan. That's a general public discourse. There's a
default anti-establishment on the right and the left. That's the default easy thing to go to.
I think Joe Rogan fans are definitely a certain type of anti-establishment though.
Like I could guess the Joe Rogan fan. Like if I were to do general population versus Joe
Rogan fan, who do you think is more likely to be anti-vaccine?
Do you have data on this? Are you just guessing?
Just guessing. Yeah. I think you are actually judging.
I am. Yeah. I think you're judging. Because I think you're also-
The beautiful thing about podcasting, this could be similar to streaming, is there's a large
number of people that just listen. Like what does it mean to be a Joe Rogan fan?
I don't think you just listen. I think people listen and absorb the information.
I would say that Joe Rogan fan base is as divided in the vaccine as the general public.
Gotcha. Man, I'm going to look for polling data on that. I'm sure somebody's got to have done it
out there. But you're basically revealing the fact they have no data. You're using your own judgment.
For sure. Based on how he's had conversations about his experience with the coronavirus,
and then based on the guests that have come on that have talked and echoed a lot of like
anti-vax talking points and been completely unchallenged. And then based on statements
he's made about like myocarditis and the vaccine and everything as well. Yeah.
So that it's the level of challenge or not that he's doing.
Well, yeah. And then what his true positions are. And then the types of guests he typically
chooses to bring on to talk about the vaccines. Yeah.
Okay. But that represents somehow a deep anti-establishment feeling versus just the vaccine.
I mean, I've seen the vaccine and other things being a thing that broke people.
They seem to- All the coronavirus, that whole one or two years broke. A lot of people.
Because there's a lot of emotion and their emotion quickly solidified into an opinion
that almost had nothing to do with like thinking through and updating your knowledge and so on.
You just made up your mind. Yeah. But I think a lot of it comes from that anti-establishment
place. Like the vaccine represents the ultimate of establishment. It was a huge private company
backed by a huge public government. And there's Fauci, and there's Biden, and there's Pfizer,
and there's all these countries locking us up in our homes telling us to do a thing.
Like the vaccine was like the ultimate submission tool to show you that the government owns you.
Not only do you have to get injected once, it's a series. And then you got to get boosters,
and it's like they're trying to keep you under their thumb, and that's the control.
I feel like that vaccine became like the ultimate rallying cry between like,
do you support, are you a sellout that is going to believe whatever the government
tells the sheep to take? Or are you going to be like the guy that stands against the crowd
and gets fired from his job and pulls his kids from school because they're not going to let the
evil Fauci medicine jab them in the arm? And the funny thing is the crowd that stands
against the institution is now larger than the crowd of sheep. There's like one sheep standing
there. Sure. Or it feels that way sometimes. One vaccinated sheep. Well, okay. What's the
defense of institutions? How do you regain the trust of institutions? Like, for first of all,
do you think that there's ways in which WHO, CDC failed? And do you think there's criticism
towards Pfizer and the big pharma companies that's deserved? Damn, there's the pharma companies,
I'm not sure. For CDC and WHO, so here's a criticism that I have of all of academia and I
feel it's stronger, stronger every day. I don't think it's enough to be a researcher or to be
correct about issues. Academia needs to increase its ability to communicate. It is just an unbelievable,
unmitigated failure that academics are unwilling to wade into the complicated topics
that exist today because other people are, you know? First, you call me spineless and then you
call me a bad communicator. But no, look, you're here, you're doing it. So you get props from me,
okay? Good job. That motherfu- But there are like so many, but I'm sure you've, I'm sure that you
must have heard another fellow academic, a fellow colleague express some amount of frustration about
like in their specific discipline, they know something to be true and they know that like,
a lot of the messaging is like wrong or bad and the public about it, but they're never going to
step out and say anything because either one, they're very measured and careful with their
take, which they feel is incompatible with what people want to hear or two, they're really worried
that they might be incorrect. So they're going to be cautious while everybody else is going out in
like hardcore. And they also don't have the support of institutions for them to go out on a limb.
Yeah, that too. So like to take risks. For example, I've heard that with lab leak theory.
I've had a lot of biologists, virologist friends that are like, yeah, it's obviously leaked from
lab early on. Oh, maybe. Okay. We can fight over this one. But sorry, go ahead. We can fight over
this. But like they, okay, I should sort of back step and say like, that's like, you talk about
shooting the shit you haven't really investigated, but it's your gut. Like, this doesn't make any
sense. There would never say that publicly. Of course. Mostly because you're saying like what
they would all say is like, we want to see data. Yeah, which would be good, which is fine. So
they're going with like, this is too many coincidence in the same place. That's the logic,
but they don't want to say anything because there's no data. You need to have evidence.
You need to have actual evidence to say one way or the other. There's that. But there's also just
like you said, I mean, effective, effective communication. You're a fan of Sean Carroll.
Oh, yes. He's like one of the only people in this whole planet that I like besides you. I love
Sean Carroll. Anytime Sean Carroll is brought up as evidenced, there's a smile that comes over your
face. I love it. Of like joy. Yeah. Of like a little kid thinking about Santa Claus. Okay,
I love Sean Carroll too. I love Sean Carroll because I hate this divide between like you're
either STEM or you're like philosophy, arts and all that other stuff. And the two worlds kind of
across. And I love that it was so good at physics, but like explorers and pays attention to all of
the like sociological stuff too. It's so rare to find that quality in a person. He's legit. One of
the really, really, really specialized, but you don't have to be a Sean Carroll. You can be just
a little better at educating. Another person in the medical and the health space is somebody
named Andrew Huberman, a friend of mine from Stanford. He's an incredible educator. There's
the kind of process and science they usually call like review or survey papers where you basically
summarize all that's going on, integrate it and like draw wisdom from it and also project like
where's the discipline headed. And Andrew does that basically on all these subcomponents of
the different stuff going on in neuroscience and biology and neurobiology, all of that. He's able
to, he does a podcast called Huberman Lab where he just summarizes all and is able to explain
like what does that actually mean for your, for your life in terms of protocols of how to make
your life better. I feel like people should be able to do that more and more, but with viral,
virology and boy, that's a tricky one. That's a really tricky one. I wish that people could have
honest conversations. Like I attack a lot of people that do the lab leak theory stuff, but
truly we should be able to have that conversation publicly. It just, it always feels like the
people that are having the conversation don't ever really want to have the conversation. They're
not being honest. Like I'm a guy that like does his own research and it's so boring reading studies
and a lot of it, I can only do abstracts and like, it's so much work, but I'll never ever say that
about myself. I'm a guy that does his own research because every time I hear somebody say that,
they don't do any research. When they say they do their own research where they mean is they've
seen one podcast and their opinion on his computer podcast is that definitely not mine
because it was mine. I wouldn't be criticizing anything they say. But yeah, so like lab leak
is another one where it's like, well, how do you know it's lab leak? How do I know it's lab leak?
Because Fauci lied and Hunter Biden laptop and it's like, okay, come on, you haven't engaged with
it at all. There's really interesting research that shows us a really strong study that shows
that there's like a high degree of certainty that it came from the wet markets, very, very high
degree of certainty. And there was an article that came out recently where it's like, Senate
concludes that virus actually came from the Wuhan virology lab or whatever. And that whole article,
if you actually read it, it never says that in the article. I don't know why they tweeted it
with that headline. But yeah, to back up, I'm sorry, I think we should have good, you should be
sorry. Yeah, I'm not sorry, actually, I get to ramble here. Okay, I'm here for a long time. I
rescind my apology. Okay, I actually rescind my apology. We should be able to have challenging
conversations about things, but you gotta man, be well read on both sides, not this like, I do
my own research. So I don't believe anything that Fauci says, like, come on, dude, do you think
you can do better than that? Not you personally, but gotcha. How does that feel?
So for people who don't know, that's the catchphrase. Gotcha. Through all tragedy and triumph,
through all the roller coaster of life, your response to it is gotcha. It's election. Let me
jump to that before I continue with political discourse. Psychologically, you are in a lot
of heated debates. And you're usually super calm under fire until you're not. Sometimes you lose
your temper completely. Very rarely. But that's like your opinion, man. Let me ask you about
your psychology. What are psychologically your strengths and weaknesses that you're
self aware about? I think I'm very non judgmental. So I can entertain a lot of different thoughts
without agreeing with them or condoning them. I think that's a really big benefit to me.
For whatever reason, I seem to be like pretty calm and dealing with annoying people. It's why
I got promoted at the casino so fast, I could deal with like drunks or whatever, like it just didn't
affect me that much. What percent of the population is annoying? Depends on how you're engaging with
them. Most people aren't really annoying ever. That's why I mean that. But if you're doing like
political debate, what percentage is annoying? I guess it depends on who I'm debating and what
the topic is. I guess I'm trying to point out the fact that sometimes you can say
that reveals something about you if you think a large percent of people are annoying.
Well, I would say working graveyard shift when alcohol is involved, that percentage of people
goes very, very, very high. Or to be more fair, actually, it's not a high percentage truly.
But if you're a server, one bad customer can ruin the rest of your shift. So you only need like
one or two people acting in that manner to just like totally throw you off. And you're able to,
at least these days, not allow that one customer to throw you off, quote unquote.
Yeah, very much like a, I noticed this especially after having a son, there's something about like
six year old kids or whatever, where it's like, if they get mad, they're never going to be mad
for that long. Like they'll move on. Like that's my mentality. I'm like a six year old kid. Like
I might be mad about something, but I'll get over it in like 30 minutes or an hour.
I'm pretty good about not carrying that through. It's very rare that I'll like hold a grudge
against anybody or like be angry about something or really disaffected by something over the
long term that almost never happens to me. What are your weaknesses psychologically,
would you say? I still have a problem with projecting. I think we all probably do,
but like my mind onto others, it's like, if I understand this and I've said this,
you should understand it. And if you're not, you're dumb. That's like an issue that I,
I still have that where I project too much. What about like holding grudges and stuff like that?
I'd never hold grudges. I'm like the least grudgy person ever. It's kind of a meme in my
community because anybody can always like come back as long as they're acting different. Yeah.
What about the, as long as they're acting different?
As long as they're acting different. I mean, all right.
The reason why I say that is because so friends, nobody likes this, but I have a strong stance
on apologies and then I hate them. I don't ever want to hear an apology. I don't care about them
ever. They don't mean anything to me. If you did something bad, as long as you've like fixed the
behavior and you're not doing that thing, then we're generally chill. It's like there's been a
lot of people that have been involved in weird stuff with me, but then like they, they go off,
they do the thing and they come back and it's like, okay, cool. As long as you don't do it again,
like we're fine. Like it's all good. I'm sorry. You feel that way. It's not your fault, Steven.
It's not your fault. Okay. Gotcha. You said plenty of negative stuff, positive stuff and
negative stuff about Hassan. Yeah. This is my podcast. I get to get you to force you to say
positive things. What do you love? I'm all about love. Let's go back to grilling me on the R word
stuff. You're going to make me compliment Hassan. This is going to be a harder conversation than
that. All right. We're going to get you to feel emotions. Okay. For people who don't know,
he's another popular political streamer. I think you had, as the kids call it, a bridge burning
over Bernie Sanders. I don't know. My research is very limited on this, but what do you respect
and love most about Hassan? He puts in a lot of work when he was like growing his stream from
2,000 concrete viewers to 15,000. He was streaming like, it was like 12 hours a day,
like every single day. So that was, I remember I did a lot of work. He does seem to be pretty good
at networking and socializing and making the correct friends and connections to continue
to build his business. What about him as a political thinker? I know you don't think
I leave him in that regard, but I think that's unfair. I honestly want to push back on that because
I have zero respect for him as a political thinker. There's not going to be almost anything.
So I will say, I admire the fact that through no actual capability or ability of his own,
he manages to wind up at some of the correct answers just because he's towing the line.
Good job for him on that. He's got a lot of correct opinions, just he has no idea why.
I think that's undeserved. I think that's too harsh, man. The reason I bring that up,
because I feel like there is a deep grudge in there somehow. So you're the father now,
so since you're so old, the grandfather of the political debate on stream,
on live stream political debater. So there could be some grudge about that
split that happened or not enough credit given all that kind of stuff. I just think he's somebody
that has a left-leaning ideology that's different than yours. He was a Bernie supporter,
and I guess you were not. Can you explain to me where the division is?
He exemplifies everything that I absolutely hate about politics, which is shallow engagement,
heavily ideologically driven, and you're not ideologically different.
Absolutely not. That's what we're talking about, like the free thinker in the real
meaning of that word. Let me qualify what I mean when I say that. I spent a lot of time,
unfortunate time, delving into the boring world of philosophy. I spent a lot of time
thinking about what are my ethical positions? How do I feel about myself, the people around me,
and how that relates to the world around me? And then from all of these positions,
I think you might have used the phrase first principles earlier. From these kind of first
principles, out of that is where all of my political positions are built out of, like full stop. So
if you ask me a question, how do you feel about the right to own a firearm, or how do you feel
about social health care? We can walk through, well, this is how I feel about it is like a
thing from the government. This is where the government gets its power. This is ethically how
groups of people are supposed to function. This is morally how we relate to each other. And
personally, this is how I feel. I'll be able to do every single political belief back there.
It's not like I'm telling you, if I were to ask Hassan, what do you feel about this political
topic, he's going to tell me what progressives are supposed to say. I don't know what he thinks
about it. I don't know if he thinks so. Don't you think that's a cynical take? Why is he,
just because his views coincide with the mainstream narrative, mainstream viewpoints
of progressive thinkers? I mean, why does that mean he's not thinking? Because his engagement with
every subject is incredibly shallow, 100% predictable. Like I could write like a, I could
probably program a script to like give you every single potential answer you could have to any
single question you could give him. Again, I think that's pretty cynical take. Okay, it could be the
case that his brain perfectly aligns with every single mainstream. But I don't know if you know
it is perfectly aligns, because I think you're just taking a very select, just extremers do of
each other, a very select slice that represents the perfect alignment, as opposed to looking at a
person struggling with ideas and thinking through ideas, and then giving him a pass like a lot of
people, like I give you a pass on just the fact that you say a lot of crazy shit on streamed for
drama, like, which is why I don't say things for drama. That might be dramatic, but I mean,
you've evolved as a fish evolves legs, you've evolved a mechanism which creates controversy.
Sure. You could say it's not intention, but it happens. I think the extremists kind of learn
that kind of thing. And so I'm sure Hassan does the same kind of stuff. And so like underneath it,
there's still thinking being that's contending with political ideas. You don't think so.
He does a really good job at hiding it. There are other political figures that I really don't
like that I wouldn't say the same thing about. So like, I don't know if you have Vosch written in
there. Like, okay, that's a person that he also split out of my community and grew up to something
and now he hates me and he's an anti fan community and they all have him. Okay, tell me something
you love about Vosch. I can tell you a lot of things about Vosch. I think Vosch legitimately
thinks through a lot of his political positions. I admire or did admire that he has like his own
like positions that we take sometimes contrary to people further left than him. He's got some
positions that don't fit his ideology kind of at all, like he's his own independent thinker.
Rhetorically, he's very effective. He was willing to sit down and do research for like his debates
and everything. He would spend a lot of time practicing like his rhetorical effectiveness
and navigating conversations. He intentionally and purposefully built like a community that
exemplified his values. Yeah, I've got a lot. I don't, we are completely split and hate each other
now, but like I have a lot. Why? Why? Why? First of all, hate is a strong, why the hate?
Okay, I don't hate him, but he hates me because we had a couple of really big debates.
What happened? Well, one had to do with whether or not you should live your values.
And can you give me the story that's a charitable interpretation? I always
give charitable interpretation. You don't. I absolutely do. You don't. Wait,
name one time it happened. Five minutes ago, you talking about Hassan.
Everything I said about Hassan is true. There is no steel man there. Okay. That's not charitable.
That's, I'm sorry. If you can, if you can prove me wrong, I would love for you to do it. Okay.
I'm using my gut instinct. Usually when somebody feels strongly about another person in that way,
it's not coming from a place of data and reason. It's coming from a place of emotion.
It's coming from a place of resentment and grudge and all that kind of stuff.
Yeah, I understand. There's deep, there's emotions deep in there. So the gacha is hiding,
the gacha is a surface of an iceberg and there's a deep ocean underneath that you yourself have
not explored. I disagree, but I understand why-
And Lav is actually a doorway. The young Lav is a doorway for you to explore the depths of-
Get into that ocean to find my fish, my pre-vol form.
I understand why you think the way you do and you should, you shouldn't believe me and I understand
that because if somebody told me the same thing, I think you probably just really don't like this
person for a reason or two. I understand what you think that way. Okay. The reality is though,
for any political person that I disagree with, like I can give them a fair shake. It's one of the
few things I think I do exceedingly well on my stream. Even with Hassan, there's been drama that
he's been involved in and I've like very, when I'm involved in drama, he'll always throw me out of
the bus, but when he's involved in stuff, I'll always say like, oh, like I think Hassan was
right here or I think that he meant this. There was a thing that came up once we're on
live stream fail. He was getting roasted because he referred to somebody, he used the expression
shit skin to refer to somebody's like the way they looked. And I have only ever heard that in
the context of 4chan people talking about like Indians or like black people. Like it's a racial
thing, but I could tell the context and everything that he was saying. He was insulting some guy.
I think it was kind of like incel virgin or whatever. He was going for like acne skin.
I think that's what he meant when he said it. And there were a whole bunch of people that were
insulting like, oh my God, did he just say racist term? And I was like, no, I don't think he was
racist. I think he was like, he was just reaching for words. And that's what came out. So like that's
an example of me being charitable. Okay, but didn't you criticize him for something? I was trying to,
I like Googled why the hell you guys split out because I thought you're friends or you should be
like, it's a little bit more common Harris video, but go ahead. Is that why is that the
I feel like you criticize them over something. And I'm okay, this is very vague memory, but
you criticize them over something. And I felt that criticism wasn't charitable.
Was it Pete Buttigieg stuff? Yeah, Pete Buttigieg. Yes, yes, yes, yes.
Yeah. So I've said this a million times, but there's no amount of context or no amount of nuances
is ever accessible to people. I don't think Hassan is homophobic, but I think the comments
made about Pete Buttigieg were really homophobic. That's what he said. Yeah. And there were a lot
of people making a lot of comments that made me really uncomfortable about Pete Buttigieg.
That was insane to me. Spurred by the comments of Hassan?
No, but it was an environment of progressives. All the progressives were attacking Pete,
and I felt like his gayness became like the subject. Yeah, but why, why throw Hassan under
the bus for that? He was jumping along with all of those types of like insults. You don't think
you've done the same kind of stuff? If I do, call me on it and I'll probably say I shouldn't have.
That's what the R word was about. That's a good call out.
But like your friend, like you should privately tell him, right? Well, no,
by then we were sworn enemies. So that wasn't the reason. No, no, no. It was over a Kamala Harris
video. Sworn enemies. He hates me. What am I supposed to, listen, for all of these people,
I will accept them back into my life if they ever want to come back in at any point in time,
but usually they're the ones that would say. If they correct themselves, right?
No, I'm not expecting anybody to. So here's the deal with Vosh and Hassan. These are like the three,
we're the three guys on line. None of us will talk to each other. Hassan, because he won't give
clout to anybody and Vosh because he thinks I'm bad faith. And then neither of them will talk to me
because they both hate me. You guys should go on a camping trip together. It's like broke back
modern, but three way and just like rejoin, refine, refine the vision for each other. Honestly,
just from the internet perspective for me as a, just stepping into this world. There's some aspect
to which you have a responsibility. I hate that word. You have an opportunity. I wish you guys
would kind of be the beacon of like forgiveness and friendship and like camaraderie and that kind
of stuff. Yeah, I agree. And even if we disagree, it would be really good content for us to argue.
Shit talk, like friends shit talk versus not, like the fact that you guys don't talk to each other.
Like I would love for you to shit talk publicly with the camaraderie always there. Like there's
love in the beginning, love in the end, but you beat the shit out of each other in the middle.
And that's what live streaming is for, the political discourses. That's great political
discourse versus I think what underlines some jealousy and so on. You get this many followers.
I just want to make sure you're clear to your audience. Everybody has to your audience.
I'm sure you have flaws and I'm just not in this dynamic. Hard to find, you know, because I'm,
your only flaws, you're too modest. Yeah. So why did you guys split up? Because I would love it
honestly. Just let me just put that idea out there for you guys to make up. Yeah, it's out there,
of course, as everybody talks, me, Vash and Hasan, it's crazy that like the three largest like
political debate left leading people online, like can't do any type of content or collaboration
at all. It's so stupid. Yeah. What was the reason you guys split up? The Kamala Harris?
So Hasan's entry into kind of like the Twitch political debate world was in, I think 2018,
I think he did a debate with Charlie Kirk and he reached out to me to kind of like review that
debate to like go on, to go over it on stream. And he came on, we went over it and then we kind
of friendship developed. We hung out in real life. I think when I came to LA, I think I saw
it on his couch, we played with his dog, we were like kind of friends. And as time went on, and
then he was a little bit more, he was farther left than he led on. So like I was a social Democrat,
he was a social Democrat. But back in those days, like 2018, when people said they were a social
Democrat, they really met socialists, but they just didn't want to say it. So he was farther
left than me. And we had a lot of deep divides in our approach to politics. Whereas like I was
very much like a first principles, this is my whole political position. And he was very much kind
of like a, this is like the political ideology I'm involved in. And this is kind of like the
field that I kind of like navigate in. So there were a couple instances where these divides would
be laid very bare. One was when it was either him or the young Turks, I think it was him.
There was a shooting in a neighborhood where a very young black child gets killed by a white
shooter. And they did a video about like hate crimes and how hate crimes are on the rise
between races and white people are evil and blah, blah, blah. Not that, but like white people,
community hate crimes against black people. And I remember saying to him, I was like,
hey, we don't have all the data yet for this. It feels really bad to make videos about this
beforehand, because it's the same type of shit that happens at airports. Is there a thing going
on? Was it a brown person? Are they Muslim? It's Islamic extremism. We see this played out so many
times in recent history, probably not a good idea to jump to conclusions. And he's like, well,
no, you don't understand, like it's not that big a deal, whatever. And obviously, as the story goes,
tale as old as time, the data comes out, it was just an errant shot. There was like gang violence,
shot goes out of nowhere, hits a kid in the car. It wasn't like a hate crime. The guy was trying to
kill a kid. But yeah, we basically, we bump up against a few kind of political disagreements like
this. And an annoying thing is happening in my community where Hassan is like the serious political
figure because he's from the young Turks. And I'm just kind of like, I do politics, but I also
game. And anytime I criticize Hassan, people like destiny, you need to be more respectful. He does
this full time. If you're going to bring criticisms, you need to be like really well read and researched
because he's got a, you know, more serious, whatever, which I thought was ridiculous.
So by the way, if people don't know, he worked at the young Turks, which is
like the largest left-leaning YouTube channel probably, or at least at the time. Yeah.
So finally, he did a video on, we skip ahead to some more minor disagreements. He does a video on
Kamala Harris. It's called the Kamala Harris. And it's like seven or eight horrible things about
Kamala Harris. And I'm like, okay, I know at least one or two of these things are not fully accurate.
So I'm going to do all the research. I'm going to have all the sources and we're going to have a
long conversation about it so that now when I provide criticism to him, it's not going to be
like this horrible, like just me saying something flippantly or whatever, it's going to be like
substantial criticism. So I was on a plane ride, JFK to Orlando, whatever, flying to Sweden to visit
my wife. And on the plane, I review all of the video, all the data, do all the research and I
write everything. I'm just like, okay, I get to my, my wife's dad's house and I'm at the table,
we're having a conversation like, hey, we should talk about the Kamala Harris stuff. And he's like,
okay, well, let's do it. And we go over it and I'll leave to the audience to watch the video.
Enough people have said this. I feel pretty common to say this. I was pretty reasonable,
pretty measured, pretty calm the whole time. And I think he started to get increasingly irritated
that I was levying like more and more serious criticisms at like the quality of work that he
did. Probably because he felt a little bit intimidated, I think by my willingness to like
dive through political stuff, there'd been a couple of awkward blobs where like on,
there was like a show called the Raj Royale, where sometimes politics would come up and
Hassan would kind of try to explain something. And there was another person one time on the
show that made the joke was like, instead of Hassan taking 10 minutes to explain this
condesity, just come here and explain it in 30 seconds. And he like exploded that he got so
fucking mad at that. So yeah, I think that when I made that kind of call out or critique of him
over the Kamala Harris stuff, he's probably feeling like increasingly irritated, threatened,
agitated. And then that's kind of what began the huge split from ours.
So you don't think you were a dick at all? I don't think so in that conversation,
especially given that like, at that point, because this is still 2018 or 20, this might be 2019,
I'm still known at that point as being very aggressive towards conservatives or all writers.
Yeah. So and with lefties is what I call them. I think I'm being like very gentle,
like my conversation with conservatives is like, you're so dumb. Like that's how I'm
like doing it. So like with him, I'm like, well, don't you think that like this is like a little
bit of like an inconsistent presentation of how like I feel gonna be nice. But I always leave
to the audience so they can go and watch that Kamala Harris video, Destiny Hassan, if they
think that I was being a dick or not. But a lot of people watch and said I was being pretty gentle.
Well, let me say as a new fan of this space, I hope you guys make up and I hope you guys fight it
out in the space of discourse and ideas. Me too. And also with empathy, understanding what the
strength of the other person is, what their buttons are. And, you know, there's like an
unspoken rule that you don't press the buttons that you don't need to, unless you're doing it
mutually and it's fun because, you know, it's fun to piece each other off. So that's kind of
like what friends do. You don't cross a certain line. But then other than that, you fight it out.
Okay, let's step back. One other super interesting aspect of your worldview is your big supporter
of Biden. Can you explain what you love about Biden? Do you love Biden more than Sean Carroll
or less? Sean Carroll is just like in another world of admiration. I feel like I'm culturally
appropriating you by saying gotcha now. But it's so convenient. It's an easy word. You just, I know
we're on the same wavelength. Okay, we're synchronizing. That's good. I mean, it is really
interesting because even people that support Biden usually don't say they love sort of,
they don't support it strongly, you know? Ideologically, philosophically, the reason
why I like Biden is because he's really committed to this bringing the left and right together,
which is something we so desperately need in the country. And his, you know, statements over and over
again of like, I'm not the Democrat president or the Republican president. I'm the president of
the United States. His desire to bring Republicans together to work on things like the infrastructure
bill, that's so incredibly needed. And I have a huge amount of respect and admiration for him
for trying to push through on that message. Do you think then it's unfortunate that he made
that comment about MAGA? MAGA Republicans? Yeah. I mean, I figured what the comment was,
but it's MAGA Republicans are not good people kind of there. I watched the full video and
he's right. There is this toxic aspect. And it's hard to call out because they're always going to
spend like, oh, he hits our Republicans. He's not. If you watch the quote, he's very specifically
calling out like this group of people that think that the election was fraudulent.
Is it clear? That's what he meant by... We can bring it up.
All right. This is... Oh, no. Uh-oh. Did I remember watching it on stream? It was like,
if you said it, yeah, that's bad. You can probably like YouTube MAGA Republicans Biden.
But like, it feels like it's pretty clear he's talking about the people that are like election
denying. Too much of what's happening in our country today is not normal. Donald Trump and the MAGA
Republicans represented extremism that threatens the very foundations of our Republic.
Now I want to be very clear, very clear up front. Not every Republican,
not even the majority of Republicans are MAGA Republicans. Not every Republican embraces
their extreme ideology. I know because I've been able to work with these mainstream Republicans.
But there's no question that the Republican Party today is dominated, driven, and intimidated
by Donald Trump and the MAGA Republicans. And that is a threat to this country.
I disagree with that, man. He didn't clearly say extremist ideology. He didn't say the
people that doubt the validity of the election. I mean, that's Donald Trump.
No, but there's... That's all the candidates that Donald Trump is supporting. How many,
what is it like, 40, 50, how many candidates right now that are MAGA candidates are election
Democrats? No, but there's 80 million or whatever people voted for Donald Trump.
You could say that's the MAGA Republicans. So to me, it sounded like he was referring to
not even the majority. I mean, that's one nice helpful clarifying statement. But basically,
there's the mainstream Republicans and then there's those that voted for Donald Trump.
That's the way I heard it. Okay.
And so maybe you should have done a better job at clarifying, but...
Yeah, I feel like there's a clear, there is a huge problem with this group of Americans.
I think the election is stolen. I feel like that's what he's trying to call.
No matter if that's what he meant, even flirting with that line is not a person who's bringing
people together. I feel like the extending a hand to the most... I've worked with Republicans in
Congress, not even a majority of Republicans are like this. No, but why say not the majority of
Republicans that like to say, we're one country. We believe the same thing. So focus on the uniting
part versus saying... Maybe he does before and after. That was 50 seconds, okay.
The point is you never say something like that. Listen, you've spoken about the Bosnian speech,
which is your favorite of his. I went back to it and listened to it.
Before I move to that, just on this, it's really hard for him to call out that group of election
deniers, I think, without it always feeling like... Well, why call them out?
Because it's arguably one of the most destructive forces that exist in this country today.
Did it destroy anything? They were trying to.
Did it though? It didn't, did it?
So does that mean we don't call it out? We wait till next time?
Because calling it out is giving fuel to the division. The people that doubted the validity
of the election, that's anger, that's frustration with the other side. You heal that as opposed to
saying all those people that believed that at any time are idiots. They're un-American.
I mean, they don't think the election was real. I don't know if Biden has the
ears of these people at all. I don't know what he can do for...
There's people that believe the same thing in 2016 with the Russian hacking, right?
There's this... Hold on. Yes.
That is a super not fair comparison. There were definitely the mainstream Democrat opinion
was that Russian intrusion in terms of social media and stuff happened, but there was never
a claim that the election was stolen. Or at least I don't know of any mainstream Democrat
that supported that. Donald Trump is not just saying there was interference and blah, blah,
blah, blah. Donald Trump is literally saying the election was literally stolen, that ballot boxes
were hidden, that vote tallies were manipulated. I think the claim is there's a huge gulf of
difference in the two. You can attack Donald Trump for that.
I believe it's not the words of a uniter to attack people that believe that.
You could argue maybe it's okay, but especially not being super clear about that,
about who you're referring to when you say MAGA Republicans, because MAGA is a hat
and a slogan that refers to whatever the number is, 70 million people who voted for Donald Trump.
Of all the Republicans that consider themselves MAGA Republicans, what percentage of them do
you think believe the election was stolen? I feel like that number is probably more than 70%.
What's a MAGA Republican? Maybe I'm not familiar...
Like a Trump supporting Republican, a MAGA Republican. They're there for Trump.
What's the difference between somebody that voted for Trump and a MAGA Republican?
My mom is a MAGA Republican. If Trump ran independently and DeSantis ran under the
Republican ticket, my mom would vote for Trump. She'll follow him to the end of the earth. That's
like a MAGA Republican. I think it's easy to mistake that distinction in these kinds of
political speeches. As to me, anybody who voted for Trump can easily in the context of the speech
be interpreted as a MAGA Republican. I understand what you're saying. Maybe you
could have been more clear, but I think in listening to that, I think it's pretty obvious who
he's talking about, but I guess if you have an emotional response to it, I can understand
the emotional response. I don't have an emotional response. I just don't like... I think I'm with
what is it? Michelle Obama, they go low, we go high. Meaning like, to me, a uniter doesn't
participate in derision. Sure, a uniter might not, but a leader has to be able to accurately
assess the situation before him and make people aware of what's going on. You mean all the
impeachment trials, all the censoring from social media, all of that didn't do the job?
That's not his job. I don't know about censoring. That mechanism, his job is to inspire a nation
to unite a nation. How can he do that when half the people don't believe that he was even legitimately
elected? I think he's done a good job at working on legislation and doing stuff that hopefully
benefits all Americans, but I think it's important to recognize that there is a contingent of
Americans that don't even believe that this is really crazy. There are plenty of people that
recognize that and are fighting that and are constantly screaming that from the rooftops.
His job is to be the inspiring figure that makes the majority of Americans be proud for him to
be a president of the nation they love. That's what the uniting aspect is. You remind people
that we are one and we love this country. We love the ideas that it represents.
He does that in other parts of that speech. It's like a 20-minute speech, isn't it?
But that's a fuck-up. You just don't participate in that division. Anyway, I understand. I just
wanted to push back on the saying one of his strengths is that he's uniting. But yes, that
is an ideal. That is a goal, is a great one, and he is one that espoused that goal for a long time.
Do you think, what else? From policy perspective and so on.
I thought the way he's handled Ukraine and everything thus far has been almost perfect.
I think he did a really good job at the political maneuvering and bringing other
countries into the fold at establishing clearly what our mission was in relation to Ukraine.
I thought he did a good job there. I admire him for pulling out of Afghanistan. Even it was a
little bit rough around the edges. We got out and we're gone. No American lives are lost.
The domestic policy, he's passed more major legislation than I think anybody thought possible.
The green energy stuff with the last bill, the infrastructure bill, a lot of the coronavirus
relief I thought was really good, especially the expansion of the child tax credit.
So from a policy perspective, foreign and domestic, I think he's been successful.
Rhetorically, I think he's generally been above board in terms of not attacking people,
being too divisive. He's trying to bring people together and work on them.
What do you think about the popular in the media criticism of his mental decline?
Do you think he's experiencing mental decline? He's an old guy.
But do you think, I mean, yeah, maybe a little bit, but he's still doing a good job.
Not from a speech perspective, you mean from a policy perspective?
Yeah, I'm analyzing it as a job. Yeah, from a speech perspective, maybe not the greatest,
but yeah, I mean, he's definitely, what is he, like 80, 81? How old is he?
I lose track after so many years. But you did say that he's probably going to run in 2024
and he's probably going to win. Did I say that? That he's probably going to win? No way did I
say that? He's probably going to run. Who knows who will win? But I think,
I feel like the incumbent advantage is so strong. You're really going to throw that away.
Like, I think it's been like one or two times in history in the US, right, where like,
the non-incumbent, the parties put somebody else up.
Yeah, I mean, the concern is like the, just the age and the mental decline, just the
wear and tear of the campaign, all of that kind of stuff, all the speech you have to make,
the debates and all that kind of stuff. Yeah, I guess we'll see what happens.
What? The least excited, I mean, two years from now is a long time. And his current mental state,
yeah, he could run and do it. He could do a passable job in two years. Man, I don't know.
I've seen videos of Bill Clinton recently, he's looking pretty rough. You know,
if Biden is looking a lot more rough, worse for wearing two years, then maybe they actually
do have to dig out another person for running. Who knows?
What do you think about Trump when he won in 2016, I think is when you came to fruition,
politically speaking. So what do you think his winning the 2016 election represents?
So for me, Trump, the reason why I got into politics was Trump was like this new
epistemic force in American politics that you'd kind of have to flirt with facts before,
even if you wanted to be nonfactual. He super didn't care. Lying was like a first language to him,
just like in speaking in terms of the way that he used language to just say to you what he felt
like you needed to hear, to support him and not care at all about what is going on about,
yeah, that's what Trump represented to me in terms of things that I cared about. He also
represents a lot more, obviously, that there was this undercurrent of American opinion that a lot
of people didn't know still existed, and it did, he got elected, that the Overton window was
misidentified by even a large amount of the Republican Party, that populism was a lot more
popular than a lot of people figured, you know, yeah, there's a lot that I guess he represented.
Do you think Trump should have been banned from Twitter? Can you make the case foreign against
it? So you're a big supporter of free speech. Yeah, so the case in favor of-
Do you think he should be brought back as Elon-
Yeah, because if he gets brought back, there's a higher chance that I'll be brought back,
so I'm supporting that all the way. Thank you, Elon. Unban my account.
So because you called me weak spine, I'm gonna have to message Elon.
Okay, at Omni Destiny, it was a verified Twitter account.
Omni Destiny. No, no, I'm just kidding.
Why'd you get banned from Twitter, Destiny?
I don't know.
I'll add that to Elon. I saw that there was a screenshot of you
referring to the rape of somebody.
Okay, that was on an older Twitter account, and that was a bad tweet.
You have multiple Twitter accounts, so you're trying to go around the bands that you keep getting.
Okay, hold on. You're slandering me a lot right now, okay?
Let's get the facts straight, okay? And I don't even remember why my first time I got banned,
but it was a wild account. I tweeted some wildly inappropriate things.
You regret?
I don't like that word. I'm gonna give the answer to most people.
They're just like, I don't regret it because I learned a lot,
so I'm glad I had the bad experiences that I did.
Why don't you like the word regret?
I think if we look at where we are, how do you feel about determinism?
I believe in hard, the hardest of determinism. That's who I am.
Okay, so who I am today is the culmination of everything that's occurred in the past.
I believe you, speaking about regret is a nice way to communicate that in this deterministic
world, you've analyzed the acts of the past, and you're no longer that person.
Yeah, of course, for sure.
That's what regret usually means.
Okay, thanks for giving me the human explanation. Okay, true.
So in that sense, there's a lot of things I've done that I regret.
Oh, you're, what are you? You're not human, you're a bot.
NPC is my preferred term.
Okay, all right.
I wish I would have been smart enough at the time to not have to have had made those mistakes.
Okay.
There you go.
Good job.
But yeah, obviously really dumb, really crazy off the wall tweets,
but that account got banned, but then I made another account called,
I can't believe I'm giving you a history-made Twitter account.
So I made another account called OmniDestiny.
It's an honor.
And that was my, I got verified, I was cool, they let me have that account
because originally they banned it and I said appeal and I was like,
oh, let me have one more.
And the back then Twitter was cool and they're like, okay, go for it.
And that account lasts for a long time.
And I don't actually know 100% why that account got banned.
I believe that the tweet that showed up in the final, I got banned for hate speech.
And it was because I was, there was a picture that I tweeted
with three different alt writers that are kind of like neo-Nazi people.
And they were all like mixed race people.
And I said, like the new alt right looks like a Disney channel original movie
in terms of racial composition.
And somehow they got flagged for instigating violence against minorities, I think.
And I think that's the tweet that got me banned
because I think that's what showed up in the final report.
But I don't know, maybe there were other reasons
because nobody ever communicates, but ever since that account went under,
it's just been ban evading ever since.
So.
Oh, ban evading ever since.
So all my new accounts that have been banned just get banned
because they finally figured out it's me and then they ban evade.
There's like one dude at Twitter HQ who's like constantly looking for my new accounts
and they get me.
Yeah.
Anyway, yeah.
So post Trump world.
Do you think, okay, I mean this.
Oh, should he be banned?
Oh, you asked me to make both cases.
Should he be banned?
I mean, damn, dude, when you're tweeting out shit
that's arguably leading stuff like January 6th, I can understand why.
Because it's like, what else is this wild dude going to tweet out?
Like, is he going to start instigating other violent events?
So I'm sympathetic towards the like, okay.
Well, he can't just be here saying stuff like this.
That's insane.
We're going to ban him.
I'm sympathetic.
Because it's instigating.
Yeah, you're instigating.
Physical violence in the physical world.
Yeah.
Like if I would tweet stuff like that, I would get banned probably.
On the flip side, this is the president of the United States.
It seems like he's like doing presidential decree by social media sometimes.
Like is it really right that one public or private, I should say,
one private company can like erase the president of the United States words from
the eyes of a lot of Americans that are using these social media feeds.
And one big one, which I for sure am against, is the permanent ban.
Yeah, I don't like that.
I hate that.
Even in my community, if somebody comes back over like a year, like, I mean-
Did you just compare yourself to the president of the United States?
No, I compare myself to Twitter banning the president of the United States.
Let me put it this way.
If I ban Donald Trump in my chat room, I don't ban him in a year.
A year?
Yeah.
What's the process for unbanning Donald Trump?
What would he have to do?
Usually people send me an email and they're like,
listen, I did this stuff.
I'm sorry, I was dumb.
I'll give them another chance.
But a year, what if they send an email a month later?
Usually I'll unban him.
That's usually my problem.
I ban pretty quickly in my community, but if you ever ask-
You're big, softy.
Yeah, I usually let him back.
I'm very-
Well, because I used to be the worst type of internet person,
and I think I'm a little bit better than I used to be.
So-
Now that you're older.
Yeah, now that I've matured.
Yeah, of course.
Age bestows a wisdom that just can't be gotten any other way.
What's your sense in general?
Is there something interesting you could say about your view on free speech?
It seems like one of those terms, it's also overused
to mean a lot of different things.
What does it mean to you?
If you have a democratic style of governance,
you are entrusting people with one of the most awesome
and radical of responsibilities.
And that's saying that you're going to pick the people
that are going to make some of the hardest decisions
in all of human history.
If you're going to trust people to vote correctly,
you have to be able to trust them,
have open and honest dialogue with each other.
Whether that's Nazis or KKK people or whoever talking,
you have to believe that your people are going to be able to rise above
and make the correct determinations
when they hear these types of speeches.
And if you're so worried that somebody's going to hear
a certain political figure
and they're going to be completely radicalized instantly,
then what that tells me is that you don't have enough faith in humans
for democracy to be a viable institution,
which is fine.
You can be anti-democratic,
but I don't think you can be pro-democracy and anti-free speech.
Within reason.
So what's the within reason?
So-
I mean, you can't post like Child porn or something on Twitter
where people try to get you on that stuff
or like direct calls to violence or probably not.
You shouldn't be tweeting out like,
we're going to meet up tomorrow and go bomb, blah, blah, blah.
Probably not.
So do you think it's okay to allow racism and anti-Semitism and hate speech?
Hate speech, yes, because that can be very broadly defined.
I can understand there being some basic rules of like no slurs on like a platform
that gets into like acceptable forms of moderation
or like excessive harassment and bullying, I can understand.
But past that, when the moderation becomes ideological,
I get a little bit nervous because, you know, for,
there's a whole other-
Yeah, there's, of course, it's all a gray area,
but when it feels like ideology has seeped into the censorship.
Not good.
Yeah.
Which it's so fascinating to think,
especially now that Elon bought Twitter,
how do you engineer a system that prevents ideology from seeping in
and nevertheless is able to create a platform that has healthy conversations?
Because if you have one guy who's just screaming nonsense, nonstop,
it has this effect where the quiet voices at the back of the room are silenced.
Yeah.
So like that's what you usually don't talk about.
Like if you let one annoying loud person in,
that's actually censoring the voice of a lot of people
that would like to speak, but they don't get a chance.
That's one of the things, especially around like trans discourse,
I have to constantly do that like reminder for my audiences.
So like when I'm dealing with these types of people on the internet,
a lot of them might seem really crazy.
A lot of these types of people might seem insane,
but like in the real world, outside of like the crazy Twitter activist world,
like the vast majority of people you're meeting from LGBT communities
are like the coolest, normalist people.
All they want us to like write to live their life in the way they want to
and to be like unobstructed and like, yeah.
But people will get this impression of like an online activist,
like a vegan or LGBT person or whatever.
And then they think that every single person in real life is like that.
And it's a really negative stereotype.
And then even the other people in that group.
Oh, is Malina coming over?
Oh yeah, actually, I don't know if that's her.
Okay, Malina just joined us.
What were we talking about?
Was it interesting?
You were saying that you were going to talk to Elon about getting at Omni Destiny,
the verified Twitter account on band.
I said, that sounds like a lot.
That's so gracious of you.
I can't even believe you would do that for me.
And then you admitted that you tried to evade the band multiple times,
which I'm sure would be very looked upon.
You know, I heard that in Norway, in their prison system,
they don't actually punish you for trying to escape jail
because that's like the natural human thing to do.
Hug you?
What are they doing?
I don't know, but they don't punish you.
Because of course you're trying to be free.
That's all I'm trying to be on Twitter.
I'm just trying to be free.
Oh, that's the natural humanistic.
Yeah, that's the natural human course, is to ban even.
You're not a destructive force.
No, I'm a force, I'm a force for good.
That's why all my accounts only get banned for banning and banning.
I don't get banned for doing bad things.
And I'm a progressive shill.
I'm like far left.
I love like progressive causes.
This is what you criticize us on for being.
I show them from a place of first principles,
not from a mindless AI echoing kind of thing, you know.
Okay, so you're a free thinking bot.
Yeah, exactly.
All right, cool.
Well, I'm sure we'll return to some politics.
That was beautiful.
William, can you tell us about yourself?
You're also a fellow streamer.
Yes, I stream and I started streaming because I am at him,
basically, kind of, but I don't do the politics.
I do like travels or talk about relationships,
talk to my audience, basically.
You're from that part of the world, right, Sweden?
Yeah, exactly.
So did you escape from prison and they didn't?
That was Norway.
You just mentioned Norway.
That's different.
I actually really, I've been to Sweden a bunch of times.
I love it.
There's a tech sector there that's really like flourishing.
Where did you go?
Which city?
I went to Stockholm.
I think I gave a few lectures there.
There's a vibrant tech sector in school and people are super nice.
Yeah, we're friendly.
We're not like very deep.
Like we don't really have much deep conversation.
It's like a meta conversation.
Oh, there's not many intellectuals that come from Sweden.
We don't really speak very highly of ourselves.
We're kind of like just chill all the time.
We don't make a scene.
We don't, we're just like talking, you know.
Do you know what the name for that is?
There's a specific name for it.
Jantelagen.
Yeah, Jantelagen, yeah.
Oh, there's a philosophy behind it.
When you're part of like Sweden or Norway,
you don't talk too highly of yourself
because it's seen as kind of like rude.
Like think of like America as the exact opposite.
You'd even really want to like,
you don't want to make yourself into a victim too much.
You don't want to be too much of anything.
You're just like sticking to the, to the group
to make big scene about yourself.
But that said, you came here and you were,
you put yourself in front of a camera and became a streamer.
Do you understand how weird that is for my friends in Sweden?
Do you have anxiety?
I just didn't talk about myself
and just like make a big deal about myself for hours every day.
Was that like terrifying?
Did you have anxiety about that?
No, because I don't see them.
But then I come back and I'm like, ooh.
Also, what do you feel like when you're actually streaming?
You feel like you're just alone in a room?
One-on-one type thing?
No, I see, I see Chad and I'm thinking,
oh, they're like a little fairies.
They're not really real.
They're just like out there.
I don't know what they look like.
I just see little names and they're just cute and just some colors.
So you're talking to little fairies inside your head?
Yes, I do.
Is that how you feel about Chad?
They're demons for me.
They're demons?
Okay, my kind of fairies.
Are they, so is Chad a source of stress or happiness?
Like is there a...
No, for me, that's a source of happiness.
I've been very intentional with like the construction
of my community.
So I'm really happy with where it's at.
How are you able to actually have deep political discourse
while playing a video game at the same time?
I have a really good chat room in terms of like the way
that people engage in conversations.
Like I was one of the earliest people to embrace the philosophy
of like I am in total control of what people watch me think,
that like I have a high level of responsibility
for how they conduct themselves.
And that if I conduct myself in a certain way,
I can expect a certain level of conduct from them.
And for the most part, it's like worked pretty well
for the past, you know, nine or 10 years, yeah.
What about the actual playing of the game?
Like you're able to parallelize the brain like...
Like it seems like Factory seems like a super complex game.
Yeah, I don't actually think that's possible.
I don't think multitasking for human brain is possible.
If you see me playing a game,
usually what's happening is the conversation is like,
I've had it a million times, so I'm not thinking about it.
I've automated that.
Or if the conversation is very challenging,
then if you watch me, if you really watch what's happening again,
I'm probably just running around in circles
because I have to think about the conversation.
Okay.
Because with Factory, it looks like a lot of stuff is going on.
Sometimes, yeah.
So I guess it's hard for a person who hasn't played the game
to detect that you're not actually...
Is that come off as like you're super intelligent in multitasking?
Or does it come off as like he's not interested in this conversation at all?
Yeah, there's a coolness to it.
Like when you're not paying attention,
if you're looking elsewhere, like you're checking your phone,
you're too cool for this conversation.
There's a sense like that.
Yeah.
The reality is though is if you watch,
it was easier to see in Minecraft
because in Minecraft, when there was a challenging conversation,
if you watch me play,
I'm literally just running around and jumping in circles
because I have to think about the conversation 100%.
I can't do a complicated task and think about the conversation.
Or like the people will always joke in my chat,
like, oh no, the notepad came out.
If it's a really challenging conversation,
I'll get rid of the game and I'll bring out a notepad
and I'll start writing stuff down to keep track of what's going on.
So what kind of stuff do you stream?
So advice?
You talk about...
Yeah, like either I talk to chatter, I travel around, basically.
Like have a conversation or we like go to countries.
I've been to like Italy.
I was in Italy for like one and a half months,
just like traveling around the loan, going to cities,
like having like my camera with me and like streaming for hours.
Where's the coolest place you've been to?
Ever.
It's probably New Zealand.
New Zealand?
I think so.
After it is probably going to be Italy, I think.
Because I like history and...
Also both history because New Zealand is also beautiful.
So it's both natural beauty and historical beauty.
Yeah, for sure.
I think it's just really like the Polynesian sort of culture.
I think it's very interesting.
Like the ocean people and it's just really beautiful.
People are very relaxed, chill.
They're very far away, which is interesting as well.
Because whenever they talk about politics or they talk about the world,
it feels really far away.
So where's home for you?
Is Austin home?
Did you...
Home for me.
A human being is home.
Yeah.
We travel, we've lived in a lot of places and traveled around.
So that's what you think of home is like humans.
I think so, yeah.
I mean, if they're going to be a place,
it's probably going to be like my childhood places probably.
Like my old country house or something like that.
We don't have it anymore.
But that's like home for me, I guess.
So how'd you guys meet each other?
You're currently married.
Yes.
To each other, yeah.
Yeah.
To each other.
All right, cool.
How'd you guys meet?
I was watching his YouTube stuff like 2018, I think.
Like because it was the Swedish election around that time
and I was interested in politics.
And then I think he said in one of his videos that he had an Instagram
and that he needed people to stop DMing him.
That wasn't cutie pies.
And then I messaged him and said, am I a cutie pie?
And then you're pie in like two minutes.
And then that's when I was in New Zealand.
And I guess you wanted to escape America or like LA for a little bit.
And that included New Zealand.
What were you mentally there?
Because we've talked to his timeline.
Where's 2018?
Was it 18, 19?
Where was the low point?
Or is that as that was way earlier?
Low point, carbiclaning.
That was like 2009, 2010.
Oh, okay.
2018 was probably your peak.
Every day, now was my peak.
What do you mean?
That was my peak.
Why would you say that?
No, nobody ever had missed being past their prime.
Just see.
Well, I mean, my prime is still coming out.
It was probably around the time where you were getting a lot
of lefties to your community and you were really like thinking
about that they would go too far.
Maybe.
That was, I think that was still when Hasan and Vash were both
in my community.
Exactly.
So I would say it feels like there was not really like much issues
when it come to your stuff or like your work stuff back then.
Oh, something we didn't talk about is that like there were no
politics on Twitch.
I exclusively inhabited that place for like two years
because nobody else did it because it was a really toxic
environment for politics.
So for a couple of years as it grew, I kind of grew the whole
space because it wasn't.
Nobody was doing that yet.
What did that look like?
You're having like political debates, political discourse.
Yeah, mainly like going into YouTube people to try to argue
with them or just doing politics on stream like reading stories,
researching stuff, talking about stuff.
But there's not like other people on Twitch to debate about politics
because there was no politics.
It was, yeah.
Was there a debate in the space of communism, socialism,
social democrats, kind of like this?
Are you trying to outline your own position during that time?
I think it was mainly me fighting against conservatives
because it was like Trump stuff.
And then it was coming off the back of like there was this
movement called Gamergate and there was all this anti-SJW stuff
on the internet.
And I was like the SJW, like the progressive that was fighting
on the progressive side of things.
So I think that's what I was known for.
But I was fighting with people off of Twitch
because on Twitch there weren't very many political discussions happening.
So you were holding the SJW flag to what degree do you still hold it?
Like what's the best?
What's the steelman case for SJW?
I mean like I'm still very much that SJW from 2018-2019
but the positions have moved so much farther left that
I don't know, some people might not call me that anymore.
I'm not sure.
It depends on who I'm talking to.
Because basically what is social justice?
Were you like being sensitive to the experience of others?
Yeah, being sensitive and empathetic towards the experience of others
and then trying to build a better world that like suits as many different types
of people as possible while being like aware of like their names.
Okay.
So you guys met, what's from your perspective?
Is the, did she, she, she telling lies?
Is it accurate?
No, it's pretty accurate.
It's pretty accurate.
Okay.
When did you guys actually meet?
I flew out in 2019.
19 in like in February.
Yeah.
Basically there was like weird stuff happening in LA.
I just come off of kind of a weird not kind of sort of relationship
and I just wanted to like go away for a while.
Another company reached out to me and they had like a fun streaming device
and they said they'd sponsor a trip if I went somewhere.
And I was like, oh, well, I know this person.
I know a couple of people in New Zealand.
And Malina was one of them.
It's like, I'll go to New Zealand.
New Zealand.
It'll be fun.
And yeah, I did that for two weeks.
Do you guys believe in love?
I feel like you lack the gotcha got us into this.
I'm not sure to the degree to which you have human emotions.
I have quite a few.
From your perspective, when did you, when did you fall in love with Malina?
When you fall in love with Malima.
Malima.
The minute I saw her.
I don't know.
We, our first two weeks together were a lot of fun.
We had a lot of chemistry in person.
I was kind of shocked that I wasn't thinking about it
because it was like, we spent like a week together and you said,
I really want to tell you something.
And you were like, you were like stalling that for the longest time.
I think she was, oh, he said that like, I love you.
No, he basically just said like,
I really like you and it never really happens.
That's what he said.
And I was like, oh, and I thought, hey, I thought.
So let's still run.
We said Trump getting banned from Twitter.
Is that what we were talking about before?
Oh yeah.
Hey, you agreed to me coming on here.
Of course I'm going to be doing those to you.
How long, so how long did that take?
Two weeks, you said?
That took like a week.
No, I don't know.
I think it was just like.
Thing is, my mind process is like information so quickly.
Two weeks to somebody like you is actually like years for me.
So.
Oh, like me.
Yeah.
There was like a lot of like factorial type of strategic thinking.
Yeah, going on.
I was seeing like all the events, like Dr. Strange or whatever
and the Avengers when he's like seeing into all the future.
Oh, so when you saw me, you just saw the future.
Yeah, I was looking at all of them, yeah.
So you're doing like some game theoretic simulation
of all the possible outcomes?
Yeah, exactly.
Okay.
But no, yeah, it was probably pretty soon I realized
that we had a lot of chemistry.
I think before I left after my two weeks there,
I was like, we need to make sure you got like a ticket
to come visit me in the United States
because it'll be fun and everything.
And then.
I kind of decided that last minute too.
It was like really like five hours before your flight back.
We kind of realized because it was kind of like men
is just like a one type thing.
And then that was it.
But we're like, oh, no, this is a lot of fun.
We should probably hang out again.
Oh, so you realized you would miss each other.
Yeah, yeah.
This was one time thing.
The melancholy side of love.
Okay, when did you fall in love with Stephen?
I thought he like hated me.
I don't know.
I thought not hated me.
She still thinks I hated her.
But no, no, I remember like what he said
that he really liked me.
I was kind of a little shocked about that because I don't know.
It was a lot of like random things happening in New Zealand.
It was a lot of fun, but it was definitely like
very interesting like things that happened.
Because I was like around a lot of other people as well.
So I thought he might have had like a really bad time.
But when he said that I was thinking about it more
and then we spent like more time together
like a week after that.
And then I felt like that was more like real.
And I think when he was about to leave,
I kind of realized like, no, I really like him.
Do you guys ever say love to each other?
Like I love you?
Yeah, of course.
Yeah.
Okay, right.
I wasn't sure.
Why would you ask that?
What has he said before?
Because I haven't, I don't think I've heard you speak.
The only time I've heard you talk about love is when you're like
criticizing the Red Pill community,
saying they don't ever talk about love in relationships.
Almost all the time I'm giving criticism to people,
like I said, I'm kind of stepping in.
I'm very disconnected from my own emotional experience
because I'm trying to talk with them there.
So it's pretty rare that I'll talk about my own.
What is your own emotional experience exactly?
Highly blunted, I guess.
There's a lot.
Okay.
What does that mean?
I mean, what's the, what's deep in there?
Are you, are you, is this just who you are genetically
or are you running for something?
I think I have a pretty good understanding of myself.
A lot of people make that accusation of me,
but I don't think I am.
Okay.
This is just who you are.
It's just who I am, yeah.
Okay.
There's not childhood stuff like trauma.
It's all sorted and done.
You figured it all out?
Yeah.
In your old age?
As I grow, every year I figure out more and more.
He did mention, I think I heard this somewhere,
that this is a source of fights for the two of you, the age thing.
I felt the ageism throughout this whole conversation.
He's basically, he's saying that he gambles like with time.
He's just like, I think she will be good later.
And then just like,
It's like an investment.
Yeah.
It's like what he's doing.
And when this treasury bond matures,
I'm going to be able to cash out for a good.
What do you think so far?
Is the stock's growing up or?
It's tumultuous.
What's that mean?
It's like Bitcoin.
Oh my God.
Like Bitcoin, crypto mill.
All right.
If you guys don't mind,
one interesting aspect of your relationship
is you're in an open relationship.
What's that like?
From a game theoretic simulation perspective,
what went into that calculation?
And like, how does that?
Like how that started or?
Yeah.
How did that start?
Sure.
The only relationships I've ever done
has been open relationships since I was like in high school
because I didn't really understand
like why wouldn't you be able to like
do other things with other people,
but then just like have your main partner basically.
So what is an open relationship?
Generally speaking,
that means you have one main partner?
Not a monogamous relationship.
Like you're somehow allowed like in different ways.
You can see other people sexually.
Sexually.
But like there's one main station.
It doesn't have to be there for some people,
but like I think it's probably easier
and we probably don't really have time
or the energy for like more than
like one person to like really like.
What about like emotional?
It's really complicated.
There's a lot of complicated stuff going on
under the hood there.
Yeah.
I think broadly speaking,
you've got like polyamorous relationships
and you've got like open relationships
where polyamorous is like,
oh, I've got like three different girlfriends
and we all hang out or sometimes even live together
or three boyfriends or whatever.
And then you've got like open relationships
which is like, oh, you know, like,
you can basically hook up with other people
and then you've got like your main relationship
and that's it.
I think ours is probably somewhere in the middle of that
to where like we've got like long-term friends,
some of them we hook up with
and that's kind of how we, yeah.
It's a delicate dance that explodes
every six months on itself.
So it does explode, you guys fight over?
We fight over some things, yeah.
It things happen, yeah.
I think it's mostly because a lot of people can handle it
and they, they agree to something
and then they realize that we're way too cool
and then they get really obsessed
and they think that they can like get in there
and then it gets really dramatic.
Have you figured it out?
I feel like we figure out things more and more
like when it comes to like,
what's a good person for us to hang out
and what's not a good person for us to hang out with
or like, I probably have more opinions
than like who he hangs out with
because he likes the fucking psychos.
Yeah, so you like this or not?
He likes the not like the crazy ones,
like the baby trap sort of women.
That's the ones and I don't like that
because that affects me.
That affects your game theory at a calculation.
Yeah, obviously, yeah.
Right, you like to surround yourself
like in general you've talked about with crazy people.
I say crazy and I really shouldn't.
It's a humorous way.
It's like, yeah.
They're very unstable.
Very, can be unstable,
but people that are very unique.
Like when I meet this person, that's like.
Not boring.
Yeah, not boring, yeah.
And you said that you're progressively becoming
not boring yourself.
No, I think I'm pretty stable.
I don't love them affect me much, but.
So you don't think they affect your.
No, if I've said that, I said a joke.
And I think I've like, I've got my stuff
like really well figured out.
It's what allows me to engage with people
like this so easily because I can engage.
I can make them feel seen and heard.
And then if it gets insane, I can cut off
and I can be chill.
Like very few things affect me in the long term.
Do you guys experience jealousy?
Usually like whenever I feel like he's not spending
the like the amount of time that I'm asking for
and he spends it on his video games or his stream
or like he sees someone else like more than
he sees me or something like that.
That would like not be good
because then it affects like our relationship.
Do you have a good sense of like, is it literally time
or is it the energy put into the.
It's probably like if like if he's with me
that like the attention in the time
like when he hangs out with me
and then there's also probably the time.
So if I feel like something else is distracting too much
like it could be work or it could be a friend
or it could be anything.
Like if I feel like it starts to take away from like me
then I'm having an issue with it.
I don't think he really cares much.
I guess the only jealousy you experience is probably
when you feel like if I get upset about him seeing someone too much
and then I go see someone more
and then he's like why can I go see my friend more
like as much as you.
So like that's the sort of like thing
that we're trying to navigate on I guess.
I think we are like diametrically opposed sometimes
in terms of how we view like engagement with people
or engagement with the world sometimes.
So like on her end of the spectrum
like a perfect week for her might be like being in a cabin
watching like fireflies at night
going hiking every morning
going swimming at the beach
because it's like you're taking in like the grandeur of nature
you're like connected with yourself
you're like very at peace
everything is like chill and cool
there's the wind the feeling of nature everything
that's like her peak living experience.
I like being present.
Yeah and like my peak experiences are like
people trying to destroy my life
like the challenge of like navigating
a really complicated discussion
like you know several different dramatic events
unfolding that might end my career
like these things are like very
I like the stress and the action
and the entertainment
and everything's like very cool for me.
So when we're together
she generally wants me to be like more chill
but if I don't feel like I'm being like
stimulated a lot
then it's easy for like my mind to wonder
to wonder somewhere else or yeah
that's kind of the issue.
We have a very different way of like engaging with the world.
So how can you find happiness and stillness?
I feel like if we're just like aware of it
and we're trying our best
like whenever we like we're supposed to do this one thing
so let's say that we want to go to New York
and I'm like we should just like go out
and do this one specific thing
we try to find something that he enjoys doing
like now that we're in Texas we can go shooting
or do something fun that he enjoys
then we can do it.
And then I think like
just like for me also to be aware
that like when he spends a lot of time on crazy people
it's not because he like loves them
or wants to be with them
it's just because he likes being
like having his life destroyed.
Like you said
which I don't really do
this is a completely different thing.
So like for me to like understand more
like how he's thinking
because it's so different from mine
and for him to understand
how I'm thinking about things
and like what I prioritize in my life
I think that's like how we navigate
but I think it's good
I think the differences can be good
like when we're finding a way.
Yeah.
Well I think you're relatable.
I'm more of a human.
No I'm definitely very difficult to get along with
like I always tell people that
that like if you're dating me
for like more than a few years
like you get like an award for that.
It's like a war zone that you've survived.
Absolutely.
You're like a veteran you get medals and stuff
and it's always like I think
there's probably been like six different
I don't think she says it anymore
but there are like six different times
in our relationship where she's like
is it always like this?
Is this actually right?
Yeah.
And like every next year it's like
You're lying in the beginning of about like
you were lying about that.
Well it got more and more.
You were like no it's just like right now
I'm having a huge argument online
about seeing the end word in private
and it's just going to be like this
and I'm going to be streaming 24 hours a day
and I'm like we're like
when are you going to come to bed?
It's been a week.
I did playing League come into this.
A little bit but I'm clean.
I'm clean of League like six months right now.
What do you hate about League of Legends?
I never got.
The humans.
Well speaking of which
I my participation in League
involved on the robot side.
Good.
Because that's an improvement.
Because both the Starcraft 2
and and League of Legends
because OpenAI and DeepMind
both participated in creating bots
and those.
I was a professional Starcraft 2 player
so I remember when the AI started to play
it's interesting the types of restrictions
that you would have to put on like a
gaming robot to make it like functional
and not totally unfair to the other side.
Yeah to make it human like.
Yeah was that interesting to you
to see AI be able to play those video games?
I think in some ways
people think things are more complicated
than they actually are
and I think video games is one of those things
are really oh my god
there's like a million possibilities
at every second and who knows
and it's like no
there's like three or four things
going at any point in time
and I'm willing to bet that like
an AI could probably solve some of these
games like pretty easily
especially if there are no constraints
on how they can learn.
Yeah can I talk to you about relationships?
Yeah you already have so.
Yeah I know but more generally speaking
we didn't get a chance to talk about
the the red pill community.
Oh sure.
Well first of all what is the red pill community
the manosphere in general?
I'd love to get both your opinions on this.
Sure.
I know I know you're probably not as
opinionated on that whole thing.
Do you think I am that?
Like probably not as you
like as much as you
but I do have opinions.
You do okay.
I usually don't like speak out too much
on it because I feel like
there's like a language barrier
that's why I don't really do politics
because this is my second language.
Yeah.
That's right you have to know the.
A lot of it like.
You know how to use
have to use derogatory terms
every other sentence
so they understand you right.
Exactly.
I don't know anything about that.
But you need like a good like you need
to be able to like speak really well
for people to take your seriously
I think.
And like that's a thing like if I
if I don't have like the words
and I don't have the
like I can't pronounce things correctly.
Yeah and you're a self person
searching for words looks stupid
essentially that's how people view it.
Tell me about it I have a podcast
that people listen to
and I mumble and they yeah.
Wait is here what's your first language.
Russian.
Oh okay.
But I speak both languages horribly.
I just not I'm not like
there is definitely a big disconnect
between my brain and my mouth module.
Like I'm not able to generate
the thoughts efficiently
like the things you're able to do
like to like speak like that.
I'm not it's very very tough.
Plus there's a huge amount of anxiety
and social interaction that I have
which makes speaking even harder.
Yeah yeah yeah it's tough.
I understand I mean.
Gotcha.
Makes sense.
Yeah the the gacha is both
a symbol of compassion
and derision at once.
It's I'm just letting you know
I understand what you say.
I'm just going to sit there
and stare at you.
Confirm.
No you can just say like yeah get it.
Like yeah I get it.
I get it.
Gotcha.
I got you.
Gotcha sounds.
No it's so it's so short.
I got you.
Say it's a longer sentence
but that means the same thing.
I understand you.
Yeah that's good that's like
not chills you know.
You get chills all like you understand me.
Yeah it feels good.
Yeah.
I hear you.
And like if you just like
hold the other person's hand
that's even better.
Maybe you gotta put in some emotion there
okay show that you have some.
Gotcha.
What do you think about Red Pill?
Sorry what is it first of all
for people I don't know?
Yeah the Red Pill community
obviously it's the matrix reference.
The Red Pill that you take
is when you realize
what dating standards and norms
really are in the world
that men are providers
and have to become some great thing
to hunt and attract you know
the woman who are just kind of
there floating around
looking for people
to give them the most resources
and it's like coming to a realization
of what the world of dating really is
broken away from the Hollywood
standards and the romantic stuff
that they try to sell you
and you know stories.
So there was kind of
maybe you can kind of educate me on this
but Red Pill used to be associated with
just maybe anti-establishment views
I don't know maybe
maybe Republican conservative viewpoints
would be all right.
Yeah they use Red Pill a lot
in like different communities
like when you say the Red Pill community
yeah that usually means dating.
The dating thing
but a lot of people say
oh Trump voters they're Red Pill
are you Red Pilled on like politics
or whatever people say stuff like that yeah.
Okay cool.
And then there's like the manosphere
that's all the similar type of stuff
and Andrew Tate is somebody
that represents kind of
the figurehead
of the manosphere
of like the Red Pill stuff
yeah I would say so
I'm pretty sure yeah.
Okay all right cool.
So what are some ideas
that they represent
and what do you think about them?
I think they do a good job
at speaking to disaffected young men
who feel like the rest of the world
is kind of left them behind
or isn't willing to speak to them
and they do identify
some true and real problems.
Feels like on the left
we have a really hard time
doing like self-improvement
or telling people how to better themselves.
We focus too much on
like structural or systemic issues
rather than what can an individual do
to uplift or empower themselves
and it also feels like
they do a good job
at speaking to some of the positive aspects
of masculinity
that it's okay to be like strong
and brave and a soldier
and a warrior
and provide for your family
and blah blah blah.
So I would say like those are like
positive messages
like self-improvement
and everything
that come from the Red Pill community.
What's the negative?
I think the analysis
on how men and women interact
is a way too transactional.
All of like the romanticism
and love and chemistry
is totally sucked out of it.
Everything is very like
sex-based
like how do you basically have sex
with the most amount of women possible
and that's going to make you happy.
And then I think people's motivation
sometimes are just spoken about
in such a shallow derogatory way
that I don't think
is always reflective of reality.
Like women only wants you
because you make six figures
and you're tall
and a guy only wants you
because he wants to have sex with you
and blah blah.
Like it feels like
there's a lot of that going on a lot.
Yeah and that misses
some fundamental aspect
about relationships
about meaningful relationships and so on.
I don't think I've never heard
Red Pill people ever ever
talk about like meaningful relationships.
It's always just how to get in one
or how to have sex really.
Mel, what bothers you about
some of that philosophy?
I feel like the people
that are like the Red Pill people
I feel like their solution
is something that doesn't actually work out.
Like where it works out
for some people
people that makes a lot of money
is like really successful
in that sort of way.
But it's not going to help
most men out there
so I feel like it's just like a pointless
like speech to give
to these like really lost guys
and they really do believe
that they can like
they can become successful
they can get money
and when they get all these things
they can get girls
but most of them
is not going to achieve that ever.
To get the money part
or become successful.
Just become a billionaire
you know like
and you will get all the girls
and which is true
but not everyone can do that.
So I feel like
when these guys are speaking
to these men
and there's like
we just care about these men out there
you know they need to hear this
it doesn't really help a lot of them.
And it doesn't inspire them
to develop compassion
towards the opposite sex
which is probably something required
to have money for relationship.
And also like
they seem to complain a lot about women
like only wanting men
that have money
and that's tall
and that's muscular
whatever you know
all those things
and but they complain about that
but that's like
also kind of what they're trying to
make the men try to do for themselves
so they kind of like
fall into the same sort of behavior
and it seems like
they're kind of unaware of that as well.
They're just playing a part of the game
instead of trying to find
a woman that doesn't look for those things
and that are looking for
not those things.
Yeah.
I actually would love to have
like straight up data
on people in that world
versus not in that world
how often they get laid.
Yeah.
Like literally so
I think for sure
people in that world
have fewer meaningful long-term
relationships that are fulfilling
that actually helped them succeed in life
that helped them be happy
and content and all that kind of stuff
but just even the straight up
the shallow goal of getting laid
I wonder
because it's very possible
that like just the roughness
with which they treat intellectually
women that might lead to
lower success
not higher success.
It's very adversarial
which I think is always disappointing
anything that talks about men and women
I think it's good to acknowledge differences
but when it becomes like adversarial
especially when you talk about sex
sex is something that men are getting
and it's something that women are giving
and that type of like trade-off
and the way they talk about it is like
yeah it sets people against each other
in a really toxic way I think.
How do you talk to people from that world
from the red pill world
like would you would you ever talk to
like somebody like Andrew Tate?
Oh yeah if I had the chance to
I've been on the Fresh and Fit podcast
a few times
and then I've got a friend Sneeko
who's like very red pill that stuff
if I'm trying to talk to them
usually the
it's kind of like approaching it
like a scared cat
the first thing you have to do is like
be very gentle and say like
I understand your issues
I understand your complaints
I know that you're I'm scary
because you think I'm going to say like
toxic masculinity and feminism
and all these scary words at you
so the first thing is always to recognize it
like a lot of what they talk about
there are like true aspects
to what they're talking about
that people on the left won't recognize
so I think it's good to acknowledge those things
that like men and women are kind of different
we do look for different things in general
when it comes to relationships
it's okay to say that
it's not there's nothing bad there
and then it'll usually be like
once I've got your trust
and I'm in your bubble
like let's talk about the things that you want
and maybe some of the strategies
that you're employing aren't necessarily
going to get you some of the things that you want
so for instance if you're really worried
about like shallow girls
like ruining your life
like Molina said
it's probably not best to build your entire world view
around trying to get shallow girls
that are going to ruin your life
like if your way of attracting a girl
is to go to the gym
get a whole bunch of money
and try to like flaunt your wealth
as much as possible
you're going to be attracting the very same type of women
that you're here like
decrying on your stream
I think we talked about that on the podcast
like you probably want to have a woman
that's going to be there
if you lose your job
it's still there
like that cares about the things
that's not just your job
it's more stable
and also I don't help you become a great man
or a great like grow
like I feel like a great friendship
and a partnership
like it helps you make you a better person
some of the most successful people I know
I mean they have families
and there's clearly a dynamic there
that's like that makes them
they wouldn't be that without
they're not an island yeah
yeah and the kids actually are a big part of that too
like for most people
if you're like a good parent
they make you step up somehow in life
you have to take responsibility for
getting your shit together
and excelling
in ways that
I guess the philosophy of the Red Bull
does not quite get to
that's always an interesting
I think I've asked that a couple of times
where it's like
would you let your daughter date Andrew Tate
and it's always funny to watch them
kind of like squirm around
those answers sometimes
but see if they if they don't have a daughter
like I you know I don't have a daughter
I think your whole philosophy changes
once you have a daughter
sure
but even at that like they can
they know that what they're answering
they feel a little bit weird about it
it's funny to watch them
like they even they know it's like
ah fuck you know
well they might say like
I want my daughter to date
like a high value male
to the degree that he's a high value male
yes
but like I don't think you'll feel that way
the definition of high value changes
completely for sure
certainly the stereotypical
measures of value contribute to the
calculation
but it's so much more than that
I think the chemistry of the whole thing is
is bigger
you've also mentioned about body count
you guys both have a high body count
this body count matter
or it depends
like like you said
it's low in some people's eyes
it's high in other people's eyes
does body count matter in relationships
it's the past matter
well the past matters
I don't think body count
not to me I don't really care
not just as it is no
I mean it could be
the past does
yeah
well the past is who you are right
like somebody tells me like
they have a 200 body count
and they're 16
something's probably going on there
that's not good
I was thinking about that too like
because it could be like really young people
that are having some sort of
like mental problems going on
or somebody's like 45
and they've like never had sex before
there's probably something going on right
so it could be indicative
but if somebody's like in their 20s
and they've had sex with you know
100 people or 50 people or whatever
it's you know whatever
there's more experience
which can be good
sure
okay so that just represents
your like sexually open
and so it doesn't really necessarily mean any kind of
not necessarily
it could though
the number alone doesn't mean anything
yeah
okay
well you could meet a guy that's like
I just really really like
want to fuck a lot of people
because it makes me so cool
like you're gonna be someone like that
which is like
so the body count doesn't matter
but like where it comes from
like yeah like why
why have you slept with the people you slept with
yes
does it hurt like the romantic aspect
of the relationship
knowing that there's a lot of people in the past
I don't know
not for us
no
is the part of the relationship fundamentally romantic
for us?
for us yeah
yeah
okay
what?
you come out for such a cold person
no I was just in my head thinking
I wanted to just say gotcha right there
it's so judgmental
I think when it comes to the sex thing
there's always like the way that I explain it is
and I understand like
I have to say this
because I don't advocate for what I do for everybody
or what she does for everybody
because obviously there's a whole bunch of
natural feelings of jealousy
that pop up for a lot of people
but when people ask me
you know it's always like
oh like isn't this like horrible
that you guys are doing this
and you don't love each other
from my perspective
I can have sex with like any person
and it can be sex
like that's not like a special thing
between two people
in my eyes
it's like anybody can have sex
but there are like certain activities
and ways that you can spend time with each other
where you're like carving out these like
precious little moments in time
with a certain person
that can do things that are special to that person
and those are the kind of like events
that I remember more than anything else
so like the idea of like
like oh wow I had sex with a person
that was so special
doesn't mean as much as like you know
us traveling to like New Zealand
or sharing some special moment
doing like some really fun activity
or event or whatever
that's usually how I like it I am
so a shared intimate moment
yeah
I kind of agree
but I can definitely connect the romance with sex
boring
I'm curious why you can't do it
see that's where the red pill's right
that's exactly
we've also talked about misogyny
which is you're clearly the embodiment of that
what were you saying
so there's some there's a connection between romance and
yeah I think it is
because I think sex could be a lot of things
right
it's it's some sort of bonding
I'd say in some way
they say that you really like BDSM
you kind of like you become submissive to someone
or you take control over someone
it's like a very bonding like intimate moment
I'd say
and that's romantic
the intimacy is romantic
I think it is
if you can show yourself as really submissive
or like weak
or you have like absolutely no control over yourself
and you let someone else do it
or you are the one being that like
you are the dominant for someone
I think that's a really like intimate thing
because you show like the weakest part of yourself
kind of
I just feel like I personally
to me some component romantic but to me
this is not judging to others
to me
maybe his haul is brought up
the romance increases
if the number of intimate interactions
are limited to one person
like for me for some reason
spreading it out
decreases
like exponentially
the the feeling of romance you feel
I don't know what that that could be just like
sort of having grown up in the Soviet Union
there's a kind of there's the fairy tale stories
and you're kind of maybe living through them
yeah I mean I think what you're saying is like really normal
like most people probably show that way
yeah
but but because you guys are able to successfully not do that
I just want to question my own understanding of it
you know
like
like why is that
why is that
like am I being very jealous for no reason
like maybe you can maximize the number of intimate experiences
if you just open up and let go of the jealousy essentially
I think I feel like in Sweden
and like in Scandinavia
we're extremely just sexually open
like in general
we're not like super religious either
we're very like relaxed
we don't like we don't feel bad about ourselves
like it's just like a different sort of thing
and I would say like it's we're more progressive
when it comes to feminism and stuff
so it's more common
they will meet women with a higher body count
than like when I meet like American girls
all of them I have like vaginisma
like super suppressed like sexually and
where did you just use
they have like issues to like
they can't relax during sex
so it just hurts for them
vaginismus
so they get really nervous
is that what it's called yeah
so like I meet so many girls
that are having like a lot of issues
with sex
and they have like a very low body count
because they just can't relax
or they yeah
and it's probably
and usually they come from like a very religious background
so they have just been told
like you cannot wear that
you cannot be like that
you can't like you know
and like where I grew up
it wasn't like that at all
but you see it as more like a casual thing
so then you can just maximize
the awesomeness of the experience
yeah I guess I don't have trouble with it
exactly
I think the important thing I think
for everybody to realize
is there's always pros and cons to everything
like my lifestyle like
obviously I get to have a lot of fun experiences
that's like a huge pro
and that's super cool
and if you're like a more monogamy
brain person
you're not going to get those experiences
but if you're a monogamy brain person
like when you're sharing that special
woman at home with somebody else
like that moment could be really really really special
because now it's the thing that you're showing yourself
and open yourself up to another person
and they're only trusting you to do that
and that's like a really special thing
that only the two of you are showing with each other
so I mean like there's always like pros and cons to everything
like I think we both would say like
like doing an open relationship is probably not
like we would not recommend it
yeah I don't think we would no
yeah I recently fasted for three days
and I ate a chicken breast at the end of that
and it was like the most delicious food I've ever eaten
so like there's some aspect of fasting
and scarcity and so on that
like you have to figure out what for your own psyche
what works the best
it's good to be a little bored or like
not do something or like work
because you can just enjoy the time
when you're doing something really fun
it's more fun otherwise you're just going to get numb
in general with everything
yeah
yeah I personally just never get bored
like I guess the the boring thing is exciting to me
the just like
you're like me because you say everything I like is boring
I gotta ask you we talked about misogyny
in the he's trying to battle it out on the internet
what's your what's your sense as a woman
about the level of misogyny on the internet
in the streaming community and how to fight it
for me because I get I guess I get it every single day
somehow like because I haven't online
like I have a chat that goes that's live right
and but I have like mods moderating that all the time
so I don't really need to see much of it
I think it's just pretty annoying
because you get to like see it all the time
so it's become like background noise
yeah a little bit and it's like the same commons over and over again
but it's usually for me I don't personally care that much
I understand that other people do
especially when it comes into like
when there's like a lot of sexism and stuff
and when there's a lot of like men not taking women seriously
like I definitely get that
and I used to get that even more like a few years ago
with my accent and everything
and like I used to be blonde as well like a few months ago
so I feel like people wouldn't take me seriously because of that
that's a bit annoying
but I feel like it's pretty easy to like see through
when someone acts that way
and for me personally I don't really care
but it's a bit annoying like being online
and like getting stuff every single day
it would say like the probably the worst thing is
when you feel like you put in a lot of effort into some sort of work
everyone is just going to say
you just got that because you're a woman and you're attractive
and that's that's probably like the worst thing
is there a way to fight that you think
yeah I don't think you can
I think it just comes up all the time
it is what it is I guess
you're just gonna keep doing whatever you do
and like not let it like emotionally control you somehow
I think having more women in those spaces is always good
it's probably good yeah
like a lot of the guys you can tell online that they don't ever
don't bring on the worst ones then
see she's being this
did you see she just did it
she did the misogyny thing
by having some bad women on
she's saying all women see you
well you you know it's true
right
see but I just agree with you
and I'm older than both of you and therefore wiser right
so
well combined we're older than you
I think we're wonderful
we're one fully matronomy
yeah we've got combined age
or it could be it could be the same thing
it was like also the age thing
and like the woman thing
a lot of people think that I'm just copying
every single thing that he says
which I think is a bit annoying as well
so I can never really like
a sonic user of that one
yeah which has been annoying
so much you know
it was about the defunding police
like my dad is a cop
friendship camaraderie and love and respect
which you both have had for a time
and have lost and I would like you to regain it
let's try to increase
not decrease the amount of love in this space
what do you think about
some of the harshness of this
of his language which we talked about
our word in the past
when you used n word
all of that kind of stuff
when he what he used to do
I mean
no like what do you think about it
like do you give him advice
to not speak a certain way
no like a little more civility
I'm just trying to get a second opinion on this
second opinion about
nor many people not internet people
are way more extreme than
yeah
she's way more extreme
no that's not true
okay so okay so here's thing for me okay
I was not online until three years ago
at all
like I would watch youtube
that's pretty much all I would do
I wouldn't do anything else
really I didn't
grew up playing video games or anything
so I'm like extremely new to everything
so when I came into this world
and I started seeing clips from him in the past
I don't think I really had much of an opinion
because it just sounded like
it was just a different like words that we were using
but it didn't mean anything
that's what it feels like
it was just like
if you're saying the R word
it's because you just want to call someone stupid
but you want to like do it a little bit more
like but it's not like
it didn't feel like it was like a
it's not like racist more like
yeah I'm not
you know it's not
agreement on this side here right
so like if he was saying the F word
because it was just like a word to like
insult someone
and he was like I don't think he was ever
I don't think you were ever homophobic
back in the day or anything like that
but I think it was just like a way
to express yourself maybe back then
I don't know I didn't do it
there's no videos of me or anything
because I wasn't even online back then
yeah so my case was
I definitely don't think
Stephen is homophobic or racer
any of those obviously
so the
there's a good heart there
and a good mind
I was just saying
he just likes being mean
well there is some
you lose yourself
and forget the bigger picture that
he's pushing for
more effective discourse on the internet
he's like an inspiration to a lot of people
especially now
of like how you can use effective
conversation to make for a better world
to derive a variety of glass people
and so on and then you lose some of that power
by losing yourself
in like the language
just more language of emotion
versus effective communication
I would say
but it's a gray area
I would say like something
that is probably recently done in that case
because it's been joking about women a lot
like it's women's fault they're bad
like it's just it's been like
a lot of jokes when it comes to misogyny
I guess in your community
and I think it's actually
turned people a little bit that way
that's why we've done the recent
misogyny
yes so that I guess that's actually
true because I don't think it was pretty
I don't think it was clear enough
I don't think it actually was
I think you did that mistake
but I think back then I was even saying
like hey you should probably not
like you probably should not do that
because it actually is pretty hard for me
because whenever I come into his community
like his chat
people are just going to spam
it's like a woman moment
it's a woman moment whenever I say something
and it's kind of like
yeah it's getting pretty annoying as I said
it's just annoying when you see it every single day
yeah
there you go
wisdom from somebody younger than you
wisdom can come from
all kind of people
yeah of course
just sometimes at very limited quantities
depends on the age
and learn something from anybody
what advice would you give to young people
the both of you
that you have both audiences
where young people look up to you
in general
if you were to give advice to somebody in high school
like how to
create a life that can be proud of
what would you say
the most important thing that I've learned
is to view people as different
and not better or worse
and when you view people as different
instead of better or worse
you learn that there's almost something
that you can learn from anybody
like be open and empathetic
towards other people's experiences
nobody does anything by random choice
like there's always reasons why people act the way they do
and as long as you're willing to kind of like
be open and receptive to the lived experiences of other people
you're going to be able to gather information
and create like a more cohesive and better view of the world
than any of your peers will
Do you have any kind of advice you can give to young folks?
I feel like something that I see
especially in America a lot
is that a lot of people
kind of get told what to do early on
like in high school
they're supposed to become this thing
like education wise
like they're supposed to like become a doctor
or this thing or whatever
and then they kind of just like give up on things
that they're actually passionate about
so I think a lot of teenagers get really confused
they get an education
and then they get that job
and they hate everything
and they think that
when they're reaching the job
when they're reaching like the journey
they're going to get happy
that's like where the happiness is going to be
but then when they get to there
they just hate everything
and then they become really depressed
and I've seen this so much
like I see this all the time
and it's pretty sad to me to see
so many people that are just wasting time
and then they just get really confused
and I don't know
it's the same thing with relationships too
no one really knows what they want anymore
I feel like everyone is just kind of doing whatever
like society is saying
or the parents are saying
or their friends are saying
and they're never really doing anything
that's super meaningful anymore
and like they don't
so what I would say is
like try to find something
that is important to you
it could be anything really
like some sort of passion
maybe like your friends
maybe like what matters to you
like figuring those things out
I think is really important
and that comes from being able to listen to
like some inner voice
so it's not gonna come from elsewhere
it's really hard because
you're living the life
and like there's things happening around you
and people tell you what to do
and what not to do and all you know
no one really has like their own opinions
everyone is just kind of like
listening to the cooler thing
or you know
except Steven
he seems to stand on his own
travel
if we think
yeah I'd say so
and like
on hashtag
like something I realized too
like because we just went to TwitchCon
and we were talking to a lot of streamers
what was that
it was interesting
I thought it was interesting
because the few people that I feel like I
that seem really cool
and that I look up to like in the streaming world
all of them wants to quit streaming
all of them wants to do it
no one wants
like no one likes it
and they're so successful
like they are around successful people
they they're working every single day
they're working hard
they're making so much money
and everyone is just complaining
and like they're complaining about
like not being able to see their partner
or you know
because they need to live somewhere else
because I see these things
and they seem extremely unhappy
and but it's so hard for them to just cut
all this successful stuff off
because that's like what you
you know learn to do
and that's like supposed to be like your happiness
but it isn't
everyone is really unhappy
yeah there's something about
maybe streaming is different
but YouTube folks too
I've interacted with a few and
even in podcasting space
people become obsessed about the views
and numbers
and subscribers and stuff like that
so I turn
I never talk about that
I don't pay attention to that
I feel like that's a drug that destroys
your mind
your your mind is an artist
ability to create
surely unique things
also your mind
in terms of the anxiety
the ups and downs of the
attention mechanism
and then also being
just if something that you make
is not popular
but it meant a lot to you
you will think of it less
because it's not popular
yeah that's a really dangerous thing
and because everyone around you
is reinforcing
like I'll get messages like
wow
this thing got this many views
or something
great job
it's like no
you don't get it
like that's not
that's not
everyone is enforcing this
like this language
of views and likes and so on
and it's
it's correlated of course
because truly impactful things
will get a lot of attention
often
but
it's not
on the individual local scale
like temporarily is
it's uh
it can really fuck with your mind
and I see that
in the creators
they become
addicts to the algorithm
lost in chasing views
like we know friends that
yes
we know cool people
and then they start streaming
and eventually they got
they're like chasing the dragon of like
and they change like
they're
yeah
it's like
this is something I've always said
that like
one of the biggest blessings
and biggest curses of humanity
is we are very good at acclimating
like you can become paralyzed
you can have all sorts of horrible
things happen to you
and you'll get used to it
and you'll be okay
you're gonna have like a good baseline
but it works the other way too
and that you can get more and more
and you acclimate to it
almost immediately
there's like
this is a phenomenon that
I bet it happens in the youtube world
but I know it happens in the streaming world
where you're streaming
1,000 viewers every day
huge event happens
and you blow up
and you got like 15,000 viewers
for a day or two
and then it starts to go down
and down and down and down and down
and then after all the drama started off
you're at like
3,000 concurrent viewers
now in the macro
you went from 1,000 to 3,000
that feels awesome
but you actually feel like
shit the whole time
because you're remembering
when you had 10 or 15,000
and now everything feels horrible
and you'll see people climb over time
and like
fuck
like but whatever that one huge stream
I had like
I've never like been able to
and it's like
dude you're doing great
what's yeah
that happens a lot
there's so many people that we know
that we find super super cool
they're passionate about things
they have so much interest
and then they just get like
so addicted to these numbers
and like all the
everything is just ruined
like all the cool things about them
is ruined
because they stop doing the things
that they actually like
to do something else
that gives them more viewers
and more money
and it's really sad to see
you know that
that temporary sacrifice
that seems temporary is
that it
it actually destroys you
like for one time
making a choice
because I come across those choices often
like I can do this
you can kind of know
what's going to be popular and not
and you have to ask yourself the question
like is this going to sacrifice
because if people are sacrificing
like intimate relationships
they're sacrificing time
with their family
they're like
sacrificing time
with the things that they
feel good about
and that they like
and that's something I kind of
realized last year
because I was working so much
and I was just grinding
and grinding and grinding
because it was kind of new for me
and then new years came by
and I was like
wait what did I even do
like the entire year
like I traveled to a bunch of places
but nothing actually
really meant anything to me
because I felt like I was just
working the entire time
I felt like I was just numb
through the
through the entire year
and I was really scary
like I rented a
like a super pretty house
like for a week
with my dad and my sister
because I wanted to spend time with them
but the entire time
I was just streaming
and I actually
didn't ever like calm down
and just like
chill with them
and I
like that's like time
I'll never get back
I don't
I don't give a shit about the money
that I made that week
but I lost the time
and like
that is really important to me
and I
yeah and a lot of people are doing that
and I feel like
as you said
like you can definitely see that
in like artists
for sure
I feel like
if you look at like artists
like back in the 60s or 70s
I feel like things were just
so much better back then
and it feels like
they were actually making music
that meant something to them
they were actually making art
and I feel like today
everything is just kind of like
whatever is cool
whatever sells
whatever you know
sounds in a certain way
everything is kind of
the same thing
and everything that is very artistic
and very cool
is actually not that popular
at all
and that's kind of sad
yeah of course there's now
bigger mechanisms and platforms
to spread
stuff
music
so as long as you could be content
with not being popular
I think you can still create good art
but not like
when people get a little popular
they get addicted to that so fast
yeah it's weird
yeah
you have been somewhat good
at least from my outside of perspective
because I think you
I can at least imagine
you making choices
that could make you more popular
and you don't seem to make those choices
sabotage my career
but it is very intentional
like you said
like and I made that choice
at every single stage of my life
one is because
from the perspective
of being a carpet cleaner
my life is way better
than that
was or ever would have been
so I'm already doing way better than I ever thought
somebody like me ever could be
but then two
I super love my job
every time I wake up
every time I fly to a place to do a podcast
every time I get to talk to really cool people
like every single part of my job
I super like
if there's something I don't like
I just cut it off
because I don't care
because I'm already making plenty of money
doing what I do
and why would I ever wake up
and not like what I'm doing
when I can't like what I'm doing
how do you guys find
through that
given that
you love it
and sometimes maybe lose yourself in the drug of it
how do you find
like work-life balance
together inside a relationship
like time for each other
I don't at all so
I'm not a good person to ask
what do you love more
Mel or Faktor
Faktor is a really good game
that's like not a fair comparison
okay you're talking about
one of the best cleanest games
best support ever made
cleanest code base
like this is
I think it's Thanos brother
yeah it's more Faktor time for me
starting to understand
where the massaging comes from
by the way
is Faktor a legit really good game
yeah of course yeah
I'm cool
if you're like
do you enjoy programming
of course that's all I do
that's all that's okay
to me programming is
is the game in itself
that I enjoy probably more than anything else
but yeah
it's very much a game like that
of like if you're into stuff like that
like you can lose hundreds of hours
like very quickly to
like you have a problem
and then you think of a solution
and then you iterate on that
over and over and over again
in larger larger schemes
sometimes you got to redesign stuff
sometimes you got like
it's a very much like that kind of game
this year essentially building a factory
like what on a foreign planet
or something like that
it's basically it's like
a bunch of you're trying to automate
different problems
so that you can build bigger things
so that you can automate bigger problems
so you can build bigger things
and automate bigger problems
so it's more complicated
than like a city building game
like some city type of thing
I wouldn't say it's more complicated
it's more it's like
Faktor is like a game of like logic
like strictly like logic
like it's almost like a building
a circuit or something
yes yeah
there's like their circuitry
and you've got your and orgs
or against you
like there's stuff like that
it's very much like that
like what are the enemies in the game
like what they're like
so I try to bite you
and you can get guns and shoot and kill them
but I saw there's like shooting going on
yeah
but that's like a mind
it's just like another problem
to solve in the game basically
yeah
okay
all right
see see what we did there
we just started talking about the game
as we're trying
oh my god that's like
like a game
okay
that's horrible
anyway is there
is that basically the struggle
not stop struggle
how to get human
like intimate human time
I feel like it was like that
a little bit more in the past
I feel like it's been better
lately
but I think it's because
when we started dating
I wasn't streaming
and I kind of just like
gave up like my trip in New Zealand
I give up like
like I left Sweden
so I was just like
in LA
which I hate
I hate LA
I don't like LA at all
it's hard to make friends
that are like real
that are into the same stuff as you
it was just really hard for me
to connect with anyone
especially also like being a European
and like being around Americans
was very strange
so the only thing I had
when I came here
was him
and I didn't expect
that situation
because yeah
because we had
we had like two weeks of hanging out
and like he would be on his computer
sometimes
and like do emails and stuff
but I wasn't thinking
that he would stream like 12 hours a day
and it was pretty
like it was pretty intense
like in the beginning of it as well
and I realized it was really hard
to like get attention
and get time
because his like love meter
would be like full
if I was just in the house
and that's just kind of like
the way he is
and for me back then
when I didn't have anything else to do
it was kind of like a
it was kind of crazy for me
I feel like right now
because I do work as well
and I have things going for me
and I have other friends
now that I made
I feel like it's a lot easier
because and I can definitely like
enjoy just like being in separate rooms
and just like hear him in the background
is really nice
so I can like
I can sit in paint
and like in my room
and I will do that for hours
while I'm just like hearing a scream
in the background
it's kind of like comforting
that he's he's just there
it feels nice
I like it
to you that's the sound of happiness
yes because I know he's right there
yeah it's nice
and they will come in
and check on me sometimes
and it's it's kind of like
it's actually very comforting
it's very nice
I like it
yeah
I think that's kind of what a relationship is
like you do fun things together
you know you share moments together
but also just like
having someone like around
you's really really nice
and I think that's probably
maybe it's me growing up
maybe that's what it is
and like I start liking like the kind of
I feel like we're like an old couple
like we're like 80
and we're just like around
we don't really have to talk much
it's it's nice to just do that
that fills your love meter
that person
I like this terminology
love me
I need both
I mean okay
you're making it sound like
that I'm like craving like
I haven't said anything
I'm not saying anything
I haven't said a single thing at all
you're making face right now
I know exactly what you're thinking so
there's so much judging going on
there's no judging at all
no but like we
I think
I think whenever we do plan something out
like if we if we go on a trip
like every other month or once a month
I feel like usually like
that's enough
as long as he's not playing
factorial the entire time
like if he if I feel like
he's going on these trips with me
and he's not
like doing things with me
or he's not he's not interested
in like spending time
or like being present with me
then I'll feel like
I just feel like I'm just wasting time
right now
and then I get kind of disappointed
but otherwise I think this
like this is fun
I think this is like spending time
together
because we're like doing something together
yeah it's fun yeah
my love meter is
your love meter is full
it's my social life
otherwise we like to
we like to think about it that way
like I need like a little bit more of
like this one thing
like quality time
and he needs like
almost zero quality time
but like let's say that I
we took away like physical touch
you would probably not be very happy
so you need physical touch
so it's not just back to me huh
no I'm a very cuddly person
yeah like cuddly
and then you're like
I guess like acts of service
like if I do something for you
get really happy
like hot chocolate
yeah
like if I give him hot chocolate
in the morning he gets really happy
so
the actual
it's not the hot chocolate
it's the giving of the hot chocolate
no it's just the hot chocolate
but if she gives it to me
I didn't have to get it myself
it was just physical touch
that's really nice
all right well if you have to choose
between Factorio and the drama
or political discourse
which probably political discourse
probably my calling
but I am a good Factorio player
like what role exactly does Factorio play
in your streaming life
oh well right now it's just
usually there are like these games
that I play in the background
as I have conversation
because it's hard for me to just sit on the computer
just talk
and not like be playing a game at the same time
so it's just something to keep me kind of like occupied
you know I was going to buy like those little like
widget things I guess
yeah that's what yours is
yeah basically yeah
it's like minecraft or Factorio for me
all right
well my love meter is full from this
Mel thank you so much for joining us
this was really fun
I'm you guys are fascinating human beings
thank you for existing
I'm glad to live in a world where you exist
and I can't wait to see what kind of beautiful
thing you create next
and the crazy kind of art that you create
through the different people you interact with
Destiny, Steven, you're an amazing human
thank you so much for talking to me
it's an honor
hope to talk with you again
talking to Ben Shapiro
you've given me a lot of inspiration
it's an honor to talk to the Ben Shapiro of the left
well thanks a lot Robert I appreciate it
thank you guys
thank you
thanks for listening to this conversation with destiny
to support this podcast
please check out our sponsors in the description
and now let me leave you with some words from Lewis Carroll
it's no use going back to yesterday
because I was a different person then
thank you for listening
and hope to see you next time