Whatever reality is, it's not what you see.
What you see is just an adaptive fiction.
The following is a conversation with Donald Hoffman,
professor of cognitive sciences at UC Irvine,
focusing his research on evolutionary psychology,
visual perception, and consciousness.
He's the author of over 120 scientific papers
on these topics, and his most recent book titled
The Case Against Reality, Why Evolution
Hid the Truth from Our Eyes.
I think some of the most interesting ideas in this world,
like those of Donald Hoffman's attempt to shake
the foundation of our understanding of reality,
and thus they take a long time to internalize deeply.
So proceed with caution. Questioning the fabric of reality
can lead you to either madness or the truth.
And the funny thing is, you won't know which is which.
This is the Lex Friedman podcast. To support it,
please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Donald Hoffman.
In your book The Case Against Reality,
Why Evolution Hid the Truth from Our Eyes,
you make the bold claim that the world we see with our eyes is not real.
It's not even an abstraction of objective reality.
It is completely detached from objective reality.
Can you explain this idea? Right.
So this is a theorem from Evolution of a Natural Selection.
So the technical question that I and my team asked was,
what is the probability that natural selection would shape
sensory systems to see true properties of objective reality?
And to our surprise, we found that the answer is precisely zero, except for one
kind of structure that we can go into if you want to.
But for any generic structure that you might think the world might have,
a total order, a topology metric, the probability is precisely zero
that natural selection would shape any sensory system of any organism
to see any aspect of objective reality.
So in that sense, what we're seeing is what we need to see
to stay alive long enough to reproduce.
So in other words, we're seeing what we need to guide adaptive behavior, full stop.
So the evolutionary process, the process that took us from the original life on earth
to the humans that we are today, that process does not maximize
for truth and maximizes for fitness, as you say.
Fitness beats truth.
And fitness does not have to be connected to truth is the claim.
And that's where you have an approach towards zero of probability that we
have evolved human cognition, human consciousness, whatever it is,
the magic that makes our mind work, evolved not for its ability to see the truth of reality,
but its ability to survive in the environment.
That's exactly right.
So most of us intuitively think that surely the way that evolution will make our senses
more fit is to make them tell us more truths, or at least the truths we need to know
about objective reality, the truths we need in our niche.
That's the standard view.
And it was the view I took.
I mean, that's sort of what we're taught or just even assume.
It's just sort of like the intelligent assumption that we would all make.
But we don't have to just wave our hands.
Evolution of a natural selection is a mathematically precise theory.
John Maynard Smith in the 70s created evolutionary game theory.
And we have evolutionary graph theory and even genetic algorithms that we can use to study this.
And so we don't have to wave our hands.
It's a matter of theorem and proof and or simulation before you get the theorems and proofs.
And a couple of graduate students of mine, Justin Mark and Brian Marion,
did some wonderful simulations that tipped me off that there was something going on here.
And then I went to a mathematician, Chaitan Prakash and Manish Singh and
some other friends of mine, Chris Fields.
And but Chaitan was the real mathematician behind all this.
And he's proved several theorems that uniformly indicate that with one exception,
which has to do with probability measures, there's no the probability zero.
The reason there's an exception for probability measures,
so-called sigma algebras or sigma additive classes, is that for any scientific theory,
there is the assumption that needs to be made that the whatever
structure, the whatever probabilistic structure the world may have,
is not unrelated to the probabilistic structure of our perceptions.
If they were completely unrelated, then no science would be possible.
So this is technically, the map from reality to our senses has to be a so-called
measurable map, has to preserve sigma algebras.
But that means it could be infinite to one and it could collapse all sorts of event information.
But other than that, there's no requirement in standard evolutionary theory for fitness payoff
functions, for example, to preserve any specific structures of objective reality.
So you can ask the technical question. This is one of the avenues we took.
If you look at all the fitness payoffs from whatever world structure you might want to
imagine, so a world with, say, a total order on it.
So it's got n states and they're totally ordered.
And then you can have a set of maps from that world into a set of payoffs,
say from zero to a thousand or whatever you want your payoffs to be.
And you can just literally count all the payoff functions.
And just do the combinatorics and count them.
And then you can ask a precise question.
How many of those payoff functions preserve the total order?
If that's what you're looking for.
Or how many preserve the topology?
And you just count them and divide.
So the number that are homomorphisms versus the total number,
and then take the limit as the number of states in the world,
and the number of payoff values goes very large.
And when you do that, you get zero every time.
Okay, there's a million things to ask here.
But first of all, just in case people are not familiar with your work,
let's sort of linger on the big, bold statement here,
which is the thing we see with our eyes
is not some kind of limited window into reality.
It is completely detached from reality,
likely completely detached from reality.
You're saying 100% likely.
Okay, so none of this is real in the way we think is real.
In the way we have this intuition,
there's like this table is some kind of abstraction,
but underneath it all, there's atoms.
And there's an entire century of physics
that describes the functioning of those atoms
and the quarks that make them up.
There's many Nobel Prizes about particles and fields
and all that kind of stuff that slowly builds up
to something that's perceivable to us,
both with our eyes, with our different senses as this table.
Then there's also ideas of chemistry
that overlays of abstraction from DNA to embryos,
the cells that make the human body.
So all of that is not real.
It's a real experience and it's a real adaptive set of perceptions.
So it's an adaptive set of perceptions, full stop.
We want to think that the perceptions are real.
So their perceptions are real as perceptions.
We are having our perceptions,
but we've assumed that there's a pretty tight relationship
between our perceptions and reality.
If I look up and see the moon,
then there is something that exists in space and time
that matches what I perceive.
And all I'm saying is that if you take evolution
by natural selection seriously, then that is precluded.
That our perceptions are there.
They're there to guide adaptive behavior, full stop.
They're not there to show you the truth.
In fact, the way I think about it is they're there to hide the truth
because the truth is too complicated.
It's just like if you're trying to use your laptop to write an email.
What you're doing is toggling voltages in the computer,
but good luck trying to do it that way.
The reason why we have a user interface
is because we don't want to know that quote unquote truth,
the diodes and resistors and all that terrible hardware.
If you had to know all that truth,
your friends wouldn't hear from you.
So what evolution gave us was perceptions
that guide adaptive behavior.
And part of that process, it turns out,
means hiding the truth and giving you eye candy.
So what's the difference between hiding the truth
and forming abstractions, layers upon layers of abstractions
over these over low level voltages and transistors and chips
and programming languages from assembly to Python
that then leads you to be able to have an interface like Chrome
where you open up another set of JavaScript and HTML programming
languages that lead you to have a graphical user interface
on which you can then send your friends an email.
So is that completely detached from the zeros and ones
that are firing away inside the computer?
It's not.
Of course, when I talk about the user interface on your desktop,
there's this whole sophisticated backstory to it,
right, that the hardware and the software
that's allowing that to happen.
Evolution doesn't tell us the backstory, right?
So the theory of evolution is not going to be adequate
to tell you what is that backstory.
It's going to say that whatever reality is,
and that's the interesting thing.
It says whatever reality is, you don't see it.
You see a user interface, but it doesn't tell you
what that user interface is, how it's built, right?
Now, we can try to look at certain aspects of the interface,
but already we're going to look at that and go,
okay, before I would look at neurons,
and I was assuming that I was seeing something
that was at least partially true.
And now I'm realizing it could be like looking
at the pixels on my desktop or icons on my desktop,
and good luck going from that to the data structures
and then the voltages.
And I mean, good luck.
There's just no way.
So what's interesting about this is that our scientific theories
are precise enough and rigorous enough to tell us certain limits,
but, and even limits of the theories themselves.
But they're not going to tell us what the next move is,
and that's where scientific creativity comes in.
So the stuff that I'm saying here, for example,
is not alien to physicists.
The physicists are saying precisely the same thing,
that space time is doomed.
We've assumed that space time is fundamental.
We've assumed that for several centuries,
and it's been very useful.
So all the things that you were mentioning,
the particles and all the work that's been done,
that's all been done in space time,
but now physicists are saying space time is doomed.
There's no such thing as space time fundamentally
in the laws of physics.
And that comes actually out of gravity together
with quantum field theory.
It just comes right out of it.
It's a theorem of those two theories put together.
But it doesn't tell you what's behind it.
So the physicists know that their best theories,
Einstein's gravity and quantum field theory put together,
entail that space time cannot be fundamental,
and therefore particles in space time cannot be fundamental.
They're just irreducible representations
of the symmetries of space time.
That's what they are.
So we have, so space time, so we put the two together.
We put together what the physicists are discovering,
and we can talk about how they do that.
And then we, the new discoveries
from evolution of a natural selection,
both of these discoveries are really in the last 20 years.
And what both are saying is space time has had a good ride.
It's been very useful.
Reductionism has been useful, but it's over.
And it's time for us to go beyond.
When you say space time is doomed, is it the space?
Is it the time?
Is it the very hard coded specification of four dimensions?
Or are you specifically referring to the kind of
perceptual domain that humans operate in,
which is space time?
You think like there's a 3D,
like our world is three-dimensional,
and time progresses forward.
Therefore, three dimensions plus one, 4D.
What exactly do you mean by space time?
What do you mean by space time is doomed?
Great, great.
So this is, by the way, not my quote.
This is from, for example, Nima Arkany Ahmed
at the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton.
Ed Whitten also there.
David Gross, Nobel Prize winner.
So this is not just something the cognitive scientists,
this is what the physicists are saying.
Yeah, the physicists, they're space time skeptics.
Yeah, they're saying that, and I can say exactly why
they think it's doomed, but what they're saying is that,
because your question was what aspect of space time,
what are we talking about here?
It's both space and time.
They're union into space time as in Einstein's theory.
That's doomed.
And they're basically saying that
even quantum theory, this is Nima Arkany Ahmed especially.
So Hilbert spaces will not be fundamental either.
So that the notion of Hilbert space,
which is really critical to quantum field theory,
quantum information theory, that's not going to figure
in the fundamental new laws of physics.
So what they're looking for is some new mathematical structures
beyond space time, beyond Einstein's four-dimensional space time,
or super symmetric version, geometric algebra,
signature, two comma four kind of,
there are different ways that you can represent it,
but they're finding new structures.
And then by the way, they're succeeding now.
They're finding, they found something called the amplitude
to hydrant.
This is Nima and his colleagues, the cosmological polytope.
These are, so there are these like polytopes,
these polyhedra in multi-dimensions, generalizations of simplices
that are coding for, for example, the scattering amplitudes
of processes in the Large Hadron Collider and other colliders.
So they're finding that if they let go of space time completely,
they're finding new ways of computing these scattering amplitudes
that turn literally billions of terms into one term.
When you do it in space and time, because it's the wrong framework,
it's, it's, it's just a user interface from,
that's now from the evolutionary point of view,
it's just user interface.
It's not a deep insight into the nature of reality.
So it's missing deep symmetry,
it's something called a dual conformal symmetry,
which turns out to be true of the scattering data,
but you can't see it in space time.
And it's making the computations way too complicated
because you're trying to compute all the loops and Feynman diagrams
and all the Feynman integrals.
So see the Feynman approach to the scattering amplitudes
is trying to enforce two critical properties of space time,
locality and uniterity.
And so by, when you enforce those,
you get all these loops and multiple, you know,
different levels of loops.
And for each of those, you have to add new terms to your computation.
But when you do it outside of space time,
you don't have the notion of uniterity.
You don't have the notion of locality.
You have something deeper.
And it's capturing some symmetries that are actually true of the data.
And, but then when you look at the geometry of the facets of these polytopes,
then certain of them will code for uniterity and locality.
So it actually comes out of the structure of these deep polytopes.
So what we're finding is there's this whole new world,
now beyond space time, that is making explicit symmetries
that are true of the data that cannot be seen in space time.
And that is turning the computations from billions of terms
to one or two or a handful of terms.
So we're getting insights into symmetries.
And we're, and all of a sudden the math is becoming simple
because we're not doing something silly.
We're not adding up all these loops in space time.
We're doing something far deeper.
But they don't know what this world is about.
So, you know, they're in an interesting position
where we know that space time is doomed.
And I should probably tell you why it's doomed,
what they're saying about why it's doomed.
But, but they need a flashlight to look beyond space time.
What, what flashlight are we going to use to look into the dark
beyond space time?
Because Einstein's theory and quantum theory can't tell us.
What's beyond them.
All they can do is tell us that when you put us together,
space time is doomed at 10 to the minus 33 centimeters,
10 to the minus 43 seconds.
Beyond that, space time doesn't even make sense.
It just has no operational definition.
So, but it doesn't tell you what's beyond.
And so they're, they're just looking for deep structures.
Like guessing is really fun.
So these really brilliant guys, generic, brilliant men and women
who are doing this work, physicists,
are making guesses about these structures.
Informed guesses, because they're trying to ask,
well, okay, what deeper structure could give us the stuff
that we're seeing in space time,
but without certain commitments that we have to make
in space time, like locality unit.
So they make these brilliant guesses.
And of course, most of the time you're going to be wrong.
But once you get one or two, that start to pay off.
And then you get some lucky breaks.
So they got lucky break back in 1986.
Couple of mathematicians named Park and Taylor
took the scattering amplitude for two gluons coming in
at high energy and four gluons going out at low energy.
So that kind of scattering thing.
So it's like apparently for people who are into this,
that's sort of something that happens so often
you need to be able to find it and get rid of those
because you already know about that and need to.
So you needed to compute them.
It was billions of terms and they couldn't do it.
Even for the supercomputers couldn't do that
for the many billions or millions of times per second
they needed to do it.
So they bagged, the experimentals bagged the theorists
and please can you, you got it.
So Park and Taylor took the billions of terms,
hundreds of pages and miraculously turned it into nine.
And then a little bit later they guessed
one term expression that turned out to be equivalent.
So billions of terms reduced to one term
that's so-called famous Park-Taylor formula, 1986.
And that was like, okay, where did that come from?
What, this is a pointer into a deep realm
beyond space and time, but no one, I mean,
what can you do with it?
And they thought maybe it was a one-off,
but then other formulas started coming up
and then eventually Neymar, Connie, Hamad and his team
found this thing called the amplituhedron
which really sort of captures the whole,
a big part of the whole ball of wax.
I'm sure they would say, no, there's plenty more to do.
So I won't say they did it all by any means.
They're looking at the cosmological polytope as well.
So what's remarkable to me is that two pillars of modern science,
quantum field theory with gravity on the one hand,
and evolution by natural selection on the other.
Just in the last 20 years have very clearly said
space-time has had a good run.
Reductionism has been a fantastic methodology.
So we had a great ontology of space-time,
a great methodology of reductionism.
Now it's time for a new trick.
But now you need to go deeper.
And show, by the way, this doesn't mean we throw away everything we've done,
not by a long shot.
Every new idea that we come up with beyond space-time
must project precisely into space-time.
And it better give us back everything that we know and love in space-time
or generalizations.
Or it's not going to be taken seriously and it shouldn't be.
So we have a strong constraint on whatever we're going to do
beyond space-time.
It needs to project into space-time.
And whatever this deeper theory is,
it may not itself have evolution by natural selection.
This may not be part of this deeper realm.
But when we take whatever that thing is beyond space-time
and project it into space-time,
it has to look like evolution by natural selection.
Or it's wrong.
So that's a strong constraint on this work.
So even the evolution by natural selection and quantum field theory
could be interfaces into something that doesn't look anything like,
like you mentioned.
I mean, it's interesting to think that evolution might be
a very crappy interface into something much deeper.
That's right.
They're both telling us that the framework that you've had can only go so far.
And it has to stop.
And there's something beyond.
And that framework, the very framework that is space and time itself.
Now, of course, evolution by natural selection is not telling us
about like Einstein's relativistic space time.
So that was another question you asked a little bit earlier.
It's telling us more about our perceptual space and time,
which we have used as the basis for creating first a Newtonian space versus time
as a mathematical extension of our perceptions.
And then Einstein then took that and extended it even further.
So the relationship between what evolution is telling us
and what the physicists are telling us is that,
in some sense, the Newton and Einstein space time are formulated as sort of
rigorous extensions of our perceptual space,
making it mathematically rigorous and laying out the symmetries that they find there.
So that's sort of the relationship between them.
So it's the perceptual space time that evolution is telling us is just a user interface effectively.
And then the physicists are finding that even the mathematical extension
of that into the Einsteinian formulation has to be,
as well, not the final story.
There's something deeper.
So let me ask you about reductionism and interfaces.
As we march forward from Newtonian physics to quantum mechanics,
these are all, in your view, interfaces.
Are we getting closer to objective reality?
How do we know if these interfaces in the process of science,
the reason we like those interfaces is because they're predictive of some aspects,
strongly predictive about some aspects of our reality.
Is that completely deviating from our understanding of that reality?
Or is it helping us get closer and closer and closer?
Well, of course, one critical constraint on all of our theories is that they are empirically tested
and pass the experiments that we have for them.
So no one's arguing against experiments being important
and wanting to test all of our current theories and any new theories on that.
So that's all there.
But we have good reason to believe that science will never get a theory of everything.
Everything, everything.
Everything, everything, right, a final theory of everything, right?
I think that my, my own take is for what it's worth is that
girdles in completeness theorem sort of points us in that direction,
that even with mathematics, any finite axiomatization that's
sophisticated enough to be able to do arithmetic,
it's easy to show that there'll be statements that are true,
that can't be proven, can't be deduced from within that framework.
And if you add the new statements to your axioms,
then there'll be always new statements that are true,
but can't be proven with a new axiom system.
And the best scientific theories in physics, for example,
and also now evolution, are mathematical.
So our theories are going to be, they're going to have their own assumptions,
and they'll be mathematically precise.
And there'll be theories perhaps of everything except those assumptions,
because assumptions are, we say,
please grant me these assumptions.
If you grant me these assumptions, then I can explain this other stuff.
But so you have the assumptions that are like miracles,
as far as the theory is concerned, they're not explained,
they're the starting points for explanation.
And then you have the mathematical structure of the theory itself,
which will have the girdle limits.
And so my take is that reality, whatever it is, is always going to transcend
any conceptual theory that we can come up with.
There's always going to be mystery at the edges.
Contradictions and all that kind of stuff.
Okay.
And truths.
So there's this idea that is brought up in the financial space of settlement,
of transactions.
It's often talked about in cryptocurrency especially.
So you could do, money, cash is not connected to anything.
It used to be connected to gold, to physical reality,
but then you can use money to exchange value to transact.
So when it was on the gold standard,
the money would represent some stable component of reality.
Isn't it more effective to avoid things like hyperinflation
if we generalize that idea?
Isn't it better to connect your, whatever we humans are doing in the social interaction
space with each other, isn't it better from an evolutionary perspective to connect it
to some degree to reality so that the transactions are settled with something that's universal,
as opposed to us constantly operating in something that's a complete illusion?
Isn't it easy to hyperinflate that?
Like where you really deviate very, very far away from the underlying reality?
Or do you not never get in trouble for this?
Can you just completely drift far, far away from the underlying reality and never get in trouble?
That's a great question.
On the financial side, there's two levels at least that we could take your question.
One is strictly evolutionary psychology of financial systems.
And that's pretty interesting.
And there, the decentralized idea, the DeFi kind of idea in cryptocurrencies may make
good sense from just an evolutionary psychology point of view.
Human nature being what it is, putting a lot of faith in a few central controllers
depends a lot on the veracity of those and trustworthiness of those few central controllers.
We have ample evidence time and again that's often betrayed.
So it makes good evolutionary sense, I would say, to have a decentralized, I mean,
democracy is a step in that direction.
We don't have a monarch now telling us what to do.
We decentralize things, because if you have Marcus Aurelio says you're emperor,
you're great.
If you have Nero, it's not so great.
And so we don't want that.
So democracy is a step in that direction.
But I think the DeFi thing is an even bigger step
and is going to even make the democratization even greater.
So that's one level.
Also, the fact that power corrupts and absolute power corrupts absolutely is also
a consequence of evolution.
That's also a feature, I think.
You can argue from the long span of living organisms, it's nice for power to corrupt.
So mad men and women throughout history might be useful to teach us a lesson.
We can learn from our negative example, right?
Exactly.
Right.
Power does corrupt, and I think that you can think about that again from an evolutionary
point of view.
But I think that your question was a little deeper.
When that was, does the evolutionary interface idea sort of unhinge science from
some kind of important test for the theories?
Does it mean that anything goes in scientific theory, but if we don't see the truth,
is there no way to tether our theories and test them?
And I think there's no problem there.
We can only test things in terms of what we can measure with our senses in space and time.
So we're going to have to continue to do experiments, but we're going to understand
a little bit differently what those experiments are.
We had thought that when we see a pointer on some machine in an experiment,
that the machine exists, the pointer exists, and the values exist even when no one
is looking at them, and that they're an objective truth.
And our best theories are telling us no.
Pointers are just pointers, and that's what you have to rely on for making your judgments.
But even the pointers themselves are not the objective reality.
So and I think Gertl is telling us that not that anything goes, but
as you develop new axiom systems, you will find out what goes within that axiom system
and what testable predictions you can make.
So I don't think we're untethered.
We continue to do experiments.
What I think we won't have that we want is a conceptual understanding
that gives us a theory of everything that's final and complete.
I think that this is, to put it another way, this is job security for scientists.
Our job will never be done.
It's job security for neuroscience.
Because before we thought that when we looked in the brain,
we saw neurons and neural networks and action potentials and synapses and so forth,
and that was the reality.
Now we have to reverse engineer that.
We have to say what is beyond space-time?
What is going on?
What is a dynamical system beyond space-time?
That when we project it into Einstein space-time,
gives us things that look like neurons and neural networks and synapses.
So we have to reverse engineer.
So there's going to be lots more work for neuroscience.
It's going to be far more complicated and difficult and challenging.
But that's wonderful.
That's what we need to do.
We thought neurons exist when they are perceived and they don't.
In the same way that if I show you, when I say they don't exist,
I should be very, very concrete.
If I draw on a piece of paper a little sketch of something that is called the necker cube,
it's just a little line drawing of a cube.
It's on a flat piece of paper.
If I execute it well and I show it to you, you'll see a 3D cube and you'll see it flip.
Sometimes you'll see one face in front.
Sometimes you'll see the other face in front.
But if I ask you, which face is in front when you don't look?
The answer is, well, neither face is in front because there's no cube.
This is a flat piece of paper.
So when you look at the piece of paper, you perceptually create the cube.
And when you look at it, then you fix one face to be in front and one face to be in front.
So that's what I mean when I say it doesn't exist.
Space time itself is like the cube.
It's a data structure that your sensory systems construct,
whatever your sensory systems mean now, because we now have to even take that for granted.
But there are perceptions that you construct on the fly.
And they're data structures and the computer science says,
and you garbage collect them when you don't need them.
So you create them and garbage collect them.
But is it possible that it's mapped well in some concrete, predictable way to objective reality?
The sheet of paper, the two-dimensional space, or we can talk about space time,
maps in some way that we maybe don't yet understand, but we'll one day understand
what that mapping is.
But it maps reliably.
It is tethered in that way.
Well, yes.
And so the new theories that the physicists are finding beyond space time have that kind of
tethering.
So they show precisely how you start with an amplitude hydrant
and how you project this high-dimensional structure into the four dimensions of space time.
So there's a precise procedure that relates the two.
And they're doing the same thing with the cosmological polytopes.
So they're the ones that are making the most concrete and fun advances going beyond space time.
And they're tethering it.
They say this is precisely the mathematical projection from this deeper structure into space time.
One thing I'll say about, as a nonphysicist, what I find interesting is that they're finding just
geometry, but there's no notion of dynamics.
Right now, they're just finding these static geometric structures,
which is impressive.
So I'm not putting them down.
This is what they're doing is unbelievably complicated and brilliant and adventurous.
It's all those things.
And beautiful from a human aesthetic perspective because geometry is beautiful.
It's absolutely.
And they're finding symmetries that are true of the data that can't be seen in space time.
But I'm looking for a theory beyond space time that's a dynamical theory.
I would love to find, and we can talk about that at some point, a theory of consciousness in which
the dynamics of consciousness itself will give rise to the geometry that the physicists are
finding beyond space time.
If we can do that, then we'd have a completely different way of looking at how consciousness
is related to what we call the brain or the physical world more generally.
Right now, all of my brilliant colleagues, about 99% of them, are trying to...
They're assuming space time is fundamental.
They're assuming that particles are fundamental, quarks, gluons, leptons, and so forth.
Elements, atoms, and so forth are fundamental.
And that therefore neurons and brains are part of objective reality.
And that somehow when you get matter that's complicated enough,
it will somehow generate conscious experiences by its functional properties.
Or if you're panpsychist, maybe in addition to the physical properties of particles, you add
consciousness property as well.
And then you combine these physical and conscious properties to get more complicated ones.
But they're all doing it within space time.
All of the work that's being done on consciousness and its relationship
to the brain has all assumed something that our best theories are telling us is doomed,
space time.
Why does that particular assumption bother you the most?
So you bring up space time.
I mean, that's just one useful interface we've used for a long time.
Surely there's other interfaces.
Is space time just one of the big ones that you...
To build up people's intuition about the fact that they do assume a lot of things strongly?
Or is it in fact the fundamental flaw in the way we see the world?
Well, everything else that we think we know are things in space time.
Sure.
And so when you say space time is doomed, this is a shot to the heart of the whole framework,
the whole conceptual framework that we've had in science.
Not to the scientific method, but to the fundamental ontology and also the fundamental
methodology, the ontology of space time and its contents, and the methodology of reductionism,
which is that as we go to smaller scales in space time, we will find more and more fundamental
laws.
And that's been very useful for space and time for centuries, reductionism for centuries.
But now we realize that that's over.
Reductionism is in fact dead as a space time.
What exactly is reductionism?
What is the process of reductionism that is different than some of the physicists that
you mentioned that are trying to let go of the assumption of space time?
What can be on?
Isn't that still trying to come up with a simple model that explains this whole thing?
Isn't it still reducing?
It's a wonderful question because it really helps to clarify two different notions,
which is scientific explanation on the one hand and a particular kind of scientific explanation
on the other, which is the reductionist.
So the reductionist explanation is saying, I will start with things that are smaller
in space time and therefore more fundamental, where the laws are more fundamental.
So we go to just smaller and smaller scales.
Whereas in science, more generally, we just say like when Einstein did the special theory
of relativity, he's saying, let me have a couple postulates.
I will assume that the speed of light is universal for all observers in uniform motion
and that the laws of physics, for uniform motion, are that's not a reductionist.
Those are saying, grant me these assumptions.
I can build this entire concept of space time out of it.
It's not a reductionist thing.
You're not going to smaller and smaller scales of space.
You're coming up with these deep, deep principles.
Same thing with this theory of gravity.
It's the falling elevator idea, right?
So it's not a reductionist kind of thing.
It's something different.
So simplification is a bigger thing than just reductionism.
Reductionism has been a particularly useful kind of scientific explanation,
for example, in thermodynamics, where the notion that we have of heat,
some macroscopic thing like temperature and heat.
It turns out that Neil Boltzmann and others discovered, well, hey, if we go to smaller
and smaller scales, we find these things called molecules or atoms.
If we think of them as bouncing around and having some kind of energy,
then what we call heat is really can be reduced to that.
So that's a particularly useful kind of reduction,
is a useful kind of scientific explanation that works within a range of scales
within space time.
But we know now precisely where that has to stop,
at 10 to the minus 33 centimeters and 10 to the minus 43 seconds.
And I would be impressed if it was 10 to the minus 33 trillion centimeters.
I'm not terribly impressed at 10 to the minus 33 centimeters.
I don't even know how to comprehend either of those numbers, frankly.
Just a small aside, because I am a computer science person,
I also find cellular automata beautiful.
So you have somebody like Stephen Wolfram, who recently has been very excitedly exploring
a proposal for a data structure that could be the numbers that would make you a little bit
happier in terms of scale, because they're very, very, very, very tiny.
So do you like this space of exploration of really thinking, letting go of space time,
letting go of everything and trying to think what kind of data structures could be
underneath this whole mess?
That's right.
So if they're thinking about these as outside of space time,
then that's what we have to do.
That's what our best theories are telling us.
You now have to think outside of space time.
Now, of course, I should back up and say, we know that Einstein surpassed Newton, right?
But that doesn't mean that there's not good work to do Newton.
There's all sorts of Newtonian physics that takes us to the moon and so forth,
and there's lots of good problems that we want to solve with Newtonian physics.
The same thing will be true of space time.
We'll still, it's not like we're going to stop using space time.
We'll continue to do all sorts of good work there.
But for those scientists who are really looking to go deeper, to actually find the next,
just like what Einstein did to Newton, what are we going to do to Einstein?
How do we get beyond Einstein and quantum theory to something deeper?
Then we have to actually let go.
And if we're going to do like this automata kind of approach,
it's critical that it's not automata in space time, it's automata prior to space time,
from which we're going to show how space time emerges.
If you're doing automata within space time, well, that might be a fun model,
but it's not the radical new step that we need.
Yeah, so the space time emerges from that whatever system,
and like you're saying, it's a dynamical system.
Do we even have an understanding what dynamical means when we go beyond?
When you start to think about dynamics, that could mean a lot of things.
Even causality could mean a lot of things if we realize that everything's an interface.
Like what, how much do we really know is an interesting question?
Because you brought up neurons, I got to ask you on another, yet another tangent.
There's a paper I remember a while ago looking at called,
Could a Neuroscientist Understand a Microprocessor?
And I just enjoyed that thought experiment that they provided, which is,
they basically, it's a couple of neuroscientists, Eric Jonas and Conrad Cording,
who use the tools of neuroscience to analyze a microprocessor.
I saw a computer chip.
If we lesion it here, what happens and so forth, and if you go and lesion in a computer,
it's very, very clear that lesion experiments on computers are not going to give you a lot
of insight into how it works.
And also the measurement devices and the kind of sort of just using the basic approaches of
neuroscience collecting the data, trying to intuit about the underlying function of it.
And that helps you understand that our scientific exploration of concepts,
depending on the field, are maybe in the very, very early stages.
I wouldn't say it leaves us astray.
Perhaps it does sometimes, but it's not a, it's not anywhere close to some fundamental
mechanism that actually makes the thing work.
I don't know if you can sort of comment on that in terms of using neuroscience to understand
the human mind and neurons.
Are we really far away potentially from understanding in the way we understand
the transistors enough to be able to build a computer?
So one thing about understanding is you can understand for fun.
The other one is to understand so you could build things.
And that's when you really have to understand.
Exactly.
In fact, what got me into the field that I at MIT was work by David Maher on this very topic.
So David Maher was a professor at MIT, but he'd done his PhD in neuroscience, studying
just the architectures of the brain.
But he realized that his work, it was on the cerebellum.
He realized that his work, as rigorous as it was, left him unsatisfied because he didn't
know what the cerebellum was for and why it had that architecture.
And so he went to MIT and he was in the AI lab there and he said, he had this three-level
approach that really grabbed my attention.
So when I was an undergrad at UCLA, I read one of his papers in a class and said,
who is this guy?
Because he said, you have to have a computational theory.
What is being computed and why?
An algorithm.
How is it being computed?
What are the algorithms?
And then the hardware.
How does it get instantiated in the hardware?
And so to really do neuroscience, he argued, we needed to have understanding at all those levels.
And that really got me.
I loved the neuroscience, but I realized this guy was saying, if you can't build it,
you don't understand it effectively.
And so that's why I went to MIT.
And I had the pleasure of working with David until he died just a year and a half later.
So there's been that idea that with neuroscience, we have to have,
in some sense, a top-down model of what's being computed and why
that we would then go after.
And the same thing with the trying to reverse engineer a computing system like your laptop.
We really need to understand what the user interface is about and why we have
what are keys on the keyboard for and so forth.
You need to know why to really understand all the circuitry and what it's for.
Now, evolution of a natural selection does not tell us the deeper question
that we're asking, the answer to the deeper question, which is why.
What's this deeper reality and what's it up to and why?
All it tells us is that whatever reality is, it's not what you see.
What you see is just an adaptive fiction.
So just to linger on this fascinating bold question that shakes you out of your dream state,
does this fiction still help you in building intuitions as literary fiction does about reality?
The reason we read literary fiction is it helps us build intuitions and an understanding
in indirect ways sneak up to the difficult questions of human nature.
Great fiction.
Same with this observed reality.
Does this interface that we get, this fictional interface,
help us build intuition about deeper truths of how this whole mess works?
Well, I think that each theory that we propose will give its own answer to that question.
When the physicists are proposing these structures like the amplitude
hydrant and cosmological polytope, associated hydrant and so forth, beyond space time,
we can then ask your question for those specific structures and say,
how much information, for example, does evolution of a natural selection and the
kinds of sensory systems that we have right now give us about this deeper reality?
And why did we evolve this way?
We can try to answer that question from within the deeper.
So there's not going to be a general answer.
I think what we'll have to do is posit these new deeper theories
and then try to answer your question within the framework of those deeper theories,
knowing full well that there'll be an even deeper theory.
So is this paralyzing though?
Because how do we know we're not completely adrift out to see
lost forever from, so like that our theories are completely lost?
So if it's all, if we can never truly deeply introspect to the bottom,
if it's always just turtles on top of turtles infinitely,
isn't that paralyzing for a scientific mind?
Well, it's interesting that you say introspect to the bottom,
because there is that, there is one, again, this isn't the same spirit of what I said before,
which is it depends on what answer you give to what's beyond space time,
what answer we would give to your question, right?
So but one answer that is interesting to explore is something that spiritual traditions
have said for thousands of years, but haven't said precisely.
So we can't take it seriously in science until it's made precise,
but we might be able to make it precise.
And that is that they've also said something like space and time aren't fundamental,
they're Maya, they're illusion.
And but that if you look inside, if you introspect
and let go of all of your particular perceptions,
you will come to something that's beyond conceptual thought.
And that is, they claim, being in contact with the deep ground of being that transcends
any particular conceptual understanding.
If that is correct, and I'm not saying it's correct,
but and I'm not saying it's not correct, I'm just saying if that's correct,
then it would be the case that as scientists, because we also are in touch with this ground of
being, we would then not be able to conceptually understand ourselves all the way.
But we could know ourselves just by being ourselves.
And so we would, there would be a sense in which there is a fundamental grounding to the whole
enterprise, because we're not separate from the enterprise.
This is the opposite of third, the impersonal third person science.
This would make science go personal all the way down.
And but but nevertheless, scientific, because the scientific method would still be
what we would use all the way down for the conceptual understanding.
Unfortunately, you still don't know if you went all the way down.
It's possible that this kind of whatever consciousness is, and we'll talk about it,
is getting the cliche statement of be yourself.
It is somehow digging at a deeper truth of reality, but you still don't know when you
get to the bottom, you know, a lot of people, they'll take psychedelic drugs, and they'll
say, well, that takes my mind to certain places where it feels like that is
revealing some deeper truth of reality.
But you still, it could be interfaces on top of interfaces.
That's, that's in your view of this, you really don't know.
I mean, Gato's incompleteness is that you really don't know.
My own view on it, for what it's worth, because I don't know the right answer,
but my own view on it right now is that it, it's never ending.
I think that there will never, that this is great, as I said before, great job security for science,
and that we, if this is true, and if, if consciousness is somehow important or
fundamental in the universe, this may be an important fundamental fact about consciousness
itself, that, that it's never ending exploration that's going on in some sense.
Well, well, that's interesting, let me push back on the job security.
Okay.
So maybe as we understand this kind of idea deeper and deeper, we understand that the pursuit
is not a fruitful one, that maybe we need to, maybe that's why we don't see aliens everywhere,
is you get smarter and smarter and smarter.
You realize that like exploration is, there's other fun ways to spend your time than exploring.
You could be, you could be sort of living maximally in some way that's not exploration.
You know, I could, there's all kinds of video games you can construct and put yourself inside
of them that don't involve you going outside of the game world.
It's, you know, feeling for my human perspective, what seems to be fun is challenging yourself,
and overcoming those challenges.
So you can constantly artificially generate challenges for yourself,
like Sisyphus and his boulder, just, and that's it.
So the scientific method that's always reaching out to the stars, that's always trying to figure
out the puzzle on bottom puzzle, the trick, always trying to get to the bottom turtle.
Maybe if we can build more and more the intuition that that's infinite pursuit, we get,
we agree to start deviating from that pursuit, start enjoying the here and now versus the
looking out into the unknown always.
Maybe that's looking out into the unknown is a early activity for a species that's evolved.
I'm just sort of saying pushing back is you probably got a lot of scientists excited in terms
of job security.
I could envision where it's not job security or scientists become more and more useless.
Maybe they're like the holders of the ancient wisdom that allows us to study our own history,
but not much more than that.
Just to find pushback.
That's good pushback.
I'll put one in there for the scientists again, but sure.
But then I'll take the other side too.
So when Faraday did all of his experiments with magnets and electricity and so forth,
came with all this wonderful empirical data and James Clerk Maxwell looked at it and
wrote down a few equations, which we can now write down in a single equation,
the Maxwell equation if we use geometric algebra, just one equation.
That opened up unbelievable technologies where people are zooming and talking to each other
around the world, the whole electronics industry.
There was something that transformed our lives in a very positive way.
With the theories beyond space time, here's one potential.
Right now, most of the galaxies that we see, we can see them,
but we know that we could never get to them no matter how fast we traveled.
They're going away from us at the speed of light or beyond, so we can't ever get to them.
There's all this beautiful real estate that's just smiling and waving at us,
and we can never get to it.
But that's if we go through space time.
But if we recognize that space time is just a data structure, it's not fundamental.
We're not little things inside space time.
Space time was a little data structure in our perceptions.
It's just the other way around.
Once we understand that and we get equations for the stuff that's beyond space time,
maybe we won't have to go through space time.
Maybe we can go around it.
Maybe I can go to Proxima Centauri and not go through space.
I can just go right there directly.
It's a data structure.
We can start to play with it.
I think that for what it's worth, my take would be that the endless
sequence of theories that we could contemplate building will lead to an endless
sequence of new remarkable insights into the potentialities, the possibilities
that would seem miraculous to us, and that we will be motivated to continue the exploration
partly just for the technological innovations that come out.
But the other thing that you mentioned, though, what about just being?
What have we decided instead of all this doing and exploring what about being?
My guess is that the best scientists will do both and that the act of being
will be a place where they get many of their ideas and that they then pull into their conceptual
realm.
And I think many of the best scientists, Einstein comes to mind where these guys say,
look, I didn't come up with these ideas by a conceptual analysis.
I was thinking in vague images and it was just something non-conceptual.
And then it took me a long, long time to pull it out into concepts and then
longer to put it into math.
But the real insights didn't come from just slavishly playing with equations.
They came from a deeper place.
And so there may be this going back and forth between the complete non-conceptual
where there's essentially no end to the wisdom.
And then conceptual systems where there's the girdle limits that we have to that.
And that may be if consciousness is important and fundamental.
That may be what consciousness, at least part of what consciousness is about, is this
discovering itself, discovering its possibilities, so to speak.
And we can talk about what that might mean by going from the non-conceptual to the conceptual
back and forth to get better and better and better at being.
Right.
Let me ask you, just to link on the evolutionary, because you mentioned
evolutionary game theory and that's really where you, the perspective from which you come
to form the case against reality.
At which point in our evolutionary history do we start to deviate the most from reality?
Is it way before life even originated on earth?
Is it in the early development from bacteria and so on?
Or is it when some inklings of what we think of as intelligence or maybe even
complex consciousness started to emerge?
So where did this deviation, just like with the interfaces in a computer,
you start with transistors and then you have assembly and then you have C, C++,
then you have Python, then you have GUIs, all that kind of, you have layers upon layers.
When did we start to deviate?
Well, David Maher, again, my advisor at MIT, in his book Vision, suggested that the more
primitive sensory systems were less realistic, less theoretical, but that by the time you got
to something as complicated as the humans, we were actually estimating the true
shapes and distances to objects and so forth.
So his point of view, and I think it was probably, it's not an uncommon view among
my colleagues, that the sensory systems of lower creatures may just not be complicated
enough to give them much, much truth.
But as you get to 86 billion neurons, you can now compute the truth or at least
the parts of the truth that we need.
When I look at evolutionary game theory,
one of my graduate students, Justin Mark, did some simulations using genetic algorithms.
So there, he was just exploring, we start off with random organisms, random sensory genetics
and random actions and the first generation was unbelievably, there was a foraging situation,
they were foraging for resources and most of them, you know, stayed in one place,
didn't do anything important and, but we could then just look at how the genes evolved and what
we found was, what he found was that basically you never even saw the truth organisms even come
on the stage.
If they came, they were gone in one generation, they just weren't.
So they came and went, even just in one generation, they just are not good enough.
The ones that were just tracking, their senses just were tracking the fitness payoffs
were far more fit than the truth seekers.
So from, so an answer at one level, I want to give an answer to a deeper level,
but just with evolutionary game theory, because my attitude as a scientist is,
I don't believe any of our theories.
I take them very, very seriously, I study them, I look at their implications, but
none of them are the gospel, they're just the latest ideas that we have.
So the reason I study evolutionary game theory is because that's the best tool we have
right now in this area.
There is nothing else that competes.
So as a scientist is my responsibility to take the best tools and see what they mean.
And the same thing the physicists are doing, they're taking the best tools and looking at what
they entail.
But I don't, I think that science now has enough experience to realize that we should not
believe our theories in the sense that we've now arrived.
In 1890, it was a lot of physicists thought we'd arrived.
They were discouraging bright young students from going into physics because it was all done.
And that's precisely the wrong attitude.
Forever is the wrong attitude forever.
The attitude we should have is a century from now, they'll be looking at us and laughing
at what we didn't know.
And we just have to assume that that's going to be the case.
Just know that everything that we think is so brilliant right now, our final theory of
everything.
A century from now, they'll look at us like we look at the physicists of 1890 and go,
how could they have been so dumb?
Yeah, so I don't want to make that mistake.
So I'm not Dr. Nair about any of our current scientific theories.
I am Dr. Nair about this.
We should use the best tools we have right now.
And with humility.
Well, so let me ask you about game theory.
There's, I love game theory, evolution game theory, but I'm always suspicious of it,
like economics.
When you construct models, it's too easy to construct things that oversimplify
just because we are human brains enjoy the simplification of constructing a few variables
that somehow represent organisms or represent people and running a simulation that then allows
you to build up intuition.
And then it feels really good because you can get some really deep and surprising intuitions.
But how do you know your models aren't the assumptions underlying your models on some
fundamentally flawed.
And because of that, your conclusions are fundamentally flawed.
So I guess my question is, what are the limits in your use of game theory,
evolution game theory, your experience with it?
What are the limits of game theory?
So I've gotten some pushback from professional colleagues and friends who have tried to rerun
simulations and try to, the idea that we don't see the truth is not comfortable.
And so many of my colleagues are very interested in trying to show that we're wrong.
And so the idea would be to say that somehow we did something, as you're suggesting,
maybe something special that wasn't completely general.
We've got some little special part of the whole search space and evolutionary game theory
in which this happens to be true.
But more generally, organisms would evolve to see the truth.
So the best pushback we've gotten is from a team at Yale.
And they suggested that if you use thousands of payoff functions,
our simulations would just use a couple, one or two,
because it was our first simulations.
So that would be a limit.
We had one or two payoff functions we showed the result in those,
at least for the genetic algorithms.
And they said, if you have 20,000 of them, then we can find these conditions in which
truth-seeing organisms would be the ones that evolved and survived.
And so we looked at their simulations, and it certainly is the case that you can find
special cases in which truth can evolve.
So when I say it's probability zero, it doesn't mean it can't happen.
It can happen.
In fact, it could happen infinitely often.
It's just probability zero.
So if probability zero things can happen infinitely often.
When you say probability zero, you mean probability close to zero.
To be very precise.
So for example, if I have a unit square on the plane,
and I use a probability measure in which the area of a region is this probability,
then if I draw a curve in that unit square,
it has measure precisely zero, precisely, not approximately, precisely zero.
And yet it has infinitely many points.
So there's an object that for that probability measure has probability zero,
and yet there's infinitely many points in it.
So that's what I mean when I say that the things that are probability zero
can happen infinitely often in principle.
Yeah, but infinity, as far as I, and I look outside often at walk around
and I look at people, I haven't never seen infinity in real life.
That's an interesting issue.
I've been looking.
I don't notice it, infinitely small or the infinitely big.
And so the tools of mathematics, you could sort of apply the same kind of criticism
that it is a very convenient interface into our reality.
That's a big debate in mathematics.
The intuitionist versus the ones who take, for example, the real numbers as real.
And that's a fun discussion.
Nicholas Giesen has a physicist who has a really interesting work recently
on how if you go with intuitionist mathematics,
you could effectively quantize Newton, and you find that Newtonian theory and quantum theory
aren't that different once you go with it.
It's funny.
It's really quite interesting.
So the issue you raise is a very, very deep one, and one that I think we should take quite
seriously, which is how shall we think about the reality of the contrast hierarchy,
a1, a2, and all these different infinities versus just a more algorithmic approach, right?
So everything's computable in some sense.
Everything's finite as big as you want, but nevertheless finite.
So yeah, ultimately boils down to whether the world is discrete or continuous in some
general sense.
And again, we can't really know, but there's just a mind-breaking thought, just common sense
reasoning, that something can happen and is yet probability of it happening is 0%.
That doesn't compute for common sense computer.
Right.
This is where you have to be a sharp mathematician to really, and I'm not.
Sharp is one word.
What I'm saying is common sense computer is, I mean that in a very kind of,
in a positive sense, because we've been talking about perception systems and interfaces,
if we are to reason about the world, we have to use the best interfaces we got.
And I'm not exactly sure that game theory is the best interface we got for this.
And applications of mathematics, tricks and tools of mathematics to game theory is the
best we got when we're thinking about the nature of reality and fitness functions and
evolution, period.
Well, that's a fair rejoinder.
And I think that that was the tool that we used.
And if someone says, here's a better mathematical tool, and here's why.
This is this mathematical tool better captures the essence of Darwin's idea.
John Maynard Smith didn't quite get it with evolutionary game theory.
There's this better, this thing.
Now, there are tools like evolutionary graph theory, which generalize evolutionary game
theory.
And then there's quantum game theory.
So you can use quantum tools like entanglement, for example, as a resource in games,
that change the very nature of the solutions, the optimal solutions of the game theory.
Well, the work from Yale is really interesting.
It's a really interesting challenge of these ideas where, okay, if you have a very large
number of fitness functions, or let's say you have a nearly infinite number of fitness functions,
or a growing number of fitness functions, what kind of interesting things start to emerging?
If you are to be an organism, if to be an organism that adapts means having to deal with
an ensemble of fitness functions.
Right.
And so we've actually redone some of our own work based on theirs.
And this is the back and forth that we expect in science, right?
And what we found was that in their simulations, they were assuming that you
couldn't carve the world up into objects.
And so we said, well, let's relax that assumption.
Allow organisms to create data structures that we might call objects.
And an object would be you take, you would do hierarchical clustering
of your fitness payoff functions, the ones that have similar shapes.
If you have 20,000 of them, maybe these 50 are all very, very similar.
So I can take all the perception action fitness stuff and make that into a data structure,
and we'll call that a unit or an object.
And as soon as we did that, then all of their results went away.
It turned out they were the special case and that the organisms that were allowed
to only see, that were shaped to see only fitness payoffs were the ones that were.
So the idea is that objects then, what are objects from an evolutionary point of view?
This bottle, we thought that when I saw a bottle, it was because I was seeing a true
object that existed whether or not it was perceived.
Evolutionary theories suggest a different interpretation.
I'm seeing a data structure that is encoding a convenient way of looking at various fitness
payoffs. I can use this for drinking. I could use it as a weapon, not a very good one.
I could beat someone with head with it. If my goal is mating, this is pointless.
So I'm seeing for what I'm coding here is all sorts of actions and the payoffs that I could get.
When I pick up an apple, now I'm getting a different set of actions and payoffs for.
When I pick up a rock, I'm getting, so for every object, what I'm getting is a different set
of payoff functions with various actions. And so once you allow that, then what you find is once
again that truth goes extinct and the organisms that just get an interface are the ones that that
win. But the question I'm just sneaking up on, this is fascinating, from where do fitness functions
originate? What gives birth to the fitness functions? So if there's a giant black box that
just keeps giving you fitness functions, what are we trying to optimize? You said that water
has different uses than an apple. So there's these objects. What are we trying to optimize?
And why is not reality a really good generator of fitness functions?
So each theory makes its own assumptions and says, grant me this and I'll explain that. So
evolutionary game theory says grant me fitness payoffs, right? And grant me strategies with payoffs
and I can write down the matrix for this strategy interacts with that strategy. These are the payoffs
that come up. If you grant me that, then I can start to explain a lot of things. Now you can ask
for a deeper question like, okay, how does physics evolve biology and where do these fitness payoffs
come from? Now that's a completely different enterprise and of course evolutionary game
theory then would be not the right tool for that. It would have to be a deeper tool that
shows where evolutionary game theory comes from. My own take is that there's going to be a
problem in doing that because space time isn't fundamental. It's just a user interface and
that the distinction that we make between living and non-living is not a fundamental distinction.
It's an artifact of the limits of our interface. So this is a new wrinkle and this is an important
wrinkle. It's so nice to take space and time as fundamental because if something looks like it's
inanimate, it's inanimate and we can just say it's not living. Now it's much more complicated.
Certain things are obviously living. I'm talking with you. I'm obviously interacting with something
that's alive and conscious. I think we've let go of the word obviously in this conversation.
I think nothing is obvious. Nothing's obvious, that's right. But when we get down to like
an ant, it's obviously living but I'll say it appears to be living. When we get down to a virus,
now people wonder and when we get down to protons, people say it's not living and my attitude is,
look, I have a user interface. The interface is there to hide certain aspects of reality
and others to... It's an uneven representation, put it that way. Certain things just get
completely hidden. Dark matter and dark energy are most of the energy and matter that's out there.
Our interface just flat out hides them. The only way we get some hint is because
gravitational things are going wrong within our... So most things are outside of our interface.
The distinction between living and non-living is not fundamental. It's an artifact of our
interface. So if we really want to understand where evolution comes from to answer the question,
the deep question you asked, I think the right way we're going to have to do that is to come up
with a deeper theory than spacetime in which there may not be the notion of time and show that
whatever this dynamics of that deeper theory is. By the way, I'll talk about how you could have
dynamics without time, but the dynamics of this deeper theory, when we project it into,
in certain ways, then we do get spacetime and we get what appears to be evolution by natural
selection. So I would love to see evolution by natural selection. Nature, red and tooth and
claw, people fighting and animals fighting for resources and the whole bit, come out of a deeper
theory in which perhaps it's all cooperation. There's no limited resources and so forth,
but as a result of projection, you get space and time, and as a result of projection, you get
nature, red and tooth and claw, the appearance of it, but it's all an artifact of the interface.
I like this idea that the line between living and non-living is very important
because that's the thing that would emerge before you have evolution, the idea of death.
So that seems to be an important component of natural selection, and if that emerged,
because that's also asking the question, I guess, that I ask, where do fitness
functions come from? That's like asking the old meaning of life question, right? It's what's the
why, why, why? And one of the big underlying whys, okay, you can start with evolution on earth,
but without living, without life and death, without the line between the living and the dead,
you don't have evolution. So what if underneath it, there's no such thing as the living and the dead?
There's no, like this concept of an organism period. There's a living organism that's defined
by a volume and space time that somehow interacts, that over time maintains its integrity somehow,
it has some kind of history, it has a wall of some kind, the outside world, the environment,
and then inside there's an organism. So you're defining an organism, and also you're defining
that organism by the fact that it can move, and it can become alive, which you kind of think of as
moving, combined with the fact that it's keeping itself separate from the environment. So you can
point out that thing is living, and then it can also die. That seems to be of all very
powerful components of space time that enable you to have something like natural selection and
evolution. Well, and there's a lot of interesting work, some of it by collaborators of Carl Friston
and others where they have Bayes net kind of stuff that they build on and the notion of a
Markov blanket. So you have some states within this network that are inside the blanket, then you
have the blanket, and then the states outside the blanket, and the states inside this Markov blanket
are conditionally independent of the states outside the blanket conditioned on the blanket.
And what they're looking at is that the dynamics inside of the states inside the Markov blanket
seem to be trying to estimate properties of the outside and react to them in a way. So it seems
like you're doing probabilistic inferences in ways that might be able to keep you alive. So
there's interesting work going on in that direction. But what I'm saying is something
slightly different. And that is, like when I look at you, all I see is skin heronize, right? That's
all I see. But I know that there's a deeper reality. I believe that there's a much deeper
reality. There's the whole world of your experiences, your thoughts, your hopes, your dreams.
In some sense, the face that I see is just a symbol that I create, right? And as soon as I
look away, I delete that symbol. But I don't delete you. I don't delete the conscious experience,
the whole world of your... So I'm only deleting an interface symbol. But that interface symbol
is a portal, so to speak. Not a perfect portal, but a genuine portal into your beliefs, into your
conscious experiences, into... That's why we can have a conversation. Your consciousness is
genuinely affecting mine. Mine is genuinely affecting yours. Through these icons, which I
create on the fly. I mean, I create your face when I look, I delete it. I don't create you,
your consciousness, that's there all the time. But I do... So now when I look at a cat, I'm creating
something that I still call living, and I still think is conscious. When I look at an ant, I create
something that I still would call living, but maybe not conscious. When I look at something I call a
virus, now I'm not even sure I would call it living. And when I look at a proton, I would say,
I don't even think it's not alive at all. It could be that I'm nevertheless
interacting with something that's just as conscious as you. I'm not saying the proton is
conscious. The face that I'm creating when I look at you, that face is not conscious. That face
is a data structure in me. That face isn't... It's an experience. It's not an experiencer.
Similarly, a proton is something that I create when I look or do a collision
in the Large Hadron Collider or something like that. But what is behind the entity and space time?
So I've got this space-time interface, and I just got this entity that I call a proton.
What is the reality behind it? Well, the physicists are finding these big, big structures,
ample two Hadron, the associate Hadron. What's behind those? Could be consciousness,
what I'm playing with. In which case, when I'm interacting with a proton,
I could be interacting with consciousness. Again, to be very, very clear, because it's
easy to... Listen, I'm not saying a proton is conscious. Just like I'm not saying your face
is conscious. Your face is a symbol I create and then delete as I look. And so your face is not
conscious, but I know that that face in my interface, the Lex Friedman face that I create,
is an interface symbol that's a genuine portal into your consciousness. The portal is less clear
for a cat, even less clear for an ant. And by the time we get down to a proton, the portal is not
clear at all. But that doesn't mean I'm not interacting with consciousness. It just means
my interface gave up. And there's some deeper reality that we have to go after. So your question
really forces out a big part of this whole approach that I'm talking about.
So this portal and consciousness, I wonder why you can't... Your portal is not as good to a cat,
to a cat's consciousness than it is to a human. Does it have to be...
It has to do with the fact that you're human and just similar organisms, organisms of similar
complexity, are able to create portals better to each other? Or is it just...
As you get more and more complex, you get better and better portals?
Well, let me answer one aspect that I'm more confident about. Then I'll speculate on that.
Why is it that the portal is so bad with protons and elementary particles more generally? So quarks,
leptons, and gluons, and so forth? Well, the reason for that is because those are just
symmetries of spacetime. More technically, they're irreducible representations of the
Poincar group of spacetime. So they're just literally representations of the data structure
of spacetime that we're using. So that's why they're not very much insightful. They're just almost
entirely tied to the data structure itself. There's not much... They're telling you only
something about the data structure, not behind the data structure. It's only when we get to higher
levels that we're starting to, in some sense, build portals to what's behind spacetime.
Sure. Yeah. So there's more and more complexity built on top of the interface of spacetime with the
cat. So you can actually build a portal, right? Yeah, right. Yeah, this interface of face and hair
and so on, skin. There's some sinking going on between humans, though, where we sink. You're
getting a pretty good representation of the ideas in my head and starting to get a foggy view of my
memories in my head. Even though this is the first time we're talking, you start to project your own
memories. You start to solve a giant hierarchy of puzzles about a human, because we're all... There's
a lot of similarities, a lot of it rhymes. So you start to make a lot of inferences and you build
up this model of a person. You have a pretty sophisticated model of what's going on underneath.
Again, I just... I wonder if it's possible to construct these models about each other and
nevertheless be very distant from an underlying reality. There's a lot of work on this. So there's
some interesting work called Signaling Games, where they look at how people can coordinate and
come to communicate. There's some interesting work that was done by some colleagues and friends of
mine, Louis Naranze and Natalia Komarova and Kimberly Jamison, where they were looking at
evolving color words. So you have a circle of colors, the color circle, and they wanted to see
if they could get people to cooperate and how they carved the color circle up into units of words.
So they had a game, theoretic kind of thing that they'd had people do. What they found was that
so most people are trichromats. You have three kinds of cone photoreceptors, but there are some
a lot of men, 7% of men have our dichromats. They might be missing the red cone photoreceptor.
They found that the dichromats had an outsized influence on the final ways that the whole
space of colors was carved up and labels attached. You needed to be able to include the dichromats
in the conversation. So they had a bigger influence on how you made the boundaries
of the language. I thought that was a really interesting kind of insight that there's going
to be, again, a game, perhaps a game or evolutionary or genetic algorithm kind of thing that goes on
in terms of learning to communicate in ways that are useful. So yeah, you can use game theory to
actually explore that or signaling games. There's a lot of brilliant work on that. I'm not doing it,
but there's work out there. So if it's okay, let us tackle once more and perhaps several more
times after the big topic of consciousness. This very beautiful, powerful things that perhaps is
the thing that makes us human. What is it? What's the role of consciousness in, let's say even just
the thing we've been talking about, which is the formation of this interface,
any kind of ways you want to kind of start talking about it?
Well, let me say first what most of my colleagues say. 99% are, again, assuming that
spacetime is fundamental. Particles in spacetime matter is fundamental. And most are reductionist.
And so the standard approach to consciousness is to figure out what complicated systems of matter
with the right functional properties could possibly lead to the emergence of consciousness.
That's the general idea. So maybe you have to have neurons. Maybe only if you have neurons,
but that might not be enough. They have certain kinds of complexity in their
organization and their dynamics, certain kind of network abilities, for example.
So there are those who say, for example, that consciousness arises from orchestrated collapse
of quantum states of microtubules and neurons. So this is Hamroff and Kenrose have this kind of.
So you start with something physical, a property of quantum states of neurons,
of microtubules and neurons. And you say that somehow an orchestrated collapse of those
is consciousness or conscious experiences. Or integrated information theory. Again,
you start with something physical. And if it has the right kind of functional properties,
it's something they call fee, with the right kind of integrated information,
then you have consciousness. Or you can be a panpsychist, Philip Goff, for example,
where you might say, well, in addition to the particles in space and time,
those particles are not just matter, they also could have a unit of consciousness.
And so, but once again, you're taking space and time and particles as fundamental.
And you're adding a new property to them, say consciousness. And then you have to talk about
how when a proton and a neutron or proton and electron get together to form hydrogen,
then how those consciousnesses merge to or interact to create the consciousness of hydrogen,
so forth. There's attention schema theory, which again, this is how neural network
processes representing to the network itself, it's attentional processes, that could be
consciousness. There's global workspace theory. And neuronal global workspace theory.
Workspace theory. So there's many, many theories of this type. What's common to all of them
is they assume that space time is fundamental. They assume that physical processes in space
time is fundamental. Panpsychism adds consciousness as an additional thing,
it's almost dualist in that regard. And my attitude is, our best science is telling us
that space time is not fundamental. So why is that important here? Well, for centuries,
deep thinkers thought of earth, air, fire, and water as the fundamental elements.
It was a reductionist kind of idea. Nothing was more elemental than those. And you could
sort of build everything up from those. When we got the periodic table of elements,
we realized that, of course, we want to study earth, air, fire, and water. There's combustion
science for fire. There's sciences for all these other things, water and so forth. So we're going
to do science for these things, but fundamental, no, no. If you're looking for something fundamental,
those are the wrong building blocks. Earth has many, many different kinds of elements
that project into the one thing that we call earth. If you don't understand that there's
silicon, that there's iron, that there's all these different kinds of things that project
into what we call earth, you're hopelessly lost. You're not fundamental. You're not going to get
there. And then after the periodic table, then we came up with quarks, leptons, and gluons,
the particles of the standard model of physics. And so we actually now know that if you really
want to get fundamental, the periodic table isn't it. It's good for chemistry and it's just
wonderful for chemistry. But if you're trying to go deep, fundamental, what is the fundamental
science? That's not it. You're going to have to go to quarks, leptons, and gluons, and so forth.
Well, now we've discovered spacetime itself is doomed. Quarks, leptons, and gluons are just
irreducible representations of the symmetries of spacetime. So the whole framework on which
consciousness research is being based right now is doomed. And for me, these are my friends and
colleagues that are doing this, they're brilliant. They're absolute, they're brilliant. I, my feeling
is, I'm so sad that they're stuck with this old framework, because if they weren't stuck,
like with earth, air, fire, and water, you could actually make progress. So it doesn't matter how
smart you are. If you start with earth, air, fire, and water, you're not going to get anywhere, right?
Can I actually just, because the word doomed is so interesting. Let me give you some options,
multiple choice quiz. It's spacetime, we could say is reality, the way we perceive it, doomed,
wrong, or fake. Because doomed just means it could still be right, and we're now ready to go deeper.
It would be that.
So it's not wrong. It's not a complete deviation from a journey toward the truth.
Right. It's like earth, air, fire, and water is not wrong. There is earth, air, fire, and water.
That's a useful framework, but it's not fundamental.
Right. Well, there's also wrong, which is, they used to believe, as I recently learned,
that George Washington was the president, the first president in the United States,
was blood to death for something that could have been easily treated,
because it was believed that you can get, actually, I need to look into this further,
but I guess you get toxins out or demons out. I don't know what you're getting out with the
bleeding of a person, but so that ended up being wrong, but widely believed as a medical tool.
So it's also possible that our assumption of spacetime is not just doomed, but it's wrong.
Well, if we believe that it's fundamental, that's wrong. But if we believe it's a useful tool,
that's right. But bleeding somebody to death was believed to be a useful tool.
It wasn't just not fundamental. I'm sure there's cases in which bleeding somebody
would work, but it would be a very tiny, tiny, tiny percentage of cases. So it could be that it's
wrong, like it's a side road that's ultimately leading to a dead end, as opposed to a truck
stop or something that you can get off of. My feeling is it's not the dead end kind of thing.
I think that what the physicists are finding is that there are these structures beyond
spacetime, but they project back into spacetime. And so spacetime, when they say
spacetime is doomed, they're explicit. They're saying it's doomed in the sense that
we thought it was fundamental. It's not fundamental. It's a useful,
absolutely useful and brilliant data structure, but there are deeper data structures like cosmological
polytool. And spacetime is not fundamental. What is doomed in the sense that it's wrong
is reductionism. Which is saying spacetime is fundamental.
Essentially. Right, right. The idea that somehow
being smaller in spacetime is a fundamental nature of reality, that's just wrong. It turned out to
be a useful heuristic for thermodynamics and so forth, and several other places,
reductionism has been very useful. But that's in some sense an artifact of how we use our interface.
Yeah, so you're saying size doesn't matter. Okay, this is very important for me to write
down ultimately. It's useful for theories like thermodynamics and also for understanding brain
networks in terms of individual neurons and neurons in terms of chemical systems inside cells.
That's all very, very useful. But the idea that we're getting to the more fundamental nature of
reality, no. When you get all the way down in that direction, you get down to the quarks and
gluons. What you realize is what you've gotten down to is not fundamental reality, just the
irreducible representations of a data structure. That's all you've gotten down to. So you're always
stuck inside the data structure. So you seem to be getting closer and closer. I went from neural
networks to neurons, to neurons to chemistry, chemistry to particles, particles to clerks and
gluons. No, I'm getting closer and closer to the actual structure of the data structure of
space and time, the irreducible representations. That's what you're getting closer to,
not to a deeper understanding of what's beyond space-time.
We'll also refer, we'll return again to this question of dynamics, because you keep
saying that space-time is doomed, but mostly focusing on the space part of that. It's very
interesting to see why time gets the bad cred too, because how do you have dynamics without time is
the thing I'd love to talk to you a little bit about. But let us return your brilliant whirlwind
overview of the different theories of consciousness that are out there.
What is consciousness if outside of space-time? If we think that we want to have a model of
consciousness, we as scientists then have to say, what do we want to write down? What kind of
mathematical model are we going to write down? And if you think about it, there's lots of things
that you might want to write down about consciousness. It's a really complicated subject.
So most of my colleagues are saying, let's start with matter or neurons and
say what properties of matter could create consciousness. But I'm saying that that whole
thing is out. Space-time is doomed, that whole thing is out. We need to look at consciousness,
qua consciousness. In other words, not as something that arises in space and time,
but perhaps as something that creates space and time as a data structure.
So what do we want? And here again, there's no hard and fast rule, but what you as a
scientist have to do is to pick what you think are the minimal assumptions that are going to
allow you to boot up a comprehensive theory. That is the trick. So what do I want? So what I
chose to do was to have three things. I said that there are conscious experiences,
feeling of headache, the smell of garlic, experiencing the color red. So that's a
primitive of theory. And the reason I want few primitives, because those are the miracles of
the theory, right? The primitives, the assumptions of the theory are the things you're not going
to explain. Those are the things you assume. And those experiences you particularly mean
there is a subjectiveness to them. That's the thing when people refer to the hard problem
of consciousness is it feels like something to look at the color red. Okay.
Exactly. It feels like something to have a headache or to feel upset to your stomach.
It feels like something. And so I'm going to grant that in this theory, there are experiences
and they're fundamental in some sense. So conscious experience. So they're not derived
from physics. They're not functional properties of particles. They are sui generis. They exist.
Just like we assume space time exists. I'm now saying space time is just a data structure. It
doesn't exist independent of conscious experiences. Sorry to interrupt once again, but should we be
focusing in your thinking on humans alone? Or is there something about in relation to other kinds
of organisms that have a sufficiently high level of complexity? Or is there some kind of
generalization of the panpsychist idea that all consciousness permeates all matter
outside of the usual definition of what matter is inside space time?
So it's beyond human consciousness. Human consciousness, from my point of view, would be
one of a countless variety of consciousnesses. And even within human consciousness, there's
countless variety of consciousnesses within us. You have your left and right hemisphere.
And apparently, if you split the corpus callosum, the personality of the left hemisphere and the
religious belief of the left hemisphere can be very different from the right hemisphere.
And their conscious experiences can be disjoint. One could have one conscious experience.
They can play 20 questions. The left hemisphere can have an idea in its mind and the right
hemisphere has to guess. And it might not get it. So even within you, there is more than just
one consciousness. It's lots of consciousnesses. So the general theory of consciousness that I'm
after is not just human consciousness. It's going to be just consciousness. And I presume human
consciousness is a tiny drop in the bucket of the infinite variety of consciousnesses.
That said, I should clarify that the black hole of consciousness is the home cat. I'm pretty sure
cat's lack is the embodiment of evil and lack all capacity for consciousness or compassion.
So I just want to lay that out. But that's the theory I'm working on. I don't have any
good evidence, but it's just a shout out. Sorry to distract. So that's the first assumption.
The first assumption is right. The second assumption is that these experiences have
consequences. So I'm going to say that conscious experiences can trigger other conscious experiences
somehow. So really, in some sense, there's two basic assumptions. There's some kind of
causality. Is there is a chain of causality? Does it relate to dynamics?
I'll say there's a probabilistic relationship. So I'm trying to be
as nonspecific to begin with and see where it leads me. So what I can write down are probability
spaces. So probability space, which contains the conscious experiences that this consciousness
can have. So I call this a conscious agent. This technical thing. Anika Harris and I've
talked about this and she rightly cautions me that people will think that I'm bringing in a
notion of a self or agency and so forth when I say conscious agent. So I just want to say that I
use the term conscious agent merely as a technical term. There is no notion of self in my fundamental
definition of a conscious agent. There are only experiences and probabilistic relationships
that of how they trigger other experiences. So the agent is the generator of the conscious
experience. The agent is a mathematical structure that includes a probability measure,
the probability space of possible conscious experiences and what an Amarcovian kernel,
which describes how if this agent has certain conscious experiences,
how that will affect the experiences of other conscious agents, including itself.
But you don't think of that as a self? No, there is no notion of a self here.
There's no notion of really of an agent. But is there a locality? Is there an organism?
So these are conscious units, conscious entities. But they're distinct
in some way because they have to interact. Well, so here's the interesting thing. When we write
down the mathematics, when you have two of these conscious agents interacting, the pair
satisfy a definition of a conscious agent. So they are a single conscious agent.
So there is one conscious agent. But it has a nice analytic decomposition into as many
conscious agents. So that's a nice interface. It's a very useful scientific interface. It's
a scale free or if you like a fractal like approach to it in which we can use the same
unit of analysis at all scales in studying consciousness. But if I want to talk about
so there's no notion of learning, memory, problem solving, intelligence, self, agency.
So none of that is fundamental. So and the reason I did that was because I want to assume
as little as possible. Everything I assume is a miracle in the theory. It's not something you
explain as something you assume. So I have to build networks of conscious agents.
If I want to have a notion of a self, I have to build a self. I have to build learning, memory,
problem solving, intelligence, and planning, all these different things. I have to build
networks of conscious agents to do that. It's a trivial theorem that networks of conscious agents
are computationally universal. That's trivial. So anything that we can do with neural networks
or automata, you can do with networks of conscious agents. That's trivial.
But you can also do more. The events in the probability space need not be computable. So
the Markovian dynamics is not restricted to computable functions because the very events
themselves need not be computable. So this can capture any computable theory. Anything we can
do with neural networks, we can do with conscious agent networks. But it leaves open the door for
the possibility of non computable interactions between conscious agents. So we have to, if we
want a theory of memory, we have to build it. And there's lots of different ways you could build.
We've actually got a paper, Chris Fields took the lead on this. And he, we have a paper called
conscious agent networks where Chris takes the lead and shows how to use these networks of
conscious agents to build memory and to build primitive kinds of learning.
But can you provide some intuition of what conscious networks, networks of conscious agents
helps you? Well, first of all, what that looks like. And I don't just mean mathematically,
of course, maybe that might help build up intuition, but how that helps us potentially
solve the hard problem of consciousness. Right. Or is that baked in that that exists?
Can you solve the hard problem of consciousness? Why it tastes delicious when you eat a delicious
ice cream with networks of conscious agents? Or is that taken as an assumption?
So the standard way the hard problem is thought of is we're assuming space and time in particles
or neurons, for example. These are just physical things that have no consciousness. And we have
to explain how the conscious experience of the taste of chocolate could emerge from those. So
that's the typical hard problem of consciousness is that problem, right? How do you boot up the taste
of chocolate, the experience of the taste of chocolate from neurons, say, or the right kind
of artificial intelligence circuitry? How do you boot that up? That's typically what the hard
problem of consciousness means to researchers. Notice that I'm changing the problem. I'm not
trying to boot up conscious experiences from the dynamics of neurons or silicon or something like
that. I'm saying that that's the wrong problem. My hard problem would go in the other direction.
If I start with conscious experiences, how do I build up space and time?
How do I build up what I call the physical world? How do I build up what we call brains?
Because I'm saying consciousness is not something that brains do.
Brains are something that consciousness makes up. It's an ephemeral experience
in consciousness. I look inside, so to be very, very clear, right now I have no neurons.
If you looked, you would see neurons. That's a data structure that you would create on the fly,
and it's a very useful one. As soon as you look away, you garbage collect that data structure,
just like that Necker cube that I was talking about on the piece of paper.
When you look, you see a 3D cube. You create it on the fly. As soon as you look away, that's gone.
When you say you, you mean a human being scientist?
Right now, that's right. More generally, it'll be conscious agents, because as you pointed out,
asking for theory of consciousness only about humans, no, it's consciousness, which human
consciousness is just a tiny sliver. But you are saying that there's a useful data structure.
How many other data structures are there? That's why I said you human. If there's another earth,
if there's another alien civilization and doing these kinds of investigations,
would they come up with similar data structures? Probably not.
What is the space of data structures, I guess, is what I'm asking.
My guess is that if consciousness is fundamental, consciousness is all there is,
then the only thing that mathematical structure can be about is possibilities of consciousness.
And that suggests to me that there could be an infinite variety of consciousnesses,
and a vanishingly small fraction of them use spacetime data structures,
and the kinds of structures that we use. There's an infinite variety of data structures.
Now, this is very similar to something that Max Tegmark has said, but I want to distinguish it.
He has his level four multiverse idea. He thinks that mathematics is fundamental.
And so that's the fundamental reality. And since there's an infinite variety of,
endless variety of mathematical structures, there's an infinite variety of multiverses
in his view. I'm saying something similar in spirit, but importantly different. There's
an infinite variety of mathematical structures, absolutely. But mathematics isn't the fundamental
reality in this framework. Consciousness is, and mathematics is to consciousness,
like bones are to an organism. You need the bones. So mathematics is not divorced from
consciousness, but it's not the entirety of consciousness by any means. And so there's an
infinite variety of consciousnesses and signaling games that consciousnesses could interact via.
And therefore worlds, common worlds, data structures that they can use to communicate.
So spacetime is just one of an infinite variety. And so I think that what we'll find is that as
we go outside of our little spacetime bubble, we will encounter utterly alien forms of conscious
experience that we may not be able to really comprehend in the following sense. If I ask
you to imagine a color that you've never seen before. Does anything happen? Nothing happens.
No. Nothing happens. And that's just one color. I'm asking for just a color. We actually know,
by the way, that apparently there are women called tetrafemes who have four color receptors,
not just three. And Kimberly Jamison and others who've studied these women have good evidence
that they apparently have a new dimension of color experience that the rest of us don't have.
So these women are apparently living in a world of color that you and I can't even
concretely imagine. No man can imagine them. And yet they're real color experiences. And so
in that sense, I'm saying now take that little baby step. Oh, there are women who have color
experiences that I could never have. Well, that's shocking. Now take that infinite. There are
consciousnesses where every aspect of their experiences is like that new color. It's something
utterly alien to you. You have nothing like that. And yet these are all possible varieties
of conscious experience. When you say there's a lot of consciousnesses as a singular consciousness,
basically the set of possible experiences you can have in that subjective way,
as opposed to the underlying mechanism. Because you say that, you know, having an
extra color receptor, you know, ability to have new experiences that somehow
a different consciousness, is there a way to see that as all the same consciousness,
the subjectivity itself? Right. Because when we have two of these conscious agents interacting,
the mathematics, they actually satisfy the definition of a conscious agent. So in fact,
they are a single conscious agent. So in fact, one way to think about what I'm saying, I'm
postulating with my colleagues, Chaitanya and Chris and others, Robert Prettner and so forth.
There is one big conscious agent, infinitely complicated. But fortunately, we can, for analytic
purposes, break it down all the way to, in some sense, the simplest conscious agent, which has
one conscious experience, one. This one agent can experience red 35. That's it. That's what
experiences. You can get all the way down to that. So you think it's possible that consciousness,
whatever that is, is much more, is fundamental, or at least much more in the direction of the
fundamental than is space time as we perceive it. That's the proposal. And therefore, what I have
to do in terms of the heart problem of consciousness is to show how dynamical systems of conscious
agents could lead to what we call space and time and neurons and brain activity. In other words,
we have to show how you get space time and physical objects entirely from a theory of
conscious agents outside of space time with the dynamics outside of space time. So I can tell you
how we plan to do that. But that's the idea. Okay. The magic of it, that chocolate is delicious.
So there's a mathematical kind of thing that we could say here, how it can emerge within the system
of networks of conscious agents. But
is there going to be at the end of the proof why chocolate is so delicious? Or no? I guess I'm
going to ask different kinds of dumb questions to try to sneak up.
Oh, well, that's the right question. And when I say that I took conscious experiences as fundamental,
what that means is in the current version of my theory, I'm not explaining conscious experiences
where they came from. That's the miracle. That's one of the miracles. So I have two
miracles in my theory. There are conscious experiences like the taste of chocolate,
and that there's a probabilistic relationship when certain conscious experiences occur,
others are more likely to occur. Those are the two miracles that are possible to
get beyond that and somehow start to chip away at the miracle-ness of that miracle.
That chocolate is still delicious. I hope so. I've got my hands full with what I'm doing right
now. But I can just say at top level how we would think about that. That would get at this
consciousness without form. This is really tough because it's consciousness without form versus
the various forms that consciousness takes for the experiences that it has.
Right. So when I write down a probability space for these conscious experiences,
I say, here's a probability space for the possible conscious experiences.
It's just like when I write down a probability space for an experiment. I'm going to flip a coin
twice. I want to look at the probabilities of various outcomes. So I have to write down a
probability space. There could be heads, heads, heads, tails, tails, tails, tails.
Any class in probability, you're told, write down your probability space. If you don't
write down your probability space, you can't get started. So here's my probability space for
consciousness. How do I want to interpret that structure? The structure is just sitting there.
There's going to be a dynamics that happens on it. Experiences appear and then they disappear.
Just like heads appears and disappears. So one way to think about that fundamental
probability space is that corresponds to consciousness without any content.
The infinite consciousness that transcends any particular content.
Well, do you think of that as a mechanism, as a thing,
like the rules that govern the dynamics of the thing outside of space-time?
If you think consciousness is fundamental, isn't it essentially getting like,
if it is solving the hard problem, which is like, from where does this thing pop up?
Which is the mechanism of the thing popping up. Whatever the consciousness is, the different
kinds was so on. That mechanism. And also the question I want to ask is, how tricky do you think
it is to solve that problem? You've solved a lot of difficult problems throughout the history of
humanity. There's probably more problems to solve left than we've solved by an infinity.
But along that long journey of intelligent species, when will we solve this consciousness one?
Which is one way to measure the difficulty of the problem.
So I'll give two answers. There's one problem I think we can solve, but we haven't solved yet.
And that is the reverse of what my colleagues call the hard problem.
The problem of how do you start with conscious experiences in the way that I've just described
them and the dynamics, and build up space and time and brains. That I think is a tough technical
problem, but some principle solvable. So I think we can solve that. So we would solve the hard
problem, not by showing our brains create consciousness, but how networks of conscious
agents create what we call the symbols that we call brains.
But does that allow you to... So that's interesting. That's an interesting idea.
Consciousness creates the brain, not the brain creates consciousness. But does that allow you
to build the thing? My guess is that it will enable unbelievable technologies. And I'll tell
you why. I think it plugs into the work that the physicists are doing. So this theory of consciousness
will be even deeper than the structures that the physicists are finding, like the Amplitude
Hadron. But the other answer to your question is less positive. As I said earlier, I think that
there is no such thing as a theory of everything. So that I think that the theory that my team is
working on, this conscious agent theory, is just a 1.0 theory. We're using probability
spaces and Markovian kernels. I can easily see people now saying, well, we can do better if we
go to category theory. And we can get a deeper, perhaps more interesting. And then someone will
say, well, now I'll go to Topoi theory. And then there'll be... So I imagine that there'll be,
you know, conscious agents 5, 10, 3 trillion, 0.0. But I think it will never end. I think ultimately,
this question that we sort of put our fingers on of, how does the formless give birth to form,
to the wonderful taste of chocolate? I think that we will always go deeper and deeper,
but we will never solve that. That in some sense, that will be a primitive. I hope I'm wrong.
Maybe it's just the limits of my current imagination. So I'll just say my imagination
right now doesn't peer that deep. Hopefully... So by the way, I'm saying this, I don't want to
discourage some brilliant 20-year-old who then later on proves me dead wrong. I hope to be proven
dead wrong. But just like you said, essentially from now, everything we're saying now, everything
you're saying, all your theories will be laughing stock. They will respect the puzzle-solving
abilities and how much we were able to do with so little. But outside of that, it will all be just
the silliness will be entertainment for a teenager. Especially the silliness when we
thought that we were so smart and we knew it all. So it would be interesting to explore your ideas
by contrasting, you mentioned Annika Harris, you mentioned Philip Goff. So outside of,
if you're not allowed to say the fundamental disagreement is the fact that space-time is
fundamental, what are interesting distinctions between ideas of consciousness between you and
Annika, for example? You guys have been on a podcast together, I'm sure in private,
you guys have some incredible conversations. So where are some interesting sticking points,
some interesting disagreements, let's say with Annika first. Maybe there'll be a few other people.
Well, Annika and I just had a conversation this morning where we were talking about
our ideas. And what we discovered really in our conversation was that we're pretty much on the
same page. It was really just- About consciousness. Yeah, our ideas about consciousness are pretty
much on the same page. She rightly has cautioned me to, when I talk about conscious agents,
to point out that the notion of agency is not fundamental in my theory. The notion of self
is not fundamental. And that's absolutely true. I can use this network of conscious agents.
As a technical term, conscious agent is a technical term for that probability space
with the Markovian dynamics. I can use that to build models of a self and to build models of
agency, but they're not fundamental. So she has really been very helpful in helping me to be a
little bit clear about these ideas and not say things that are misleading. Sure. I mean,
this is the interesting thing about language, actually, is that language, quite obviously,
is an interface to truth. It's so fascinating that individual words can have so much ambiguity
and the slight, the specific choices of a word within a particular sentence, within the context
of a sentence can have so much such a difference in meaning. It's quite fascinating, especially when
you're talking about topics like consciousness, because it's a very loaded term. It means a lot
of things to a lot of people. And the entire concept of shrouded in a mystery. So combination
of the fact that it's a loaded term and that there's a lot of mystery, people can just interpret it
in all kinds of ways. And so you have to be both precise and help them avoid getting stuck on some
kind of side road of miscommunication, loss in translation, because you use the wrong word.
That's interesting. I mean, because for, for a lot of people, consciousness is ultimately connected
to a self. I mean, that's our experience of consciousness is very, it's connected to this
ego. I mean, I just, I mean, what else could it possibly be? I can't even, how do you begin to
comprehend, to visualize, to conceptualize a consciousness that's not connected to like this
particular organism? Well, I have a way of thinking about this whole problem now that's,
that's, that comes out of this, this framework that's different. So we can imagine a dynamics of
consciousness, not in space and time, just abstractly. It could be cooperative, for all we know, it
could be very friendly, I don't know. And you can set up a dynamics, a Markovian dynamics that is
so-called stationary. And that's a technical term, which means that the entropy effectively is not
increasing. There is some entropy, but it's constant. So there's no increasing entropy.
And in that sense, the dynamics is timeless. There is no entropic time. But it's a trivial theorem,
three line proof, that if you have a stationary Markovian dynamics, any projection that you make
of that dynamics by conditional probability, and if you want, I can state a little more,
even more mathematically precisely for, for some readers or listeners. But if any projection you
take by conditional probability, the induced image of that Markov chain will have increasing entropy.
You will have entropic time. So, so I'll be very, very precise. I have a Markov chain x1 x2
through xn, where xn, n goes to infinity, right? The entropy h, capital H of xn is equal to the
entropy h of xn minus one for all n. So the entropy is the same. But it's a, it's a theorem that h
of xn, say given x sub one is greater than or equal to h of xn minus one, given x1.
Sure. Where does the grader come from? Because with the theorem, the three line proof,
h of xn given x1 is greater than or equal to h of xn given x1 and x2, because conditioning reduces.
But then h of xn minus one given x1 comma x2 is equal to h of xn
given x2, xn minus one given x2 by the Markov property. And then because it's stationary,
it's equal to h of x. I have to write it down. xn minus, I have to write it down. Anyway,
there's a three line proof. Sure. So, but the assumption of stationarity,
we're using a lot of terms that people won't understand, doesn't matter.
So there's some kind of, some Markovian dynamics is basically trying to model some kind of system
with some probabilities and there's agents and they interact in some kind of way. And you could
say something about that system as it evolves. Stationarity, so stationary system is one that
has certain properties in terms of entropy very well. But we don't know if it's stationary or not.
We don't know what the properties, right? You see, you have to kind of take assumptions and see,
okay, well, what is, what does the systems behave like under these different properties?
The more constraints, the more assumptions you take, the more predictive, the more
interesting, powerful things you can say, but sometimes they're limiting.
That said, we're talking about consciousness here. How does that, you said cooperative,
okay, competitive. It just, I like chocolate. I'm sitting here. I have a brain. I'm wearing a suit.
It sure as hell feels like I'm a self. Right. Now, what am I tuning in? Am I plugging into
something? Am I a projection, a simple trivial projection into space time from some much larger
organism that I can't possibly comprehend? How the hell, you're saying some, you're building
up mathematical intuitions. Fine. Great. But I'm just, I'm having an existential crisis here,
and I'm going to die soon. We'll all die pretty quickly. So I, I want to, I want to figure out
why chocolate is so delicious. So help me out here. So let's just keep sneaking up to this.
Right. So the whole technical, technical thing was to say this, even if the dynamics of consciousness
is stationary so that there is no entropic time, any projection of it, any view of it
will have the artifact of entropic time. That's a limited resource, limited resources.
So the fundamental dynamics may have no limits, limited resources whatsoever. Any projection
will have certainly time as a limited resource and probably lots of other limited resources.
Hence we could get competition and evolution and nature, red, and tooth, and claw as an artifact
of a deeper system in which those aren't fundamental. And, and in fact, I take it as
something that this theory must do at some point is to show how networks of conscious agents,
even if they're not resource limited, give rise to evolution of a natural selection via a projection.
Yeah. But you're saying, I'm trying to understand how the limited resources that give rise
to, so first the thing gives rise to time, it gives rise to limited resource, it gives rise to
evolution by natural selection, how that has to do with the fact that chocolate is delicious.
Well, it's not going to do that directly. It's going to get to this notion of self.
Oh, it's going to give you the notion of self.
Oh, the evolution gives you the notion of self.
And also of a self separate from other selves. So the idea would be that competition has life
and death, all those kinds of things.
That's right. So it won't, I don't think, as I said, I don't think that I can tell you how
the formless gives rise to the experience of chocolate. Right now, my current theory says
that's, that's one of the miracles I'm assuming. Yeah.
So my theory can't do it. And the reason my theory can't do it is because
Hoffman's brain can't do it right now. But, but the notion of self, yes,
the notion of self can be an artifact of the projection of it. So there's one conscious agent.
Because anytime conscious agents interact, they form a new conscious agent. So there's one
conscious agent. Any projection of that one conscious agent gives rise to time, even if
there wasn't any time in that one conscious agent. And it gives rise, I want to, I haven't
proven this. So this is, so now this is me guessing where the theory is going to go.
Not, I haven't done this. There's no paper on this yet. So now I'm speculating.
My guess is I'll be able to show, or the, or the, but my brighter colleagues working with me
will be able to show that, that we will get evolution of a natural selection, the notion
of individual selves, individual physical objects, and so forth coming out as a projection of this
thing. And, and, and that the self, this thing will be, be really interesting in terms of how
it starts to interact with certain spiritual traditions, right? Where they will say that
there is a notion of self that needs to be let go, which is this finite self that's competing
with other selves to, you know, get more money and prestige and so forth. That self in some sense
has to die. But there's a deeper self, which is the timeless
being that preclude, that precedes, not precludes, but precedes any particular
conscious experiences, the ground of all experience, that there's that notion of a deep
capital self. But our little capital, lowercase s selves could be artifacts of projection.
And it may be that what consciousness is doing in this framework is, right? It's projected itself
down into a self that calls itself Don and a self that calls itself Lex. And through conversations
like this, it's trying to find out about itself, and eventually transcend the limits of the Don
and Lex little icons that it's using, and that little projection of itself through this conversation
is somehow it's learning about itself. So that thing dressed me up today in order to understand
itself. And in some sense, you and I are not separate from that thing, and we're not separate
from each other. Yeah. Well, I have to question the fashion choices on my end. All right. So
you mentioned you agree on in terms of consciousness on a lot of things with Annika.
Is there somebody friend or friendly foe that you disagree with in some nuanced, interesting way,
or some major way about consciousness about these topics of reality that you return to
often? It's like Christopher Hitchens with Rabbi David Walby have had interesting conversations
through years that added to the complexity and the beauty of their friendship. Is there somebody
like that, that over the years has been a source of disagreement with you that strengthened your
ideas? My ideas have been really shaped by several things. One is the physicalist framework that
my scientific colleagues almost to a person have adopted, and that I adopted too, until the reason
I walked away from it was because it became clear that we couldn't start with unconscious
ingredients and boot up consciousness. Can you define physicalist in contrast to reductionist?
So a physicalist, I would say is someone who takes space time and the objects within space
time as ontologically fundamental. Right. And then reductionist is saying the smaller,
the more fundamental. That's a methodological thing. That's saying within space time as you go
to smaller and smaller scales in space, you get deeper and deeper laws, more and more fundamental
laws. And the reduction of temperature to particle movement was an example of that,
but I think that the reason that worked was almost an artifact of the nature of our interface.
That was for a long time, and your colleagues, including yourself or physicalist, and now
you broke away. I broke away because I think you can't start with unconscious ingredients and boot
up consciousness. And so even with Roger Penrose, where there's like a gray area.
Right. And here's the challenge I would put to all of my friends and colleagues who are,
give one specific conscious experience that you can boot up. So if you think that it's
integrated information, and this I've asked this of Julia to know me a couple times back in the
90s, and then just a couple of years ago, I asked Julia, okay, so great integrated information. So
we're all interested in explaining some specific conscious experiences. So what, what is, you
know, pick one, the taste of chocolate? What is the integrated information, precise structure
that we need for chocolate? And why does that structure have to be for chocolate? And why,
why is it that it could not possibly be vanilla? Is there any, last time, is there any one specific
conscious experience that you can account for? Because notice, they've set themselves the task
of booting up conscious experiences from physical systems. That's the task they've set
themselves. But that doesn't mean they're, I understand your intuition, but that doesn't mean
they're wrong just because they can't find a way to boot it up yet. That's right. No, that doesn't
mean that they're wrong. It just, it just means that they haven't done it. I think it's principled.
The reason is principled, but, but I'm happy that they're exploring it. But the fact is, the
remarkable fact is there's not one theory. So integrated information theory, orchestrated
collapse of microtubules, global workspace theory. These are all theories of consciousness.
These are all theories of consciousness. There's not a single theory that can give you a specific
conscious experience that they say, here is the physical dynamics or the physical structure
that must be the taste of chocolate or whatever one they want. So you're saying it's impossible,
they're saying it's just hard. Yeah. My attitude is, okay, no one said you had to start with neurons
or physical systems and boot up consciousness. You guys are just taking that. You chose that
problem. So since you chose that problem, how much progress have you made? Well,
when you've not been able to come up with a single specific conscious experience,
and you've had these brilliant people working on it for decades now,
that's not really good progress. Let me ask you to be, to play devil's advocate. Can you try to
steal man, steal man, meaning argue the best possible case for reality, the opposite of your
book title. So, or maybe just stick into consciousness. Can you take the physicalist view?
Can you steal man, the physicalist view for a brief moment, playing devil's advocate too?
Or steal man, the person you used to be. Right.
She's a physicalist. What's a good, like saying that you might be wrong right now?
What would be a convincing argument for that? Well, I think the argument I would give and
that I believed was, look, when you have very simple physical systems, like a piece of dirt,
there's not much evidence of life for consciousness. It's only when you get really
complicated physical systems like that have brains and really the more complicated the brains,
the more it looks like there's consciousness and the more complicated that consciousness is.
Surely that means that simple physical systems don't create much consciousness,
if maybe not any, or maybe panpsychists, they create the most elementary kinds of
simple conscious experiences. But you need more complicated physical systems to boot up,
to create more complicated consciousnesses. I think that's the intuition that drives most of my
colleagues. And you're saying that this concept of complexity is ill-defined when you ground it to
space-time. Well, I think it's well-defined within the framework of space-time, right?
No, it's ill-defined relative to what you need to actually understand consciousness
because you're grounding complexity in just in space-time.
Oh, got you. Right. Yeah. What I'm saying is, if it were true that space-time was fundamental,
then I would have to agree that if there is such a thing as consciousness, given the data that we've
got, that complex brains have consciousness and dirt doesn't, that somehow it's the complexity of
the dynamics or organization, the function of the physical system that somehow is creating the
consciousness. So under those assumptions, yes. But when the physicists themselves are telling us
that space-time is not fundamental, then I can understand. See, then the whole picture starts
to come into focus. Why, my colleagues are brilliant, right? These are really smart people.
I mean, Francis Crick worked on this for the last 20 years of his life. These are not stupid
people. These are brilliant, brilliant people. The fact that we've come up with not a single
specific conscious experience that we can explain and no hope. There's no one that says,
oh, I'm really close. I'll have it for you in a year. No, there's just like, there's this
fundamental gap. So much so that Steve Pinker in one of his writings says, look, he likes the
global workspace theory. But he says the last dollop of the theory in which there's something
it's like to, he says we may have to just stipulate that as a brute fact. Pinker is brilliant,
right? He understands the state of play on this problem of the hard problem of consciousness,
starting with physical assumptions and then trying to boot up consciousness. You've set
yourself the problem. I'm starting with physical stuff that's not conscious. I'm trying to get
the taste of chocolate out as maybe some kind of function of the dynamics of that.
We've not been able to do that. And so Pinker is saying, we may have to punt.
We may have to just stipulate that last bit. He calls it the last dollop. And just say,
stipulate it as a bare fact of nature that there is something it's like. Well,
from my point of view as the physical, the whole point, the whole promise of the physicalist was
we wouldn't have to stipulate. I was going to start with the physical stuff and explain where
the consciousness came from. If I'm going to stipulate consciousness, why don't I just stipulate
consciousness and not stipulate all the physical stuff too? So I'm stipulating less. I'm saying,
okay, I agree. The panpsychist perspective. Well, it's actually what I call the conscious
realist perspective. Panpsychists are effectively dualists, right? They're saying there's physical
stuff that really is fundamental and then consciousness stuff. So I would go with Pinker
and say, look, let's just stipulate the consciousness stuff, but I'm not going to stipulate the
physical stuff. I'm going to actually now show how to boot up the physical stuff from just the
consciousness stuff. So I'll stipulate less. Is it possible? So if you stipulate less,
is it possible for our limited brains to visualize reality as we delve deeper and deeper and deeper?
Is it possible to visualize somehow with the tools of math, with the tools of computers,
with the tools of our mind? Are we hopelessly lost? You said there's ways to intuit
what's true using mathematics and probability and sort of Markovian dynamics, all that kind
of stuff, but that's not visualizing. That's what's the kind of building intuition, but is it possible
to visualize in the way we visualize so nicely in space time, in four dimensions, in three dimensions?
Sorry. Well, we really are looking through a two-dimensional screen until
what we intuit to be a three-dimensional world and also inferring dynamic stuff,
making it 4D. Anyway, is it possible to visualize some pretty pictures that give us
a deeper sense of the truth of reality? I think that we will incrementally be able to do that.
I think that, for example, the picture that we have of electrons and photons interacting
and scattering, it may have not been possible until Faraday did all of his experiments and
then Maxwell wrote down his equations, and we were then sort of forced by his equations to think
in a new way. And then when Planck in 1900, desperate to try to solve the problem of black
body radiation, what they call the ultraviolet catastrophe, where Newton was predicting infinite
energies, there weren't infinite energies in black body radiation. And he, in desperation, proposed
packets of energy. Then once you've done that, and then you have an Einstein come along five years
later and show how that explains the photoelectric effect. And then eventually, in 1926, you get
quantum theory. And then you get this whole new way of thinking that was, from the Newtonian point
of view, completely contradictory and counterintuitive, certainly. And maybe if
Giesen is right, not contradictory. Maybe if you use intuition as math, they're not contradictory.
But still, certainly you wouldn't have gone there. And so here's a case where the experiments
and then a desperate mathematical move, sort of we use those as a flashlight into the deep fog,
right? And so that science may be the flashlight into the deep fog.
I wonder if it's still possible to visualize in the, like we talk about consciousness in,
from a self perspective, experience it. Hold that idea in our mind, the way you can experience
things directly. We've evolved to experience things in this 3D world. And that's a very rich
experience. When you're thinking mathematically, you still, in the end of the day, have to project
it down to a low dimensional space to make, to make conclusions. Their conclusions will be a
number or a line or a plot or a visual. So I wonder like how we can really touch some deep truth
in a subjective way, like experience it, really feel the beauty of it, you know,
in the way that humans feel beauty. Right. Are we screwed? I don't think we're screwed.
I think that we get little hints of it from psychedelic drugs and so forth. We get hints
that there are certain interventions that we can take on our interface. I apply this chemical,
which is just some element of my interface, to this other, to a brain. I ingest it. And all of
a sudden, I seem like I've opened new portals into conscious experiences. Well, that's very,
very suggestive. That's like the black body radiation doing something that we didn't expect,
right? It doesn't go to infinity when we thought it was going to go to infinity and we're forced to
propose these quanta. So once we have a theory of conscious agents,
and it's projection to space, I should sketch what I think that projection is.
But then I think we can then start to ask specific questions. When you're taking DMT,
or you're taking LSD or something like that. Now that we have this deep model that we've
reverse engineered space and time and physical particles, we've pulled them back to this theory
of conscious agents. Now we can ask ourselves in this idealized future, what are we doing to
conscious agents when we apply 5MEO DMT? What are we doing? Are we opening a new portal?
So when I say that, I mean, I have a portal into consciousness that I call my body of
Lex Friedman that I'm creating. And it's a genuine portal, not perfect, but it's a genuine portal
I'm definitely communicating with your consciousness. And we know that we have
one technology for building new portals. We know one technology and that is having kids.
Having kids is how we build new portals into consciousness. It takes a long time.
Can you elaborate that? Oh, oh, oh, you mean like your son and your daughter didn't exist.
That was a portal though. You're having contact with consciousness that you never would have had
before. But now you've got a son or a daughter, you had, you went through this physical process,
they were born, then you, there was all the training. But is that portal yours? So when you
have kids, are you creating new portals that are completely distinct from the portals that you've
created with other consciousness? Like, can you elaborate on that? To which degree are the
consciousness of your kids a part of you? Well, so every person that I see, that symbol that I
see, the body that I see is, is a portal potentially for me to interact with, with the
consciousness. Yeah. And, and each consciousness has a unique character that we call a personality
and so forth. So with each new kid that's born, we come in contact with a personality that
we've never seen before. And a version of consciousness that we've never seen before.
At a deeper level, as I said, the theory says there's one agent. So this is a different projection
of that one agent. But, but, so that's what I mean by a portal is within my own interface,
my own projection, can I see other projections of that one consciousness? So can I get portals in,
in that sense? And I, so and I think, I think we will get a theory of that, that we will get a
theory of portals. And then we can ask how the psychedelics are acting, are they actually
creating new portals or not? If they're not, we should nevertheless, then understand how we could
create a new portal, right? Maybe we have to just study what happens when we make, when we have kids.
We know that that technology creates new portals. So we have to reverse engineer that and then say,
okay, could we somehow create new portals de novo with that?
With, with something like, like brain-computer interfaces, for example.
Yeah, maybe just a chemical or something. So probably more complicated than a chemical. That's
why I think that the psychedelics, the psychedelics may, because they might be affecting this portal
in certain ways that it turns it around and opens up. Whereas it may be, once we understand what
this thing is a portal, your body as a portal, understand all of its complexities, maybe we'll
realize that that portal can be shifted and to different parts of the deeper consciousness
and give new windows on it. And so in that way, maybe, yes, psychedelics could open up new portals
in the sense that they're taking something that's already a complex portal and just
tweaking it a bit. Well, but creating is a very powerful difference between morphing.
Tweaking versus creating, I agree. But maybe it gives you intuition to at least the full space
of the kinds of things that this particular system is capable of. I mean, you, I mean,
the idea, your idea of the consciousness creates brains. I mean, that breaks my brain because
there's a, you know, I'm, I guess I'm still a physicalist in that sense, because that you could,
it's just much easier to intuit the world. It's very, it's practical to think there's a neural
network and what are the different ways fascinating capabilities can emerge from this neural network?
I agree. It's easier. And so you start to, and then present to yourself the problem of, okay,
well, how does consciousness arise? How does intelligence arise? How does emotion arise?
How does memory arise in the, how do we filter within the system all the incoming
sensory information we're able to allocate attention in different interesting ways? How do
all those mechanisms arise to say that there's other fundamental things we don't understand
outside of space time that are actually core to how this whole thing works is a bit paralyzing
because it's like, oh, we're not, we're not 10% done. We're like 0.001% done.
Well, it's the immediate feeling. I certainly understand that. My attitude about it is,
if you look at the young physicists who are searching for these structures beyond space
time, like the episode of Eden and so forth, they're having a ball. Space time, that's what
the old folks did. That's what our, the older generation did. We're doing something that
really is fun and new and they're having a blast and they're finding all these new structures.
So I think that we're going to succeed in getting a new deeper theory. I can just say what I'm
hoping with the theory that I'm working on, I'm hoping to show that I could have this timeless
dynamics of consciousness, no entropic time. I take a projection and I show how this timeless
dynamics looks like the Big Bang and the entire evolution of space time. In other words, I see
how my whole space time interface. So not just the projection, it just doesn't just look like
space time. You can explain with it the whole from the origin of the universe.
That's what we have to do and that's what the physicists understand. When they go beyond
space time to the amplitude and the cosmological polytope, they ultimately know that they have
to get back the Big Bang story and the whole evolution, that whole story where there were no
living things. There was just a point and then the explosion and then just particles at high energy
and then eventually the cooling down and the differentiation and finally
matter, condenses and then life and then consciousness. That whole story has to come
out of something that's deeper and without time and that's what we're up to. The whole story
that we've been telling ourselves about Big Bang and how brains evolve in consciousness
will come out of a much deeper theory. For someone like me, it's a lot. But for the
younger generation, this is like, oh wow, all the low cherries aren't picked. This is really
good stuff. This is really new, fundamental stuff that we can do. I can't wait to read the papers
of the younger generation and I want to see them. Kids these days with their non-space time
assumptions. It's just interesting looking at the philosophical tradition of the difficult ideas
you struggle with. If you look like somebody like Emmanuel Kant, what are some interesting
agreements and disagreements you have with a guy about the nature of reality?
So there's a lot in agreement. So Kant was an idealist, transcendental idealist and
he basically had the idea that we don't see nature as it is. We impose a structure on nature.
So in some sense, I'm saying something similar. I'm saying that, by the way, I don't call myself
an idealist. I call myself a conscious realist because idealism has a long history, a lot of
different ideas come under idealism and there's a lot of debates and so forth. It
tends to be identified with, in many cases, anti-science and anti-realism. And I don't
want either connection with my ideas. And so I just called my conscious realism with an emphasis
on realism and not anti-realism. But one place where I would, of course, disagree with Kant was
that he thought that Euclidean space time was a priori. We just know that that's false.
So he went too far on that. But in general, the idea that we don't start with space time,
that space and time is, in some sense, the forms of our perceptions. Yes, absolutely.
And I would say that there's a lot in common with Barclay in that regard.
There's a lot of ingenious arguments in Barclay. Leibniz in his monodology understood very clearly
that the hard problem was not solvable. He posed a hard problem and basically dismissed it and
just said, you can't do this. And so if he came here and saw where we are, he said,
look, guys, I told you this 300 years ago. And he had his monodology. He was trying
to do something like this. It's different from what I'm doing. But he had these things that
were not in space and time, these monads. He was trying to build something. I'm trying to build
a theory of consciousness. My guess is that if he came here, I could just, if he saw what I was
doing, he would say, he would understand it and immediately take off with it and go places that
I couldn't. He would have no problems. Right. There would be overlap of the spirit of the ideas.
Absolutely. It would be totally overlapping. But his genus would then just run with it far
faster than I could. I love the humility here. So let me ask you about sort of practical
implications of your ideas to our world, our complicated world. When you look at the big
questions of humanity of hate, war, what else is there, evil? Maybe there's the positive aspects
of that, of meaning, of love. What is the fact that reality is an illusion perceived as? What is
the conscious realism when applied to daily life? What kind of impact does it have?
A lot. And it's sort of scary. We all know that life is ephemeral. And spiritual traditions have
said, wake up to the fact that anything that you do here is going to disappear.
But it's even more ephemeral than perhaps we've thought. I see this bottle because I create it
right now. As soon as I look away, that data structure has been garbage collected. That bottle,
I have to recreate it every time I look. So I spend all my money. I buy this fancy car.
That car, I have to keep recreating it every time I look at it. It's that ephemeral.
So all the things that we invest ourselves in, we fight over, we kill each other over,
and we have wars over, these are all, it's just like people in a virtual reality simulation.
Right? And there's this Porsche. We all see the Porsche. Well, that Porsche exists when I look
at it. I turn my headset and I look at it. And then if Joe turns his headset the right way,
he'll see his Porsche. But it's not even the same Porsche that I see. He's creating his own Porsche.
So these things are exceedingly ephemeral. And now, just imagine saying that that's my Porsche.
Well, you can agree to say that it's your Porsche, but really, the Porsche only exists as long as you
look. So this all of a sudden, what the spiritual traditions have been saying for a long, long time,
this gets cashed out in mathematically precise science. It's saying ephemeral, yes, in fact,
it lasts for a few milliseconds, a few hundred milliseconds while you look at it, and then it's
gone. So the whole idea, why are we fighting? Why do we hate? We fight over possessions
because we think that we're small little objects inside this pre-existing space time. We assume
that that mansion, that car exists independent of us and that somehow we, these little things,
can have our sense of self and importance enhanced by having that special car or that special house
or that special person. In fact, it's just the opposite. You create that mansion every time you
look. You're something far deeper than that mansion. You're the entity which can create that
mansion on the fly. And there's nothing to the mansion except what you create in this moment.
So all of a sudden, when you take this point of view, it has all sorts of implications for how we
interact with each other, how we treat each other. And again, a lot of things that spiritual
traditions have said, it's a mixed bag. Spiritual traditions are a mixed bag. So let me just be
right up front about that. I'm not promoting any particular, but they do have some insights.
Yeah, they have wisdom. They have certain wisdom. They have, I can point to nonsense,
I won't go into it, but I can also point to lots of nonsense. So the issue is to then
to look for the key insights. And I think they have a lot of insights about the ephemeral nature of
objects in space and time and not being attached to them, including our own bodies and reversing
that I'm not this little thing, a little consciousness trapped in the body. And the
consciousness itself is only a product of the body. So when the body dies, the consciousness
disappears, it turns completely around, the consciousness is fundamental, the body,
my hand exists right now because I'm looking at it. My hand is gone. I have no hand. I have,
I have no brain. I have no heart. If you looked, you'll see a heart. Whatever I am
is this really complicated thing in consciousness. That's what I am. All the stuff that I thought
I was is something that I create on the fly and delete. So this whole, so this is completely
a radical restructuring of how we think about possessions, about identity, about survival
of death, and so forth. This is completely transformative. But the nice thing is that
this whole approach of consciousness agents, unlike the spiritual traditions, which have
said, in some cases, similar things, they've said it in precisely. This is mathematics.
We can actually now begin to state precisely, here's the mathematical model of consciousness,
conscious agents. Here's how it maps onto space time, which I should sketch really briefly.
And here's why things are ephemeral. And here's why you shouldn't be worried about the ephemeral
nature of things, because you're not a little tiny entity inside space and time,
quite the opposite. You're the author of space and time.
The I and the am and the I am is all kind of emerging through this whole process of evolution
and so on. That's just surface waves. And there's a much deeper ocean that we're trying to figure
out here. So how does you said, this said, some of the stuff you're thinking about maps the space
time, how does it map the space? Right. So just a very, very high level, and I'll keep it brief.
The structures that the physicists are finding, like the amplitude heat, it turns out they're
just static structure, they're polytopes. But they remarkably, most of the information in them
is contained in permutation matrices. So it's a matrix, like an n by n matrix that just has zeros
and ones. That contains almost all of the information. And you can they have these plabbit
graphs and so forth that they use to boot up the scattering, you can compute those scattering
amplitudes almost entirely from these permutation matrices. So that's just now from my point of
view, I have this conscious agent dynamics, it turns out that the stationary dynamics that I was
talking about, where the entropy is increasing, all the stationary dynamics are sketched out by
permutation matrices. So if you there's so called Birkhoff polytope, all the vertices of this
polytope, all the points are permutation matrices, all the internal points are Markovian kernels
that have the uniform measure as a stationary measure.
I need to intuit a little better what the heck you're talking about. But so basically,
there's some complicated thing going on with the network of conscious agents, and that's
mappable to this. You're saying it to dimensional matrix that scattering has to do with what,
without the perception like that's like photon stuff. I mean, I don't know if it's useful to
sort of dig into detail. I'll do just the high level thing. Yes. So the high level is the long
term behavior of the conscious agent dynamics. So that's the projection of just looking at the
long term behavior. I'm hoping we'll give rise to the amplitude, the amplitude, then gives rise to
space time. So then I can just use their link to go all the way from consciousness through its
asymptotics to through the amplitude and into space time and get the map all the way into our
interface. And that's why you mentioned the permutation matrix because it gives you a nice
thing to try to generate. That's right. It's the connection with the amplitude, the permutation
matrices are the core of the amplitude, and it turns out they're the core of the asymptotic
description of the conscious agents. So not to sort of bring up the idea of a creator,
but I like, first of all, I like video games and you mentioned this kind of simulation idea.
First of all, do you think of it as an interesting idea, this thought experiment that will live in
a simulation? And in general, do you think we'll live in a simulation? So the Nick Bostrom's idea
about the simulation is typically couched in a physicalist framework. Yes. So there is the bottom
level. There's some programmer in a physical space time, and they have a computer that they've
programmed really cleverly, where they've created conscious entities. So you have the hard problem
of consciousness, right? The standard hard problem, how could a computer simulation create a
which isn't explained by that simulation theory. But then the idea is that the next level, the
entities that are from the, that are created in the first level simulation, then can write
their own simulations and you get this this nesting. So, so the idea that this is a simulation
is fine. But the idea that this starts with a physical space, I think is important. There's
different properties here, the partial rendering. And to me, that's the interesting idea is not
whether the entirety of the universe is simulated, but how efficiently can you
create interfaces that are convincing to all other entities that can appreciate such interfaces?
How little does it take? Because you said like partial rendering, or like temporal,
ephemeral rendering of stuff, only render the tree falling in the forest when there's somebody
there to see it. It's interesting to think how can you do that superficially without having
to render everything. And that to me is one perspective on the simulation, just like it is
with video games, where a video game doesn't have to render every single thing. It's just
the thing that the observer is looking at. Right. There is actually, that's a very nice question.
And there's whole groups of researchers that are actually studying in virtual reality, what
is the sort of minimal requirements on the system? What, how does it have to operate
to give you an immersion experience, to give you the feeling that you have a body,
to get you to take it real? And there's actually a lot of really good work on that right now.
And it turns out it doesn't take that much. You do need to get the perception action loop
tight. And you have to give them the perceptions that they're expecting, if you want them to.
But if you, you can lead them along, if you give them perceptions that are close to what
they're expecting, you can then maybe move their reality around a bit.
Yeah, it's a trick engineering problem, especially when you're trying to create a product
that costs little, but that's, it feels like an engineering problem, not a deeply scientific
problem. Or meaning obviously it's a scientific problem, but as a scientific problem, it's not
that difficult to trick us descendants of apes. But here's, here's a case for just us in our own,
if this is a virtual reality that we're experiencing right now. So here's something you
can try for yourself. If you just close your eyes and look at your experience in front of you,
to be aware of your experience in front of you, what you experience is just like a modeled
dark gray, where there's all sort of, there's some dynamics to it, but it's just dark gray.
But now I ask you, instead of having your attention forward, put your attention backward,
what is it like behind you with your eyes closed? And there, it's like nothing.
It's real. So what is going on here? What, what am I experiencing back there?
Right. Well, it's, I don't know if it's nothing. It's, it's like, I guess it's the absence of,
it's not even like darkness or something. It's not even darkness. There's no, there's no
qualia to it. And yet there is a sense of being. And that's the interesting thing.
There's a sense of being back. So I close my, I put my attention forward. I just,
I have the quality of a gray model thing. But when I put my attention backward,
there's no quality at all, but there is a sense of being.
I personally, you haven't been to that side of the room. I have been to that side of the room.
So for me, memories, I start, I started playing the engine of memory replay,
which is like, I take myself back in time and think about that place where I was hanging
out in that part. That's when I see what I'm behind. So that's an interesting quirk of humans too,
we're able to, we're collecting these experiences and we can replay them in interesting ways,
whenever we feel like it. And it's almost like being there, but not really, but almost.
That's right. And yet we can go our entire lives in this. You're talking about the minimal thing
for VR. We can go our entire lives and not realize that all of my life, it's been like
nothing behind me. We're not even aware that all of our lives, if you just, for the,
just pay attention, close your eyes, pay attention to what's behind me, you're like,
oh, holy smoke. It's sort of scary. I mean, it's like nothing. There's no quality there at all.
How did I not notice that my entire life? We're so immersed in the simulation, we buy it so much.
Yeah. I mean, you could see this with children, right? Though with persistence, you know, you
could do the peek-a-boo game. You can hide from them and appear and they're fully tricked. And in
the same way, we're fully tricked. There's nothing behind us and we assume there is.
And that's really interesting. These theories are pretty heavy.
You as a human being, as a mortal human being, how has these theories been to you personally?
Like, are there good days and bad days when you wake up and look in the mirror and the fact that
you can't see anything behind you? The fact that it's rendered like, is there interesting quirks?
You know, Nietzsche with his, if you gaze long into the abyss, the abyss gazes into you.
How has these theories, these ideas changed you as a person?
It's been very, very difficult. The stuff is not just abstract theory building because it's about us.
Sometimes I've realized that there's this big division of me that my mind is doing all this
science and coming with these conclusions. And the rest of me is not integrating. I was just like,
I don't believe it. I just don't believe this. I mean, it seems. So as I start to take it seriously,
I get scared myself. Then I read these spiritual traditions and realize they're saying very,
very similar things. There's a lot of convergence. So for me, the first time I thought it might be
possible that we're not seeing the truth was in 1986. It was from some mathematics we were doing.
And when that hit me, it hit me like a ton of bricks. I had to sit down. It was, it really,
it was scary. It was really a shock to the system. And then to realize that everything that has been
important to me, like, you know, getting a house, getting a car, getting a reputation and so forth.
Well, that car is just like the car I see in the virtual reality. It's there when you
perceive it and it's not there. So the whole question of, you know,
what am I doing and why? What's worthwhile doing in life? Clearly,
getting a big house and getting a big car. I mean, we all knew that we were going to die.
So we tend not to know that. We tend to hide it, especially when we were young. Before age 30,
we don't believe we're going to die. But we factually maybe know that you kind of are supposed
to, yeah. But they'll figure something out and probably the generation that is the first one
that doesn't have to die. That's the kind of thing. But when you really face the fact that
you're going to die, and then when I start to look at it from this point of view that, well,
this thing was an interface to begin with. So what I'm really, is what I'm really going to be doing,
just taking off a headset. So I've been playing in a virtual reality game all day.
And I got lost in the game when I was fighting over a Porsche. And I shot some guys up and I
punctured their tires and I got the Porsche. Now I take the headset off. And what was that for?
Nothing. It was just, it was a data structure and the data structure is gone. So all of the wars,
the fighting and the reputations and all this stuff, you know, where it's just a headset.
So now, and so my theory says that intellectually, my mind, my emotions rebel all over the place.
This is like, you know, and so I have to meditate. I meditate a lot.
Well, what percent of the day would you say you spend as a physicalist sort of living life,
pretending your car matters, your reputation matters? Like, how much was that Tom Waits song?
I like my town with a little drop of poison. How much poison do you allow yourself to have?
I think my default mode is physicalist. I think that that's just the default. I, when I'm not
being conscious, consciously attentive.
Then intellectually conscious, because if you're just, you're still, if you're tasting coffee and
not thinking or drinking or just taking it in the sunset, you're not being intellectual,
but you're still experiencing it. So it's when you turn on the like the introspective machine,
that's when you can start and turn off the thinker. When I actually just start looking
without thinking. So that's when I feel like I, all of a sudden, I'm starting to see through.
I'm sort of like, okay, part of the addiction to the interface is all the stories I'm telling
about it. It's really important for me to get that really important to do that. So I'm telling all
these stories and so I'm all wrapped up. Almost all of the mind stuff that's going on in my head
is about attachment to the interface. And so what I found is that the essentially the only way to
really detach from the interface is to literally let go of thoughts altogether. And then all of a
sudden, even my identity, you know, my whole history, my name, my education, all this stuff
is almost irrelevant because it's just now here is the present moment. And this is this is the
reality right now. And all of that other stuff is an interface story. But this conscious experience
right now, this is the only, this is the only reality as far as I can tell, the rest of it's a
story. And, but that is, again, not my default, that is, I have to make a really
conscious choice to say, okay, I know intellectually this is all an interface.
I'm going to take the headset off and so forth. And then immediately sink back into the game and
just be out there playing the game and get lost. And so I'm always lost in the game unless I
literally consciously choose to stop thinking. Isn't it terrifying to acknowledge that
to look beyond the game? Isn't it scares the hell out of me? It's really a scary
because I'm so attached. I'm attached to this body. I'm attached to the interface.
Are you ever worried about breaking your brain a bit? Meaning like, it's,
I mean, some of these ideas, when you think about reality, even with like Einstein,
just realizing you said interface, just realizing that light, you know, that there's a speed of
light and you can't go faster than the speed of light and like what kind of things black holes and
can do with light, even that can mess with your head. Yes. But that's still space time.
That's a big mess, but it's still just space time. It's still a property of our interface.
That's right. But it's still like even, even Einstein realized that this particular thing,
some of the stories you tell ourselves is constructing interfaces that are oversimplifying
the way things work because it's nice. The stories are nice. Stories are nice.
That's what I mean. It's just like video games. They're nice.
Right. But Einstein was a realist, right? He was a famous realist in the sense that he
was very explicit in a 1935 paper with Podolski and Rosen, the EPR paper where he,
they said, if without in any way disturbing a system, I can predict with probability one,
the outcome of a measurement, then there exists in reality that element,
right? That value, that, and we now know from quantum theory that that's false.
That Einstein's idea of local realism is strictly speaking false.
Yeah. And so we can predict, we can set up, in quantum theory, you can set up,
and there's a paper by Chris Fuchs, quantum Bayesianism, where he, he scouts this out,
it was done by the people, but he gives a good presentation of this,
where they have a sequence of like something like nine different quantum measurements
that you can make. And you can predict with probability one, what a particular outcome
will be, but you can actually prove that it's impossible that the value existed before you
made the measurement. So you know with probability one, what you're going to get,
which you also know with certainty that that value was not there until you made the measurement.
So the, so we know from quantum theory that the act of observation is an act of fact creation.
And that is built in to what I'm saying with this theory of consciousness.
If consciousness is fundamental, space time itself is an act of fact creation. It's,
it's an interface that we create, consciousness creates, plus all the objects in it. So local
realism is not true. Quantum theory is established that also non-contextual realism
is not true. And that, that fits in perfectly with this idea that consciousness is fundamental.
These things are, these exist as data structures when we create them.
As, as, as Chris Fuchs says, the act of observation is an act of fact creation.
But I must say on a personal level, I'm having to spend, I spend a couple hours a day
just sitting in meditation on this and facing the rebellion
in me that goes to the core, it feels like it goes to the core of my being,
rebellion against these ideas. So, so here it's very, very interesting for me to look at this
because so here I'm a, I'm a scientist and I'm a person. The science is really clear.
Local realism is false. Non-contextual realism is false. Spacetime is doomed. It's, it's very,
very clear. It couldn't be clearer. And my, my emotions rebel left and right. When I sit there
and say, okay, I am not something in space and time. Something inside of me says, you're crazy.
Of course you are. And I'm completely attached to it. I'm completely attached to all this stuff.
I'm attached to my body. I'm attached to the headset. I'm attached to my car.
Attached to people. I'm attached to all of it. And, and yet I know as a absolute fact,
I'm going to walk away from all of it. I'm going to die. It'll, you know, in fact, I almost died
last year. COVID almost killed me. I, I sent a goodbye text to my wife. So I was, I thought I
was, I sent her a goodbye. I thought I was in the emergency room and it attacked my heart
and it had been at 190 beats per minute for 36 hours. I, I couldn't last much longer. I knew
I, they couldn't stop it. So that was, that was it. So that was it. So, so I texted her goodbye
from the emergency room. I love you. Goodbye kind of thing. Yeah. Right. Yeah. And that was it.
So, so were you afraid? God, it scares the hell out of you, right? But there, there is,
there was, you're just feeling so bad anyway, that, that all, you know, you,
that, that sort of, you're scared, but you're just feeling so bad that in some sense,
you just want to stop anyway. So, so I've, I've, I've been there and faced it just, just a year ago.
How did that change you by the way? Having, having this intellectual reality that's so
challenging that you meditate on a year, it's just an interface. And one of the,
one of the hardest things to come to terms with is that, that means that, you know, it's going to end.
How did I change you having come, come so close to the reality of it? It's not just an
intellectual reality. It's, it's a reality of death. It's, it's forced. I've, I've meditated for
20 years now. And then I would say averaging three or four hours a day.
But it's put a new urgency, but urgency is not the right word because that, that
it's, it's riveted my attention. I'll put it that way. It's really riveted my attention. And
I've really paid, I spent a lot more time looking at what spiritual traditions say.
I don't, by the way, again, not taking it with the, you know, take it all with a green
assault. But on the other hand, I think it's stupid for me to ignore it. So I try to listen
to the best ideas and, and to sort out nonsense from, and it's just, we all have to do it for
ourselves, right? It's not easy. So what makes sense? And I have the advantage of some science,
so I can look at what science says and try to compare with spiritual tradition.
I try to sort it out for myself. And, but then I also look and realize that there's another
aspect to me, which is this whole emotional aspect. The, I seem to be wired up
as evolutionary psychology says, I'm wired up, right? All these defensive mechanisms. So, you
I'm, I'm inclined to lie if I need to, I'm inclined to, to be angry, to protect myself,
to have an in group and an out group, to try to, you know, make my reputation as big as possible,
to try to demean the out group. There's all these things that evolutionary psychology
is spot on. It's really brilliant about the human condition. And yet I think evolution,
as I said, evolutionary theory is a projection of a deeper theory where there may be no
competition. So how, so I'm in this very interesting position where I feel like, okay,
according to my own theory, I'm consciousness. And maybe this is what it means for consciousness
to wake up. It's not easy. It's, it's, it's almost like I have, I feel like I have real
skin in the game. It really is scary. I really was scared when I was about to die. It really was
hard to say goodbye to my wife. It really, it really pained. And
to then look at that, and then look at the fact that I'm going to walk away from this anyway,
and it's just an interface. How do I, so it's, it's trying to put all this stuff together and really
grok it, so to speak, not just intellectually, but grok it at an emotional level.
Yeah. What are you afraid of? You silly evolved organism that's gotten way too attached to the
interface. What are you really afraid of? That's right. Is there a very personal, you know, it's
very, very personal. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, speaking of the text, what do you think is this whole love
thing? What's the role of love in our human condition? This interface thing we have this,
is this somehow interweaved, interconnected with consciousness, this attachment we have to other
humans, and this deep, like some quality to it that seems very interesting, peculiar.
Well, there are two levels I would think about that. There's love in the sexual sense, and there's
love in a deeper sense. And in the sexual sense, we can give an evolutionary account of that and
so forth. And I think that's pretty clear to people. In this deeper sense, right? So, of course,
I married your, I love my wife in a sexual sense, but there was a deeper sense as well.
When I was saying goodbye to her, there was a deeper, much deeper love that was really at play
there. That's one place where I think that the mixed bag from spiritual traditions has something
right. When they say, you know, love your neighbor as yourself, that some, in some sense, love is
fundamental. I think that they're onto something, something very, very deep and profound. And
every once in a while, I can get a personal glimpse of that, especially when I'm in the
space with no thought. Like when I can really let go of thoughts, I get little glimpses of a love
in the sense that I'm not separate. It's a love in the sense that I'm not different from that. I,
you know, yeah, if you and I are separate, then there's, I can fight you. But if you and I are
the same, if there's a union there, the togetherness of it, yeah. What, who's God? All those gods,
the stories that have been told throughout history, you said through the spiritual traditions,
what do you think that is? Is that us trying to find that common thing at the core?
Oh, well, in many traditions, not all. The one I was raised in, so my dad was a Protestant minister,
we tend to think of God as a being. But I think that that's not right. I think the closest way
to think about God is being, period, not a being, but being the very ground of being itself is God.
I think that's the deep, and from my point of view, that's the ground of consciousness. So the
ground of conscious being is what we might call God. But the word God has always been, you know,
for example, you don't believe the same God as my God, so I'm going to fight you. We'll have wars
over, because the being, the specific being that you call God is different from the being that I
call God, and so we fight. Whereas if it's not a being, but just being, and you and I share being,
then you and I are not separate, and there's no reason to fight. We're both part of that one
being, and loving you is loving myself, because we're all part of that one being. The spiritual
traditions that point to that, I think are pointing in a very interesting direction, and that does seem
to match with the mathematics of the conscious agent stuff that I've been working on as well,
that it really fits with that, although that wasn't my goal.
Is there, you mentioned, you mentioned that the young physicist that you talk to or whose work
you follow have quite a lot of fun breaking with the traditions of the past, the assumptions of
the past. What advice would you give to young people today in high school, in college, not just
physicists, but in general, how to have a career they can be proud of, how they can have a life
they can be proud of, how to make their way in the world from the lessons, from the wins and
the losses in your own life. What little insights could you pull out? I would say the universe is
a lot more interesting than you might expect, and you are a lot more special and interesting
than you might expect. You might think that you're just a little tiny, irrelevant 100-pound,
200-pound person in a vast billions of light years across space, and that's not the case.
You are, in some sense, the being that's creating that space all the time, every time you look.
So, waking up to who you really are outside of space and time, as the author of space and time,
is the author of everything that you see. The author of space and time, you're the author of
space and time, and I'm the author of space and time. Space and time is just one little data
structure. Many other consciousnesses are creating other data structures. They're authors of various
other things. So, realizing, and then realizing that I had this feeling that growing up and going
and reading all these textbooks, oh man, it's all been done. If I'd just been there 50 years ago,
I could have discovered this stuff, but it's all in the textbooks now. Well, believe me,
the textbooks are going to look silly in 50 years, and it's your chance to write the new
textbook. So, of course, study the current textbooks. You have to understand them. There's
no way to progress until you understand what's been done. But then, the only limit is your
imagination, frankly. That's the only limit. The greatest books, the greatest textbooks ever written
on earth are yet to be written. Exactly. What do you think is the meaning of this whole thing?
What's the meaning of life from your limited interface? Can you figure it all out? Why?
So, you said the universe is trying to figure itself out through us. Why?
Yeah, that's the closest I've come. So, I'll give you. So, I will say that I don't know, but here's
my guess, right? That's a good first sentence. That's a good starting point. And maybe that's
going to be a profound part of the final answer is to start with the I don't know. It's quite
possible that that's really important to start with the I don't know. My guess is that if consciousness
is fundamental and if girdle, girdle's incompleteness theorem holds here, and there's infinite variety
of structures for consciousness to some sense explore, that maybe that's what it's about.
This is something that Onika and I talked about a little bit, and she doesn't like this way of
talking about it. And so, I'm going to have to talk with her some more about this way of talking.
But right now, I'll just put it this way, and I'll have to talk with her more and see if I
can say it more clearly. But the way I'm talking about it now is that
there's a sense in which there's being, and then there's experiences or forms that come out of
being. That's one deep, deep mystery. And the question that you asked, what's it all about?
Somehow it's related to that. Why does being, why doesn't it just stay without any forms?
Why does it, why do we have experiences? Why should, why not just have, when you close your eyes
and pay attention to what's behind you, there's nothing. But there's being.
Why don't we just stop there? Why didn't we just stop there? Why did we create all tables and chairs
on the sun and moon and people, all this really complicated stuff? Why? And all I can guess right
now, and I'll probably kick myself in a couple of years and say that was dumb, but all I can
guess right now is that somehow consciousness wakes up to itself by knowing what it's not.
So here I am, I'm not this body. And I sort of saw that, it was sort of in my face when I
sent a text goodbye. But then as soon as I'm better, it's sort of like, okay, I sort of don't want to
go there, right? Okay, so I just, so I am my body. I go back to the standard thing, I am my body,
and then I want to get that car. And even though I was just about to die a year ago, so that comes
rushing back. So, so consciousness immerses itself fully into a particular headset, gets lost in it,
and then slowly wakes up. Just so it can escape and that is the waking up, but it needs to have
a negative. It needs to know what it's not. It needs to know what you are. You have to say,
oh, I'm not that, I'm not that, that wasn't important, that wasn't important.
That's really powerful done. Let me just say that, because I've been a long-term fan of yours,
and we're supposed to have a conversation doing this very difficult moment in your life. Let me
just say you're a truly special person. And I for one, I know there's a lot, a lot of others,
they agree. I'm glad that you're still here with us on this earth, if for a short time.
So, whatever, whatever the universe, whatever plan it has for you that brought you close to
death, to maybe enlighten you some kind of way, I think, I think has an interesting plan for you.
You're one of the truly special humans, and it's a huge honor that you would sit and talk with me
today. Thank you so much. Thank you very much, Lex. I really appreciate that. Thank you.
Thanks for listening to this conversation with Donald Hoffman. To support this podcast,
please check out our sponsors in the description. And now, let me leave you with some words from
Albert Einstein, relevant to the ideas discussed in this conversation. Time and space are modes by
which we think, and not conditions in which we live. Thank you for listening, and hope to see you
next time.