The following is a conversation with Eric Weinstein, his fourth time on the podcast,
both sadness and hope run through his heart and his mind, and the result is a complicated,
brilliant human being who I am fortunate to call a friend.
Quick mention of our sponsors. Indeed Hiring Site, TheraGun Muscle Recovery Device, Wine Access
Online Wine Store, and Blinkist app that summarizes books. Click the sponsor links to get a discount
and to support this podcast. As a side note, let me ask that whenever we touch difficult
topics in this or other conversations that you listen with an open mind and forgive me or the
guest for a misstep in an imperfectly thought out statement. To have any chance at truth,
I think we have to take risks and make mistakes in conversation and then learn from those mistakes.
Please try not to close your mind and heart to others because of a single sentence or an
expression of an idea. Try to assume that the people in this conversation are just people in
general are good, but not perfect and far from it, but always striving to add a bit more love
into the world in whatever way we know how. If you enjoy this thing, subscribe on YouTube,
review it on Apple Podcast, follow on Spotify, support on Patreon, or connect with me on Twitter
at Lex Freedman. And now here's my conversation with Eric Weinstein. You often talk about
getting off this planet and I think you don't often talk about extra terrestrial life, intelligent
life out there. Do you wonder about this kind of thing, about intelligent civilizations out there?
I do, but I try to not wonder about it in a particular way. In a certain sense, I do find
that speculating about Bigfoot and the Loch Ness Monster and Space Aliens is kind of a recreation
for when things aren't going very well. At least it gives us some meaning and purpose in our lives.
So I worry about, for example, the simulation hypothesis is taking over from religion. You
can't quite believe enough to go to church or synagogue or the mosque on the weekend. So then
you just take up an interest in the simulation theory because that's something like what you
do for your job coding. I do think that in some sense, the issue of aliens is a really
interesting one, but has been spoiled by too much sort of recreational escapism.
The key question that I find is, let's assume that it is possible to look out at the night sky
and see all of these distant worlds and then go visit them. If that is possible, it's almost
certainly possible through some as yet unknown or not accepted theory of physics beyond Einstein.
It doesn't have to be that way, but probably is. If that theory exists, there would be a
percentage of the worlds that have life in sort of a Drake equation kind of a way that would have
encountered the ability to escape soon enough after unlocking the power of the atom at a
minimum and whatever they have that is probably analogous to the cell on that world. So assuming
that life is a fairly generic thing that arises, probably not carbon-based, probably doesn't have
DNA, but that something that fits the pattern of Darwinian theory, which is descent with variation,
differential success. And thereby constantly improving and so on that through time, there'll
be a trajectory where there'll be something increasingly complex and fascinating and beautiful
like us humans, but much more. That can also off-gas whatever entropy it creates to give an
illusion that you're defeating thermodynamics. So whatever these things are, probably has an
analog of the bilipid layer so that cells can get rid of the chaos on one side of the barrier and
keep order on the other. Whatever these things are that create life, assuming that there is a
theory to be found that allows that civilization to diversify, we would have to imagine that
such a civilization might have taken an interest in its concept of the universe and have come here.
They would come here. They would have a deep understanding of the physics of the universe
sufficient to have arrived here. Well, there's two questions, whether they could arrive physically
and whether their information could be sent here and whether they could gain information from us.
It's possible that they would have a way of looking into our world without actually reaching it. I
don't know. But yes, if my hope, which is that we can escape this world, can be realized if that's
feasible, then you would have to imagine that the reverse is true and that somebody else should be
here. First of all, I want to say this. My purpose when I come on to your show and I reframe the
questions is not to challenge you. I can sit inside all of those. It's to give you better audio and
video because I think we've been on an incredible role. I really love what you do. I am trying to
honor you by being as disagreeable about frame breaking as possible. I think some of your listeners
don't understand that it's actually a sign of respect as opposed to some sort of a complex
dynamic, which is I think you can play outside of some of the frames and that these are sort of
offerings to get the conversation started. So let me try to break that frame and give you something
different. Beautiful. I think what's going on here is that I can prove effectively that we're
not thinking about this in very deep terms. As soon as I say we've got to get off this planet,
the number of people who assume that I'm talking about faster than light travel
is very high. Faster than light travel assumes some sort of Einsteinian paradigm that then is broken
by some small adjustment. I think that that's fascinating. It shows me that our failure to
imagine what could be being said is profound. We don't have an idea of all of the different
different ways in which we might be able to visit distant worlds. All we think about is,
okay, it must be, it must be Einsteinian space times and then some means of exceeding the
speed limit. And it's just, it's fascinating to me that we don't really have, we've lost
the ability to just realize we don't know the framework. And what does it even mean? So one
of the things I think about a lot is worlds with more than one temporal dimension.
It's very hard to think about more than one temporal dimension.
So that's a really strong mental exercise of breaking the framework in which we think,
because most of the frameworks would have a single temporal dimension, right?
Well, first of all, most of the frameworks in which we think would have no temporal dimension,
would have pure, like in mathematics, the differential geometry that Riemann came up with
in the 1800s. We don't usually talk about what we would call split signature metrics,
or Lorentzian signature. In fact, if it weren't for relativity, this would be the most obscure
topic out there. Almost all the work we do is in Euclidean signature, and then there's this
one freakish case of relativity theory in physics that uses this one time and the rest spatial
dimensions. Fascinating. So it's usually momentary and just looking at space?
Yes. We have these three kinds of equations that are very important to us. We have
elliptic, hyperbolic, and parabolic. And so the idea is if I'm chewing gum after eating garlic bread,
when I open my mouth and I've got chewing gum between my lips,
maybe it's going to form an elliptic object called a minimal surface. Then when I pop that and
blow through it, you're going to hear a noise that's going to travel to you by a wave equation,
which is going to be hyperbolic. But then the garlic breath is going to diffuse towards you,
and you're eventually going to be very upset with me, according to a heat equation,
which will be parabolic. So those are the three basic paradigms for most of the work that we do.
And a lot of the work that we do in mathematics is elliptic, whereas the physicists are in the
hyperbolic case. And I don't even know what to do about more than one temporal dimension,
because I think almost no one studies that. I can't believe you just captured
much of modern physics in the example of chewing gum.
Well, I have an off-color one, which I chose not to share, but hopefully the kids at home...
Can imagine.
Okay, so that is the place where we come from. Now, if we want to arrive at a possibility of
breaking the frameworks with two versus zero temporal dimensions, how do we even begin to
think about that? Well, let's think about it as you and I getting together in New York City.
So if you tell me, Eric, I want to meet you in New York City, go to the corner
of, I don't know, 34th Street and 3rd Avenue, and you'll find a building on the northwest corner
and go up to the 17th floor, right? So when we have 3rd Avenue, that's one coordinate,
34th Street, that's the second coordinate, and go up to the 17th. And what time is that? Oh,
12 noon. All right. Well, now imagine that we traded the ability to get up to a particular
height in a building that's all flatland, but I'm going to give you two temporal coordinates. So
meet me at 5 p.m. and 12 noon at the corner of 34th and 3rd. That gets to be too mind-blowing.
I've got two separate watches. And presumably that's just specifying a single point in those
two different dimensions, but then being able to travel along those dimensions. Let me see your
right hand. You have no watch on that. I'm very concerned, Lex, that you're going through life
without a wristwatch. That is my favorite and most valued wristwatch. I want you to wear it.
This guy's funnier than basically any human on earth. That has been in my family for months.
It's a Fitbit. Now, what I want you to understand is Lex Fridman is now in a position to live
in two spatial and two temporal dimensions unlike the rest of us. I clearly am only fit for four
spatial dimensions. So I'm frozen, whereas you can double move.
I can double move, which is funny because this is set in Austin time. So it's 4 p.m. and this is set
in Los Angeles time. Well, but that's just with an affine shift in mod 12. But my point is,
wouldn't that be interesting if there were two separate time scales and you had to coordinate
both of those, but you didn't have to worry about what floor of the building because everything
was on the ground floor. That is the confusion that we're having. And if you do one more show,
then they're going to put a watch on your ankle and you're only going to have one spatial dimension
that you can move around. But my claim is that all of these are actually sectors of my theory,
in case we're interested in that, which is geometric unity. There is a 2-2 sector and a 3-1
and a 1-3 and a 0-4 and a 4-0. And all of these sectors have some physical reality. We happen
to live in a 1-3 sector. But that's the kind of thinking that we don't do. When I say we have
to get off this planet, people imagine, oh, okay, it's just Einstein plus some ability to break the
law. By the way, even though you did this for humor's sake, I perhaps am tempted to pull a Putin.
Am I going to get whacked? No, not quite. But he was given a Super Bowl ring
to look at. And he, instead of just looking at it, put it on his finger and walked away with it.
Robert Kraft? Robert Kraft, that's right. In the same way, I will, if you don't mind,
walk away with this Fitbit and taking the entirety of your life story with it because
there's all these steps on it. Boy, have you lost a lot of weight.
And where have I been? Exactly.
Right. That's what we're talking about. We're talking about, you want to get into aliens.
Let's have an interesting alien conversation. Let's stop having the typical free will conversation,
the typical alien conversation, the typical AGI morality conversation. It's like, we have to
recognize that we're amusing ourselves because we're not making progress. Time to have better
versions of all these conversations. Is there some version of the alien conversation that could
incorporate the breaking of frameworks? Well, I think so. I mean, the key question would be,
we've had the Pentagon release multiple videos of strange UFOs that undermined a lot of us.
I just think it's also really fascinating to talk about the fact that those of us who were
trained to call BS on all of this stuff just had the rug pulled out from under us by the
Pentagon choosing to do this. And you know what the effect of that is? You've opened the door
for every stupid theory known to man. My aunt saw a ghost. Okay. Now we're going to have to listen to,
well, hey, the Pentagon used to deny it. Then it turned out there were UFOs, dude.
Whoever is in charge of lying to the public, they need a cost function that incorporates
the damage and trust because I held this line that this was all garbage and all BS.
Now I don't know what to think. There's a fascinating aspect to this alien discussion,
the breaking of frameworks that involves the release of videos from the Pentagon,
which is almost like another dimension that trust in itself or the nature of truth and
information is a kind of dimension along which we're traveling constantly that is
messing with my head to think about because it almost feels like you need to incorporate
that into your study of the nature of reality is like the constant shifting of the notation,
the tools we use to communicate that reality. And so what am I supposed to think about these
videos? Is it a complete distraction? Is it a kind of cosmic joke? I don't know, but you know what,
I'm tired of these people just completely tired of these people on the Pentagon side or the people
who are interpreting this stuff on the Pentagon side. I'm tired of the authorities playing games
with what we can know. The fact that you and I don't, do you have a security clearance?
Some level of it for because I was funded for DARPA for a while.
I don't have a security clearance. You know, I am going to release whatever theory I have
my guess is that there is zero interest from our own government.
And so the Chinese will find out about it at the same time our government does
because Lord knows what they do in these buildings. I watch crazy people walk in and out of the
intelligence community, walk in and out of DARPA. And I think, wow, you're talking to that person?
That's really fascinating to me. We don't seem to have a clue as to who might have the ball.
Complete lack of transparency. Do you think it's possible there is the government is in
possession of something deeply fundamental to understanding of the world that they're not
releasing? So this is one, one thing is, this is one of the famous distractions that people
play with the narrative of alien life forms and spacecraft and possession that the government
is in possession of alien spacecraft. That's the narrative. Yeah.
I don't think the government really exists at the moment. I believe, and this is not an idea
that was original to me. There was a guy named Michael Tidalbaum who used to be at the Sloan
Foundation. And at some point I pointed out that the US government had completely contradictory
objectives when it came to the military and science. And one branch said this,
one branch said that. I said, you know, I don't understand which is true. What is the
government want? He said, do you think there's a government? And I said, what do you mean?
He said, what makes you think that the people in those two offices have ever coordinated?
What is it that allows each office to have a coherent plan with respect to every other office?
And that's when I first started to understand that there are periods where the government coheres
and then there are periods where the coherence just decays. And I think that that's been going
on since 1945, that there have been a few places where there's been increased coherence, but in
general, everything is just getting less and less coherent. And that what war did was focus us on
the need to have a government of people, a mission, capacity, technology, commitment, ideology.
And then as soon as that was gone, you know, different people, those who'd been through
World War II had one set of beliefs, those born in the 1950s, you know, or late 40s by the time
they got to Woodstock, they didn't buy any of that. So coherence is the complete opposite of like
bureaucracy being paralyzed by bureaucracy. So coherence is efficient functional government,
because when you say there's no government, meaning there's no emergent function from a
collection of individuals, it's just a bunch of individuals stuck in their offices without
any kind of efficient communication with each other on a single mission. And so a government
that is truly at the epitome of what a government is supposed to be is when a bunch of people working
together. What are we about? Are we about freedom? Are we about growth? Are we about decency and
fairness? Are we about the absence of a national culture so that we can all just do our own thing?
I've called this thing the USAN, the United States of Absolutely Nothing. These are all
different visions for our country. So it's possible that there's an alien spacecraft somewhere, and
there's like 20 people that know about it, and then they're kind of, as you communicate further and
further into the offices, that information dissipates, it gets distorted in some kind of way, and then
it's completely lost. The power, the possibility of that information is lost.
We bought a house, and I had this idea that I wanted to find out what all the switches did.
And I quickly found out that your house doesn't keep updating its plans. As people do modifications,
they just do the modifications, and they don't actually record why they were doing what they
were doing or what things lead to. So they're all sorts of bizarre, like there's a switch in my
house that says privacy. I don't know what privacy is. Does it turn on an electromagnetic field?
Does some lead shielding go over the house? That's what we have. We have a system in which
the people who've inherited these structures have no idea why their grandparents built them.
I'd be funny if there's a freedom of speech switch that you could also control,
and there would be perfect metaphor for our current state of things.
Because what they figured out is that if they can just make sure that we don't have any public
options for communication, then, hey, every thing that we say to each other goes through a
private company. Private companies can do whatever they want. And this is one of the greatest moves
that we didn't really notice. Electronic and digital speech makes every other kind of speech
irrelevant. And because there is no public option, guess what? There's always somebody named Sundar
or Jack or Mark who controls whether or not you could speak and what it appears to be that is
being said and who stuff is weighted more highly than others. It's an absolute nightmare. And by
the way, the Silicon Valley intellectual elite, Lord knows what is going on. People are so busy
making money that they are not actually upholding any of the values. So Silicon Valley is sort of
maximally against it. It has this kind of libertarian, free, progressive sheen to it when it goes to
Burning Man. And then it quickly just imposes rules on all of the rest of us as to what we
could say to each other if we're not part of the inner elite. So what do you think the ideal
of the freedom of speech means? Well, this is very interesting. I keep getting lectured on
social media by people who have no idea how much power the Supreme Court has to abstract things.
Right now, you have the concept of the letter of the law and the spirit of the law. And the spirit
of the law would have to say that our speech that matters is free, at least at the level of ideas.
I don't claim that I have the right to endanger your life with speech or to reveal your private
information. So I really am not opining about directed speech intended to smear you. And
that's a different kettle of fish. And maybe I have some rights to do that,
but I don't think that they're infinite. What I am saying is that the freedom of speech for ideas
is essential that the court abstract it and shove it down the throat of Google, Facebook,
Twitter, Amazon, whoever these infrastructure companies are, because it really matters which
abstraction use. The case that I really like is search and seizure. If I have private data
that I entered in my house that is stored on a server that you hold outside of my house,
but is the abstraction that it's only the perimeter of my house that I have the right to
protect? Or does my password extend the perimeter of my house to the data on the server that is
located outside of my house? These are choices for the court. And the court is supposed to pretend
that they can divine the true intent of the framers. But all of the sort of, and I've taken
the calling this the problem of internet hyenas, people with ready-made answers and LOLs and you're
such a moron. These folks love to remind you, it's a private company, dude, it can do whatever it wants.
No, the court has to figure out what the abstractions are. And just the way, for example,
the Griswold decision found that there was a penumbra because there was too little in the
constitution. Therefore, there were all sorts of things implied that couldn't be in the document.
Somebody needs to come up with the abstraction right now that says,
Jack, cannot do it over your wants. It's really, so you say the courts, but it's also us,
people who think about the world, it's you. No, no, no. It's the courts. But the courts don't do this.
We're toast. But we can still think about it. I mean, I don't feel like going down the drain.
Here's what I'm thinking about it because it's tricky how far it should extend. I mean, that's
an ongoing conversation. Don't you think the interpretation of the law? I think I'm trying
to say something very simple and it's just not going to be popular for a while.
Tech dwarfs previous forms of communication. Print or shouting in a public park. And so,
you know, I can go to a public park and I can shout if I get a permit. Even there,
I think it was in the late 1980s in Atlanta. We came up with free speech zones where you
can't protest at a convention. You bet you can go to a park 23 miles out and they'll fence off
a little area where you can have your free speech. No, speech is dangerous. Ideas are dangerous.
We are a country about danger and risk. And yes, I agree that targeted speech at individuals trying
to reveal their private stuff and all that kind of, that is very different. So forget a lot of
that stuff. But free speech for ideas is meant to be dangerous and people will die as a result of
free speech. The idea that one life is too much is preposterous. Like why did we send,
if one life is preposterous, why did we send anyone to the beaches of Normandy? I just don't
get this. So one thing that I was clearly bothered by, and maybe you can be my therapist as well,
I thought you were mine. This is, this is a little bit of a miscommunication on both of our
parts then. Because who's paying who for this? I was really bothered by Amazon banning parlor
from AWS because my assumption was that the infrastructure, I drew a distinction between
AWS, the infrastructure on which competing platforms could be created is different than the
actual platforms. So the standard of the ideal of freedom of speech, I in my mind, in a shallow way
perhaps applied differently to AWS than I did to Twitter. It felt that we've created a more
dangerous world, that freedoms were violated by banning parlor from AWS, which I saw as the
computing infrastructure which enables the competition of tools, the competition of
frameworks of communication. What do you think about this? First of all, let me give you the
internet hyena answer. I don't understand dude, just build your own Amazon. Yeah, right? Yes.
Well, so that's a very shallow statement, but it's also one that has some legitimacy. We can't
completely dismiss it because there's levels to this game. Yes and no, but if you really wanted
to chase that down, one of the great things about a person-to-person conversation is opposed to like,
let's have 30 of our closest friends. Whenever we have a conversation with 30 of our closest
friends, you know what happens? It's like passing light through a prism. Every person says something
interesting and as a result, it's always muddled. Nothing ever resolves. Well, one of my
conversational techniques you mentioned, you pushed back, is first this childlike naivety and
curiosity, but also- Real or simulated? Real, I'm afraid. I would say 8% real.
So in this paradigm, how could you not see this coming? I mean, I did a show with
Ashley Matthews, who's the woman behind Riley Reed, and specifically about this. It was about
the idea that if I move away from politics and go towards sex, I know that there's always a move
to use the infrastructure to shut down sex workers. And in this case, we had Operation
Choke Point under the Obama administration. We have a positive passion for people who want
to solve problems that they don't like. This company, they don't like. That company,
Payday Loans would be another one. And so you have legal companies that are harassed by our
financial system that you can't, you know, as Riley Reed, Ashley couldn't get a mailchimp
account according to her, if I understand her correctly. And this idea that you charge these
people higher rates because of supposed chargebacks on credit cards, even if they're chargebacks are
low. Yes, we have an unofficial policy of harassment. There's something about everybody
who shows up at Davos. They get drunk in the Swiss Alps, and then they come back home,
and they coordinate. And they coordinate things like build back better. We don't really understand
what build back better is, but my guess is is that build back better has to do with extremism
in America. How do we shut down the Republican Party as the source of extremism? Now, I do think
the Republican Party has got very extreme under Trump. And I do believe that that was responsive
to how extreme the Democratic Party got under Clinton first, and then Obama, and then Hillary.
And in all of these circumstances, it's amazing how much we want to wield these things as weapons.
Well, our extremism is fine because we pretend that Tifa doesn't exist and we don't report
what goes on in Portland, but your extremism, my God, that's disgusting. This is the completely
ridiculous place that we're in. And by the way, our friends in part are coked up on tech money,
and they don't appear to hold the courage of their convictions at a political level because
it's not in keeping with shareholder value. At some level, shareholder value is the ultimate
shield with which everyone can cloak themselves. Well, on that point, Donald Trump was banned from
Twitter, and I'm not sure it was a good financial decision for Twitter. Perhaps you can correct
me if I'm wrong. Well, are you thinking locally, or are you thinking if Twitter refused to ban
Donald Trump, what is the odds that the full force of the antitrust division might find them?
I don't know. Oh, I see. I see. So there's a complicated thing. Well, look, these guys are
all having a discussion in very practical terms. You can imagine the sorts of conversation.
Jack, Mark, Senator, we're really glad you're all here. We're all trying to
sing from the same hymnal and row in the same direction. We understand free speech. We're
completely committed to it, but we have to draw on with extremism, guys. We just need,
we need to make sure we're all on the same page. Well, they use the term violence too,
and they, I think, overapply it. So basically anybody...
I'm telling you, I say dumb things to incentivize thoughtful conversation.
Well, whatever these things are, there is no trace... Like, how old are you, Lex? You're in
your mid-thirties? Yeah, to late-forties.
Mid... Late-twenties to late-forties, somewhere in there.
That's the demographic.
I do think that partially what's happened is that your group has never seen functional
institutions. These institutions have been so compromised for so long,
you've probably never seen an adult. Sometimes I think Elon looks like an adult.
Well, I know that he has a wild lifestyle, but I also see him looking like an adult.
What does an adult look like, exactly?
Oh, you know, somebody who weighs things, speaks carefully, thinks about the future
beyond their own lifespan. Somebody who has a pretty good idea of how to get things done,
isn't wildly caught up in punitive actions, is more focused on breaking new ground than
playing rent-seeking games. I mean, I really had a positive... I was so completely chastised
when Elon must end up as the world's richest person. He was like, well, that's interesting,
back to work. That's what an adult would do.
That's what a grown-up would do. And weirdly, I said something about, isn't it amazing that the
world's richest person knows what a Lagrangian is, and he made a terrible Lagrange joke about
potentials? But yeah, I mean, I do think that ultimately, Elon may be one of the closest
things we have to an adult. And I can tell you that the internet hyenas will immediately descend
as to what a fraudster he is for pumping his stock price, talking his book and all this stuff.
Shut up.
So, looking at the world seriously and rigorously, you're saying that the people who are running
tech companies or running the mediums on which we can exercise the ideal of free speech are not
adults?
I think not. I think, first of all, a lot of them are Silicon Valley utopian businessmen,
where you talk a utopian line and you use it... You've heard my take, which is that
the idealism of every era is the cover story of its greatest thefts.
And I believe that in many ways, the idealism of Silicon Valley about connecting the world,
a world of abundance, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera, is really about the
software eating the world, as Mark Andreessen likes to say, through all these legacy properties,
and by simply being a bad tech version of something that previously existed like a newspaper,
you could immediately start to dwarf that by aggregating newspapers and their digital versions,
because digital is so much more powerful. As a result, yes, we have lots of man-children
wandering around what once was the Bay Area and is now Austin and Miami and other places,
maybe Singapore, that all of these people... These are friends of ours and they're brilliant
with respect to a certain amount of stuff, but none of them can get off the drip.
It's amazing that none of them have FU money. We've got billionaires who don't have FU money.
Okay. I think the argument used by Jack Dorsey was that there was an incitement of violence,
and not just Jack Dorsey, but everybody that was banning people. And then this word violence was
used as a kind of just like extremism and so on without much reason behind it. You think it's
impossible for Jack Dorsey or anybody else to be, as you said, an adult, a grown-up and...
Well, Jack is pretty close to being a grown-up. It seems like he is.
As you've discussed, it seems that he's been on the verge of almost being
quite serious and transparent and real. I don't know where the Jack Dorsey that I met
went, and I worry that that must be something behind the scenes that I can't see.
From my perspective, what I think is the stress, the burden of that when people are
screaming at you. Jack is a Zen monk. He really is. Jack is an incredibly impressive person,
intellectually, morally, spiritually, at least for a couple of meetings. I don't know him very
well, but I'm very impressed by the person I met, and I don't know where that person is,
and that terrifies me. But do you think somebody could step up in that way?
No. Does a human being have the capacity to be transparent about the reasoning behind the banning,
or do you think all banning eventually, all banning of people from mediums of communication
is eventually destructive, or it's impossible for human beings to reason with ourselves about it?
Well, let's see what the problem is. My phone has been on airplane mode. I'm going to unlock it.
I'm going to take a picture of Lex Fridden. Now, if I can, I'm going to tweet that picture out.
Great. But here's the weird part about it. That picture sitting with
Lex today. This, ladies and gentlemen, is how the sausage is made.
Okay. In so doing, I have just sent a picture of you and a tiny piece of text all over the
planet that has arrived at, if statistics tell the truth, just under half a million different
accounts. And then more from sharing and so on. Well, in some of those accounts are dead,
we don't really know how many places it went. But the key issue with that tweet is that
that is a non-local phenomenon. Yes. So I just broadcasted to an entire planet. Somebody in
Uganda is reading that at the same time as somebody in Uruguay. There is no known solution to have
so many people with the ability to communicate non-locally because locality was part of the
implicit nature of speech inside of the constitution. Friction, locality, there were all sorts of other
aspects to speech. So if you think about speech as a bundle, I like this.
Then it got unbundled. And some of those aspects that we were naturally counting on to retard
the impact of speech aren't present. And we don't have the courage to say,
I wonder if the First Amendment really applies in the modern era in the same way,
or we have to work through an abstraction. Either we probably have to amend the constitution,
or we have to abstract it properly. And that issue is not something we're facing up to. I watch us
constantly look backwards. We don't seem to try to come up with new ideas and new theories. Nobody
really imagines that we're going to be able to wisely amend the constitution anymore inside of
the United States. Many people abroad will say, why are these guys talking about the US? It's a
US-centric program. Well, that's because nobody knows where this program lives.
The fact, by the way, that you and I happen to be in a physical place together is also
bizarre. It could be anywhere. It doesn't really matter that it happens to be here.
So the difference between logical and between physical, local, non-local,
frictional, non-fictional, it's the same thing with firearms. Nobody imagined that the
gatling gun was going to be present when you had to reload a musket.
And that's fascinating to think about. You're exactly right that the nature of this particular
freedom that seems so foundational to this nation, to what made this nation great, and perhaps
much of the world that is great, made it great, is changing completely. Can we try to reason through
how the ideal freedom of speech is to be changed? I guess I'm struggling. It feels really wrong,
perhaps because I wasn't paying attention to it. It feels really wrong to ban Donald Trump
from Twitter, to ban not just the president. That's really wrong to me. But this particular
human for being divisive. But then when there's an incitement of violence,
that is an overused claim. But perhaps there was actual brewing of local violence happening. So
one of the things I know what's happening on Parler is people were scheduling meetings together
in physical space. So you're now going back from this dynamic, social, large-scale people
from Uganda, people from all over the world being able to communicate. You're now mapping that into
now back meeting in the physical space that is similar to what the founding of this nation was.
But if the violence were digital, if ransomware suddenly was unleashed, the key issue is the
abstractions. So what was freedom of speech as a bundle? And then how do we abstract the bundle
into the digital era? Do you think we just need to raise the question and talk about it? Do you
have ideas? Well, sure I have ideas. But the key point is that I'm not even welcome in mainstream
media. I've never seen you on mainstream media. Do you do mainstream media? So we exist in part
of an alternate universe because the mainstream media is trying to have a coherent story, which I
have called the gated institutional narrative. And the institutions pretend that they plug their
fingers in their ears and pretend that nothing exists outside of MSNBC talking to CNN about what
was in the New York Times as covered by the Washington Post. And so that's effectively like a
professional wrestling promotion where they, you know, the undertaker faces off against Hulk Hogan
and Rowdy Roddy Piper. Okay, well, that's very different than MMA. You've recently been on
Glenn Beck's program. Yeah. And there was this kind of one of the things you've talked about
is being able to have this conversation. I don't know if you would put it as a type of
conversation that was happening outside the mainstream media, but a conversation that
reaches across different worldviews and having a nuanced or just like a respectful
conversation that's grounded and mutual. But we can't have the reality because the main model is
the center, both left and right is in the process of stealing all the wealth that we built up.
And they've organized the extremes into two LARPing teams that I've called
MAgastand and Wokastand. And then you have everybody who isn't part of that complex,
all seven of us, the number of us who are able to earn a living looking at all of these mad
people playing this game. You know, there's a phrase inside finance when the investment banks
are trying to look at price action. And somebody says, this doesn't make any sense.
And somebody will say, it's just the locals stealing from each other. And that's really
what we have. We've got the leaders of MAgastand and Wokastand championing these two teams sponsored
by the center because it's a distraction while they steal all the silver and cut the paintings
out of the frames. That's what you and I are looking at. So when you ask me, do you have any
ideas about the abstraction for free speech? I've never met Mark Zuckerberg. I've never met
Sundar Pichai. I never met Larry Page. I was once in a room with Sergey Brin. I've never
spoken to Elon Musk. I hang out with Peter Thiel, but we have a very deep relationship,
but I don't really speak to that many other people at sort of at this level.
We're not having any kind of smart conversation at a national level. In fact, it's almost as if
we've destroyed every sandbox in which we could play together. There's no place
that we actually talk except long form podcasting. And by the way, they've found,
you see what's going on with like Alex Stamos and the Hoover Institution.
There's a loophole left. Long form podcasting allows people to speak at levels above daytime
CNN. It's like, well, why do you think they're not watching daytime CNN?
But that's just silly journalism. They currently have no power to
displace podcasting. That's why it's so powerful. RSS feed. I mean, that's why the big challenge
with Joe Rogan and Spotify is like, there's this dance that's fascinating to see is Joe Rogan is
not part of the system. And then he's also uncancelable. And there's this tension that's
happening. Well, Howard Stern, Howard Stern became much less relevant. So if they can't control Joe
by bringing him in house, the key question is, is he going to continue? Like, you know, this
Joe says this thing about FU money. Yeah. Joe's one of the only people with FU money who's actually
said FU. Yeah. I don't understand this. I don't have FU money. What exactly is, can we break apart
FU money? Because I always thought I've been fortunate enough to have always have FU money
in the sense that my standards were so low that a basic salary in the United States.
This is the stoic point, which is it can live on rice and beans. You're uncancelable because
you're always rich relative to your needs. So isn't that FU fundamental FU money? Why do you say
that tech billionaires don't have FU money? When you need to hire private security to protect
your family, how do you protect your two children? I don't have those yet. Bingo. Yeah. My point is,
is that FU money insulates everything that you care about. It's not just about you. So you're
saying as the level of responsibility grows, the amount of money required for FU
we have a war going on. The war is on academic freedom. Academic freedom used to be present
in the system as a, in terms of the idea, we trust our elite. Now we have an idea like,
you want to be the elite, you know, you want a Lord above us. That's like, first of all,
there's like a populist anti-elitist thing. Then there's the idea that we're going to defer tenure
for forever. Then we're going to tell people stay in your lane. Your tenure is only good for your
own particular tiny micro subject. Then we're going to also control your grants and we'll
be able to load up your teaching load if we don't like who you are and we'll make your life
absolutely impossible. We lost academic freedom and we ushered in peer review, which was a disaster.
And then we lost funding so that people were confident that they would have the ability to
do research no matter what they said. And as a result, what you find is, is a world in which
there's no ability to get people to say, no, I'm not going to sign your diversity and inclusion
forced loyalty oath. I won't sign any loyalty oath. Get the hell out of my office. FU.
FU. And you're connecting money to that, but. Well, my point is, is that academic freedom
is the whole idea behind it was that you will have the freedom of a billionaire
on a much smaller salary. Right. Okay. We've lost that. Yeah. The only reason in part that I wanted
to go into academic, academics as a profession, as opposed to wanting to do physical or mathematical
research, the great prize was freedom. Ralph Gomery of the Sloan Foundation previously of IBM
research pointed it out. He says, if you lose freedom, you lose the only thing we had to offer
top minds, top minds value their intellectual freedom and their physical and economic security
at a different level than other human beings. And so people say, you know,
I don't understand, dude, you have the ability to do X, Y and Z. What's the problem? It's like, well,
I value my ability to raise the middle finger as an American practically above everything else.
I want to talk to you about freedom here in the context of something you've mentioned, which
one way to take away freedom is to put a human being into a cage to create constraints. The other
one that worries me is something that I think you spoke into Twitter a little bit on Twitter is
we bleed freedom by kind of slowly scaring you into not doing, not expressing the full spectrum
of opportunities you can as freedom. So like when you ban Donald Trump, when you ban Parler,
you give a little doubt in the minds of millions like me, a person who's a tech person,
who's an entrepreneur, there's a little, that's what I'm afraid of when I look in the mirror.
Is there not a little doubt in there that limits the amount of options I will try?
How certain are you that the COVID virus didn't come from the Wuhan lab and his biosafety level
for? We both know that we're both supposed to robotically say the idea that the COVID virus
came from a lab is a discredited conspiracy theory. There is no evidence that suggests
that this is true. The World Health Organization and the CDC have both upon this to say otherwise
would be incredibly irresponsible. And the threat of that is the thing that ultimately limits
the freedoms we feel. I should be tweeting about Jeff Epstein all the time.
And you're afraid. In a sense.
It's also boring. I mean, I said it in the public many times.
Why is it we don't ask where the records are from Velard House? Where are the financial records?
Where are the SEC filings? Where are the questions on the record to the intelligence
agencies? Was he known to be part of the intelligence community? So we're not interested
in asking questions. Am I going to die as a result of asking the question?
Was Jeff Epstein part of the intelligence community of any nation?
Is there a reason we're not asking about the financial records of the supposed hedge fund
that he didn't run? Just like the Wuhan lab.
Okay. How do we get to the core of the Jeffrey Epstein, the truth behind Jeffrey Epstein, in
a sense? I mean, there's some things that are just useless conspiracy theories around it,
even if they're true. There's some things they get.
I hate to say it. You're not going to like it.
Look at the 1971 media Pennsylvania break-in of the Citizens' Committee to investigate the FBI.
Those kids, and by the way, they weren't all kids, did what had to be done.
They broke in. They broke the law. It was an incredible act of civil disobedience.
And God bless Judy Feingold for taking to her, she was going to take to her grave.
That she'd been part of this, like the coolest thing of all time.
They didn't say anything for forever. So civil disobedience. I mean, you have to...
We are founded on civil disobedience. Civil disobedience is incredibly...
You screw it up and you're just a vandal. You screw it up, you're a hooligan.
Those cats were so disciplined. It's an art form.
It was an art form and they risked everything they were willing to pay with their freedom.
Those are the sorts of people who earned the right by putting themselves at risk.
I would not do this. I am not volunteering to break into anything.
I think it was William Davodon who was a student of Murray Gelman and a physics professor at Haverford
who corralled these people and led this effort.
And right now, what we need is somebody to blow the lid off of what is controlling everything.
I'm happy to hear that it's a system of incentive structures,
that it's a system of selective pressures. I'm happy to find out that it's emergent.
I'm happy to find that it's partially directed by our own intelligence community.
I'm happy to hear that, in fact, we've been penetrated by North Korea, Iran, China, and Russia.
But I need to know why people aren't... The firebombing of the courthouse in Portland,
Oregon has no explanation. And somehow this is normal. This is not normal to any human being.
We have video that people don't believe. I come back to the shaggy defense of it wasn't me.
It's like...
You remember that song? Shaggy, yeah. It wasn't me. He caught you
banging him in the shower on the counter. Yeah, exactly. It wasn't me.
His friend says, well, your strategy makes no sense at all.
But this is what MSNBC is doing. You dropped him from the graphic. It wasn't me.
It wasn't me. You came up with another yank. It wasn't me.
I will never see MSNBC the same again. So you've spoken about him before. I think it would be nice
to maybe honor him to break it apart a little bit. Aaron Schwartz. Why was he a special human
being in this ilk of what we're talking about now, civil disobedience? How do we honor him
now moving forward as human beings who are willing to take risks in this world?
Well, I don't know. Are you inspired by Aaron Schwartz?
I am. How do you feel about JSTOR? Let's talk about JSTOR first. Let's say what JSTOR is all about.
We the taxpayer pay for research and then the people who do the research do all the work for a
bunch of companies who then charge us $30 an article to read what it is that we already paid
for. And if we don't cite these articles, we're told that we're in violation. Okay.
I almost never call for civil disobedience because I don't really want to, but
fuck JSTOR, fuck Elsevier, fuck Springer. Who the fuck are these people?
Yeah. The smart people need to take the greedy people behind the woodshed and explain to them
what science is. I have a very old fashioned idea that's so out of favor that I will immediately
be seen as a knuckle-dragger. I believe in the great woman theory of history and the great man
theory of history. Emmy Nerder is fantastic as an example. And I believe in editors over peer
reviewers. And I believe that wrong things should be allowed into the literature. And I believe that
the gatekeeping should go towards zero because the costs associated with distribution are very,
very slight. I believe that we should be looking at the perverse incentives of sending your paper
blindly into your competitors' clutches, particularly if you're a young person being
reviewed by an older person. Are you familiar with the Duat de Senor? Are you familiar with
the legend of the Magnaia? No. The Magnaia is the Miller's daughter. And the largest food fight
in the entire universe, I believe, is held, I think in Italy. It's called the Battle of the
Oranges. And it celebrates the Miller's daughter who had fallen in love with her beloved. And when
it came time for them to marry, the Virginal Magnaia was in fact told that the Lord of the land
had the right to have the first night with the bride. Well, the Magnaia had a different idea.
So she seemed to consent to this perhaps mythical right, also called the Prima note the first night.
And by legend, she concealed a dagger underneath her robes. And when it came time for the hated
Lord of the Manor to extract this right, she pulled the knife out and killed him. And I think it
also echoes a little bit of particularly wonderful scene from Game of Thrones. But that inspired
both men and women. And the Magnaia is the legendary hero. Right now, what we need to do is we need
to resist the Prima note, the right of first look, right? F you, you don't have the right of first
look. I don't want to send something blindly to my competitors. I don't want to subject myself to
you naming what work I've done. Why are you in my story? That's my question. Get out of my story.
If I do work, and then you have an idea, oh, well, it's the Matthew principle. To him,
who has much more will be given. I've gone to the National Academy of Sciences and talked about
these things. And it's funny, I've been laughed at by the older people who think, well, Eric,
you know, science proceeds funeral by funeral, that's plonk. You know, the Matthew principle,
you know, the Matilda principle that things done by women are attributed to men,
that these are not new. And you guys just live like this?
Yeah. So the revolutionary act now is to resist all of these things that are not new.
So you asked me about Aaron Schwartz. Aaron Schwartz was the Magnaia. One of the things
you've done very beautifully is to communicate love. And I think about some of our conversations.
You got me to talk a little bit about my own experiences in 02138 and 39.
We are the product of our trauma. And what people don't understand is that very often,
when you see people taking countermeasures against what appear to be imaginary forces,
they're really actually replaying things that really happen to them.
And having been through this system and watching all of the ways in which it completely rewrites
the lives of the people who I am counting on to cure our diseases, build our new industries,
keep us safe from our foes, the amount of pressure the system is putting on the most
hopeful minds is unimaginable. And so my goal is to empower somebody like an Aaron Schwartz in memory
and to talk about a Jeffrey Epstein situation. Do you know that the first person outside
of me to get a look at geometric unity was Jeffrey Epstein?
How did he know I was working on this? I don't know.
So your ideas that formed geometric unity was something that his eyes have seen?
I was pushed to talk to Jeffrey Epstein as one of the only people who could help me.
No, no, no, listen to this. Yeah, how does this connect?
Okay. Well, first of all, my old synagogue, my old school, was the conservative minion at Harvard
Hillel. And I believe it's called Rossofsky Hall after Henry Rossofsky in the economics department
who was a Japan scholar, if I'm correct. And he became provost or dean of Harvard.
I believe that that was built with Jeffrey Epstein's money. And I wondered in part whether the Jewish
students at Harvard all sort of passed through a bottleneck of Harvard Hillel. So that was something
I found very curious, but I don't know much about it. I also found that Jeffrey Epstein hanging
around scientists. I don't think that either you or Joe exactly, I mean, got me correct
in your last interchange. For the record, for people who didn't have a listen to Joe Rogan
program, Joe has claimed that Eric Weinstein was the only person who has gotten laid. And you said
you also got paid as a young man, right? I believe the word was laid, but allegedly.
My hearing isn't so good at age 55. All right, leaving that aside.
What was Jeffrey Epstein doing hanging around all of these scientists? I don't think that was the
same program that was about compromising political leaders and business people and entertainment
figures. I think these are two different programs that were being run through one individual.
And Joe seemed to think that I didn't think he was smooth. I thought he was glib. I think what Joe
was really trying to get at was that I found his mysticism meretricious. He had an ability to deflect
every conversation that might go towards revealing that he didn't know what he was talking about.
Every time you started to get close to something where the rubber hit the road, the rubber wouldn't
hit the road. And yet, can you help me untangle the fact that you thought deeply about the physics
of the nature of our universe? And Jeffrey Epstein was interested.
How did he know? I wasn't really talking about this stuff until
even my close friends didn't really know what I was up to.
And yet, you're saying he did not have sufficient brilliance to understand
when the rubber hit the road. So why did he have sufficient interest and curiosity?
Tell me what I thought. I've been waiting to find out, does my government even know I exist?
Do you have an answer to that question? A couple times, the government has reached out to me.
In general, there is zero interest in me, less than zero interest. I find that fascinating.
As far as you know, right? Well, that's what I'm trying to say. The question about not being able
to see through a half-silvered mirror, you don't know what's going on behind the half-silvered
mirror. To you, all you see is your reflection. But your intuition still holds. This is where I've
mentioned that I... This is where I'll say naive dumb things, but I still hold on to this intuition
that Jeff... I'm not confident in this, but I lean towards that direction that Jeffrey Epstein is the
source of evil, not something that's underlying him. You have a bias. It's different than mine.
Our Bayesian priors are tutored by different life experiences. If I was mostly concerned,
like Sam Harris is concerned, that people fill their heads with nonsense,
I would have a very strong sense that people need order in the world, that they take
mysterious situations, they build entire castles in the air, and then they go move in if they
really get crazy. The old saying is that neurotics build castles in the air and
psychotics move in. Coming from a progressive family, we had a different experience. It's
really weird when the government is actually out to get you, when they actually send a spy,
when they actually engage in disinformation campaigns, when they smear you. And if you've
ever had that brought to bear on your family, you have a Howard Zinn sort of understanding
of the country, which is different than having a, wow, do people believe crazy stuff because
they watch too much TV? And both of these things have some merit to them, but it's a question
of regulated expression. When do you want to express more Sam Harris and when do you want to
express more Howard Zinn? You can express both, correct? The one human being can express both?
Sure, but there's a trade-off between them. In other words, most people, like the Michael
Shermers of the world are going to tilt very strongly to extraordinary claims, require extraordinary
evidence. You're going to have that kind of energy. And then somebody else is going to say,
how many times do I have to hammer my own thumb before I realize that there's a problem?
So my feeling about this is, yes, people see patterns in clouds. They see faces and scripture
and all sorts of things, and it's just random cloud patterns. And it's also the case that there's
tremendous pressure not to see conspiracies when conspiracies are relatively more common
than the people who shout conspiracy theory will claim. So both of these things are true. And you
have to ask, when do you express your inner Zinn and when your inner Harris? And those are different.
One fundamental difference you and I biases aside is you've actually met Jeffrey Epstein.
And I'm listening to reverberations years later of stories and narratives throughout the story.
Luckily, I only met him once. And I think I had one or perhaps two phone conversations with him
other than the one meeting. You can learn a lot in just a few words from a human being.
Well, that's true. But I think that the bigger issue was I saw something that I don't hear
much remarked upon, which is Jeffrey Epstein is all that there is. In other words, there's the
National Science Foundation, National Institute of Health, Howard Hughes, there's all this stuff
that kind of has the same feel to it, a little bit of variation and difference,
Department of Energy. If you fall outside of that, there's just Jeffrey Epstein. That's what you're
told. That's not quite true. There's Cavley. Maybe Jim Simons is now in the game. Peter
Thiel has done some stuff. You had Yuri Milner and Mark Zuckerberg try. So there is other money
running around, Templeton. But very strongly, there was a belief that if you're doing something
really innovative and the system can't fund it because we become pussies, Jeffrey Epstein's your
guy. And that's because it's funnel that you're supposed to go through.
That's right. And the idea is that you get called to the great man's house and the sort of
lubricious version of Ralph Lauren takes you in and asks you bizarre questions and maybe he has
an island, maybe he has a plane. And when you're starved, somebody showing you a feast or when
you're dehydrated in a death's door and somebody says, oh, I have a well. That's what it is.
And so the thought is, wow, can somebody get some effing money into the science system so that we
don't have super creeps trying to learn all of our secrets ahead of time? WTF, what is your problem
with transparency and taxpayer dollars? All of you, you wouldn't have a country. You'd be speaking
German. So essentially, you believe that human beings would not be able to, when the money is
lacking in the system, like in research. We produce public goods. You and I are meant to produce
public goods. Now, I sell athletic greens and I sell Theragun and I sell Unagi scooters
and Chili Pat. Can I be honest? I love these products. But I didn't get into this game for the
purpose of selling. I'm trying to figure out how do you have an FU lifestyle? But you know something
like, I don't know why you built this channel. It's kind of a mystery. I'll tell you why I built
my channel. It's going to be a lot harder to roll me this time in an alley. I got rolled multiple
times and my point is I didn't want to become a celebrity. I didn't want to become well known,
but it's a lot harder to roll somebody who's getting, you know, I think I'm, I don't know if
this is mistaken, but I think I'm the math PhD with the largest number of followers on Twitter.
And there was nothing you could do before. I mean, again, to put a little responsibility on you.
So you've created something really special for the distribution of your own ideas. I mean,
but because it's not necessarily currently scalable, you also, perhaps you and I have
the responsibility of giving other people also a chance to spread their ideas. I mean, Joe Rogan
did this very effectively for a bunch of people that. That's why they're angry at him because
he's a gatekeeper and he let all sorts of people through that gate from Roger, from Roger Penrose
to Alex Jones. To Jordan Peterson to, I mean, even, first of all, to you and to Abby Martin.
To Abby Martin. To Barry Weiss. Yeah. That's the problem. Well, but you have not successfully
built up a thing that allows that to carry that forward. No, no, no, no. We are all vulnerable
to reputational attack because what happens, you see, the problem Lexis is that you are now in
an institution at some level. You walk around with all this equipment in a duffel bag,
the last suit, the last suit you'll ever need. And you have the reach of something like CNN
to people who matter. Okay. So now the question is, how do we control something that doesn't
have a board, doesn't have shareholders, doesn't have to make SEC filings, FCC. So the best
answer they have is, well, we just have to destroy reputations. All it takes is for us
to take something that gets said or done or alleged. And I think it's incredibly important.
One of the things people don't understand is that I'm going to fight general reputational attacks,
not because some people don't deserve to have their reputations drag through the mud,
but because it's too powerful of a tool to hand it to CNN, MSNBC, Princeton, Harvard,
the State Department. Yes. But as some of it is also...
Jake Morgan. Muhammad Ali style being good enough at
doing everything you need to do without giving enough meat for the reputational attacks,
not being afraid, but not giving enough meat. I don't see why the people who have good ideas
have to lead lives that are that clean. If you can do it. You can be messy. Yeah. You should
be able to be messy that otherwise we're suppressing too many people. Look. Too many, too
billion minds. Yeah. Can you believe Elon Musk smoked a blunt? I still people tell me this.
Okay. I have discussions about Elon and people,
the Avi Loeb, the Harvard scientist who's talking about Amua Amua that it might be alien technology.
He told me this outside the box thinker. Yeah. When speaking to me about Elon,
said, called him the guy who smoked, he smokes weed. The blunt in a dismissive way.
Like this guy is crazy because he smoked some weed. I was looking at him. I was like, why? Wow.
Wow. I think you should be able to have consensual drug filled orgies. Fuck perfect lives.
Yeah. You should be allowed to be messy. Yeah. Right. I take back my statement. I'm just saying.
Respectability is the unique prison where all of the gates are open and the inmates
beg to stay inside. It's time to end their prison of respectability because it's too
effective of a means of sidelining and silencing people, including it is better that we have bad
people in our system than this idea of no platforming people who are beyond the pale
because it's such a simple technique. So what's the heroic action here on the...
Well, for example, having Ashley Matthews on my program. By the way, she was absolutely
delightful as a guest. She is polite in the extreme, far more polite than I am.
And I had her right after Roger Penrose as a guest because I wanted to highlight this
program can go anywhere. We can talk to anyone. What about social media? You've started highlighting
people being banned on social media. How do we fight this? Like if you get banned from social
media, so you're saying nobody will stand up to me? Well, just figure out what your incentive
structure is before. Assume that I get banned on social media because somebody wants to make
sure that my message doesn't interfere with the dominant narrative. Yeah. Okay.
What will happen? By the way, I'm very glad to be able to explain this on your show because
that video will presumably be archived and they can't easily make you take it down. Okay.
So what's going to happen is that there'll be a whole bunch of very low quality bot-like
accounts that dog you every time you talk about me.
Right. Dude, it's getting old. It's getting boring. We already heard you. Dude, that was like,
let it go. Not a good look. Not a good look is one of my favorites.
But what about the high-profile ones? Well, then you'll get a few high-profile ones and some of
the high-profile ones command armies. Like at some point, I had 10,000 people using exactly the
same templated tweeting at me. It was just actually, it got to the point where it was funny because
everybody said, did you hear that in a hipster coffee shop? I was like,
why are you all suddenly talking about hipster coffee? It's hilarious.
Those things will cause you to think better of it. You'll start to see your follower can't go down
because it's easy to give you a bunch of bot-like follows and then just pull them.
So I think it's pretty well known how, and then maybe your account will be suspended and it can't
be revoked and etc. And then three days later, you'll be told it was an error.
So let me push back. I just don't see not defending you. So what are the things you would do
that, given that I can actually talk to you offline, that would make me not defend you?
Well, first of all, I can imagine some. But all of us have things. If somebody says,
do you hear what your boy Lex said about you? What did Lex say about me? Oh, he said you were
flawed, dude. Oh, shit. They're so distressed because none of us want to stand behind flawed
people. That's why you have everybody rushing to say, I neither condemn nor condone. I know,
I don't condemn nor condone. What is that? We're all trying to say-
By the way, for the record, I said that Eric is smarter than me in a brilliant human being,
but flawed like all humans are. My point is, I've now come up with a new policy,
which is I don't care what my friends have done. I am not disavowing my friends. Not because
they didn't do the wrong thing. Maybe they did do the wrong thing. I don't know.
What's the value of friendship if that's not that? Like, for example, we've had the situation
with Brian Callan. Brian Callan was featured recently in the Los Angeles Times. I know nothing
about the allegations. I can't. I didn't even know Brian at the time, right? I've known him for
roughly the time I've been in Los Angeles, maybe a year and a half during that period of time.
I've never seen anything wrong. Now I'm in a situation. What do you think he did? Do you think
he didn't? It's like, you know what? I don't know. But I do know this. Everyone's entitled to have
friends because we can't afford isolated people. And if your friends do the wrong thing,
they're still your friends. And if they do terrible, terrible things, you bring that up with
them privately. And it's not my responsibility to disavow in public. We've had this situation
that I don't like where particular people that I've been close to, I'm put under tremendous
pressure to disavow them. What do you think now about your buddy? I like Dave Rubin and all that
kind of stuff. Here's the thing. My friends are my friends. I don't disavow my friends.
We all need to make a statement that we will not be brought under pressure to disavow our friends,
our family members, because mass murderers are dangerous the more isolated they become.
It is not a good idea to constantly push to isolate people. And it's dangerous.
It sends a signal to everybody else to fit in, to be more cynical about the
human connection we have to each other. If I find out you've been selling heroin
to elementary school students, you're still my friend and I will not be disavowing you.
And if I have a problem with you selling heroin to elementary school students
during school hours, I will bring it up with you privately because we don't need to hear my voice
added to that condemnation. Are there things that you could do that would cause me to say,
actually, F this guy? Yeah, above and beyond that. But simply doing the wrong thing, I think we've
gone down a terrible path. I think isolated people are about the most dangerous thing we could have
in a heavily armed society. So I deeply agree with you. I'm Brian Callan and all these people
that quote unquote got canceled. And I'm not saying that I don't know the truth value because we
can't. And even if I did know the truth value, I'm not setting up an incentive structure for the
personal destruction as a means of letting institutions combat the fact that individuals
are the last thing that can say none of you guys make any sense. I don't treat these things like,
you know, I had a conversation where Kevin Spacey was at the dinner table when I came down from a
hotel room. And I had a very long conversation with Kevin Spacey. I will not detail because
I don't do that as to what we discussed. But we talked very specifically about him being canceled.
And I don't think that the world has heard that story in part because there's a very strong sense
that he has to be out grouped. And as a result, you know, I mean, do we want do we want to disavow
the space program because it touched Werner von Braun? Do we want to disavow quantum mechanics
because Pascal Jordan and Werner Heisenberg passed through it? Is Aaron Fest theorem false
because he murdered his child? I mean, at what point do we recognize that we are the problem?
Humans are humans. And there is no perfect, there is no perfect group of people, even all of the
most oppressed people, the supposed victims of the world who we now have fetishized into thinking
that they're all oracles because their lived experience informs us and their pain is more
salient than everyone else's pain. Those people are necessarily great people. You know, it's like
none of us, we can't, we can't do this in this fashion. So when we sit down to have a conversation
across the table from somebody, you should be willing to, like you should not have NPR in your
mind, you should be willing to take the full risk and to see the good in the person without,
with limited information and to do your best to understand that person.
Everybody is entitled to a hypocrisy budget. I don't believe this is of institutions.
Everybody is entitled to a certain amount of screwing up in life.
You're entitled to a mendacity budget. You're entitled to an aggression budget.
The idea of getting rid of everybody is, you know, people haven't even blown through their
budgets and we're already. Yeah. I think about, for example, one person, I'd be curious to get
your thoughts about Alex Jones. Let's not talk about Alex Jones for a second. Let's talk about
the National Enquirer. Is everything the National Enquirer says false? No. Okay. Do you remember
the John Edwards story? Did she run his wife? Sorry. He had a child from an extramarital affair.
Yes. I believe that the National Enquirer broke the story.
And then what does the New York Times do? The New York Times, I think, is allowed to report that
the National Enquirer is making a claim. That way they don't have to substantiate the story.
So why is the New York Times talking to Mike Cernovich or using the National Enquirer as a
source? Are they using Alex Jones as a source? Who, here's the big problem that we're having.
Why are certain people entitled to talk to everybody and other people are entitled to talk
to no one? I don't really understand this. This is an indulgence system. This is how the Catholic
Church used to do things. It's hard to fight the system because the reason you don't talk to Alex
Jones is because the platforms on which we do the communication will de-platform, will remove you.
But I'm not platformed. I used to do NPR and I used to do the news hour and I used to
provide stories to Washington Post New York Times. That has gone away. They've circled the
wagons closer and closer and more of us are unacceptable. And right now I have no question
that they're going through anybody who has a platform trying to say, okay, what do we have
against that person in case we need to shut that down? We have to make a different decision, Lex.
And the different decision is that it doesn't matter how many times Joe said the N-word.
It doesn't matter that somebody else, with mathematical theorems, if the worst person
in the world proves a mathematical theorem like the Unabomber, we can't undo the theorem.
And I point out Charles Manson's song, Look At Your Game Girl is an amazing song. It's a really
good song. I don't think it's one of the greatest songs ever, but it happens that he wasn't a no
talent. And I don't know how Hitler was as an artist. Fiction, not bad.
Okay, we've got to get past this. We've got to get past this idea that we're going to purge
ourselves of our badness. And we're just going to, this is like, I liken it to teenage girls in
cutting. We're just, all we're doing is destroying ourselves in search of perfection. And the answer
is no, we're not perfect. We're flawed. We're screwed up. And we've always been this way.
And we're not going to silence everyone who you can point a laser beam at and say, well,
that person, look at how bad that person is. If we do that, kiss the whole thing goodbye.
We might as well just, let's learn Chinese. But there is an art to having those messy
conversations, whether with Alex or anybody else. Okay, let's talk about Alex. There's
particular stuff that Alex does that's absolutely nauseating. And there's other stuff that he's
doing that's funny. The methodology of the way he carries. And sometimes he's talking about the
truth. And sometimes he's talking about a conspiracy theory. His variance is incredibly high.
The right way to approach Alex Jones or James O'Keefe or the National Enquirer or anything you
don't like is to say, great, go long short. What's that mean? Well, if you invest in a mutual fund,
all the stocks in the mutual fund are held long. But if you invest in a hedge fund,
you do something called relative value trade. It's like, well, you long tech or short tech?
Well, actually, I'm long Microsoft and I'm short Google. Why is that? Oh, because I believe Google
got way too much attention and that Microsoft has been unfairly maligned. And so this is really a
play on legacy tech over more modern tech. Okay. Which part of Alex Jones are you long?
And which part are you short? One of the things that should be a requirement for being a reporter
is like, what did Donald Trump do that was good? Nothing. Okay, then you're not a reporter.
What did Hitler do that was good?
The Rosenstrasza protest.
Non-Jewish women campaign for their Jewish men to be returned home to them
from certain death almost in death camps. It should have been that not there were no death camps.
It should have been that everybody was returned home. But you know what? The fact that the women
of the Rosenstrasza protest, I mean, sorry, I get very emotional about, you know, some of the
baddest ass chicks in the world got their husbands returned to them, colica vote. And not, not
celebrating Hitler, Hitler's the worst of the worst. But God damn it, you know, this idea
that we can just say everything that person does is a lie. Everything that person does is evil.
Evil. This reflects a simplicity of mind that humanity cannot afford. Is Google evil,
evil because it will sell you mine comp? Is Amazon evil because it will sell you mine comp?
If you find out that mine comp rests on somebody's bookshelves, do you have any idea what it means?
If you find out that a scholar used the N word, should that person lose their job? Come on,
grow the hell up. I guess our responsibility to lead by example in that, because you have to
acknowledge that the fact, like the current public discourse. Have somebody on your podcast
who you're worried about. But do it in a principled fashion. I mean, in other words,
I'm not here to whitewash everything. On the other hand, if somebody makes, you know, some
allegations, I don't know that I'm obligated to treat every set of allegations as if,
now, how do you defend yourself against the, no, allegations are so cheap to make at this moment.
Well, my, sort of my standard, I don't know, maybe you could speak to it is,
I don't care. Like in the case of Alex Jones, for example, I don't,
I'm willing to have a conversation with Alex Jones and people like him. If I know he's not
going to try to manipulate me. Assume that he is going to try to manipulate you.
I can't. Then, then we're not going to be two humans.
Okay. But Lex, I want you to think well of me. I put on a jacket. I don't usually wear a jacket.
Okay? Thank you, Eric.
All right. I'm trying to manipulate you. There's an entire field. No, there's an entire field
that says that speech may be best thought of as an attempt to manipulate each other.
This is too simplistic. Everything that we keep talking through.
Yes. You know better than this.
I disagree. I think, I think there is ways.
There's, of course, it's a gray area, but there is a threshold where your intent with
which you come to a meeting to an interaction is one that is not one that's grounded in like
a respect for a common humanity, like a love for each other as deeply messy.
If somebody is doing really bad stuff, I expect you to try to keep them from doing really bad
stuff. But, you know, just keep in mind that when I was a younger man, I saw an amazing
anti pornography documentary and it was called Rate It X and I don't know where it went.
But the conceit of it was we're going to get some pornographers in front of a camera because
they want to talk and we're going to ask them about what they do for a living and why it's okay.
No commentary.
Okay. You could potentially, if you really think Alex Jones is the worst, and again,
I'm not intimately familiar with him, you could decide to just let him talk.
Now, I have decided not to do that with particular people. You know, I've spoken to Stefan Molenu.
Stefan Molenu makes many good points, makes many bad points, and he makes many good points in bad
ways and I worry about it and I don't feel that it's not my obligation to make sure that
Stefan Molenu has a voice on the portal. But I did stand up and say I didn't want him banned
from social media and I do think that a lot of the people who are being banned from social media
were worried that they're right rather than that they're wrong. I certainly don't really think that
I'm worried in some sense that some of the really wrong people are wrong. But if you look at, for
example, Curtis Jarvin, there's a tremendous amount of interest. Is Eric going to speak to Curtis
Jarvin? Curtis Jarvin says many interesting things and he says many horrible, stupid things,
very provocative. And I haven't invited him onto the portal, but I haven't said I will never invite
him onto the portal. We are all in a difficult position. That's what I'm saying. I think it's
a much more difficult task and burden who carry it as people who have conversations because
Curtis Jarvin is a good example. How much work do I have to put in reading Curtis's work
to really understand? We should talk about the problem of Curtis Jarvin because I think it's
a problem to be illustrative. There's this big question as why does somebody who says such
stupid ass things listen to by so many people? Very smart people, people who are part of our
daily lives discuss Curtis Jarvin in hush tones. Now, it's a good question. My belief is that Curtis
Jarvin has made a number of very interesting provocative points and they associate Curtis
Jarvin as the person who has made these points and they treat the completely asinine stuff that
he says that's super dangerous as, well, that's Curtis. Right? Right. They give him the credit
for, he's kind of like, sorry to use the term, first principles, deep thinker about the way
the world, some space about the world. But as a result, we don't actually know why Curtis
Jarvin is knocking around so many Silicon Valley luminaries lives.
See, you said that he said a lot of asinine stupid stuff and that's the sense I got from
a few things I've read, not just about it. This is not just like Wikipedia stuff. Is he,
he's a little like I've said before, he seems to be careless.
I don't think he's careless. No, no, it's like Jim Watson. Jim Watson wants to say very provocative
things in order to prove that he's free. It's not a question of careless. He enjoys
the freedom to say these things. And the key point is, is that there's, I expect something
more of Curtis. I expect that if somebody is insightful about all sorts of things up to that
point, that they're going to have enough care. Now, I, for example, make this point repeatedly
that vaccines are not 100% safe. Most people who have an idea that anybody is an anti-vaxxer
should be silenced, are in a position where they, they probably don't say vaccines are 100%
safe, but you keep finding that statement over and over again. Like believe all women, vaccines
are 100% safe. Climate science is settled science. Whatever this Montenegro is where you make
extraordinarily vapid blanket claims and then you retreat into something, well, defund the pull,
you know, we don't want no more police actually just means we want the police to
not take on mental health duties. We've come up with an incredibly disingenuous society.
And what I'm claiming is, is that I might talk to Curtis Yardvin, but I have really very little
interest to talk to a guy who seems to be kind of giddy about who makes good slaves and who makes
bad slaves. It's like, why do I want to do that on the portal? One, first of all, because just as
you said, that's not Curtis's main thing. He has a lot of ideas and the, what I've read of him,
which is not a huge amount, is there's, he's very thoughtful about the way this world works.
And on top of that, he's an important historical figure in the birth and the development of the
alt-right or what would be called the alt-right. The new reaction. Yeah. And there's, so he's in
just an important intellectual. And so it makes sense to talk to him. The question is,
how much work do you put in? Well, this is the issue of Fugu. I'm not a chef
that necessarily can serve that Fugu. So you have, you have a puffer fish. You can eat the puffer
fish. You can, you can get a kind of a tingly sensation on your tongue if you get a little bit
of the poison organ. But my point is, I don't know how to serve Curtis Yardvin. Yeah. So that,
in fact, I'm not worried about what happens. But I believe that if somebody else was a student
of the new reactionary movement, that person might be in a better position to host Curtis Yardvin.
So somebody, that's a really good example. Somebody I think you've spoken with,
that's an intermediary. That's a powerful one is Michael Malis. And he's spoken with Curtis Yardvin.
And Michael wrote a book about. By the way, Michael somewhat changed my mind about Michael Malis.
I'm glad he did. I think I would call him a friend. And I think he's a underneath it all
really kind human being. And I think your skepticism about him was initially from a surface level of
what did you call him hyenas, the trolls and so on. I'm not happy about his.
It's been so long since I've seen good trolls. Yes. So he needs higher quality of trolling,
but he aspires to that. I mean, it, you know, disagree or not. I really enjoy how much care
he puts into the work he does, like on North Korea and the study of the world,
and how much privately, but also in public love he has for people, especially those who are powerless.
Just a genuine admiration for them. But I think Curtis actually,
does too. I don't know. I mean, you have to appreciate the first time I met Curtis,
he introduced me, he says, I'm the most right-wing person you've ever met.
I was just like, well, this is a conversation that's already over.
It's theatrical in a way that's not conductive to actually having a real connection.
Well, it just, it turned me so, it turned me off because it was like,
you need to be the most right-wing person. And so it's like, I'm a troll, I'm a troll.
Yeah. Okay. Why are we doing this?
Yeah. But what I'm trying to get at is different. I'm trying to say that Michael Malice is a friend
of yours. If you found out something terrible, you should still be a friend.
You should still continue to be his friend. And in Michael Malice's case,
it's very likely that we'll find out something. Curtis is an acquaintance of mine,
because he hangs around with some people that I know. I did not get it. I've started to understand
why the people in my life, some of them are Curtis Yarvin fans. Many of them disregard the stupid
stuff. But my feeling is, is that too much poison organ, not enough fish. I don't know how to serve
that too intermingled. I'm not your chef. Speaking for defending your friends, staying with your
friends and bringing the old band together again, you coined the term IDW, Intellectual Dark Web.
I like it. It represents a certain group of people that are struggling with, that are almost like
challenged the norms of social and political discourse from all different angles.
Right. What do you think is the state of the IDW? What do you think is its future? Is it still
a useful? Well, it never exists. Is it a protocol? Is it a collection of people featured in an article?
What I learned very clearly is that there's a tremendous desire in the internet age to pin
people down. Well, what do you say? Who's in it? What are the criteria? It's like, I understand.
You want to play the demarcation game and you want to make everything that is demarcated
instantly null and void. No, thank you. I resisted saying who was in it. I resisted saying what it
was. I resisted saying that Barry Weiss's article was the definitive thing. They chose a ridiculous
concept for the photographs that we couldn't get out of. I did not want those photographs taken.
They decided that the Pulitzer Prize-winning photographer needed to take them all at twilight.
I didn't even necessarily want to do the article. Barry convinced me that it was the right thing
to do. Undoubtedly, Barry was right. I was wrong. But the key point is nothing can grow in this
environment. There's a reason we're not building. It does not appear that we found a way to grow
anything organic and good and decent that we need right now. That's the key issue.
Who's the weed? Do you mean us as a society? Those of us who wish to have a future for our
great grandchildren. Let's take the subset of people who are worried about things long after
their demise. Do you think it's useful to have a term like the IDW to capture some set of people,
some set of ideas or maybe principles that capture what I think the IDW... Okay, you can say it's
not supposed to me. It doesn't exist. It doesn't mean anything. But to the public, to me. Okay,
I'll just speak to me. It represented something. I think I said this to you. In my first attempt
to interview the great Eric Weinstein, I said that I spoke about you, but IDW in general is
trying to point out the elephant in the room or that the emperor has no clothes. The set of people
that do that in their own way. If there are multiple elephants in the room. Yes. The point is that
the IDW was more interested in seeing the totality of elephants and trying to figure out how do we
move forward as opposed to saying I can spot the other guy's elephant in the room, but I can't see
my own. In large measure, we didn't represent an institutional base. Therefore, it wasn't
maximally important that we look at our own hypocrisy because we weren't on the institutional
spectrum. This is where friendship comes into play with the different figures that are loosely
associated with IDW is you are somehow responsible for the exact thing that you said. Did you hear
what Sam Harris said about IDW? Yeah. That kind of thing. I chuckled.
Lovingly or chuckled? I was angry at some people who had said things that caused Sam to say what Sam
said about turning his imaginary club membership into the IDW. People said very silly things and
I think that there is just this confusion that integrity means calling out your friends in
front of the world. I've been pretty clear about this. I try to choose my friends carefully and
if you would like to recuse me because I'm not a source of reliable information, people that I
know and love the most, maybe that's reasonable for you. Maybe you prefer somebody who was willing
to throw a friend under the bus at the first sign of trouble. By all means, exit my feed.
You don't have to subscribe to me. If that's your concept of integrity, you're barking up the wrong
tree. What I will say is that I knew these people well enough to know that they're all flawed.
Thank you for the callback. But the issue is that I love people who are flawed and I love
people who have to earn a living even if you call them a grifter. I love people who like the fact
that Donald Trump didn't get us into new wars even if you call them alt-right. I love the fact that
some people believe in structural oppression and want to fight it even if they're not woke
because they don't believe that structural oppression is hiding everywhere.
I care and love different people in different ways and I think that the overarching thing
like so we're not getting at is that we were sold a bill of goods that you can go through life
like an Eliza program with pre-programmed responses. Well, it's what aboutism? It's both
sidesism. It's alt-right. It's the loony left. It's campus madness. It's like, okay,
why don't you just empty the entire goddamn magazine? All of those pre-recorded
snips. Now that you've done all of that, now we can have a conversation. Your son put it
really well, which is we should in all things resist labels. But we can't deal without labels.
We have to generalize, but we also have to keep in mind that just in the way in science,
you deal with an effective theory that isn't a fundamental one. In science, most of our theories
we consider to be effective theories. If I generalize about Europe, about women, about
Christians, those things have to be understood to mean something and not to have their
definitions extend so broadly that they mean nothing at all, nor that they're so rigid that
their claims that clearly won't bear scrutiny. Lex, what do you really want to talk about? That's
always my question to you. That always gets me. Maybe you are the therapist. But you and I could
talk about people love up until now at least. People have loved listening to the two of us in
conversation. My feeling is that we're not talking about neural nets. We're not talking
about geometric unity. We're not talking about where distributed computing might go. I don't
think that we're really focused on some of the most exciting things we could do to transform
education. We're still caught in this world of other people that we don't belong in. I don't
belong in the world as it's been created. I'm trying to build a new world and I'm astounded
that the people with the independent means to help build that world are so demotivated
that they don't want to build new structures. The people who do want to build new structures
seem to be wild-eyed. Wild-eyed? What do you mean by wild-eyed? They're not.
I guarantee you that I will get some message in my DMs. It says, hey, Eric, I'm a third-year
chemistry student at South Dakota State and I've got a great idea. I just need funding.
I want to build... They don't have the means. The people who have the means have become...
Or the sophistication. It's like you're looking for somebody who's proven themselves a few times
to say, I've got $4 billion behind me that soft-circled. I want to figure out what a new
university would be and what it would take to protect academic freedom and who we would hire
and what are the different characteristics because I can clearly see that everything
following the current model is falling apart. Nobody in my understanding is saying that.
Nobody is saying, let's take that which is functioning independently and make it less
vulnerable. Let's boost those signals. A critical component as money, you think?
It's not only that, but it's also a kind of... These people are mobbed up hands-off.
Let's imagine for the moment that Sundar Pichai, Jack Dorsey, and Mark Zuckerberg
founded a university-come-social-media entity. They said, the purpose of this is to make sure
that academic freedom will not perish from this earth because it's necessary to keep us from
all going crazy. We are going to lock ourselves out. We've come up with this governance system.
The idea is that these people will be assigned the difficult task of making sure that society
doesn't go crazy in any particular direction, that we have a fact-based, reality-based,
feasibility-based understanding. We can try to figure out where our real opportunities are.
It feels like everybody with the ability to do something like that and with the brains and
experience and the resources would rather sit in the current system and hope to figure out
where they can flee to if the whole thing comes apart.
Maybe to push back on a little bit. I agree with you, but it feels like some people are
trying that. For example, Google purchased DeepMind. DeepMind is a company that represents a lot of
radical ideas. They've become acceptable, actually. AGI, Artificial General Intelligence,
used to be really radical of a thing to talk about. DeepMind and OpenAI are two places
which has made it more acceptable. I know you can now start to criticize, well, they're really,
now that it's become acceptable, they're not taking the further stuff would be more and more
radical. But that was an attempt by Google to say that let's try some wild stuff.
Sort of like Boston Dynamics.
Sort of like Boston Dynamics. Boston Dynamics is a really good example of trying radical ideas
for perhaps no purpose whatsoever except to try to try out their ideas.
The idea is that innovation is like dessert. You can have dessert after you solve
the problem of the main course. The main course is a bunch of insoluble problems.
We can get into innovation once we perfect ourselves.
And you're saying that we need to make innovation the main meal.
Well, I'm saying that there really is structural pressure. If you train
a deep learning system on exclusively white faces, it's going to get confused.
So let's not disagree that there are real issues around this. In fact,
that's an issue of innovation and data. Your data should be responsive. On the other hand,
there are things we can't do anything about that are actually fundamental.
Those things may have to do with the fact that some of us taste cilantro as soap
and some of us don't. There are differences between people and some of them are in the
hardware, some of them are in the firmware, some of them are in the software that is the human mind.
And this completely simplistic idea that every failure of an organization to promote
each person who has particular intersexual characteristics,
we cannot hold progress hostage to that. And you've talked about, perhaps we'll
save this for another time because it's such a fascinating conversation. You talked about this
with Glenn Beck is the whole stagnation of growth and all that kind of stuff. Your idea is that
in as much as the current situation is a kind of Ponzi scheme, the current situation in the United
States is a kind of Ponzi scheme built on the promise of constant unending innovation, we need
to fund the true innovators and encourage them and empower them and sort of culturally say
that this is what this country is about is the brilliant minds.
We're going to kill each other if we don't grow. Growth is like an immune system
and you always have pathogens present, but if you don't have growth present, you can't fight the
pathogens in your society. And right now the pathogens are spreading everywhere.
So if we don't get growth into our system fairly quickly, we are in really seriously bad shape.
So it's very important that if I had a horrible person who was capable of building something
that would give us all a certain amount of what I've called financial beta to some new technology
where we all benefit, let's say quantum computing comes in and everybody, the dry cleaner has a
quantum computing angle. That's necessary to keep this system that we built going.
We can try to redesign the system, but our system expects growth and we've started
started for growth and the madness that we're seeing is the failure of our immune system to
be able to handle the pathogens that have always been present. So people can say, well,
this was always there. Yes, it was. What's changed was your immune system.
We have got to make sure that one, we understand why diversity is potentially really important.
We have mined certain communities to death. You and I are Ashkenazi Jews.
Everyone knows that Ashkenazi Jews are good at technical stuff.
We know that the Chinese are good at technical stuff. The Indians have many people who are good
at technical stuff as the Japanese. I also believe that we have communities where if you
think about the Pareto idea of diminishing returns, if you've never mined a community,
many of the people you're going to get at the beginning are going to be amazing
because that community, it's like, did you drill for more oil in Texas? Texas is pretty
thoroughly picked over. Do you find some place that's completely insane? Maybe there's oil there.
Who knows? In particular, I would like to displace our reliance on our military competitors in Asia
in our scientific laboratories with women, with African-Americans, with Latinos, people who are
in different categories than we have traditionally sourced. And I would like to get them the money
that the market would normally give these fields were we not using visas in place of payment.
Now, I have a crazy idea which is that you and I both play music and I find the analytic work
that I do when I'm trying to figure out chord progressions and symmetries and tritones and
all these sorts of things to be very similar to the work that I do when I do physics or math.
I believe that one of the things that is true is that the analytic contributions of African-Americans
to music are probably fungible to science. I don't know that that's true. It's true. I haven't done
controlled research, but I believe that it is very important to let the People's Republic of China
know that they are not staffing our laboratories anymore and that we need to look to our own people.
And in particular, we are going to get a huge benefit from making sure that women,
black Americans, Latinos, are in a position to take over some of these things because many of
these communities have been underutilized. Now, I don't know if that's an insane idea. I want to
hear somebody tell me why it's an insane idea, but I believe that part of what we need to do
is we need to recognize that there are security issues. There are geopolitical issues with the
funding of science and that what we've done is we've starved our world for innovation. And if we
don't get back to the business of innovation, we should be doing diversity and inclusion out of
greed rather than guilt. Now, part of the problem with this is that a lot of the energy behind
diversity and inclusion is based on guilt and accusation. And what I want is I want to kick
ass. And my hope is that diminishing returns favors mining the communities that have not
been traditionally mined in order to extract output from those communities, unless there's a
flaw in that plan. If there's a flaw, somebody needs to tell me. If there isn't a flaw, we need
to get greedy about innovation rather than guilty about innovation. That's really brilliantly put.
My biggest problem with what I see is, it exactly speaks to that in the discussion of diversity.
It's used when it's grounded in guilt. It's then used as a hammer to shame people that don't care
about diversity enough. F that shit. Okay. So my point is, I'm excited about the idea of Jimi
Hendrix doing quantum field theory. I'm excited about the idea of art Tatum trying to figure out
what the neural nets figured out about protein folding. I have some idea of the level of intellect
of people who have not found their way into STEM subjects in incredibly technically demanding
areas. And if there's a flaw in that theory, I want somebody to present the flaw.
But right now, my belief is that these things are merit based. And if you really believe in
structural oppression, you do not want an affirmative action program. You want to make
sure that people have huge amounts of resources to get themselves into position. I want to push
out. I just tried this on this clubhouse application. I want to push out Klein bottles as a secret sign
inside of rap videos in hip hop. I want people to have an idea that there's an amazing world.
And I want to get the people who hopefully I'm trying to lure into science and engineering.
I want to get them paid. I don't want them as the cheap substitutes for the fleeing
white males who've learned that they can't make any money in science and engineering.
So the problem is that we need to take over the ship, Lex. And it doesn't need to be you and me
because, quite honestly, I have no desire to administer. I don't want to be the chief executive
officer of anything. What I do want is I want the baby boomers who've made this mess and can't see it
to be gone. They had almost all of our universities. And I want fresh blood, fresh resources. I want
academic freedom. And I want greed for our country and for the future to determine diversity inclusion
as opposed to shame and guilt, which is destroying our fabric. That's as good of a diversity statement
as I've ever heard. This is a U-turn, but somebody commented on the tweet you sent
that as one of the top comments, they definitely have to ask you about cryptocurrency. So it's a
U-turn, but not really. Since you're an economist, since you're deep, not an economist, you...
I mean, I pretend to be an economist hoping that the economists will take issue that I'm not an
economist so that I can advance gauge theoretic and field theoretic economics, which the economics
profession has failed to acknowledge was a major innovation that happened approximately 25 years
ago. I don't think that economists understand what a price index is that measures inflation,
nor do I think economists understand what a growth index or a product quantity index is
that measures GDP. I think that they don't even understand the basics of price and quantity
index construction. And therefore, they can't possibly review field theoretic economics. They
can't review gauge theoretic economics. They're intellectually not in a position to manage their
own field. You talked about that there's a stagnation in growth currently. I looked at,
from my microeconomics, macroeconomics and college perspective, GDP doesn't seem to capture
the productivity, the full spectrum of what I think is a functioning, successful society.
What do you think is broken about GDP? What does it need to include at these indices?
Let me explain what they don't understand to begin with.
Sure. Imagine that all prices and all quantities of output are the same at the end of a year as
they are at the beginning. And you ask, what happened during that year? Was there inflation?
They meandered over the course of the year, but miraculously, they all came back to exactly their
values. The amount produced at the end of the year is the same as at the beginning in every
single quantity. Typically, the claim would be that the price index should be 1.0 and that the
quantity index should be 1.0. That's clearly wrong. Right. Well, it speaks to a fundamental
confusion that economists have. They don't understand that the economy is curved and not flat.
In a curved economy, everything should be path dependence, but they view path dependence as a
problem because they are effectively the flat earth society of market analysis. They don't
understand that what they've called, and they've actually called it the cycling problem,
is exactly what they need to understand to advance their field. So I'll give you a very
simple example. Let's imagine that we have Bob and Carol in one hedge fund and Ted and Alice
in another. In both cases, the females that is Alice and Carol are the chief investment officers,
and Bob and Ted are the chief marketing officers in charge of trying to get money into the fund
and trying to get people not to, in fact, remove their money from the funds. If you, in fact, had
Bob and Carol and Ted and Alice, and both hedge funds were invested in assets whose prices came
back to the same levels and whose exposures were in the same quantities, and you wanted to
compensate these two hedge funds, would you compensate them the same necessarily? What if,
for example, Carol was killing it in terms of investments? Every time she bought some sort
of security, the price of that security went up. But Bob was the worst marketing officer,
and as chief marketing officer, there were tons of redemptions because Bob was constantly drunk,
Bob was making off-color comments. Now, as a result, at the end of the year, the fund hasn't
grown in size because even though Carol was crushing it in terms of the investments,
Bob was screwing up everything and the redemptions were legendary, so people were making money and
still pulling it out of the fund. In the other fund, Alice can't seem to buy a base hit every
time she gets into a security, the thing plummets, but Ted's amazing marketing skills allowed
the fund to get all sorts of new subscriptions and halted the redemptions as people hoped that
the fund would get its act together. Okay. Price indices should be how Carol and Alice are compensated,
and quantity indices should be how Bob and Ted are compensated. So even though both funds
had closed loops that come back to the original states, what happened during the period that
they were active tells you how people are supposed to be compensated.
Now, we know that whatever the increase in the price index is, is compensated by a decrease
in the quantity index or conversely because prices and quantities return to their original values.
You could have another fund where nothing much happened, there were no redemptions, no subscriptions,
prices, the fund remained in cash the whole time. So in that third fund,
you know, let's call that Tristan and Izalda, that fund should have no bonuses paid because
nobody did anything, but nobody should be fired either. Now, the fact that economists don't even
understand that this is what their price and quantity indices were intended to do, that they
don't understand that you can actually give what would be called ordinal agents, the freedom to
change their preferences and still have something defined as a conus cost of living adjustment.
They don't even understand the mathematics of their field.
So the indices need to be able to capture some kind of dynamics that-
We have had indices that capture these dynamics due to the work of Francois de Vizier since 1925.
But the economists have not even understood what de Vizier's index truly represents.
What do you miss with such crude indices then?
Well, you miss the fact that you're supposed to have a field theoretic subject.
The representative consumer should actually be a probability distribution on the space of all
possible consumers weighted by the probability of getting any particular pull from the distribution.
We should not have a single gauge of inflation. What is that in 1973 dollars? Any more than you
should be able to say it was 59 degrees Fahrenheit on earth yesterday.
So when we get to the cryptocurrency, what I'm going to say is that because we didn't
found economic theory on the proper marginal revolution, because we missed the major opportunity,
which is that the differential calculus of markets is gauge theory. It's not ordinary
differential calculus. We found that out in finance that it was stochastic differential
calculus. We have the wrong version of the differential calculus underneath all of modern
economic theory. And part of what I've been pushing for in cryptocurrencies is the idea
that we should be understanding that gold is a gauge theory, just as modern economic theory is
supposed to be a gauge theory, and that we should be looking to liberate cryptocurrencies, and more
importantly, distributed computing, from the problem of this unwanted global aspect, which is
the blockchain. The thing that is most celebrated in some sense about Bitcoin is in fact the reason
that I'm least enthusiastic about it. I'm hugely enthusiastic about what Satoshi did.
But it's an intermediate step towards trying to figure out what should digital gold actually be.
If physical gold is a collection of up quarks and down quarks in the form of protons and neutrons
held together, the quarks by gluons with electrons orbiting it held together by photons with the
occasional weak interaction beta decay, all of those are gauge theories. So gold is actually
coming from gauge theory, and markets are coming from gauge theory, and the opportunity to do
locally enforced conservation laws, which effectively is what a Bitcoin transaction is,
should theoretically be founded on a different principle that is not the blockchain. It should
be a gauge theoretic concept in which effectively the tokens are excitations on a network of computer
nodes. And the fact that, let's imagine that this is some token, by moving it from my custodianship
to your custodianship, effectively, I pushed that glass as a gauge theory towards your region of the
table. We should be recognizing the gauge theory is the correct differential calculus for the 21st
century. In fact, it should have been there in the 20th century. You're saying it captures these
individual dynamics. Why should my giving you a token have to be, why should we alert the global
community in this token that that occurred? You can talk about side change. You can talk about any
means of doing this. But effectively, we have a problem, which is if I think about this differently,
I have a glass that is extant. You have a glass that is absent. We're supposed to call
the constructor method on your glass at the same moment we call the destructor method on my glass
in order to have a conservation principle. It would be far more efficient to do this
with the one system that is known never to throw an exception, which is nature.
And nature has chosen gauge theory and geometry for her underlying language.
We now know due to work of Pia Malani at Harvard in economics in the mid 1990s,
which I was her co-author on. But I wish to promote her as well as this being my idea.
We know that modern economic theory is a naturally occurring gauge theory. And the failure of that
community to acknowledge that that work occurred and that it was put down for reasons that make no
analytic sense is important in particular due to the relatively new innovation of distributed
computing and Satoshi's brainchild. So you're thinking we need to have the mathematics that
captures, that enforces cryptocurrency as a distributed system as opposed to a centralized
one where the blockchain says that crypto should be centralized.
The abundance economy much discussed in Silicon Valley or what's left of it is actually a huge
threat to the planet because what it really is is that it is what Mark Andreessen is called
software eating the world. And what that means is that you're going to push things from being
private goods and services into public goods and services. And public goods and services cannot
have price and value tied together. Ergo, people will produce things of incredible value to the
world that they cannot command a price and they will not be able to capture the value that they
have created or a significant enough fraction of it. The abundance economy is a disaster.
It will lead to a reduction in human freedom. The great innovation of Satoshi is locally enforced
or semi locally enforced conservation laws where the idea is why is gold hard to
create or destroy? It's because it's created not only in stars but in violent events involving
stars like supernova collisions. When gold is created and we transact, we're using conservation
laws, the physics determines the custodianship, whatever it is that I don't have, you now have
and conversely. In such a situation, we should be looking for the abstraction that most closely
matches the physical world because the physical world is known not to throw an exception.
The blockchain is a vulnerability. The idea that the 51% problem isn't solved, that you could have
crazy race conditions, all of these things, we know that they're solved inside of gauge theory
somehow. So the important thing is to recognize that one of the greatest intellectual feats ever
in the history of economic theory took place already and was essentially instantly buried
and I will stand by those comments. Satoshi, wherever you are, I probably know you.
Are you Satoshi? No. No, no, I don't have that kind of ability. I really don't. I do other things.
Speaking of Satoshi and gauge theory, you've mentioned to Brian Keating
that you may be releasing a geometric community paper this year or some other form of additional
material on the topic. What is your thinking around this? What's the process you're going
through now? Well, it's very interesting. I used April 1st to try to start a tradition,
which I hope to use to liberate mankind. The tradition is that at least one day a year,
you should be able to say heretical things and not have Jack Dorsey boot you off
or Mark Zuckerberg. Your provost shouldn't call you up and say, what did you say?
We need at some level to have a jubilee from centralized control. And so my hope is that
you know what a tradition is in America, something a baby boomer did twice.
Impeachment? That's very funny. Anyway, so I'm not a baby boomer, but as an exer,
I thought about whether or not April 1st would be a good date on which to release a printed version
of what I already said in lecture form, because I think it's hysterically funny that the physics
community claims that it can't decode a lecture. Yeah. It must be paper. And you know what? There
will be a steady stream of new complaints up until the point that they fit it into a narrative that
they like. Yeah, I'm thinking about April 1st as a date in which to release a document and it won't
be perfectly complete, but it'll be very complete. And then they'll try to say, it's wrong or you
already did it or no, that was dumb, but what we just did on top of it is brilliant. Or it doesn't
match experiment or who knows what, they'll go through all of their usual nonsense. It's time to go.
Is there still puzzles in your own mind that need to be figured out for you to try to put it on
paper? I mean, those are different mediums, right? It was a great question. I did not count on something
that turns out to be important. When you work on your own outside of the system for a long time,
you probably don't think you're going to be doing this as a 55-year-old man. And I have been so long
outside of math and physics departments and I've been occupied with so many other things, as you
can see, that the old idea that I had was if I always did it in little pieces, then I was always
safe because it wouldn't be steelable. And so now those pieces never got assembled completely.
In essence, I have all the pieces and I can fit them together, but there's probably a small amount
of glue code. There are a few algebraic things I've forgotten how to do. I may or may not figure
them out between now and April 1st, but it's pretty complete. But that's the puzzle you're kind of
struggling to now figure out to get it all in the same, the glue together.
I can't tell you whether the theory is correct or incorrect. But for example,
there's what's the exact form of the supersymmetry algebra or what's the rule for passing a minus
sign through a particular operator. And all of that stuff got a lot more difficult because I didn't
do it. Look, it's a little bit like if you're a violinist and you don't touch
your violin regularly for 15 years, you come back to it and you pretty much know the pieces
sort of, but there's lots of stuff that's missing. Your tone is off and that kind of stuff.
I would say I'll get the ship to the harbor and it'll require a tugboat probably to get it in.
And if the tugboat doesn't show up, then I'll pilot the thing right into the dock myself.
But it's not a big deal. I think that it is essentially complete.
Psychologically, just as a human being, this is, I remember perhaps by accident,
but maybe there's no accidents in the universe, I was tuned in, I don't remember where,
on April 1st, to you, oh, I think in your discord, kind of thinking about thinking through this
release. I mean, it wasn't like, it wasn't obvious that you were going to do it. You were thinking
through it. And I remember there was intellectual, personal, psychological struggle with this.
Yeah. Well, because I thought it was dangerous. If this turns out to be right, I don't know what
it unlocks. If it's wrong, I think I understand where we are. If it's wrong, it'll be the first
fool's gold that really looks like a theory of everything.
It'll be the iron pyrides of physics. And we haven't even had fool's gold, in my opinion yet.
Got it. So what is your intuition, why this looks right to you? Why it feels like it would be,
if wrong, the first fool's gold? I can say it very simply. It's way smarter than I am.
Can you break that apart a little more? Every time you poke at it, it's giving you intuitions
that follow with the currently known fit. Well, let's put it in computer science terms.
Yes, please. Okay. There's a concept of technical debt that computer scientists struggle with.
As you commit crimes, you have to pay those crimes back at a later date.
In general, most of the problem with physical theories is that as you try to do something
that matches reality, you usually have to go into some structure that gets you farther away.
And your hope is that you're going to be able to pay back the technical debt.
And in general, these wind up as checkkiting schemes, or like you're funding a startup and
there are too many pivots. So you keep adding epicycles in order to cover things that have gone
wrong. My belief is that this thing represents something like a summit to me. And I'm very
proud of having found a route up this summit. But the route is what's due to me. The summit
can't possibly be due to me. Edmund Hillary and Tenzing Norge did not create Mount Everest.
They know that they didn't create that. They figured out a way up.
You got to tell me what Mount Everest is in this metaphor and also connected to the technical
debt. So technical debt is a negative thing that you'll eventually have to pay it. Are you
saying in the ascent that you're seeing now in the theory is you do not have much technical debt?
Well, that's right. I think that what happens is that early on,
what I would say is, I believe now that the physics community has said many things incorrectly
about the current state of the universe. They're not wildly off, which is why,
like for example, the claim is that there are three generations of matter. I do not believe
that there are three generations of matter. I believe that there are two generations of matter.
And there's a third collection that looks like a generation of matter as the first two,
only at low energy. Okay, well, that's not a frequent claim. People imagine that there are
three or more generations of matter. I would claim that that's false. People claim that the matter
is chiral, that is, it knows it's left from its right. I would claim that the chirality is not
fundamental, but it is emergent. We could keep going at all these sorts of things. People think
that space time is the fundamental geometrical construct. I do not agree. I think it's something
that I've termed the observers. All of these different things represent a series of over
interpretations of the world that preclude progress. So you gave, I think you gave some
credit to string theory as string theory, I think loop quantum gravity, if I remember correctly,
as like getting close to the fool's gold. Well, I've said that Garrett Leasy,
Garrett Leasy, phenomenologically gets a lot of things right. He's got a reason for chirality,
a reason for uniqueness using E8. In fact, E8 uses something called vial fermions, which are chiral.
He has a way of getting geometry to get Riemann's geometry underneath general relativity to play with
Eris Mann's geometry, which is underneath the standard model using something called
Cartan connections that are out of favor. He's figured out something involving super connections
to make sure that the fermion, the matter in the system isn't quantized the same way as the
bosons were, which is a problem in his old theory. He's got something about three generations for
triality. He's got a lot of phenomenological hits. I don't think Garrett's theory works. It also has a
very simple Lagrangian. He's basically using the Yang-Mills norm squared, the same thing you would
use as a cost function if you were doing neural nets. The string theorists have a different
selling point, which is that they may have gotten a renormalizable theory of gravity if quantum
gravity was what we were meant to do. They've done some stuff with black holes that they can get
some solutions correct. Then they have lots of agreements where they show mathematical
truths that mathematicians didn't even know. I'm very underwhelmed by string theory based on how
many people have worked on it and how little is supporting the claims to it being a theory of
everything. Those are the two that I take quite seriously. I don't yet take Wolframs quite seriously
because if he really finds one of these cellular automatons that are really distinct and generative,
it'll be amazing. He's looking for such a thing. I don't think he's found anything.
Techmark, I view as a philosopher who is somehow taking credit for Platonism, which I don't see
any reason for fighting with Max because I like Max, but if it ever comes time, I'm putting a
post-it note that I'm not positive. The mathematical universe hypothesis is really anything new.
In general, loop quantum gravity really, I think, grew out of some hopes that the general
relativistic community had that they would be able to do particle theory. I don't think that
they've shown any particle theoretic realism. Essentially, here's what I really think, Lex.
I think we didn't understand how big the difference between an effective theory and a theory of
everything is conceptually. Maybe it's not mathematically that different, but conceptually,
trying to figure out what a theory of everything, how does the universe, and I've compared it to
Escher's drawing hands, how do two hands draw themselves into existence? That's the puzzle
that I think has just been wanting. I'll be honest, I'm really surprised that the theoretical physics
community didn't even get up on their high horse and say, this is the most stupid nonsense imaginable,
because clearly, I always say, I'm not a physicist. I'm an amateur with the heart
as big as all outdoors. In your journey of releasing this, and I'm sure there may be
it will be another American tradition on April 1st that will continue for years to come,
in my, there's crumbs along the way that I'm hoping to collect in my naive view of things
of the beauty that in your geometric view of the universe. So one question I'd like to ask is,
if you were to challenge me to visualize something beautiful, something important about
geometric community in my struggle to appreciate some of its beauty from the outsider's perspective,
what would that thing be? Interesting question. Perhaps we can both
have a journey towards April 1st. Take a look at that.
Some kind of a scrunchie that I picked up on Melrose, not Melrose, on Montana in Santa Monica.
Now you'll notice that all of those discs rotate independently. Yes.
If you rotate groups of those in a way that is continuous, but not uniform everywhere, what
you're doing is a so-called gauge transformation on the torus seen as a U1 bundle over a U1
spacetime. So the concept of spacetime here in a very simplified case isn't four-dimensional,
but it's one-dimensional. It's just a circle. And there's a circle above every point in the
circle represented by those little discs. Imagine, if you will, that we took a rubber band
and placed it around here and decided that that was a function from the circle into
this circle that is representing a y-axis that's wrapped around itself. Well, you would have an
idea of what it means for a function to be constant if it just went all around the outside.
But what happens if I turn this a little bit? Then the function would be mostly constant.
It would have a little place where it dipped and it went back. It turns out that you can transform
that function and transform the derivative that says that function is equal to zero when I take
its derivative at the same time. That's what a gauge transformation is. Amazing to me that we
don't have a simple video visualizing things that I've already had built and that I can clearly
demonstrate. When you do that torus whose the code of the torus is itself generating spinning
Yeah. This is a U1 principle bundle. And the world needs to know what a gauge theory is,
not by analogy, not what Lawrence Krauss is saying. It's like a checkerboard. If you change
some of the colors this way, not saying that it's a local symmetry involving links,
none of those things. It's a theory of differential calculus where the functions and the derivatives
are both subject to a particular kind of change so that if a function was constant under one
derivative, then the new function is constant under the new derivative transformed in the same
fashion. And would you put that under the category of just gauge transformations? Yes,
that would be gauge transformations applied to sections and connections where connections
are the derivatives in the theory. This is easily explained. It is pathological that the community
of people who understand what I'm saying have never bothered to do this in a clear fashion
for the general public. You and I could visualize this overnight. This is not hard.
The public needs to know in some sense that, let's say quantum electrodynamics, the theory of
photons and electrons, more or less electrons are functions and photons are derivatives. Now,
there's some you can object in some ways, but basically a gauge theory is the way in which
you can translate a shift in the definition of the functions and the shift of the definition of
the derivatives so that the underlying physics is not harmed or changed. So you have to do both
at the same time. Now, you and I can visualize that. So if what you wanted to do rather than going
directly to geometric unity is that I could sit down with you and I could say, here are the various
components of geometric unity. And if the public needs a visualization in order to play along,
we've got a little over two months and I'd be happy to work with you.
I love that as a challenge and I'll take it on and I hope we do make it happen.
And David Goggins, if Lex doesn't do some super macho thing because he's got to work
to get some of this stuff done, you'll understand he'll be available to you after April.
Thank you for the escape clause. I really needed that escape clause.
I'm glad that's on record. I'm worried, 48 miles and 48 hours.
By the way, I just want to say how much I admire your willingness to keep this kind
of hardcore attitude. I know that Russians have it and Russian Jews have it in spades,
but it's harder to do in a society that's sloppy and that's weak and that's lazy.
And the fact that you bring so much heart to saying, I'm going to bring this to jujitsu,
I'm going to bring this to guitar, I'm going to bring this to AI, I'm going to bring this to
podcasting. It comes through loud and clear. I just find it completely and utterly inspiring
that you keep this kind of hardcore aspect at the same time that you're the guy who's extolling
the virtue of love in a modern society and doing it at scale.
Thank you. That means a lot. I don't know why I'm doing it, but I'm just following my heart on it
and just going with the gut. This seems to make sense somehow.
I personally think we better get tougher or we're going to get in a world of pain and I
do think that when it comes time to lead, it's great to have people who you know don't crack
under pressure. Do you mind if we talk about love and what it takes to be a father for a bit?
Sure. Do you mind if Zev joins us? I'd be an honor.
Eric, I've talked to your son Zev who's an incredible human being, but let me
ask you, this might be difficult because you're both sitting together,
what advice do you have for him as he makes his way in this world, especially given that,
as we mentioned before, on Joe Rogan, you're flawed and that just like all humans, you're mortal?
Well, at some level, I guess one of my issues is that I've got to stop giving quite so much advice.
Early on, I was very worried that I could see Zev's abilities and I could see his
challenges and I saw them in terms of myself. A certain amount of Zev rhymes with whatever I
went through as a kid and I don't want to doom him to the same outcomes that
suffice for me. I think that he's got a much better head on his shoulders at age 15. He's
much better adjusted and in part, it's important for me to recognize that because I think I did a
reasonably decent job early on, I don't need to get this part right. I'm looking at
at Zev's trajectory and saying, you're going to need to be incredibly and even pathologically
self-confident. The antidote for that is going to be something you're going to need to carry on
board, which is radical humility. You're going to have to have those in a dialectical tension,
which is never resolved, which is a huge burden. You are going to have to forgive people who do
not appreciate your gifts because your gifts are clearly evident and many people will have to pretend
not to see them because if they see your gifts, then they're going to have to question their
entire approach to education or employment or critical thinking. What my hope is is that you
can just forgive those who don't see them and who complicate and frustrate your life and realize
that you're going to have to take care of them too. Zev, let me ask you the more challenging
question because the guy sitting right here, what advice do you have for your dad?
Since after talking to you, I realize you're the more brilliant aside from the better-looking
member of the family.
You could say anything you want. This is the last time we're going to be seeing them.
This could be an awkward drive home.
I think a new perspective I've taken on parenting is that it is a task for which
no human is really supposed to be prepared. In Jewish tradition, for example, there are
myriad analogies in the Torah and the Talmud that compare the role of a parent to the role of a
God. No human is prepared to play God and create and guide a life, but somehow we're forced into
it as people. I think sometimes it's hard for children to understand that however their parents
are failing sort of has to be. It's something for which we must budget because our parents
play a role in our lives of which they're not worthy and they devote themselves to
regardless because that becomes who they are in a certain sense.
I hope to have realistic expectations of you as a human because I think too often it's easy to
have godly expectations of people who are far from such a role. I think I'm really happy that you've
been as open as you have with me about the fact that you don't pretend to be a god in my life.
You are a guide who allows me to see myself and that's been very important considering the fact
that by your self-teaching paradigm I will have to guide myself and being able to see it
and see myself accurately has been one of the greatest gifts that you've given me.
So I'm very appreciative and I want you to know that I don't buy into the the role that you're
supposed to sort of fake your way through in my in my life but I
am unbelievably happy with a more realistic connection that we've been able to build in
lieu of it. I think it's been easier on you actually as you come to realize what I don't know,
what I can't do and that there's been a period of time I guess that's fascinating to me where
you're sort of surprised that I don't know the answer to a certain thing as well as you do and
that I remember going through this with a particular mathematician who I held and I still
hold an awe named David Kajdan and you know he famously said to him and weirdly our family
knew his family in the Soviet Union but he said you know Eric I always appreciate you coming to
my office because I always find what you have to say interesting but you have to realize that in
the areas that you're talking about you are no longer the student you are actually my teacher
and I wasn't prepared to hear that and there are many ways in which as I was just saying with the
Mozart I am learning at an incredible rate from you I used to learn from you because I didn't
understand what was possible you were very much I mean this is the weird thing there used to be
this thing called Harvey the invisible rabbit this guy could had a rabbit that was like six feet
tall that only he could see maybe was talking and that was like you at age four is you were saying
batch of crazy things that were all totally sensible and nobody else could put them together
and so what's wonderful is that the world hasn't caught on but enormous numbers of people
are starting to and I really do hope that that genuineness of spirit and that outside the box
intellectual commitment serves you well as the world starts to appreciate that I think you're a
very trustworthy voice you don't get everything right but the idea that we have somebody at your
age who's embedded in your generation who can tell us something about what's happening is really
valuable to me and I do hope that you'll consider boosting that voice more than just at the dinner
table. I apologize for saying this four-letter word but do you love Zav? I was really worried
it was going to be another four-letter word. There's so many. It doesn't even rise to the
level of a question. I mean I just there are a tiny number of people with whom you share so much
life that you can't even think of yourself in their absence and I don't know if Zav would find that
but it's you can have a kid and never make this level of connection. I think even right down to
the fact that you know when Zav chooses boogie woogie piano for his own set of reasons why I
would choose boogie woogie piano if I could play in any style it's a question about a decrease in
loneliness. You know like my grandfather played the mandolin and I had to learn some mandolin because
otherwise that instrument would go silent. You don't expect that you get this much of a chance
to leave this much of yourself in another person who is choosing it and recreating it rather than it
being directly instilled and my proudest achievement is in a certain sense having not
taught him and having shared this much so you know it's not even love it's like well beyond.
So you mentioned love for you making a less lonely world I think I speak for I would argue probably
millions of people that you Eric because this is a conversation with you have made for many people
for me a less lonely world and I can't wait to see how you Zav develop as an intellect but also
I'm so heartworn by the optimism and the hopefulness that was in you that I hope develops further
and lastly I'm deeply thankful that you Eric are my friend and would give me would honor me
with this watch it means more than words can say. Thanks guys thanks for talking today. Thank you.
Thanks for listening to this conversation with Eric Weinstein and thank you to our sponsors
indeed hiring site Theragun muscle recovery device wine access online wine store and blinkest app
that summarizes books click the sponsor links to get a discount and to support this podcast
and now let me leave you some words from Socrates to find yourself think for yourself
thanks for listening and hope to see you next time