The following is a conversation with Gary Marcus.
He's a professor emeritus at NYU, founder of robust AI and geometric intelligence.
The latter is a machine learning company that was acquired by Uber in 2016.
He's the author of several books on natural and artificial intelligence,
including his new book, Rebooting AI, Building Machines We Can Trust.
Gary has been a critical voice highlighting the limits of deep learning and AI in general
and discussing the challenges before our AI community that must be solved in order to achieve
artificial general intelligence. As I'm having these conversations, I try to find paths toward
insight towards new ideas. I try to have no ego in the process. It gets in the way.
I'll often continuously try on several hats, several roles. One, for example, is the role of
a three-year-old who understands very little about anything and asks big what and why questions.
The other might be a role of a devil's advocate who presents counter-ideas with the goal of
arriving at greater understanding through debate. Hopefully, both are useful, interesting,
and even entertaining at times. I ask for your patience as I learn to have better conversations.
This is the Artificial Intelligence Podcast. If you enjoy it, subscribe on YouTube,
give it five stars on iTunes, support it on Patreon, or simply connect with me on Twitter
at Lex Freedman, spelled F-R-I-D-M-A-N. And now, here's my conversation with Gary Marcus.
Do you think human civilization will one day have to face an AI-driven technological singularity
that will, in a societal way, modify our place in the food chain of intelligent living beings
on this planet? I think our place in the food chain has already changed.
So there are lots of things people used to do by hand that they do with machine.
If you think of a singularity as one single moment, which is, I guess, what it suggests,
I don't know if it'll be like that. But I think that there's a lot of gradual change,
and AI is getting better and better. I'm here to tell you why I think it's not nearly as good
as people think. But the overall trend is clear. Maybe Ray Kurzweil thinks it's an exponential,
and I think it's linear. In some cases, it's close to zero right now, but it's all going to
happen. I mean, we are going to get to human-level intelligence or whatever you want. Artificial
general intelligence at some point. And that's certainly going to change our place in the food
chain because a lot of the tedious things that we do now, we're going to have machines do,
and a lot of the dangerous things that we do now, we're going to have machines do. I think our whole
lives are going to change from people finding their meaning through their work, through people
finding their meaning through creative expression. So the singularity will be a very gradual,
in fact, removing the meaning of the word singularity. It'll be a very gradual transformation
in your view. I think that it'll be somewhere in between, and I guess it depends what you mean
by gradual and sudden. I don't think it's going to be one day. I think it's important to realize
that intelligence is a multi-dimensional variable. So people write this stuff as if
IQ was one number, and the day that you hit 262 or whatever, you displace the human beings.
And really, there's lots of facets to intelligence. So there's verbal intelligence,
and there's motor intelligence, and there's mathematical intelligence, and so forth.
Machines, in their mathematical intelligence, far exceed most people already in their ability
to play games. They far exceed most people already. In their ability to understand language,
they lag behind my five-year-old, far behind my five-year-old. So there are some facets of
intelligence, the machines of graphs, and some that they haven't. And we have a lot of work left
to do to get them to, say, understand natural language or to understand how to flexibly approach
some kind of novel MacGyver problem-solving kind of situation. And I don't know that all of these
things will come once. I think there are certain vital prerequisites that we're missing now.
For example, machines don't really have common sense now. So they don't
understand that bottles contain water, and that people drink water to quench their thirst,
and that they don't want to dehydrate. They don't know these basic facts about human beings. And
I think that that's a great limiting step for many things. It's a great limiting step for reading,
for example, because stories depend on things like, oh my god, that person's running out of water.
That's why they did this thing. Or if they only had water, they could put out the fire.
So you watch a movie, and you're knowledge about how things work matter. And so a computer can't
understand that movie if it doesn't have that background knowledge. Same thing if you read a
book. And so there are lots of places where if we had a good machine interpretable set of common
sense, many things would accelerate relatively quickly. But I don't think even that is a single
point. There's many different aspects of knowledge. And we might, for example, find that we make a lot
of progress on physical reasoning, getting machines to understand, for example, how keys fit into
locks or that kind of stuff, or how this gadget here works, and so forth. And so machines might do
that long before they do really good psychological reasoning, because it's easier to get labeled
data or to do direct experimentation on a microphone stand than it is to do direct
experimentation on human beings to understand the levers that guide them.
That's a really interesting point, actually, whether it's easier to gain common sense knowledge
or psychological knowledge. I would say that common sense knowledge includes both physical
knowledge and psychological knowledge. And the argument I was making.
Physical versus psychological. Yeah, physical versus psychological. And the argument I was
making is physical knowledge might be more accessible, because you could have a robot,
for example, lift a bottle, try putting a bottle cap on it, see that it falls off if it does this,
and see that it could turn it upside down. And so the robot could do some experimentation.
We do some of our psychological reasoning by looking at our own minds. So I can sort of guess
how you might react to something based on how I think I would react to it. And robots don't have
that intuition. And they also can't do experiments on people in the same way, or we'll probably
shut them down. So if we wanted to have robots figure out how I respond to pain by pinching
me in different ways, that's probably not going to make it past the human subjects board,
and companies are going to get sued or whatever. So there's certain kinds of practical
experience that are limited or off limits to robots. That's a really interesting point.
What is more difficult to gain a grounding in? Because to play devil's advocate, I would say
that human behavior is easier expressed in data and digital form. And so when you look at Facebook
algorithms, they get to observe human behavior. So you get to study and manipulate even a human
behavior in a way that you perhaps cannot study or manipulate the physical world. So it's true
why you said pain is like physical pain. But that's again the physical world. Emotional pain
might be much easier to experiment with, perhaps unethical, but nevertheless, some would argue
it's already going on. I think that you're right, for example, that Facebook does a lot of experimentation
in psychological reasoning. In fact, Zuckerberg talked about AI at a talk that he gave NIPPS.
I wasn't there, but the conference has been renamed NeurOps, but he used to be called NIPPS when he
gave the talk. And he talked about Facebook basically having a gigantic theory of mind.
I think it is certainly possible. Facebook does some of that. I think they have a really good
idea of how to addict people to things. They understand what draws people back to things.
And I think they exploit it in ways that I'm not very comfortable with. But even so,
I think that there are only some slices of human experience that they can access through
the kind of interface they have. And of course, they're doing all kinds of VR stuff. And maybe
that'll change and they'll expand their data. And I'm sure that that's part of their goal.
So, it is an interesting question. I think love, fear, insecurity, all of the things that
I would say some of the deepest things about human nature and the human mind could be
exported to digital form. You're actually the first person just now that brought up.
I wonder what is more difficult because I think folks who are the slow and we'll talk a lot about
deep learning, but the people who are thinking beyond deep learning are thinking about the physical
world. You're starting to think about robotics in the home robotics. How do we make robots manipulate
objects which requires an understanding of the physical world and then requires common sense
reasoning? And that has felt to be like the next step for common sense reasoning. But
you've not brought up the idea that there's also the emotional part. And it's interesting
whether that's hard or easy. I think some parts of it are and some aren't. So, my company that I
recently founded with Brod Brooks from MIT for many years and so forth, we're interested in both.
We're interested in physical reasoning and psychological reasoning, among many other things.
There are pieces of each of these that are accessible. So, if you want a robot to figure
out whether it can fit under a table, that's a relatively accessible piece of physical reasoning.
If you know the height of the table and you know the height of the robot, it's not that hard.
If you wanted to do physical reasoning about Jenga, it gets a little bit more complicated.
And you have to have higher resolution data in order to do it. With psychological reasoning,
it's not that hard to know, for example, that people have goals and they like to act on those
goals. But it's really hard to know exactly what those goals are. But ideas of frustration. I mean,
you could argue it's extremely difficult to understand the sources of human frustration
as they're playing Jenga with you or not. Yeah, I mean, that is very accessible.
There's some things that are going to be obvious and some not. So, I don't think anybody really
can do this well yet, but I think it's not inconceivable to imagine machines in the not so
distant future being able to understand that if people lose in a game that they don't like that.
Right. You know, that's not such a hard thing to program and it's pretty consistent across people.
Most people don't enjoy losing and so, you know, that makes it relatively easy to code.
On the other hand, if you wanted to capture everything about frustration, well, people
get frustrated for a lot of different reasons. They might get sexually frustrated,
they might get frustrated, they can get their promotion at work, all kinds of different things.
And the more you expand the scope, the harder it is for anything like the existing techniques to
really do that. So, I'm talking to Gary Kasparov next week and he seemed pretty frustrated with
this game against Deep Blue. So, yeah, well, I'm frustrated with my game against him last year
because I played him. I had two excuses. I'll give you my excuses up front. It won't mitigate the
outcome. I was jet lagged and I hadn't played in 25 or 30 years, but the outcome is he completely
destroyed me and it wasn't even close. Have you ever been beaten in any board game by a machine?
I have. I actually played the predecessor to Deep Blue. Deep thought, I believe it was
called and that too crushed me. And after that, you realized it's over for us.
Well, there's no point in my playing Deep Blue. I mean, it's a waste of Deep Blue's
computation. I mean, I played Kasparov because we both gave lectures this
same event and he was playing 30 people. I forgot to mention that not only did he crush me, but he
crushed 29 other people at the same time. I mean, but the actual philosophical and emotional
experience of being beaten by a machine, I imagine, is to you who thinks about these things
may be a profound experience or no, it was a simple mathematical experience.
Yeah, I think a game like chess, particularly where it's, you know, you have perfect information,
it's two player closed end and there's more computation for the computer. It's no surprise
the machine. I mean, I'm not sad when a computer calculates a cube root faster
than me. Like, I know I can't win that game. I'm not going to try.
Well, with a system like AlphaGo or AlphaZero, do you see a little bit more magic in a system
like that, even though it's simply playing a board game, but because there's a strong learning
component? You know, I find you should mention that in the context of this conversation because
Kasparov and I are working on an article that's going to be called AI is not magic.
And you know, neither one of us thinks that it's magic. And part of the point of this
article is that AI is actually a grab bag of different techniques and some of them have,
or they each have their own unique strengths and weaknesses. So, you know, you read media accounts
and it's like, ooh, AI, it must be magical or can solve any problem. Well, no, some problems
are really accessible like chess and go and other problems like reading are completely outside the
current technology. And it's not like you can take the technology that drives AlphaGo
and apply it to reading and get anywhere. You know, DeepMind has tried that a bit. They have
all kinds of resources. You know, they built AlphaGo and they have, you know, they, I wrote a piece
recently that they lost, and you can argue about the word lost, but they spent $530 million more
than they made last year. So, you know, they're making huge investments. They have a large budget
and they have applied the same kinds of techniques to reading or to language. It's just much less
productive there because it's a fundamentally different kind of problem. Chess and go and so
forth are closed-in problems. The rules haven't changed in 2,500 years. There's only so many
moves you can make. You can talk about the ex-financial as you look at the combinations of
moves, but fundamentally, you know, the Go board has 361 squares. That's it. That's the only, you
know, those intersections are the only places that you can place your stone. Whereas when you're
reading, the next sentence could be anything. You know, it's completely up to the writer what
they're going to do next. That's fascinating that you think this way. You're clearly a brilliant
mind who points out the emperor has no clothes, but so I'll play the role of a person who says-
You're gonna put clothes on the emperor? Good luck with it.
Romanticizes the notion of the emperor, period, suggesting that clothes don't even matter.
Okay, so that's really interesting that you're talking about language. So there's the physical
world of being able to move about the world, making an omelet and coffee and so on. There's
language where you first understand what's being written and then maybe even more complicated than
that having a natural dialogue. And then there's the game of Go and chess. I would argue that
language is much closer to Go than it is to the physical world. Like it is still very constrained.
When you say the possibility of the number of sentences that could come, it is huge, but it
nevertheless is much more constrained. It feels maybe I'm wrong than the possibilities that the
physical world brings us. There's something to what you say in some ways in which I disagree. So
one interesting thing about language is that it abstracts away. This bottle, I don't know if it'll
be in the field of view, is on this table. And I use the word on here. And I can use the word
on here, maybe not here. But that one word encompasses in analog space a sort of infinite
number of possibilities. So there is a way in which language filters down the variation of the world.
And there's other ways. So we have a grammar and more or less, you have to follow the rules of
that grammar. You can break them a little bit, but by and large, we follow the rules of grammar.
And so that's a constraint on language. So there are ways in which language is a constrained system.
On the other hand, there are many arguments that say there's an infinite number of possible sentences,
and you can establish that by just stacking them up. So I think there's water on the table. You
think that I think there's water on the table. Your mother thinks that you think that I think
the water is on the table. Your brother thinks that maybe your mom is wrong to think that you
think that I think. We can make sentences of infinite length or we can stack up adjectives.
This is a very silly example, a very, very silly example, a very, very, very, very, very, very,
example and so forth. There are good arguments that there's an infinite range of sentences. In
any case, it's vast by any reasonable measure. And for example, almost anything in the physical
world we can talk about in the language world. And interestingly, many of the sentences that we
understand, we can only understand if we have a very rich model of the physical world. So I don't
ultimately want to adjudicate the debate that I think you just set up, but I find it interesting.
You know, maybe the physical world is even more complicated than language. I think that's fair,
but you think that language is really, really complicated. It's hard.
It's really, really hard. Well, it's really, really hard for machines,
for linguists, people trying to understand it. It's not that hard for children and that's part of
what's driven my whole career. I was a student of Stephen Pinkers and we were trying to figure out
why kids could learn language when machines couldn't. I think we're going to get into language,
we're going to get into communication intelligence and neural networks and so on. But let me
return to the high level of the futuristic for a brief moment. So you've written in your book,
in your new book, it will be arrogant to suppose that we could forecast where AI will be,
where the impact it will have in a thousand years or even 500 years. So let me ask you to be arrogant.
What do AI systems with or without physical bodies look like a hundred years from now?
You can't predict, but if you were to philosophize and imagine, do.
Can I first justify the arrogance before you try to push me beyond it?
Sure.
I mean, there are examples. Like, you know, people figured out how electricity worked.
They had no idea that that was going to lead to cell phones, right? I mean,
things can move awfully fast once new technologies are perfected. Even when they made transistors,
they weren't really thinking that cell phones would lead to social networking.
There are nevertheless predictions of the future, which are statistically unlikely to come to be,
but nevertheless, is the best. You're asking me to be wrong.
Asking you to be... In which way would I like to be wrong?
Pick the least unlikely to be wrong thing, even though it's most very likely to be wrong.
I mean, here's some things that we can safely predict, I suppose.
We can predict that AI will be faster than it is now.
It will be cheaper than it is now. It will be better in the sense of being more general
and applicable in more places. It will be pervasive. I mean, these are easy predictions.
I'm sort of modeling them in my head on Jeff Bezos' famous predictions. He says,
I can't predict the future, not in every way. I'm paraphrasing,
but I can predict that people will never want to pay more money for their stuff.
They're never going to want it to take longer to get there.
You can't predict everything, but you can predict something. Sure, of course,
it's going to be faster and better. We can't really predict is the full scope of
where AI will be in a certain period. I mean, I think it's safe to say that,
although I'm very skeptical about current AI, that it's possible to do much better.
There's no in-principled argument that says AI is an insolvable problem,
that there's magic inside our brains that will never be captured. I mean,
I've heard people make those kind of arguments. I don't think they're very good.
So AI is going to come and probably 500 years is plenty to get there. And then once it's here,
it really will change everything. So when you say AI is going to come,
are you talking about human level intelligence? I like the term general
intelligence. So I don't think that the ultimate AI, if there is such a thing,
is going to look just like humans. I think it's going to do some things that humans do
better than current machines like reason flexibly and understand language and so forth.
But this doesn't mean they have to be identical to humans. So for example, humans have terrible
memory and they suffer from what some people call motivated reasoning. So they like arguments that
seem to support them and they dismiss arguments that they don't like. There's no reason that a
machine should ever do that. So you see that those limitations of memory as a bug, not a feature?
Absolutely. I'll say two things about that. One is I was on a panel with Danny Kahneman,
the Nobel Prize winner last night, and we were talking about this stuff. And I think what we
converged on is that humans are a low bar to exceed. They may be outside of our skill right now,
as AI programmers, but eventually AI will exceed it. So we're not talking about human level AI.
We're talking about general intelligence that can do all kinds of different things and do it
without some of the flaws that human beings have. The other thing I'll say is I wrote a whole book
actually about the flaws of humans. It's actually a nice book end to the counterpoint to the current
book. So I wrote a book called Cluj, which was about the limits of the human mind. The current
book is kind of about those few things that humans do a lot better than machines.
Do you think it's possible that the flaws of the human mind, the limits of memory, our mortality,
our bias is a strength, not a weakness. That is the thing that enables from which motivation
springs and meaning springs. I've heard a lot of arguments like this. I've never found them
that convincing. I think that there's a lot of making lemonade out of lemons. So we, for example,
do a lot of free association, where one idea just leads to the next and they're not really that well
connected. And we enjoy that and we make poetry out of it and we make movies with free associations
and it's fun and whatever. I don't think that's really a virtue of the system. I think that
the limitations in human reasoning actually get us in a lot of trouble. For example,
politically, we can't see eye to eye because we have the motivational reasoning I was talking
about and something related called confirmation bias. So we have all of these problems that
actually make for a rougher society because we can't get along because we can't interpret the
data in shared ways. And then we do some nice stuff with that. So my free associations are
different from yours and you're kind of amused by them and that's great and hence poetry. So
there are lots of ways in which we take a lousy situation and make it good. Another example
would be our memories are terrible. So we play games like Concentration where you flip over
two cards, try to find a pair. Can you imagine a computer playing that? A computer is like,
this is the dullest game in the world. I know where all the cards are. I see it once. I know
where it is. What are you even talking about? So we make a fun game out of having this terrible
memory. So we are imperfect in discovering and optimizing some kind of utility function,
but you think in general, there is a utility function. There's an objective function that's
better than others. I didn't say that. But see the presumption, when you say...
I think you could design a better memory system. You could argue about utility functions and
how you want to think about that. But objectively, it would be really nice to do
some of the following things. To get rid of memories that are no longer useful.
Objectively, that would just be good. And we're not that good at it. So when you park in the same
lot every day, you confuse where you parked today with where you parked yesterday with where you
parked the day before and so forth. So you blur together a series of memories. There's just no
way that that's optimal. I mean, I've heard all kinds of wacky arguments, people trying to defend
that. But in the end of the day, I don't think any of them hold water. Or trauma memories of
traumatic events would be possibly a very nice feature to have to get rid of those.
It'd be great if you could just be like, I'm going to wipe this sector. I'm done with that.
I didn't have fun last night. I don't want to think about it anymore. Bye-bye.
I'm gone. But we can't.
Do you think it's possible to build a system? So you said human-level intelligence is a weird
concept. I'm saying I prefer general intelligence. I mean, human-level intelligence is a real thing.
And you could try to make a machine that matches people or something like that.
I'm saying that per se shouldn't be the objective, but rather that we should learn from humans the
things they do well and incorporate that into our AI, just as we incorporate the things that
machines do well that people do terribly. So I mean, it's great that AI systems can do all
this brute force computation that people can't. And one of the reasons I work on this stuff
is because I would like to see machines solve problems that people can't,
that in order to be solved would combine the strengths of machines to do all this computation
with the ability, let's say, of people to read. So I'd like machines that can read the entire
medical literature in a day, 7,000 new papers or whatever the numbers comes out every day.
There's no way for any doctor or whatever to read them all. The machine that could read would be a
brilliant thing. And that would be strengths of brute force computation combined with kind of
subtlety and understanding medicine that, you know, a good doctor or scientist has.
So if we can linger a little bit on the idea of general intelligence.
So Jan Lacoon believes that human intelligence isn't general at all. It's very narrow.
How do you think? I don't think that makes sense. We have lots of narrow intelligences for specific
problems. But the fact is like anybody can walk into, let's say a Hollywood movie and reason
about the content of almost anything that goes on there. So you can reason about what happens
in a bank robbery or what happens when someone is infertile and wants to go to IVF to try to have
a child. The list is essentially endless. And not everybody understands every scene in the
movie, but there's a huge range of things that pretty much any ordinary adult can understand.
His argument is that actually the set of things seems large to us humans because we're very limited
in considering the kind of possibilities of experience as they're possible.
But in fact, the amount of experience that are possible is infinitely larger.
Well, I mean, if you want to make an argument that humans are constrained in what they can
understand, I've no issue with that. I think that's right. But it's still not the same thing at all
as saying, here's a system that can play go. It's been trained on five million games.
And then I say, can it play on a rectangular board rather than a square board? And you say,
well, if I retrain it from scratch on another five million games, I can't. That's really,
really narrow. And that's where we are. We don't have even a system that could play go.
And then without further retraining play on a rectangular board, which any human could do
with very little problem. So that's what I mean by narrow. And so it's just wordplay to say
semantics. Then it's just words. Then yeah, you mean general in a sense that you can do all kinds
of go board shapes flexibly? Well, I mean, that would be like a first step in the right direction.
Obviously, that's not what it really meaning. You're kidding. What I mean by general is that you
could transfer the knowledge you learn in one domain to another. So if you learn about bank
robberies in movies and there's chase scenes, then you can understand that amazing scene in
Breaking Bad when Walter White has a car chase scene with only one person. He's the only one in it.
And you can reflect on how that car chase scene is like all the other car chase scenes you've
ever seen and totally different and why that's cool. And the fact that the number of domains you
can do that with is finite doesn't make it less general. So the idea of general is you can just
do it on a lot of transfer across a lot of domains. Yeah, I mean, I'm not saying humans are infinitely
general or that humans are perfect. I just said a minute ago, it's a low bar, but it's just it's
a low bar. But you know, right now, like the bar is here and we're there and eventually we'll get
way past it. So speaking of low bars, you've highlighted in your new book as well, but a couple
years ago wrote a paper titled Deep Learning a Critical Appraisal that lists 10 challenges
faced by current deep learning systems. So let me summarize them as data efficiency, transfer
learning, hierarchical knowledge, open-ended inference, explainability, integrating prior
knowledge, causal reasoning, modeling on a stable world, robustness, adversarial examples, and so
on. And then my favorite problem is reliability and engineering of real world systems. So
whatever people can read the paper, they should definitely read the paper, should definitely
read your book. But which of these challenges is solved in your view has the biggest impact on the
AI community? It's a very good question. And I'm going to be evasive because I think that
they go together a lot. So some of them might be solved independently of others. But I think a
good solution to AI starts by having real what I would call cognitive models of what's going on.
So right now we have an approach that's dominant where you take statistical approximations of
things, but you don't really understand them. So you know that bottles are correlated in your data
with bottle caps, but you don't understand that there's a thread on the bottle cap that fits with
the thread on the bottle and that that's tightens in if I tighten enough that there's a seal and
the water can come out. Like there's no machine that understands that. And having a good cognitive
model of that kind of everyday phenomena is what we call common sense. And if you had that,
then a lot of these other things start to fall into at least a little bit better place. Right now
you're like learning correlations between pixels when you play a video game or something like that.
And it doesn't work very well. It works when the video game is just the way that you
studied it. And then you alter the video game in small ways, like you move the paddle and break
out a few pixels and the system falls apart because it doesn't understand, it doesn't have
a representation of a paddle, a ball, a wall, a set of bricks and so forth. And so it's reasoning
at the wrong level. So the idea of common sense is full of mystery. You've worked on it, but it's
nevertheless full of mystery, full of promise. What does common sense mean? What does knowledge
mean? So the way you've been discussing it now is very intuitive. It makes a lot of sense that
that is something we should have and that's something deep learning systems don't have.
But the argument could be that we're oversimplifying it because we're oversimplifying the notion of
common sense because that's how it feels like we as humans at the cognitive level approach
problems. So a lot of people aren't actually going to read my book. But if they did read the book,
one of the things that might come as a surprise to them is that we actually say a common sense
is really hard and really complicated. So my critics know that I like common sense, but
that chapter actually starts by us beating up not on deep learning, but kind of on our own
home team as it will. So Ernie and I are first and foremost people that believe in at least some
of what good old fashioned AI tried to do. So we believe in symbols and logic and programming.
Things like that are important. And we go through why even those tools that we hold fairly dear
aren't really enough. So we talk about why common sense is actually many things. And some of them
fit really well with those classical sets of tools. So things like taxonomy. So I know that a bottle
is an object or it's a vessel, let's say, and I know a vessel is an object and objects are
material things in the physical world. So I can make some inferences. If I know that vessels need to
not have holes in them, then I can infer that in order to carry their contents, then I can infer
that a bottle shouldn't have a hole in order to carry its contents. So you can do hierarchical
inference and so forth. And we say that's great, but it's only a tiny piece of what you need
for common sense. We give lots of examples that don't fit into that. So another one that we talk
about is a cheese grater. You've got holes in a cheese grater. You've got a handle on top. You
can build a model in the game engine sense of a model so that you could have a little cartoon
character flying around through the holes of the grater. But we don't have a system yet. Taxonomy
doesn't help us that much. It really understands why the handle is on top and what you do with the
handle or why all of those circles are sharp or how you'd hold the cheese with respect to the
grater in order to make it actually work. Do you think these ideas are just abstractions that could
emerge on a system like a very large deep neural network? I'm a skeptic that that kind of emergence
per se can work. So I think that deep learning might play a role in the systems that do what I
want systems to do, but it won't do it by itself. I've never seen a deep learning system really
extract an abstract concept. What they do, principal reasons for that stemming from how
back propagation works, how the architectures are set up. One example is deep learning people
actually all build in something called convolution, which Jan Lacoon is famous for,
which is an abstraction. They don't have their systems learn this. So the abstraction is an
object that looks the same if it appears in different places. And what Lacoon figured out and
why, you know, essentially why he was a co-winner of the Thuring Ward was that if you programmed
this in innately, then your system would be a whole lot more efficient. In principle, this
should be learnable, but people don't have systems that kind of reify things that make them
more abstract. And so what you really wind up with if you don't program that in advance is a system
that kind of realizes that this is the same thing as this, but then I take your little clock there
and I move it over and it doesn't realize that the same thing applies to the clock.
So the really nice thing you're right that convolution is just one of the things that's
like it's an innate feature that's programmed by the human expert, but we need more of those
not less. So the, but the nice feature is it feels like that requires coming up with that brilliant
idea can get your Thuring Award, but it requires less effort than encoding and something we'll
talk about the expert system. So encoding a lot of knowledge by hand. So it feels like one,
there's a huge amount of limitations, which you clearly outline with deep learning,
but the nice feature deep learning, whatever it is able to accomplish, it does it,
it does a lot of stuff automatically without human intervention.
Well, and that's part of why people love it, right? But I always think of this quote from
Bertrand Russell, which is it has all the advantages of theft over honest toil. It's
really hard to program into a machine a notion of causality or, you know, even how a bottle
works or what containers are. Ernie Davis and I wrote a, I don't know, 45 page academic paper
trying just to understand what a container is, which I don't think anybody ever read the paper,
but it's a very detailed analysis of all the things. Well, not even all the some of the things
you need to do in order to understand a container. It would be a whole lot nice. And, you know,
I'm a co-author on the paper, I made it a little bit better, but Ernie did the hard work for that
particular paper. And he took him like three months to get the logical statements correct.
And maybe that's not the right way to do it. It's a way to do it. But on that way of doing it,
it's really hard work to do something as simple as understanding containers.
And nobody wants to do that hard work. Even Ernie didn't want to do that hard work.
Everybody would rather just like feed their system in with a bunch of videos with a bunch of
containers and have the systems infer how containers work. It would be like so much
less effort. Let the machine do the work. And so I understand the impulse. I understand why
people want to do that. I just don't think that it works. I've never seen anybody build a system
that in a robust way can actually watch videos and predict exactly, you know, which containers would
leak and which ones wouldn't or something like. And I know someone's going to go out and do that
since I said it and I look forward to seeing it. But getting these things to work robustly is really,
really hard. So Yann LeCun, who was my colleague at NYU for many years,
thinks that the hard work should go into defining an unsupervised learning algorithm
that will watch videos, use the next frame basically in order to tell it what's going on.
And he thinks that's the royal road and he's willing to put in the work in
devising that algorithm. Then he wants the machine to do the rest. And again, I understand the impulse.
My intuition based on years of watching this stuff and making predictions 20 years ago that
still hold even though there's a lot more computation and so forth, is that we actually
have to do a different kind of hard work, which is more like building a design specification
for what we want the system to do, doing hard engineering work to figure out how we do things
like what Yann did for convolution in order to figure out how to encode complex knowledge
into the systems. The current systems don't have that much knowledge other than convolution,
which is again this, you know, objects being in different places and having the same perception,
I guess I'll say, same appearance. People don't want to do that work. They don't see how to naturally
fit one with the other. I think that's, yes, absolutely. But also on the expert system side,
there's a temptation to go too far the other way. So we're just having an expert sort of sit down
and encode the description, the framework for what a container is, and then having the system
reason the rest. From my view, like one really exciting possibility is of active learning where
it's continuous interaction between a human and machine. As the machine, there's kind of deep
learning type extraction of information from data patterns and so on. But humans also guiding
the learning procedures, guiding both the process and the framework of how the machine
learns whatever the task is. I was with you with almost everything you said except the phrase
deep learning. What I think you really want there is a new form of machine learning. So
let's remember deep learning is a particular way of doing machine learning. Most often it's done
with supervised data for perceptual categories. There are other things you can do with deep learning.
Some of them quite technical, but the standard use of deep learning is I have a lot of examples
and I have labels for them. So here are pictures. This one's the Eiffel Tower. This one's the Sears
Tower. This one's the Empire State Building. This one's a cat. This one's a pig and so forth.
You just get millions of examples, millions of labels. And deep learning is extremely good at
that. It's better than any other solution that anybody has devised. But it is not good at representing
abstract knowledge. It's not good at representing things like bottles contain liquid and have tops
to them and so forth. It's not very good at learning or representing that kind of knowledge.
It is an example of having a machine learn something, but it's a machine that learns a
particular kind of thing, which is object classification. It's not a particularly good
algorithm for learning about the abstractions that govern our world. There may be such a thing.
Part of what we counsel in the book is maybe people should be working on devising such things.
So one possibility, I wonder what you think about it, is deep neural networks do form
abstractions, but they're not accessible to us humans in terms of we can't.
There's some truth in that. So is it possible that either current or future neural networks
form very high level abstractions, which are as powerful as our human abstractions of common
sense, we just can't get a hold of them. And so the problem is essentially what we need to make
them explainable. This is an astute question, but I think the answer is at least partly no.
One of the kinds of classical neural network architecture is what we call an auto-associator.
It just tries to take an input, goes through a set of hidden layers, and comes out with an output.
And it's supposed to learn essentially the identity function, that your input is the same as your
output. So you think of those binary numbers, you've got like the 1, the 2, the 4, the 8,
the 16, and so forth. And so if you want to input 24, you turn on the 16, you turn on the 8. It's
like binary 1, 1, and bunch of zeros. So I did some experiments in 1998 with the precursors of
contemporary deep learning. And what I showed was you could train these networks on all the even
numbers and they would never generalize to the odd number. A lot of people thought that I was,
I don't know, an idiot or faking the experiment or wasn't true or whatever, but it is true that
with this class of networks that we had in that day, that they would never ever make this
generalization. And it's not that the networks were stupid, it's that they see the world in a
different way than we do. They were basically concerned, what is the probability that the
rightmost output node is going to be 1? And as far as they were concerned, in everything they'd
ever been trained on, it was a 0. That node had never been turned on. And so they figured,
why turn it on now? Whereas a person would look at the same problem and say, well,
it's obvious, we're just doing the thing that corresponds. The Latin for it is mutatus mutatus,
will change what needs to be changed. And we do this, this is what algebra is. So I can do f of x
equals y plus two. And I can do it for a couple of values, I can tell you if y is three, then x is
five, and if y is four, x is six. And now I can do it with some totally different number,
like a million, then you can say, well, obviously it's a million and two, because you have
an algebraic operation that you're applying to a variable. And deep learning systems kind of
emulate that, but they don't actually do it. The particular example, you could
fudge a solution to that particular problem. The general form of that problem remains
that what they learn is really correlations between different input and output nodes.
They're complex correlations with multiple nodes involved and so forth. But ultimately,
they're correlative. They're not structured over these operations over variables. Now, someday,
people may do a new form of deep learning that incorporates that stuff. And I think it will
help a lot. And there's some tentative work on things like differentiable programming right now
that fall into that category. But the sort of classic stuff like people use for ImageNet
doesn't have it. And you have people like Hinton going around saying,
symbol manipulation like what Marcus, what I advocate is like the gasoline engine,
it's obsolete, we should just use this cool electric power that we've got with the deep
learning. And that's really destructive, because we really do need to have the gasoline engine stuff
that represents, I don't think it's a good analogy, but we really do need to have the stuff that
represents symbols. And Hinton as well would say that we do need to throw out everything
and start over. Hinton said that to Axios. And I had a friend who interviewed him and
tried to pin him down on what exactly we need to throw. And he was very evasive.
Well, of course, because we can't, if he knew that he'd throw it out himself. But I mean,
you can't have it both ways. You can't be like, I don't know what to throw out,
but I am going to throw out the symbols. And not just the symbols, but the variables and
the operations over variables. Don't forget the operations over variables, the stuff that I'm
endorsing, and which John McCarthy did when he founded AI, that stuff is the stuff that we build
most computers out of. There are people now who say, we don't need computer programmers anymore.
Not quite looking at the statistics of how much computer programmers actually get paid right now.
We need lots of computer programs. And most of them, they do a little bit of machine learning,
but they still do a lot of code, right? Code where it's like, if the value of x is greater
than the value of y, then do this kind of thing, like conditionals and comparing operations over
variables. There's this fantasy you can machine learn anything. There's some things you would
never want to machine learn. I would not use a phone operating system that was machine learned.
Like you made a bunch of phone calls and you recorded which packets were transmitted and
you just machine learned it. It would be insane. Or to build a web browser by taking logs of key
strokes and images, screenshots, and then trying to learn the relation between them. Nobody would
ever, no rational person would ever try to build a browser that way. They would use symbol
manipulation, the stuff that I think AI needs to avail itself of in addition to deep learning.
Can you describe what your view of symbol manipulation in its early days? Can you
describe expert systems and where do you think they hit a wall or a set of challenges?
First, I just want to clarify. I'm not endorsing expert systems per se. You've been
kind of contrasting them. There is a contrast, but that's not the thing that I'm endorsing.
So expert systems try to capture things like medical knowledge with a large set of rules.
So if the patient has this symptom and this other symptom, then it is likely that they have this
disease. So there are logical rules and they were symbol manipulating rules of just the sort
that I'm talking about. They encode a set of knowledge that the experts have put in.
Very explicitly so. So you'd have somebody interview an expert and then try to turn that stuff into
rules. At some level, I'm arguing for rules, but the difference is those guys did in the 80s
who was almost entirely rules, almost entirely handwritten with no machine learning. What a lot
of people are doing now is almost entirely one species of machine learning with no rules.
And what I'm counseling is actually a hybrid. I'm saying that both of these things have their
advantage. So if you're talking about perceptual classification, how do I recognize a bottle?
Deep learning is the best tool we've got right now. If you're talking about making
inferences about what a bottle does, something closer to the expert systems is probably still
the best available alternative. And probably we want something that is better able to handle
quantitative and statistical information than those classical systems typically were.
So we need new technologies that are going to draw some of the strengths of both the expert
systems and the deep learning, but are going to find new ways to synthesize them.
How hard do you think it is to add knowledge at the low level? So mind human intellects
to add extra information to symbol manipulating systems.
In some domains, it's not that hard, but it's often really hard, partly because a lot of the
things that are important, people wouldn't bother to tell you. So if you pay someone on
Amazon Mechanical Turk to tell you stuff about bottles, they probably won't even bother to tell
you some of the basic level stuff that's just so obvious to a human being and yet so hard to capture
in machines. They're going to tell you more exotic things, and they're all well and good,
but they're not getting to the root of the problem. So untutored humans aren't very good at knowing,
and why should they be, what kind of knowledge the computer system developers actually need.
I don't think that that's an irremediable problem. I think it's historically been a problem. People
had crowd sourcing efforts, and they don't work that well. There's one at MIT. We're
recording this at MIT called Virtual Home, and we talk about this in the book.
Find the exact example there, but people were asked to do things like describe an exercise
routine. And the things that the people describe it are very low level and don't really capture
what's going on. So they're like, go to the room with the television and the weights,
turn on the television, press the remote to turn on the television, lift weight, put weight down.
It's like very micro level, and it's not telling you what an exercise routine is really about,
which is like, I want to fit a certain number of exercises in a certain time period. I want to
emphasize these muscles. You want some kind of abstract description. The fact that you happen
to press the remote control in this room when you watch this television isn't really the essence of
the exercise routine. But if you just ask people what did they do, then they give you
this fine grain. And so it takes a little level of expertise about how the AI works in order to
craft the right kind of knowledge. So there's this ocean of knowledge that we all operate on.
Some of it may not even be conscious, or at least we're not able to communicate it effectively.
Yeah, most of it we would recognize if somebody said it if it was true or not,
but we wouldn't think to say that it's true or not. It's a really interesting
mathematical property. This ocean has the property that every piece of knowledge in it,
we will recognize it as true if we're told, but we're unlikely to retrieve it in the reverse.
So that interesting property, I would say there's a huge ocean of that knowledge.
What's your intuition? Is it accessible to AI systems somehow? Can we?
Yeah, I mean, most of it is not, I'll give you an asterisk on this in a second, but most of it is
not ever been encoded in machine interpretable form. And so, I mean, if you say accessible,
there's two meanings of that. One is like, could you build it into a machine? Yes.
The other is like, is there some database that we could go, you know, download and stick into our
machine? But the first thing, no. Could we? What's your intuition? I think we could. I think it
hasn't been done right. The closest, and this is the asterisk, is the CYC psych system. Try to do
this. A lot of logicians worked for Doug Lennon for 30 years on this project. I think they stuck
too closely to logic, didn't represent enough about probabilities, tried to hand code it.
There are various issues, and it hasn't been that successful. That is the closest
existing system to trying to encode this. Why do you think there's not more excitement
slash money behind this idea currently? There was. People view that project as a failure. I think that
they confused the failure of a specific instance that was conceived 30 years ago for the failure
of an approach, which they don't do for deep learning. So, in 2010, people had the same
attitude towards deep learning. They're like, this stuff doesn't really work. And, you know,
all these other algorithms work better and so forth. And then certain key technical advances
were made, but mostly it was the advent of graphics processing units that changed that.
It wasn't even anything foundational in the techniques. And there were some new tricks, but
mostly it was just more compute and more data, things like ImageNet that didn't exist before,
that allowed deep learning. And it could be to work. It could be that, you know,
psych just needs a few more things or something like psych. But the widespread view is that
that just doesn't work. And people are reasoning from a single example. They don't do that with
deep learning. They don't say nothing that existed in 2010. And there were many, many efforts in
deep learning was really worth anything. Right? I mean, really, there's no model from 2010
in deep learning. So, this is the deep learning that has any commercial value
whatsoever at this point, right? They're all failures. But that doesn't mean that there wasn't
anything there. I have a friend, I was getting to know him, and he said, I had a company too,
I was talking about, I had a new company. He said, I had a company too, and it failed. And I said,
well, what did you do? And he said, deep learning. And the problem was he did it in 1986 or something
like that. And we didn't have the tools then or 1990. We didn't have the tools then, not the
algorithms. His algorithms weren't that different from other algorithms, but he didn't have the GPUs
to run it fast enough. He didn't have the data. And so it failed. It could be that
simple manipulation per se with modern amounts of data and compute and maybe some advance in
compute for that kind of compute might be great. My perspective on it is not that we want to
resuscitate that stuff per se, but we want to borrow lessons from it, bring together with
other things that we've learned. And it might have an ImageNet moment where it will spark the
world's imagination, and it'll be an explosion of simple manipulation efforts. Yeah, I think that
people at AI2, Paul Allen's AI Institute, are trying to build datasets that, well, they're not
doing it for quite the reason that you say, but they're trying to build datasets that at least
spark interest in common sense reasoning. To create benchmarks. Benchmarks for common sense.
That's a large part of what the AI2.org is working on right now.
So speaking of compute, Rich Sutton wrote a blog post titled Bitter Lesson. I don't know if you've
read it, but he said that the biggest lesson that can be read from 70 years of AI research
is that general methods that leverage computation are ultimately the most effective.
The most effective of what? So they have been most effective for perceptual classification
problems, and for some reinforcement learning problems, he works on reinforcement learning.
Well, no, let me push back on that. You're actually absolutely right. But I would also
say they've been most effective generally, because everything we've done up to the world.
Would you argue against that? To me, deep learning is the first thing that has been
successful at anything in AI. And you're pointing out that this success is very limited, folks,
but has there been something truly successful before deep learning?
Sure. I want to make a larger point, but on the narrower point, classical AI
is used, for example, in doing navigation instructions. It's very successful. Everybody
on the planet uses it now, multiple times a day. That's a measure of success.
I don't think classical AI was wildly successful, but there are cases like that that is used all
the time nobody even notices them, because they're so pervasive. So there are some successes for
classical AI. I think deep learning has been more successful, but my usual line about this,
and I didn't invent it, but I like it a lot, is just because you can build a better ladder,
it doesn't mean you can build a ladder to the moon. So the bitter lesson is if you have a
perceptual classification problem, throwing a lot of data at it is better than anything else.
But that has not given us any material progress in natural language understanding,
common sense reasoning like a robot would need to navigate a home. Problems like that,
there's no actual progress there. So flip side of that, if we remove data from the picture,
another bitter lesson is that you just have a very simple algorithm and you wait for compute
to scale. This doesn't have to be learning, it doesn't have to be deep learning, it doesn't
have to be data driven, but just wait for the compute. So my question for you, do you think
compute can unlock some of the things with either deep learning or simple manipulation that?
Sure, but I'll put a proviso on that. The more compute's always better. Nobody's going to argue
with more compute, it's like having more money. There's diminishing returns on more money.
Exactly, there's diminishing returns on more money, but nobody's going to argue if you want
to give them more money, right? Except maybe the people who signed the giving pledge and some of
them have a problem, they've promised to give away more money than they're able to. But the rest of
us, if you want to give me more money, fine. Say more money, more problems, but okay.
That's true too. What I would say to you is your brain uses 20 watts and it does a lot of things
that deep learning doesn't do or that simple manipulation doesn't do, that AI just hasn't
figured out how to do. So it's an existence proof that you don't need server resources that are
Google scale in order to have an intelligence. I built, with a lot of help from my wife,
two intelligences that are 20 watts each and far exceed anything that anybody else
has built at a silicon. Speaking of those two robots, what have you learned about AI from
having- Well, they're not robots, but- Sorry, intelligent agents.
There's two intelligent agents. I've learned a lot by watching my two intelligent agents.
I think that what's fundamentally interesting, well, one of the many things that's fundamentally
interesting about them is the way that they set their own problems to solve.
So my two kids are a year and a half apart. They're both five and six and a half.
They play together all the time and they're constantly creating new challenges. That's what
they do is they make up games and they're like, well, what if this or what if that or what if I
had this superpower or what if you could walk through this wall. They're doing these what if
scenarios all the time and that's how they learn something about the world and grow their minds
and machines don't really do that. So that's interesting. You've talked about this. You've
written about it. You've thought about it. Nature versus nurture. So what innate knowledge do you
think we're born with and what do we learn along the way in those early months and years?
Can I just say how much I like that question? You phrased it just right and almost nobody ever does,
which is what is the innate knowledge and what's learned along the way. So many people
dichotomize it and they think it's nature versus nurture. When it is obviously, it has to be nature
and nurture. They have to work together. You can't learn the stuff along the way unless you have some
innate stuff. But just because you have the innate stuff doesn't mean you don't learn anything.
And so many people get that wrong, including in the field. People think if I work in machine
learning, the learning side, I must not be allowed to work on the innate side where
that will be cheating. Exactly. People have said that to me and it's just absurd. So thank you.
But you could break that apart more. I've talked to folks who studied the development of the brain
and the growth of the brain in the first few days, in the first few months, in the womb,
all of that, you know, is that innate? So that process of development from a stem cell to the
growth of the central nervous system and so on to the information that's encoded through the long
arc of evolution. So all of that comes into play and it's unclear. It's not just whether it's a
dichotomy or not. It's where most or where the knowledge is encoded. So what's your intuition
about the innate knowledge, the power of it, what's contained in it, what can we learn from it?
One of my earlier books was actually trying to understand the biology of this. The book was
called The Birth of the Mind. Like how is it the genes even build innate knowledge? And from the
perspective of the conversation we're having today, there's actually two questions. One is what
innate knowledge or mechanisms or what have you? People or other animals might be endowed with.
I always like showing this video of a baby ibex climbing down a mountain. That baby ibex, you
know, a few hours after his birth, knows how to climb down a mountain. That means that it knows,
not consciously, something about its own body and physics and 3D geometry and all of this kind of
stuff. So there's one question about it. Like what does biology give its creatures? You know,
what has evolved in our brains? How is that represented in our brains? The question I
thought about in the book The Birth of the Mind. And then there's a question of what AI should have.
And they don't have to be the same. But I would say that it's a pretty interesting
set of things that we are equipped with that allows us to do a lot of interesting things. So
I would argue or guess based on my reading of the developmental psychology literature,
which I've also participated in, that children are born with a notion of space,
time, other agents, places, and also this kind of mental algebra that I was describing before.
No certain of causation, if I didn't just say that. So at least those kinds of things. They're
like frameworks for learning the other things. So are they disjoint in your view or is it just
somehow all connected? You've talked a lot about language. Is it all kind of connected in some
mesh that's language like? If understanding concepts all together? I don't think we know
for people how they're represented in machines just don't really do this yet. So I think it's an
interesting open question both for science and for engineering. Some of it has to be at least
interrelated in the way that like the interfaces of a software package have to be able to talk to
one another. So the systems that represent space and time can't be totally disjoint because a lot
of the things that we reason about are the relations between space and time and cause. So
I put this on and I have expectations about what's going to happen with the bottle cap on top of the
bottle and those span space and time. If the cap is over here, I get a different outcome. If
the timing is different, if I put this here after I move that, then I get a different outcome
that relates to causality. So obviously these mechanisms, whatever they are,
can certainly communicate with each other. So I think evolution had a significant role to play
in the development of this whole collage. How efficient do you think is evolution? Oh, it's
terribly inefficient except that it's inefficient except that once it gets a good idea, it runs with
it. So it took I guess a billion years, roughly a billion years to evolve to a vertebrate
brain plan. Once that vertebrate plan evolved, it spread everywhere. So fish have it and dogs
have it and we have it. We have adaptations of it and specializations of it and the same thing
with a primate brain plan. So monkeys have it and apes have it and we have it. So there are
additional innovations like color vision and those spread really rapidly. So it takes evolution a
long time to get a good idea and being anthropomorphic and not literal here. But once it has that
idea, so to speak, which caches out into one set of genes or in the genome, those genes spread
very rapidly and they're like subroutines or libraries, I guess the word people might use
nowadays or be more familiar with. They're libraries that can get used over and over again.
So once you have the library for building something with multiple digits, you can use it for a hand
but you can also use it for a foot. You just kind of reuse the library with slightly different
parameters. Evolution does a lot of that, which means that the speed over time picks up. So
evolution can happen faster because you have bigger and bigger libraries. And what I think has
happened in attempts at evolutionary computation is that people start with libraries that are
very, very minimal, like almost nothing and then progress is slow and it's hard for someone to get
a good PhD thesis out of it and then give up. If we had richer libraries to begin with, if you were
evolving from systems that hadn't originate structure to begin with, then things might speed up.
Or more PhD students, if the evolution process is indeed in a meta way,
runs away with good ideas, you need to have a lot of ideas,
pool of ideas in order for it to discover one that you can run away with. And
PhD students representing individual ideas as well.
Yeah. I mean, you could throw a billion PhD students at it.
Yeah. The monkeys are typewriters with Shakespeare. Yep.
Well, I mean, those aren't cumulative, right? That's just random. And part of the point that
I'm making is that evolution is cumulative. So if you have a billion monkeys independently,
you don't really get anywhere. But if you have a billion monkeys, I think Dawkins made this
point originally, or probably other people. Dawkins made it very nice in either selfish
gene or blind watchmaker. If there is some sort of fitness function that can drive you toward
something, I guess that's Dawkins' point. And my point, which is a little variation on that,
is that if the evolution is cumulative of the related points, then you can start going faster.
Do you think something like the process of evolution is required to build the intelligence
systems? Not logically. So all the stuff that evolution did, a good engineer might be able to
do. So for example, evolution made quadrupeds, which distribute the load across a horizontal
surface. A good engineer could come up with that idea. I mean, sometimes good engineers come up
with ideas by looking at biology. There's lots of ways to get your ideas. Part of what I'm suggesting
is we should look at biology a lot more. We should look at the biology of thought and the
understanding and the biology by which creatures intuitively reason about physics or other agents
or how do dogs reason about people? They're actually pretty good at it. If we could understand,
at my college we joked, dognition. If we could understand dognition well and how it was implemented,
that might help us with our AI. Do you think it's possible that the kind of timescale that
evolution took is the kind of timescale that will be needed to build intelligence systems,
or can we significantly accelerate that process inside a computer?
I think the way that we accelerate that process is we borrow from biology.
Not slavishly, but I think we look at how biology has solved problems and we say,
does that inspire any engineering solutions here? Try to mimic biological systems and then
therefore have a shortcut. There's a field called biomimicry. People do that for material
science all the time. We should be doing the analog of that for AI. The analog for that for AI
is to look at cognitive science or the cognitive sciences, which is psychology,
maybe neuroscience, linguistics, and so forth. Look to those for insight.
What do you think is a good test of intelligence in your view?
I don't think there's one good test. In fact, I try to organize a movement towards something
called a Turing Olympics. My hope is that Francois is actually going to take, Francois Chalet,
is going to take over this. I think he's interested and I just don't have place in my
busy life at this moment. The notion is that there'll be many tests and not just one because
intelligence is multifaceted. There can't really be a single measure of it because it isn't a single
thing. Just at the crudest level, the SAT is a verbal component and a math component because
they're not identical. Howard Gardner has talked about multiple intelligence like
kinesthetic intelligence and verbal intelligence and so forth. There are a lot of things that go
into intelligence and people can get good at one or the other. In some sense, every expert has
developed a very specific kind of intelligence and then there are people that are generalists.
I think of myself as a generalist with respect to cognitive science, which doesn't mean I know
anything about quantum mechanics, but I know a lot about the different facets of the mind.
There's a kind of intelligence to thinking about intelligence. I like to think that I have some
of that, but social intelligence, I'm just okay. There are people that are much better at that than
I am. Sure, but what would be really impressive to you? I think the idea of a touring Olympics is
really interesting, especially if somebody like Francois is running it, but to you in general,
not as a benchmark, but if you saw an AI system being able to accomplish something
that would impress the heck out of you, what would that thing be? Would it be natural language
conversation? For me personally, I would like to see a kind of comprehension that relates
to what you just said. I wrote a piece in The New Yorker in I think 2015, right after Eugene
Gustman, which was a software package, won a version of the touring test. The way you win
the touring test, it's called win it, is the touring test is you fool a person into thinking
that a machine is a person. You're evasive, you pretend to have limitations, so you don't have
to answer certain questions and so forth. This particular system pretended to be a 13-year-old
boy from Odessa who didn't understand English and was kind of sarcastic and wouldn't answer your
questions and so forth. Judges got fooled into thinking briefly with a very little exposure
as a 13-year-old boy, and it docked to all the questions the touring was actually interested
in, which is like, how do you make the machine actually intelligent? That test itself is not
that good. In The New Yorker, I proposed an alternative, I guess. The one that I proposed
there was a comprehension test. I must like Breaking Bad because I've already given you
one Breaking Bad example. In that article, I have one as well, which was something like,
if Walter White, you should be able to watch an episode of Breaking Bad or maybe you have to
watch the whole series to be able to answer the question and say, if Walter White took a hit
out on Jesse, why did he do that? If you could answer kind of arbitrary questions about characters
motivations, I would be really impressed with that. I mean, you build software to do that.
They could watch a film or they're different versions. Ultimately, I wrote this up with
Praveen Paratosh in a special issue of AI magazine that basically was about the Touring
Olympics. There were like 14 tests proposed. The one that I was pushing was a comprehension
challenge and Praveen, who's at Google, was trying to figure out how we would actually run it. We
wrote a paper together. You could have a text version too. You could have an auditory podcast
version. You could have a written version. But the point is that you win at this test if you can do,
let's say, human level or better than humans at answering kind of arbitrary questions. Why did this
person pick up the stone? What were they thinking when they picked up the stone? Were they trying to
knock down glass? I mean, ideally, these wouldn't be multiple choice either because multiple choice
is pretty easily gamed. If you could have relatively open-ended questions and you can answer why people
are doing this stuff, I would be very impressed. Of course, humans can do this. If you watch a
well-constructed movie and somebody picks up a rock, everybody watching the movie knows why they
picked up the rock. They all know, oh my gosh, he's going to hit this character or whatever.
We have an example in the book about when a whole bunch of people say, I am Spartacus.
You know this famous scene? The viewers understand, first of all, everybody or everybody minus one
has to be lying. They can't all be Spartacus. We have enough common sense knowledge to know
they couldn't all have the same name. We know that they're lying and we can infer why they're
lying. They're lying to protect someone and to protect things they believe in. You get a machine
that can do that. They can say, this is why these guys all got up and said, I am Spartacus.
I will sit down and say AI has really achieved a lot. Thank you.
Without cheating any part of the system. Yeah. If you do it, there are lots of ways you can
cheat. You could build a Spartacus machine that works on that film. That's not what I'm talking
about. You can do this with essentially arbitrary films from a large set.
Even beyond films because it's possible such a system would discover that the number of narrative
arcs in film is limited to like 93. Well, there's a famous thing about the classic seven plots or
whatever. I don't care if you want to build in the system, boy meets girl, boy loses girl,
boy finds girl. That's fine. I don't mind having some headstone. Any knowledge?
I mean, you could build it in an Ailey or you could have your system watch a lot of films again.
If you can do this at all, but with a wide range of films, not just one film in one genre,
but even if you could do it for all Westerns, I'd be reasonably impressed.
So in terms of being impressed just for the fun of it, because you've put so many interesting
ideas out there in your book, challenging the community for further steps, is it possible
on the deep learning front that you're wrong about its limitations? That deep learning will
unlock. Yanlacoon next year will publish a paper that achieves this comprehension.
So do you think that way often as a scientist, do you consider that your intuition that deep
learning could actually run away with it? I'm worried about rebranding as a kind of political
thing. So I mean, what's going to happen, I think, is that deep learning is going to start to encompass
simple manipulation. So I think Hinton's just wrong. Hinton says we don't want hybrids. I think
people will work towards hybrids and they will relabel their hybrids as deep learning. We've
already seen some of that. So AlphaGo is often described as a deep learning system, but it's
more correctly described as a system that has deep learning, but also Monte Carlo tree search,
which is a classical AI technique. And people will start to blur the lines in the way that IBM
blurred Watson. First, Watson meant this particular system, and then it was just
anything that IBM built in their cognitive division. But purely, let me ask for sure,
that's a branding question, and that's a giant mess. I mean, purely a single neural network
being able to accomplish reasonable comprehension. I don't step at night
worrying that that's going to happen. And I'll just give you two examples. One is
a guy at DeepMind thought he had finally outfoxed me at Xergy Lord, I think is his Twitter handle.
And he specifically made an example. Marcus said that such and such, he fed it into GP2,
which is the AI system that is so smart that OpenAI couldn't release it because it would
destroy the world, right? You remember that a few months ago. So he feeds it into GPT2.
And my example was something like a rose is a rose, a tulip is a tulip,
a lily is a blank. And he got it to actually do that, which was a little bit impressive. And I
wrote back and I said, that's impressive. But can I ask you a few questions? I said, was that just
one example? Can it do it generally? And can it do it with novel words, which is part of what I
was talking about in 1998, when I first raised the example. So a DAX is a DAX, right? And he
sheepishly wrote back about 20 minutes later and the answer was, well, it had some problems with
those. So I made some predictions 21 years ago that still hold in the world of computer science.
That's amazing, right? Because there's a thousand or a million times more memory and computations,
million times, do million times more operations per second, spread across a cluster,
and there's been advances in replacing sigmoids with other functions and so forth. There's all
kinds of advances, but the fundamental architecture hasn't changed and the fundamental limit hasn't
changed. And what I said then is kind of still true. And then here's a second example. I recently
had a piece in WIRED that's adapted from the book. And the book was when to press before GP2 came out.
But we describe this children's story and all the inferences that you make in this story about a boy
finding a lost wallet. And for fun, in the WIRED piece, we ran it through GP2. GPT2 at something
called TalkToTransformer.com, and your viewers can try this experiment themselves, go to the WIRED
piece that has the link and has the story. And the system made perfectly fluent text that was
totally inconsistent with the conceptual underpinnings of the story. And this is what, again,
I predicted in 1998. And for that matter, Chomsky Miller made the same prediction in 1963. I was
just updating their claim for a slightly new text. So those particular architectures that
don't have any bills to acknowledge, they're basically just a bunch of layers doing correlational
stuff. They're not going to solve these problems. So 20 years ago, you said the emperor has no
clothes. Today, the emperor still has no clothes. The lighting's better, though. The lighting is
better. And I think you yourself are also, I mean, and we found out some things to do with naked
emperors. I mean, it's not like stuff is worthless. I mean, they're not really naked. It's more like
they're in their briefs and everybody thinks that. And so like, I mean, they are great at speech
recognition. But the problems that I said were hard, because I didn't literally say the emperor
has no clothes. I said, this is a set of problems that humans are really good at. And it wasn't
couched as AI. It was couched as cognitive science. But I said, if you want to build a neural model
of how humans do certain class of things, you're going to have to change the architecture. And
I stand by those claims. And I think people should understand you're quite entertaining in your
cynicism, but you're also very optimistic and a dreamer about the future of AI, too. So you're
both is just there's a famous saying about being people overselling technology in the short run
and underselling it in the long run. And so I actually end the book or Ernie Davis and I end
our book with an optimistic chapter, which kind of killed Ernie because he's even more pessimistic
than I am. He describes me as a contrarian and him as a pessimist. But I persuaded that we should
end the book with a look at what would happen if AI really did incorporate, for example,
the common sense reasoning and the nativism and so forth, the things that we counseled for. And
we wrote it and it's an optimistic chapter that AI suitably reconstructed so that we could trust
it, which we can't now could really be world changing. So on that point, if you look at the
future trajectories of AI, people have worries about negative effects of AI, whether it's
at the large existential scale or smaller short term scale of negative impact on society. So
you write about trustworthy AI. How can we build AI systems that align with our values that make
for a better world that we can interact with that we can trust? The first thing we have to do is to
replace deep learning with deep understanding. So you can't have alignment with a system that
traffics only in correlations and doesn't understand concepts like bottles or harm.
Asimov talked about these famous laws. The first one was first do no harm. And you can quibble
about the details of Asimov's laws, but we have to if we're going to build real robots in the
real world have something like that. That means we have to program in a notion that's at least
something like harm. That means we have to have these more abstract ideas that deep learning is
not particularly good at. They have to be in the mix somewhere. You could do statistical analysis
about probabilities of given harms or whatever, but you have to know what a harm is in the same
way that you have to understand that a bottle isn't just a collection of pixels.
You're implying that you need to also be able to communicate that to humans. So the AI systems
would be able to prove to humans that they understand that they know what harm means.
I might run it in the reverse direction, but roughly speaking, I agree with you. So
we probably need to have committees of wise people, ethicists, and so forth,
think about what these rules ought to be, and we should just leave it to software engineers.
It shouldn't just be software engineers, and it shouldn't just be people who
own large mega corporations that are good at technology. Ethicists and so forth should be
involved. But there should be some assembly of wise people, as I was putting it,
that tries to figure out what the rules ought to be, and those have to get translated into code.
You can argue code or neural networks or something. They have to be
translated into something that machines can work with, and that means there has to be a way of
working the translation, and right now we don't. We don't have a way. So let's say you and I were
the committee, and we decide that Asimov's first law is actually right, and let's say it's not just
two white guys, which would be unfortunate, and then we have a broad representative sample of the
world or however we want to do this, and the committee decides eventually, okay, Asimov's
first law is actually pretty good. There are these exceptions to it. We want to program in
these exceptions, but let's start with just the first one, and then we'll get to the exceptions.
First one is first do no harm. Well, somebody has to now actually turn that into a computer
program or a neural network or something, and one way of taking the whole book, the whole
argument that I'm making is that we just don't have to do that yet, and we're fooling ourselves
if we think that we can build trustworthy AI. If we can't even specify in any kind of,
you know, we can't do it in Python and we can't do it in TensorFlow, we're fooling ourselves
and thinking that we can make trustworthy AI if we can't translate harm into something that we
can execute, and if we can't, then we should be thinking really hard, how could we ever do such
a thing? Because if we're going to use AI in the ways that we want to use it to make job interviews
or to do surveillance, not that I personally want to do that, or whatever, I mean, if we're going to
use AI in ways that have practical impact on people's lives or medicine, it's got to be able
to understand stuff like that. So one of the things your book highlights is that, you know,
a lot of people in the deep learning community, but also the general public, politicians, just
people in all general groups and walks of life have different levels of misunderstanding of AI.
So when you talk about committees, what's your advice to our society? How do we grow? How do we
learn about AI such that such committees could emerge, where large groups of people could have
a productive discourse about how to build successful AI systems?
Part of the reason we wrote the book was to try to inform those committees. So part of the reason
we wrote the book was to inspire a future generation of students to solve what we think are the
important problems. So a lot of the book is trying to pinpoint what we think are the hard problems
where we think effort would most be rewarded. And part of it is to try to train people who
talk about AI, but aren't experts in the field to understand what's realistic and what's not.
One of my favorite parts in the book is the six questions you should ask
anytime you read a media account. So number one is if somebody talks about something,
look for the demo. If there's no demo, don't believe it. The demo that you can try. If you
can't try it at home, maybe it doesn't really work that well yet. So we don't have this example
in the book. But if Sundar Pinchai says, we have this thing that allows it to sound like human
beings in conversation, you should ask, can I try it? And you should ask how general it is. And it
turns out at that time, I'm alluding to Google Duplex, when it was announced, it only worked on
calling hairdressers, restaurants, and finding opening hours. That's not very general. That's
narrow AI. And I'm not going to ask your thoughts about Sophia. But yeah, I understand that's a
really good question to ask of any kind of high-top idea. So Sophia has very good material written
for her, but she doesn't understand the things that she's saying. So a while ago, you've written a
book on the science of learning, which I think is fascinating. But the learning case studies of
playing guitar, guitar zero, I love guitar myself, I've been playing my whole life. So let me ask
a very important question. What is your favorite song, rock song to listen to or try to play?
Well, those would be different. But I'll say that my favorite rock song to listen to is probably
all along the Watchtower, the Jimi Hendrix version. Jimi Hendrix version feels magic to me.
I've actually recently learned that I love that song. I've been trying to put it on YouTube,
myself singing. Singing is the scary part. If you could party with a rock star for a weekend,
living or dead, who would you choose? And pick their mind, it's not necessarily about the partying.
Thanks for the clarification. I guess John Lennon is such an intriguing person. I mean,
a troubled person, but an intriguing one. So beautiful. Well, Imagine is one of my favorite
songs. So also one of my favorite songs. That's a beautiful way to end it. Gary,
thank you so much for talking to me. Thanks so much for having me.