The following is a conversation with George Hotz, a.k.a. Geohot, his second time on the podcast.
He's the founder of Kamma AI, an autonomous and semi-autonomous vehicle technology company
that seeks to be, to Tesla autopilot, what Android is, to the iOS. They sell the Kamma 2 device for
$1,000 that, when installed in many of their supported cars, can keep the vehicle centered
in the lane even when there are no lane markings. It includes driver sensing that ensures that the
driver's eyes are on the road. As you may know, I'm a big fan of driver sensing. I do believe Tesla
Autopilot and others should definitely include it in their sensor suite. Also, I'm a fan of Android
and a big fan of George, for many reasons, including his non-linear out-of-the-box brilliance and the
fact that he's a superstar programmer of a very different style than myself. Styles make fights
and styles make conversations, so I really enjoyed this chat and I'm sure we'll talk many more times
on this podcast. Quick mention of a sponsor followed by some thoughts related to the episode.
First is ForSigmatic, the maker of delicious mushroom coffee. Second is the coding digital,
a podcast on tech and entrepreneurship that I listen to and enjoy. And finally, ExpressVPN,
the VPN I've used for many years to protect my privacy on the internet. Please check out the
sponsors in the description to get a discount and to support this podcast. As a side note,
let me say that my work at MIT on autonomous and semi-autonomous vehicles led me to study the human
side of autonomy enough to understand that it's a beautifully complicated and interesting problem
space, much richer than what can be studied in the lab. In that sense, the data that comma AI,
Tesla Autopilot, and perhaps others like Cadillac Supercruiser Collecting, gives us a chance to
understand how we can design safe semi-autonomous vehicles for real human beings in real-world
conditions. I think this requires bold innovation and a serious exploration of the first principles
of the driving task itself. If you enjoyed this thing, subscribe on YouTube, review it with
five stars and up a podcast, follow on Spotify, support on Patreon, or connect with me on Twitter
at Lex Freedman. And now here's my conversation with George Hotz. So last time we started talking
about the simulation, this time let me ask you, do you think there's intelligent life out there in
the universe? I always maintained my answer to the Fermi paradox. I think there has been intelligent
life elsewhere in the universe. So intelligent civilizations existed, but they've blown themselves
up. So your general intuition is that intelligent civilizations quickly, like there's that parameter
in the Drake equation, your sense is they don't last very long. Yeah. How are we doing on that?
Have we lasted pretty good? Oh, no. How do we do? Oh, yeah. I mean, not quite yet.
Well, it's only as Yukowski, IQ required to destroy the world falls by one point every year.
Okay. So technology democratizes the destruction of the world.
When can a meme destroy the world?
It kind of is already, right?
Somewhat. I don't think we've seen anywhere near the worst of it yet. World's going to get weird.
Well, maybe a meme can save the world. We thought about that, the meme Lord Elon Musk fighting on
the side of good versus the meme Lord of the darkness, which is not saying anything bad about
Donald Trump, but he is the Lord of the meme on the dark side. He's a Darth Vader of memes.
I think in every fairy tale, they always end it with, and they lived happily ever after,
and I'm like, please tell me more about this happily ever after. I've heard 50% of marriages
end in divorce. Why doesn't your marriage end up there? You can't just say happily ever after. So
the thing about destruction is it's over after the destruction. We have to do everything right
in order to avoid it. And one thing wrong, I mean, actually, this is what I really like about
cryptography. Cryptography, it seems like we live in a world where the defense wins.
Versus nuclear weapons, the opposite is true. It is much easier to build a warhead that splits
into 100 little warheads than to build something that can take out 100 little warheads. The offense
has the advantage there. So maybe our future is in crypto. So cryptography, right? The Goliath
is the defense. And then all the different hackers are the Davids, and that equation is flipped for
nuclear war. Because there's so many, like one nuclear weapon destroys everything, essentially.
Yeah, and it is much easier to attack with a nuclear weapon than it is to like, the technology
required to intercept and destroy a rocket is much more complicated than the technology required to
just orbital trajectory send a rocket to somebody. Okay, your intuition that there were intelligent
civilizations out there, but it's very possible that they're no longer there. It's kind of a sad
picture. They enter some steady state. They all wirehead themselves. What's wirehead? Stimulate
their platter centers and just live forever in this kind of stasis. They become, well, I mean,
I think the reason I believe this is because where are they? If there's some reason they stopped
expanding, because otherwise they would have taken over the universe. The universe isn't that big.
Or at least, you know, let's just talk about the galaxy, right? 70,000 light years across.
I took that number from Star Trek Voyager. I don't know how true it is. But yeah, that's not big.
Right? 70,000 light years is nothing. For some possible technology that you can imagine that
leverage like wormholes or something like that. You don't even need wormholes. Just a von Neumann
probe is enough. A von Neumann probe and a million years of sub light travel, and you'd have taken
over the whole universe. That clearly didn't happen. So something stopped it. So you mean a few,
right, for like a few million years, if you sent out probes that travel close, what's sub light?
You mean close to the speed of light? Let's say 0.1c. And it just spreads. Interesting. Actually,
that's an interesting calculation. So what makes you think that we'd be able to communicate with
them? Like, yeah, what's why do you think we would be able to be able to comprehend
intelligent lies that are out there? Like, even if they were among us kind of thing? Like,
or even just flying around? Well, I mean, that's possible. It's possible that there is some sort
of prime directive that'd be a really cool universe to live in. And there's some reason
they're not making themselves visible to us. But it makes sense that they would use the same,
well, at least the same entropy. Well, you're implying the same laws of physics. I don't know
what you mean by entropy in this case. Oh, yeah. I mean, if entropy is the scarce resource in the
universe. So what do you think about like Steven Wolfram and everything is a computation? And
then what if they are traveling through this world of computation? So if you think of the
universe as just information processing, then what you're referring to with entropy, and then
these pockets of interesting complex computation swimming around, how do we know they're not
already here? How do we know that this, like all the different amazing things that are full of
mystery on earth are just like little footprints of intelligence from light years away?
Maybe. I mean, I tend to think that as civilizations expand, they use more and more energy.
And you can never overcome the problem of waste heat. So where is their waste heat?
So we'd be able to, with our crude methods, be able to see like, there's a whole lot of
energy here. But it could be something we're not, I mean, we don't understand dark energy,
dark matter. It could be just stuff we don't understand at all. Or they can have a fundamentally
different physics, you know, like that we just don't even comprehend. Well, I think, okay,
I mean, it depends how far out you want to go. I don't think physics is very different on the
other side of the galaxy. I would suspect that they have, I mean, if they're in our universe,
they have the same physics. Well, yeah, that's the assumption we have. But there could be like
super trippy things like, like our cognition only gets to a slice, and all the possible
instruments that we can design only get to a particular slice of the universe. And there's
something much like weirder. Maybe we can try a thought experiment. Would people from the past
be able to detect the remnants of our, we'll be able to detect our modern civilization?
And I think the answer is obviously yes. You mean past from a hundred years ago?
Well, let's even go back further. Let's go to a million years ago.
The humans who were lying around in the desert probably didn't even have, maybe they just barely
had fire. They would understand if a 747 flew overhead. In this vicinity, but not if a 747 flew
on Mars. Like, because they wouldn't be able to see far, because we're not actually communicating
that well with the rest of the universe. We're doing okay, just sending out random like 50s tracks
of music. True. And yeah, I mean, they'd have to, you know, the, we've only been broadcasting radio
waves for 150 years. And well, there's your light cone. So yeah, okay. What do you make about all
the, I recently came across this, having talked to David's favor. I don't know if you caught
what the videos that Pentagon released and the New York Times reporting of the UFO sightings.
So I kind of looked into it, quote unquote. And there's actually been like hundreds of thousands
of UFO sightings, right? And a lot of it, you can explain it way in different kinds of ways.
So one is it could be interesting physical phenomena. Two, it could be people wanting to
believe. And therefore they conjure up a lot of different things that just, you know, when you
see different kinds of lights, some basic physics phenomena, and then you just conjure up ideas
of possible out there mysterious worlds. But, you know, it's also possible like you have a case of
David Fravor, who is a Navy pilot, who's, you know, as legit as it gets in terms of humans who
are able to perceive things in the environment and make conclusions, whether those things are
a threat or not. And he and several other pilots saw a thing, I don't know if you followed this,
but they saw a thing that they've since then called TikTok that moved in all kinds of weird ways.
They don't know what it is. It could be technology developed by the United States,
and they're just not aware of it and the surface level from the Navy, right? It could be
different kind of lighting technology or drone technology, all that kind of stuff. It could
be the Russians and the Chinese, all that kind of stuff. And of course their mind, our mind,
can also venture into the possibility that it's from another world. Have you looked into this at
all? What do you think about it? I think all the news is a scythe. I think that the most plausible...
Nothing is real. Yeah, I listened to the, I think it was Bob Lazar on Joe Rogan. And like,
I believe everything this guy is saying. And then I think that it's probably just some like MK
Ultra kind of thing, you know? What do you mean? Like, they, you know, they made some weird thing
and they called it an alien spaceship. You know, maybe it was just to like stimulate young
physicists' minds and tell them it's alien technology and we'll see what they come up with,
right? Do you find any conspiracy theories compelling? Like, have you pulled at the
string of the, of the rich complex world of conspiracy theories that's out there?
I think that I've heard a conspiracy theory that conspiracy theories were invented by the CIA in
the 60s to discredit true things. Yeah. So, you know, you can go to ridiculous conspiracy theories
like Flat Earth and Pizza Gate and, you know, these things are almost to hide like conspiracy
theories that like, you know, remember when the Chinese like locked up the doctors who discovered
coronavirus? Like I tell people this and I'm like, no, no, no, that's not a conspiracy theory. That
actually happened. Do you remember the time that the money used to be backed by gold and now it's
backed by nothing? This is not a conspiracy theory. This actually happened. Well, that's one of my
worries today with the idea of fake news is that when nothing is real, then like you dilute the
possibility of anything being true by conjuring up all kinds of conspiracy theories. And then you
don't know what to believe. And then like the idea of truth of objectivity is lost completely.
Everybody has their own truth. So you used to control information by censoring it.
Then the internet happened and governments are like, oh, shit, we can't censor things anymore.
I know what we'll do. You know, it's the old story of the story of like,
tying a flag with a leprechaun tells you as gold is buried and you tie one flag and you make the
leprechaun swear to not remove the flag and you come back to the field later with a shovel and
this flag's everywhere. That's one way to maintain privacy, right? In order to protect the contents
of this conversation, for example, we could just generate like millions of deep fake conversations
where you and I talk and say random things. So this is just one of them and nobody knows which
one was the real one. This could be fake right now. Classic steganography technique.
Okay, another absurd question about intelligent life because you're an incredible programmer
outside of everything else we'll talk about just as a programmer. Do you think intelligent beings
out there, the civilizations that were out there had computers and programming? Did they
do naturally have to develop something where we engineer machines and are able to encode both
knowledge into those machines and instructions that process that knowledge, process that
information to make decisions and actions and so on? And would those programming languages,
if you think they exist, be at all similar to anything we've developed?
So I don't see that much of a difference between quote unquote natural languages and programming
languages. I think there's so many similarities. So when asked the question what do alien languages
look like, I imagine they're not all that dissimilar from ours. And I think translating in and out of
them wouldn't be that crazy. It was difficult to compile like DNA to Python and then to see.
There is a little bit of a gap in the kind of languages we use for
touring machines and the kind of languages nature seems to use a little bit. Maybe that's just,
we just haven't understood the kind of language that nature uses well yet.
DNA is a CAD model. It's not quite a programming language. It has no sort of serial execution.
It's not quite a CAD model. So I think in that sense, we actually completely understand it.
The problem is simulating on these CAD models. I played with it a bit this year. It's super
computationally intensive. If you want to go down to the molecular level where you need to go to see
a lot of these phenomenon like protein folding. So yeah, it's not that we don't understand it.
It just requires a whole lot of compute to kind of compile it.
For human minds, it's inefficient both for the data representation and for the programming.
Yeah, it runs well on raw nature. It runs well on raw nature. And when we try to build
emulators or simulators for that, well, they're mad slow and I've tried it.
It runs in that, yeah, you've commented elsewhere. I don't remember where that
one of the problems is simulating nature is tough. And if you want to sort of deploy a prototype,
I forgot how you put it, but it made me laugh. But animals or humans would need to be involved
in order to try to run some prototype code. If we're talking about COVID and viruses and so on,
if you were to try to engineer some kind of defense mechanisms like a vaccine
against COVID or all that kind of stuff, that doing any kind of experimentation like you can
with autonomous vehicles would be very technically and ethically costly.
I'm not sure about that. I think you can do tons of crazy biology and test tubes. I think
my bigger complaint is more, all the tools are so bad.
Like literally, you mean like like libraries and I'm not pipetting shit. Like your hand
of me, I gotta, no, no, no, no, there has to be some like automating stuff. And like the
yeah, but human biology is messy. Like it seems like, look at those Duranos videos. They were
joke. It's like a little gantry. It's like a little XY gantry high school science project
with the pipet. I'm like, really? Gotta be something better. You can't build like nice
microfluidics and I can program the computation to biointerface. I mean, this is going to happen.
But like right now, if you are asking me to pipet 50 milliliters of solution, I'm out.
This is so crude. Yeah. Okay. Let's get all the crazy out of the way. So a bunch of people
asked me, since we talked about the simulation last time, we talked about hacking the simulation.
Do you have any updates, any insights about how we might be able to go about
hacking simulation if we indeed do live in a simulation?
I think a lot of people misinterpreted the point of that South by talk. The point of the
South by talk was not literally to hack the simulation. I think that this
is an idea is literally just I think theoretical physics. I think that's the whole
goal. You want your grand unified theory, but then, okay, build a grand unified theory,
search for exploits. I think we're nowhere near actually there yet. My hope with that was just
more to like, are your people kidding me with the things you spend time thinking about? Do you
understand kind of how small you are? You are bites and God's computer, really?
And the things that people get worked up about. So basically, it was more a message of we should
humble ourselves. What are we humans in this byte code? Yeah. And not just humble ourselves,
but I'm not trying to make people feel guilty or anything like that. I'm trying to say literally,
look at what you are spending time on, right? What are you referring to? You're referring to
the Kardashians? What are we talking about? I'm referring to, no, the Kardashians,
everyone knows that's kind of fun. I'm referring more to the economy, this idea that
we got to up our stock price. Or what is the goal function of humanity?
You don't like the game of capitalism? You don't like the games we've constructed for
ourselves as humans? I'm a big fan of capitalism. I don't think that's really the game we're playing
right now. I think we're playing a different game where the rules are rigged.
Okay, which games are interesting to you that we humans have constructed and which
aren't? Which are productive and which are not? Actually, maybe that's the real point of the talk.
It's like, stop playing these fake human games. There's a real game here. We can play the real
game. The real game is nature wrote the rules. This is a real game. There still is a game to play.
But if you look at, sorry to interrupt, I don't know if you've seen the Instagram account,
Nature is Metal. The game that nature seems to be playing is a lot more cruel than we humans
want to put up with. Or at least we see it as cruel. It's like the bigger thing eats the smaller
thing and does it to impress another big thing so it can mate with that thing.
And that's it. That seems to be the entirety of it.
Well, there's no art. There's no music. There's no comma AI. There's no comma one,
no comma two, no George Hott's with his brilliant talks at South by Southwest.
I disagree though. I disagree that this is what nature is. I think nature just provided
basically a open world MMORPG. And here it's open world. I mean, if that's the game you want to
play, you can play that game. Isn't that beautiful? I know if you play Diablo, they used to have,
I think, cow level where it's, so everybody will go just, they figured out this,
like the best way to gain like experience points is to just slaughter cows over and over and over.
And so they figured out this little sub game within the bigger game that this is the most
efficient way to get experience points. And everybody somehow agreed that getting experience
points in RPG context where you always want to be getting more stuff, more skills, more levels,
keep advancing. That seems to be good. So might as well spend sacrifice, actual enjoyment of
playing a game, exploring a world and spending like hundreds of hours of your time in cow level.
I mean, the number of hours I spent in cow level, I'm not like the most impressive person because
people have probably thousands of hours there, but it's ridiculous. So that's a little absurd game
that brought me joints and weird dopamine drug kind of way. So you don't like those games.
You don't think that's us humans failing the nature. I think so.
And that was the point of the talk. Yeah. So how do we hack it then?
Well, I want to live forever. And wait, I want to live forever.
And this is the goal. Well, that's a game against nature.
Yeah. Immortality is the good objective function to you.
I mean, start there and then you can do whatever else you want because you got a long time.
What if immortality makes the game just totally not fun? I mean,
like why do you assume immortality is somehow a good objective function?
It's not immortality that I want. A true immortality where I could not die.
I would prefer what we have right now. But I want to choose my own death, of course.
I don't want nature to decide when I die. I'm going to win. I'm going to be you.
And then at some point, if you choose commit suicide, how long do you think you'd live?
Until I get bored?
See, I don't think people, brilliant people like you that really ponder
living a long time are really considering how meaningless life becomes.
Well, I want to know everything and then I'm ready to die.
But why do you want, isn't it possible that you want to know everything because
it's finite? Like the reason you want to know quote unquote everything is because you
don't have enough time to know everything. And once you have unlimited time, then you realize
like why do anything? Like why learn anything?
I don't want to know everything and then I'm ready to die.
It's a terminal value. It's not in service of anything else.
I'm conscious of the possibility. This is not a certainty. But the possibility of
that engine of curiosity that you're speaking to is actually a symptom of the finiteness of life.
Like without that finiteness, your curiosity would vanish like a morning fog.
Okosky talked about love like that.
Let me solve immortality. Let me change the thing in my brain that reminds me of the fact
that I'm immortal tells me that life is finite shit. Maybe I'll have it tell me that life ends
next week. I'm okay with some self manipulation like that. I'm okay with deceiving myself.
Oh, Rika, changing the code.
If that's the problem, right? If the problem is that I will no longer have that curiosity,
I'd like to have backup copies of myself which I check in with occasionally to make sure they're
okay with the trajectory and they can kind of override it. Maybe a nice like I think of like
those wave nets, those like logarithmic go back to the copies.
But sometimes it's not reversible. I've done this with video games. Once you figure out the
cheat code or like you look up how to cheat old school like single player, it ruins the game for
you. Absolutely. I know that feeling. But again, that just means our brain manipulation
technology is not good enough yet. Remove that cheat code from your brain.
So it's also possible that if we figure out immortality that all of us will kill ourselves
before we advance far enough to be able to revert the change.
I'm not killing myself till I know everything.
That's what you say now because your life is finite.
You know, I think self modifying systems comes up with all these hairy complexities and
can I promise that I'll do it perfectly? No, but I think I can put good safety structures in place.
So that talk in your thinking here is not literally
referring to a simulation in that our universe is a kind of computer program running in a computer.
That's more of a thought experiment. Do you also think of the potential of the sort of
Bostrom, Elon Musk, and others that talk about an actual program that simulates our universe?
Oh, I don't doubt that we're in a simulation. I just think that it's not quite that important.
I mean, I'm interested only in simulation theory as far as like it gives me power over nature.
If it's totally unfalsifiable, then who cares?
I mean, what do you think that experiment would look like? Like somebody on Twitter asks
George what signs we would look for to know whether or not we're in the simulation,
which is exactly what you're asking is like the step that precedes the step of knowing how to
get more power from this knowledge is to get an indication that there's some power to be gained.
Get an indication that you can discover and exploit cracks in the simulation,
or it doesn't have to be in the physics of the universe.
Show me. I mean, like a memory leak would be cool.
Like some scrying technology. What kind of technology?
Scrying. What's that? That's a weird. Scrying is the paranormal ability to
like remote viewing, like being able to see somewhere where you're not.
So, I don't think you can do it by chanting in a room, but if we could find, it's a memory leak,
basically. It's a memory leak. Yeah, you're able to access parts you're not supposed to.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. And thereby discover shortcut.
Yeah, memory leak means the other thing as well. But I mean like, yeah,
like an ability to read arbitrary memory. And that one's not that horrifying.
The right ones start to be horrifying. Read it right. So, the reading is not the problem.
Yeah, it's like Heartbleed for the universe. Oh boy, the writing is a big, big problem.
It's a big problem. It's the moment you can write anything, even if it's just random noise.
That's terrifying. I mean, even without, even without that, like even some of the, you know,
the nanotech stuff that's coming, I think. I don't know if you're paying attention, but
actually Eric Weinstein came out with the theory of everything. I mean, that came out. He's been
working on a theory of everything in the physics world called geometric unity. And then for me,
from computer science person, like you, Stephen Wolfram's theory of everything of like,
hypergraphs is super interesting and beautiful. But not from a physics perspective, but from a
computational perspective. I don't know, have you paid attention to any of that?
So, again, like what would make me pay attention and like why like a hate string theory is,
okay, make a testable prediction, right? I'm only interested in, I'm not interested in theories
for their intrinsic beauty. I'm interested in theories that give me power over the universe.
So, if these theories do, I'm very interested.
Can I just say how beautiful that is? Because a lot of physicists say, I'm interested in
experimental validation. And they skip out the part where they say, to give me more power in
the universe. I just love the clarity of that. I want 100 gigahertz processors. I want transistors
that are smaller than atoms. I want like power. That's true. And that's where people from aliens
to this kind of technology where people are worried that governments, like who owns that power?
Is it George Haatz? Is it thousands of distributed hackers across the world? Is it governments?
You know, is it Mark Zuckerberg? There's a lot of people that, I don't know if anyone trusts
anyone individual with power. So, they're always worried.
It's the beauty of blockchains.
That's the beauty of blockchains, which we'll talk about on Twitter.
Somebody pointed me to a story, a bunch of people pointed me to a story a few months ago,
where you went into a restaurant in New York, and you can correct me if I'm saying this is wrong,
and ran into a bunch of folks from a company in a crypto company who are trying to scale up Ethereum.
And they had a technical deadline related to a solidity to OVM compiler.
So, these are all Ethereum technologies. So, you stepped in, they recognized you,
pulled you aside, explained their problem, and you stepped in and helped them solve the problem,
thereby creating legend status story. So, can you tell me the story a little more detail? It seems
kind of incredible. Did this happen? Yeah, yeah, it's a true story. It's a true story. I mean,
they wrote a very flattering account of it. So, the company is called Optimism,
spin-off of Plasma. They're trying to build L2 solutions on Ethereum. So, right now,
every Ethereum node has to run every transaction on the Ethereum network.
And this kind of doesn't scale, right? Because if you have N computers, well,
if that becomes two N computers, you actually still get the same amount of compute.
Right? This is like O of one scaling because they all have to run it. Okay, fine. You get more
blockchain security, but like, blockchain is already so secure. Can we trade some of that off
for speed? So, that's kind of what these L2 solutions are. They built this thing, which kind of
sandbox for Ethereum contracts. So, they can run it in this L2 world, and it can't do certain
things in L1. Can I ask you for some definitions? What's L2? Oh, L2 is Layer 2. So, L1 is like the
base Ethereum chain, and then Layer 2 is like a computational layer that runs
elsewhere, but still is kind of secured by Layer 1. And I'm sure a lot of people know,
but Ethereum is a cryptocurrency, probably one of the most popular cryptocurrency, second to
Bitcoin, and a lot of interesting technological innovations there. Maybe you can also slip in
whenever you talk about this, any things that are exciting to you in the Ethereum space.
And why Ethereum? Well, I mean, Bitcoin is not turned complete. Ethereum is not technically
turned complete with the gas limit, but close enough. With the gas limit? What's the gas limit?
Yeah, I mean, no computer is actually turned complete.
They're just fine at RAM. I can actually solve the whole problem.
What's the word gas limit? You just have so many brilliant words. I'm not even gonna ask.
Well, that's not my word. That's Ethereum's word.
Ethereum, you have to spend gas per instruction. So, different op codes use different amounts of
gas, and you buy gas with Ether to prevent people from basically de-dossing the network.
So, Bitcoin is proof of work, and then what's Ethereum?
It's also proof of work. They're working on some proof of stake Ethereum 2.0 stuff,
but right now, it's proof of work. It uses a different hash function from Bitcoin
that's more ASIC resistance because you need RAM.
So, we're all talking about Ethereum 1.0. So, what were they trying to do to scale
this whole process? So, they were like, well, if we could run contracts elsewhere,
and then only save the results of that computation, well, we don't actually have
to do the compute on the chain. We can do the compute off chain and just post what the results
are. Now, the problem with that is, well, somebody could lie about what the results are.
So, you need a resolution mechanism, and the resolution mechanism can be really expensive
because you just have to make sure that the person who is saying, look, I swear that this
is the real computation. I'm staking $10,000 on that fact, and if you prove it wrong, yeah,
it might cost you $3,000 in gas fees to prove wrong, but you'll get the $10,000 bounty.
So, you can secure using those kind of systems. So, it's effectively a sandbox,
which runs contracts, and like just like any kind of normal sandbox, you have to like replace
syscalls with, you know, calls into the hypervisor.
Sandbox, syscalls, hypervisor, what do these things mean?
As long as it's interesting to talk about.
Yeah, I mean, you can take like the Chrome sandbox is maybe the one to think about, right?
So, the Chrome process is doing a rendering. I can't, for example, read a file from the file
system. If it tries to make an open syscall in Linux, you can't make an open syscall. No, no,
no. You have to request from the kind of hypervisor process or like, I don't know what's
called in Chrome, but the, hey, could you open this file for me? And then it does all these checks,
and then it passes the file, handle back in if it's approved. So, that's yeah.
What's the, in the context of Ethereum, what are the boundaries of the sandbox that we're talking
about? Well, like one of the calls that you actually reading and writing any state to the
Ethereum contract or to the Ethereum blockchain. Writing state is one of those calls that you're
going to have to sandbox in layer two, because if you let layer two just arbitrarily write to the
Ethereum blockchain. So, layer two is really sitting on top of layer one. So, you're going to
have a lot of different kinds of ideas that you can play with. And they're all, they're not fundamentally
changing the source code level of Ethereum. Well, you have to replace a bunch of calls
with calls into the hypervisor. So, instead of doing the syscall directly, you replace it with a
call to the hypervisor. So, originally they were doing this by first running the, so solidity is
the language that most Ethereum contracts are written in, it compiles to a bytecode. And then
they wrote this thing they called the transpiler. And the transpiler took the bytecode and it
transpiled it into OVM safe bytecode, basically bytecode that didn't make any of those restricted
syscalls and added the calls to the hypervisor. This transpiler was a 3000 line mess.
And it's hard to do. It's hard to do if you're trying to do it like that because you have to
kind of like deconstruct the bytecode, change things about it, and then reconstruct it. And
I mean, as soon as I hear this, I'm like, well, why don't you just change the compiler?
Right? Why not the first place you build the bytecode, just do it in the compiler?
So, yeah, you know, I asked them how much they wanted it. Of course, we're measured in dollars
and I'm like, well, okay. And yeah, you wrote the compiler. Yeah, I modified, I wrote a 300
line diff to the compiler. It's open source, you can look at it. Yeah, I looked at the code last
night. Yeah, exactly. Qt is a good word for it. And it's C++. C++, yeah. So when asked how you
were able to do it, you said, you just got to think and then do it right. So can you break that
apart a little bit? What's your process of one thinking and two doing it right?
You know, the people who I was working for are amused that I said that it doesn't really mean
anything. Okay. I mean, is there some deep profound insights to draw from like how you problem solve
from that? This is always what I say. I'm like, do you want to be a good programmer? Do it for 20
years? Yeah, there's no shortcuts. What are your thoughts on crypto in general? So what parts
technically or philosophically defined, especially beautiful, maybe? Oh, I'm extremely bullish on
crypto long term, not any specific crypto project, but this idea of, well, two ideas. One,
the Nakamoto consensus algorithm is I think one of the greatest innovations of the 21st century.
This idea that people can reach consensus, you can reach a group consensus using a relatively
straightforward algorithm is wild. And like Satoshi Nakamoto, people always ask me who
I look up to. It's like, whoever that is. Who do you think it is? Elon Musk? Is it you?
It is definitely not me. And I do not think it's Elon Musk. But yeah, this idea of groups
reaching consensus in a decentralized yet formulaic way is one extremely powerful idea from crypto.
Maybe the second idea is this idea of smart contracts. When you write a contract between
two parties, any contract, this contract, if there are disputes, it's interpreted by lawyers.
Lawyers are just really shitty overpaid interpreters. Let's talk about them in terms of like,
let's compare a lawyer to Python. Well, okay. That's brilliant. I never thought of it that way.
It's hilarious. So Python, I'm paying even 10 cents an hour. I'll use the nice Azure machine.
I can run Python for 10 cents an hour. Lawyers cost $1,000 an hour. So Python is 10,000x better
on that axis. Lawyers don't always return the same answer. Python almost always does.
Cost. Yeah. I mean, just cost, reliability, everything about Python is so much better than
lawyers. So if you can make smart contracts, this whole concept of code is law. I would love to
live in a world where everybody accepted that fact. So maybe you can talk about what smart contracts
are. So let's say we have even something as simple as a safety deposit box. Safety deposit box that
holds a million dollars. I have a contract with the bank that says two out of these three parties
must be present to open the safety deposit box and get the money out. So that's a contract with
the bank. And it's only as good as the bank and the lawyers. Let's say somebody dies and now,
oh, we're going to go through a big legal dispute about whether, oh, was it in the will? Was it not
in the will? It's just so messy. And the cost to determine truth is so expensive versus a smart
contract, which just uses cryptography to check if two out of three keys are present.
Well, I can look at that and I can have certainty in the answer that it's going to return.
And that's what all businesses want is certainty. You know, they say businesses don't care,
Viacom YouTube. YouTube's like, look, we don't care which way this lawsuit goes. Just please
tell us so we can have certainty. I wonder how many agreements in this, because we're talking about
financial transactions only in this case, correct? The smart contracts. Oh, you can go to,
you can go to anything. You can go, you can put a prenup in the theorem blockchain.
Married smart contract. Sorry, divorce lawyer. Sorry, you're going to be replaced by Python.
Okay, so that's, so that's another beautiful idea. Do you think there's something that's
appealing to you about any one specific implementation? So if you look 10, 20, 50 years
down the line, do you see any like Bitcoin, Ethereum, any of the other hundreds of cryptocurrencies
winning out? Is there like, what's your intuition about the space? Are you just sitting back and
watching the chaos and look who cares what emerges? Oh, I don't, I don't speculate. I don't
really care. I don't really care which one of these projects wins. I'm kind of in the Bitcoin
as a meme coin camp. I mean, why does Bitcoin have value? It's technically kind of, you know,
not great. Like the block size debate, or when I found out what the block size debate was, I'm
like, are you guys kidding? What's the block size debate? You know what, it's really, it's too stupid
to even talk. People can look it up, but I'm like, wow, you know, Ethereum seems, the governance of
Ethereum seems much better. I've come around a bit on proof of stake ideas. You know, very
smart people thinking about some things. Yeah, you know, governance is interesting. It does feel
like Vitalik, it could just feel like an open, even in these distributed systems, leaders are
helpful because they kind of help you drive the mission and the vision. And they put a face to
a project. It's a weird thing about us humans. Geniuses are helpful, like Vitalik. Yeah, brilliant.
Leaders are not necessarily, yeah. So you think the reason he's the face
of Ethereum is because he's a genius. That's interesting. I mean, that was,
it's interesting to think about that we need to create systems in which the quote unquote leaders
that emerge are the geniuses in the system. I mean, that's arguably why the current state of
democracy is broken is the people who are emerging as the leaders are not the most competent, are
not the superstars of the system. And it seems like at least for now in the crypto world, oftentimes
the leaders are the superstars. Imagine at the debate, they asked,
what's the sixth amendment? What are the four fundamental forces in the universe?
What's the integral of two to the X? Yeah, I'd love to see those questions asked. And that's
what I want as our leader. It's a little bit. What's Bayes rule? Yeah, I mean, even, oh, wow,
you're hurting my brain. My standard was even lower, but I would have loved to see
just this basic brilliance, like I've talked to historians. There's just these,
they're not even like, they don't have a PhD or even education history. They just
like a Dan Carlin type character who just like, holy shit, how did all this information get
into your head? They were able to just connect Genghis Khan to the entirety of the history of
the 20th century. They know everything about every single battle that happened. And they know the
like the game of thrones of the different power plays and all that happened there.
And they know like the individuals and all the documents involved. And they integrate that into
their regular life. It's not like they're ultra history nerds. They're just, they know this information.
That's what competence looks like. Yeah. Because I've seen that with programmers too, right? That's
what great programmers do. But yeah, it'll be, it's really unfortunate that those kinds of people
aren't emerging as our leaders. But for now, at least in the crypto world, that seems to be the
case. I don't know if that always, you could imagine that in 100 years, it's not the case,
crypto world has one very powerful idea going for it. And that's the idea of forks.
I mean, imagine we'll use a less controversial example. This was actually in my joke
app in 2012. I was like, Barack Obama, Mitt Romney, let's let them both be president.
All right. Like imagine we could fork America and just let them both be president. And then
the Americas could compete and people could invest in one, pull their liquidity out of one,
put it in the other. You have this in the crypto world. Ethereum forks into Ethereum and Ethereum
Classic. And you can pull your liquidity out of one and put it in another. And people vote with
their dollars, which forks, companies should be able to fork. I'd love to fork Nvidia.
Yeah. Like different business strategies. And then try them out and see what works.
Like even take, yeah, take common AI that closes its source and then take one that's open source
and see what works. Take one that's purchased by GM and one that remains Android Renegade
in all these different versions and see the beauty of common AI. Someone can actually do that.
Please take common AI and fork it. That's right. That's the beauty of open source.
So you're, I mean, we'll talk about autonomous vehicle space, but it does seem that you're
really knowledgeable about a lot of different topics. So the natural question a bunch of people
ask this, which is how do you keep learning new things? Do you have like practical advice
if you were to introspect like taking notes, allocate time, or do you just mess around and
just allow your curiosity to drive? I'll write these people a self-help book and I'll charge $67
for it. And I will write on the cover of the self-help book. All of this advice is completely
meaningless. You're going to be a sucker and buy this book anyway. And the one lesson that I hope
they take away from the book is that I can't give you a meaningful answer to that.
That's interesting. Let me translate that as you haven't really thought about what it is you do
systematically because you could reduce it. And then some people, I mean, I've met brilliant
people that this is really clear with athletes. Some are just the best in the world at something
and they have zero interest in writing like a self-help book or how to master this game.
And then there are some athletes who become great coaches and they love the analysis,
perhaps the over-analysis. And you right now, at least at your age, which is an interesting,
you're in the middle of the battle. You're like the warriors that have zero interest in writing
books. So you're in the middle of the battle. So yeah. This is a fair point. I do think I have
a certain aversion to this kind of deliberate, intentional way of living life.
You eventually, the hilarity of this, especially since this is recorded,
it will reveal beautifully the absurdity when you finally do publish this book.
That guarantee you will. The story of comma AI, maybe it'll be a biography written about you.
That'll be better, I guess. And you might be able to learn some cute lessons if you're starting
a company like comma AI from that book. But if you're asking generic questions like,
how do I be good at things? Dude, I don't know. Well, I mean, the interesting- Do them a lot.
Do them a lot. But the interesting thing here is learning things outside of your current trajectory,
which is what it feels like from an outsider's perspective. I don't know if there's
advice on that, but it is an interesting curiosity. When you become really busy,
you're running a company. Hard time. Yeah. But there's a natural inclination and
trend. Just the momentum of life carries you into a particular direction of wanting to focus.
And this kind of dispersion that curiosity can lead to gets harder and harder with time.
You get really good at certain things, and it sucks trying things that you're not good at,
like trying to figure them out. I mean, you do this with your live streams. You're on the fly
figuring stuff out. You don't mind looking dumb. No. You just figured out pretty quickly.
Sometimes I try things and I don't figure them out quickly. My chest rating is like a 1400,
despite putting like a couple hundred hours in. It's pathetic. I mean, to be fair, I know that
I could do it better. If I did it better, don't play five minute games, play 15 minute games at
least. I know these things, but it just doesn't. It doesn't stick nicely in my knowledge stream.
All right. Let's talk about Kama AI. What's the mission of the company? Let's look at the biggest
picture. Oh, I have an exact statement. Solve self-driving cars while delivering shipable intermediaries.
So long-term vision is have fully autonomous vehicles and make sure you're making money along
the way. I think it doesn't really speak to money, but I can talk about what solve self-driving cars
means. Solve self-driving cars, of course, means you're not building a new car. You're building
a person replacement. That person can sit in the driver's seat and drive you anywhere a person can
drive with a human or better level of safety, speed, quality, comfort.
And what's the second part of that?
Delivering shipable intermediaries is, well, it's a way to fund the company. That's true,
but it's also a way to keep us honest. If you don't have that, it is very easy with
this technology to think you're making progress when you're not. I've heard it best described on
Hacker News as you can set any arbitrary milestone, meet that milestone, and still be infinitely
far away from solving self-driving cars. So it's hard to have real deadlines when you're
cruise or Waymo when you don't have revenue. Is revenue essentially the thing we're talking
about here? Capitalism is based around consent. Capitalism, the way that you get
revenue is real capitalism. Common is in the real capitalism camp. There's definitely scams out there,
but real capitalism is based around consent. It's based around this idea that if we're getting
revenue, it's because we're providing at least that much value to another person. When someone buys
$1,000 comma two from us, we're providing them at least $1,000 of value, but they wouldn't buy it.
Brilliant. So can you give a world-wind overview of the products that Kamii provides?
Like throughout its history and today? I mean, yeah, the past ones aren't really that interesting.
It's kind of just been refinement of the same idea. The real only product we sell today is the comma
two, which is a piece of hardware with cameras. So the comma two, I mean, you can think about it
kind of like a person. You know, in future hardware will probably be even more and more person-like.
So it has eyes, ears, a mouth, a brain, and a way to interface with the car.
Does it have consciousness? Just kidding. That was a trick question.
I don't have consciousness either. Me and the comma two are the same.
They are the same.
I have a little more compute than it. It only has like the same compute as a B.
You're more efficient energy-wise for the compute you're doing.
Far more efficient energy-wise. 20 pay-to-flops, 20 wants, crazy.
Do you lack consciousness? Sure.
Do you fear death? You do. You want immortality.
Of course I fear death.
Does Kamii fear death? I don't think so.
Of course it does. It very much fears, well, it fears negative loss. Oh, yeah.
Okay. So comma two, when did that come out? That was a year ago? No, two.
Early this year.
Wow, time, it feels, yeah. 2020 feels like it's taken 10 years to get to the end.
It's a long year.
It's a long year. So what's the sexiest thing about comma two, feature-wise?
So, I mean, maybe you can also link on like, what is it? Like, what's its purpose?
Because there's a hardware, there's a software component. You've mentioned the sensors, but
also like, what is it, its features and capabilities?
I think our slogan summarizes it well. A comma slogan is make driving chill.
I love it. Okay. Yeah, I mean, it is, you know, if you like cruise control, imagine cruise control,
but much, much more. So it can do adaptive cruise control things, which is like, slow down for
cars in front of it, maintain a certain speed. And it can also do lane keeping, so stay in the
lane and do it better and better and better over time. It's very much machine learning based.
So there's cameras, there's a driver facing camera too.
What else is there? What am I thinking? So the hardware versus software, so open pilot versus
the actual hardware, the device. What's, can you draw that distinction? What's one? What's the other?
I mean, the hardware is pretty much a cell phone with a few additions, a cell phone with a cooling
system and with a car interface connected to it. And by cell phone, you mean like Qualcomm Snapdragon?
Yeah, the current hardware is a Snapdragon 821. It has Wi-Fi radio, it has an LTE radio, it has a screen.
We use every part of the cell phone. And then the interface of the car is specific to the car,
so you keep supporting more and more cars? Yeah, so the interface to the car, I mean,
the device itself just has four CAN buses, has four CAN interfaces on it, they're connected
through the USB port to the phone. And then, yeah, on those four CAN buses, you connect it to the car
and there's a little part to do this. Cars are actually surprisingly similar. So CAN is the
protocol about which cars communicate and then you're able to read stuff and write stuff to be
able to control the car depending on the car. So what's the software side? What's open pilot?
So, I mean, open pilot is, the hardware is pretty simple compared to open pilot, open pilot is...
Well, so you have a machine learning model, which it's an open pilot, it's a blob, it's just a blob
of weights. It's not like people are like, oh, it's closed source, I'm like, it's a blob of weights,
what do you expect? So it's primarily neural network based?
Well, open pilot is all the software kind of around that neural network, that if you have
a neural network that says, here's where you want to send the car, open pilot actually goes and
executes all of that. It cleans up the input to the neural network, it cleans up the output and
executes on it. So it's the glue that connects everything together. Runs the sensors, does a
bunch of calibration for the neural network, does, you know, deals with like, you know, if the car
is on a banked road, you have to counter steer against that. And the neural network can't necessarily
know that by looking at the picture. So you can do that with other sensors, infusion and localizer.
Open pilot also is responsible for sending the data up to our servers, so we can learn from it,
logging it, recording it, running the cameras, thermally managing the device,
managing the disk space on the device, managing all the resources on the device.
So what, since we last spoke, I don't remember when, maybe a year ago, maybe a little bit longer,
how has open pilot improved?
We did exactly what I promised you. I promised you that by the end of the year,
we would be able to remove the lanes. The lateral policy is now almost completely end to end. You
can turn the lanes off and it will drive slightly worse on the highway if you turn the lanes off,
but you can turn the lanes off and it will drive well trained completely end to end on user data.
And this year we hope to do the same for the longitudinal policy.
So that's the interesting thing is you're not doing, you don't appear to be,
maybe you can correct me, you don't appear to be doing lane detection or lane marking
detection or kind of the segmentation task or any kind of object detection task,
you're doing what's traditionally more called like end to end learning.
So entrained on actual behavior of drivers when they're driving the car manually.
And this is hard to do. It's not supervised learning.
Yeah, but so the nice thing is there's a lot of data, so it's hard and easy.
We have a lot of high quality data, yeah.
Like more than you need in the sun.
Well, we've way more than we do. We've way more data than we need.
I mean, it's an interesting question, actually, because in terms of amount, you have more than
you need. But the, you know, driving is full of edge cases.
So how do you select the data you train on?
I think this is an interesting open question.
Like what's the cleverest way to select data?
That's the question Tesla is probably working on.
That's, I mean, the entirety of machine learning can be,
they don't seem to really care. They just kind of select data.
But I feel like that if you want to solve, if you want to create intelligence systems,
you have to pick data well, right?
And so do you have any hints, ideas of how to do it well?
So in some ways, that is the definition I like of reinforcement learning versus supervised learning.
In supervised learning, the weights depend on the data, right?
And this is obviously true, but the, in reinforcement learning, the data depends on the weights.
Yeah.
Right. And actually both ways.
That's poetry.
That's brilliant.
How does it know what data to train on?
Well, let it pick.
We're not there yet, but that's the eventual.
So you're thinking this almost like a reinforcement learning framework.
We're going to do RL on the world.
Every time a car makes a mistake, user disengages.
We train on that and do RL on the world.
Ship out a new model. That's an epoch, right?
And for now, you're not doing the Elon style promising that it's going to be fully autonomous.
You really are sticking to level two and like it's supposed to be supervised.
It is definitely supposed to be supervised and we enforce the fact that it's supervised.
We look at our rate of improvement in disengagements.
OpenPilot now has an unplanned disengagement about every 100 miles.
This is up from 10 miles, like maybe, maybe a, maybe a year ago.
Yeah. So maybe we've seen 10x improvement in a year, but 100 miles is still a far cry
from the 100,000 you're going to need.
So you're going to somehow need to get three more 10x's in there.
And you're, what's your intuition?
You're basically hoping that there's exponential improvement built into the,
baked into the cake somewhere.
Well, that's even, I mean, 10x improvement, that's already assuming exponential, right?
There's definitely exponential improvement.
And I think when Elon talks about exponential, like these things,
these systems are going to exponentially improve.
Just exponential doesn't mean you're getting 100 gigahertz processors tomorrow, right?
Like it's going to still take a while because the gap
between even our best system and humans is still large.
So that's an interesting distinction to draw.
So if you look at the way Tesla is approaching the problem,
and the way you're approaching the problem, which is very different than the rest of the
self-driving car world.
So let's put them aside.
Is you're treating most, the driving task as a machine learning problem.
And the way Tesla is approaching it is with the multitask learning,
where you break the task of driving into hundreds of different tasks.
And you have this multi-headed neural network that's very good at performing each task.
And there's presumably something on top that's stitching stuff together
in order to make control decisions, policy decisions about how you move the car.
But what that allows you, there's a brilliance to this because it allows you to
master each task, like lane detection, stop sign detection, the traffic light detection,
drivable area segmentation, vehicle bicycle pedestrian detection.
There's some localization tasks in there.
Also predicting how the entities in the scene are going to move.
Everything is basically a machine learning task, where there's a classification,
segmentation, prediction, and it's nice because you can have this entire engine,
data engine that's mining for edge cases for each one of these tasks.
And you can have people, like engineers that are basically masters of that task,
they become the best person in the world at, as you talk about, the cone guy for Waymo.
Yeah, we're a good old cone guy.
Become the best person in the world at cone detection.
So that's a compelling notion from a supervised learning perspective,
automating much of the process of edge case discovery and retraining neural network for
each of the individual perception tasks. And then you're looking at the machine learning
in a more holistic way, basically doing end-to-end learning on the driving tasks, supervised,
trained on the data of the actual driving of people they use comma AI,
like actual human drivers, their manual control, plus the moments of disengagement
that maybe with some labeling could indicate the failure of the system.
You have a huge amount of data for positive control of the vehicle, like successful control
of the vehicle, both maintaining the lane as I think you're also working on
longitude, no control of the vehicle, and then failure cases where the vehicle does
something wrong that needs disengagement. So why do you think you're right and Tesla is wrong
on this? Do you think you'll come around the Tesla way? Do you think Tesla will come around to your way?
If you were to start a chess engine company, would you hire a bishop guy?
See, we have, this is Monday morning quarterbacking, is yes, probably.
Oh, our Rook guy. Oh, we stole the Rook guy from that company. Oh, we're gonna have real good Rooks.
Well, there's not many pieces, right? There's not many guys and gals to hire.
You just have a few that work on the bishop, a few that work on the Rook.
But is that not ludicrous today to think about in a world of AlphaZero?
But AlphaZero is a chess game. So the fundamental question is how hard is driving compared to chess?
Because so long term, end to end will be the right solution. The question is how many years
away is that? End to end is going to be the only solution for level five.
For the only way we get there. Of course. And of course, Tesla is going to come around to my
way. And if you're a Rook guy out there, I'm sorry. The cone guy. I don't know.
We're going to specialize each task. We're going to really understand Rook placement. Yeah.
I understand the intuition you have. I mean, that is a very compelling notion that we can
learn the task end to end, like the same compelling notion you might have for natural
language conversation. But I'm not sure. Because one thing you sneaked in there is assertion that
it's impossible to get to level five without this kind of approach. I don't know if that's
obvious. I don't know if that's obvious either. I don't actually mean that. I think that it is much
easier to get to level five with an end to end approach. I think that the other approach is
doable, but the magnitude of the engineering challenge may exceed what humanity is capable of.
But what do you think of the Tesla data engine approach, which to me is an active learning
task is kind of fascinating, is breaking it down into these multiple tasks and mining their data
constantly for like edge cases for these different tasks. But the tasks themselves are not being
learned. This is feature engineering. I mean, it's a higher abstraction level of feature
engineering for the different tasks. It's task engineering in a sense. It's slightly better
feature engineering, but it's still fundamentally as feature engineering. And if anything about the
history of AI has taught us anything, it's that feature engineering approaches will always be
replaced and lose to end to end. Now, to be fair, I cannot really make promises on timelines,
but I can say that when you look at the code for stock fish and the code for alpha zero,
one is a lot shorter than the other. A lot more elegant required a lot less programmer hours to
write. Yeah, but there was a lot more murder of bad agents on the alpha zero side. By murder, I mean
agents that played a game and failed miserably. Yeah. Oh, in simulation, that failure is less
costly. Yeah. In real world. Wait, do you mean in practice, like alpha zero has lost games
miserably? No, I haven't seen that. No, but I know the requirement for alpha zero is
to be able to like evolution, human evolution, not human evolution, biological evolution of life
on earth from the origin of life has murdered trillions upon trillions of organisms on the path
thus humans. So the question is, can we stitch together a human like object without having to
go through the entirety process of evolution? Well, no, but do the evolution in simulation?
Yeah, that's the question. Can we simulate? So do you ever sense that it's possible to simulate
some aspect of it? Mu zero is exactly this. Mu zero is the solution to this. Mu zero, I think,
is going to be looked back as the canonical paper. And I don't think deep learning is everything.
I think that there's still a bunch of things missing to get there. But Mu zero, I think,
is going to be looked back as the kind of cornerstone paper of this whole deep learning era.
And Mu zero is the solution to self-driving cars. You have to make a few tweaks to it. But
Mu zero does effectively that. It does those rollouts and those murdering in a learned
simulator and a learned dynamics model. It's interesting. It doesn't get enough love.
I was blown away when I was blown away when I read that paper. I'm like, okay, I've always
said a comma. I'm going to sit and I'm going to wait for the solution to self-driving cars to come
along. This year, I saw it. It's Mu zero. So sit back and let the winning roll in.
So your sense just to elaborate a little bit to link on the topic. Your sense is neural networks
will solve driving. Yes. Like we don't need anything else.
I think the same way chess was maybe the chess and maybe Google are the pinnacle of like
search algorithms and things that look kind of like a star. The pinnacle of this error is going
to be self-driving cars. But on the path that you have to deliver products and it's possible that
the path to full self-driving cars will take decades. I doubt it. How long would you put on it?
Like what are we? You're chasing it. Tesla's chasing it. What are we talking about? 5 years,
10 years, 50 years? Let's say in the 2020s. In the 2020s. The later part of the 2020s.
With the neural network, that would be nice to see. And on the path to that, you're delivering
products, which is a nice L2 system. That's what Tesla is doing, a nice L2 system.
Just gets better every time. The only difference between L2 and the other levels
is who takes liability. And I'm not a liability guy. I don't want to take liability. I'm going to
level 2 forever. Now on that little transition, I mean, how do you make the transition work?
Is this where driver sensing comes in? Like how do you make the, because you said 100 miles,
like is there some sort of human factor psychology thing where people start to
over-trust the system, all those kinds of effects. Once it gets better and better and
better and better, they get lazier and lazier and lazier. Is that, like how do you get that
transition right? First off, our monitoring is already adaptive. Our monitoring is already seen
adaptive. Driver monitoring is just the camera that's looking at the driver. You have an infrared
camera. Our policy for how we enforce the driver monitoring is seen adaptive. What's that mean?
For example, in one of the extreme cases, if the car is not moving, we do not actively enforce
driver monitoring. If you are going through like a 45-mile-an-hour road with lights
and stop signs and potentially pedestrians, we enforce a very tight driver monitoring policy.
If you are alone on a perfectly straight highway, and it's all machine learning,
none of that is hand-coded. Actually, the stop is hand-coded, but...
So there's some kind of machine learning estimation of risk.
Yeah. I mean, I've always been a huge fan of that. That's a, it's difficult to do
every step into that direction is a worthwhile stop to take. It might be difficult to do really
well. Like us humans are able to estimate risk pretty damn well. Whatever the hell that is,
that feels like one of the nice features of us humans. Because we humans are really good drivers
when we're really tuned in. And we're good at estimating risk, like when are we supposed to
be tuned in? Yeah. And people are like, oh, well, why would you ever make the driver monitoring policy
less aggressive? Why would you always not keep it at its most aggressive? Because then people
are just going to get fatigued from it. Yeah. Well, they get annoyed. You want them,
you want the experience to be pleasant. Obviously, I want the experience to be pleasant,
but even just from a straight up safety perspective, if you alert people when they look
around and they're like, why is this thing alerting me? There's nothing I could possibly hit right
now. People will just learn to tune it out. People will just learn to tune it out, to put
weights on the steering wheel, to do whatever, to overcome it. And remember that you're always
part of this adaptive system. So all I can really say about how this scales going forward is,
yeah, something we have to monitor for. We don't know. This is a great psychology experiment at
scale. We'll see. Yeah, it's fascinating. Track it. And making sure you have a good
understanding of attention is a very key part of that psychology problem.
Yeah. I think you and I probably have a different come to it differently, but to me,
it's a fascinating psychology problem to explore something much deeper than just driving. It's
it's such a nice way to explore human attention and human behavior, which is why, again,
we've probably both criticized Mr. Elon Musk on this one topic from different avenues.
So both offline and online, I had little chats with Elon and
like, I love human beings as a computer vision problem, as an AI problem. It's fascinating.
He wasn't so much interested in that problem.
It's like, in order to solve driving, the whole point is you want to remove the human from the
picture. And it seems like you can't do that quite yet. Eventually, yes, but you can't quite do that
yet. So this is the moment where you can't yet say, I told you so to Tesla, but it's getting there
because I don't know if you've seen this, there's some reporting that they're in fact starting to do
driver monitoring. Yeah, they ship the model in shadow mode.
We though, I believe only a visible light camera. It might even be fisheye. It's like a low resolution.
Low resolution visible light. I mean, to be fair, that's what we have in the Eon as well,
our last generation product. This is the one area where I can say our hardware is ahead of Tesla.
The rest of our hardware way way behind, but our driver monitoring camera.
So you think, I think on the third row Tesla podcast or somewhere else, I've heard you say that
obviously eventually they're going to have driver monitoring.
I think what I've said is Elon will definitely ship driver monitoring before he ships level
five. And I'm willing to bet 10 grand on that. And you bet 10 grand on that.
I mean, now I don't want to take the bet, but before, maybe someone would have thought I should
have got my money. It's an interesting bet. I think you're right. I'm actually on a human level
because he's made the decision. He said that driver monitoring is the wrong way to go.
But you have to think of as a human as a CEO. I think that's the right thing to say when
like sometimes you have to say things publicly that different than when you actually believe
because when you're producing a large number of vehicles and the decision was made not to
include the camera, like what are you supposed to say? Like our cars don't have the thing that I
think is right to have. It's an interesting thing. But like on the other side as a CEO,
I mean, something you could probably speak to as a leader, I think about me as a human
to publicly change your mind on something. How hard is that? Well, especially when assholes
like George Haas say, I told you so. All I will say is I am not a leader and I am happy to change
my mind. You think Elon will? Yeah, I do. I think he'll come up with a good way to make it
psychologically okay for him. Well, it's such an important thing, man, especially for a first
principles thinker because he made a decision that driver monitoring is not the right way to go.
And I could see that decision and I could even make that decision. Like I was on the fence
too. Like I'm not a driver monitoring is such an obvious simple solution to the problem of
attention. It's not obvious to me that just by putting a camera there, you solve things. You
have to create an incredible compelling experience just like you're talking about.
I don't know if it's easy to do that. It's not at all easy to do that, in fact, I think. So
as a creator of a car that's trying to create a product that people love, which is what Tesla
tries to do, right? It's not obvious to me that as a design decision, whether adding a camera
is a good idea. From a safety perspective either, like in the human factors community,
everybody says that you should obviously have driver sensing, driver monitoring. But like
that's like saying it's obvious as parents you shouldn't let your kids go out at night.
But okay. But like they're still going to find ways to do drugs.
Yeah. You have to also be good parents. So it's much more complicated than just
you need to have driver monitoring. I totally disagree on, okay, if you have a camera there
and the camera is watching the person but never throws an alert, they'll never think about it.
Right? The driver monitoring policy that you choose to, how you choose to communicate with
the user is entirely separate from the data collection perspective. Right? So there's one
thing to say, tell your teenager they can't do something. There's another thing to gather the
data. So you can make informed decisions. That's really interesting. But you have to make that,
that's the interesting thing about cars. But even true with Comm AI, you don't have to
manufacture the thing into the car is you have to make a decision that anticipates
the right strategy long term. So like you have to start collecting the data and start making
decisions. Started it, started it three years ago. I believe that we have the best driver
monitoring solution in the world. I think that when you compare it to Supercruise is the only
other one that I really know that shipped and ours is better. What do you like and not like about
Supercruise? I mean, I had a few Supercruise, the sun would be shining through the window,
would blind the camera, and it would say I wasn't paying attention when I was looking completely
straight. I couldn't reset the attention with a steering wheel touch and Supercruise would
disengage. Like I was communicating to the car, I'm like, look, I am here, I am paying attention.
Why are you really going to force me to disengage? And it did. So it's a constant
conversation with the user. And yeah, there's no way to ship a system like this if you can OTA.
We're shipping a new one every month. Sometimes we balance it with our users on Discord. Sometimes
we make the driver monitoring a little more aggressive and people complain. Sometimes they
don't. We want it to be as aggressive as possible where people don't complain and it doesn't feel
intrusive. So being able to update the system over the air is an essential component. I mean,
that's probably, to me, that is the biggest innovation of Tesla, that it made it. People
realize that over the air updates is essential. Yeah. Was that not obvious from the iPhone?
The iPhone was the first real product that OTAed, I think. Was it? Actually, that's brilliant.
You're right. I mean, the game consoles used to not, right? The game consoles were maybe the
second thing that did. Well, I didn't really think about it. One of the amazing features
of a smartphone isn't just like the touchscreen isn't the thing. It's the ability to constantly
update. Yeah. It gets better. It gets better. I love my iOS 14. Yeah. One thing that I probably
disagree with you on driver monitoring is you said that it's easy. I mean, you tend to say
stuff is easy. I guess you said it's easy relative to the external perception problem there.
Can you elaborate why you think it's easy? Feature engineering works for driver monitoring. Feature
engineering does not work for the external. So human faces are not, human faces and the movement
of human faces and head and body is not as variable as the external environment? Yeah.
Yeah. Because you're intuition. Yes. And there's another big difference as well.
Your reliability of a driver monitoring system doesn't actually need to be that high.
The uncertainty, if you have something that's detecting whether the human's paying attention
and it only works 92% of the time, you're still getting almost all the benefit of that
because the human, you're training the human. You're dealing with a system that's
really helping you out. It's a conversation. It's not the external thing where guess what?
If you swerve into a tree, you swerve into a tree. You get no margin for error there.
Yeah. I think that's really well put. I think that's the right, exactly the place where
comparing to the external perception and the control problem, driver monitoring is easier
because the bar for success is much lower. Yeah. But I still think the human face
is more complicated actually than the external environment. But for driving, you don't give a
damn. I don't need something that complicated to have to communicate the idea to the human
that I want to communicate, which is, yo, system might mess up here. You got to pay attention.
Yeah. See, that's my love and fascination is the human face. And it feels like this is
a nice place to create products that create an experience in the car. It feels like there should
be more richer experiences in the car. That's an opportunity for something like AMAI or just any
kind of system like a Tesla or any of the autonomous vehicle companies is because software,
there's much more sensors and so much is running on software and you're doing machine learning anyway,
there's an opportunity to create totally new experiences that we're not even anticipating.
You don't think so? No. You think it's a box that gets you from A to B and you want to do it chill?
Yeah. I mean, I think as soon as we get to level three on highways, okay, enjoy your candy crush,
enjoy your Hulu, enjoy your, you know, whatever, whatever. Sure, you get this, you can look at
screens basically versus right now, what do you have? Music and audiobooks. So level three is
where you can kind of disengage and stretch this of time. Well, you think level three is possible?
Like on the highway going 400 miles and you can just go to sleep? Oh yeah, sleep. So again,
I think it's really all on a spectrum. I think that being able to use your phone while you're on
the highway and like this all being okay and being aware that the car might alert you and you have
five seconds to basically. So the five second thing is that you think it's possible? Yeah,
I think it is. Oh yeah. Not in all scenarios. Right. Some scenarios it's not. It's the whole
risk thing that you mentioned is nice is to be able to estimate like how risk is this situation.
That's really important to understand. One other thing you mentioned comparing comma and autopilot
is that something about the haptic feel of the way comma controls the car when things are uncertain,
like it behaves a little bit more uncertain when things are uncertain. That's kind of an
interesting point. And then autopilot is much more confident always, even when it's uncertain,
until it runs into trouble. That's a funny thing. I actually mentioned that to Elon,
I think, and then the first time we talked he was inviting is like communicating uncertainty.
I guess comma doesn't really communicate uncertainty explicitly. It communicates it
through haptic feel. Like what's the role of communicating uncertainty, do you think?
We do some stuff explicitly. We do detect the lanes when you're on the highway,
and we'll show you how many lanes we're using to drive with. You can look at where it thinks
the lanes are. You can look at the path. We want to be better about this. We're actually hiring.
We want to hire some new UI people. UI people. You mentioned this because it's such a UI problem
too. We have a great designer now, but we need people who are just going to build this and
debug these UIs, QT people. QT. Is that what the UI has done with this QT?
Moving. The new UI is in QT. C++, QT?
Tesla uses it too. We had some React stuff in there.
React.js or just React. React has its own language, right?
React Native. React is a JavaScript framework. It's all based on JavaScript, but I like C++.
QT. What do you think about Dojo with Tesla and their foray into what appears to be
specialized hardware for training on that? I guess it's something, maybe you can correct me,
for my shallow looking at it. It seems like something that Google did with TPUs,
but specialized for driving data. I don't think it's specialized for driving data.
QT. It's just legit, just TPU. They want to go the Apple way. Basically,
everything required in the chain is done in-house.
QT. You have a problem right now. This is one of my concerns. I really would like to see
somebody deal with this. If anyone out there is doing it, I'd like to help them if I can.
You basically have two options right now to train. Your options are Nvidia or Google.
QT. Google is not even an option. Their TPUs are only available in Google Cloud.
Google has absolutely onerous terms of service restrictions. They may have changed it,
but back in Google's terms of service, it said explicitly you are not allowed to use
Google Cloud ML for training autonomous vehicles or for doing anything that competes with Google
without Google's prior written permission. Google is not a platform company.
I wouldn't touch TPUs with a 10-foot pole. That leaves you with the monopoly.
QT. Nvidia?
QT. Nvidia.
QT. You're not a fan of?
QT. Well, look, I was a huge fan of 2016 Nvidia. Jensen came sat in the car. Cool guy
when the stock was $30 a share. Nvidia stock has skyrocketed. I witnessed a real change
in who was in management over there in 2018. Now they are, let's exploit, let's take every
dollar we possibly can out of this ecosystem. Let's charge $10,000 for A100s because we know
we got the best share in the game. Let's charge $10,000 for an A100 when it's really not that
different from $3080, which is $699. The margins that they are making off of those high-end chips
are so high that I think they're shooting themselves in the foot just from a business
perspective because there's a lot of people talking like me now who are like, somebody's
got to take Nvidia down. Where they could dominate, Nvidia could be the new Intel.
QT. Yeah, to be inside everything essentially. Yet the winners in certain spaces like in
autonomous driving, the winners, only the people who are like desperately falling back and trying
to catch up and have a ton of money like the big automakers are the ones interested in partnering
with Nvidia. Jensen. Oh, and I think a lot of those things are going to fall through. If I were
in Nvidia, sell chips. Sell chips at a reasonable markup. QT. To everybody. Jensen. To everybody.
QT. Without any restrictions. Jensen. Without any restrictions. Intel did this. Look at Intel.
They had a great long run. Nvidia is trying to turn their, they're like trying to productize
their chips way too much. They're trying to extract way more value than they can sustainably.
Sure. You can do it tomorrow. Is it going to up your share price? Sure. If you're one of those
CEOs, it's like, how much can I strip mine in this company? And that's what's weird about it too.
Like the CEO is the founder. It's the same guy. I mean, I still think Jensen's a great guy.
It is great. Why do this? You have a choice. You have a choice right now. Are you trying to cash
out? Are you trying to buy a yacht? If you are, fine. But if you're trying to be the next huge
semiconductor company, sell chips. Well, the interesting thing about Jensen is he is a big
vision guy. So he has a plan like for 50 years down the road. So it makes me wonder like...
How does price gouging fit into it? Yeah. How does that fit? It doesn't seem to make sense of the
plan. I worry that he's listening to the wrong people. Yeah. That's the sense I have too sometimes
because I, despite everything, I think Nvidia is an incredible company. Well, one, I'm deeply
grateful to Nvidia for the products they've created in the past. Me too. And so...
The 1080 Ti was a great GPU. Still have a lot of them.
Still is. Yeah. But at the same time, it just feels like...
It feels like you don't want to put all your stock in Nvidia. And so the Elon is doing...
What Tesla is doing with autopilot and Dojo is the Apple way. Because they're not going to share
Dojo with George Hott's. I know. They should sell that chip. Oh, they should sell that.
Even their accelerator. The accelerator that's in all the cars, the 30 watt one.
Sell it. Why not? So open it up. Make me... Why does Tesla have to be a car company?
Well, if you sell the chip, here's what you get. Yeah. Makes the money out of the chips. It doesn't
take away from your chip. You're going to make some money, free money. And also the world is going
to build an ecosystem of tooling for you. All right. You're not going to have to fix the bug
in your 10H layer. Someone else already did. Well, the question... That's an interesting question.
I mean, that's the question Steve Jobs asked. That's the question Elon Musk is
perhaps asking is, do you want Tesla stuff inside other vehicles inside? Potentially inside like
iRobot Vacuum Cleaner? Yeah. I think you should decide where your advantages are. I'm not saying
Tesla should start selling battery packs to automakers because battery packs to automakers,
they're straight up in competition with you. If I were Tesla, I'd keep the battery technology
totally as far as we make batteries. But the thing about the Tesla TPU is anybody can build that.
It's just a question of, are you willing to spend the money? It could be a huge source of revenue
potentially. Are you willing to spend $100 million? Anyone can build it. And someone will.
And a bunch of companies now are starting trying to build AI accelerators. Somebody's
going to get the idea right. And hopefully they don't get greedy because they'll just lose to
the next guy who finally... And then eventually the Chinese are going to make knockoff and video
chips and that's... From your perspective, I don't know if you're also paying attention to
Stan Tesla for a moment. Elon Musk has talked about a complete rewrite of the neural net that
they're using that seems to... Again, I'm half paying attention, but it seems to involve basically
a kind of integration of all the sensors to where it's a four-dimensional view. You have a 3D model
of the world over time and then you can... I think it's done both for the... Actually,
so the neural network is able to in a more holistic way deal with the world and make predictions
and so on, but also to make the annotation task more easier. You can annotate the world in one
place and they kind of distribute itself across the sensors and across the different...
Like the hundreds of tests that are involved in the hydranet. What are your thoughts about this
rewrite? Is it just like some details that are kind of obvious, there are steps that should be taken
or is there something fundamental that could challenge your idea that end-to-end
is the right solution? We're in the middle of a big review right now as well. We haven't shipped a
new model in a bit. Of what kind? We're going from 2D to 3D. Right now, all our stuff like, for
example, when the car pitches back, the lane lines also pitch back because we're assuming the flat
world hypothesis, the new models do not do this. The new models output everything in 3D.
But there's still no annotation, so the 3D is more about the output.
We have Zs and everything. We've... Zs. We added Zs. We unified a lot of stuff as well.
We switched from TensorFlow to PyTorch. My understanding of what Tesla's thing is,
is that their annotator now annotates across the time dimension.
I mean, cute. Why are you building an annotator? I find their entire pipeline.
I find your vision, I mean, the vision of end-to-end very compelling. But I also like the
engineering of the data engine that they've created. In terms of supervised learning
pipelines, that thing is damn impressive. You're basically the idea is that you have
hundreds of thousands of people that are doing data collection for you by doing their experience.
So that's kind of similar to the Kama AI model. And you're able to mine that data based on the
kind of education you need. I think it's harder to do in the end-to-end learning.
The mining of the right edge cases. That's what feature engineering is actually really powerful
because us humans are able to do this kind of mining a little better. But yeah, there's obvious,
as we know, there's obvious constraints and limitations to that idea.
Carpathian just tweeted, he's like, you get really interesting insights if you sort your
validation set by loss and look at the highest loss examples. So yeah, we have a little data
engine-like thing. We're training a Sagnat. Anyway, it's not fancy, it's just like, okay,
train the new Sagnat, run it on 100,000 images, and now take the thousand with highest loss,
select 100 of those by human, put those, get those ones labeled, retrain, do it again.
So it's a much less well-written data engine. And yeah, you can take these things really far.
And it is impressive engineering. And if you truly need supervised data for a problem,
yeah, things like data engine are at the high end of what is attention? Is a human paying
attention? I mean, we're going to probably build something that looks like data engine to push
our driver monitoring further. But for driving itself, you have it all annotated beautifully
by what the human does. Yeah, that's interesting. I mean, that applies to driver attention as well.
Do you want to detect the eyes? Do you want to detect blinking and pupil movement?
Do you want to detect all the like face alignments, the landmark detection and so on,
and then doing kind of reasoning based on that? Or do you want to take the entirety of the face
over time and do end to end? I mean, it's obvious that eventually you have to do end to end with
some calibration, some fixes and so on. But it's like, I don't know when that's the right move.
Even if it's end to end, there actually is, there is no kind of, you have to supervise that with
humans. Whether a human is paying attention or not is a completely subjective judgment.
Like you can try to like automatically do it with some stuff, but you don't have.
If I record a video of a human, I don't have true annotations anywhere in that video.
The only way to get them is with other humans labeling it really.
Well, I don't know. If you think deeply about it, you might be able to, depending on the task,
you might be able to discover self-anitating things like, you can look at like steering
wheel reverse or something like that. You can discover little moments of lapse of attention.
That's where psychology comes in. Is there an indicator? Because you have so much data to look
at. So you might be able to find moments when there's just inattention that even with smartphone,
if you want to take smartphone use, you can start to zoom in. I mean, that's the gold mine,
sort of the comma AI. I mean, Tesla is doing this too, right? They're doing
annotation based on like self-supervised learning too. It's just a small part of the
entire picture. That's kind of the challenge of solving a problem in machine learning if you
can discover self-anitating parts of the problem, right? Our driver monitoring team is half a person
right now. Half a person. You know, once we have... Scale to a full... Once we have two,
three people on that team, I definitely want to look at self-anitating stuff for attention.
Let's go back for a sec to a comma. For people who are curious to try it out,
how do you install a comma in say a 2020 Toyota Corolla? Or like, what are the cars that are
supported? What are the cars that you recommend? And what does it take? You have a few videos out,
but maybe through words, can you explain what's it take to actually install a thing?
So we support... I think it's 91 cars. 91 makes models. We get to 100 this year.
Nice. The 2020 Corolla, great choice. The 2020 Sonata, it's using the stock longitudinal. It's
using just our lateral control, but it's a very refined car. Their longitudinal control is not
bad at all. So yeah, Corolla, Sonata. Or if you're willing to get your hands a little dirty and
look in the right places on the internet, the Honda Civic is great, but you're going to have to
install a modified EPS firmware in order to get a little bit more torque. And I can't help you
with that. Comma does not efficiently endorse that, but we have been doing it. We didn't ever release
it. We waited for someone else to discover it. And then, you know... And you have a Discord server
where people... There's a very active developer community, I suppose. So depending on the level
of experimentation you're willing to do, that's a community. If you just want to buy it and you
have a supported car, it's 10 minutes to install. There's YouTube videos. It's IKEA furniture level.
If you can set up a table from IKEA, you can install a Comma 2 in your supported car,
and it will just work. Now you're like, oh, but I want this high-end feature or I want to fix this
bug. Okay, well, welcome to the developer community. So what... If I wanted to... This is something I
asked you offline, like a few months ago. If I wanted to run my own code to... So use Comma as a
platform and try to run something like OpenPilot, what does it take to do that?
So there's a toggle in the settings called enable SSH. And if you toggle that, you can SSH into
your device. You can modify the code. You can upload whatever code you want to it. There's a whole
lot of people. So about 60% of people are running stock Comma. About 40% of people are running Forks.
And there's a community of... There's a bunch of people who maintain these Forks. And these Forks
support different cars or they have different toggles. We try to keep away from the toggles
that are disabled driver monitoring. But some people might want that kind of thing. And yeah,
you can... It's your car. It's your... I'm not here to tell you. We have some... We ban... If you're
trying to subvert safety features, you're banned from our Discord. I don't want anything to do with
you. But there's some Forks doing that. Got it. So you encourage responsible Forking. Yeah. Yeah,
we encourage... Some people... Yeah, some people... Like there's Forks that will do... Some people just
like having a lot of readouts on the UI. Like a lot of flashing numbers. So there's Forks that do
that. Some people don't like the fact that it disengages when you press the gas pedal. There's
Forks that disable that. Got it. Now, the stock experience is what like... So it does both lane
keeping and longitudinal control altogether. So it's not separate like it is an autopilot.
No. So, okay. Some cars, we use the stock longitudinal control. We don't do the longitudinal
control in all the cars. Some cars, the ACCs are pretty good in the cars. It's the lane
keep that's atrocious in anything except for autopilot and supercruise. But you just turn it on
and it works. What does disengagement look like? Yeah. So we have... I mean, I'm very concerned
about mode confusion. I've experienced it on supercruise and autopilot where like autopilot
disengages. I don't realize that the ACC is still on. The lead car moves slightly over and then the
Tesla accelerates to like whatever my set speed is super fast and like what's going on here.
We have engaged and disengaged. And this is similar to my understanding. I'm not a pilot,
but my understanding is either the pilot is in control or the copilot is in control.
And we have the same kind of transition system. Either open pilot is engaged or open pilot is
disengaged. Engage with cruise control, disengage with either gas break or cancel.
Let's talk about money. What's the business strategy for karma?
Profitable. Well, you did it. So congratulations. What... So it's basically selling, we should
say, karma costs a thousand bucks, comma two. Two hundred for the interface to the car as well.
It's 1200. I'll send that. Nobody's usually upfront like this. You gotta add the tack on, right?
I love it. I'm not gonna lie to you. Trust me, it will add $1,200 of value to your life.
Yes, it's still super cheap. 30 days, no questions asked, money back guarantee,
and prices are only going up. If there ever is future hardware, it could cost a lot more than
$1,200. So comma three is in the works. It could be. All I will say is future hardware is going
to cost a lot more than the current hardware. Yeah. The people that use... The people I've
spoken with that use comma, they use open pilot, they... At first, they use it a lot.
So people that use it, they fall in love with it. Oh, our retention rate is insane.
It's a good sign. Yeah. It's a really good sign. 70% of comma two buyers are daily active users.
Yeah, it's amazing. Oh, also, we don't plan on stopping selling the comma two.
So whatever you create that's beyond comma two, it would be potentially a phase shift.
It's so much better that... You could use comma two and you can use comma whatever.
Depends what you want. It's 3.41, 42. Yeah. Auto pilot, hardware one versus hardware two.
The comma two is kind of like hardware one. Got it. You can still use both. Got it.
I think I heard you talk about retention rate with the BR headsets that the average is just once.
I mean, it's such a fascinating way to think about technology. And this is a really,
really good sign. And the other thing that people say about comma is they can't believe
they're getting this 4,000 bucks. It seems like some kind of steal. But in terms of long-term
business strategies, it's currently in 1,000 plus cars. 1,200. More. So yeah,
uh, daily is about 2,000. Weekly is about 2,500. Monthly is over 3,000.
Wow. We've grown a lot since we last talked.
Is the goal... Can we talk crazy for a second? I mean, what's the goal to overtake Tesla?
Let's talk... Okay, so... I mean, Android did overtake iOS.
That's exactly it, right? So... Yeah.
They did it. I actually don't know the timeline of that one. But let's talk...
Because everything is in alpha now. The autopilot, you could argue, is in alpha in terms of
towards the big mission of autonomous driving, right? And so what... Yeah,
it's your goal to overtake millions of cars, essentially. Of course. Where would it stop?
Like, it's open-source software. It might not be millions of cars with a piece of comma hardware.
But yeah, I think OpenPilot at some point will cross over autopilot in users,
just like Android crossed over iOS. How does Google make money from Android?
It's complicated. Their own devices make money.
Google... Google makes money by just kind of having you on the internet.
Yes. Google Search is built in. Gmail is built in.
Android is just a shield for the rest of Google's ecosystem kind.
Yeah, but the problem is, Android is not... It's a brilliant thing. I mean,
Android arguably changed the world. So there you go. You can feel good ethically speaking.
But as a business strategy, it's questionable.
It's so hardware.
So hardware. I mean, it took Google a long time to come around to it,
but they are now making money on the Pixel.
You're not about money. You're more about winning.
Yeah, of course.
But if only 10% of OpenPilot devices come from comma AI...
They still make a lot.
That is still yes. That is a ton of money for our company.
But can't somebody create a better comma using OpenPilot?
Or are you basically saying we'll out-compete them?
We'll out-compete you.
Is... Can you create a better Android phone than the Google Pixel?
Right.
I mean, you can, but like, you know...
I love that. So you're confident, like, you know what the hell you're doing.
Yeah.
It's competence and merit.
I mean, our money... Yeah, our money comes from... We're a consumer electronics company.
Yeah.
And put it this way. So we sold... We sold like 3,000 comma twos.
2,500 right now.
Okay. We're probably going to sell 10,000 units next year.
10,000 units. Even just $1,000 a unit. Okay. We're at $10 million in revenue.
Get that up to $100,000. Maybe double the price of the unit.
Now we're talking like $200 million revenue.
We're talking like a series.
Yeah, actually making money.
One of the rare semi-autonomous or autonomous vehicle companies that are actually making
money. Yeah.
You know, if you have... If you look at a model,
when we were just talking about this yesterday, if you look at a model and like you're testing,
like you're A-B testing your model, and if you're one branch of the A-B test,
the losses go down very fast in the first five epochs.
That model is probably going to converge to something considerably better than the one
where the losses are going down slower. Why do people think this is going to stop?
Why do people think one day there's going to be a great like,
well, Waymo's eventually going to surpass you guys?
Well, they're not.
Do you see like a world where like a Tesla or a car like a Tesla would be able to basically
press a button and you like switch to open pilot, you know, you load in?
No. So I think, so first off, I think that we may surpass Tesla in terms of users.
I do not think we're going to surpass Tesla ever in terms of revenue.
I think Tesla can capture a lot more revenue per user than we can.
But this mimics the Android iOS model exactly.
There may be more Android devices, but you know,
there's a lot more iPhones than Google pixels.
So I think there'll be a lot more Tesla cars sold than pieces of comma hardware.
And then as far as a Tesla owner being able to switch to open pilot,
does iOS, does iPhones run Android?
No, but you can if you really want to do it, but it doesn't really make sense.
Like it's not.
It doesn't make sense.
Who cares?
What about if a large company like automakers for GM Toyota came to George
Hotz or on the tech space, Amazon, Facebook, Google came with a large pile of cash?
Would you consider being purchased?
Do you see that as a one possible?
Not seriously, no.
I would probably see how much shit they'll entertain for me.
And if they're willing to jump through a bunch of my hoops, then maybe.
But no, not the way that M&A works today.
I mean, we've been approached.
And I laugh in these people's faces.
I'm like, are you kidding?
Yeah, because it's so demeaning.
The M&A people are so demeaning to companies.
They treat the startup world as their innovation ecosystem.
And they think that I'm cool with going along with that so I can have some of their scam fake
Fed dollars, Fed coin.
What am I going to do with more Fed coin, Fed coin, man?
I love that.
So that's the cool thing about podcasting actually is people criticize.
I don't know if you're familiar with Spotify giving Joe Rogan 100 million.
I'd talk about that.
And they respect, despite all the shit that people are talking about Spotify,
people understand that podcasters like Joe Rogan know what the hell they're doing.
So they give them money and say, just do what you do.
And the equivalent for you would be like, George, do what the hell you do because you're good at it.
Try not to murder too many people.
There's some kind of common sense things like just don't go on a weird rampage of...
Yeah, it comes down to what companies I could respect.
You know, could I respect GM? Never.
No, I couldn't.
I mean, could I respect like a Hyundai?
More so.
Right?
That's a lot closer.
Toyota?
What's your...
Nah, no, Korean is the way.
I think that the Japanese, the Germans, the US, they're all too...
They all think they're too great to be honest.
What about the tech companies?
Apple?
Apple is of the tech companies that I could respect.
Apple is the closest.
Yeah.
I mean, I could never...
It would be ironic.
It would be ironic if Kama AI is acquired by Apple.
I mean, Facebook.
Look, I quit Facebook 10 years ago because I didn't respect the business model.
Google has declined so fast in the last five years.
What are your thoughts about Waymo and its present and its future?
Let me start by saying something nice,
which is I've visited them a few times and I've written in their cars,
and the engineering that they're doing, both the research and the actual development,
and the engineering they're doing and the scale they're actually achieving
by doing it all themselves, is really impressive.
And the balance of safety and innovation.
And the cars work really well for the routes they drive.
Like, they drive fast, which was very surprising to me.
Like, it drives the speed limit, or faster than the speed limit, it goes.
And it works really damn well, and the interface is nice.
And channel Arizona, yeah.
Yeah, and channel Arizona is in a very specific environment.
It gives me enough material in my mind to push back
against the madmen of the world, like George Hutz, to be like...
Because you kind of imply there's zero probability they're going to win.
Yeah.
And after I've written in it, to me it's not zero.
Oh, it's not for technology reasons.
Bureaucracy?
No, it's worse than that.
It's actually for product reasons, I think.
Oh, you think they're just not capable of creating an amazing product?
No, I think that the product that they're building doesn't make sense.
So, a few things.
You say the Waymo's are fast.
Benchmark a Waymo against a competent Uber driver.
Right.
The Uber driver's faster.
It's not even about speed.
It's the thing you said.
It's about the experience of being stuck at a stop sign.
Because pedestrians are crossing non-stop.
I like when my Uber driver doesn't come to a full stop at the stop sign, you know?
And so, let's say the Waymo's are 20% slower than an Uber, right?
You can argue that they're going to be cheaper.
And I argue that users already have the choice to trade off money for speed.
It's called Uber Pool.
I think it's like 15% of rides at Uber pools.
Right.
Users are not willing to trade off money for speed.
So, the whole product that they're building is not going to be competitive
with traditional ride-sharing networks.
Right.
Like, and also, whether there's profit to be made depends entirely on one company having a monopoly.
I think that the level for autonomous ride-sharing vehicles market is going to look a lot like
the scooter market if even the technology does come to exist, which I question.
Who's doing well in that market?
Yeah.
It's a race to the bottom, you know.
Well, it could be closer like an Uber and a Lyft where it's just a one or two players.
Well, the scooter people have given up trying to market scooters as a practical means of
transportation and they're just like, they're super fun to ride.
Look at wheels.
I love those things and they're great on that front.
Yeah.
But from an actual transportation product perspective, I do not think scooters are viable
and I do not think level four autonomous cars are viable.
If you, let's play a fun experiment.
If you ran, let's do Tesla and let's do Waymo.
All right.
If Elon Musk took a vacation for a year, he just said, screw it.
I'm going to go live on an island, no electronics.
And the board decides that we need to find somebody to run the company
and they decide that you should run the company for a year.
How do you run Tesla differently?
I wouldn't change much.
Do you think they're on the right track?
I wouldn't change.
I mean, I'd have some minor changes.
But even my debate with Tesla about end-to-end versus segnets, that's just software.
Who cares?
It's not like you're doing something terrible with segnets.
You're probably building something that's at least going to help you debug the end-to-end
system a lot.
It's very easy to transition from what they have to an end-to-end kind of thing.
Right.
And then I presume you would, in the Model Y or maybe in the Model 3,
start adding driver sensing with infrared.
Yes, I would add infrared lights right away to those cars.
And start collecting that data and do all that kind of stuff.
Yeah.
Very much.
I think they're already kind of doing it.
It's an incredibly minor change.
If I actually were CEO of Tesla first off, I'd be horrified that I wouldn't be able
to do a better job as Elon.
And then I would try to understand the way he's done things before.
You would also have to take over as Twitter.
God, I don't tweet.
Yeah, what's your Twitter situation?
Why are you so quiet on Twitter?
Oh, I mean.
I says Dukama is like, what's your social network presence like?
Because on Instagram, you do live streams.
You understand the music of the internet, but you don't always fully engage into it.
Part-time.
Why do you still have a Twitter?
Yeah, I mean, Instagram is a pretty place.
Instagram is a beautiful place.
It glorifies beauty.
I like Instagram's values as a network.
Twitter glorifies conflict, glorifies like taking shots of people.
And it's like, Twitter and Donald Trump are perfect for each other.
So Tesla is on the right track in your view.
Okay, so let's really try this experiment.
If you ran Waymo, let's say they're, I don't know if you agree,
but they seem to be at the head of the pack of the kind of...
What would you call that approach?
It's not necessarily lighter-based because it's not about lighter.
Level four robotaxi.
Level four robotaxi all in before making any revenue.
So they're probably at the head of the pack.
If you said, hey, George, can you please run this company for a year?
How would you change it?
I would go, I would get Anthony Lewandowski out of jail,
and I would put him in charge of the company.
Let's try to break that apart.
You want to destroy the company by doing that?
Or do you mean you like renegade style thinking that pushes,
that throws away bureaucracy and goes to first principle thinking?
What do you mean by that?
I think Anthony Lewandowski is a genius,
and I think he would come up with a much better idea
of what to do with Waymo than me.
So you mean that unironically.
He is a genius.
Oh, yes. Oh, absolutely.
Without a doubt.
I mean, I'm not saying there's no shortcomings,
but in the interactions I've had with him, yeah.
He's also willing to take, like,
who knows what he would do with Waymo?
I mean, he's also out there, like far more out there than I am.
Yeah, his big risks.
What do you make of him?
I was going to talk to him in his pockets,
and I was going back and forth.
I'm such a gullible naive human, like I see the best in people.
And I slowly started to realize that there might be some people out there
that, like, have multiple faces to the world.
They're, like, deceiving and dishonest.
I still refuse to, like, I just, I trust people,
and I don't care if I get hurt by it,
but, like, you know, sometimes you have to be a little bit careful,
especially platform-wise and podcast-wise.
What am I supposed to think?
So you think, you think he's a good person?
Oh, I don't know.
I don't really make moral judgments.
And it's difficult to...
Oh, I mean this about the Waymo.
Actually, I mean that whole idea, very non-ironically,
about what I would do.
The problem with putting me in charge of Waymo
is Waymo is already $10 billion in the haul, right?
Whatever idea Waymo does, look,
comma's profitable, comma's raised $8.1 million.
That's small, you know, that's small money.
Like, I can build a reasonable consumer electronics company
and succeed wildly at that
and still never be able to pay back Waymo's $10 billion.
So I think the basic idea with Waymo,
well, forget the $10 billion because they have some backing,
but your basic thing is, like,
what can we do to start making some money?
Well, no, I mean, my bigger idea is, like,
whatever the idea is that's going to save Waymo,
I don't have it.
It's going to have to be a big risk idea,
and I cannot think of a better person
than Anthony Lewandowski to do it.
So that is completely what I would do with CEO of Waymo.
I've called myself a transitionary CEO.
Do everything I can to fix that situation up.
Transitionary CEO, yeah.
Yeah.
Because I can't do it, right?
Like, I can't, I can't, I mean,
I can talk about how what I really want to do
is just apologize for all those corny, you know,
ad campaigns and be like,
here's the real estate of the technology.
Yeah, that's, like, I have several criticism.
I'm a little bit more bullish on Waymo than you seem to be,
but one criticism I have is it went into corny mode too early.
Like, it's still a startup.
It hasn't delivered on anything.
So it should be, like, more renegade
and show off the engineering that they're doing,
which just can be impressive,
as opposed to doing these weird commercials of, like,
your friendly car company.
I mean, that's my biggest,
my biggest snipe at Waymo was always,
that guy's a paid actor.
That guy's not a Waymo user.
He's a paid actor.
Look here, I found his call sheet.
Do kind of like what SpaceX is doing with the rocket launch
is just get, put the nerds up front,
put the engineers up front,
and just, like, show failures too, just...
I love SpaceX's, yeah.
Yeah, the thing that they're doing is right,
and it just feels like the right...
But we're all so excited to see them succeed.
Yeah.
I can't wait to see Waymo fail, you know?
Like, you lie to me.
I want you to fail.
You tell me the truth.
You be honest with me.
I want you to succeed.
Yeah.
Yeah, and that requires the renegade CEO, right?
I'm with you.
I still have a little bit of faith in Waymo
for the renegade CEO to step forward, but...
It's not, it's not John Kraft.
Yeah.
It's, you can't...
It's not Chris Omston.
And those people may be very good at certain things.
Yeah.
But they're not renegades.
Yeah, because these companies are fundamentally,
even though we're talking about billion dollars,
all these crazy numbers,
they're still, like, early-stage startups.
I mean, I just, if you are pre-revenue
and you've raised $10 billion, I have no idea.
Like, this just doesn't work.
You know, it's against everything Silicon Valley.
Where's your minimum viable product?
You know, where's your users?
Where's your growth numbers?
This is traditional Silicon Valley.
Why do you not apply it to what you think
you're too big to fail already?
Like...
How do you think autonomous driving will change society?
So the mission is, for comma, to solve self-driving.
Do you have, like, a vision of the world of how it'll be different?
Is it as simple as A to B transportation?
Or is there, like...
Because these are robots.
It's not about autonomous driving in and of itself.
It's what the technology enables.
It's, I think it's the coolest applied AI problem.
I like it because it has a clear path
to monetary value.
But as far as that being the thing that changes the world...
I mean, no.
Like, there's cute things we're doing in comma.
Like, who'd have thought you could stick a phone
on the windshield and it'll drive.
But, like, really the product that you're building
is not something that people were not capable
of imagining 50 years ago.
So, no, it doesn't change the world on that front.
Could people have imagined the Internet 50 years ago?
Only true genius visionaries.
Everyone could have imagined autonomous cars 50 years ago.
It's like a car, but I don't drive it.
See, I have the sense, and I told you, like,
I'm my long-term dream is robots with whom you have deep connections.
And there's different trajectories towards that.
And I've been thinking of launching a startup.
I see autonomous vehicles as a potential trajectory to that.
That's not where the direction I would like to go.
But I also see Tesla or even Kamii like pivoting
into robotics broadly defined at some stage.
In the way, like you're mentioning, the Internet didn't expect.
Let's solve, you know, when I say a comma about this.
We could talk about this, but let's solve self-driving cars first.
Gotta stay focused on the mission.
You're not too big to fail.
For however much I think comm is winning, like, no, no, no, no.
You're winning when you solve level five self-driving cars.
And until then, you haven't won and won.
And, you know, again, you want to be arrogant in the face of other people?
Great. You want to be arrogant in the face of nature?
You're an idiot.
Right. Stay mission focused, brilliantly put.
Like I mentioned, thinking of launching a startup,
I've been considering, actually, before COVID,
I've been thinking of moving to San Francisco.
Oh, I wouldn't go there.
So why is, well, and now I'm thinking about potentially Austin.
And we're in San Diego now.
San Diego, come here.
So why, what, I mean, you're such an interesting human.
You've launched so many successful things.
What, why San Diego?
What do you recommend?
Why not San Francisco?
Have you thought, so in your case,
San Diego with Qualcomm and Staff Dragon, I mean, that's an amazing combination.
But that wasn't really why.
That wasn't the why?
No. I mean, Qualcomm was an afterthought.
Qualcomm was, it was a nice thing to think about.
It's like you can have a tech company here and a good one.
I mean, you know, I like Qualcomm, but no.
Well, so why is San Diego better than San Francisco?
Why does San Francisco suck?
Well, so, okay.
So first off, we all kind of said, like, we want to stay in California,
people like the ocean, you know, California for its flaws.
It's like a lot of the flaws of California are not necessarily California as a whole,
and they're much more San Francisco specific.
San Francisco, so I think first-tier cities in general have stopped wanting growth.
Well, you have like in San Francisco, you know, the voting class always
votes to not build more houses because they own all the houses and they're like, well,
you know, once people have figured out how to vote themselves more money, they're going to do it.
It is so insanely corrupt.
It is not balanced at all, like political party-wise.
You know, it's a one-party city.
And for all the discussion of diversity, it stops lacking real diversity of thought,
of background, of approaches, of strategies, of ideas.
It's kind of a strange place that it's the loudest people about diversity
and the biggest lack of diversity.
I mean, that's what they say, right?
It's the projection.
Projection, yeah.
Yeah, it's interesting.
And even people in Silicon Valley telling me that's like high up people,
everybody is like, this is a terrible place.
It doesn't make sense.
I mean, and coronavirus is really what killed it.
San Francisco was the number one Exodus during coronavirus.
We still think San Diego is a good place to be.
Yeah, I mean, we'll see.
We'll see what happens with California a bit longer term.
Like, Austin's an interesting choice.
I wouldn't, I wouldn't, I don't have really anything bad to say about Austin
either except for the extreme heat in the summer, which, you know,
but that's like very on the surface, right?
I think as far as like an ecosystem goes, it's cool.
I personally love Colorado.
Colorado is great.
Yeah, I mean, you have these states that are, you know, like just way better run.
Um, California is, you know, it's especially San Francisco.
It's on its high horse and like, yeah.
Can I ask you for advice to me and to others about
what's the take to build a successful startup?
Oh, I don't know.
I haven't done that.
Talk to someone who did that.
Well, you know, this is like another book of yours that I'll buy for $67, I suppose.
Uh, so there's, um,
one of these days I'll sell out.
Yeah, that's right.
Jail breaks are going to be a dollar and books are going to be 67.
How I, uh, how I, you know, broke the iPhone by George Hots.
That's right.
How I jail broke the iPhone and you can do it.
You can't do it in 21 days.
That's right.
Oh God.
Okay.
I can't wait, but quite, so you have an introspective, you have built
a very unique company.
I mean, not, not you, but you and others.
But I don't know, um, there's no, there's nothing.
You have an interest, but you haven't really sat down and thought about like,
well, like if you and I were having a bunch of, we're having some beers
and you're seeing that I'm depressed and whatever I'm struggling.
There's no advice you can give.
Oh, I mean, more beer.
More beer.
Uh, uh, yeah.
I think it's all very like situation dependent.
Um, here's, okay.
If I can give a generic piece of advice, it's the technology always wins.
The better technology always wins and lying always loses.
Build technology and don't lie.
I'm with you.
I agree very much.
Long run.
Sure.
That's the long run.
And you know what?
The market can remain irrational longer than you can remain solvent.
True fact.
Well, this is, this is an interesting point because I ethically and just as a human believe that, um,
like, like hype and smoke and mirrors is not at any stage of the company is a good strategy.
I mean, there's some like, you know, PR magic kind of like, you know, you want a new product,
right?
If there's a call to action, if there's like a call to action like buy my new GPU,
look at it.
It takes up three slots and it's this big.
It's huge buy my GPU.
Yeah, that's great.
If you look at, you know, especially in that, in AI space broadly, but autonomous vehicles,
like you can raise a huge amount of money on nothing.
And the question to me is like, I'm against that.
I'll never be part of that.
I don't think I hope not willingly not.
But like, is there something to be said to, uh, essentially lying to raise money,
like fake it till you make it kind of thing?
I mean, this is Billy McFarlane the fire festival.
Like we all, we all experienced, uh, you know, what happens with that?
No, no, don't fake it till you make it.
Be honest and hope you make it the whole way.
The technology wins.
Right.
And like there is, I'm not used to like the anti-hype, you know, that's, that's
Slava KPSS reference, but, um, hype isn't necessarily bad.
I loved camping out for the iPhones.
You know, and as long as the hype is backed by like substance, as long as it's backed by
something I can actually buy and like it's real, then hype is great and it's a great feeling.
It's when the hype is backed by lies that it's a bad feeling.
I mean, a lot of people call Elon Musk a fraud.
How could he be a fraud?
I've noticed this, this kind of interesting effect, which is he does tend to over promise
and deliver, what's, what's the better way to phrase it?
Promise a timeline that he doesn't deliver on, he delivers much later on.
What do you think about that?
Because I do that.
I think that's a programmer thing too.
I do that as well.
You think that's a really bad thing to do or is that okay?
Oh, I think that's again, as long as like you're working toward it and you're going to deliver
on it and it's not too far off, right?
Yeah.
Right?
Like, like, you know, the whole, the whole autonomous vehicle thing, it's like,
I mean, I still think Tesla's on track to beat us.
I still think even with their, even with their missteps, they have advantages we don't have.
You know, Elon is better than me at like marshalling massive amounts of resources.
So, you know, I still think given the fact they're maybe making some wrong decisions,
they'll end up winning.
And like, it's fine to hype it if you're actually going to win, right?
If Elon says, look, we're going to be landing rockets back on Earth in a year and it takes four,
like, you know, he landed a rocket back on Earth and he was working toward it the whole time.
I think there's some amount of like, I think what it becomes wrong is if you know you're not
going to meet that deadline.
If you're lying.
Yeah.
That's brilliantly put.
Like, this is what people don't understand, I think.
Like, Elon believes everything he says.
He does.
As far as I can tell, he does.
And I detected that in myself too.
Like, if I, it's only bullshit if you're like conscious of yourself lying.
Yeah, I think so.
Yeah.
No, you can't take that to such an extreme, right?
Like, in a way, I think maybe Billy McFarland believed everything he said too.
Right.
That's how you start a cult and then everybody kills themselves.
Yeah.
Like, it's you need, you need, if there's like some factor on it, it's fine.
And you need some people to like, you know, keep you in check.
But like, if you deliver on most of the things you say and just the timelines are off, man.
It does piss people off though.
I wonder, but who cares in a long arc of history that people, everybody gets pissed off at the
people who succeed, which is one of the things that frustrates me about this world is they
don't celebrate the success of others.
Like, there's so many people that want Elon to fail.
It's so fascinating to me.
Like, what is wrong with you?
Like, so Elon Musk talks about like people at short, like they talk about financial,
but I think it's much bigger than the financials.
I've seen like the human factors community, they want, they want other people to fail.
What?
Like, even people, the harshest thing is like, you know, even people that like seem to really
hate Donald Trump, they want him to fail.
Yeah, I know.
Or like the other president, or they want Barack Obama to fail.
It's like.
We're all on the same boat, man.
It's weird, but I want that, I would love to inspire that part of the world to change because,
well, damn it, if the human species is going to survive, we can celebrate success.
Like, it seems like the efficient thing to do in this objective function that like we're all
striving for is to celebrate the ones that like figure out how to like do better at that
objective function as opposed to like dragging them down back into them, into the mud.
I think there is, this is the speech I always give about the commenters on hacker news.
So first off, something to remember about the internet in general,
is commenters are not representative of the population.
I don't comment on anything.
You know, commenters are representative of a certain sliver of the population.
And on hacker news, a common thing I'll say is when you'll see something that's like,
you know, promises to be wild out there and innovative.
There is some amount of, you know, checking them back to earth, but there's also some amount of,
if this thing succeeds, well, I'm 36 and I've worked at large tech companies my whole life.
They can't succeed because if they succeed, that would mean that I could have done something
different with my life, but we know that I could have, we know that I couldn't have,
and that's why they're going to fail.
And they have to root for them to fail to kind of maintain their world image.
Tune it out.
And they comment, well, it's hard.
So one of the things, one of the things I'm considering startup wise is to change that
because I think the, I think it's also a technology problem.
It's a platform problem.
I agree.
It's like, because the thing you said most people don't comment,
I think most people want to comment.
They just don't because it's all the assholes for commenting.
Exactly.
I don't want to be grouped in with them on that.
You don't want to be at a party where everyone's an asshole.
And so they, but that's a platform problem that's.
I can't believe what Reddit's become.
I can't believe the group think in Reddit comments.
There's a, Reddit is interesting one because they're subreddits.
And so you can still see, especially small subreddits that like,
that are little like havens of like joy and positivity and like deep, even disagreement,
but like nuanced discussion, but it's only like small little pockets.
But that's, that's emergent.
The platform is not helping that or herring that.
So I guess naturally something about the internet,
if you don't put in a lot of effort to encourage nuance and positive, good vibes,
it's naturally going to decline into chaos.
I would love to see someone do this well.
Yeah.
I think it's, yeah, very doable.
I think actually, so I feel like Twitter could be overthrown.
Yasho Bach talked about how like, if you have like and retweet,
like that's only positive wiring, right?
The only way to do anything like negative there is with a comment.
And that's like that asymmetry is what gives, you know,
Twitter its particular toxicness.
Whereas I find YouTube comments to be much better because YouTube comments have a,
have a, have an up and a down and they don't show the downloads.
Without getting into depth of this particular discussion,
the point is to explore possibilities and get a lot of data on it.
Because I mean, I could disagree with what you just said.
It's, it's on the point is it's unclear.
It's a, it hasn't been explored in a really rich way.
Like the, these questions of how to create platforms that encourage positivity.
Yeah.
I think it's a, it's a technology problem.
And I think we'll look back at Twitter as it is now.
Maybe it'll happen within Twitter, but most likely somebody overthrows them is,
we'll look back at Twitter and say, we can't believe we put up with this level of toxicity.
You need a different business model too.
Any, any social network that fundamentally has advertising as a business model,
this was in the social dilemma, which I didn't watch, but I liked it.
It's like, you know, there's always the, you know, you're the product, you're not the,
but they had a nuanced take on it that I really liked.
And it said, the product being sold is influence over you.
The product being sold is literally your, you know, influence on you.
That can't be, if that's your idea, okay.
Well, you know, guess what?
It can't not be toxic.
Yeah.
Maybe there's ways to spin it, like with, with giving a lot more control to the user
and transparency to see what is happening to them as opposed to in the shadows as possible.
But that can't be the primary source of,
But the users aren't, no one's going to use that.
It depends.
I think, I think that the, your, your not going to, you can't depend on self-awareness of the users.
It's a, it's another, it's a longer discussion because you can't depend on it, but
you can reward self-awareness.
Like if, for the ones who are willing to put in the work of self-awareness,
you can reward them and incentivize and perhaps be pleasantly surprised how many people
are willing to be self-aware on the internet.
Like we are in real life.
Like I'm putting in a lot of effort with you right now being self-aware about,
if I say something stupid or mean, I'll like look at your, like body language.
Like I'm putting in that effort, it's costly.
For an introvert, it's a great costly thing.
But on the internet, fuck it.
Like most people are like, I don't care if this hurts somebody.
I don't care if this is not interesting or if this is, yeah, the mean or whatever.
I think so much of the engagement today on the internet is so disingenuine too.
You're not doing this out of a genuine, this is what you think.
You're doing this just straight up to manipulate others.
Whether you're in, you just became an ad.
Yeah. Okay, let's talk about a fun topic, which is programming.
Here's another book idea for you.
Let me pitch.
What's your perfect programming setup?
So like, this by George Hott's.
So like what, listen, you're-
Give me a MacBook Air, sit me in a corner of a hotel room and you know I'll still have food.
So you really don't care.
You don't fetishize like multiple monitors, keyboard.
Those things are nice and I'm not going to say no to them,
but do they automatically unlock tons of productivity?
No, not at all.
I have definitely been more productive on a MacBook Air in a corner of a hotel room.
What about IDE?
So which operating system do you love?
What text editor do you use, IDE?
What, is there something that is like the perfect, if you could just say
the perfect productivity setup for George Hott's?
Doesn't matter.
Literally doesn't matter.
You know, I guess I code most of the time in VIM.
Like literally I'm using an editor from the 70s, you know, you didn't make anything better.
You know, okay, VS Code is nice for reading code.
There's a few things that are nice about it.
I think that there, you can build much better tools.
How like, Ida's X refs work way better than VS codes, why?
Yeah, actually, that's a good question.
Like why?
I still use, sorry, Emacs for most, I've actually never, I have to confess something dark.
So I've never used VIM.
I think maybe I'm just afraid that my life has been like a waste.
I'm so, I'm not, I'm not even gelical about Emacs.
This is how I feel about TensorFlow versus PyTorch.
Yeah.
Having just like, we've switched everything to PyTorch.
Now put months into the switch.
I have felt like I've wasted years on TensorFlow.
I can't believe it.
I can't believe how much better PyTorch is.
Yeah.
I've used Emacs in VIM.
Doesn't matter.
Yeah, still just my heart somehow.
I fell in love with Lisp.
I don't know why.
You can't, the heart wants what the heart wants.
I don't, I don't understand it, but it just connected with me.
Maybe it's the functional language at first I connected with.
Maybe it's because so many of the AI courses before the deep learning revolution were
taught with Lisp in mind.
I don't know.
I don't know what it is, but I'm stuck with it.
But at the same time, like why am I not using a modern ID for some of these programming?
I don't know.
They're not that much better.
I've used modern IDs there.
But at the same time, so like to just, we're not to disagree with you, but
like I like multiple monitors.
Like I have to do work on a laptop and it's a pain in the ass.
And also I'm addicted to the Kinesis weird keyboard.
You could see there.
Yeah, so you don't have any of that.
You can just be on a MacBook.
I mean, look at work.
I have three 24 inch monitors.
I have a happy hacking keyboard.
I have a razor death header mouse.
But it's not essential for you.
No.
Let's go to a day in the life of George Hots.
What is the perfect day productivity wise?
So we're not talking about like Hunter S. Thompson drugs and let's look at productivity.
What's the day look like on like hour by hour?
Is there any regularities that create a magical George Hots experience?
I can remember three days in my life and I remember these days vividly when I've gone
through kind of radical transformations to the way I think.
And what I would give, I would pay $100,000.
If I could have one of these days tomorrow, the days have been so impactful.
And one was first discovering LEIs of Yudkowsky on the Singularity and reading that stuff.
And like my mind was blown.
And the next was discovering the Hunter price and that AI is just compression.
Like finally understanding AIXI and what all of that was.
You know, I like read about it when I was 18, 19, I didn't understand it.
And then the fact that like lossless compression implies intelligence.
The day that I was shown that.
And then the third one is controversial.
The day I found a blog called Unqualified Reservations and read that.
And I was like, wait, which one is that?
That's what's the guy's name?
Curtis Garvin.
Yeah.
So many people tell me I'm supposed to talk to him.
Yeah, the day he sounds insane or brilliant, but insane or both.
I don't know.
The day I found that blog was another like this was during like like
Gamergate and kind of the run up to the 2016 election.
And I'm like, wow, okay, the world makes sense now.
This is like, I had a framework now to interpret this,
just like I got the framework for AI and a framework to interpret technological progress.
Like those days when I discovered these new frameworks or.
Oh, interesting.
So it's not about, but what was special about those days?
How did those days come to be?
Is it just you got lucky?
Like, sure.
I like, you just encountered a hunter prize on on hacking news or something like that.
Um, like what?
But you see, I don't think it's just, see, I don't think it's just that like,
I could have gotten lucky at any point.
I think that in a way.
You were ready at that moment.
Yeah, exactly.
To receive the information.
But is there some magic to the day today of like,
like eating breakfast?
And it's the mundane things.
Nah.
Nothing.
No, I drift through, I drift through life.
Without structure.
I drift through life hoping and praying that I will get another day like those days.
And there's nothing in particular you do to, uh, to be a receptacle
for another for day number four.
No, I didn't do anything to get the other ones.
So I don't think I have to really do anything now.
I took a month long trip to New York and
I mean, the Ethereum thing was the highlight of it, but the rest of it was pretty terrible.
I did a two week road trip and I got, I had to turn around.
I had to turn around, I'm driving in, uh, in Gunnison, Colorado.
I passed through Gunnison and, uh, the snow starts coming down.
There's a pass up there called Monarch Pass in order to get through to Denver.
You got to get over the Rockies.
And I had to turn my car around.
I couldn't, I watched, uh, I watched a F-150 go off the road.
I'm like, I got to go back.
And like that day was meaningful because like, like it was real.
Like I actually had to turn my car around.
It's rare that anything even real happens in my life.
Even as, you know, mundane is the fact that, yeah, there was snow.
I had to turn around, stay in Gunnison and leave the next day.
Something about that moment felt real.
Okay. So it's interesting to break apart the three moments you mentioned if it's okay.
So it'll, uh, I always have trouble pronouncing his name, but allows a Yurkowski.
So what, how did your worldview change in starting to consider the
exponential growth of AI and AGI that he thinks about and the, uh,
the threats of artificial intelligence and all that kind of ideas?
Like, can you, is it just like, can you maybe, uh, break apart?
Like what exactly was so magical to you as a transformation experience?
Today, everyone knows him for threats and AI safety.
This was pre that stuff.
There was, I don't think a mention of AI safety on the page.
This is, this is old Yurkowski stuff.
He'd probably denounce it all now.
He'd probably be like, that's exactly what I didn't want to happen.
Oh, sorry, man.
Is there something specific you can take from his work that you can remember?
Yeah. Uh, it was this realization that, uh, computers double in power every 18 months
and humans do not.
And they haven't crossed yet, but if you have one thing that's doubling every 18 months
and one thing that's staying like this, you know, here's your log graph.
Here's your line, you know, you calculate that.
And then did that open the door to the exponential thinking?
Like thinking that, like, you know what, with technology, we can actually transform the world.
It opened the door to human obsolescence.
It, it opened the door to realize that in my lifetime, humans are going to be replaced.
And then the matching idea to that of artificial intelligence with the Hutter Prize.
You know, I'm torn.
I go back and forth on what I think about it.
Yeah.
But the, the, the basic thesis is it's nice.
It's a nice compelling notion that we can reduce the task of creating an intelligent system,
a generally intelligent system, into the task of compression.
So you, you can think of all of intelligence in the universe.
In fact, this is a kind of compression.
Do you find that a, was that just at the time you found that as a compelling idea?
Or do you still find that a compelling idea?
I still find that a compelling idea.
I think that it's not that useful day-to-day, but actually one of maybe my quests before that
was a search for the definition of the word intelligence.
And I never had one.
And I definitely have a definition of the word compression.
It's a very simple, straightforward one.
And you know what compression is.
You know what lossless, is lossless compression, not lossy, lossless compression.
And that that is equivalent to intelligence, which I believe,
I'm not sure how useful that definition is day-to-day,
but like I now have a framework to understand what it is.
And he just 10x'd the prize for that competition, like recently a few months ago.
You ever thought of taking a crack at that?
Oh, I did.
I spent, I spent the next, after I found the prize, I spent the next six months of my life
trying it.
And well, that's when I started learning everything about AI.
And then I worked at Vicarious for a bit.
And then I learned, read all the deep learning stuff.
And I'm like, okay, now I like, I'm caught up to modern AI.
And I had, I had a really good framework to put it all in from the compression stuff.
Right.
Like some of the first, some of the first deep learning models I played with were,
were GTT, GPT basically.
But before Transformers, before it was still RNNs to do character prediction.
But by the way, on the compression side, I mean, the, especially with neural networks,
what do you make of the lossless requirement with the harder prize?
So, you know, human intelligence and neural networks can probably compress stuff pretty
well, but there will be lossy.
It's imperfect.
You can turn a lossy compression into a lossless compressor pretty easily using an arithmetic
encoder, right?
You can take an arithmetic encoder and you can just encode the noise with maximum efficiency.
Right. So even if you can't predict exactly what the next character is,
the better a probability distribution you can put over the next character,
you can then use an arithmetic encoder to, right?
You don't have to know whether it's an E or an I.
You just have to put good probabilities on them and then, you know, code those.
And if you have, it's a bit of entropy thing, right?
So let me, on that topic, it could be interesting as a little side tour.
What are your thoughts in this year about GPT3 and these language models and these
transformers?
Is there something interesting to you as an AI researcher?
Or is there something interesting to you as an autonomous vehicle developer?
Nah, I think, uh, I think it's all right.
I mean, it's not like it's cool.
It's cool for what it is.
But no, we're not just going to be able to scale up to GPT12 and get general purpose
intelligence.
Like your loss function is literally just, you know, you know, cross entropy loss on the
character, right?
Like that's not the loss function of general intelligence.
Is that obvious to you?
Yes.
Can you imagine that, like to play devil's advocate on yourself, is it possible that
you can, the GPT12 will achieve general intelligence with something as dumb as this
kind of loss function?
I guess it depends what you mean by general intelligence.
So there's another problem with the GPTs and that's that they don't have a, uh, they
don't have long-term memory.
Right.
All right.
So like just GPT12, a scaled up version of GPT2 or 3, I find it hard to believe.
Well, you can scale it in.
It's, uh, so it's a hard-coded, hard-coded length, but you can make it wider and wider
and wider.
Yeah, you're going to get, you're going to get cool things from those systems.
But I don't think you're ever going to get something that can like, you know,
build me a rocket ship.
What about solve driving?
So, you know, you can use transformer with video, for example.
You think, is there something in there?
No, because look, we use, we use a grew.
We use a grew.
We could change that grew out to a transformer.
Um, I think driving is much more Markovian than language.
So Markovian, you mean like the memory, which, which aspect of Markovian?
I mean that like most of the information in the state at T minus one is also in the,
is in state T, right?
And it kind of like drops off nicely like this, whereas sometime with language,
you have to refer back to the third paragraph on the second page.
I feel like there's not many, like, like you can say like speed limit signs,
but there's really not many things in autonomous driving that look like that.
But if you look at, uh, to play devil's advocate is, uh, the risk estimation thing
that you've talked about is kind of interesting.
Is, uh, it feels like there might be some longer term, uh, aggregation of context
necessary to be able to figure out like the context.
Yeah, I'm not even sure.
I'm, I'm believing my, my own devil's.
We have a nice, we have a nice like vision model, which outputs like a,
a one to four dimensional perception space.
Um, can I try transformers on it?
Sure.
I probably will.
At some point we'll try transformers and then we'll just see.
Do they do better?
Sure.
I'm, I'm,
but it might not be a game changer.
No, well, I'm not like, like might transformers work better than grooves for autonomous driving?
Sure.
Might we switch?
Is this some radical change?
No.
Okay.
We used a slightly different, you know, we switched from RNNs to grooves like,
okay, maybe it's grooves to transformers, but no, it's not.
Well, on the, on the topic of general intelligence, I don't know how much
I've talked to you about it.
Like what, um, do you think we'll actually build an AGI?
Like if, if you look at Ray Kurzweil with a singularity, do you, do you have like an
intuition about, you're kind of saying driving is easy.
Yeah.
And I, I tend to personally believe that solving driving will have really deep,
important impacts on our ability to solve general intelligence.
Like I think driving doesn't require general intelligence, but I think they're going to
be neighbors in a way that it's like deeply tied because it's so, like driving is so deeply
connected to the human experience that I think solving one will help solve the other.
But, but so I don't see, I don't see driving as like easy and almost like separate than
general intelligence, but like what's your vision of a future with a singularity?
Do you see there'll be a single moment, like a singularity where it'll be a face shift?
Are we in the singularity now?
Like what, do you have crazy ideas about the future in terms of AGI?
We're definitely in the singularity now.
We are.
Of course, of course.
Look at the bandwidth between people.
The bandwidth between people goes up.
All right.
The singularity is just, you know, when the bandwidth, but
What do you mean by the bandwidth of people?
Communications, tools, the whole world is networked.
The whole world is networked and we raise the speed of that network, right?
Oh, so you think the communication of information in a distributed way is a
empowering thing for collective intelligence?
Oh, I didn't say it's necessarily a good thing, but I think that's like
when I think of the definition of the singularity, yeah, it seems kind of right.
I see, like it's a change in the world beyond which
like the world be transformed in ways that we can't possibly imagine.
No, I mean, I think we're in the singularity now in the sense that there's like, you know,
one world in a monoculture and it's also linked.
Yeah, I mean, I kind of shared the intuition that the singularity will originate from the
collective intelligence of us ants versus the like some single system AGI type thing.
Oh, I totally agree with that.
Yeah, I don't, I don't really believe in like like a hard takeoff AGI kind of thing.
Yeah, I don't think, I don't even think AI is all that different in kind
from what we've already been building.
With respect to driving, I think driving is a subset of general intelligence,
and I think it's a pretty complete subset.
I think the tools we develop at comma will also be extremely helpful
to solving general intelligence.
And that's, I think the real reason why I'm doing it.
I don't care about self-driving cars.
It's a cool problem to beat people at.
But yeah, I mean, yeah, you're kind of, you're of two minds.
So one, you do have to have a mission and you want to focus and make sure you get,
you get there.
You can't forget that.
But at the same time, there is a thread that's much bigger than the
capacity entirety of your effort that's much bigger than just driving.
With AI and with general intelligence, it is so easy to delude yourself
into thinking you've figured something out when you haven't.
If we build a level five self-driving car, we have indisputably built something.
Yeah.
Is it general intelligence?
I'm not going to debate that.
I will say we've built something that provides huge financial value.
Yeah, beautifully put.
That's the engineer and credo, just build the thing.
It's like, that's why I'm with Elon on Go to Mars.
Yeah, that's a great one.
You can argue who the hell cares about Go to Mars.
But the reality is, set that as a mission, get it done, and then you're going to crack some
problem that you've never even expected in the process of doing that.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, I think if I had a choice between humanity going to Mars and solving
self-driving cars, I think going to Mars is better.
But I don't know, I'm more suited for self-driving cars.
I'm an information guy.
I'm not a modernist.
I'm a post-modernist.
Post-modernist, all right.
Beautifully put.
Let me drag you back to programming for a sec.
What three, maybe three to five programming languages should people learn, do you think?
Like if you look at yourself, what did you get the most out of from learning?
Well, so everybody should learn C and assembly.
We'll start with those two, right?
Assembly.
Yeah.
If you can't code in assembly, you don't know what the computer's doing.
You don't understand, you don't have to be great in assembly, but you have to code in it.
And then you have to appreciate assembly in order to appreciate all the great things C gets you.
And then you have to code in C in order to appreciate all the great things Python gets you.
So I'll just say assembly C and Python, we'll start with those three.
The memory allocation of C and the fact that assembly is to give you a sense of just how
many levels of abstraction you get to work on in modern-day programming.
Yeah, yeah.
Graph coloring for assignment, register assignment, and compilers.
The computer only has a certain number of registers.
You can have all the variables you want in a C function.
So you get to start to build intuition about compilation, like what a compiler gets you.
What else?
Well, then there's kind of... So those are all very imperative programming languages.
Then there's two other paradigms for programming that everybody should be familiar with.
One of them is functional.
You should learn Haskell and take that all the way through, learn a language with dependent
types like Coq. Learn that whole space, like the very PL theory heavy languages.
And Haskell is your favorite functional? Is that the go-to, you'd say?
Yeah, I'm not a great Haskell programmer. I wrote a compiler in Haskell once.
There's another paradigm, and actually there's one more paradigm that I'll even talk about
after that that I never used to talk about when I would think about this.
But the next paradigm is learn Verilog or HDL.
Understand this idea of all of the instructions executed once.
If I have a block in Verilog and I write stuff in it, it's not sequential.
They all execute it once.
And then think like that. That's how hard it works.
So I guess assembly doesn't quite get you that.
Assembly is more about compilation, and Verilog is more about the hardware,
like giving a sense of what actually the hardware is doing.
Assembly, C, Python are straight like they sit right on top of each other.
In fact, C is kind of coded in C.
But you could imagine the first C was coded in assembly, and Python is actually coded in C.
So you can straight up go on that.
Got it. And then Verilog gives you that.
That's brilliant. Okay.
And then I think there's another one now.
Everyone's Carpathian calls it programming 2.0, which is learn a...
I'm not even gonna... Don't learn TensorFlow. Learn PyTorch.
So machine learning.
We've got to come up with a better term than programming 2.0 or...
But yeah.
It's a programming language.
I wonder if it can be formalized a little bit better.
We feel like we're in the early days of what that actually entails.
Data-driven programming?
Data-driven programming, yeah.
But it's so fundamentally different as a paradigm than the others.
Like it almost requires a different skill set.
But you think it's still... Yeah.
And PyTorch versus TensorFlow, PyTorch wins.
It's the fourth paradigm.
It's the fourth paradigm that I've kind of seen.
There's like this imperative functional hardware.
I don't know a better word for it.
And then ML.
Do you have advice for people that want to get into programming
and want to learn programming?
You have a video.
What is programming?
Newb lessons, exclamation point.
And I think the top comment is like,
warning, this is not for noobs.
Do you have a newb, like TLDW for that video,
but also a newb friendly advice on how to get into programming?
We're never going to learn programming by watching a video
called Learn Programming.
The only way to learn programming, I think,
and the only one is the only way everyone I've ever met
who can program well learned it all in the same way.
They had something they wanted to do,
and then they tried to do it.
And then they were like, oh, well, okay, this is kind of,
you know, it'd be nice if the computer could kind of do this.
And then, you know, that's how you learn.
You just keep pushing on a project.
So the only advice I have for learning programming is go program.
Somebody wrote to me a question like,
we don't really, they're looking to learn
about recurring neural networks.
And it's saying like, my company's thinking of doing,
using recurring neural networks for time series data.
But we don't really have an idea of where to use it yet.
We just want to, like, do you have any advice on how to learn about,
these are these kind of general machine learning questions.
And I think the answer is like, actually have a problem
that you're trying to solve and just.
I see that stuff.
Oh my God, when people talk like that, they're like,
I heard machine learning is important.
Could you help us integrate machine learning
with macaroni and cheese production?
You just, I don't even, you can't help these people.
Like who lets you run anything?
Who lets that kind of person run anything?
I think we're all, we're all beginners at some point.
So.
It's not like they're a beginner.
It's like, my problem is not that they don't know about machine learning.
My problem is that they think that machine learning has something to say
about macaroni and cheese production.
Or like, I heard about this new technology.
How can I use it for why?
Like, I don't know what it is, but how can I use it for why?
That's true.
And you have to build up an intuition of how,
because you might be able to figure out a way,
but like the prerequisites is you should have a macaroni and cheese problem to solve first.
Exactly.
And then two, you should have more traditional,
like the learning process involved more traditionally applicable problems
in the space of whatever that is of machine learning.
And then see if it can be applied to macrophages.
At least start with, tell me about a problem.
Like, if you have a problem, you're like,
you know, some of my boxes aren't getting enough macaroni in them.
Can we use machine learning to solve this problem?
That's much, much better than,
how do I apply machine learning to macaroni and cheese?
One big thing, maybe this is me talking to the audience a little bit,
because I get these days so many messages,
advice on how to like, learn stuff.
Okay. My, this is not me being mean.
I think this is quite profound actually, is you should Google it.
Oh yeah.
Like one of the like skills that you should really acquire as an engineer,
as a researcher, as a thinker, like one,
there's two complementary skills.
Like one is with a blank sheet of paper with no internet to think deeply.
And then the other is to Google the crap out of the questions you have.
Like that's actually a skill.
People often talk about, but like doing research,
like pulling at the thread and like looking up different words,
going into like GitHub repositories with two stars,
and like looking how they did stuff,
like looking at the code or going on Twitter,
seeing like there's little pockets of brilliant people that are like having discussions.
Like if you're a neuroscientist, go into signal processing community.
If you're an AI person going into the psychology community,
like the switch communities that keep searching, searching, searching,
because it's so much better to invest in like finding somebody else
who already solved your problem than is to try to solve the problem.
And because they've often invested years of their life,
like entire communities are probably already out there who have tried to solve your problem.
I think they're the same thing.
I think you go try to solve the problem.
And then in trying to solve the problem,
if you're good at solving problems,
you'll stumble upon the person who solved it already.
Yeah, but the stumbling is really important.
I think that's a skill that people should really put,
especially in undergrad, like search.
If you ask me a question, how should I get started in deep learning?
Especially that is just so Google-able.
The whole point is you Google that and you get a million pages
and just start looking at them.
Yeah.
Start pulling at the thread, start exploring, start taking notes,
start getting advice from a million people that already spent their life
answering that question, actually.
Oh, well, yeah.
I mean, that's definitely also when people ask me things like that,
I'm like, trust me, the top answer on Google is much, much better
than anything I'm going to tell you.
Anything you want to say.
Right?
Yeah.
People ask.
It's an interesting question.
Let me know if you have any recommendations.
What three books, technical or fiction or philosophical,
had an impact on your life or you wouldn't recommend, perhaps?
Maybe we'll start with the least controversial.
Infinite Jest.
Infinite Jest is a...
David Foster Wallace.
Yeah, it's a book about wireheading, really.
Very enjoyable to read, very well-written.
You will grow as a person reading this book.
It's effort.
And I'll set that up for the second book, which is pornography.
That's called Atlas Shrugged, which...
Atlas Shrugged is pornography.
Yeah, I mean, it is.
I will not defend the...
I will not say Atlas Shrugged is a well-written book.
It is entertaining to read, certainly, just like pornography.
The production value isn't great.
There's a 60-page monologue in there that Anne Rand's editor really wanted to take out.
And she paid out of her pocket to keep that 60-page monologue in the book.
But it is a great book for a kind of framework of human relations.
And I know a lot of people are like, yeah, but it's a terrible framework.
Yeah, but it's a framework.
Just for context, in a couple of days, I'm speaking for probably four plus hours with
Yaron Brooke, who's the main living, remaining objectivist.
Objectivist.
Interesting.
So I've always found this philosophy quite interesting on many levels.
One of how repulsive some large percent of the population find it, which is always funny to
me when people are unable to even read a philosophy because of some...
I think that says more about their psychological perspective on it.
But there is something about objectivism and Anne Rand's philosophy that's deeply connected
to this idea of capitalism, of the ethical life is the productive life,
that was always compelling to me.
I didn't seem to interpret it in the negative sense that some people do.
To be fair, I read the book when I was 19.
So you had an impact at that point.
Yeah, and the bad guys in the book have this slogan, from each according to their ability
to each according to their need.
I'm looking at this and I'm like, these are the most...
This is team rocket level cartoonishness, right?
No, bad guy.
And then when I realized that was actually the slogan of the Communist Party, I'm like,
wait a second, wait, no, no, no, no, no.
You're telling me this really happened?
Yeah, it's interesting.
One of the criticisms of her work is she has a cartoonish view of good and evil.
The reality, as Jordan Peterson says, is that each of us have the capacity for good and evil in
us as opposed to there's some characters who are purely evil and some characters are purely good.
And that's in a way why it's pornographic.
The production value, I love it.
Well, evil is punished and they're very clearly like, you know, there's no, you know,
you know, just like porn doesn't have, you know, like character growth, you know,
neither does Alice Rodney to like.
Brilliant, well put.
But at 19 year old George Hots, it was good enough.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
What's the third?
You have something?
I could give these two I'll just throw out.
They're sci-fi, Perbutation City.
Great thing, just try thinking about copies yourself.
And then the minute...
Isn't that by?
Sorry to interrupt.
That is Greg Egan.
That might not be his real name.
Some Australian guy.
It might not be Australian.
I don't know.
And then this one's online.
It's called the Metamorphosis of Prime Intellect.
It's a story set in a post-singularity world.
It's interesting.
Is there, can you, in either of the worlds, do you find something
philosophical interesting in them that you can comment on?
I mean, it is clear to me that
Metamorphosis of Prime Intellect is like written by an engineer.
Which is, it's very, it's very almost a pragmatic take on a utopia, in a way.
Positive or negative?
That's up to you to decide reading the book.
And the ending of it is very interesting as well.
And I didn't realize what it was.
I first read that when I was 15.
I've reread that book several times in my life.
And it's short, it's 50 pages.
I want you to go read it.
What's, sorry, it's a little tangent.
I've been working through the foundation.
I've been, I haven't read much sci-fi in my whole life.
And I'm trying to fix that in the last few months.
That's been a little side project.
What's to use the greatest sci-fi novel that people should read?
Or is it, or?
I mean, I would, yeah, I would, I would say like, yeah,
Permutation City, Metamorphosis of Prime Intellect.
Got it.
I don't know.
I didn't like Foundation.
I thought it was way too modernist.
Be like Dune and like all of those.
I've never read Dune.
I have to read it.
Fire Upon the Deep is interesting.
Okay, I mean, look, everyone should read,
everyone should read Neuromancer.
Everyone should read Snow Crash.
If you haven't read those, like, start there.
Yeah, I haven't read Snow Crash.
I haven't read Snow Crash.
Oh, it's, I mean, it's very entertaining.
It's surprising.
Go to Lesher Bach.
And if you want the controversial one, Bronze Age Mindset.
All right, I'll look into that one.
Those aren't sci-fi, but just to round out books.
So a bunch of people asked me on Twitter and Reddit and so on
for advice.
So what advice would you give a young person today about life?
What, yeah, I mean, looking back,
especially when you're a young, younger, you did,
and you continued it, you've accomplished a lot of interesting things.
Is there some advice from those,
from that life of yours that you can pass on?
If college ever opens again, I would love to give a graduation speech.
At that point, I will put a lot of somewhat satirical effort into this question.
Yeah, at this, you haven't written anything at this point.
You know what, always wear sunscreen.
This is water, like.
I think you're plagiarizing.
I mean, you know, but that's the, that's the, like,
put clean your room.
You know, yeah, you can plagiarize them from all of this stuff.
And it's, it's,
there is no,
self-help books aren't designed to help you.
They're designed to make you feel good.
Like, whatever advice I could give, you already know.
Everyone already knows.
Sorry, it doesn't feel good.
Right?
Like, you know, you know.
If I tell you that you should, you know,
eat well and read more and it's not going to do anything.
I think the whole, like, genre of those kind of questions is meaningless.
I don't know.
If anything, it's don't worry so much about that stuff.
Don't be so caught up in your head.
Right.
I mean, you're, yeah, in the sense that your whole life,
your whole existence is like moving version of that advice.
I don't know.
There's, there's something, I mean,
there's something in you that resists that kind of thinking in that,
in itself is, it's just illustrative of who you are.
And there's something to learn from that.
I think you're, you're clearly not overthinking stuff.
Yeah.
And you know what?
There's a gut thing.
I, even when I talk about my advice, I'm like,
my advice is only relevant to me.
It's not relevant to anybody else.
I'm not saying you should go out.
If you're the kind of person who overthinks things,
to stop overthinking things, it's not bad.
It doesn't work for me.
Maybe it works for you.
I, you know, I don't know.
Let me ask you about love.
Yeah.
So I think last time we talked about the meaning of life,
and it was, it was kind of about winning.
Of course.
I don't think I've talked to you about love much,
whether romantic or just love for the common humanity amongst us all.
What role has love played in your life?
In this, in this quest for winning, where does love fit in?
Well, where love, I think means several different things.
There's love in the sense of, maybe I could just say,
there's like love in the sense of opiates and love in the sense of oxytocin,
and then love in the sense of maybe like a love for math.
I don't think fits into either of those first two paradigms.
So each of those, have they, have they, have they given something to you in your life?
I'm not that big of a fan of the first two.
Why?
The same reason I'm not a fan of, you know,
the same reason I don't do opiates and don't take ecstasy.
And there were times, look, I've tried both.
I like opiates way more than ecstasy.
But they're not, the ethical life is the productive life.
So maybe that's my problem with those.
And then like, yeah, a sense of, I don't know, like abstract love for humanity.
I mean, the abstract love for humanity, I'm like, yeah, I've always felt that.
And I guess it's hard for me to imagine not feeling it.
And maybe there's people who don't and I don't know.
Yeah.
That's just like a background thing that's there.
I mean, since we brought up drugs, let me ask you,
this is becoming more and more a part of my life because I'm talking to a few researchers
that are working on psychedelics.
I've eaten shrooms a couple of times.
And it was fascinating to me that like the mind can go to like,
just fascinating, the mind can go to places I didn't imagine it could go.
And I was very friendly and positive and exciting.
And everything was kind of hilarious in the place.
Wherever my mind went, that's where I went.
Is what do you think about psychedelics?
Do you think they have, where do you think the mind goes?
Have you done psychedelics?
Where do you think the mind goes?
Is there something useful to learn about the places it goes?
Once you come back.
I find it interesting that this idea that psychedelics have something to teach
is almost unique to psychedelics.
People don't argue this about amphetamines.
And I'm not really sure why.
I think all of the drugs have lessons to teach.
I think there's things to learn from opiates.
I think there's things to learn from amphetamines.
I think there's things to learn from psychedelics,
things to learn from marijuana.
But also at the same time, recognize that I don't think you're learning things
about the world.
I think you're learning things about yourself.
And what's the, it might have even been.
Might have even been a Timothy Leary quote.
I don't know his quote.
But the idea is basically like, everybody should look behind the door.
But then once you've seen behind the door, you don't need to keep going back.
So, I mean, and that's my thoughts on all real drug use too.
So maybe for caffeine.
It's a little experience that it's good to have, but.
Oh yeah.
No, I mean, yeah, I guess, yeah, psychedelics are definitely.
So you're a fan of new experiences, I suppose.
Yes.
Because they all contain a little, especially the first few times,
it contains some lessons that can be picked up.
Yeah.
And I'll, I'll revisit psychedelics maybe once a year.
Usually small, smaller doses.
Maybe they turn up the learning rate of your brain.
I've heard that, I like that.
Yeah, that's cool.
Big learning rates have frozen comms.
Last question, and this is a little weird one,
but you've called yourself crazy in the past.
First of all, on a scale of one to 10, how crazy would you say, are you?
Oh, I mean, it depends how you, you know, when you compare me to
Elon Musk and I say Levin Dalsky, not so crazy.
So like, like a seven?
Let's go with six.
Six, six, six.
What, uh.
I like seven, seven's a good number.
Seven, sorry.
Well, yeah, I'm sure day by day changes, right?
So, but you're in that, in that area.
What, uh, in thinking about that, what do you think is the role of madness?
Is that a feature or a bug if you were to dissect your brain?
So, okay, from like a, like mental health lens on crazy,
I'm not sure I really believe in that.
I'm not sure I really believe in like a lot of that stuff, right?
This concept of, okay, you know, when you get over to like,
like, like, like hardcore bipolar and schizophrenia,
these things are clearly real, somewhat biological.
And then over here on the spectrum, you have like ADD and oppositional defiance disorder
and these things that are like, wait, this is normal spectrum human behavior.
Like this isn't, you know, where's the, the line here?
And why is this like a problem?
So there's this whole, you know, the neurodiversity of humanity is huge.
Like people think I'm always on drugs.
People are always saying this to me on my streams and like guys,
you know, like I'm real open with my drug use.
I would tell you if I was on drugs and I mean, I had like a cup of coffee this morning,
but other than that, this is just me.
You're witnessing my brain in action.
So, so the word madness doesn't even make sense.
And then you're in the rich neurodiversity of humans.
I think it makes sense, but only for like some insane extremes.
Like if you are actually like visibly hallucinating, you know, that's okay.
But there is the kind of spectrum on which you stand out.
Like that, that's like, if I were to look, you know, at decorations on a Christmas tree
or something like that, like if you were a decoration that would catch my eye.
Like that thing is sparkly.
Whatever the hell that thing is, there's something to that.
Just like refusing to be boring or maybe boring is the wrong word, but to,
yeah, I mean, be willing to sparkle.
You know, it's, it's like somewhat constructed.
I mean, I am who I choose to be.
I'm going to say things as true as I can see them.
I'm not going to, I'm not going to lie.
And but that's a really important feature in itself.
So like whatever the neurodiversity of your, whatever your brain is,
not putting constraints on it that force it to fit into the mold of what society is,
like defines what you're supposed to be.
So you're one of the specimens that, that doesn't mind being yourself.
Being right is super important, except at the expense of being wrong.
Without breaking that apart.
I think it's a beautiful way to end it.
George, you're, you're one of the most special humans I know.
It's truly an honor to talk to you.
Thanks so much for doing it.
Thank you for having me.
Thanks for listening to this conversation with George Hots.
And thank you to our sponsors for Sigmatic, which is the maker of delicious mushroom coffee,
Decoding Digital, which is a tech podcast that I listen to and enjoy,
and ExpressVPN, which is the VPN I've used for many years.
Please check out these sponsors in the description to get a discount
and to support this podcast.
If you enjoy this thing, subscribe on YouTube, review it with five stars on Apple podcast,
follow on Spotify, support on Patreon, or connect with me on Twitter at Lex Freedman.
And now let me leave you with some words from the great and powerful Linus Torvald.
Talk is cheap.
Show me the code.
Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.