Can you imagine possible features that Python 4.0 might have that would necessitate the creation
of the new 4.0 given the amount of pain and joy, suffering and triumph that was involved in the
move between version 2 and version 3? The following is a conversation with Guido van
Rossum, his second time on this podcast. He is the creator of the Python programming language
and is Python's emeritus BDFL, benevolent dictator for life. This is the Lex Friedman podcast.
To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description. And now dear friends,
here's Guido van Rossum. Python 3.11 is coming out very soon. In it,
Cpython claimed to be 10 to 60% faster. How did you pull that off? And what's Cpython?
Cpython is the last Python implementation standing also the first one that was ever created. The
original Python implementation that I started over 30 years ago. So what does it mean that Python,
the programming language is implemented in another programming language called C?
What kind of audience do you have in mind here? People who know programming?
No, there's somebody on a boat that's into fishing and have never heard about programming,
but also some world-class programmers. You're going to have to speak to both. Imagine a boat
with two people. One of them has not heard about programming is really into fishing.
And the other one is like an incredible Silicon Valley programmer that's programmed in everything.
C, C++, Python, Rust, Java. It knows the entire history of programming languages. So you're going
to have to speak to both. I imagine that boat in the middle of the ocean. I'm going to please
the guy who knows how to fish first. Yes, please. He seems like the most useful in the middle of
the ocean. You got to make him happy. I'm sure he has a cell phone. So he's probably very suspicious
about what goes on in that cell phone, but he must have heard that inside a cell phone is a tiny
computer. And a programming language is computer code that tells the computer what to do.
Very low-level language. It's zeros and ones, and then there's assembly, and then...
Oh, yeah. We don't talk about these really low levels because those just confuse people. I mean,
when we're talking about human language, we're not usually talking about vocal tracts and
how you position your tongue. I was talking yesterday about how when you have a Chinese person
and they speak English, this is a bit of a stereotype. They often don't know...
They can't seem to make the difference well between an L and an R. And I have a theory about
that, and I've never checked this with linguists, that it probably has to do with the fact that
in Chinese, there is not really a difference. And it could be that there are regional variations
in how native Chinese speakers pronounce that one sound that sounds like L to some of them,
like R to others. So, it's both the sounds you produce with your mouth throughout the history
of your life and what you're used to listening to. I mean, every language has that. Russian has...
Exactly. The Slavic languages have sounds like the letters
like Americans or English speakers don't seem to know the sounds.
They seem uncomfortable with that sound. Yeah. Oh, yes. Okay. So, we're not going to the shapes
of tongues and the sounds that the mouth can make. Fine. And similarly, we're not going into the
ones and zeros or machine language. I would say a programming language is a list of instructions
like a cookbook recipe that sort of tells you how to do a certain thing, like make a sandwich. Well,
acquire a loaf of bread, cut it in slices, take two slices, put mustard on one, put
jelly on the other or something, then add the meat, then add the cheese. I've heard that science
teachers can actually do great stuff with recipes like that and trying to interpret their students'
instructions incorrectly until the students are completely unambiguous about it.
With language, see, that's the difference between natural languages and programming languages.
I think ambiguity is a feature, not a bug in human spoken languages. Like,
that's the dance of communication between humans.
Well, for lawyers, ambiguity certainly is a feature. For plenty of other cases,
the ambiguity is not much of a feature, but we work around it, of course. What's more important
is context. So, with context, the precision of the statement becomes more and more concrete, right?
But, you know, when you say, I love you to a person that matters a lot to you,
the person doesn't try to compile that statement and return an error saying,
please define love, right? No, but I imagine that my wife and my son interpreted very differently.
Yes. Even though it's the same three words. But in precisely still.
Oh, for sure. Well, lawyers have a lot of follow-up questions for you. Nevertheless,
the context is already different in that case. Yes, fair enough. So, that's a programming language
is ability to unambiguously state a recipe. Actually, let's go back. Let's go to Pepe.
You go through in Pepe, the style guide for Python code, some ideas of what this language should
look like, feel like, read like. And the big idea there is that code readability counts.
What does that mean to you? And how do we achieve it? So, this recipe should be readable.
That's a thing between programmers. Because on the one hand, we always explain the concept of
programming language as computers need instructions and computers are very dumb and they need very
precise instructions because they don't have much context. In fact, they have lots of context,
but their context is very different. But what we've seen emerge during the development of
software starting in the probably in the late 40s is that software is a very social activity.
A software developer is not a mad scientist who sits alone in his lab writing brilliant code.
A software is developed by teams of people. Even the mad scientist sitting alone in his lab
can't type fast enough to produce enough code so that by the time he's done with his coding,
he still remembers what the first few lines he wrote mean. So, even the mad scientist coding
alone in his lab would be sort of wise to adopt conventions on how to format the instructions
that he gives to the computer so that the thing is there is a difference between a cookbook recipe
and a computer program. The cookbook recipe, the author of the cookbook writes it once
and then is printed in 100,000 copies and then lots of people in their kitchens try to
recreate that recipe, that particular pie or dish from the recipe. And so there the
goal of the cookbook author is to make it clear to the human reader of the recipe,
the human amateur chef in most cases. When you're writing a computer program, you have two audiences
at once. It needs to tell the computer what to do but it also is useful if that program is readable
by other programmers because computer software unlike the typical recipe for a cherry pie
is so complex that you don't get all of it right at once. You end up with the activity of debugging
and you end up with the activity of... So debugging is
trying to figure out why your code doesn't run the way you thought it should run.
That means broadly it could be stupid little errors or it could be big
logical errors. It could be anything from a typo to a wrong choice of algorithm to
building something that does what you tell it to do but that's not useful.
Yeah it seems to work really well 99% of the time but does weird things 1% of the time on some
edge cases. That's pretty much all software nowadays. All good software right? Well yeah for
for bad software then. That 99 goes down a lot so but it's not just about the complexity of the
program it's like you said it is a social endeavor in that you're constantly improving that recipe
for the cherry pie. But you're sort of you're in a group of people improving that recipe
or the mad scientist is improving the recipe that he created a year ago and making it better
or adding something. He decides that he wants I don't know he wants some decoration on his pie
or icing or... So there's broad philosophical things and there's specific advice on style.
So first of all the thing that people first experience when they look at Python
there is a it is very readable but there's also like a spatial structure to it.
Can you explain the indentation style of Python and what is the magic to it? Spaces are important
for readability of any kind of text. If you take a cookbook recipe and you remove all the sort of
all the bullets and other markup and you just crunch all the text together maybe you leave the
spaces between the words but that's all you leave. When you're in the kitchen trying to figure out
oh what are the ingredients and what are the steps and where does this step end and the next step
begin you're going to have a hard time if it's if it's just one solid block of text. On the other
On the other hand what what a typical cookbook does if the paper is not too expensive
each recipe starts on its own page maybe there's a picture next to it. The list of ingredients comes
first there's a standard notation there's there's shortcuts so that you don't have to
sort of write two sentences on how you have to cut the onion because there are only three ways
that people ever cut onions in the kitchen small medium and in slices or something like that.
Right. None of my examples make any sense to real cooks of course but yeah.
We're talking to programmers with the metaphor of cooking I love it but there is a strictness to
the spacing that Python defines so there's some looser things some stricter things but the four
spaces for the indentation is really interesting it really defines what the language looks and
feels like. Because indentation sort of taking a block of text and then having inside that block
of text a smaller block of text that is indented further as sort of a group it's like you have
a bulleted list in a complex business document and inside some of the bullets are other bulleted
lists you will indent those two if each bulleted list is indented several inches then at two levels
deep there's no no space left on the page to put any of the words of the text so you can't indent
too far on the other hand if you don't indent at all you can tell whether something is a top level
bullet or a second level bullet or a third level bullet so you have to have some compromise and
based on ancient conventions and the sort of the typical width of a computer screen in the 80s
and all sorts of things sort of we came up with sort of four spaces as a compromise
I mean there there are groups there are large groups of people who code with two spaces per
indent level for example the google style guide all the google python code and I think also all
the google c++ code is indented with only two spaces per block if you're not used to that it's
harder to at a glance understand the code because the sort of the high level structure
is determined by the indentation on the other hand there are there are other programming languages
where the indentation is eight spaces or a whole tap stop in in sort of classic unix and to me that
looks weird because you you sort of after three indent levels you've you've got no room left well
there is some languages where the indentation is a recommendation it's a stylistic one the code
compiles even without any indentation and then python really indentation is a fundamental part
of the language right it doesn't have to be four spaces so you you can code python with
two spaces per block or four or six spaces or 12 if you really want to go wild but
sort of everything that belongs to the same block needs to be indented the same way
in practice in most other languages people recommend doing that anyway if you look at
c or rust or c++ all those languages java don't have a requirement of indentation
but except in extreme cases they're just as anal about having their code properly indented
so any ide that the syntax highlighting that works with java or c++ they will yell at you
aggressively if you don't do proper indentation they'd suggest the proper indentation for you
like in c you type a few words and then you type a curly brace which there is their notion of
sort of begin an an indented block then you hit return and then it automatically indents
four or eight spaces depending on your style preferences or how your editor is configured
was there a possible universe in which you considered having braces in python
absolutely yeah well it was a 60 40 70 30 in your head uh what was the tradeoff
for a long time i was actually convinced that the indentation was just better
without context i would still claim that indentation is better
it reduces clutter however as i started to say earlier context is almost everything
and in the context of coding most programmers are familiar with multiple languages even if
they're only good at one or two and apart from python and maybe fortran i don't know how that's
written these days anymore but all the other languages java rust cc plus plus javascript
typescript pearl are all using curly braces uh to sort of indicate blocks and so python is the odd
one out so it's a radical idea do you still as a radical renegade revolutionary do you still
stand behind this idea of space of indentation versus braces like what what can you dig into it
a little bit more why you still stand behind indentation because context is not the whole story
history in in a sense provides more context so for python there is no chance that we can switch
python is using curly braces for something else dictionaries mostly we would get in trouble if
we wanted to switch just like you couldn't redefine c to use indentation even if you agree that that
indentation sort of in a greenfield environment would be better you can't change that kind of thing
in a language yeah it's hard enough to reach agreement over over much more minor details maybe
i mean in the past in python we did have a big debate about teps versus spaces and four spaces
versus fewer or more and we sort of came up with a recommended standard and sort of options for people
who want to be different but yes i guess the thought experiment i'd like you to consider
is if you could travel back through time when the when the compatibility is not an issue
and you started python all over again can you make the case for indentation still
well it frees up a pair of matched brackets of which there are never enough in the world
for other purposes it really makes the language slightly sort of easier to grasp
for people who don't already know another programming language
because the sort of one of the things and i i mostly got this from my mentors who
taught me programming language design in the earlier 80s when you're teaching programming
for for the the the total newbie who has not coded before in not in any other language
a whole bunch of concepts in programming are very alien or sort of new and and maybe very
interesting but also distracting and confusing and there are many different things you have to learn
you have to sort of in a typical 13 week programming course you have to if if it's
like really learning to program from scratch you have to cover algorithms you have to cover
data structures you have to cover syntax you have to cover variables loops functions recursion
classes expressions operators there are so many concepts if you you sort of if you can spend a
little less time having to worry about the syntax the classic example was often oh the compiler
complains every time i put a semicolon in the wrong place or i forget to put a semicolon
python doesn't have semicons in that sense so you can't forget them and you are also not
sort of misled into putting them where they don't belong because you don't learn about them in the
first place the flip side of that is forcing the strictness onto the beginning programmer
to teach them that programming is values attention to details you don't get to just
write the way you write in english many of other details that they have to pay attention to so i
think they'll they'll still get the message about paying attention to details the interesting
design choice so i still program quite a bit in php and i'm sure there's other languages like this
but the dollar sign before a variable that was always an annoying thing for me it didn't quite
fit into my understanding of why this is good for a programming language i'm not sure if you
ever thought about that one that is a historical thing there is a whole lineage of programming
languages php is one pearl was one on the unix shell uh is one of the oldest or or all the
different shells the dollar was invented for that purpose because the very earliest shells had a
notion of scripting but they did not have a notion of parameterizing the scripting right and so a
script is just a few lines of text where each line of text is a command that is read by a very
primitive command processor that then sort of takes the first word on the line as the name of a
program and passes all the all the rest of the line as text into the program for the program to
figure out what to do with as arguments and so by the time scripting was slightly more mature
than the very first script there was a convention that just like the first word on the line is
uh the name of the program the following words uh could be names of files input dot text output dot
html things like that the next thing that happens is oh it would actually be really nice if we could
have variables and especially parameters for scripts parameters are usually what starts this
process but now you have a problem because you can't just say the parameters are x y and z
and so now we we call say let's say x is the input file and y is the output file and let's
forget about z for now i have my program and i write program x y well that already has a meaning
because that presumably means x itself is the file it's a file name it's not a variable name
and so the inventors of of things like the unique shell and i'm sure job command language
in at IBM before that uh had to use something that made it clear to the script processor
here is an x that is not actually the name of a file which you just pass through to the
to the program you're running here is an x that is the name of a variable yeah and
when you're writing a script processor you try to keep it as simple as possible
because at that as certainly in the the 50s and 60s uh the thing that interprets the script
was itself a very had to be a very small program because it had to fit in a very small part of
memory and so saying oh just look at each character and if you see a dollar sign you jump to another
section of the code and then you gobble up characters or say until the next space or something
and you say that's the variable name and so it was was sort of invented as
a clever way to make parsing of things that contain both contain both variable and fixed parts
very easy in a very simple script processor it also helps even then it also helps the human
author and the human reader of the the script to quickly see oh 20 lines down in the script
i see a reference to x y z oh it has a dollar in front of it so now we know that x y z must be
one of the parameters of the script well this is fascinating several things to say which is
the leftovers from the simple script processor languages are now in code bases like behind
facebook or behind most of the back end i think php's probably still runs most of the back end
of the internet oh yeah i think there's a lot of it in wikipedia too for example yeah it's funny
that those decisions are not funny it's fascinating that those decisions permeate through time
just like biological systems right i mean that the sort of the inner workings of dna
have been stable for well i don't know how long it was like 300 million years half a billion years
yeah and there there are all sorts of weird quirks there that don't make a lot of sense if
you were to design a system like self-replicating molecules from scratch well that system has a
lot of interesting resilience it has redundancy that results like it messes up in interesting ways
that still is resilient when you look at the system level of the organism code doesn't
necessarily have that a program a computer programming code you'd be surprised how much
resilience modern code has i mean if you if you look at the number of bugs per line of code
even in in very well tested code that in practice works just fine there are actually
lots of things that don't work fine and there are error correcting or self-correcting mechanisms
at many levels including probably the user of the code well in the end the user who sort of is
told well you got to reboot your your pc is part of that system and a slightly less drastic thing
is reload the page which we all know how to do without thinking about it when something weird
happens you try to reload a few times before you say oh there's something really weird
okay or try to click the button again if the first time didn't work well yeah that that we
should all have learned not to do that because that's probably just gonna turn the light back off
yeah true so do it three times that's the that's the right lesson so uh and i wonder how many people
actually like the dollar sign like you said it is documentation so to me it's whatever the
opposite of syntactic sugar is syntactic poison to me it is such a pain in the ass that i have to
type in a dollar sign also super error prone so it's not self documenting it's it's like a bug
generating thing it is a kind of documentation that's the pro and the con is it's a source of a
lot of bugs but actually i have to ask you um this is a really interesting idea of bugs per line of
code if you look at all the computer systems out there from the code that runs nuclear weapons
to the code that runs all the amazing companies that you've been involved with and not the code
that runs twitter and facebook and dropbox and google and microsoft windows and so on and we like
laid out wouldn't that be a cool like table bugs per line of code and what let's let's put like
actual companies aside do you think we'd be surprised by the number we see there for all
these companies that depends on whether you've ever read about research that's been done in this
area before and i don't know that the the last time i i saw some research like that there was
probably in the 90s and the research might have been done in the 80s but the the conclusion was
across a wide range of different software different languages different companies different
development styles the number of bugs is always i think it's in the order of about one bug per
thousand lines in sort of mature software that that is considered interesting as good as it gets
can't give you some facts here there's a lot of good papers so you said mature software right so
here's a report from a uh like programming analytics company now this is from a developer
perspective let me just say what it says because this is very weird and surprising
on average a developer creates 70 bugs per 1000 lines of code
15 bugs per 1000 lines of code find their way to the customers
this is in software they've oh i was i was wrong by an order working on an order fixing a bug takes
30 times longer than writing a line of code that i can believe yeah 75 of a developer's time is
spent on debugging um that's for an average developer that they analyze this 15 argue
1500 hours a year in us alone 113 billion dollars to spend annually on identifying and fixing bugs
and i imagine this is marketing literature for someone who claims to have a golden bullet or
silver bullet that makes all that investment in fixing bugs go away but that that is usually
not going to yeah that's not gonna happen well they're uh i mean they're referencing a lot of
stuff of course but it is the page uh that is you know there's a contact us button at the bottom
presumably if you just spend a little bit less than 100 billion dollars we're willing to solve
the problem for you right and there's also a report on stack exchange and stack overflow on the
exact same topic but when i open it up at the moment the page says stack overflow is currently
offline for maintenance oh that is ironic yes uh by the way their error page is awesome anyway
i mean can you believe that number of bugs oh absolutely isn't that scary that 70 bugs per
1000 lines of code so even 10 bugs per 1000 lines well that's about one bug every 15 lines and
that's when you're first typing it in yeah from a developer but like how many bugs are going to be
found if you're if you're typing well the development process is extremely iterative yeah typically you
don't make a plan for what software you're going to release a year from now yeah and work out all
the details because actually all the details uh themselves consist they sort of compose a program
and that that being a program all your plans will have bugs in them too and inaccuracies
but what what you actually do is you do a bunch of typing and i'm i'm actually
really i'm a really bad typist that's just i've never learned to type with 10 fingers
how many do you use well i use all 10 of them but not very well but i never i never took a
typing class and i never sort of corrected that so the first time i i seriously learned i had to
learn the layout of a of a qwerty keyboard was actually in college in my first programming classes
where we used punch cards and so with my two fingers i sort of pecked out my code
watch anyone give you a little coding demonstration they'll have to produce like four lines of code
and now see how many times they use the backspace key yeah because they made a mistake and and
and some people especially when when someone else is looking
will will backspace over 20 30 40 characters to fix a typo earlier in the line if you're
if you're slightly more experienced of course you use your arrow buttons to go or your mouse to
but the mouse is usually slower than than the arrows but a lot of people when they type a
20 character word which is not unusual and they realize they made us made a mistake at the start
of the word they backspace over the whole thing and then retype it and sometimes it takes three four
times to get it right so i don't know what your definition of bug is arguably mistyping a word
and then correcting it immediately is not a bug on the other hand you you already do sort of lose
time and every once in a while there's sort of a typo that you don't get in that process
and now you've you've you've typed like 10 lines of code and somewhere in the middle of it you
don't know where yet is a typo or maybe a thing code where you you forgot that you had to initialize
a variable or something but those are two different things and i would say yes you have to actually
run the code to discover that typo but forgetting to initialize a variable is a fundamentally different
thing because that thing could go undiscovered that depends on the language in python it will not
right and sort of modern compilers are usually pretty good at catching that even even foresee
so for that specific thing but actually deeper it might there might be another variable that
is initialized but logically speaking the one you meant related yep it's like name the same but
it's a different thing and you forgot to initialize whatever some counter or some some basic variable
they're using i can tell that you've coded yes by the way i should mention that i use a kinesis
keyboard which has the backspace under the thumb and one of the biggest reasons i use that keyboard
is because you realize in order to use the backspace on a usual keyboard you have to stretch
your pinky out and like the for most normal keyboards the backspace is under the pinky
and so i don't know if people realize the pain they go through in their life because of the backspace
key being so far away so with the kinesis it's right under the thumb so you don't have to actually
move your hands the backspace and what do you do if you're ever not with your own keyboard and you
have to use someone else's pc keyboard that has that standard layout so first of all it turns out
that you can actually go your whole life always having the keyboard with you so this well except
for that that little tablet that you're using so we're not taking right now right uh yeah so it's
very inefficient note-taking but i'm not i'm just looking stuff up but in most cases i would be actually
using the keyboard here right right now i just don't anticipate you have to calculate how much
typing do you anticipate if i anticipate quite a bit then i'll just i have a keyboard you pull
that and same same with i mean the embarrassing i've accepted being the weirdo that i am but
you know when i go on an airplane and i anticipate to do programming or a lot of typing
i will have a laptop that will pull out a kinesis keyboard in addition to the laptop
and it's just who i am you have to you have to accept who you are but also it's a you know for a
lot of people for me certainly there's a comfort space where there's a certain kind of setups that
maximize productivity and it's like some people have a warm blanket that they like
when they watch a movie i like the kinesis keyboard takes me to a place of focus and i still mostly
i i'm trying to make sure i use the state of the art ids for everything but my comfort place
just like the kinesis keyboard is still emacs so i still use i still i mean that's one of some
of the debates i have with myself about everything from a technology perspective is how much to hold
on to the tools you're comfortable with versus how much to invest in using modern tools and the
signal that the communities provide you with is the noisy one because a lot of people year to
year get excited about new tools and you have to make a prediction are these tools defining a new
generation of something that will transform programming or is this just a fad that will pass
certainly with javascript frameworks and front and the back end of the web there's a lot of
different styles that came and went i remember learning um what was it called action script
i remember for flash um you know learning how to program in flash learning how to design
doing graphic animation all that kind of stuff for flash same with java applets i remember
creating quite a lot of java applets thinking that this potentially defines the future of the
web and did not well you know in most cases like that the particular technology eventually gets
replaced but many of the concepts that the technology introduced or made accessible first
are preserved of course because yeah we're not using java applets anymore but the notion of
reactive web pages that sort of contain little bits of code that respond directly to something
you do like pressing a button or a link or hovering even uh is has certainly not gone away
and that those animations that were made painfully complicated with flash i mean flash was an
innovation when it first came up and when it was replaced by javascript equivalents stuff
it was a somewhat better way to do animations but those animations are still there not all of them
but but sort of again there is an evolution and often so often with technology
that the sort of the technology that was eventually thrown away or replaced was still
essential to to sort of get started there wouldn't be jet planes without propeller planes
i bet you but from a user perspective yes from the feature set yes but i from a programmer
perspective it feels like all the time i've spent with action script all the time i spent with
java on the applet side for the GUI development i well no java i have to push back that that was
useful that because it transfers but the flash doesn't transfer so some things you learn and
invest time in what yeah what what you learned the skill the skill you picked up learning action
script yeah was sort of it was perhaps a super valuable skill at the time you picked it up
if you if you if you learned action script early enough but that skill is no longer
in demand well that's the calculation you have to make when you're learning new things like today
people start learning programming today i'm trying to to see what are the new languages to try what
are the new systems to try that what are the new ideas to try to to keep keep improving that's
that's why we start when we're young right when when we're but but that seems very true to me that
that when you're young you have your whole life ahead of you and you're you're allowed to make
mistakes in fact you should you should feel encouraged to to do a bit of stupid stuff yeah
try not to get yourself killed or seriously maimed but try stuff that deviates from from
what everybody else is doing and like nine out of ten times you'll just learn why everybody else
is not doing that or why everybody else is doing it some other way and one out of ten times you
sort of you discover something that's better or that that somehow works i mean there are all
sorts of crazy things that were invented by accident by people trying trying stuff together
that's great advice to try random stuff make a lot of mistakes once you're married with kids
you're probably going to be a little more risk averse because now there's more at stake and
you've already hopefully had some time where you where you were experimenting with crazy shit
i like how marriage and kids solidifies your choice of programming language how does that the
the robber frost poem with the the road less taken which i think is misinterpreted by most people
but anyway i i feel like the choices you make early on especially if you go all in they're
going to define the rest of your life's trajectory in a way that like you basically are picking a
camp so you know there's if you invest a lot in php if you invest a lot in dot net if you
invest a lot in java script you're going to stick there you that's that's your life journey
it's very hard to tell only as far as that technology remains relevant yes yes i mean
if if at age 16 you learn coding in c and by the time you're 26 c is like a dead language
then there's still time to switch there's probably some kind of survivor bias or whatever it's called
in in sort of your observation that that you pick a camp because there are many different
camps to pick and if you pick dot net then then you can coast for the rest of your life because
that technology is now so ubiquitous of course that it's even if it's if it's bound to die it's
going to take a very long time well for me personally i had a very difficult and in my own
head brave leap that i had to take relevant to our discussion which is most of my life i programed
in c and c plus plus and so uh having that hammer everything looked like a nail so i would literally
even do scripting in c plus plus like i would create programs i do script like things and uh
when i first came to google and before then it became already before tensile for before all of
that there was a growing realization that c plus plus is not the right tool for machine learning
we could talk about why that is it's unclear why that is a lot of things has to do with
community and culture and how it emerges and stuff like that but for me to decide to take
the leap to python like all out basically switch completely from c plus plus except for
highly performant robotics applications there were still a there's still a culture of c plus
plus in in the space of robotics that was a big leap like i had to you know like like people have
like existential crises or midlife crises or whatever you have to realize almost like walking
away from uh from a person you love um because i was sure that c plus plus would have to be a life
long companion for a lot of problems i would want to solve c plus plus would be there and it was a
question to say well that might not be the case because c plus plus is still one of the most
popular languages in the world one of the most used one of the most dependent on it's also
still evolving quite a bit i mean that that is not a sort of a fossilizing community
yes they they are doing great innovative work actually a lot but yet the sort of their innovations
are hard to follow if you're not already a hardcore c plus plus user well this was the thing it pulls
you in it's a rabbit hole i was a hardcore the all meta programming template programming like
i i would start using the modern c plus plus as it developed right not just the not not just the
shared pointer in the garbage collection that's you that makes it easier for you to work with some
of the flaws but the detail like the meta programming the the crazy stuff that's that's coming out there
but then you have to just empirically look and step back and say what language am i more productive in
sorry to say what language do i enjoy my life with more and uh readability and able to think
through and all that kind of stuff that those questions are harder to ask when you already have
a loved one which in my case was c plus plus and then there's python uh like that meme was
is the the grass is greener on the other side am i just infatuated with a new fad new cool thing
new cool thing or is this actually going to make my life better and i think a lot of people face
that kind of decision it was a difficult decision for me um when i made it at this time it's an
obvious switch if you're into machine learning but that time it wasn't quite yet so obvious so it was
a risk and you know you have the same kind of stuff with um i still because of my connection
to wordpress i still do a lot of back end programming in php
and the question is you know no j s python do you switch to do you switch back end to any of those
programming there's the case for no j s for me well more more more of the front end it runs in
java script um and fascinating cool stuff is done as java script maybe use the same program
language for the back end as well uh the case for python for the back end is well you're doing so
much programming outside of the web in python so maybe use python for the back end and then the
case for php well most of the web still runs in php you have a lot of experience with php
why uh fix something that's not broken those are my own personal struggles but i think they
reflect the struggles of a lot of people with different programming languages with different
problems they're trying to solve it's a weird one and there there's not a single answer right
because depending on how much time you have to learn new stuff where you are in your life
what what you're currently working on who you want to work with what communities you like
there's not one right choice maybe if you if you sort of if you can look back 20 years you can say
well that whole detour through action script was a waste of time but nobody could know that
so you can't you can't beat yourself up over that uh you just need to accept that not every choice
you make is going to be perfect maybe sort of keep a plan be in the back of your mind
but don't don't overthink it don't don't try to sort of don't don't create a spreadsheet with like
where you're trying to estimate well if i learn this language i expect to make x million dollars
in a lifetime and if i learn that language i expect to make y million dollars in a lifetime
and which which is higher and what which has more risk and where is the chance that it's like
picking picking a stock kind of kind of but uh i think with stocks you can do diversifying your
investment is good with productivity in life boy that spreadsheet is possible to construct
like if you actually carefully analyze what your interests in life are where you think you can
maximally impact the world there really is better and worse choices for programming language
that are not just about the syntax but about the community about where you predict the
community's headed what large systems are programmed in that but can you create that
spreadsheet because that's sort of you're mentioning a whole bunch of inputs that go
into that spreadsheet where you have to estimate things that are very hard to measure and even
harder i mean they're they're hard to measure retroactively and they're even harder to predict
like what is the better community well better is is one of those incredibly difficult words
what's better for you is not better for someone else no but we're not doing a public
speech about what's better we're doing a personal spiritual journey i can determine a circle of
friends circle circle one and circle two and i can have a bunch of parties with one and a bunch
of parties with two and then write down or take a mental note of what made me happier right and
that you know you have if you're a machine learning person you want to say okay i want to build a
large company that does that is grounded in machine learning but also has a sexy interface
that has a large impact on the world what languages do i use you look at what facebook is using you
look at what twitter is using then you look at performant more newer languages like rust or you
look at languages that have taken that most of the community uses in machine learning space that's
python and you can like think through you can hang out and think through it and it's it's always a
invest and the the level of activity of the community is also really interesting like you
said c plus boss and python are super active in terms of the development of the language itself
but do you think that you can make objective choices there no no no but there's a gut you
build up like don't you don't you believe in that gut feeling oh everything is very subjective and
yes you most certainly can have a gut feeling and your gut can also be wrong that's why there are
billions of people because they're not all right i mean clearly there are more people
living in the bay area who have plans to sort of create a google sized company than there's
room in the world for google sized companies and they're going to have to duke it out in the market
the space and there's many more choices than just the programming language speaking of which
let's go back to the boat with the with the fisherman who's tuned out long ago
let's talk to the programmer let's jump around and go back to c python that we tried to define
as the reference implementation and one of the big things that's coming out in 3.11 what's the
right way to we tend to say 3.11 because it really was like we went 3.8 3.9 3.10 3.11 and
we're planning to go up to 3.99 99 what happens after 99 probably just 3.100 what if i make it
there okay and go all the way to 4.20 i got it forever python v3 we'll talk about four but more
for fun so 3.11 is coming out one of the big sexy things in it is it'll be much faster so how
did you beyond hiring a great team or working with a great team make it faster what are some ideas
uh that me makes it faster it has to do with simplicity of software versus performance
and so even though c is known to be a low-level language which is great for writing sort of
a high performance language interpreter when i originally started python or c python i
didn't expect there would be great success and fame in my future uh so i i try to get something
working and useful uh in about three months and so i i sort of i cut corners
i borrowed ideas left and right when it comes to language design as well as implementation
uh i also wrote much of the code as simple as it could be and there there are like there are
many things that you can code more efficiently by adding more code it's a bit of a sort of a time
space trade-off where you can compute a certain thing from a small number of inputs
and every time you get presented with a new input you do the whole computation from the top
that can be simple looking code it's easy to understand it's easy to reason about that you
you can tell quickly that it's correct at least in the sort of mathematical sense of correct
because it's implemented in c maybe it performs relatively well but over time as sort of
as the requirements for that code and the need for performance go up you might be able to rewrite
that same algorithm using more memory maybe remember previous results so you don't have to
recompute everything from scratch like the the classic example is computing prime numbers like
is 10 a prime number well you sort of is it divisible by two is it divisible by three is
it divisible by four and we go all the way to is it divisible by nine and it is not well actually
10 is divisible by two so there we stop at say 11 it's divisible by 10 the answer is nine is no
10 times in a row so now we know 11 is a prime number on the other hand if we already know that
two three five and seven are prime numbers and you know a little bit about the mathematics of
how prime numbers work you know that if you have a rough estimate for the square root of 11
you don't actually have to check is it divisible by four or is it divisible by five you all you
have to check in the case of 11 is is it divisible by two is it divisible by three because take 12
if it's divisible by four well 12 divided by four is three so you you should have come across the
question is it divisible by three first so if you know basically nothing about prime numbers
except the definition maybe you go for x from two through n minus one is n divisible by x
and then at the end if you got uh all knows uh for every single one of those questions
you know oh it must be a prime number well the first thing is you can stop iterating when you
find a yes answer and the second is you can also stop iterating when you had have reached
the square root of n because you know that if it has a divisor larger than than the square root
did not also have a divisor smaller than the square root then you say oh except for two
we don't need to bother with checking for even numbers because all even numbers are divisible
by two so if it's divisible by four we would already have come across the question is it
divisible by two and so now you go special case check is it divisible by two and then you just
check three five seven eleven uh and so now you you sort of reduced your search space by 50% again
by skipping all the even numbers it kept for two if you think a bit more about it or you just
read in your book about the history of math one of the first algorithms ever written down
all you have to do is check is it divisible by any of the previous prime numbers that are
smaller than the square root and before you get to a better algorithm than that
you have to have several phd's in in discrete math so that's as much as i know
so of course that same story applies to a lot of other algorithms string matching is a good example
of how to come up with an efficient algorithm and sometimes yeah the more efficient algorithm
is not so much more complex than the inefficient one but that's an art and it's not always the case
in the general cases the more performant the algorithm the more complex it's going to be
there's a there's a kind of trade-off the simpler algorithms are also the ones that people invent
first because when you're looking for a solution you look at the simplest way to get there first
and so if there is a simple solution even if it's not the best solution not the fastest
or the memory most memory efficient or whatever a simple solution and simple is is fairly subjective
but mathematicians have also thought about sort of what is a good definition for simple in the
case of algorithms but the simpler the simpler solutions tend to be easier to follow for other
programmers who haven't made a study of a particular field and when i when i started with python i
i was a good programmer in general i knew sort of basic data structures and knew the c-language
pretty well but there were many areas where i was only somewhat familiar with the state of the art
and so i i picked in many cases the simplest way i could solve a particular sub problem because
when you when you're designing and implementing a language you have to like you have many hundreds
of little problems to solve and you have to have solutions for every one of them
before you can can sort of say i've invented the programming language
first of all so c python what kind of things does it do it's an interpreter it takes in this
readable language that we talked about that is python what is it supposed to do the interpreter
basically it it's sort of a recipe for understanding recipes so instead of a recipe that says bake me
a cake we have a recipe for well given the text of a program how do we run that program and and
that is sort of the recipe for building a computer the recipe for the baker and the chef yeah what are
the algorithmically tricky things that happen to be low hanging fruit that could be improved on
maybe throughout the history of python but also now how is it possible that 3.11 in year 2022
it's possible to get such a big performance improvement we focused
on a few areas where we we still felt there was low hanging fruit the biggest one is actually
the interpreter itself and this has to do with details of how python is defined so
i don't know if the fisherman is going to follow this story he already he already jumped off the
boat he's he's he's he's a board yeah stupid python is actually even though it's always called an
interpreted language it's there's also a compiler in there it just doesn't compile to machine code
it compiles to bytecode which is sort of code for an imaginary computer that is called the python
interpreter so it's compiling code that is more easily digestible by the interpreter or is digestible
it is the code that is digested by the interpreter that's the compiler we tweaked
very minor bits of the compiler almost all the work was done in the interpreter because
when you have a program you compile it once and then you run the code a whole bunch of times
or maybe there's one function in the in the code that gets run many times
uh now i know that that's sort of people who who know this field are expecting me to at some point
say we built a just-in-time compiler actually we didn't we just made the interpreter uh a little
more efficient what's a just-in-time compiler that is a thing from the java world although it's
now applied to almost all programming languages especially interpreted ones so you see the
compiler inside python not like a just-in-time compiler but it's a compiler that creates bytecode
that is then fed to the interpreter and the compiler was there something interesting to
say about the compiler it's interesting that you haven't changed that tweaked out at all or much
we changed some parts of the bytecode but not very much and so we only had to change the parts of
the compiler where we decided that the the breakdown of a python program in bytecode instructions had
to be slightly different uh but that didn't that didn't gain us the performance uh improvements
that performance improvements were like making the interpreter faster in part by sort of removing
the fat from some internal data structures used by the interpreter but uh the the key idea is an
adaptive specializing interpreter let's go what is adaptive about it what is specialized about it
well let me first talk about the specializing part because the adaptive part is the sort of
the second order effect but they're both important so bytecode is a bunch of machine
instructions but it's an imaginary machine but the machine can do things like call a function
add two numbers print a value those are sort of typical instructions in python
and if we take the example of adding two numbers actually in python the language there's no such
thing as adding two numbers there's just the the compiler uh doesn't know that you're adding two
numbers you might as well be adding two strings or two lists uh or two instances of some user-defined
class that happen to implement this operator called add that's a very interesting and and
fairly powerful mathematical concept it's mostly a user interface trick because it means that
a certain category of functions uh can be written using a symbols single symbol the plus sign
and sort of a bunch of other functions can be written using another single symbol the multiply
sign uh so if we take addition the way traditionally in python the add bytecode was executed is
pointers pointers and more pointers so first we we we have two objects an object is basically
a pointer to a bunch of memory that contains more pointers pointers all the way down well not quite
but there there are a lot of them so to simplify a bit uh we look up in one of the objects
what is the type of that object and does that object type define an add operation
and so you can imagine that there is a sort of a type integer that knows how to add itself to
another integer and there is a type floating point number that knows how to add itself to
another floating point number and the integers and floating point numbers are sort of important
I think mostly historically because in the first computers uh you used the sort of the same bit
pattern when interpreted as a floating point number had a very different value than when
interpreted as an integer can ask a dumb question here please do given the basics of int and float
and add who carries the knowledge of how to add two integers is it the integer it's the type integer
versus it's the type integer and the type float what about the operator is the operator just
exist as a platonic form possessed by the integer the operator is more like
it's an index in a list of functions that the integer type defines and so the integer type
is really a collection of functions and there is an add function and there's a multiply function
and there are like 30 other functions for other operations there's a power function for example
and you can imagine that in in memory there is a distinct slot for the add operations let's say the
add operation is the first operation of a type and the multiply is the second operation of a type
so now we take the integer type and we take the floating point type
uh in both cases the add operation is the first slot and multiply is the second slot
but each slot contains a function and the functions are different because the the add
to integers function interprets the bit patterns as integers the add to float function interprets the
same bit pattern as as a floating point number and then there is the string
data type which again interprets the the bit pattern as the address of a of a sequence of
characters there are lots of lies in that story but that's that's that's sort of a basic idea
I could tell I could tell the fact the fake news and the fabrication going out here at the table
but uh where's the optimization is it on the operators is it different
so the optimization is the observation that in a particular line of code
so now you you write your little python program and you write a function and that function sort of
takes a bunch of inputs and at some point it adds two of the inputs together now I bet you even if
you call your function a thousand times that all those calls are likely all going to be about integers
because maybe your program is all about integers or maybe on that particular line of code where
that there's that plus operator every time the program hits that line the variables a and b
that b are being added together happen to be strings and so what we do is instead of having
this single byte code that says here's an ad operation and the implementation of ad is fully
generic it looks at the object from the object it looks at the type then it takes the type and it
looks at looks up the function pointer then it calls the function now the function has to be
has to look at the other argument and has to double check that the other argument has the
right type and then there's a bunch of error checking before it can actually just go ahead
and add the two bit patterns in the right way what we do is every time we execute an ad instruction
like that we we keep a little note of in the end after after we hit the code that that did the addition
for a particular type what type was it and then after a few times through that code if it's this
same type all the time we say oh so this ad operation even though it's the generic ad operation
it might as well be the ad integer operation and the ad integer operation is much more efficient
because it just says assume that a and b are integers do the addition operation do it right
there in line and produce the result and the big lie here is that in python even if you have great
evidence that in the past it was always two integers that you were adding at some point in
the future that same line of code could still be hit with two floating points or two strings or maybe
a string and an integer it's not a great lie that's just the fact of life i didn't account for what
should happen in that case in in the way i told the story there is some accounting for and and so
what we actually have to do is when we have the ad integer operation we still have to check
are the two arguments in fact integers we applied some tricks to make those checks efficient
and we know statistically that the outcome is almost always yes they were they are both integers
and so we quickly make that check and then we proceed with the the sort of ad integer operation
and then there is a fallback mechanism where we say oops one of them wasn't an integer
now we're going to pretend that there was just the fully generic ad operation we wasted a few
cycles believing it was what was going to be two integers and then we had to back up
but we didn't waste that much time and statistically most of the time basically we were we're sort of
hoping that most of the time we guess right because if we if it turns out that we guessed wrong too
often uh or we didn't have a good guess at all uh things might actually end up running a little
slower so someone with armed with this knowledge and a copy of the implementation someone could
easily construct a counter example where they say oh i have a program and now it runs five
times as slow in python 3 11 than it did in python 3 10 but that's a very unrealistic program that's
that's just like an extreme fluke it's a fun reverse engineering task though oh yeah so there's a
people like fun yes so there's some presumably heuristic of what defines the momentum of
saying you know you seem to be working adding two integers not two generic types uh so
how do you figure out that heuristic i think that the heuristic is actually we assume that the
weather tomorrow is going to be the same as the weather today so you don't need two days of the
weather no that is already so much better than than than guessing randomly that so how do you
find this idea hey i wonder if instead of adding two generic types we uh start assuming that the
weather tomorrow is the same as the weather today where do you find the idea for that because that
ultimately for you to do that you have to kind of understand how people are using the language
right python is not the first language to do a thing like this this is a fairly well known trick
especially from other interpreted languages that had reason to be sped up we occasionally
look at papers about hhvm which is for facebook's efficient compiler for php there are tricks known
from the jvm and sometimes it just comes from academia so the trick here is that the type itself
doesn't the variable doesn't know what type it is so this is not a statically typed language where you
can you can get afford to have a shortcut to saying it's ints this is a trick that is especially
important for uh for interpreted languages with dynamic typing because if if the compiler could
read in the source these x and y that we're adding are integers the compiler can just
insert the single add machine code that hardware machine instruction that exists
on every cpu and ditto for floats but because in python you don't generally declare your the
types of your variables you you don't even declare the existence of your variables they just spring
into existence when you first assign them which is really cool and and sort of helps those beginners
because there is less bookkeeping they have to learn how to do before they can start playing
around with code but it makes the the interpretation of the code less efficient and so we're we're sort of
trying to to make the interpretation more efficient without losing the the super dynamic nature of
the language that's always the challenge 3.5 got the pep 484 type hints what is type hinting and
is it used by the interpreter the hints or is it just syntactic sugar so the type hints is an optional
mechanism that people can use and it's especially popular with sort of larger companies that have
very large code bases written in python do you think of it as almost like documentation saying
these two variables are this type more than documentation i mean so it it it is a sub language
of python where where you can express the types of variables so here's a variable and it's an
integer and here's an argument to this function and it's a string and here is a function that
returns a list of strings but that's not checked when you run the code but exactly there there is a
separate piece of software called a static type checker that reads all your source code without
executing it and thinks long and hard about what it looks from just reading the code that code
might be doing and double checks if that makes sense if you take the types as annotated into
account so this is something you're supposed to run as you develop it's like a linter yeah that's
definitely a development tool but the type annotations currently are not used for speeding up the
interpreter and there are a number of reasons uh many people don't use them even when they do use them
they sometimes contain lies where the static type checker says everything's fine
i cannot prove that this integer is ever not an integer but at runtime somehow someone
manages to violate that assumption and the interpreter ends up doing just fine if we
started enforcing type annotations in python many python programs would no longer work
and some python programs wouldn't even be possible because they're too dynamic
and so we made we made the choice of not using the annotations there there is a possible future
where eventually three four five releases in the future we could start using those annotations to
sort of provide hints because we can we can still say well the source code leads us to
believe that these x and y are both integers and so we can generate an add an add integer instruction
but we can still have a fallback that says oh if the if somehow the code
coded runtime provided something else maybe it provided two decimal numbers
we can still use that generic add operation as a fallback but we're not there is there currently
a mechanism or do you see something like that where you can almost add like an assert inside
a function that says please check that my type hints are actually mapping to reality
sort of like insert manual static typing there are third party libraries that are in that business
it's possible to do that kind of thing it's possible to for a third party library to take a hint
and enforce it seems like a tricky thing but what what what we actually do is and this I think
this is a fairly unique feature in python the type hints can be introspective at runtime
so while the program is running they mean python is a very introspective language you can look at
a variable and ask yourself what the what is the type of this this variable and if that maybe
that variable happens to refer to a function you can ask what are the arguments to the function
and nowadays you can also ask what are the type annotations for the function
so the type annotations are there inside the variable as it's at runtime they're mostly associated
with the function object not with each individual variable but uh right you can sort of map from
from the arguments to the variables and that's what a third party library can help exactly and
the problem with that is that all that extra runtime type checking uh is going to slow your
code down instead of speed it up I think uh to reference this uh sales pitchy blog post
that says 75% of developers time is spent on debugging I would say that in some cases that
might be okay it might be okay to pay the cost of performance for the catching of the types
the type errors and in most cases doing it statically before you ship your code to production
is more efficient than doing it at runtime piecemeal yeah can you tell me about
my py my py project what is it what's the mission and in general what is the future
of static typing in python well so my py uh was started by a Finnish developer yuka letus hello
so many cool things out of Finland I gotta say just that part of the world I guess people have
nothing better to do in those long cold winters yeah I don't know I think yuka lived in England
when he invented that stuff actually but my py is the original static type checker for python
and the the type annotations that were introduced with pet 484 were sort of developed together
with the the static type checker and in fact yuka had first invented a different syntax
that wasn't quite compatible with python and uh yuka and I sort of met at a python conference
in I think in 2013 and we we sort of came up with a compromise syntax that would not require any
changes to python and that would let my py sort of be an add-on static type checker for python
just out of curiosity was it like double colon or something what was he proposing that would break
python I think he was using angular brackets for uh types like in c++ or uh java generics yeah you
can't use angular brackets in python it'll be too tricky for temp well we the the key thing is that
we already had uh no uh syntax for annotations we just didn't know what to use them for yet
so type annotations were just the sort of most logical thing to to use that existing dummy
syntax for but there was no there was no syntax for uh defining generics directly syntactically
in the language my py literally meant my version of python where my it refers to yuka he had a
parser that translated my py into python by like doing the type checks and then
removing the annotations and all the angular brackets uh from the positions where where he
was using them but a preprocessor model doesn't work very well with the typical workflow of
python development projects that's funny I mean that could have been another major split if it
became successful like uh if you watch typescript versus javascript is like a split in the community
over types right that seems to be stabilizing now it's not necessarily a split there are certainly
plenty of people who don't use typescript but just use the original javascript notation just
like there are many people in the python world who don't use type annotations and don't use static
type checkers now you know but there is a bit of a split between typescript and javas old school
javascript es whatever well in the javascript world transpilers are sort of the standard way of
working anyway which is why typescript being a transpiler itself is not a big deal and transpilers
for people who don't know it's what's the exact thing you said with my py it's the code I guess
you call preprocessing code that translates from one language to the other and that's part of the
culture part of the workflow of the javascript community so that's right at the same time
an interesting development in the javascript slash typescript world at the moment is that
there is a proposal under consideration it's only a stage one proposal that proposes to add a feature
to javascript where just like python it will ignore certain syntax when running the javascript code
and what it ignores is more or less a superset of the typescript annotation syntax
interesting so that would mean that eventually if you wanted to you could take typescript
and you could shove it directly into a javascript interpreter without
translation the interesting thing in the javascript world at least the web browser world
the web browsers have changed how they deploy and they they sort of update their javascript engines
much more quickly than they used to in the the early days and so there's much less of a need for
translation in javascript itself because most browsers just support the most recent version
of ECMAScript just an attention of attention do you see if you will recommend somebody use a thing
would you recommend typescript or javascript i would recommend typescript just because of the
strictness of the typing it's an enormously helpful extra tool that helps you sort of
keep your head straight about what your code is actually doing i mean it's it's it
it helps with editing your code it helps with ensuring that your code is not too incorrect
and it's actually quite compatible with javascript never mind this syntactic
sort of hack that is still years in the future but any library that is written in pure javascript
can still be used from typescript programs and also the other way around you can write a library
in typescript and then export it in a form that is totally consumable by javascript that sort of
compatibility is is sort of the key to this to the success of typescript yeah just to look at
it it's almost like a biological system that's evolving it's fascinating to see javascript
evolve the way it does well maybe we should consider that biological systems are just
engineering systems too right yes just very advanced with with more history but it's almost
like the most visceral in the javascript world because there's just so much code written in
javascript that for its history was messy if you talk about bugs per line of code i just feel like
javascript eats the cake or whatever the terminology is it beats python by a lot in terms of the number
of bugs meaning like way more bugs in javascript and then and then the obviously the browsers
just there's so much active development it feels a lot more like evolution where a bunch of stuff
is born and dies and there's experimentation debates versus python there's more all that stuff is
happening but there's just a longer history of stable working giant software systems written in
python versus javascript is just a giant beautiful i would say mess of code it's very different culture
and to some extent differences in culture are random but to some extent they the differences
have to do with the environment yeah and the fact that javascript is primarily
the language for developing web applications especially the client side and the fact that it's
basically the only language for developing web applications makes that community sort of just
have a different nature than the community of other languages plus the graphical component
and the fact that they're deploying it on all kinds of shapes of screens and devices and all
that kind of stuff it just creates a beautiful chaos anyway back to my pie so what okay you
met you talked about a syntax that could work where does it currently stand
what's the future static typing in python it is still controversial but it is much more accepted
than when my pie and pep 484 were were young what's the connection between pep 484 type hints
and my pie my pie was the original static type checker so it my pie quickly evolved from yuka's
own variant of python to a static type checker for python and sort of pep 484 that that was it like
a very productive year where like many hundreds of messages were exchanged debating the merits
of every aspect of of that pep and so my pie is a static type checker for python it is itself
written in python most additional static typing features that we introduced in the time since 36
uh were also prototyped through my pie my pie being an open source project with a very small
number of maintainers it was successful enough that people said this static type checking stuff
for python is actually worth an investment for our company nice but somehow they chose not to support
making my pie faster say or adding new features to my pie but both google and facebook and later
microsoft developed their own static type checker i think facebook was one of the first they
decided that they wanted to use the same technology that they had successfully used for uh hhvm
because they they sort of they had a bunch of compiler writers and and sort of static
type checking experts who had written the hhvm compiler and it was a big success within the
company and they had done it in a certain way sort of they wrote a big highly parallel application
in an obscure language named oh camel which is apparently mostly very good for writing static
type checkers interesting i have a lot of questions about how to write a static type
checker then that's very confusing facebook wrote their version and they worked on it
in secret for about a year and then they came clean and went open source uh google in the meantime
was developing something called pie type which was mostly interesting because it as you may have
heard they have one gigantic monorepo so all the code is checked into a single repository facebook
has a different approach so facebook developed pyre which which was written in oh camel which
worked well with facebook's development workflow uh google developed something they called py type
which was actually itself written in python uh and it was meant to sort of fit well in
their static type checking needs in google's gigantic monorepo so google was in one giant
got it so the just to clarify this static type checker philosophically is the thing that's
supposed to exist outside of the language itself and it's just a workflow like a debugger for the
program it's a linter for people who don't know a linter maybe you can correct me but it's it's a
thing that runs through the code continuously preprocessing to find issues based on style
documentation i mean there's all kinds of linters right it can check that what usual
things does a linter do maybe check that you haven't too many characters in a single line
linters often do static analysis where they try to point out things that are likely mistakes but
not incorrect according to the language specification like maybe you have a variable that you never use
for the compiler that is valid you might sort of you might be planning to use it in a future
version of the of the code and the compiler might just optimize it out but the compiler's not going
to tell you hey you're never using this variable a linter will tell you that variable is not used
maybe there's a typo somewhere else where you're meant to use it but you accidentally use something
else or there are a number of sort of common scenarios and a linter is often
a big collection of little heuristics where by looking at the combination of how your code is
laid out maybe how it's indented maybe the common structure but also just things like definition
of names use of names it'll tell you likely things that are wrong and in some cases linters are
are really style checkers uh for python there are a number of linters that check things like
do you use the the pep8 recommended naming scheme for your functions and classes and variables
because like classes start with an uppercase and the rest starts with a lower case and
there's like differences there and so the linter can tell you hey you have a class that uh whose
first letter is not an uppercase letter and that's just i just find it annoying if i wanted that to
be an uppercase letter i i would have typed an uppercase letter but other people find it very
comforting that if the linter is no longer complaining about their code that they have
followed all the style rules maybe it's a fast way for a new developer joining a team to learn
the style rules right yeah there's definitely that but the best use of a linter is probably
not so much to to sort of enforce team uniformity but to actually help developers
catch bugs that the compilers for whatever reason don't catch and there is lots of that in python
and so uh but aesthetic type checker focuses on uh a particular aspect of the linting which
i mean it might probably doesn't care how you name your classes and variables
but it is meticulous about when you say that there was an integer here and you're passing
a string there it will tell you hey that string is not an integer so something's wrong either
either you were incorrect when you said it was an integer or you're incorrect when you're passing
into string if this is a race of static type checkers there's somebody winning as you said
it's interesting that the companies didn't choose to invest in this centralized development
of mypi is is is there a future for mypi what do you see is that well one of the companies
went out and everybody uses like a py type whatever google's is called well microsoft is hoping that
microsoft's horse in that race called py right is going to win py right right like ri ghd correct
yeah my my all my word processors tend to type out correct that as py right the name of the i don't
know what it is some kind of semi precious metal oh right i love it okay so okay that's the microsoft
hope but okay so let me ask the question a different way is there going to be ever a future
whereas the static type checker gets integrated into the language
nobody is currently excited about doing any work towards that that doesn't mean that five
or ten years from now the situation isn't different at the moment all the static type checkers
still evolve at a much higher speed than python and its annotation syntax evolve you get a new
release of python once a year those are the only times that you can introduce new annotation
syntax and there's there are always people who invent new new annotation syntax that they're
trying to push uh and worse once we've all agreed that we are going to put some new syntax in we
can never take it back at least a sort of deprecating an existing feature takes many releases because
you have to assume that people started using it as soon as we announced it and then you can't take
it away from them right away you have to start telling them well this will go away but we're not
gonna tell you that it's an error yet and then later it's going to be a warning and then eventually
three releases in the future maybe we remove it on the other hand the typical static type checker
still has a release like
every month every two months certainly many times a year uh some type checkers also
include a bunch of experimental ideas that aren't official standard python syntax yet
the static type checkers also just get better at discovering things that that sort of are
unspecified by the language but that sort of could make sense and so each static type checker actually
has it's sort of strong and weak points so it's cool it's like a laboratory of experiments yeah
microsoft google and all and you get to see and you see that everywhere right because there's not
one single uh java script in engine either there is one in chrome there is one in safari there's one
in firefox but that said you said there's not interest i think there is a lot of interest in
type hinting right uh in the pep 484 actually like how many people use that do you have a sense
how many people use because it's optional this is sugar i can't put a number on it but
from the number of packages that do interesting things with it at runtime and the fact that there
are like now three or four very mature type checkers that each have their their segment
of the market and oh and then there is a pie charm which has a sort of more heuristic based
type checker that also supports the same syntax my assumption is that many many people developing
python software professionally for some kind of production situation are using a static type
checker especially any anybody who has a continuous integration cycle probably has uh one of the steps
in in there they're testing routine that that happens for basically every every commit uh is
run a static type checker and in most in most cases that will be my pie
so i think it's pretty popular topic according to this web page 20 to 30 of python three code
bases are using type hints wow i wonder how they measured that did they just scan all of github
yeah that's what it looks like yeah they did a quick sent not all of but like a random sampling
so you mentioned pie charm let me ask you the uh the big subjective question
what's the best ide for python and you're extremely biased now that you're with microsoft
is it pie charm vs code vim or emacs historically i actually started out with using vim but when
it was still called vi uh for a very long time i think from the early 80s to uh i'd say two years ago
i was emacs user nice between i'd say 2013 and 2018 i dabbled with pie charm uh mostly because it had
had a couple of features i mean pie charm is like driving an 18-wheeler truck whereas emacs is more
like driving your comfortable Toyota car that's that's that you've had for 100,000 miles and you
know what every little rattle of the car means i was very comfortable in emacs but there were
certain things it couldn't do it wasn't very good at that sort of at least the way i had configured it
i didn't have very good tooling in emacs for finding the definition of a function
got it when i was at Dropbox exploring a five million line python code base
uh just grabbing all that code for where there where is there a class foobar well turns out that
if you grab all five million lines of code there are many classes with the same name
and so pie charm sort of once once you fired it up and once it's indexed your repository
was very helpful but the soonest i had to edit code i would jump back to emacs and do all my
editing there because i could type much faster and switch between files when i when i knew which
file i wanted much much quicker and i never really got used to the the whole pie charm user interface
yeah i feel torn in that same kind of way because i've used pie charm off and on exactly in that
same way and i feel like i'm just being an old grumpy man for not learning how to quickly
switch between files and all that kind of stuff i feel like that has to do with shortcuts that has
to do with um i mean you just have to get accustomed just like with touch typing yeah you have to just
want to to learn that i mean if you don't need it much you don't need touch typing either you can
type with two fingers just fine in the short term but in the long term your life will become better
psychologically and productivity wise if you learn how to type with 10 fingers if you do a lot of
keyboard input before everyone emails and stuff right like you look at the the next 20 30 years of
your life you have to anticipate where technology is going um do you want to invest in handwriting
notes probably not more and more people are doing typing versus handwriting notes so you can anticipate
that so there's no reason to actually practice handwriting there's more reason to practice typing
you can actually estimate back to the spreadsheet the number of paragraphs sentences or words you'll
write for the rest of your life you can probably go again with the spreadsheet of my life i mean
all of that is not actual like converted to a spreadsheet but the gut feeling
like i have the same kind of gut feeling about books i've almost exclusively switched to kindle
now for ebook readers even though i still love and probably always will the smell the feel of a
physical book and you the reason i switched to kindle is like all right well this is really paving
the future is going to be digital in terms of consuming books and content of that nature so
you should get you know you should let your brain get accustomed to that experience and that same
way it feels like pie charm or vs code i think pie charm is is the most sort of sophisticated
feature full uh python id it feels like i should probably at some point very soon switch entire
like i'm not allowed to use anything else for python than this id or vs code it doesn't matter
but walk away from emacs for this particular application because i think i'm limiting myself
in the same way that using two fingers for typing is limiting myself it's i'm this is a therapy
session this is i'm not even but i'm sure a lot of people are thinking i'm not gonna stop you uh i
i think that that's sort of everybody has to decide for themselves which one they want to
invest more time in i actually ended up giving vs code a very tentative try when i started out at
microsoft and really liking it and it sort of it took me a while before i realized why that was
but and and i think that actually the founders of vs code may not necessarily agree with me on this
but to me vs code is in a sense the spiritual successor of emacs because as you probably know
as an old emacs hack the the key part of emacs is that it it's mostly written in in lisp and
that that's sort of new features of of emacs usually update all the list packages and add new
list packages and oh yeah there's also some very obscure thing improved in the part that's not in
lisp but that's usually not why you would upgrade to a new version of emacs there's a core implementation
that that sort of can read a file and it can put bits on the screen and it can sort of manage
memory and buffers and then what makes it an editor full of features is all the list packages
and of course the design of how the list packages interact with each other and with that that sort
of that base layer of the core immutable engine but almost everything in that core engine in emacs
case can still be overridden or replaced and so vs code has a similar architecture where there is
like a base engine that you have no control over i mean it's open source but nobody
except the people who work on that part changes it much and it has a sort of a package manager
and a whole series of interfaces for packages and an additional series of conventions for how
packages should interact with the lower layers and with each other and powerful primitive operations
that let you move the cursor around or select pieces of text or delete pieces of text or
interact with the keyboard and the mouse and whatever peripherals you have
and and so the sort of the the extreme extensibility and the package ecosystem
that you that you see in vs code is a mirror of very similar architectural features in emacs
well i'll have to give it a serious try because as far as sort of the hype and the excitement
in the general programming community vs code seems to dominate the interesting thing about
our pie charm and what is it php storm which are these jetbrains specific ids that are designed
for one programming language it's interesting to when an ids are specialized right they're usually
actually just specializations of intelligent because underneath it's all the same editing
engine with different veneer on top where in vs code many things you do require loading
third-party extensions in pie charm it is possible to have third-party extensions
but it is it is a struggle to create one yes it's not part of the culture all that kind of stuff
yeah we that i remember that might have been five years ago or so we were trying to get
some better my pie integration into pie charm because my pie is sort of python tooling and pie
charm had had its own type checking heuristic thing that we wanted to replace with uh something
based on my pie because that was what we were using in the company and it for the for the guy
who was writing that by charm extension it was really a struggle to to sort of find documentation
and get the development workflow going and and debug his code and all that so that that was
was not a pleasant experience let me talk to you about parallelism in your post titled
reasoning about asyncio semaphore you talk about a fast food restaurant in silicon valley that
has only one table is this a real thing i just wanted to ask you about that is that just like a
metaphor you're using or is that an actual restaurant in silicon valley it was it was a
metaphor of course okay i can imagine such a restaurant so for people who don't then read the
thing you should you should but it was a idea of a restaurant where there's only one table and you
show up one at a time and they are prepared and actually looked it up and there is restaurants
like this throughout the world and it just seems like a fascinating idea you stand in line you show
up there's one table they um they ask you all kinds of questions they cook just for you that's
fascinating it sounds like you'd find places like that in tokyo it sounds like a very japanese thing
or in the bay area there are pop of places that probably more or less work like that but i've
never eaten at such a place the fascinating thing is you propose is a fast food this is all for burger
it was one of my rare sort of more literary or poetic moments where i thought i'll i'll just open
with a crazy example to catch your attention and the rest is very dry stuff about uh locks and
semaphores and how a semaphore is a generalization of a lock well it was very poetic and well
delivered and it actually made me wonder if it's real or not because you don't make that explicit
and it feels like it could be true and in fact i wouldn't be surprised if somebody like
listens to this and knows exactly a restaurant like this in silicone valley anyway can we step back
and can you just talk about parallelism concurrency threading asynchronous all these different terms
what is it sort of a high philosophical level the uh the fisherman is back in the boat well
the idea is if the fisherman has uh two fishing rods uh since fishing is mostly a matter of waiting
for a fish to nibble well it depends on how you do it actually but if you had to if if you're doing
the style of fishing where you sort of you you throw it out and then you let it sit for a while
until maybe you see a nibble one fisherman can easily run two or three or four fishing rods and
so as long as you can afford the equipment you can catch four times as many fish by a small
investment in four fishing rods and so you since your time you sort of say you have all saturday
to go fishing if you can catch four times as much fish you have a much higher productivity
and that's actually i think how deep sea fishing is done you could just have a rod and you put in
a hole so you can have many rods uh what is there an interesting difference between parallelism and
concurrency and asynchronous is there one that's upset of the other to you like how do you think
about these terms in the computer world there is a big difference when people are talking about
parallelism like a parallel computer that's usually really several complete cpus that are
sort of tied together and and share something like memory or an iobus concurrency can be a much
more abstract concept where you have the illusion that things happen simultaneously but what the
computer actually does is it spends a little time running some this program for a while and
then it spends some time running that program for a while and then spending some time for the third
program for a while so parallelism is the reality and concurrency is part reality part
illusion yeah parallelism typically implies that there is multiple copies of the hardware
you write that implementing synchronization primitives is hard in that blog post and you
talk about locks and semaphores why is it hard to implement synchronization primitives because
at the conscious level our brains are not trained to to sort of keep track of multiple things
at the same time like obviously you can walk and chew gum at the same time because they're both
activities that require only a little bit of your conscious activity but try balancing your
checkbook and watching a murder mystery on tv yeah you'll mix up the digits or you'll miss
an essential clue on in the tv show so why does it matter that the programmer the human
is uh is bad because the programmer is at least with the current state of the art is responsible
for writing the code correctly and it's hard enough to keep track of a recipe that you just
execute one step at a time chop the carrots then peel the potatoes mix the icing you need your
whole brain when you're when you're reading a piece of code what what is going on okay we're
we're we're loading the number of mermaids in variable a and the number of mere men in variable
b and uh now we take the average or whatever uh i like we're just jumping from metaphor to metaphor
i like it you have to keep in your head what is in a what is in b what is in c uh hopefully you
have better names and that is challenging enough if you have two different pieces of code that are
are sort of being executed simultaneously whether it's using the parallel or the concurrent
approach if like a is the number of fishermen and b is the number of programmers but in another
part of the code a is the number of mermaids and b is the number of merman and somehow
that's the same variable if you do it sequentially if first you do your mermaids more people
computation and then you do your people in the boat computation it doesn't matter that the variables
are called a and b and that is literally the same variable because you you're done with one use of
that variable but when you mix them together suddenly the number of mere people replaces the
number of fishermen and your computation goes dramatically wrong and there's all kinds of ordering
of operations that could result in the assignment of those variables and so you have to anticipate
all possible orderings and you think you're smart and you'll put a look around it and in practice
in terms of bugs per line per thousand lines of code this is an area where everything is worse
so a lock is a mechanism by which you forbid only one chef can access the oven at a time
something like that and then semaphores allow you to do what multiple ovens that's not a bad
idea because if you're sort of if you're preparing if you're baking cakes and you have multiple people
all baking cakes but there's only one oven then maybe you can tell that the oven is in use but
maybe it's preheating and so you have to maybe maybe you make a sign that says oven in use
and you flip the sign over and it says oven is free when you're done baking your cake
and that's a lock that's sort of and and what do you do when you have two ovens or maybe you
have 10 ovens you you can put a separate sign on each oven or maybe you can sort of someone who
comes in wants to see at a glance and maybe there's an electronic sign that says there's
still five ovens available or maybe there are already three people waiting for an oven so you
can if you see an oven that's not in use it's already reserved for someone else who got in line
first and that's sort of what what what the restaurant metaphor was trying to explain
yeah and so you're now tasked you're sitting as a designer of python with a team of brilliant
core developers and you have to try to figure out to what degree can any of these ideas be
integrated and not so maybe this is a good time to ask what is a sync i o and how has it evolved
since python 3.4 wow yeah so we had this really old library for for doing things
concurrently especially things that had to do with i o and uh networking i o was especially
uh a sort of a popular topic and in the python standard library we had a brief period where
there was lots of development and i think it was late 90s maybe early 2000s and like
two little modules were added that were the state of the art of doing a synchronous i o or
sort of non-blocking a i o which means that you can keep multiple network connections open and
sort of service them all in parallel like a typical web server does so i o is input and
outputs you're writing either to the network yes the network connection or reading and writing to
hard drive the storage also possible and you can do uh the ideas you could do to multiple
while also doing computation so running some code that does some fancy stuff yeah like when
you're writing a web server when a request comes in a user the sort of needs to see a particular
web page uh you have to find that page maybe in the database and format it properly and send it
back to the client and there's a lot of waiting waiting for the database waiting for the network
and so you can handle hundreds or thousands or millions of requests concurrently on one machine
anyway waste of doing that in python were kind of stagnated and uh i forget it might have been around
2012 2014 uh when someone for the umpteenth time actually said these async chat and async core
modules that you have in the standard library are not quite enough to solve my particular problem
can we add one tiny little feature and everybody said no that stuff is not too but you're not
supposed to use that stuff write your own using uh third party library and then everybody started
the debate about what the right third party library was and somehow i i felt that there was
actually a queue for well maybe we need a better state of the art module in the standard library
for for multiplexing input output from different sources you could say that it spiraled out of
control a little bit it was at the time it was the largest python enhancement proposal that was
ever proposed and you were deeply involved with that at the time i was very much involved with
that i was like the lead architect uh i ended up talking to people who had already developed
serious third party libraries that did similar things and sort of taking ideas from them and
getting their feedback on my design and eventually we put it in the standard library and after a few
years i got distracted i think the thing the big thing that distracted me was actually type annotations
uh but other people kept it alive and kicking and it's been quite successful actually uh
in the world of python web clients so initially what are some of the design challenges there
in that debate for the pep and what are some things that got rejected what are some things that
got accepted to stand out to you there are a couple of different ways you can handle parallel i o and
this happens sort of at an architectural level in operating systems as well like windows prefers
to do it one way and unix prefers to do it the other way you sort of you have an object that
represents a network endpoint say a connection with a web browser that your client and say you're
you're waiting for an incoming request two fundamental approaches are okay i'm waiting
for an incoming request i'm doing something else come wake me up or of course sort of come tell me
when uh something interesting happened like a packet came in on that network connection
and the other paradigm is we're on a team of a whole bunch of people with maybe a little mind
and we we can only manage one web connection at a time so i'm just sitting looking at this
this web connection and i'm just blocked until something comes in and then uh i'm already waiting
for it uh i get i get the data i process the data and then i go back to the top and say no
sort of i'm waiting for the next packet those are about the two paradigms one is a paradigm
where there is sort of notionally a threat of control whether it's an actual operating system
thread or more an abstraction in asyncio we call them tasks but a task in asyncio or a
thread in other contexts is devoted to one thing and it has logic for all the stages like when it's
a web request like first wait wait for the first line of the web request parse it because then you
know if it's a get or a post or a put or whatever or an error then wait until you have a bunch of
lines until there's a blank line then parse that as headers and then interpret that and then wait
for the rest of the data to come in if there is any more that you request expect that sort of
standard web stuff and the other thing is and there's always endless debate about which approach
is more efficient and which approach is more error prone where i just have a whole bunch of stacks in
front of me and whenever a packet comes in i sort of look at the number of the pack that there's
some number on the packet and i say oh that packet goes on this pile and then i can do a little bit
and then sort of that pile provides my context and as soon as i'm done with with the processing i sort
of i can forget everything about what's going on because the next packet will come in from some
random other client and it's that pile or this pile uh and every time a pile is maybe empty or
full or whatever the criteria is i can toss it away or use it for a new space but several
traditional third party libraries for asynchronous i o processing in python chose the model of a
callback and that's that's the idea where you have a bunch of different stacks of paper in front of
you and every time someone gives you a piece gives you a new sheet you decide which stack it belongs
to and that leads to a certain style of spaghetti code that i find sort of aesthetically not pleasing
and i i was sort of never very successful and i had heard many stories about people who were also
sort of complaining about that style of coding uh it was very prevalent in javascript at the time
at least because it was like how the javascript event loop basically works and so i thought well
the task based model where each task has a bunch of logic we had mechanisms in the python language
that we could easily reuse for for that and i thought i want to build a whole library for
asynchronous networking i o uh and all the other things that may need to be done asynchronously
uh based on that paradigm and so i just chose a paradigm and try to see how far i could get
with that and it turns out that it's pretty good paradigm so people enjoy that kind of
paradigm programming for asynchronous i o relative to callbacks okay beautiful so how does that all
interplay with the infamous gill the goal the global interpreter lock maybe can you say what
the gill is and how does it dance beautifully with asynchio the global interpreter lock
solves the problem that python originally was not written with either asynchronous or or
parallelism in mind at all there was no concurrency in the language there was no
parallelism there were no threads only a small number of years into python's initial development
all the new cool operating systems like uh suno s and silicon graphics iris and then
eventually posix and windows all came with threading libraries that lets you do multiple
things in parallel and there is a certain certain sort of principle which is the operating system
handles the threads for you and the program can pretend that there are as many cpus as as there
are threads in the program and those cpus were completely independently and if you don't have
enough cpus the operating system sort of simulates those extra cpus on the other hand if you have
enough cpus you can get a lot of work done by deploying those multiple cpus but python wasn't
written to to do that and so
as libraries for for multi-threading were added to c but every operating system vendor was adding
their own version of that we thought and maybe we were wrong but at the time we thought well we
quickly want to be able to support these multiple threads because they seemed at the time in the
early 90s when they were new at least to me they seemed a cool interesting programming paradigm
and one of the things that that python at least at the time felt was nice about the language was
that we could give a safe version of all kinds of cool new operating system toys to the python
programmer like i remember one or two years before threading i i had spent some time adding
networking sockets to python and they were very literal translation of the networking sockets
that were in the bsd operating system so unix bsd but the nice thing was if you were using sockets
from python then all the things you can do wrong with sockets in c would automatically give you a
clear error message instead of just ending up with a malfunctioning hanging program and so we
thought well we'll do the same thing with threading but we didn't really want to rewrite the interpreter
to be thread safe because that that was was like that would be a very complex refactoring of all
the interpreter code and all the runtime code because all the objects were written with the
assumption that there's only one thread and so we said okay well we'll take our losses we'll provide
something that looks like threads and as long as you only have a single cpu on your computer
which most computers at the time did uh it feels just like threads because
the the whole idea of of multiple threads in the os was that even if your your computer only had
one cpu you could still fire up at many threads as you wanted well within reason maybe 10 or 12
not 5 000 and so we thought we had conquered the the abstraction of threads pretty well because
multi-core cpus were were not in in most python programmers hands anyway and then of course a
couple of more iterations of morse law and computers getting faster and at some point
uh the chip designers decided that they couldn't make the cpus faster but they could still make
them smaller and so they could put multiple cpus on one chip and suddenly there was all this pressure
about do things in parallel and that's where the the solution we had in python didn't work
and that's that's sort of the moment that the gill became became infamous because the gill the gill
was the solution we used to sort of take this single interpreter and share it between all the
different operating system threads that you could create and so as long as the the hardware
hardware physically only had one cpu that was all fine and then as hardware vendors were suddenly
telling us all oh you got to paralyze everything's got to be paralyzed people started saying oh uh
but we can use multiple threads in python and uh then they discovered oh but actually all threads
run on a single me a single core yeah i mean is there a way is there ideas in the future to remove
the global interpreter law gill like maybe multiple sub interpreters some tricky interpreters on top of
interpreters kind of thing yeah there there are a couple of possible uh futures there the
the most likely future is that we'll get multiple sub interpreters which each run a completely
independent python program nice but there there's still some benefit of of sort of faster communication
between those programs but it's also managing for you this running a multiple python programs
like yeah so it's hidden from you right the it's it's hidden from you but you have to spend more
time communicating between those programs because the sort of the attractive thing about the multi
threaded model is that the threads can share objects at the same time that's also the downfall
of the multi-threaded programming model because when you do share objects you weren't and you
didn't necessarily intend to share them or there were aspects of those objects that that were not
reusable you get all kinds of concurrency bugs and so the reason i wrote that little blog post
about semaphors was that concurrency bugs are just harder it would be nice if python had no
globally interpreter lock and it had the so-called free threading
but it would also cause a lot more software bugs the interesting thing is that there is still a
possible future where we are actually going to or where we could experiment at least with that
because there is a guy working for facebook who has developed a fork of c python that he called
the no gill interpreter where he removed the gill and made a whole bunch of optimizations
so that the single threaded case doesn't run too much slower and multi-threaded case will actually
use all the cores that you have
and so that that would be an interesting possibility if we would be willing as
python core developers to actually maintain that code indefinitely and if we're willing to put up
with the additional complexity of the interpreter and the additional sort of overhead for the single
threaded case and i'm personally not convinced that there are enough people needing the speed of
multiple threads with their python programs that it's worth to sort of take that performance
hit and that complexity hit and i i feel that the gill actually is a pretty nice
goldilocks point between no threads and all threads all the time but not everybody agrees on that
so that is definitely a possible future the sub interpreters look like a fairly safe bet for
312 so say a year from now a year so the goal is to do a new version every year
for python let me ask you perhaps a fun question but there's a philosophy to
will there ever be a python 4.0 now before you say it's currently a joke and probably not
we're going to go to 3.99 or 3.99999 can you imagine possible features
that python 4.0 might have that would necessitate the creation of the new 4.0 given the amount of
pain and joy suffering and triumph that was involved in the move between version 2 and version 3
yeah well we're we as a community and as a core development team we have a large amount of
painful memories about the python 3.0 transition which is one reason that sort of
everybody is happy that we've decided there's not going to be a 4.0 at least
not anytime soon and if there is going to be one it will sort of plan the transition very
differently because clearly we underestimated the pain that transition caused for our users
in the python 3.0 case and had we known we could have sort of designed python 3.0 somewhat
differently without making it any worse we just thought that we had a good plan but we
underestimated where what what sort of the users were capable of when it comes to that kind of
transition by the way i think we talked way before like a year and a half before the python 2
officially end of life end of life oh yeah what was that what was your memory of the end of life
did you shed a tear on january 1st 2020 that was there everyone standing alone the core team had
basically moved on years before yeah it was it was purely it was a little symbolic moment
to signal to the the remaining users that
there was no longer going to be any new releases or support for python 2.7
did you shed a single tear while looking out over the horizon
i'm not not a very poetic person and i don't shed tears like that but no
now we we actually had planned a party but the party was planned for the python con the
us python conference that year which would never happened of course because of the pandemic
oh is it like a march yeah the conference was uh going to be i think late april that year
so that that was a very difficult decision to cancel it but
they did so anyway if we're going to have a python 4 we're going to have to have both a
different reason for for having that and a different process for managing the transition
can you imagine a possible process that so so i think you're implying that if there is a 4.0 in
some ways it would break back compatibility well so here is here is a concrete thought i've had
and i'm not unique but not everyone agrees with this so this is definitely a personal opinion
if we were to try something like that no gill python uh my expectation is that
it would feel just different enough at least for the the part of the python ecosystem that
is heavily based on c extensions and that is like the entire machine learning data science
scientific python world is all based on c extensions for python and so those people would likely
feel the pain the most because they even if we don't change anything about the syntax of the
language and the semantics of the language when you're writing python code we we could even say
suppose that after python say 319 instead of 320 we'll have 4.0 suppose that's the time when we
flip the switch to 4.0 will will not have a gill imagine it was like that so i would probably
say that particular year the release that we named 4.0 will be syntactically it will not have any
new syntactical features no new modules in the standard library no new built-in functions
everything will be at the python level will be purely compatible with python 3.19 however
extension modules will have to make a change they will have to be recompiled they will not
have the same binary interface the semantics and and apis for for some things that are
frequently accessed by c extensions will be different and so for a pure python user
4.0 would be a breeze except that there are very few pure python users left because
everybody who is using python for something significant is using third-party extensions
there are like i don't know several hundreds of thousands of third-party extensions on the
pypi service and i'm not saying they're all they're all good but there is a large list of
extensions that would have to do work and some of those extensions are currently already low on
maintainers and they're struggling to keep afloat so there you can give a huge heads up to them
if you go to 4.0 to really keep developing it yeah we probably have to do something like
several years before who knows maybe five years earlier like 3.15 we would have to say
and and i'm just making that the specific numbers up but we at some point we'd have to say
the nogil python could be an option it might be a compile time option
if you want to use nogil python you have to recompile python from source for your platform
using your tool set all you have to do is change one configuration variable and then you just run
make or configure and make and it will build it for you but now you also have to use the
the nogil compatible versions of all extension modules you want to use and so as long as many
extension modules don't have fully functional sort of variants that work in the nogil world
that's not a very practical thing for python users but it would allow extension developers
to test the waters see what they need to syntactically to be able to compile at all maybe
they're using functions that are defined by the python 3 runtime that won't be in the python 4
runtime those functions will not work they'll have to find an alternative
but they can experiment with that and sort of write test applications and that would be a way
to transition and that that could be a series of releases where that python 4 is more and more imminent
we have supported more and more third-party extension modules to have solid support that
works for nogil python for that new api and then sort of python python 4.0 is like the official
moment that the mayor comes out and cuts the ribbon and now python now the sort of nogil mode
is the default and maybe the only mode there is the internet wants to know from reddit
it's uh it's a small and fun question there's many fun questions but
out of the pypy packages pypi packages do you have a do you have ones you like do you in your
opinion are there must have pypy libraries or ones you use all the time constantly oh my that
i should really have a standard answer for that question but like a positive standard
answer but my current standard answer is that i'm not a big user of third-party packages
when i write python code i'm usually developing some tooling around building python itself
and uh the last thing we want is dependencies on third-party packages so i i tend to just
use the standard library and that's where your focus is that's where your mind is
but do you do you keep an eye of what's out there to understand where the standard library
could be moving should be moving it's a good kind of landscape of what's missing from the standard
library well usually when something's missing from the standard library nowadays uh it is a
relatively new idea and there is a third-party implementation or maybe possibly multiple third
party implementations but they evolve at a much higher rate than they could when they're in the
standard library so they it would be a big reduction in in activity to incorporate things like that
in the standard library so i i like that there is a lively package ecosystem and that sort of
recent trends in the standard library are actually that we're doing the occasional
spring cleaning where we're just we're we're choosing some modules that have not had a lot of
change in a long time and that maybe would be better off not existing at all at this point
because there might be a better third-party alternative anyway and we're we're sort of
slowly removing those that like often those are things that i sort of i spiked somewhere in 1992
or 1993 and if you look look through the commit history it's very sad like all cosmetic changes
like changes in the indentation style or the name of this other standard library module got changed
or nothing nothing of any substance the api is identical to what it was 20 years ago
so speaking of packages they have a a lot of impact on a lot of people's lives does it make
sense to you why python has become the primary the dominant language for the machine learning
community so packages like pie torch tensorflow second learn and even like the lower level
stuff like non-pi sci-pi pandas matplot lib with visualization can you like does it make sense to
you why it uh permeated the entire data science machine learning ai community well it's part of
it is an effect that's as simple as we're all driving on the right side of the road right
uh it's compatibility yeah it's it's and and and part of it is uh
not not quite as as as fundamental as driving on the right side of the road which you have to do
for for safety reasons i mean you have to agree on something every they could have picked javascript
or pearl there was there was a time in the early 2000s that it really looked like pearl what was
going to dominate like biosciences because dna search was all based on regular expressions
and pearl has the fastest and most comprehensive regular expression engine still does i spent
quite a long time with pearl that was another letting go letting go of this kind of uh data
processing uh system the reasons why python became the lingua franca of the scientific code and and
machine learning in particular and data science it really had a lot to do with
anything was better than c or c plus plus recently a guy who worked at lauren's livermore
national laboratories in the the sort of computing division wrote me his his his memoirs and and he
had his his own view of how he helped something he called computational steering into existence
and this was the idea that you you take libraries that in in his days were written in fortran
that that solved universal mathematical problems
and those libraries still work but uh the scientists that use the libraries
use them to solve continuously different specific applications and answer different
questions and so those poor scientists were were required to to use say fortran because fortran
was the library the language that the library was written in and then the scientist would have to write
an application that sort of uses the library to solve a particular equation or set off of answer
a set of questions and the same for c plus plus because there's there's interoperability so the
dusty decks are written either in c plus plus or fortran uh and so paul du bois was one of the people
who i think in the mid 90s saw that that you needed a higher level language for the scientists
to to sort of tie together the fundamental mathematical algorithms of linear algebra
and and other stuff and so gradually some libraries started appearing that did very fundamental
stuff with arrays of numbers in python i mean when i first created python i was not expecting it to
be used for arrays of numbers much i thought that was like an outdated data type and everything was
like objects and strings and like python was good and fast at string manipulation and objects
obviously but arrays of numbers were not very efficient and the multi-dimensional arrays didn't
even exist in the language at all uh but there were people who realized that python had extensibility
that was flexible enough that they could write third-party packages that did support
large arrays of numbers and operations on them very efficiently and somehow they got a foothold
through sort of different parts of the scientific community i i remembered that the Hubble space
telescope people in baltimore were somehow big python fans in the late 90s and at various
points small improvements were made and more people got in touch with using python to derive
these libraries of interesting uh algorithms and like once once you have a bunch of scientists
who are working on similar problems say they're all working on stuff that that data that comes in
from the Hubble space telescope but they're looking at different things some some are looking at stars
in this galaxy other are looking at galaxies the math is completely different but the the underlying
libraries are still the same and so they exchange code they say well i wrote this python program
or i wrote a python library to solve this class of problems and the other guys either say oh i can
use that library too or if you make a few changes i can use that library too why right why start from
scratch in pearl or java script where there's not that infrastructure uh for arrays of numbers yet
whereas in python you have it and so more and more scientists at different places doing different
different work discovered python and then then people who had an idea for an important new
fundamental library decided oh python is is actually already known to our users so let's use python as
the user interface i think that's how tensor i imagine at least that's how tensor flow ended up
with python as the user interface interface right but with tensor flow there's a deeper
history of what the community is it's not just like what packages it needs it's like what the
community leans on for programming language because tensor flow had a prior library that was
internal to google but there was also competing machine learning frameworks like the ano
cafe they were in python there was some scala um some other languages but python was really
dominating it and it's interesting because um there's other languages from the engineering
space like matlab that a lot of people used but different design choices by the company by the
core developers led to it not spreading and one of the choices with matlab by mathworks is to not
make it open source right or yeah not you know having people pay it was a very expensive product
and so uh universities especially disliked it because it was a price per seat i i remember hearing
yeah but i think that's not why it failed or i failed to spread i think the universities
didn't like it but they would still pay for it the thing is it didn't feed into that github open
source uh packages culture so like and that's somehow a precondition for um for viral spreading
the hacker culture like the tinkerer culture uh with with python it feels like you can build a
package from scratch or solve a particular problem and get excited about sharing that package with
others and that creates an excitement about a language i tend to like python's approach to
open source in particular because it's sort of it's almost egalitarian uh there's there's little
hierarchy there's there's obviously some because like you all need to decide whether you drive on
the left or the right side of the road sometimes but there is a lot of access for people with
little power you don't have to work for a big tech company to make a difference in the python world
we have affordable events that really care about community and support people
and sort of the community is is is like a big deal at our conferences and in in the psf
when the psf funds events it's always about growing the community the psf funds very little
development they that they do some but most of the develop most of the money that the psf
forks out uh is to community fostering things so speaking of egalitarian last time we talked
four years ago it was just after you stepped down from your role as the benevolent dictator for
life bdfl now looking back what are your insights and lessons you learn from that experience about
python developer community about human nature about human civilization life itself oh my uh
i probably held on to the position too long i remember being just extremely stressed for a
long time and it wasn't very clear to me what was leading what was causing the stress
and looking back uh i i should have sort of relinquished my central role as bdfl sooner
what were the pros and cons of the bdfl role like what were the you not relinquishing it what
what what are the benefits of that for the community and what are the drawbacks well the
the benefits for the community would be things like uh clarity of vision and sort of
a clear direction because i i had certain ideas in in mind when i created python and
while i sort of let myself be influenced by many other ideas as python evolved and became
more successful and more complex and more used i also stuck to certain principles and it and
still hard to say what are python's core principles but the fact that i was playing that role and
sort of always very active grew the community in a certain way it modeled to the community how to
think about how to how to solve a certain problem well that was a source of stress but it was also
beneficial it was a source of stress for me personally but it was beneficial for the community
because uh people people sort of over time had learned how i was thinking and could predict
yeah but how how i would would decide about a particular issue and not always perfectly of
course but there was like there wasn't a lot of jerking around like this year we're all
this year the democrats are in power and we're doing these kind of things and now the republicans
are in power and they roll all that back and do those kind of things there is a clear fairly
straight path ahead and so fortunately the the successor structure with the steering council
has has sort of found a similar way of of leading the community in a fairly steady
direction without stagnating and and for me personally it's more fun because there are
there are things i can just ignore yeah oh yeah there's a bug in multi-processing let someone
else decide whether that's important to solve or not i'll i'll i'll stick to typing in the
async io and the faster interpreter yeah it allows you to focus a little bit more yeah
what are interesting differences in culture if you can comment on between google dropbox and
microsoft from a python programming perspective all places you've been to the positive
is there a difference or is it just about people and there's great people everywhere
or is there a culture differences sort of dropbox is much smaller than the other two in your list
yeah so that that is a big difference the set of products they provide is more it's narrower so
they're more focused smaller code based yeah and and dropbox sort of at least during the time i was
there had the tendency of sort of making a big plan putting the whole company behind that plan
for a year and then evaluate and then suddenly find that everything was wrong about the plan
and then they had to do something completely different and so there were there was like
the annual engineering reorg was was sort of an unpleasant tradition at dropbox because like
oh there's a new vp of engineering and so now all the directors are being reshuffled and
this guy was in charge of of infrastructure one year and the next year he was made in
charge of i don't know product development it's fascinating because like you don't think about
these companies internally but i you know dropbox to me from the very beginning was one of my favorite
uh services there's certain like programs and online services that make me happy make me more
efficient and all that kind of stuff but one of the powers of those kinds of services they disappear
that you're not supposed to think about how it all works but it's incredible to me that you can
think stuff effortlessly across so many machines so quickly and like don't have to worry about
conflicts they they take care of the you know as a person that comes from a version of repositories
and all that kind of stuff or merge is super difficult and uh just keeping different versions
of different files is very tricky the fact that they could take care of that just i don't know
the the engineering behind the scenes must be super difficult both on the compute infrastructure
and the software a lot of internal sort of hand-wringing about things like that
but the the product itself always worked very smoothly yeah well there's probably a lot of
lessons to that you can have a lot of turmoil inside on the engineering side but if the product
is good the product is good and don't maybe don't mess with that either to you know when it's good
keep it's like with google focus on the search and the ads right and the money will come yeah
and make sure that's done extremely well and don't forget what you do extremely well in
in what ways do you provide value and happiness to the world make sure you do that well
is there something else to say about google and microsoft microsoft has had a very fascinating
shift recently with the new ceo uh what you know recent ceo with purchasing github
embracing open source culture embracing the developer culture is pretty interesting to see
that's like why i joined microsoft i mean after after retiring and thinking that i would
stay retired for the rest of my life which of course was a ridiculous thought
but that i was i was done working for a bit and then the pandemic made me realize that work
work and also provide a source of fulfillment keep you keep you out of trouble
microsoft is a very interesting company because it has this incredible very long and
varied history and this amazing catalog of products that many of which also date way back
i mean i've been been talking to a bunch of excel people lately and excel is like 35 years old
yeah and they can still read spreadsheets that that they might find on an old floppy drive
yeah yeah there's man there's so many incredible tools through the years excel one of one of the
great shames of my life is that i've never learned how to use excel well i mean it just
always felt like so many features are there it's similar with ad is like pie charm it feels like
i converged quickly to the dumbest way to use a thing to get the job done when clearly there's
so much more power your fingertips yeah but there's i i do think there's probably expert users of
excel oh excel is a cash cow actually oh it actually brings the money oh yeah a lot of the
engineering sort of if you look deep inside excel there's some very good engineering very
very impressive stuff okay now i need to definitely learn excel a little better
i had issues because i'm a keyboard person so i had issues coming up with shortcuts and microsoft
sometimes it's changed over the years but sometimes they kind of want to make things easier for you
on the surface and therefore make it harder for like people that like to have shortcuts and all
that kind of stuff to optimize their workflow now excel is probably people are probably yelling at
me it's like no excel probably has a lot of ways to optimize the workflow but in fact i keep discovering
that there are many features in excel that only exists at keyboard shortcuts yeah that's the sense
i have and now like i'm embarrassed that it's just you just have to know what they are yeah that's
that's like there's no logic or or reason to the assignment of the keyboard shortcuts because they
they go back even longer than 35 years can you maybe comment about such an adela and how hard it
is for a ceo to sort of pivot a company towards open source towards developer culture is there
something you could see about like how what's the role of leadership in such a pivot and definition
of a new vision i've never met him but uh i hear he's just a really sharp thinker
but he also has an incredible business sense he took the organization that had very solid pieces
but that was also struggling with all sorts of shameful things especially the steve balmer time
i imagine in part through his personal charm and thinking and of course the the great trust that
that the the rest of the leadership has in him he managed to to really turn the company around and
sort of change it from from openly hostile to open source to to actively embracing open source
and that doesn't mean that suddenly excel is going to go open source but that means that
there's room for a product like vs code which is open source yeah it's fascinating it gives me faith
that large companies with good leadership can grow can expand can change and pivot and so on develop
because it gets harder and harder as the company gets large um you wrote a blog post in response
to a person looking for advice about whether with a cs degree to choose a nine to five job
or to become an entrepreneur it's an interesting question if you just think from first principles
right now somebody has took a few years in programming has loved software engineering
in some sense creating python is an entrepreneurial endeavor that's a choice that a lot of people
that are good programmers have to make do i work for a big company or do i create something new
or you can work for a big company and create something new there
oh inside the yeah i mean big companies have individuals who create new stuff
that eventually grows big all the time and if you're the person that creates a new thing
it grows big you you'll have a chance to move up quickly in the company to run that thing
if that's your aspiration what what what can also happen is that someone is brilliant engineer and
sort of builds a great first version of a product and has no aspirations to then become a manager
and grow the team from five people to 20 people to a hundred people to a thousand people and
be in charge of hiring and meetings and they move on to inventing another crazy thing inside
the same company or sometimes they they found a startup or they moved to a different great
large or small company there's all sorts of models and sometimes people sort of do have this
whole trajectory from engineer buckling down writing code not nine to five but more like
noon till midnight seven days a week and coming up with a product and sort of
staying in charge i mean if you take Drew Houston Dropbox's founder he is still the CEO
and at least when when i was there he had not checked out or anything he was
he was a good CEO but he had started out as the technical inventor or co-inventor
and so he was someone who i don't know if he always aspired that i think when when he was 16
he already started a company so maybe maybe he did but he sort of it turned out that that he
did have the the personal sort of skill set needed to to grow and and stay on top and other people
sort of are brilliant engineers and horrible at management i count myself at least in the
second category yeah so your your your first love and still your love is to be the quote-unquote
individual contributor so the programmer yep do you have advice for a programming beginner
on how to learn python the right way find something you actually want to do with it if you say i want
learn skill x that's not enough motivation you need to pick something
and it can be a it can be a crazy problem you want to solve it it can be completely unrealistic
but something that that challenges you into actually learning coding in in some language
and there's so many projects out there you can look for like that that doesn't have to be some
big ambitious thing it could be writing a small bot if you're into social media you can write a
red a bot or a twitter bot or or some aspect of automating some as something that you do every
single day processing files all that kind of stuff nowadays you can take machine learning components
and and sort of plug those things together so you cool stuff with them so that's actually a
really good example so if you're interested in machine learning the state of machine learning is
such that like a a tutorial that takes an hour can get you to start using uh pre-trained models
to do something super cool and that's a good way to learn python because you learn just enough to
run this model and that's like a sneaky way to get get in there to figure out how to import
stuff how to write basic io how to run functions and i'm not sure if it's the best way to learn
the basics in python but could be nice to just get fall in love first and then figure out the basics
right yeah you can't expect to learn python from a one hour video of course i'm blanking out on the
name of of someone who who wrote a very funny blog post where he said i see all these ads for things
like learn python in 10 days or so and he said the the goal should be learn python in 10 years
that's hilarious but i completely disagree with that i think the criticism behind that is that
the the place is just like the blog post from earlier the places that tell you learn python
in five minutes or 10 minutes they're actually usually really bad tutorials so the thing is i
do believe that you can learn a thing in an hour to like get some interesting quick like it hooks you
i mean this but it just takes a tremendous amount of skill to be that kind of educator
richard feinlin was able to condense a lot of ideas and physics in a very short amount of time
but that takes a deep deep understanding and so yes of course the actual i think the 10 the 10
years is about the experience the pain along the way and there's something you have to practice
you can memorize the syntax but well i couldn't but maybe maybe someone else can but that doesn't
make you a coder yeah actually coding has changed in fascinating ways because so much of coding is
copying pacing from stack overflow and then adjusting which is another way of coding and i
don't want to talk down to that kind of style of coding because it's kind of a nicely efficient
but you know where that is going a code generation get no seriously get a co-pilot yeah co-pilot
i use it every day and it really yeah it writes a lot of code for me and usually it's slightly
wrong but it still saves me typing because all i have to do is like change one word in a line
of text that otherwise it it generated perfectly and like how many times are you looking for like
oh what was i doing this morning i was looking for an begin marker and i was looking for an
end marker and so begin is blah blah blah search for begin this is the begin token and then the next
line i type e and it it completes the whole line with end instead of begin that's a very simple
example sometimes it it's sort of if i name my function right it writes a five or ten line function
and you know python enough to very quickly then detect the issues so it's it becomes a really
good dance partner then it doesn't save me a lot of thinking but since i'm a poor typist i'm very
much appreciative of all the all the typing it does for me much better actually than the the
previous generation of suggestions that are also still built in vs code uh where when you hit like
a dot it it tries to guess what the type is of the variable to the left of the dot and then it
gives you a list on the pop down menu of what the attributes of that object are but copilot is much
much smoother than that well it's fascinating to hear that you use github copilot uh do you think
do you worry about the future of that uh did the automatic cogeneration the increasing amount of
that kind of capability are programmers jobs threatened or is there still a significant
role for humans are programmers jobs threatened by the existence of stack overflow i don't think so
it helps you take care of the boring stuff and you shouldn't try to use it to do something that
you have no way of understanding what you're doing yet a tool like that is always best when
the question you're asking is please remind me of how i do this which i i could do i could look
up how to do it but right now i've forgotten whether the method is called foo or bar or how you
what the shape of the api is does it use a builder object or a constructor or a factory or
something else and what are the parameters it serves that role it's like a great assistant
but the creative work of sort of deciding what you want what you want the code to do is is totally
yours what do you think is the future of python in the next 10 20 50 years 100 years you look
forward you ever think about you ever imagine a future of human civilization or living inside the
metaverse on mars human or robots everywhere what part does python play in that it'll eventually
become a sort of a legacy language uh that plays an important role but that's that most people
have never heard of and uh don't need to know about just like all kinds of basic structures in in
biology like mitochondria so it permeates all of life all of digital life but people just build
on top of it and they only know the stuff that's on top of it yeah you guys you build layers of
obstructions i mean most programmers nowadays rarely need to do binary arithmetic right
yeah or even think about it or even learn about it or they could go quite far without knowing
i started building little digital circuits out of nend gates that i built myself with
transistors and resistors so i sort of i feel very blessed that with with that start when i was
a teenager i i learned some of the basic at least concepts that that go into building a computer
and i sort of every part i have some understanding what what it's for and why it's there and how it
works and i can't forget about all that most of the time but i sort of i enjoy knowing oh if you go
deeper you at at some point you get to uh nend gates and have adders and shift registers and
when it comes to the point of how do you how do you actually make a chip out of silicon i have no idea
that's just magic to me but you enjoy knowing that you can walk a while towards the lower and lower
layers but you don't need to it's nice the other day as a sort of a mental exercise i was trying to
figure out if i could build a flip flop circuit out of relays i was just sort of trying to remember
oh how does a real relay work yeah there's like this electromagnetic force that pulls a switch
open or shut uh and you can have have like it can open one switch in another shut another and
you can have multiple contacts that go at once and how many relays do i really need to
sort of represent one bit of information can the relay just feed on itself there was
i don't think i i i got to the final solution but it was fun that i i could still do a little
bit of problem solving and thinking at that level and it's cool how we build on top of each other
so there's people there just you you stood on the shoulders of giants and there's others
who'll stand on your shoulders and it's it's a giant beautiful higher yeah i feel i sort of
covered this middle layer of the technology stack where i sort of peters out below the
the level of of of nan gates and at the at the top i sort of i lose track when it gets to machine
learning and then eventually the machine learning will build higher and higher layers that will
help us understand the lowest layer of the physics and thereby the universe figures out how it itself
works maybe maybe not yeah i did i mean it's it's possible i mean if you think of human
consciousness if that's even the right concept it's it's interesting that that's sort of we
have this super parallel brain that does all these incredible parallel operations like image
recognition i recognize your face does huge amount of processing that goes on in parallel
there's lots of nerves between my eyes and my brain and the brain does a whole bunch of stuff
all at once because it's actually really slow circuits but there are many of them that all
work together on the other hand when i'm speaking everything is completely sequential
i i i have to sort of string words together one at a time and when i'm thinking about stuff
i'm when i'm when i'm understanding the world i'm also thinking of everything like one step at a time
and so we we've we've sort of we've got all this this incredible
parallel circuitry in our brains and eventually we use that to simulate a single threaded
much much higher level interpreter it's exactly i mean that's the illusion of it that's the illusion
of it for us that it's a single sequential set of thoughts and all of that came from a single cell
through the process of embryogenesis so dna is the code dna holds the entirety of the code
the information and how to use that information to build up an organism the entire like the arms the
how is it built yeah the brain so it's you don't buy a computer you buy like a you buy a seed a
yeah diagram and then you plant the computer and it builds itself in almost the same way
and then does the computation and then is uh eventually dies it gets stale but gives birth
to young computers more and more and gives them lessons but they figure stuff out on their own
and over time it goes on that way and those computers when they go to college tried to
figure out how to program and they built their own little computers and they're increasingly
more intelligent increasingly higher and higher levels of abstractions isn't it interesting that
that you sort of you see the same thing appearing at different levels though because you have like
cells that that create new cells and and eventually that builds a whole organism but then
the animal or the plant or the human has its own mechanism of replication that that is is sort of
connected in a very complicated way to the mechanism of replication of the cells and then
if you if you look inside the cell if you see how dna and proteins are are connected then
there is yet another completely different mechanism whereby proteins are mass produced
using enzymes and and and a little bit of code from from dna and of course viruses
break into it at that level and while the mechanisms might be different it seems like
the nature of the mechanism is the same and it carries across natural languages and programming
languages humans maybe even human civilizations or intelligent civilizations and then all the way
down to the single cell organisms it is it is fascinating to see what abstraction levels
are built on top of individual humans yeah and how you have like whole societies
that that sort of have a similar self-preservation i don't know what it is instinct nature abstraction
as the individuals have and the cells have and they self-replicate and breed in different ways
it's hard for us humans to introspect it because we were very focused on our particular layer of
abstraction but from an alien perspective looking on earth they'll they'll probably see
the higher level organism of human civilization as part of this bigger organism of life on earth
itself in fact that could be an organism just alone just life life life on earth this has been a
wild both philosophical and technical conversation you're you're an amazing human being you're
you were gracious enough to talk to me when i was first doing this podcast you're one of the
earliest first people i've talked to somebody i admired for a long time it's just a huge honor
that you did it at that time and you do it again you're awesome thank you lex thanks for listening
to this conversation with guido van rossum to support this podcast please check out our sponsors
in the description and now let me leave you some words from oscar wild experience is the name that
everyone gives to their mistakes thank you for listening and hope to see you next time