A lot of people have said for many years that there will come a time when we want to pause a little bit.
That time is now.
The following is a conversation with Max Tegmark, his third time in the podcast.
In fact, his first appearance was episode number one of this very podcast.
He is a physicist and artificial intelligence researcher at MIT, co-founder of FutureLeft
Institute and author of Life 3.0, being human in the age of artificial intelligence.
Most recently, he's a key figure in spearheading the open letter calling for a six-month pause
on giant AI experiments like training GPT-4. The letter reads,
We're calling for a pause on training of models larger than GPT-4 for six months.
This does not imply a pause or ban on all AI research and development,
or the use of systems that have already been placed on the market.
Our call is specific and addresses a very small pool of actors who possess this capability.
The letter has been signed by over 50,000 individuals, including 1,800 CEOs and over 1,500
professors. Signatories include Joshua Benio, Steele Russell, Elon Musk, Steve Wozniak,
Yuval Noah Harari, Andrew Yang, and many others. This is a defining moment in the history of human
civilization, where the balance of power between human and AI begins to shift. And Max's mind
and his voice is one of the most valuable and powerful in a time like this. His support,
his wisdom, his friendship has been a gift I'm forever deeply grateful for.
This is Alex Friedman podcast. To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now, dear friends, here's Max Tagmark. You were the first ever guest on this podcast,
episode number one. So first of all, Max, I just have to say thank you for giving me a chance.
Thank you for starting this journey. It's been an incredible journey. Just thank you for
sitting down with me and just acting like I'm somebody who matters, that I'm somebody who's
interesting to talk to. And thank you for doing it. That meant a lot.
Thanks to you for putting your heart and soul into this. I know when you delve into controversial
topics, it's inevitable to get hit by what Hamlet talks about, the slings and arrows and stuff.
And I really admire this. It's in an era where YouTube videos are too long and now it has to
be like a 20-second TikTok clip. It's just so refreshing to see you going exactly against
all of the advice and doing these really long-form things. And the people appreciate it.
Reality is nuanced. And thanks for sharing it that way.
So let me ask you again, the first question I've ever asked on this podcast, episode number one,
talking to you. Do you think there's intelligent life out there in the universe?
Let's revisit that question. Do you have any updates? What's your view when you look out to the stars?
So when we look out to the stars, if you define our universe the way most astrophysicists do,
not as all of space, but the spherical region of space that we can see with our telescopes,
from which light has the time to reach us since our big man. I'm in the minority. I
estimate that we are the only life in this spherical volume that has
invented internet, radios, gotten our level of tech. And if that's true,
then it puts a lot of responsibility on us to not mess this one up. Because if it's true,
it means that life is quite rare and we are stewards of this one spark of advanced consciousness,
which if we nurture it and help it grow, eventually life can spread from here out
into much of our universe. And we can have this just amazing future. Whereas if we instead
are reckless with the technology we build and just snuff it out due to the stupidity,
or infighting, then maybe the rest of cosmic history in our universe is just going to be
a plenty of empty benches. But I do think that we are actually very likely to get visited by aliens,
alien intelligence quite soon. But I think we are going to be building that alien intelligence.
So we're going to give birth to an intelligent alien civilization. Unlike anything human,
the evolution here on Earth was able to create in terms of the path, the biological path it took.
Yeah, and it's going to be much more alien than a cat or even the most exotic
animal on the planet right now. Because it will not have been created through the usual
Darwinian competition where it necessarily cares about self preservation, the afraid of death,
any of those things. The space of alien minds that you can build is just so much faster than
what evolution will give you. And with that also comes great responsibility for us to make
sure that the kind of minds we create are those kind of minds that it's good to create minds that
will share our values and be good for humanity and life, and also create minds that don't suffer.
Do you try to visualize the full space of alien minds that AI could be? Do you try to consider
all the different kinds of intelligences, sort of generalizing what humans are able to do to the
full spectrum of what intelligent creatures entities could do?
I try, but I would say I fail. I mean, it's very difficult for human minds
to really grapple with something so completely alien, even for us, right? If we just try to
imagine how would it feel if we were completely indifferent towards death or individuality?
Even if you just imagine that, for example, you could just copy my knowledge of how to speak
Swedish. Boom, now you can speak Swedish. And you could copy any of my cool experiences, and
then you could delete the ones you didn't like in your own life, just like that. It would already
change quite a lot about how you feel as a human being, right? You probably spend less effort studying
things if you just copy them. And you might be less afraid of death, because if the plane you're on
starts to crash, you'd just be like, oh, shucks, I haven't backed my brain up for four hours.
So I'm going to lose all these wonderful experiences out of this flight.
We might also start feeling more compassionate, maybe with other people, if we can so readily
share each other's experiences and knowledge and feel more like a hive mind. It's very hard,
though. I really feel very humble about this, to grapple with it, how it might actually feel.
The one thing which is so obvious, though, which I think is just really worth reflecting on is,
because the mind space of possible intelligence is so different from ours,
it's very dangerous if we assume they're going to be like us or anything like us.
Well, the entirety of human written history has been through poetry, through novels,
been trying to describe through philosophy, trying to describe the human condition and what's
entailed in it. Like Jessica said, fear of death and all those kinds of things, what is love,
and all of that changes if you have a different kind of intelligence, all of it. The entirety,
all those poems, they're trying to sneak up to what the hell it means to be human,
all of that changes. How AI concerns and existential crises that AI experiences,
how that clashes with the human existential crisis, the human condition. It's hard to fathom,
hard to predict. It's hard, but it's fascinating to think about also. Even in the best case scenario,
where we don't lose control over the ever more powerful AI that we're building to other humans
whose goals we think are horrible and where we don't lose control to the machines and AI
provides the things that we want, even then you get into the questions, do you touch here?
Maybe it's the struggle that it's actually hard to do things. It's part of the things that give
this meaning as well. For example, I found it so shocking that this new Microsoft GPT-4
commercial that they put together has this woman talking about showing this demo,
how she's going to give a graduation speech to her beloved daughter and she asks GPT-4 to write it.
If it's frigging 200 words or so, if I realized that my parents couldn't be bothered struggling
a little bit to write 200 words and outsource that to their computer, I would feel really offended,
actually. I wonder if eliminating too much of this struggle from our existence,
do you think that would also take away a little bit of what means to be human? We can't even predict.
Somebody mentioned to me that they started using Chat GPT with a 3.5 and not 4.0
to write what they really feel to a person and they have a temper issue and they're
basically trying to get Chat GPT to rewrite it in a nicer way, to get the point across,
but rewrite it in a nicer way. We're even removing the inner asshole from our communication.
There's some positive aspects of that, but mostly it's just the transformation of how
humans communicate and it's scary because so much of our society is based on this glue of
communication. We're now using AI as the medium of communication that does the language for us.
So much of the emotion that's laden in human communication, so much of the intent
that's going to be handled by outsourced AI. How does that change everything? How does that
change the internal state of how we feel about other human beings? What makes us lonely? What
makes us excited? What makes us afraid? How we fall in love? All that kind of stuff.
For me personally, I have to confess the challenge is one of the things that really makes
my life feel meaningful. If I go hike a mountain with my wife, Maya, I don't want to just press
a button and be at the top. I want to struggle and come up there sweaty and feel like, wow,
we did this in the same way. I want to constantly work on myself to become a better person. If I
say something in anger that I regret, I want to go back and really work on myself rather than just
tell an AI from now on, always filter what I write so I don't have to work on myself,
because then I'm not growing. Yeah, but then again, it could be like with chess. An AI
wants it significantly, obviously supersedes the performance of humans. It will live in its own
world and provide maybe a flourishing civilizations for humans, but we humans will continue hiking
mountains and playing our games, even though AI is so much smarter, so much stronger, so much
superior in every single way, just like with chess. That's one possible hopeful trajectory here,
is that humans will continue to human and AI will just be a medium that enables the human
experience to flourish. Yeah, I would phrase that as rebranding ourselves from Homo sapiens
to Homo sentiens. Right now, sapiens, the ability to be intelligent, we've even put it in our
species name. We're branding ourselves as the smartest information processing
entity on the planet. That's clearly going to change if AI continues ahead.
So maybe we should focus on the experience instead, the subjective experience that we have
with Homo sentiens, and that's what's really valuable, the love, the connection, the other things.
Get off our high horses and get rid of this hubris that only we can do integrals.
So consciousness, the subjective experience is a fundamental value to what it means to be human.
Make that the priority. That feels like a hopeful direction to me, but that also requires more
compassion, not just towards other humans, because they happen to be the smartest
on the planet, but also towards all our other fellow creatures on this planet. I personally
feel right now, we're treating a lot of farm animals horribly, for example, and the excuse we're
using is, oh, they're not as smart as us. But if we admit that we're not that smart in the grand
scheme of things either in the post AI epoch, then surely we should value the subjective
experience of a cow also. Well, allow me to briefly look at the book, which at this point
is becoming more and more visionary that you've written, I guess, over five years ago, Life 3.0.
So first of all, 3.0. What's 1.0? What's 2.0? What's 3.0? And how's that vision sort of evolve?
The vision in the book evolved to today. Life 1.0 is really dumb, like bacteria,
and that it can't actually learn anything at all during the lifetime. The learning just comes from
this genetic process from one generation to the next. Life 2.0 is us and other animals which
have brains, which can learn during their lifetime a great deal. And you were born without being able
to speak English, and at some point you decided, hey, I want to upgrade my software. Let's install
an English speaking module. So you did? And Life 3.0 does not exist yet, can replace not only its
software the way we can, but also its hardware. And that's where we're heading towards at high
speed. We're already maybe 2.1 because we can put in an artificial knee, a pacemaker, etc, etc.
And if Neuralink and other companies succeed, we'll be Life 2.2, etc. But the companies trying
to build AGI or trying to make is, of course, full 3.0. And you can put that intelligence
in something that also has no biological basis whatsoever.
So less constraints and more capabilities, just like the leap from 1.0 to 2.0. There is,
nevertheless, you speaking so harshly about bacteria, so disrespectfully about bacteria,
there is still the same kind of magic there that permeates Life 2.0 and 3.0. It seems like maybe
the thing that's truly powerful about life intelligence and consciousness was already
there in 1.0. Is it possible? I think we should be humble and not be so quick to
make everything binary and say either it's there or it's not. Clearly, there's a great
spectrum. And there is even a controversy about whether some unicellular organisms,
like amoebas, can maybe learn a little bit, you know, after all. So apologies if I offended
any bacteria here. It wasn't my intent. It was more that I wanted to talk up how cool it is to
actually have a brain where you can learn dramatically within your lifetime.
Typical human. And the higher up you get from 1.0 to 2.0 to 3.0,
the more you become the captain of your own ship, the master of your own destiny,
and the less you become a slave to whatever evolution gave you. By upgrading your software,
we can be so different from previous generations and even from our parents,
much more so than even a bacterium, no offense to them. And if you can also swap out your hardware,
take any physical form you want, of course, really, the sky is the limit.
Yeah. So it accelerates the rate at which you can perform the computation that determines your
destiny. Yeah. And I think it's worth commenting a bit on what you means in this context. Also,
if you swap things out a lot, right? This is controversial, but my
current understanding is that life is best thought of not as a bag of meat or even a bag of
elementary particles, but rather as a system which can process information and retain its own
complexity, even though nature is always trying to mess it up. So it's all about information
processing. And that makes it a lot like something like a wave in the ocean, which is not its
water molecules, right? The water molecules bob up and down, but the wave moves forward. It's an
information pattern. In the same way, you, Lex, you're not the same atoms as during the first
time you did with me. You've swapped out most of them, but it's still you. And the information
pattern is still there. And if you could swap out your arms and whatever, you can still have
this kind of continuity. It becomes much more sophisticated sort of way before in time where
the information lives on. I lost both of my parents since our last podcast. And it actually
gives me a lot of solace that this way of thinking about them, they haven't entirely died because
a lot of mommy and daddy's, sorry, I'm getting a little emotional here, but a lot of their values
and ideas and even jokes and so on, they haven't gone away, right? Some of them live on, I can
carry on some of them. And we also live on a lot of other, and a lot of other people. So in this
sense, even with life 2.0, we can to some extent already transcend our physical bodies and our
death. And particularly if you can share your own information, your own ideas with many others,
like you do in your podcast, then that's the closest immortality we can get with our bio bodies.
You carry a little bit of them in you in some sense. Do you miss them? You miss your mom and
dad? Of course. Of course. What did you learn about life from them if it can take a bit of a
tangent? I know so many things. For starters, my fascination for math and the physical mysteries
of our universe, I think you got a lot of that from my dad. But I think my obsession for really big
questions and consciousness and so on, that actually came mostly from my mom. And when I got
from both of them, which is very core part of really who I am, I think is this feeling comfortable with
not buying into what everybody else is saying.
Doing what I think is right.
They both very much did their own thing and sometimes they got flack for it and they did it
anyway. That's why you've always been an inspiration to me, that you're at the top of your field and
you're still willing to tackle the big questions in your own way. You're one of the people that
represents MIT best to me. You've always been an inspiration to that. So it's good to hear that
you got that from your mom and dad. Yeah, you're too kind. But yeah, I mean, the good reason to do
science is because you're really curious, you want to figure out the truth. If you think
this is how it is and everyone else says no, no, that's bullshit. And it's that way, you know,
you stick with what you think is true. And even if everybody else keeps thinking it's
bullshit, there's a certain, I always root for the underdog when I watch movies. And my dad once,
I, one time, for example, when I wrote one of my craziest papers ever, talking about our
universe ultimately being mathematical, which we're not going to get into today. I got this email
from a quite famous professor saying this is not only bullshit, but it's going to ruin your career.
You should stop doing this kind of stuff. I sent it to my dad. Do you know what he said?
He replied with a quote from Dante. Segui il tuo corso e la sedire la gente. Follow your own path
and let the people talk. Go dad. This is the kind of thing. He's dead, but that attitude
is not. How did losing them as a man, as a human being change you? How did it expand your thinking
about the world? How did it expand your thinking about, you know, this thing we're talking about,
which is humans creating another living sentient perhaps being? I think it
mainly did two things. One of them just going through all their stuff after they had passed
away and so on, just drove home to me. How important it is to ask ourselves,
why are we doing this things we do? Because it's inevitable that you look at some things they spent
an enormous time on. And you ask the, at hindsight, would they really have spent so much time on this?
Would they have done something that was more meaningful? So I've been looking more in my life
now and asking, you know, why am I doing what I'm doing? And I feel it should either be something I
really enjoy doing or it should be something that I find really, really meaningful because it helps
humanity. And if it's in none of those two categories, maybe I should spend less time on it,
you know. The other thing is dealing with death up in personal like this, it's actually made me
less afraid of even less afraid of other people telling me that I'm an idiot, you know,
which happens regularly and just let my life do my thing, you know. And
it made it a little bit easier for me to focus on what I feel is really important.
What about fear of your own death? Has it made it more real that this is
something that happens? Yeah, it's made it extremely real and I'm next in line in our
family now, right? Me and my younger brother. But they both handled it with such dignity.
That was a true inspiration also. They never complained about things and, you know, when
you're old and your body starts falling apart, it's more and more to complain about. They
looked at what could they still do that was meaningful. And they focused on that rather than
wasting time talking about or even thinking much about things they were disappointed in.
I think anyone can make themselves depressed if they start their morning by making a list of
grievances. Whereas if you start your day with a little meditation and just things you're grateful
for, you basically choose to be a happy person. Because you only have a finite number of days
to spend them being grateful. Yeah.
Well, you do happen to be working on a thing which seems to have potentially
some of the greatest impact on human civilization of anything humans have ever created,
which is artificial intelligence. This is on the both detailed technical level and in a
high philosophical level you work on. So you've mentioned to me that there's an open letter
that you're working on. It's actually going live in a few hours. So I've been having late
nights and early mornings. It's been very exciting, actually. In short, have you seen
Don't Look Up? the film? Yes, yes. I don't want to be the movie spoiler for anyone watching this
who hasn't seen it. But if you're watching this, you haven't seen it, watch it. Because we are
actually acting out. It's life-imitating art. Humanity is doing exactly that right now, except
it's an asteroid that we are building ourselves. Almost nobody is talking about it. People are
squabbling across the planet about all sorts of things which seem very minor compared to the
asteroid that's about to hit us, right? Most politicians don't even have the radar
this on the radar. They think maybe in 100 years or whatever. Right now we're at a fork on the road.
This is the most important fork humanity has reached in its over 100,000 years on this planet.
We're building effectively a new species that's smarter than us. It doesn't look so much like a
species yet because it's mostly not embodied in robots. But that's the technicality which will
soon be changed. And this arrival of artificial general intelligence that can do all our jobs
as well as us and probably shortly thereafter superintelligence which greatly exceeds our
cognitive abilities, it's going to either be the best thing ever to happen to humanity or the worst.
I'm really quite confident that there is not that much middle ground there.
But it would be fundamentally transformative to human civilization?
Of course. Utterly and totally. Again, we branded ourselves as homo sapiens because it seemed like
the basic thing. We're the king of the castle on this planet. We're the smart ones. If we can
control everything else, this could very easily change. We're certainly not going to be the smartest
on the planet very long unless AI progress just halts. And we can talk more about why I
think that's true because it's controversial. And then we can also talk about
reasons you might think it's going to be the best thing ever. And the reason you think it's going
to be the end of humanity, which is of course super controversial. But what I think we can,
anyone who's working on advanced AI can agree on is it's much like the film
don't look up and that it's just really comical how little serious public debate there is
about it given how huge it is. So what we're talking about is a development of currently
things like GPT-4 and the signs it's showing of rapid improvement that may in the near-term
lead to development of super intelligent AGI AI general AI systems and what kind of impact that
has on society. When that thing achieves general human level intelligence and then beyond that
general super human level intelligence. There's a lot of questions to explore here. So one you
mentioned halt. Is that the content of the letter? Is it to suggest that maybe we should
pause the development of these systems? Exactly. So this is very controversial
from when we talked the first time we talked about how I was involved in starting the Future
Life Institute and we worked very hard on 2014-2015 was the mainstream AI safety.
The idea that there even could be risks and that you could do things about them.
Before then a lot of people thought it was just really kooky to even talk about it and a lot of
AI researchers felt worried that this was too flaky and it could be bad for funding and that
the people who talked about it were just not didn't understand AI. I'm very very happy with
how that's gone and that now you know just completely mainstream you go on any AI conference
and people talk about AI safety and it's a nerdy technical field full of equations and
as it should be. But there's this other thing which has been quite taboo up until now
calling for slowdown. So what we've constantly been saying including myself I've been
biting my tongue a lot you know is that you know we don't need to slow down AI development we just
need to win this race the wisdom race between the growing power of the AI and the growing wisdom
with which we manage it and rather than trying to slow down AI let's just try to accelerate the
wisdom do all this technical work to figure out how you can actually ensure that your powerful AI
is going to do what you wanted to do and have society adapt also with incentives and regulations
so that these things get put to good use. Sadly that didn't pan out. The progress on technical AI
on capabilities has gone a lot faster than than many people thought back when we started this in
2014 turned out to be easier to build really advanced AI than we thought. And on the other side
it's gone much slower than we hoped with getting policy makers and others to actually
put incentives in place to steer this in the good direction. Maybe we should unpack it and
talk a little bit about each so why did it go faster than a lot of people thought.
In hindsight it's exactly like building flying machines. People spent a lot of time wondering
about how how do birds fly you know and that turned out to be really hard. Have you seen the
TED Talk with a flying bird? Like a flying robotic bird? Yeah flies around the audience
but it took a hundred years longer to figure out how to do that than for the Wright brothers to
build the first airplane because it turned out there was a much easier way to fly and evolution
picked a more complicated one because it had its hands tied. It could only build a machine that
could assemble itself which the Wright brothers didn't care about. They can only build a machine
that use only the most common atoms in the periodic table. Wright brothers didn't care about that.
They could use steel iron atoms and it had to be able to repair itself and it also had to be
incredibly fuel efficient. You know a lot of birds use less than half the fuel of a remote
control plane flying the same distance. For humans just throw a little more put a little more fuel
in a roof. There you go a hundred years earlier. That's exactly what's happening now with with
these large language models. The brain is incredibly complicated. Many people made the
mistake you're thinking we have to figure out how the brain does human level AI first before
we could build in a machine. That was completely wrong. You can take an incredibly simple
computational system called a transformer network and just train it to do something incredibly dumb.
Just read a gigantic amount of text and try to predict the next word.
And it turns out if you just throw a ton of compute at that and ton of data it gets to be
frighteningly good like GPT-4 which I've been playing with so much since it came out right.
And there's still some debate about whether that can get you all the way to full human level or not
but yeah we can come back to the details of that and how you might get the human level AI even if
large language models don't. Can you briefly if it's just a small tangent comment on your
feelings about GPT-4? Suggest that you're impressed by this rate of progress but where is it? Can GPT-4
reason? What are like the intuitions? What are human interpretable words you can assign to the
capabilities of GPT-4 that makes you so damn impressed with it? I'm both very excited about it
and terrified. It's an interesting mixture of emotions. All the best things in life include
those two somehow. Yeah I can absolutely reason. Anyone who hasn't played with it I highly recommend
doing that before dissing it. It can do quite remarkable reasoning and I've had to do a lot
of things which I realized I couldn't do that myself that well even and it obviously does it
dramatically faster than we do too when you watch a type and it's doing that well servicing a massive
number of other humans at the same time. At the same time it cannot reason as well as a human can
on some tasks. It's obviously a limitation from its architecture. We have in our heads what in
GeekSpeak is called a recurrent neural network. There are loops. Information can go from this
neuron to this neuron to this neuron and then then back to this one. You can like ruminate on
something for a while. You can self reflect a lot. These large language models they cannot
like GPT-4. It's a so-called transformer where it's just like a one-way street of information
basically and in GeekSpeak it's called a feed-forward neural network and it's only so deep
so it can only do logic that's that many steps and that deep. You can create problems which
will fail to solve for that reason. The fact that it can do so amazing things with this incredibly
simple architecture already is quite stunning and what we see in my lab at MIT when we look inside
large language models to try to figure out how they're doing it. That's the key core
focus of our research. It's called mechanistic interpretability in GeekSpeak. You have this
machine that does something smart. You try to reverse engineer and see how does it do it.
You think of it also as artificial neuroscience. That's exactly what neuroscientists do with
actual brains but here you have the advantage that you don't have to worry about measurement
errors. You can see what every neuron is doing all the time and a recurrent thing we see again
and again. There's been a number of beautiful papers quite recently by a lot of researchers.
Some of them here in this area is where when they figure out how something is done
you can say oh man that's such a dumb way of doing it and you immediately see how it can be
improved like for example there was a beautiful paper recently where they figured out how a large
language model stores certain facts like Eiffel Tower is in Paris and they figured out exactly
how it's stored and the proof that they understood it was they could edit it. They changed some of
the synapses in it and then they asked it where is the Eiffel Tower and they said it's in Rome
and then they asked you how do you get there? Oh how do you get there from Germany? Oh you take
this train and the Roma Termini train station and this and that and what might you see if you're
in front of it? Oh you might see the Colosseum. So they had edited it. So they literally moved
it to Rome. But the way it's storing this information it's incredibly dumb for any
fellow nerds listening to this. There was a big matrix and roughly speaking there are certain
row and column vectors which encode these things and they correspond very hand-wavely to principal
components and it would be much more efficient for a sparse matrix just store in the database.
But everything so far we've figured out how these things do are ways where you can see they can
easily be improved and the fact that this particular architecture has some roadblocks built into it
is in no way going to prevent crafty researchers from quickly finding workarounds and making
other kinds of architectures sort of go all the way. So in short it's turned out to be a lot
easier to build human close to human intelligence than we thought and that means our runway as a
species that get our shit together has shortened. And it seems like the scary thing about the
effectiveness of large language models. So Sam Altman every standard conversation with
and he really showed that the leap from GPT-3 to GPT-4 has to do with just a bunch of hacks.
A bunch of little explorations with smart researchers doing a few little fixes here
and there. It's not some fundamental leap and transformation in the architecture.
And more data and more compute. And more data and compute but he said the big leaps has to do
with not the data and the compute but just learning this new discipline just like you said.
So researchers are going to look at these architectures and there might be big leaps
where you realize why are we doing this in this dumb way. And all of a sudden this model is 10x
smarter and that can happen on any one day on any one Tuesday or Wednesday afternoon.
And then all of a sudden you have a system that's 10x smarter. It seems like it's such
a new discipline. It's such a new like we understand so little about why this thing works so damn well
that the linear improvement of compute or exponential but the steady improvement of
compute steady improvement of the data may not be the thing that even leads to the next
leap. It could be a surprise little hack that improves everything.
Or a lot of little leaps here and there because so much of this is out in the open also.
So many smart people are looking at this and trying to figure out little leaps here and there.
And it becomes a sort of collective race where a lot of people feel if I don't take the leap
someone else with. And it is actually very crucial for the other part of it. Why do we
want to slow this down? So again what this open letter is calling for is just pausing
all training of systems that are more powerful than GPT for for six months.
Give a chance for the labs to coordinate a bit on safety and for society to adapt.
Give the right incentives to the labs because you know you've interviewed a lot of these
people who lead these labs and you know just as well as I do that they're good people.
They're idealistic people. They're doing this first and foremost because they believe that
AI has a huge potential to help humanity. But at the same time they are trapped in this
horrible race to the bottom. Have you read Meditations on Moloch by Scott Alexander?
Yeah it's a beautiful essay on this poem by Ginsburg where he interprets it as being about
this monster. It's this game theory monster that pits people against each other in this
race to the bottom where everybody ultimately loses. The evil thing about this monster is
even though everybody sees it and understands they still can't get out of the race.
A good fraction of all the bad things that we humans do are caused by Moloch and I like
Scott Alexander's naming of the monster so we humans can think of it as a thing.
If you look at why do we have overfishing, why do we have more generally the tragedy
of the commons, why is it that so live, I don't know if you've had her on your podcast.
Yeah she's become a friend. Great she made this awesome point recently that beauty filters that
a lot of female influencers feel pressured to use are exactly Moloch in action again.
First nobody was using them and people saw them just the way they were and then some of them started
using it and becoming ever more plastic fantastic and then the other ones that weren't using it
started to realize that if they want to just keep their their market share they have to start
using it too and then you're in a situation where they're all using it and none of them has
any more market share or less than before so nobody gained anything. Everybody lost
and they have to keep becoming ever more plastic fantastic also right and but nobody can go back
to the old way because it's just too costly right. Moloch is everywhere and Moloch is not a new
arrival on the scene either. We humans have developed a lot of collaboration mechanisms
to help us fight back against Moloch through various kinds of constructive collaboration.
The Soviet Union and the United States did sign the number of arms control treaties
against Moloch who is trying to stoke them into unnecessarily risky nuclear arms races etc etc
and this is exactly what's happening on the AI front. This time it's a little bit geopolitics
but it's mostly money where there's just so much commercial pressure. If you take any of these
leaders of the top tech companies if they just say this is too risky I want to pause
for six months they're going to get a lot of pressure from shareholders and others.
They're like well you know if you pause but those guys don't pause. We don't want to get
our lunch eaten and shareholders even have the power to replace the executives in the worst case
right so we did this open letter because we want to help these idealistic tech executives to do
what their heart tells them by providing enough public pressure on the whole sector to just pause
so that they can all pause in a coordinated fashion and I think without the public pressure
none of them can do it alone push back against their shareholders no matter how good-hearted they
are. Moloch is a really powerful foe. So the idea is to for the major developers of AI systems
like this so we're talking about Microsoft, Google, Meta and anyone else? Open AI is very close with
Microsoft now of course and there are plenty of smaller players for example Anthropic which is
very impressive there's Conjecture there's many many many players I don't want to make a long
list so leave anyone out and for that reason it's so important that some coordination happens
that there's external pressure on all of them saying you all need to pause because then the
people the researchers in these organizations the leaders who want to slow down a little bit they
can say their shareholders you know everybody's slowing down because of this pressure and it's
the right thing to do. Have you seen in history their examples where it's possible to pause the
absolutely and even like human cloning for example you could make so much money on human cloning
why aren't we doing it? Because biologists thought hard about this and felt like this is
way too risky they got together in the 70s in the Selomar and decided even
to stop a lot more stuff also just editing the human germline
gene editing that goes into our offspring and decided let's not do this because
it's too unpredictable what it's going to lead to we could lose control over what happens to our
species so they paused there was a ton of money to be made there so it's very doable but you just
need you need a public awareness of what the risks are and the broader community coming in and saying
hey let's slow down and you know another common pushback I get today is we can't stop in the west
because China and in China undoubtedly they also get told we can't slow down because the west
because both sides think they're the good guy but look at human cloning you know
did China forge ahead with human cloning there's been exactly one human cloning that's actually
been done that I know of it was done by a Chinese guy do you know where he is now in jail
and you know who put him there who Chinese government not because westerners said China
looked this is no the Chinese government put him there because they also felt
they like control the Chinese government if anything maybe they are even more concerned
about having control then the western governments have no incentive of just losing control over
where everything is going and you can also see the Ernie bot that was released by I believe Baidu
recently they got a lot of pushback from the government and had to reign it in you know in a
big way I think once this basic message comes out that this isn't an arms race it's a suicide race
where everybody loses if anybody's AI goes out of control it really changes the whole dynamic
it's not it's I'll say this again because this is a very basic point I think a lot of people get
wrong because a lot of people dismiss the whole idea that AI can really get very superhuman
because they think there's something really magical about intelligence such that it can only exist
in human minds you know because they believe that they think it's kind of kind of get to just more or
less GPT-4 plus plus and then that's it they don't see it as a super as a suicide race they think
whoever gets that first they're going to control the world they're going to win but that's not how
it's going to be and we can talk again about the scientific arguments from why it's not going to
stop there but the way it's going to be is if anybody completely loses control and you know
you don't care if someone manages to take over the world who really doesn't share your goals
you probably don't really even care very much about what nationality they have you're not going
to like it much worse than today if you live in Orwellia in dystopia what do you care who
created it right and if it goes farther and we just lose control even to the machines
so that it's not us versus them it's us versus it what do you care who who created this this
unaligned entity which has goals different from humans ultimately and we get marginalized we get
made obsolete we get replaced that's why I what I mean when I say it's a suicide race
it's kind of like we're rushing towards this cliff but the closer the cliff we get the more
scenic the views are and the more money there is there and so we keep going but we have to also
stop at some point right quit while we're ahead and uh it's um it's a suicide race which cannot be
won but the way to really benefit from it is to continue developing awesome AI a little bit slower
so we make it safe make sure it does the things that humans want and create a condition where
everybody wins the technology has shown us that you know geopolitics and and politics in general
is not a zero-sum game at all so there is some rate of development that will lead
us as a human species to lose control of this thing and the hope you have is that there's some
lower level of development which will not which will not allow us to lose control this is an
interesting thought you have about losing control so what if you have somebody if you are somebody
like santa prachai or sam altman at the head of a company like this you're saying if they develop an
agi they too will lose control of it so no one person can maintain control no group of individuals
can maintain control if it's if it's created very very soon and is a big black box that we
don't understand like the large language models yeah then i'm very confident they're going to lose
control but this isn't just me saying it you know sam altman and them as the sabbis have both said
themselves acknowledge that you know there's really great risks with this and they they want to slow
down once they feel it gets it's scary it's but it's clear that they're stuck in this again malloc
is forcing them to go a little faster than they're comfortable with because of pressure from just
commercial pressures right to get a bit optimistic here you know of course this is a problem that
can be ultimately solved uh it's just to win this wisdom race it's clear that what we hope that
is going to happen hasn't happened the the capability progress has gone faster than a lot of people
thought then and the the progress in in the public sphere of policy making and so on has gone slower
than we thought even the technical ai safety has gone slower a lot of the technical safety research
was kind of banking on that um large language models and other poorly understood systems couldn't
get us all the way that you had to build more of a kind of intelligence that you could understand
maybe it could prove itself safe you know things like this and um i'm quite confident that this
can be done um so we can reap all the benefits but we cannot do it as quickly as uh this out of
control express train we are on now is going to get the agi that's why we need a little more time
i feel is there something to be said what like sam alman talked about which is while we're in the
pre agi stage to release often and as transparently as possible to learn a lot so as opposed to being
extremely cautious release a lot don't uh don't invest in a closed development where you focus on
ai safety while it's somewhat dumb quote unquote uh release as often as possible and as you start
to see signs of uh human level intelligence or superhuman level intelligence then you put a halt
on it well what a lot of safety researchers have been saying for many years is that the most dangerous
things you can do with an ai is first of all teach it to write code yeah because that's the
first step towards recursive self-improvement which can take it from agi to much higher levels
okay oops we've done that and uh another thing high risk is connected to the internet let it go
to websites download stuff on its own and talk to people oops we've done that already you know
eliezer yukowski you said you interviewed him recently right yes he had this tweet recently
which gave me one of the best laughs in a while where he's like hey people used to make fun of me
and say you're so stupid eliezer because you're saying you're saying uh you have to worry of
obviously developers once they get to like really strong ai the first thing you're gonna do is like
never connect it to the internet keep it in the box yeah where you know you can really study it
it's if so he had written it in the like in the meme forms was like then yeah and then that and then
now let's lol let's make a chatbot yeah and the third thing is steward russell yeah you know
amazing ai researcher he has argued for a while that we should never teach ai anything about humans
above all we should never let it learn about human psychology and how you manipulate humans
that's the most dangerous kind of knowledge you can give it yeah you can teach it all it needs to
know how to about how to cure cancer and stuff like that but don't let it read daniel kahneman's
book about cognitive biases and all that and then oops lol you know let's invent social media
I'll recommend our algorithms which do exactly that they they look get so good at knowing us
and pressing our buttons that we've we're starting to create a world now where we're just
having ever more hatred because they figured out that these algorithms not for out of evil but
just to make money on advertising that the best way to get more engagement the euphemism get people
glued to their little rectangles right is just to make them pissed off that's really interesting
that a large ai system that's doing the recommender system kind of tasks on social media is basically
just studying human beings because it's a bunch of us rats giving it signal nonstop signal it'll
show a thing and then we give signal and whether we spread that thing we like that thing that thing
increases our engagement gets us to return to the platform it has that on the scale of hundreds
of millions of people constantly so it's just learning and learning and learning and presumably
if the parameter the number of parameters in your network that's doing the learning and more
and to end the learning is the more it's able to just basically encode how to manipulate human
behavior how to control humans at scale exactly and that is not something I think is in humanity's
interest yes right now it's mainly letting some humans manipulate other humans for profit
and power which already caused a lot of damage and eventually that's a sort of skill that can
make ai's persuade humans to let them escape whatever safety precautions be it but you know
there was a really nice article in the New York Times recently by Yuval Noah Harari and
two co-authors including Tristan Harris from the social dilemma and they have this phrase in there
I love he said humanity's first contact with advanced AI was social media and we lost that one
we now live in a country where there's much more hate in the world where there's much more hate in
fact and in our democracy that we're having this conversation and people can't even agree on who
won the last election you know and we humans often point fingers at other humans and say it's
their fault but it's really malloc and these AI algorithms we got the algorithms and then malloc
pitted the social media companies are against each other so nobody could have a less creepy
algorithm because then they would lose out on revenue to the other company is there any way to
win that battle back just if we just linger on this one battle that we've lost in terms of social
media is it possible to redesign social media this very medium in which we use as a civilization
to communicate with each other to have these kinds of conversation to have discourse to try
to figure out how to solve the biggest problems in the world whether that's nuclear war or the
development of AGI is is it possible to do social media correctly I think it's not only possible
but it's it's necessary who are we kidding that we're going to be able to solve all these other
challenges if we can't even have a conversation with each other that's constructive the whole idea
the key idea of democracy is that you get a bunch of people together and they have a real
conversation the ones you try to foster on this podcast or you respectfully listen to people you
disagree with and you realize actually you know there are some things actually we some common ground
we have and let's it's yeah we both agree let's not have nuclear wars let's not do that and etc etc
we're kidding ourselves the thinking we can face off the second contact with
whatever more powerful AI that's happening now with these large language models if we can't even
have a functional conversation in the public space that's why I started the improve the news
project improve the news.org but I'm an optimist fundamentally in
and that there is a lot of intrinsic goodness in people and that what makes the difference
between someone doing good things for humanity and bad things is not some sort of fairy tale thing
that this person was born with the evil gene and this one was not born with a good gene no
I think it's whether we put whether people find themselves in situations that bring out the best
in them or the bring out the worst in them and I feel we're building an internet and a society that
brings out the worst but it doesn't have to be that way no it does not it's possible to create
incentives and also create incentives that make money uh they both make money and bring out the
best in people I mean in the long term it's not a good investment for anyone you know it's have a
nuclear war for example and you know is it a good investment for humanity if we just ultimately
replace all humans by machines and then we're so obsolete that eventually there's no humans left
well depends against how you do the math but I would say by any reasonable economic standard
if you look at the future income of humans and there aren't any you know that's not a good investment
moreover like why why can't we have a little bit of pride in our species damn it you know why should
we just build another species that gets rid of us if we were neanderthals would we really consider
it a smart move if if we had really advanced biotech to build homo sapiens you you know you
might say hey max you know yeah let's let's build build these homo sapiens they're going to be smarter
than us maybe they can help us defend this better against predators and help fix their
bar caves make them nicer we'll control them undoubtedly you know so then they build build
a couple a little baby girl a little baby boy they either and and then you have some some
wise old and the underthrall elder was like hmm I'm scared that uh we're opening a pandora's box
here and that we're going to get outsmarted by these super neanderthal intelligences
and there won't be any neanderthals left but then you have a bunch of others in the cave
right you are you such a luddite scare monger of course they're going to want to keep us around
because we are their creators and and why you know the smarter I think the smarter they get the
nicer they're going to get they're going to leave us they're going to they're going to want this around
and that's going to be fine and and besides look at these babies they're so cute it's clearly
they're totally harmless that's exact those babies are exactly GPT-4 yeah it's not I want to be clear
it's not GPT-4 that's terrifying it's the GPT-4 is a baby technology you know and Microsoft even
had a paper recently out uh with a title something like sparkles of AGI whatever basically saying
this is baby AI like these little neanderthal babies and it's going to grow up there's going to be
other systems from from the same company from other companies they'll be way more powerful and
but they're going to take all the things ideas from these babies and before we know it we're
going to be like those last neanderthals who are pretty disappointed and when they realized
they were getting replaced well this interesting point you make which is the programming it's
entirely possible that GPT-4 is already the kind of system that can change everything
by writing programs life three it's yeah it's because it's life 2.0 the systems I'm afraid of
are going to look nothing like a large language model and they're not but once it gets once
it or other people figure out a way of using this tech to make much better tech right it's just
constantly replacing its software and from everything we've seen about how how these work
under the hood they're like the minimum viable intelligence they do everything in a dumbest
way that still works sort of yeah and um so they are life 3.0 except when they replace their software
it's a lot faster than when you when when you decide to learn swedish
and moreover they think a lot faster than us too so when uh you know we don't think on how one
logical step every nanosecond or few or so the way they do and we can't also just suddenly scale
up our hardware massively in the cloud which is so limited right uh so they are they are also life
to have consumed become a little bit more like life 3.0 in that if they need more hardware hey
just rent it in the cloud you know how do you pay for it well with all the services you provide
and what we haven't seen yet which could change a lot is uh entire
software system so right now programming is done sort of in bits and pieces uh as as an assistant
tool to humans but i do a lot of programming and with the kind of stuff that gbt4 is able to do i
mean is replacing a lot what i'm able to do but i you still need a human in the loop to kind of
manage the design of things manage like what are the prompts that generate the kind of stuff to
to do some basic adjustment of the code to do some debugging but if it's possible to add on top of
gbt4 kind of uh feedback loop of of uh self-debugging improving the code and then you launch that
system onto the wild on the internet because everything is connected and have it do things
have it interact with humans and then get that feedback and now you have this giant ecosystem
yeah of humans that's one of the things that um yeah elon musk recently sort of tweeted as a case
why everyone needs to pay seven dollars or whatever for twitter to make sure they're real
they're make sure they're real we're now going to be living in a world where the the bots are
getting smarter and smarter and smarter to a degree where you can't uh you can't tell the
difference between a human and a bot that's right and now you can have uh bots outnumber humans by
a one million to one which is why he's making a case why you have to pay to prove you're human
which is one of the only mechanisms to which is depressing and i yeah i feel we have to remember
as individuals we should from time to time ask ourselves why are we doing what we're doing
all right then as a species we need to do that too so if we're building as as you say machines
that are outnumbering us and more and more outsmarting us and replacing us on the job
market not just for the dangerous and then boring tasks but also for writing poems and doing art
and things that a lot of people find really meaningful gotta ask ourselves why why are we
doing this uh we are the answer is malloc is tricking us into doing it and it's such a clever
trick that even though we see the trick we still have no choice but to fall for it right
come also the thing you said about you using uh co-pilot ai tools to program faster how many
what factor faster would you say you code now does it go twice as fast or i don't really uh
because it's a new tool yeah it's i don't know if speed is significantly improved
but it feels like i'm a year away from being uh five to ten times faster so if that's typical
for programmers then uh you're already seeing another kind of self recursive self-improvement
right because previously one like a major generation of improvement of the codes
would happen on the human r&d timescale and now if that's five times shorter
then it's going to take five times less time than otherwise would to develop the next level
of these tools and so on so this these these are the this is exactly the sort of beginning of an
of an intelligence explosion there can be humans in the loop a lot in the early stages and then
eventually humans are needed less and less and the machines can more kind of go along but you
what you weren't you said there is just an exact example of these sort of things another thing which
which um i was kind of lying on my psychiatrist imagining i'm on a psychiatrist couch here saying
what are my fears that people would do with um ai systems another so i mentioned three that i had
fears about many years ago that they would do uh namely uh teach it the code uh connected to the
internet and teach it to manipulate humans a fourth one is building an api where code can
control the super powerful thing right that's very unfortunate because one thing that systems like
gpt4 have going for them is that they are an oracle in the sense that they just answer questions
there is no robot connected to the gpt4 gpt4 can't go and do stock trading based on its thinking
it's not an agent and an intelligent agent is something that takes in information from the
world processes it to figure out what action to take based on its goals that it has and then
does something back on the world but once you have an api for example gpt4 nothing stops
joe schmo and a lot of other people from building real agents which just keep making calls somewhere
and some inner loop somewhere to these powerful oracle systems and which makes them themselves
much more powerful that's another kind of um unfortunate development which i think we would
have been better off uh delaying i don't want to pick on any particular companies i think
they're all under a lot of pressure to make money yeah and um again we the reason we're calling for
this pause is to give them all cover to do what they know is the right thing slow down a little bit
at this point but everything we've talked about i hope we'll can we'll make it clear to people
watching this you know why these sort of human level tools can cause a gradual acceleration
you keep using yesterday's technology to build tomorrow's technology yeah and when you do that
over and over again you naturally get an explosion you know that's the definition of an explosion
in science right like if you have um two people um they fall in love now you have four people and
then they can make more babies and now you have eight people and then then you have 16 32 64 etc
we call that a population explosion where it's just that each if it's instead free neutrons
in a nuclear reaction that if each one can make more than one then you get an exponential growth
in that we call it a nuclear explosion all explosions are like that an intelligence
explosion it's just exactly the same principle that some quantities some amount of intelligence
can make more intelligence than that and then repeat you always get the exponentials
what's your intuition why does you mention there's some technical reasons why it doesn't stop
at a certain point what's your intuition and uh do you have any intuition why it might stop
it's obviously going to stop when it bumps up against the laws of physics
there are some things you just can't do no matter how smart you are allegedly
and because we don't know the full laws of physics yeah like Seth Lloyd wrote a really cool
paper on the physical limits on computation for example if you make it put too much energy into
it and the finite space it'll turn into a black hole you can't move information around fast and
the speed of light stuff like that but uh it's hard to store way more than than a modest number
of bits per atom etc but you know those limits are just astronomically above like 30 orders of
magnitude above where we are now so bigger different bigger jump in intelligence than if
you go from a from an ant to a human I think of course what we want to do is have a controlled
thing a nuclear reactor you put moderators in to make sure exactly it doesn't blow up out of control
right when we do experiments with biology and cells and so on you know we also try to make
sure it doesn't get out of control um we can do this with AI too the thing is we haven't succeeded
yet and malloc is exactly doing the opposite just fueling just egging everybody on faster faster
faster or the other company is going to catch up with you or the other country is going to catch up
with you we do this we have to want to stop we have and and I don't believe in this just asking
people to look into their hearts and do the right thing it's easier for others to say that but like
if if you're in the situation where your company is going to get screwed if you
by other companies they're not stopping you know you're putting people in a very hard situation
the right thing to do is change the whole incentive structure instead
and and this is not an old maybe I should say one more thing about this because malloc
has been around as humanity's number one or number two enemy since the beginning of civilization
and we came up with some really cool countermeasures like first of all already over a hundred thousand
years ago evolution realized that it was very unhelpful that people kept killing each other all
the time yeah so it genetically gave us compassion and made it so that it like if you get too drunk
dudes getting into a pointless bar fight they might give each other black eyes but they have a lot of
inhibition towards just killing each other that's a and similarly if you find a baby lying on the
street when you go out for your morning jog tomorrow you're gonna stop and pick it up right
even though it may be a make you late for your next podcast so evolution gave us these genes
that make our own egoistic incentives more aligned with what's good for the greater group
we're part of right and then as we got a bit more sophisticated and developed language
we invented gossip which is also a fantastic anti malloc right because now
it it's really discourages liars moochers cheaters because it their own incentive now is not to do
this because word quickly gets around and then suddenly people aren't going to invite them to
their dinners anymore and or trust them and then when we got still more sophisticated and bigger
societies you know invented the legal system where even strangers who didn't couldn't rely on gossip
and and things like this would treat each other would have an incentive
now those guys in the bar fights even if they someone is so drunk that he
actually wants to kill the other guy he also has a little thought in the back of his head that you
know do i really want to spend the next 10 years eating like really crappy food in a small room
i'm just gonna chill out you know so and we we similarly have tried to give these incentives
to our corporations by having having regulation and all sorts of oversight so that their incentives
are aligned with the greater good we tried really hard and the big problem that we're failing now
is not that we haven't tried before but it's just that the tech is growing much
is developing much faster than the regulators been able to keep up right so
regulators it's kind of comical that european union right now is doing this AI act right which
and in the beginning they had a little opt-out exception that gpt4 would be completely excluded
from regulation brilliant idea what's the logic behind that some lobbyists pushed successfully
for this so we were actually quite involved with the future life institutes um mark brackel
mr uke anthony agir and others you know we're quite involved with um talking to very educating
various people involved in this process about these general purpose AI models coming and pointing
out that they would become the laughing stock if they didn't put it in so it the french started
pushing for it it got put in to the draft and it looked like all was good and then there was a huge
counterpush from lobbyists yeah there were more lobbyists sent in brussels from tech companies and
from oil companies for example and it looked like it might as we can maybe get taken out again
and now gpt4 happened and i think it's going to stay in but this just shows you know malloc
can be defeated but the the challenge you're facing is that the tech is generally much faster than
what the policy makers are and a lot of the policy makers also don't have a tech background so it's
you know we really need to work hard to educate them on how on what's taking place here so so
we're getting the situation where the first kind of non so you know i define artificial
intelligence just as non-biological intelligence all right and by that definition a company a
corporation is also an artificial intelligence because the corporation isn't it's humans it's a
system if its CEO decides the CEO of a tobacco company decides one morning the CEO he doesn't
want to sell cigarettes anymore they'll just put another CEO in there it's not enough to align
the incentives of individual people or align individual computers incentives to their owners
which is what technically iSafety research is about you also have to align the incentives of
corporations with a greater good and some corporations have gotten so big and so powerful
very quickly that in many cases their lobbyists instead align the regulators to what they want
rather than the early way around the classic regulatory capture all right is is the thing
that the slowdown hopes to achieve is give enough time to the regulators to catch up or enough time
to the companies themselves to breathe and understand how to do AI safety correctly i think
both and but i think that the vision path to success i see is first you give a breather
actually to to the people in these companies their leadership who wants to do the right thing and
they all have safety teams and so on on their companies give them a chance to get together
with the other companies and the outside pressure can also help catalyze that right and and work out
what is it that's what are the reasonable safety requirements one should put on future systems
before they get rolled out there are a lot of people also in academia and elsewhere outside
of these companies who can be brought into this and have a lot of very good ideas and then i think
it's very realistic that within six months you can get these people coming up so here's a white
paper here's where we all think is reasonable you know you didn't just because cars killed a
lot of people you didn't ban cars but they got together a bunch of people and decided you know
in order to be allowed to sell a car it has to have a seat belt in it there the analogous things
that you can start requiring a future AI systems so that they are are safe and once this heavy
lifting this intellectual work has been done by experts in the field which can be done quickly
i think it's going to be quite easy to get policymakers to to see yeah this is a good idea
and it's it's you know for the fight for the companies to fight mallock they want and i
believe sam altman has explicitly called for this they want the regulators to actually adopt it so
that their competition is going to abide by it too right you don't want
you don't want to be enacting all these principles then you abide by them and then
there's this one little company that doesn't sign on to it and then now they can gradually overtake
you then the companies will get be able to sleep secure knowing that everybody's playing by the
same rules so do you think it's possible to develop guardrails that keep the systems from
from basically damaging irreparably humanity while still enabling sort of the capitalist
fueled competition between companies as they develop how to best make money with this AI
you think there's a balancing that's possible absolutely i mean we've seen that in many other
sectors where you've had the free market produce quite good things without uh causing particular
harm um when the guardrails are there and they work you know capitalism is a very good way of
optimizing for just getting the same things on more efficiently it was but it was good you know
and like in hindsight i've never met anyone even even on parties way over on the right
in in in any country who who think it was a bad it thinks it was a terrible idea to
ban child labor for example yeah but it seems like this particular technology has gotten so
good so fast become powerful to a degree where you could see in the near term the ability to make
a lot of money yeah and to put guardrails develop guardrails quickly in that kind of context seems
to be tricky it's not uh similar to cars or child labor it seems like the opportunity to make a lot
of money here very quickly is right here before again it's there's this cliff yeah it gets quite
seated closer to the cliff there you go yeah the more the more go there more money there is more
gold in gets there on the ground you can pick up or whatever it's you want to drive there very fast
but it's not in anyone's incentive that we go over the cliff and it's not like everybody's in their
own car all the cars are connected together with a chain yeah so if anyone goes over they'll start
dragging others down the others down too and so ultimately it's in the selfish
interests also of the people in the companies to slow down when the when you can start seeing
the corners of the cliff there in front of you right and the problem is that even though the
people who are building the technology and the CEOs they really get it the shareholders and
these other market forces they are people who don't honestly understand that the cliff is there
they usually don't you have to get quite into the weeds to really appreciate how powerful this is
and how fast and a lot of people are even still stuck again in this idea that intelligence in this
carbon chauvinism as I like to call it that you can only have our level of intelligence in
humans that there's something magical about it whereas the people in the tech companies
who build this stuff they all realize that intelligence is information processing of a
certain kind and it really doesn't matter at all whether the information is processed by carbon
atoms in neurons in brains or by silicon atoms in some technology we build so you brought up
capitalism earlier and there are a lot of people who love capitalism and a lot of people who really
really don't and it's it struck me recently that the what's happening with capitalism here is exactly
analogous to the way in which super intelligence might wipe us out so you know I studied economics
for my undergrad in Stockholm school of economics yay well no no I tell me so I was very interested
in how how you could use market forces to just get stuff done more efficiently but give the right
incentives to market so that it wouldn't do really bad things so Dylan had Phil Manel who's a
professor and colleague of mine at MIT wrote this really interesting paper with some collaborators
recently where they proved mathematically that if you just take one goal that you just optimize for
on and on and on indefinitely that you think is gonna bring you in the right direction
what basically always happens is in the beginning it will make things better for you
but if you keep going at some point it's going to start making things worse for you again and then
gradually it's going to make it really really terrible so just as a simple the way I think of
the proof is suppose you want to go from here back to Austin for example and you're like okay yeah
let's just let's go south but you put in exactly the right sort of the right direction just optimize
that south as possible you get closer and closer to Austin but there's always some little error
so you you're not going exactly towards Austin but you get pretty close but eventually you start
going away again and eventually you're gonna be leaving the solar system yeah and they they proved
it's beautiful mathematical proof this happens generally and this is very important for AI
because for even though Stuart Russell has written a book and given a lot of talks on why
it's a bad idea to have AI just blindly optimize something that's what pretty much all our systems
do yeah we have something called a loss function then we're just minimizing or reward function
we're just minimize maximizing and um capitalism is exactly like that too we wanted to get stuff
done more efficiently that people wanted so introduce the free market things got done much
more efficiently than they did and and say communism right and it got better but then
it just kept optimizing it and kept optimizing and you got ever bigger companies and ever more
efficient information processing and I was also very much powered by it and eventually a lot of
people are beginning to feel wait we're kind of optimizing a bit too much like why did we just chop
down half the rain for us you know and why why did suddenly these regulators get captured by lobbyists
and so on it's just the same optimization that's been running for too long if you have an AI that
actually has power over the world and you just give it one goal and just like keep optimizing
that most likely everybody's gonna be like yay this is great in the beginning things are getting
better but um it's almost impossible to give it exactly the right direction to optimize in and then
eventually all hey breaks loose right nick boss drum and others are given examples that sound
quite silly like what if you just want to like tell it to cure cancer or something and that's all
you tell it maybe it's gonna decide to take over entire continents just so we can get more
super computer facilities in there and figure out a cure cancer backwards and then you're like
wait that's not what I wanted right and um the the the issue with capitalism and the issue with
the front of way I have kind of merged now because the malloc I talked about is exactly the capitalist
malloc that we have built an economy that has is optimized for only one thing profit right and
that worked great back when things were very inefficient and then now it's getting done better
and it worked great as long as the companies were small enough that they couldn't capture the
regulators but that's not true anymore but they keep optimizing and now we they realize that that
they can these companies can make even more profit by building ever more powerful AI even if it's
reckless but optimize more and more and more and more so this is malloc again showing up and I just
want to anyone here who has any concerns about about late stage capitalism having gone a little too
far you should worry about superintelligence because it's the same villain in both cases it's
malloc and optimizing one objective function aggressively blindly is going to take us there
yeah we have to pause from time to time and look into our hearts and ask why are we doing this is
this am I still going towards austin or have I gone too far you know maybe we should change direction
and that is the idea behind the halt for six months why six months it seems like a very short
period just can we just linger and explore different ideas here because this feels like a
really important moment in human history where pausing would actually have a significant positive
effect we said six months because we figured the number one pushback we were going to get
in the west was like but china and everybody knows there's no way that china is going to catch up
west on this in six months so it's that argument goes off the table and you can
forget about geopolitical competition and just focus on the real issue that's why we put this
that's really interesting but you've already made the case that even for china if you actually
want to take on that argument china too would not be bothered by a longer halt because they
don't want to lose control even more than the west doesn't that's what I think that's a really
interesting argument like I have to actually really think about that which the the kind of
thing people assume is if you develop an agi that open ai if they're the ones that do it for example
they're going to win but you're saying no they're everybody loses yeah it's going to get better
and better and better and then kaboom we all lose that's what's going to happen when lose and win
a define and a metric of basically quality of life for human civilization and for sam altman
I have to be people on my personal guess you know and people can quibble with this is that we're
just gonna there won't be any humans that's it that's what I mean by lose you know if you we can
see in history once you have some species or some group of people who aren't needed anymore
and doesn't usually work out so well for them right yeah there were a lot of horses for were used
for traffic in boston and then the car got invented and most of them got you know we don't
need to go there and uh if you look at humans you know right now we why did the labor movement
succeed and after the industrial revolution because it was needed even though we had a lot
of mollocks and there was child labor and so on you know the company still needed to have workers
and that's why strikes had power and so on if we get to the point where most humans aren't
needed anymore I think it's like it's quite naive to think that they're going to still be treated
well you know we say that yeah yeah everybody's equal and the government will always we'll always
protect them but if you look in practice groups that are very disenfranchised and don't have any
actual power usually get screwed and now in the beginning so industrial revolution we automated
away muscle work but that got went worked out pretty well eventually because we educated ourselves
and started working with our brains instead and got usually more interesting better paid jobs
but now we're beginning to replace brain work so we replaced a lot of boring stuff like we got the
pocket calculator so you don't have people adding multiplying numbers anymore at work fine there were
better jobs they could get but now gpt4 you know and the stable diffusion and techniques like this
they're really beginning to blow away some real some jobs that people really love having it was a
heartbreaking article just post just yesterday social media I saw about this guy who was doing
3d modeling for gaming and he and all of a sudden now they got this new software he just give
says prompts and he feels his whole job that he loved lost its meaning you know and I asked gpt4
rewrite twinkle twinkle little star in the style of Shakespeare I couldn't have done such a good
job it was really impressive you've seen a lot of art coming out here right so I'm all for
automating away the dangerous jobs and the boring jobs but I think you hear a lot some
arguments which are too glib sometimes people say well that's all that's going to happen we're
getting rid of the boring boring tedious dangerous jobs it's just not true there are a lot of really
interesting jobs that are being taken away now journalism is getting going to get crushed
coding is going to get crushed I predict the job market for programmers salaries are going to start
dropping you know if you said you can code five times faster you know then you need five times
fewer programmers maybe there will be more output also but you'll still end up using fewer program
needing fewer programmers than today and I love coding you know I think it's super cool
so we we need to stop and ask ourselves why again are we doing this as humans right
I feel that AI should be built by humanity for humanity and let's not forget that
it shouldn't be by malloc for malloc or what it really is now is kind of by humanity
for malloc which doesn't make any sense it's for us that we're doing it then and
make a lot more sense if we build develop figure out gradually safely how to make all this tech
and then we think about what are the kind of jobs that people really don't want to have
you know automate them all the way and then we ask what are the jobs that people really find
meaning in like maybe taking care of children in the daycare center maybe doing art etc etc and
even if it were possible to automate that way we don't need to do that right it's we built these
machines well it's possible that we redefine or rediscover what are the jobs that give us meaning
for me the thing it is really sad like I
half the time I'm excited half the time I'm crying as I'm generating code because
I kind of love programming it's an act of creation you have an idea you design it and then you
bring it to life and it does something especially if there's some intelligence to it does something
it doesn't even have to have intelligence bringing printing hello world on screen
you made a little machine and it comes to life and there's a bunch of tricks you learn along
the way because you've been doing it for for many many years and then to see AI be able to generate
all the tricks you thought were special I don't know it's very it it's scary it's almost painful
like a loss loss of innocence maybe like yeah maybe when I was younger I remember before I learned
that sugar is bad for you you should be on a diet I remember I enjoyed candy deeply in a way I just
can't anymore that I know is bad for me I enjoyed it unapologetically fully just intensely and I
lost that now I feel like a little bit of that is lost for me with program or being lost with
programming similar as it is for the 3d modeler no longer being able to really enjoy the art of
modeling 3d things for gaming I don't know I don't know what to make sense of that maybe I would
rediscover that the true magic of what it means to be human is connecting with other humans to
have conversations like this I don't know to uh to have sex to have to eat food to really intensify
the value from conscious experiences versus like creating other stuff you're pitching the rebranding
again from homo sapiens the homo sapiens the meaningful experiences and just to inject some
optimism in this year so we don't sound like a bunch of gloomers you know we can totally have
our cake and eat it you hear a lot of totally bullshit claims that we can't afford having more
teachers yeah have to cut the number of nurses you know that's just nonsense obviously with
anything even quite far short of agi we can dramatically improve grow the gdp and produce
this wealth of goods and services it's very easy to create a world where everybody is better off
than today including the richest people can be better off as well right it's not a zero-sum game
you know technology again you can have two countries like sweden and danmark had all these
ridiculous wars century after century and uh sometimes that sweden got a little better off
because it got a little bit bigger and then danmark got a little better off because sweden got a
little bit smaller and and but then we then technology came along and we both got just
dramatically wealthier without taking away from anyone else it was just a total win for everyone
and uh ai can do that on steroids if you can build safe agi if you can build super intelligence
basically all the limitations that cause harm today can be completely eliminated right it's a
wonderful you talk possibility and this is not sci-fi this is something which is clearly possible
according to the laws of physics and i we can talk about ways of making it safe also um but
unfortunately that'll only happen if we steer in that direction that's absolutely not the default
outcome that's why income inequality keeps going up that's why the life expectancy in the u.s has
been going down now i think it's four years in a row i just read a heartbreaking study from
the cdc about how something like one-third of all teenage girls in the u.s i've been thinking
about suicide you know like those are steps in the totally the wrong direction and and it's
important to keep our eyes on the prize here that we can we have the power now for the first time
in the history of our species to harness artificial intelligence to help us really flourish
and help bring out the best in our humanity rather than the worst of it to help us have
really fulfilling experiences that feel truly meaningful and and we you and i shouldn't sit
here and dictate the future generations what they will be let them figure it out but let's
give them a chance to live and and not foreclose all these possibilities for them by just messing
things up right now for that we have to solve the ai safety problem i just it'll be nice if
we can link on exploring that a little bit so one interesting way to enter that discussion is
you tweeted and elon replied you tweeted let's not just focus on whether gpt4 will do more harm or
good on the job market but also whether it's coding skills will hasten the arrival of super
intelligence that's something we've been talking about right so elon proposed one thing in their
reply saying maximum truth seeking is my best guess for ai safety can you maybe uh steelman the
case for this uh sense this objective function of truth and uh maybe make an argument against it
and in general what uh are your different ideas to start approaching the the solution to ai safety
i didn't see that reply actually oh interesting so but i really resonate with it because
ai is not evil it it caused people around the world to hate each other much more
but that's because we made it in a certain way it's a tool we can use it for great things and
bad things and we could just as well have ai systems and this is this is part of my vision
for success here truth seeking ai that really brings us together again you know why do people
hate each other so much between countries and within countries it's because they each have
totally different versions of the truth right if they all have the same truth that they trusted
for good reason because they could check it and verify it and not have to believe in some
self-proclaimed authority right they wouldn't be as nearly as much hate there'd be a lot more
understanding instead and this is i think something ai can help enormously with for example
a little baby step in this direction is this website called metaculous where
people bet and make predictions not for money but just for their own reputation
and it's kind of funny actually you treat the humans like you treat ai as you have a
lost function where they get penalized if they're super confident on something and then the opposite
happens yeah whereas if you're kind of humble and then you're like i think it's 51% chance this
is going to happen and then the other happens you don't get penalized much and and what you can see
is that some people are much better at predicting than others they've earned your trust right one
project that i'm working on right now is an outgrowth to improve the news foundation together
the metaculous folks is seeing if we can really scale this up a lot with more powerful ai because
i would love it i would love further to be like a really powerful truth seeking system where
that is trustworthy because it keeps being right about stuff and people who come to it and
maybe look at its latest trust ranking of different pundits and newspapers etc if they
want to know why some someone got a low score they can click on it and see all the predictions
that they actually made and how they turned out you know this is how we do it in science
you trust scientists like einstein who said something everybody thought was bullshit
and turned out to be right you get a lot for a trust point and he did it multiple times even
i think ai has the power to really heal a lot of the rifts we're seeing
by creating trust system it has to get away from this idea today with some fact-checking sites
which might themselves have an agenda and you just trust it because of its reputation
you want to have it so these sort of systems they earn their trust and that's completely
transparent this i think would actually help a lot that i think help heal the very dysfunctional
conversation that humanity has about how it's going to deal with all its biggest challenges
in the world today and then on the technical side you know another common sort of gloom
comment that yet from people are saying we're just screwed there's no hope
is well things like gpt4 are way too complicated for a human to ever understand
and prove that they can be trustworthy they're forgetting that ai can help us
prove that things work right and and there's this very fundamental fact that in math it's much
harder to come up with a proof than it is to verify that the proof is correct
you can actually write a little proof checking code it's quite short but you can as human
understand and then it can check most monstrously long proof ever generated even by a computer and
say yeah this is valid so so right now we we have um this uh this approach with virus checking
software that it looks to see if there's something if you should not trust it and if it can prove
to itself that you should not trust that code it warns you right what if you flip this around
and this is an idea i should give credit to steve i'm a hundred or four so that it will only run
the code if it can prove instead of not running it if it can prove that it's not trustworthy if
it will only run and if it can prove that it's trustworthy so it asks the code prove to me
that you're going to do what you say you're going to do and and it gives you this proof
and you a little proof tricker can check it now you can actually trust
an AI that's much more intelligent than you are right because you it's its problem to come
up with this proof that you could never have found that you should trust it so this is the
interesting point i i agree with you but this is where eliezer yakovsky might disagree with you
his claim not with you but with this idea is his claim is super intelligent AI
would be able to know how to lie to you with such a proof
how to lie to you and give me a proof that i'm gonna think is correct yeah but but it's not me
it's lying to you that's the trick my proof checker so yes so his general idea is a super
intelligent system can lie to a dumber proof checker so you're going to have as a system
because more and more intelligent there's going to be a threshold where a super intelligent system
would be able to effectively lie to a slightly dumber AGI system like there's a threat like he
really focuses on this weak AGI the strong AGI jump where the strong AGI can make all the weak
AGI's think that it's just one of them but it's no longer that and that leap is when it runs away
yeah i i don't buy that argument i think no matter how super intelligent an AI is it's never
going to be able to prove to me that they're only finitely many primes for example
and it just it just can't and and um it can try to snow me we're making up all sorts of new weird
rules of of deduction and that and say trust me you know the way your proof checker work is too
limited and we have this new hyper math and it's true but then i would i would just take the attitude
okay i'm going to forfeit some of these this supposedly super cool technologies i'm only
going to go with the ones that i can prove in my own trusted proof checker then i don't i think
it's fine there's still of course this is not something anyone has successfully implemented
at this point but i think it i just give it as an example of hope we don't have to do all the
work ourselves right this is exactly the sort of very boring and tedious tasks is perfect outsourced
to an AI and this is a way in which less powerful and less intelligent agents like us can actually
continue to control and trust more powerful ones so build a gi systems that help us defend against
other a gi systems well for starters begin with a simple problem of just making sure that the system
that you own or that's supposed to be loyal to you has to prove to itself that it's always
going to do the things that you actually wanted to do right and if it can't prove it maybe it's
still going to do it but you won't run it so you just forfeit some aspects of all the cool things
that i can do i i bet your dollars and donuts it can still do some incredibly cool stuff for you
yeah there are other things too that we shouldn't sweep under the rug like not every human agrees on
exactly where what direction we should go with humanity right yes and you've talked a lot about
geopolitical things on this on on your podcast to this effect you know but
i think that shouldn't distract us from the fact that there are actually a lot of things that
everybody in the world virtually agrees on that hey you know like having no humans on the planet
in a in a in a near future let's not do that right you look at something like the united
nation sustainable development goals some of them were quite ambitious and basically all the
countries agree us china russia ukraine you all agree so instead of quibbling about the little
things we don't agree on let's start with the things we do agree on and and and get them done
instead of being so distracted by all these things we disagree on that mollock wins because
frankly mollock going wild now it feels like a war on life playing out in front of our eyes
if you if you just look at it from space you know we're on this planet beautiful vibrant ecosystem
now we start chopping down big parts of it even though nobody most people thought that was a
bad idea always start doing ocean acidification wiping out all sorts of species oh now we have
all these close calls you almost had a nuclear war and we're replacing more and more of the biosphere
with non-living things we're also replacing in our social lives a lot of the things which
we're so valuable to humanity a lot of social interactions now are replaced by people staring
into their rectangles right and i i'm not a psychologist i'm out of my depth here but i
suspect that part of the reason why teen suicide and suicide in general in the u.s the
record-breaking levels is actually caused by again a so ai technologies and social media
that making people spend less time with with actually an actually just human interaction
we've all seen a bunch of good-looking people in restaurants staring into the rectangles
instead of looking into each other's eyes right that so that's also a part of the war on life
that that we're we're replacing so many really life-affirming things by technology we're we're
putting technology between us the technology that was supposed to connect us is actually
distancing us ourselves from each other and um and and then we're giving ever more power to
things which are not alive these large corporations are not living things right they're just maximizing
profit there i want to win them war on life i think we humans together with all our fellow
living things on this planet will be better off if we can remain in control over the non-living
things and make sure that they they work for us i really think it can be done can you just linger
on this um maybe high-level philosophical disagreement with eliezer yadkowski
i in this the hope you're stating so he is very sure he puts a very high probability
very close to one depending on the day he puts it at one uh that ai is going to kill humans
that there's just he does not see a trajectory which it doesn't end up with that conclusion
what uh what trajectory do you see that doesn't end up there and maybe can you
can you see the point he's making and and can you also see a way out
first of all i tremendously respect eliezer yadkowski and his his thinking second i do
share his view that there's a pretty large chance that we're not going to make it as humans there
won't be any humans on the planet and not the distant future and and that makes me very sad
you know we just had a little baby and i keep asking myself you know is um
how old is even gonna get you know and and um i asked myself it feels i i said to my wife recently
it feels a little bit like i was just diagnosed with some sort of um cancer which has some you know
risk of dying from and some risk of surviving you know uh except this is a kind of cancer which
would kill all of humanity so i completely take seriously his um his concerns i think um
but i don't absolutely don't think it's hopeless i think um there is a there is um first of all
a lot of momentum now for the first time actually since the many many years that have
passed since my since i and many others started warning about this i feel most people are getting
it now i i uh just talking to this guy in the gas station they were house the other day my
and he's like i think we're getting replaced and i think in it so that's positive that they're
finally we're finally seeing this reaction which is the first step towards solving the problem
uh second uh i really think that this this vision of only running ai's really if the stakes are
really high they can prove to us that they're safe it's really just virus checking in reverse
again i i think it's scientifically doable i don't think it's hopeless um we might have to
forfeit some of the technology that we could get if we were putting blind faith in our ai's
but we're still gonna get amazing stuff do you envision a process with a proof checker like
something like gpt4 gpt5 will go through a process no rigorous no no i think it's hopeless
that's like trying to prove fair about five spaghetti okay what i think well how the the
whole the vision i have for success is instead that you know just like we human beings were able
to look at our brains and and distill out the key knowledge Galileo when his dad threw him
an apple when he was a kid he was able to catch it because his brain could in this funny spaghetti
kind of way you know predict how parabolas are going to move his conaman system one right
but then he got older and it's like wait this is a parabola it's it's y equals x squared i can
distill this knowledge out and today you can easily program it into a computer and it can
simulate not just that but how to get tamars and so on right i envision a similar process
where we use the amazing learning power of neural networks to discover the knowledge in the first
place but we don't stop with a black box and and use that we then do a second round of ai
where we use automated systems to extract out the knowledge and see what is it look what are the
insights it's had okay and it's and then we we put that knowledge into a completely different
kind of architecture or programming language or whatever that's that's made in a way that
it can be both really efficient and also is more amenable to the very formal verification
that's that's my vision i'm not saying sitting here saying i'm confident
100 sure that it's gonna work you know but i don't think this chance is certainly not zero
either and it will certainly be possible to do for a lot of really cool ai applications
that we're not using now so we can have a lot of the fun that we're excited about
if we if we do this we're gonna need a little bit of time that's why it's good to pause and
put in place requirements one more thing also i i think you know someone might think well zero
percent chance we're gonna survive let's just give up right that's very dangerous
because there's no more guaranteed way it's a fail than to convince yourself that it's impossible
and not to try you know any if you you know when you're studying history and military history the
first thing you learn is that that's how you do psychological warfare you persuade the other side
that that's hopeless so they don't even fight and then of course you win right let's not do this
psychological warfare on ourselves and say there's a hundred percent probability we're all gonna we're
all screwed anyway it's sadly i i do get that a little bit sometimes from from uh
let's see some young people who are like so convinced that we're all screwed that they're like
i'm just gonna play game play computer games and do drugs and because we're screwed anyway right
it's important to keep the hope alive because it actually has a causal impact
and makes it makes it more likely that we're gonna succeed it seems like the people that actually
build solutions to a problem seemingly impossible to solve problems are the ones that believe yeah
they're the ones who are the optimists yeah and it's like uh it seems like there's some fundamental
law to the universe where fake it till you make it kind of works like believe yeah it's possible
and it becomes possible yeah was it henry ford who said that if you can if you tell yourself
that it's impossible it is so let's not make that mistake yeah and this is a big mistake
society is making you know i think all in all everybody's so gloomy and the media are also
very biased towards if it bleeds it leads and gloom and doom right so um most visions of the
future we have or or dystopian which really demotivates people we want to really really really
focus on the upside also to give people the willingness to fight for it and um
for ai you and i mostly talked about gloom here again but let's not remember not forget that you
know we have probably both lost someone we really cared about some disease that we were told were
was incurable well it's not there's no law of physics saying they had to die of that cancer
whatever of course you can cure it and there are so many other things where that we with
our human intelligence have also failed to solve on this planet which ai could also very much help
us with right so if we can get this right just be a little more chill and slow down a little bit
so we get it right it's mind blowing how awesome our future can be right we talked a lot about
stuff on earth can be great but even if you really get ambitious and look up into the skies right
there's no reason we have to be stuck on this planet for the rest of um the remain for billions
of years to come we totally understand now as laws of physics let life spread out into space
to other solar systems to other galaxies and flourish for billions of billions of years
and this to me is a very very hopeful vision
that really motivates me to to fight and coming back to the end something you talked about again
you know this the struggle how the human struggle is one of the things that also really gives meaning
to our lives if there's ever been an epic struggle this is it and isn't it even more epic if you're
the underdog if most people are telling you this is gonna fail it's impossible right and you persist
and you succeed right and that's what we can do together as a species on this one a lot of
pundits are ready to count this out both in the battle to keep AI safe and becoming a
multi-planetary species yeah and they're they're the same challenge if we can keep AI safe that's
how we're gonna get multi-planetary very efficiently i have some sort of technical questions about
how to get it right so one idea that i'm not even sure what the right answer is to is
should systems like GPT-4 be open sourced in whole or in part can make the can you see the
case for either i think the answer right now is no i think the answer early on was yes so we could
bring in all the wonderful great thought process of everybody on this but asking should we open
source GPT-4 now is just the same as if you say well is it good should we open source
how to build really small nuclear weapons should we open source how to make bio weapons
should we open source how to make a new virus that kills 90% of everybody who gets it of course we
shouldn't so it's already that powerful it's already that powerful that we have to respect
the power of the systems we've built the knowledge that you get
from open sourcing everything we do now might very well be powerful enough that people looking at
that can use it to build the things that you're really threatening again let's get it remember
open AI is GPT-4 is a baby AI baby sort of baby proto almost a little bit AGI according to what
Microsoft's recent paper said right it's not that that we're scared of what we're scared about
is people taking that who are who might be a lot less responsible than the company that made it
and just going to town with it that's why we want to it's it's an information hazard
there are many things which yeah are not open sourced right now in society for a very good reason
like how do you make certain kind of very powerful toxins out of stuff you can buy
and Home Depot you know you don't open source those things for a reason
and this is really no different so I'm saying that I have to say it feels in a bit weird in a
way a bit weird to say it because MIT is like the cradle of the open source movement and I love
open source in general power to the people let's say but there's always gonna be some stuff that
you don't open source and you know it's just like you don't open source so we have a three month old
baby right when he gets a little bit older we're not going to open source to him all the most
dangerous things he could do in the house yeah right but it does it's a weird feeling because
this is one of the first moments in history where there's a strong case to be made not to open
source software this is when the software has become too dangerous yeah but it's not the first
time that we didn't want to open source a technology technology yeah
is there something to be said about how to get the release of such systems right like GPT-4 and
GPT-5 so open AI went through a pretty rigorous effort for several months you could say it could
be longer but nevertheless it's longer than you would have expected of trying to test the system
to see like what are the ways it goes wrong to make it very difficult for people while
somewhat difficult for people to ask things how do I make a bomb for one dollar or how do I
say I hate a certain group on Twitter in a way that doesn't get me blocked from Twitter ban from
Twitter those kinds of questions yeah so you basically use the system to do harm yeah is there
something you could say about ideas you have it's just on looking having thought about this problem
of AI safety how to release such system how to test such systems when you have them inside the company
yeah so
a lot of people say that the two biggest risks from large language models are
it's spreading disinformation harmful information of various types
of threats and second being used for offensive cyber weapon
design I think those are not the two greatest threats they're very serious threats and it's
wonderful that people are trying to mitigate them a much bigger elephant in the room is how
is this going to disrupt the economy in a huge way obviously and maybe take away a lot of the
most meaningful jobs and an even bigger one is the one we spent so much time talking about here
that that this becomes the bootloader for the more powerful AI right code connected to the
internet manipulate humans yeah and before we know when we have something else which is not
at all a large language model that looks nothing like it but which is way more intelligent and
capable and has goals and that's the that's the elephant in the room and and obviously no matter
how hard any of these companies have tried they that's not something that's easy for them to verify
with large language models and the only way to be really lower that risk a lot would be
to not let for example train not never let it read any code not train on that and not put it
into an API and not not give it access to so much information about how to manipulate humans
so but that doesn't mean you still can't make a lot a ton of money on them you know we're
going to just watch now this coming year right Microsoft is rolling out the new office suite
where you go into Microsoft Word and give it a prompt that it writes the whole text for you
and then you edit it and then you're like oh give me a PowerPoint version of this and it makes it
and now take the spreadsheet and blah and you know all of those things I think are you can debate
the economic impact of it and whether society is prepared to deal with this disruption but those
are not the things which that's not the elephant of the room that keeps me awake at night for wiping
out humanity and I think that's the biggest misunderstanding we have a lot of people think
they were scared of like automatic spreadsheets that's not the case that's not what Eliezer
was freaked out about either is there in terms the actual mechanism of how AI might kill all humans
so something you've been outspoken about you've talked about a lot is it autonomous weapon systems
so the use of AI in war is that one of the things that still you carry a concern for
as these systems become more and more powerful and carry a concern for it not that all humans
are going to get killed by slaughterbots but rather just this express route into Orwellian dystopia
where it becomes much easier for very few to kill very many and therefore it becomes very easy for
very few to dominate very many right if you want to know how I could kill all people just ask yourself
we humans have driven a lot of species extinct how do we do it you know we were smarter than them
usually we didn't do it even systematically by going around one on one one after the other and
stepping on them or shooting them or anything like that we just like chopped down their habitat
because we needed it for something else in some cases we did it by putting more carbon dioxide
in the atmosphere because of some reason that those animals didn't even understand and now
they're gone right so if if you're in AI and you just want to figure something out then you decide
you know we just really need them this space here to build more compute facilities you know
if that's the only goal it has you know we are just the sort of accidental roadkill along the
way and you could totally imagine yeah maybe this oxygen is kind of annoying because it
caused more corrosion so let's get rid of the oxygen and good luck surviving after that you
know I I'm not particularly concerned that they would want to kill us just because
that would be like a goal in itself you know when we
driven number we've driven a number of the elephant species extinct right it wasn't
because we didn't like elephants what the basic problem is you just don't want to give
you don't want to seed control over your planet to some other more intelligent
entity that doesn't share your goals it's that simple so which brings us to another key challenge
which AI safety researchers have been grappling with for a long time like how do you make AI
first of all understand our goals and then adopt our goals and then retain them as they get smarter
right and all three of those are really hard right like a human child first they're just not
smart enough to understand our goals they can't even talk and then eventually they're teenagers
and understand our goals just fine but they don't share yeah but there's fortunately a
magic phase in the middle where they're smart enough to understand our goals and malleable
enough that we can hopefully with good parenting and teach them right from wrong and instead good
goal is still good goals in them right and so those are all tough challenges with computers
and then you know even if you teach your kids good goals when they're little they might outgrow
them too and that's a challenge for machines and they keep improving so these are a lot of hard
hard challenges we're up for but I don't think any of them are insurmountable the fundamental
reason why eliezer looked so depressed when I last saw him was because he felt it just wasn't
enough time oh that not that it was unsolvable correct it's just not enough time he was hoping
that humanity was going to take this threat more seriously so we would have more time yeah
and now we don't have more time that's why the open letter is calling for more time
but even with time the ai alignment problem seems to be really difficult oh yeah
but it's also the most worthy problem the most important problem for humanity to ever solve
because if we solve that one lex that aligned the eye can help us solve all the other problems
because it seems like it has to have constant humility about his goal constantly question the goal
because as you optimize towards a particular goal and you start to achieve it that's when
you have the unintended consequences all the things you mentioned about so how do you enforce and
code a constant humility as your ability become better and better and better and better
steward professor steward russell berkeley who's also one of the
driving forces behind this letter he uh has a whole research program about this
i think of it as ai humility exactly although he calls it inverse reinforcement learning
and other nerdy terms but it's about exactly that instead of telling the ai here's his goal go
optimize the the bejesus out of it you tell it okay do what i want you to do but i'm not going
to tell you right now what it is i want you to do you need to figure it out so then you give the
incentives to be very humble and keep asking you questions along the way is this what you really
meant is this what you wanted and oh this the other thing i tried didn't work seemed like it
didn't work out right should i try it differently what's nice about this is it's not just philosophical
mumbo jumbo it's theorems and technical work that with more time i think it can make a lot of
progress and there are a lot of brilliant people now working on ai safety we just not we just need
to give them a bit more time but also not that many relative to the scale of the problem no
exactly there there should be at least as just like every university worth its name has some
cancer research going on in its biology department right every university that's computer that does
computer science should have a real effort in this area and it's nowhere near that this is
something i hope is changing now thanks to the gpt4 right so i i think um if there's a silver lining
to um what's happening here even though i think many people would wish it would have been rolled
out more carefully is that this might be the wake-up call that humanity needed to really
stop the stop fantasizing about this being 100 years off and stop fantasizing about this being
completely controllable and predictable because it's so obvious it's it's not predictable you know
why is it that open that that i think it was gpt chat gpt tried to persuade um a journalist
a journalist where was the gpt4 to divorce his wife you know it was not because the
engineers had built it was like let's put this in here and and screw a little bit with people
they hadn't predicted at all they built the giant black box and trained to predict the next word
and got all these emergent properties and oops it did this you know um
i think this is a very powerful wake-up call and anyone watching this who's not scared
i would encourage them to just play a bit more with these these tools they're out there now like
gpt4 and um it's a wake-up call it's first step once you've woken up uh then gotta slow down a
little bit the risky stuff to give a chance to all everyone who's woken up to to catch up with
us on the safety front you know what's interesting is you know mit that's computer science but in
general but let's just even say computer science curriculum how does the computer science curriculum
change now you mentioned you mentioned programming yeah like why would you be when i was coming up
programming as a prestigious position like why would you be dedicating crazy amounts of
time to become an excellent programmer like the nature of programming is fundamentally changing
the nature of our entire education system is completely torn on its head i has anyone been
able to like load that in and like think about because it's really turning i mean some english
professors or english teachers are beginning to really freak out now yeah right they give an essay
assignment and they get back all these fantastic pros like this is the style of Hemingway and
and then they realize they have to completely rethink and even you know just like we stopped
teaching writing uh script is that what you're saying english yeah handwritten yeah yeah when
when everybody started typing you know like so much of what we teach our kids today
yeah i mean that's uh everything is changing and it's changing very it is changing very quickly
and so much of us understanding how to deal with the big problems of the world is through the
education system and if the education system is being turned on its head then what what's next
it feels like having these kinds of conversations is essential to try to figure it out and everything
is happening so rapidly uh i don't think there's even you're speaking of safety what the broad
ai safety defined i don't think most universities have courses on ai safety no it's a philosophy
and like i'm an educator myself so it pains me to see this say this but i feel our education
right now is that completely obsoleted by what's happening you know you put a kid into first grade
and then uh you envisioning like and then they're gonna come out of high school 12 years later
and you've already pre-planned now what they're gonna learn when you're not even sure if there's
going to be any world left to come out to like clearly you need to have a much more
opportunistic education system that keeps adapting itself very rapidly as society re-adapts
the the skills that were really useful when the curriculum was written i mean how many of those
skills are going to get you a job in 12 years i mean seriously if we just linger on the gpt4 system
a little bit you kind of hinted at it especially talking about the importance of consciousness
in uh in the human mind with home ascents do you think gpt4 is conscious i love this question
so let's define consciousness first because in my experience like 90% of all arguments
about consciousness are allowed to the two people arguing having totally different
definitions of what it is and they're just shouting past each other i define consciousness
as subjective experience right now i'm experiencing colors and sounds and emotions you know
but does a self-driving car experience anything that's the question about whether it's conscious
or not right other people think you should define consciousness differently fine by me but then maybe
use a different word for it or they i'm gonna use consciousness for this at least um so um
but if people hate the yeah so is gpt4 conscious does gpt4 have subjective experience
short answer i don't know because we still don't know what it is that gives this wonderful
subjective experience that is kind of the meaning of our life right because meaning itself the
feeling of meaning is a subjective experience joy is a subjective experience love is a subjective
experience we don't know what it is i've written some papers about this a lot of people have
the julio tononi professor has stuck his neck out the farthest and written down actually very
bold mathematical conjecture for what's the essence of conscious information processing
he might be wrong he might be right but we should test it uh he postulates that consciousness has
to do with loops in the information processing so our brain has loops information can go round
and round in computer science nerd speak you call it a recurrent neural network where some
of the output gets fed back in again and with his mathematical formalism if it's a feed forward
neural network where information only goes in one direction like from your eye retina into the
back of your brain for example that's not conscious so he would predict that your retina itself isn't
conscious of anything or a video camera now the interesting thing about gpt4 is it's also just
one way flow of information so if tononi is right and gpt4 is a very intelligent zombie
that can do all this smart stuff but isn't experiencing anything and this is both a relief
in that you don't have if it's true you know in that you don't have to feel guilty about turning
off gpt4 and wiping its memory whenever a new user comes along i wouldn't like if someone used that
to me neuralized me like in men in black but it's also creepy that you can have very high
intelligence perhaps then it's not conscious because if we get replaced by machines
otherwise it's sad enough that humanity isn't here anymore because i kind of like humanity
but at least if the machines were conscious it could be like well but there are descendants and
maybe we they have our values and there are children but if if tononi is right and it's all
these are all transformers that are not in the sense of the of hollywood but in the sense of these
one-way direction neural networks so they're all the zombies that's the ultimate zombie apocalypse
now we have this universe that goes on with great construction projects and stuff but there's no one
experiencing anything that would be like the ultimate depressing future so i i actually think
as we move forward to the building world last day i should do more research on figuring out what
kind of information processing actually has experience because i think that's what it's all
about and i completely don't buy the dismissal that some people some people will say well this
is all bullshit because consciousness equals intelligence right it's obviously not true you
can have a lot of conscious experience when you're not really accomplishing any goals at all you're
just reflecting on something and you can sometimes um have things doing things that are quite
intelligent probably without being being conscious but i also worry that we humans won't
we'll discriminate against the AI systems that clearly exhibit consciousness that we will not
allow AI systems to have consciousness we'll come up with theories about measuring consciousness
that will say this is a lesser being and this is why i worry about that because maybe we humans
will create something that is better than us humans in the in the way that we find beautiful
which is they they have a deeper subjective experience of reality not only are they smarter
but they feel deeper and we humans will hate them for it as we as human history is shown
they'll be the other we'll try to suppress it they'll create conflict they'll create war
all of this i i worry about this too are you saying that we humans sometimes come up with
self-serving arguments no we would never do that would be well that's the danger here is uh
even in this early stages we might create something beautiful yeah and uh we'll erase its memory i i uh
was horrified as a kid when someone started boiling uh boiling lobsters like oh my god that
that's so cruel and some grown up there that's back in sweden so it doesn't feel pain i'm like
how do you know that oh scientists have shown that and then there was a recent study where they
show that lobsters actually do feel pain when you boil them so they banned lobsters boiling in
switzerland now you have to kill them in a different way first so presumably that scientific research
boiled out to someone asked the lobsters has this hurt survey so we do the same thing with
cruelty to farm animals also all these self-serving arguments for why they're fine and yeah so we
should certainly be watchful i think step one is just be humble and acknowledge that consciousness
is not the same thing as intelligence and i believe that consciousness still is a form of
information processing where it's really information being aware of itself in a certain way and
let's study it and give ourselves a little bit of time and i think we will be able to figure out
actually what it is that causes consciousness and then we can make probably unconscious robots
that do the boring jobs that we would feel are immoral to get the machines but if you have a
companion robot taking care of your mom or something like that you would probably want it
to be conscious right so the emotions it seems to display aren't fake all these things can be
done in a good way if we give ourselves a little bit of time and don't run and take on this challenge
is there something you could say to the timeline that you think about about the development of AGI
depending on the day i'm sure that changes for you but when do you think there will be a really big
leap in intelligence where you definitively say we have built AGI do you think it's one year from
now five years from now 10 20 50 what's your gut say honestly
for the past decade i've deliberately given very long timelines because i didn't want to fuel some
kind of stupid malloc race yeah um but i think that cat has really left the bag now
and i think it might be very very close i don't think the microsoft paper is totally off when
they say that there are some glimmers of AGI it's not AGI yet it's not an agent there's a lot of
things it can't do but um i wouldn't bet very strongly against it happening very soon that's
why we decided to do this open letter because you know if there's ever been a time to pause
you know it's today there's a feeling like this GPT-4 is a big transition into waking everybody
out to the effectiveness of the system and so the next version will be big yeah and if that
next one isn't AGI maybe the next next one will and there are many companies trying to do these
things and the basic architecture of them is not some sort of super well-kept secret so
this is this is a time to a lot of people have said for many years that there will come a time
when we want to pause a little bit that time is now
you have spoken about and thought about nuclear war a lot over the past year we've
we've seemingly have come closest to the precipice of nuclear war than uh at least in my lifetime
yeah what do you learn about human nature from that it's our old friend Malak again
it's really scary to see it where America doesn't want there to be a nuclear war Russia
doesn't want there to be a global nuclear war either we know we both know that it's just
being others if we just try to do it it both sides try to launch first it's just another
suicide race right so why are we why is it the way you said that this is the closest we've come
since 1962 in fact i think we've come closer now than even the Cuban Missile Crisis it's
because of Malak you know you you have these other forces on one hand you have the west
saying that we have to drive Russia out of Ukraine it's a matter of pride and we've staked so much
on it that it would be seen as a huge loss of the credibility of the west if we don't drive
Russia out entirely of the Ukraine and on the other hand you have Russia who has and you have
the Russian leadership who knows that if they get completely driven out of Ukraine you know
it might it's not just going to be very humiliating for them but they might it often happens when
countries lose wars that things don't go so well for their leadership either like you remember when
Argentina invaded the Falkland Islands the the military junta that ordered that right people
were cheering on the streets at first when they took it and then when they got their butt kicked
by the British you know what happened to those guys they were out and I believe those were
still alive or in jail now right so so you know the Russian leadership is entirely cornered where
they know that just getting driven out of Ukraine is not an option and
so this to me is a typical example of Malik you you have these incentives of the two parties
where both of them are just driven to escalate more and more right if Russia starts losing in
the conventional warfare the only thing they can do is to back against the war is to keep
escalating and but and the west has put itself in the in the situation now we're sort of already
committed to the dry rush out so the only option the west has is to call Russia's bluff and keep
sending in more weapons this really bothers me because Malik can sometimes drive competing
parties to do something which is ultimately just really bad for both of them and you know
what makes me even more worried is not just that it's difficult to see an ending
a quick peaceful ending to this tragedy that doesn't involve some horrible escalation
but also that we understand more clearly now just how horrible it was going to be
there was an amazing paper that was published in Nature Food this August
by some of the top researchers who've been studying nuclear winter for a long time and what
they basically did was they combined climate models with food agricultural models so instead
of just saying yeah you know it gets really cold blah blah blah they figured out actually how
many people would die in the different different countries and it's uh it's pretty mind blowing
you know so basically what happens you know is that the thing that kills the most people is not
the explosions it's not the radioactivity it's not the EMP mayhem it's not the rampaging mobs
foraging food no it's the fact that you get so much smoke coming up from the burning cities
into the stratosphere that spreads around the earth from the jet streams so in typical models
you get like 10 years or so where it's just crazy cold and during the first year or
after the the war and their models the temperature drops in in Nebraska and in the Ukraine
bread baskets you know by like 20 Celsius or so if I remember no yeah 20 30 Celsius depending
on where you are 40 Celsius in some places which is you know 40 Fahrenheit to 80 Fahrenheit colder
than what it would normally be so you know I'm not good at farming but uh if it's snowing
if it drops below freezing pretty much most days in July and then like that's not good so
they worked out they put this into their farming models and what they found was really interesting
the countries that get the most hard hit are the ones in the northern hemisphere
so in in the US and and one model they had about 99 percent of all Americans starving to death
in Russia and China and Europe also about 99 98 percent starving to death
so you might be like oh it's kind of poetic justice that both the Russians and the Americans
99 percent of them have to pay for it because it was their bombs that did it but
you know that doesn't particularly cheer people up in Sweden or other random countries that have
nothing to do with it right and um it uh I think it hasn't entered the mainstream
not understanding very much just like how bad this is most people especially a lot of people
in decision-making positions still think of nuclear weapons as something that makes you powerful
uh scary powerful they don't think of it as something where uh yeah just
to within a percent or two you know we're all just just gonna starve to death
and um and starving to death is is um the worst way to die as holly molly is all all the
famines in history show the torture involved in that probably brings out the worst in people also
when when people are desperate like this it's not so some people I've heard some people say that
if that's what's gonna happen they'd rather be at round zero and just get vaporized you know
but uh so but I think people underestimate the risk of this because they they
they aren't afraid of malloc they think oh it's just gonna be because humans don't want this so
it's not gonna happen that's the whole point the malloc that things happen that nobody wanted
and that applies to nuclear weapons and that applies to agi
exactly and it applies to some of the things that people have gotten most upset with capitalism
for also right where everybody was just kind of trapped you know it it's not to see if some
company does something uh it causes a lot of harm and not that the ceo is a bad person
but she or he knew that you know that the other all the other companies were doing this too so
malloc is um as a formable foe I hope which someone makes good movies so we can see who
the real enemy is we don't because we're not fighting against each other uh malloc makes
us fight against each other that's more that's what malloc superpower is the hope here is any
kind of technology or the mechanism that lets us instead realize that we're fighting the wrong
enemy right now it's such a fascinating battle it's not us versus them it's us versus it yeah yeah
we are fighting malloc for human survival yeah we as a civilization have you seen the movie
needful things it's a steven king novel I love steven king and uh max von sudo of
Swedish actors playing the guys it's brilliant exactly I just thought I hadn't thought about
that until now but that's the closest I've seen to a a movie about malloc I don't want to spoil
the film for anyone who wants to watch it but basically it's about this guy who turns out to
you can interpret him as the devil or whatever but he doesn't actually ever go around or
and kill people or torture people will go burning coal or anything he makes everybody fight each
other it makes everybody hate fear each other hate each other and then kill each other so that
that's the movie about malloc you know love is the answer that seems to be um one of the ways to
fight malloc is by um compassion by seeing the common humanity yes yes and to not sound so we
don't sound like like uh was it kumbaya tree huggers here right we're not just saying love
and peace man we're trying to actually help people understand the true facts about the other side
and feel the compassion because the truth makes you more compassionate right
so I that's why I really like using AI for truth and for truth seeking technologies can
that can as a result you know get us more love than hate and and even if you can't get love you
know settle for settle for some understanding which already gives compassion if someone is like you
know I really disagree with you lex but I can see why you're where you're coming from you're not a
bad person who needs to be destroyed but I disagree with you and I'm happy to have an
argument about it you know that's a lot of progress compared to where we are 2023 in
the public space wouldn't you say if we solve the AI safety problem as we've talked about
and then you max tag mark who has been talking about this uh for many years get to sit down
with the agi with the early agi system on a beach with a drink uh what what what kind of what would
you ask her what kind of question would you ask what would you talk about something so much smarter
than you would be would you be afraid we're gonna get me with a really zinger of a question
would you be afraid to ask some questions yeah so I'm not afraid of the truth I'm very humble I
know I'm just a meat bag you with all these flaws you know but yeah I I have the I we talked a lot
about homo sentience I've really already tried that for a long time with myself just so that is
what's really valuable about being alive for me is that I have these meaningful experiences
it's not that I'm have what I'm good at this or good at that or whatever there's so much I suck at
and so you're not afraid for the system to show you just how dumb you are no no in fact my son
reminds me that you could find out how dumb you are in terms of physics how little how little
we humans understand I'm cool with that I think I think um so I can't waffle my way out of this
question it's a fair one I think given that I'm a really really curious person that's
really the defining part of who I am I'm so curious
uh I have some physics questions I love to love to understand I have some questions about
consciousness about the nature of reality I would just really really love to understand also
I could tell you one for example that I've been obsessing about a lot recently
so I believe that so suppose tenoni is right as opposed there are some information processing
systems that are conscious and some they're not suppose you can even make reasonably smart things
like gpt4 they're not conscious but you can also make them conscious here's the question that keeps
me naked night is it the case that the unconscious zombie systems that are really intelligent
are also really efficient so they're really inefficient so that when you try to make things
more efficient we still naturally be a pressure to do they become conscious I'm kind of hoping
that that's correct and I do you want me to give you a hand away the argument for it please you know
like in my lab again every time we look at how how these large language models do something we
see they do them in really dumb ways and you could you could make it make it better if if you uh
we have loops in our computer language for a reason the code would get way way longer if you
weren't allowed to use them it's more efficient to have the loops and in order to have self-reflection
whether it's conscious or not right even an operating system knows things about itself right
you need to have loops already right so I think this is I'm waving my hands a lot but I suspect that
the most efficient way of implementing a given level of intelligence
has loops in it the self-reflection can and will be conscious isn't that great news yes if it's
true it's wonderful because then we don't have to fear the ultimate zombie apocalypse and I think
if you look at our brains actually our brains are part zombie and part conscious
when I open my eyes I immediately take all these pixels that hit my on my retina right and like oh
that's Lex but I have no freaking clue of how I did that computation it's actually quite complicated
right it was only relatively recently we could even do it well with machines right you get a bunch
of information processing happening in my retina then it goes to the lateral genicular nucleus
my thalamus and the vision the area v1 v2 v4 and the fusiform face area here that Nancy can
wish her at MIT invented and blah blah blah blah and I have no freaking clue how that worked right
it feels to me subjectively like my conscious module just got a little email say
face facial processing uh fit task complete it's Lex yeah and I'm gonna just go with that right
so uh this fits perfectly with Tanone's model because this was all one way information processing
mainly and uh it turned out for that particular task that's all you needed and it probably was
kind of the most efficient way to do it but there were a lot of other things that we associated with
higher intelligence and planning and and so on and so forth where you kind of want to have loops and
be able to ruminate and self-reflect and introspect and so on where my hunch is that if you want to
fake that with a zombie system that just all goes one way you have to like unroll those loops and it
just really really long and it's much more inefficient so I'm actually hopeful that AI
if in the future we have all these very sublime and interesting machines that do cool things
and are lined with us that they will at least they will also have consciousness for the kind of
these things that we do that great intelligence is also correlated to great consciousness or a deep
kind of consciousness yes so that's a happy thought for me because the zombie apocalypse
really is my worst nightmare of all it would be like adding insult to injury not only did we get
replaced but we friggin replaced ourselves by zombies like how dumb can we be uh that's such a
beautiful vision and that's actually a provable one that's one that we humans can uh intuit and
prove that those two things are correlated as we start to understand what it means to be intelligent
and what it means to be conscious which these systems uh early AGI like systems will help us
understand and I just want to say one more thing which is super important most of my colleagues
when I started going on about consciousness tell me that it's all bullshit and I should stop talking
about it I hear a little inner voice from my father and from my mom saying keep talking about it
because I think they're wrong and and and the main way to convince people like that that they're
wrong if they say that consciousness is just equal to intelligence is to ask them what's wrong with
torture now why are you against torture if it's just about you know these these particles
moving this way around on that way and there is no such thing as subjective experience what's
wrong with torture I mean do you have a good comeback to that no it seems like suffering
suffering imposed on other humans is somehow deeply wrong in a way that intelligence doesn't
quite explain and if someone tells me well you know it's just an illusion consciousness
whatever you know I like to invite them the next time they're having surgery to do it without
anesthesia like what is anesthesia really doing if you have it you can have a local anesthesia
when you're awake I had that when they fixed my shoulder I was super entertaining uh
uh what was that that it did it just removed my subjective experience of pain it didn't change
anything about what was actually happening in my shoulder right so if someone says that's all
bullshit skip the anesthesia as my advice this is incredibly central it could be fundamental
to whatever this thing we have going on here it is fundamental because we're we what we feel
is so fundamental is suffering and joy and pleasure and meaning and
that's all those are all subjective experiences there and let's not those are the elephant in
the room that's what makes life worth living and that's what can make it horrible if it's just
those are suffering so let's not make the mistake of saying that that's all bullshit and let's not
make the mistake of uh not instilling the AI systems with that same thing that makes us
special yeah max it's a huge honor that you will sit down to me the first time
on the first episode of this podcast it's a huge honor to sit down again and talk about this what
I think is the most important topic the most important problem that we humans have to face
and hopefully solve yeah well the honor is all mine and I'm I'm so grateful to you for making
more people aware of this fact that humanity has reached the most important fork in the road
ever in its history and let's turn in the correct direction thanks for listening to this conversation
with max tag mark to support this podcast please check out our sponsors in the description and
now let me leave you with some words from frank harbert history is a constant race
between invention and catastrophe thank you for listening and hope to see you next time