Today we have Josh Tenenbaum. He's a professor here at MIT, leading the Computational Cognitive
Science Group. Among many other topics in cognition and intelligence, he is fascinated
with the question of how human beings learn so much from so little, and how these insights
can lead to build AI systems that are much more efficient learning from data. So please
give Josh a warm welcome.
Alright, thank you very much. Thanks for having me. Excited to be part of what looks like
really quite a very impressive lineup, especially starting after today. And it's, I think, quite a
great opportunity to get to see perspectives on artificial intelligence from many of the
leaders in industry and other entities working on this great quest. So I'm going to talk to you
about some of the work that we do in our group, but also I'm going to try to give a broader
perspective, reflective of a number of MIT faculty, especially those who are affiliated with the
Center for Brains, Minds, and Machines. So you can see up there on my affiliation, academically
I'm part of Brain and Cognitive Science, or Course 9. I'm also part of CSAIL, but I'm also part of
the Center for Brains, Minds, and Machines, which is an NSF-funded center, Science and Technology
Center, which really stands for the bridge between the science and the engineering of intelligence. It
literally straddles Vassar Street in that we have CSAIL and BCS members. We also have partners at
Harvard and other academic institutions. And again, what we stand for, I want to try to convey
some of the specific things we're doing in the center and where we want to go with a vision that
really is about jointly pursuing the science, the basic science of how intelligence arises in the
human mind and brain, and also the engineering enterprise of how to build something increasingly
like human intelligence in machines. And we deeply believe that these two projects have something to do
with each other and are best pursued jointly. Now it's a really exciting time to be doing anything
related to intelligence or certainly to AI for all the reasons that, you know, brought you all here.
I don't have to tell you this. We have all these ways in which AI is kind of finally here. We finally
live in the era of something like real practical AI, or for those who've been around for a while and
have seen some of the rises and falls, you know, AI is back in a big way. But from my perspective,
and I think maybe this reflects, you know, why we distinguish what we might call AGI from AI, we don't
really have any real AI, basically. We have what I like to call AI technologies, which are systems
that do things we used to think that only humans could do. And now we have machines that do them,
often quite well, maybe even better than any human who's ever lived, right? Like a machine that plays go.
But none of these systems, I would say, are truly intelligent. None of them have anything like common sense.
None of them have anything like the flexible general purpose intelligence that each of you might use to learn
every one of these skills or tasks, right? Each of these systems had to be built by large teams of engineers,
working together often for a number of years at often at great cost to somebody who's willing to pay for it.
And each of them just does one thing. So AlphaGo might beat the world's best, but it can't drive to the match,
or even tell you what go is. It can't even tell you that go is a game, because it doesn't even know what a game is, right?
So what's missing? What is it that makes every one of your brains, maybe you can't beat, you know, the world's best in go,
but any one of you can get behind the wheel of a car. I think of this because my daughter is going to turn 16 tomorrow.
If she lived in California, she'd have a driver's license. It's a little bit down the line for us here in Massachusetts.
But, you know, she didn't have to be specially engineered by billion-dollar startups.
And, you know, she got really into chess recently, and now she's taught herself chess by playing just, you know,
and a handful of games, basically. And she can do any one of these activities, and any one of us can.
So what is it? What makes up the difference? Well, there's many things, right?
I'll talk about the focus for us in our research, and a lot of us, again, in CBMM, is summarized here.
What drives the successes right now in AI, especially in industry, okay, and all these AI technologies, is many, many things, many things.
But what's where the progress has been made most recently, and what's getting most of the attention is, of course, deep learning,
but other kinds of machine learning technologies, which essentially represent the maturation of a decades-long effort to solve the problem of pattern recognition.
That means taking data and finding patterns in the data that tell you something you care about, like how to label a class or how to predict some other signal, okay?
And pattern recognition is great. It's an important part of intelligence, and it's reasonable to say that deep learning as a technology
has really made great strides on pattern recognition, and maybe even, you know, has come in close to solving the problems of pattern recognition.
But intelligence is about many other things. Intelligence is about a lot more. In particular, it's about modeling the world,
and think about all the activities that a human does to model the world that go beyond, just say, recognizing patterns in data,
but actually trying to explain and understand what we see, for instance, okay?
Or to be able to imagine things that we've never seen, that never seen, maybe even very different from anything we've ever seen,
but what I want to see, and then to set those as goals, to make plans and solve problems needed to make those things real,
or thinking about learning, again, that, you know, some kinds of learning can be thought of as pattern recognition
if you're learning sufficient statistics or weights in a neural net that are used for those purposes.
But many activities of learning are about building out new models, right?
Either refining, reusing, improving old models, or actually building fundamentally new models as you've experienced more of the world.
And then think about sharing our models, communicating our models to others, modeling their models, learning from them.
All these activities of modeling, these are at the heart of human intelligence, and it requires a much broader set of tools.
So I want to talk about the ways we're studying these activities of modeling the world and something in a pretty non-technical way
about what are the kind of tools that allow us to capture these abilities.
Now, I think it's, I want to be very honest up front and to say this is just the beginning of a story, right?
When you look at deep learning successes, that itself is a story that goes back decades.
I'll say a little bit about that history in a minute.
But where we are now is just looking forward to a future when we might be able to capture these abilities,
at a really mature engineering scale.
And I would say we are far from being able to capture all the ways in which humans richly, flexibly, quickly build models of the world
at the kind of scale that, say, Silicon Valley wants.
Either big tech companies like Google, or Microsoft, or IBM, or Facebook, or small startups, right?
We can get there.
And I think what I want to talk to you about here is one route for trying to get there.
And this is the route that CBMM stands for.
The idea that by reverse engineering how intelligence works in the human mind and brain,
that will give us a route to engineering these abilities in machines.
When we say reverse engineering, we're talking about science, but doing science like engineers.
This is our fundamental principle.
That if we approach cognitive science and neuroscience like an engineer,
where, say, the output of our science isn't just a description of the brain or the mind in words,
but in the same terms that an engineer would use to build an intelligent system,
then that will be both the basis for a much more rigorous and deeply insightful science,
but also direct translation of those insights into engineering applications.
Now, before I talk a little bit about history, what I mean by that is this.
Again, if part of what brought you here is deep learning, and I know,
even if you've never heard of deep learning before, which I'm sure is unlikely,
you saw a good spectrum of that in the overview session last night.
It's really interesting and important to look back on the history of where did techniques for deep learning come from,
or reinforcement learning.
Those are the two tools in the current machine learning arsenal that are getting the most attention.
Things like back propagation or end-to-end stochastic gradient descent
or temporal difference learning or Q-learning.
Here's a few papers from the literature.
Maybe some of you have read these original papers.
Here's the original paper by Rumelhardt, Hinton, and colleagues
in which they introduced the back propagation algorithm for training multi-layer perceptrons,
multi-layer neural networks.
Here's the original perceptron paper by Rosenblatt,
which introduced the one-layer version of that architecture
and the basic perceptron learning algorithm.
Here's the first paper on the temporal difference learning method
for reinforcement learning from Sutton and Bartow.
Here's the original Boltzmann machine paper also by Hinton and colleagues,
those of you who don't know that architecture think of a probabilistic undirected multi-layer perceptron.
For example, before there were LSTMs, if you know about current-recurrent neural network architecture,
earlier much simpler versions of the same idea were proposed by Jeff Elman
and his simple-recurrent networks.
The reason I want to put up the original papers here
is for you to look at both when they were published and where they were published.
If you look at the dates, you'll see papers going back to the 80s,
but even the 60s or even the 1950s.
Look at where they were published.
Most of them were published in psychology journals.
The journal Psychological Review, if you don't know,
it is like the leading journal of theoretical psychology and mathematical psychology,
or Cognitive Science, the journal of the Cognitive Science Society,
or the back prop paper was published in Nature, which is a general interest science journal,
but by people who are mostly affiliated with the Institute for Cognitive Science in San Diego.
What you see here is already a long history of scientists thinking like engineers.
These are people who are in psychology or cognitive science departments
and publishing in those places,
but by formalizing even very basic insights about how humans might learn
or how brains might learn in the right kind of math,
that led to, of course, progress on the science side,
but it led to all the engineering that we see now.
It wasn't sufficient.
We needed, of course, lots of innovations and advances
in computing, hardware, and software systems.
But this is where the basic math came from
and it came from doing science like an engineer.
What we want to talk about in our vision is what does the future of this look like?
If we were to look 50 years into the future,
what would we be looking back on now over this time scale?
Well, here's a long-term research roadmap that reflects some of my ambitions
and some of our center's goals and many others, too.
We'd like to be able to address basic questions, fundamental questions
of what it is to be and to think like a human,
questions, for example, of consciousness or meaning in language or real learning,
questions like, you know, even beyond the individual, like questions of culture
or creativity.
Those are our big ideas up there.
And for each of these, there are basic scientific questions, right?
How do we become aware of the world and ourselves in it?
It starts with perception, but it really turns into awareness,
awareness of yourself and of the world and what we might call consciousness, right?
Or how does a word start to have a meaning?
What really is a meaning and how does a child grasp it?
Or how do children actually learn?
What do babies' brains actually start with?
Are they blank slates or do they start with some kind of cognitive structure?
And then what does real learning look like?
These are just some of the questions that we're interested in working on.
Or when we talk about culture, we mean,
how do you learn all the things you didn't directly experience, right?
But that's somehow you got from the accumulation of knowledge in society over many generations.
Or how do you ever think of new ideas or answers to new questions?
How do you think of the new questions themselves?
How do you decide what to think about?
These are all key activities of human intelligence
when we talk about how we model the world, where our models come from,
what we do with our models, this is what we're talking about.
And if we could get machines that could do these things,
well, again, on the bottom row, think of all the actual real engineering payoffs.
Now, in our center, in both my own activities and a lot of what my group does these days
and what a number of other colleagues in the center for brains, minds, and machines do,
as well as very broadly people in BCS and CSAIL,
one place where we work on the beginnings of these problems in the near term.
This is the long term, like, think 50 years, okay?
Maybe shorter, maybe longer, I don't know, but think well beyond 10 years, okay?
But in the short term, 5 to 10 years, a lot of our focus is around visual intelligence.
And there's many reasons for that.
Again, we can build on the successes of deep networks
and a lot of pattern recognition and machine vision.
It's a good way to put these ideas into practice.
When we look at the actual brain, the visual system in the brain,
in the human and other mammalian brains, for example,
is really very clearly the best understood part of the brain.
And at a circuit level, it's the part of the brain that's most inspired current deep learning
and neural network systems.
But even there, there's things which we still don't really understand like engineers.
So here's an example of a basic problem in visual intelligence
that we and others in the center are trying to solve.
Look around you and you feel like there's a whole world around you.
And there is a whole world around you.
You feel like your brain captures it.
But what the actual sense data that's coming in through your eyes
looks more like this photograph here where you can see there's a crowd scene
but it's mostly blurry except for a small region of high resolution in the center.
So that corresponds biologically to what part of the image is in your fovea.
That's the central region of cells in the retina
where you have really high resolution visual data.
The size of your fovea is roughly like if you hold out your thumb at arm's length.
It's a little bit bigger than that but not much bigger, right?
Most of the image, in terms of the actual information coming in
in a bottom-up sense to your brain is really quite blurry.
But somehow by looking at just one part and then by saccading around
or making a few eye movements, you get a few glimpses,
each not much bigger than the size of your thumb at arm's length.
Somehow you stitch that information together into what feels like
and really is a rich representation of the whole world around you.
And when I say around you, I mean literally around you.
So here's another kind of demonstration.
Without turning around, nobody's allowed to turn around.
Ask yourself what's behind you.
Now the answer is going to be different for different people
depending on where you're sitting, right?
For most of you, you might think, well, I think there's a person
pretty close behind me, right?
You know you're in a crowded auditorium, although you haven't seen that person.
You know that they're there, right?
For people in the very back row, you know there isn't a person behind you
and you're conscious of being in the back row, right?
You might be conscious that there's a wall right behind you.
But now for the people who are in the room, not in the very back,
think about how far behind you is the back,
like where's the nearest wall behind you?
Maybe we can call out, try a little demonstration.
So I don't know. I'm pointing to someone there.
Can you say something if you think I'm pointing at you?
Well, I could have been pointing at you,
but I'm pointing someone behind you, okay?
I'll point to you. Yeah, I'm pointing to you.
All right, so how far is the nearest wall...
No, you can't turn around. You've blown your chance.
Without turning around. Okay, so you were...
Okay, do you see I'm pointing to you there with the tie?
Okay, so without turning around, how far is the nearest wall behind you?
Sorry, how far?
Five meters. Okay, well, I mean, that might be about right.
Other people can turn around.
Now, how about you? How far is the nearest wall behind you?
Ten meters.
Ten meters, okay.
That might be right, yeah.
How about here? What do you think?
20, okay.
So yeah, since I didn't grow up in the metric system, I barely know.
But yeah, I mean...
The point is that like, you're...
Each of you is surely not exactly right,
but you're certainly within an order of magnitude,
and I guess if we actually tried to measure, you know, you're probably...
My guess is you're probably right within, you know, 50% or less,
often, you know, maybe just 20% error.
Okay, so how do you know this?
I mean, even if it's not... What did you say, 20 meters?
Even if it's not 20 meters, it's probably closer to 20 meters
than it is to 5 or 10 meters, and then it is to 50 meters.
So how did you know this? You haven't turned around in a while, right?
So how do you know if your brain is tracking the whole world around you, right?
And how many people are behind you?
Yeah, like a few hundred, right?
I mean, I don't know if it's 200 or 300 or...
But it's not a thousand.
I don't think so.
And it's certainly not 10 or 20 or 50, right?
So you track these things, and you use them to plan your actions.
Okay, so again, think about how instantly, effortlessly,
and very reliably, okay?
Your brain computes all these things.
There's a lot of people and objects around you,
and it's not just approximations.
Certainly, when we're talking about what's behind you in space,
there's a lot of imprecision.
But when it comes to reaching for things right in front of you,
very precise shape and physical property estimates
needed to pick up and manipulate objects.
And then when it comes to people, it's not just the existence of the people,
but something about what's in their head, right?
You track whether someone's paying attention to you
and you're talking to them, what they might want from you,
what they might be thinking about you,
what they might be thinking about other people, okay?
So when we talk about visual intelligence,
this is the whole stuff we're talking about.
And you can start to see how it turns into basic questions, I think,
of what we might call the beginnings of consciousness,
or at least our awareness of our self in the world,
and of ourselves as a self in the world,
but also other aspects of higher level intelligence and cognition
that are not just about perception, like symbols, right?
To describe even to ourselves what's around us and where we are
and what we can do with it.
We can go beyond just what we would normally call the stuff of perception
to say the thoughts in somebody's head and your own thoughts about that, okay?
So what we've been doing in CBMM
is trying to develop an architecture for visual intelligence.
And I'm not going to go into any of the details of how this works,
and this is just notional, this is just a picture,
it's like a sketch from a grand proposal of what we say we want to do.
But it's based on a lot of scientific understanding
of how the brain works.
There are different parts of the brain that correspond to these different modules
of architecture, as well as some kind of emerging engineering way
to try to capture at the software and maybe even hardware levels
how these modules might work.
So we talk about sort of an early module of visual or perceptual stream,
which is like bottom-up visual or other perceptual input.
That's the kind of thing that is pretty close to what we currently have
in say deep convolutional neural networks.
But then we talk about some kind of, the output of that isn't just pattern class labels,
but what we call the cognitive core or core cognition.
And an understanding of space and objects, their physics,
other people, their minds, that's the real stuff of cognition
that has to be the output of perception.
But somehow we have to have, this is what we call the brain OS in this picture,
we have to get there by stitching together the bottom-up inputs
from a glimpse here, a glimpse here, a little bit here and there,
and accessing prior knowledge that comes from our memory systems
to tell us how to stitch these things together
into the really core cognitive representations of what's out there in the world.
And then if we're going to start to talk about it in language
or to build plans on top of what we have seen and understood,
that's where we talk about symbols coming into the picture.
The building blocks of language and plans and so on.
So now we might say, well, okay, this is an architecture
that is brain-inspired and cognitively inspired
and we're planning to turn into real engineering.
And you can say, well, do we need that?
Again, I know this is a question you considered in the first lecture.
Maybe the engineering toolkit that's currently been making a lot of progress
in, let's say, industry, maybe that's good enough.
Maybe, you know, let's take deep learning
but to stand for a broader set of modern pattern recognition-based
and reinforcement learning-based tools
and say, okay, well, maybe that can scale up to this.
And you might, you know, maybe that's possible.
I'm happy in the question period if people want to debate this.
My sense is, no.
I think that it's not, when I say no,
I don't mean like it can't happen or it won't happen.
What I mean is the highest value, the highest expected route right now
is to take this more science-based reverse engineering approach.
And that at least if you follow the current trajectory
that industry incentives especially optimize for,
it's not even really trying to take us to these things.
So think about, for example, a case study of visual intelligence
that is in some ways, as pattern recognition, very much of a success.
It's again been mostly driven by industry.
It's something that if you read in the news
or even play around with in certain publicly available data sets
feels like we've made great progress.
And this is an aspect of visual intelligence
which is sometimes called image captioning.
It's mapping images to text.
You know, basically there's been a bunch of systems.
Here's a couple of press releases.
I guess this one's about Google.
Google's AI can now capture images almost as well as humans.
Here's one's about Microsoft.
A couple of years ago, I think there were something like
eight papers all released on to archive around the same time
from basically all the major industry computer vision groups
as well as a couple of academic partners, okay,
which all driven by basically the same data set
produced by some Microsoft researchers and other collaborators,
trained a combination of deep convolutional neural networks,
you know, state-of-the-art visual pattern recognition
with recurrent neural networks which had recently been developed
for, you know, basically kinds of neural statistical language modeling,
glued them together and produced a system
which made very impressive results in a big training set
and a held out test set where the goal was to take an image
and write a sentence like a short sentence caption
that would seem like the kind of way a human would describe that image.
And these systems, you know, surpassed human level accuracy
on the held out test set from a big training set.
But what you can see when you really dig into these things
is there's often a lot of what I would call data set overfitting.
It's not overfitting to the training set,
but it's overfitting to whatever are the particular characteristics
of this data set, you know, wherever it came from,
certain set of photographs and certain ways of captioning them, okay,
which even a big data set, it's not about quantity,
it's more about the quality, the nature of what people are doing, all right.
So one way to test this system is to apply it
to what seems like basically the same problem
but not within a certain curated or built data set.
And there's a convenient Twitter bot that lets you do this.
So there's something called the PIC desk bot,
which takes one of the state of the art industry AI captioning systems,
a very good one. Again, this is not meant to,
I'm not trying to critique these systems for what they're trying to do,
I'm just trying to point out what they don't really even try to do.
So this takes the Microsoft caption bot
and just every couple of hours takes a random image from the web,
captions it and uploads the results to Twitter.
And a couple of months ago when I prepared the first version of this talk,
I just took a few days in the life of this Twitter bot.
I didn't take every single image, but I took, you know,
most of the images in a way that was meant to be representative of the successes
and the kinds of failures that such a system will make.
So we can go through this and it's a little bit entertaining
and I think quite informative.
So here's just a somewhat random sample of a few days in the life
of one of these caption bots.
So here we have a picture of a person holding,
fortunately my screen is very small here and I can't read up there,
so maybe you'll have to tell me what it is.
But a person holding a cell phone, I guess I'll just read along with you.
So you have a person holding a cell phone.
Well, it's not a person holding a cell phone, but it's kind of close.
It's a person holding some kind of machine.
I don't even know what that is, but it's some kind of musical instrument, right?
So that's a mixed success or failure.
Here's a pretty good one, a group of people on a field playing football.
I would call that an A result, maybe even A plus.
Here's a group of people standing on top of a mountain.
So less good, there's a mountain, but as far as I can tell there's no people.
But these systems like to see people because of both the combination,
because in the data set they were trained on there's a lot of people
and people often talk about people.
And the fact that you can appreciate both what I said and why it's funny,
there you did some of my cognitive activities that this system is not even trying to do.
Here we've got a building with a cake.
I'll go through these fast.
Building with a cake, a large stone building with a clock tower.
I think that's pretty good.
I'd give that like a B plus.
There's no clock, but it's plausibly right.
There might be a clock in there.
There's definitely something like that.
Here's a truck parked on the side of a building.
I don't know, maybe a B minus.
There is a car on the side of a building, but it's not a truck
and it doesn't seem like the main thing in the image.
Here's a necklace made of bananas.
Here's a large ship in the water.
This is pretty good.
I give this like an A minus or B plus because there is a ship in the water,
but it's not very large.
It's really more of like a tugboat or something.
Here's a sign sitting on the grass.
You know, in some sense, that's great.
No, but in another sense, it's really missing what's actually
interesting and important and meaningful to humans.
Here's a garden is in the dirt.
A pizza sitting on top of a building.
A small house with a red brick building.
That's pretty good, although a kind of weird way of saying it.
A vintage photo of a pond.
That's good.
They like vintage photos.
A group of people that are standing in the grass near a bridge.
Again, there's two people and there's some grass and there's a bridge,
but it's really not what's going on.
A person in a yard, kind of.
A group of people standing on top of a boat.
There's a boat.
There's a group of people.
They're standing.
But again, the sentence that you see is more based on a bias of what people
have said in the past about images that are only vaguely like this.
A clock tower is a little bit night.
That's really, I think, pretty impressive.
A large clock mounted to the side of a building.
A little bit less so.
A snow-covered feel, very good.
A building with snow on the ground.
A little bit less good.
There's no snow.
It's white.
Some people who I don't know them, but I bet that's probably right
because identifying faces and recognizing people who are famous
because they won medals in the Olympics,
probably I would trust current pattern recognition systems to get that.
A painting of a vase in front of a mirror.
Less good.
Also a famous person there, but we didn't get him.
A person walking in the rain.
Again, there is sort of a person and there's some puddles.
A group of stuffed animals.
A car parked in a parking lot.
That's good.
A car parked in front of a building.
Less good.
A plate with a fork and knife.
A clear blue sky.
Okay.
So you get the idea.
Again, if you actually go and play with this system,
partly because I think my friends at Microsoft told me they've improved it some.
This is partly for entertainment values.
I chose what also would be the funnier examples.
So I want to be quite honest about this.
I'm not trying to take away what are impressive AI technologies,
but I think it's clear that there's a sense of understanding any one of these images,
that it's important to see that even when it seems to be correct,
if it can make the kind of errors that it makes,
that even when it seems to be correct,
it's probably not doing what you're doing
and it's probably not even trying to scale towards the dimensions of intelligence
that we think about when we're talking about human intelligence.
Another way to put this,
I want to show you a really insightful blog post from one of your other speakers.
So in a couple of days,
I'm not sure you're going to have Andre Carpathi,
who's one of the leading people in deep learning.
This is a really great blog post he wrote a couple of years ago,
when he was, I think, still at Stanford.
He got his PhD from Stanford.
He worked at Google a little bit on some early big neural net AI projects there.
He was at OpenAI.
He was one of the founders of OpenAI,
and recently he joined Tesla as their director of AI research.
But about five years ago,
he was looking at the state of computer vision from a human intelligence point of view
and lamenting how far away we were.
So this is the title of his blog post,
the state of computer vision and AI.
We are really, really far away.
And he took this image, which was a sort of a famous image in its own right.
It was a popular image of Obama back when he was president,
kind of playing around as he liked to do when he was on tour.
If you take a look at this, you can see,
you probably all can recognize the previous president of the United States,
but you can also get the sense of where he is and what's going on,
and you might see people smiling,
and you might get the sense that he's playing a joke on someone.
Can you see that?
So how do you know that he's playing a joke and what that joke is?
Well, as Andre goes on to talk about in his blog post,
if you think about all the things that you have to really deploy in your mind to understand that,
it's a huge list.
Of course, it starts with seeing people and objects and maybe doing some face recognition,
but you have to do things like, for example,
notice his foot on the scale and understand enough about how scales work,
that when a foot presses down, it exerts force,
that the scale is sensitive, doesn't just magically measure people's weight,
but it does that somehow through force.
You have to see who can see that he's doing that and who can't,
who cannot see that he's doing that, right,
in particular the person on the scale,
and why some people can see that he's doing that
and can see that some other people can't see it,
and that makes it funny to them.
And someday, we should have machines that can understand this,
but hopefully you can see why the kind of architecture that I'm talking about
would be the building blocks of the ingredients to be able to get them to do that.
Now, again, I prepared a version of this talk a few months ago
and I wrote to Andre and I said, I was going to use this
and I was curious if he had any reflections on this
and where he thought we were relative to five years ago,
because certainly a lot of progress has been made.
But he said, here's his email, I hope he doesn't mind me sharing it,
but I mean, again, he's a very honest person
and that's one of the many reasons why he's such an important person right now in AI.
He's both very technically strong and honest about what we can do what we can't do,
and as he says, what does he say?
It's nice to hear from you, it's fun you should bring this up.
I was also thinking about writing a return to this
and in short, basically I don't believe we've made very much progress, right?
He points out that in his long list of things that you need to understand the image,
we have made progress on some, the ability to, again,
detect people and do face recognition for well-known individuals, okay?
But that's kind of about it, all right?
And he wasn't particularly optimistic that the current route that's being pursued in industry
is anywhere close to solving or even really trying to solve these larger questions.
If we give this image to that caption bot,
what we see is, again, represents the same point.
Here's the caption bot, it says,
I think it's a group of people standing next to a man in a suit and tie, right?
So that's right, right?
As far as it goes, it just doesn't go far enough,
and the current ideas of build a data set,
train a deep learning algorithm on it, and then repeat,
aren't really even, I would venture, trying to get to what we're talking about.
Or here's another, I'll just give you one other example of a couple of photographs
from my recent vacation in a nice warm tropical locale,
which I think illustrate ways in which, again, the gap where we have machines
that can, say, beat the world's best at go,
but can't even beat a child at tic-tac-toe.
Now, what do I mean by that?
Well, of course, we don't even need reinforcement learning or deep learning
to build a machine that can win or tie, do optimally in tic-tac-toe.
But think about this, this is a real tic-tac-toe game,
which I saw on the grass outside my hotel, right?
What do you have to do to look at this and recognize that it's a tic-tac-toe game?
You have to see the objects, you have to see what's, you know, in some sense,
there's a three-by-three grid, but it's only abstract, right?
It's only delimited by these ropes or strings, okay?
It's not actually a grid in any simple geometric sense, all right?
But yet a child can look at that, and indeed, here's an actual child who was looking at it
and recognize, oh, it's a game of tic-tac-toe, and even know what they need to do to win,
namely put the X and complete it, and now they've got three in a row, right?
That's literally child's play, okay?
You show this sort of thing, though, to one of these, you know, image-understanding caption bots,
and I think it's a close-up of a sign, okay?
Again, saying that this is a close-up of a sign is not the same thing, I would venture,
as a cognitive or computational activity that's going to give us what we need to say,
recognize the objects, recognize it as a game to understand the goal
and how to plan to achieve those goals.
Whereas this kind of architecture is designed to try to do all of these things, ultimately, right?
And I bring in these examples of games or jokes to really show where perception goes to cognition,
you know, all the way up to symbols, right?
So to get objects and forces and mental states, that's the cognitive core,
but to be able to get goals and plans and what do I do or how do I talk about it, that symbols, okay?
Here's another way into this, and it's one that also motivates, I think, a lot of really good work on the engineering side
and a lot of our interest in the science side is think about robotics
and think about what do you have to do to, you know, what does the brain have to be like to control the body?
So again, you're going to hear from, shortly, I think maybe it's next week, from Mark Rayburt,
who's one of the founders of Boston Dynamics, which is one of my favorite companies anywhere.
They're, without doubt, the leading maker of humanoid robots, legged, locomoting robots in industry.
They have all sorts of other really cool robots, robots like dogs, robots that have all, you know,
I think you'll even get to see a live demonstration of one of these robots.
It's really awesome, impressive stuff, okay?
But what about the minds and brains of these robots?
Well, again, if you ask Mark, ask them how much of human-like cognition do they have in their robots,
and I think he would say very little.
In fact, we have asked him that, and he would say very little.
He has said very little.
He's actually one of the advisors of our center, and I think in many ways we're very much on the same page.
We both want to know how do you build the kind of intelligence that can control these bodies like the way a human does?
All right, here's another example of an industry robotics effort.
This is Google's arm farm, where, you know, they've got lots of robot arms,
and they're trying to train them to pick up objects using various kinds of deep learning and reinforcement learning techniques.
And I think it's one approach.
I just think it's very, very different from the way humans learn to, say, control their body and manipulate objects.
And you can see that in terms of things that go back to what you were saying when you were introducing me, right?
Think about how quickly we learn things, right?
Here you have these, the arm farm is trying to generate, you know, effectively, maybe if not infinite,
but hundreds of thousands, millions of examples of reaches and pickups of objects, even with just a single gripper.
And yet a child who in some ways can't control their body nearly as well as robots can be controlled at the low level
is able to do so much more.
So I'll show you two of my favorite videos from YouTube here, which motivate some of the research that we're doing.
The one on the left is a one-and-a-half-year-old and the other one's a one-year-old.
So just watch this one-and-a-half-year-old here doing a popular activity for many kids.
Is it playing?
Hmm.
You see video up there?
Okay, there we go.
Okay, so he's doing this stacking cup activity.
All right, he's stacking up cups to make a tall tower.
He's got a stack of three.
And what you can see for the first part of this video is it looks like he's trying to make a second stack
that he's trying to pick up at once.
Basically, he's trying to make a stack of two that'll go on the stack of three.
And, you know, he's trying to debug his plan because it got a little bit stuck here.
But, and think about, I mean, again, if you know anything about robots manipulating objects,
even just what he just did, no robot can decide to do that and actually do it, right?
At some point, he's almost got it.
It's a little bit tricky, but at some point he's going to get that stack of two.
He realizes he has to move that object out of the way.
Look at what he just did.
Move it out of the way, use two hands to pick it up.
And now he's got a stack of two on a stack of three, and suddenly, you know, sub-goal completed.
He's now got a stack of five.
And he gives himself a hand because he knows he accomplished a key waypoint along the way to his final goal.
That's a kind of early symbolic cognition, right?
To understand that I'm trying to build a tall tower, but a tower is made up of little towers.
And you can take a tower and put it on top of another tower or stack a stack on a stack,
and you have a bigger stack, right?
So think about how he goes from bottom-up perception to the objects that the physics needed
to manipulate the objects to the ability to make even those early kinds of symbolic plans.
At some point, he keeps doing this.
He puts another stack on there.
I'll just jump to the end.
Oops, sorry.
You missed.
Sorry.
He gets really excited and he gives himself another big hand, but falls over.
Okay.
Again, Boston Dynamics now has robots that could pick themselves up after that.
That's really impressive, again.
But all the other stuff to get to that point, we don't really know how to do in a robotic setting.
Or think about this baby here.
This is a younger baby.
This is one of the Internet's very most popular videos because it features a baby and a cat.
But the baby's doing something interesting.
He's got the same cups, but he's decided, again, decided to try a new thing.
So think about creativity.
He's decided that his goal is to stack up cups on the back of a cat, I guess.
He's asking, how many cups can I fit on the back of a cat?
Well, three.
Let's see, can I fit more?
Let's try another one.
Okay.
Well, he can't fit more than three.
It turns out.
And then he, then it's not working.
So he changes his goal.
Now his goal appears to be to get the cups on the other side of the cat.
Now watch that part when he reaches back behind him there.
I'll just pause it there for a moment.
So when he just reached back there, that's a particularly striking moment in the video.
It shows a very strong form of what we call in cognitive science, object permanence.
Okay.
That's the idea that you represent objects as these permanent, enduring entities in the
world, even when you can't see them.
In this case, he hadn't seen or touched that object behind him for like at least a minute,
right?
Maybe much longer, I don't know.
And yet he still knew it was there and he was able to incorporate it in his plan, right?
There's a moment before that when he's about to reach for it, but then he sees this other
one, right?
And it's only when he's now exhausted all the other objects here that he can see.
He's like, okay, now time to get this object and bring it into play, right?
So think about what has to be going on in his brain for him to be able to do that, right?
That's like the analog of you understanding what's behind you, okay?
It's not that these things are impossible to capture machines far from it.
It's just that like training a deep neural network or any kind of pattern recognition
system we don't think is going to do it.
But we think by reverse engineering how it works in the brain, we might be able to do
it.
I think we can do it, okay?
It's not just humans that do this kind of activity.
Here's a couple of, again, rather famous videos.
You can watch all of these on YouTube.
Crows are famous object manipulators and tool users, but also orangutans, other primates,
rodents.
We can watch, if we just, here, let me pause this one for a second.
If we watch this orangutan here, he's got a bunch of big Legos.
And over the course of this video, he's building up a stack of Legos.
It's really quite impressive.
He's just jumping to the end.
There's actually some controversy out there of whether this video is a fake.
But the controversy isn't about, you know, it's not like whether it was, I don't know,
done with computer animation.
Some people think the video was actually filmed backwards, that a human built up the stack
and the orangutan just slowly disassembled it piece by piece.
And it turns out it's remarkably hard to tell whether it's played forward or backwards in
time.
And people have argued over little details because, you know, it would be quite impressive
if an orangutan actually was able to build up this really impressive stack of Legos.
And I would submit that it would be almost as impressive if he disassembled it.
Think about the activity.
I mean, if I wanted to disassemble that, the easiest thing to do would just be to knock it over.
That's really all most robots could do.
But to piece by piece disassemble it, even if it's played backwards like this,
that's still a really impressive act of symbolic planning on physical objects.
Or here you've got this famous mouse, this you can find on the internet under the
Mouse vs. Cracker video.
And what you'll see here over the course of this video is a mouse valiantly and mostly
hopelessly struggling with a cracker that they're hoping to bring back to their nest.
I guess it's a very appealing big meal.
And at some point after just trying to get it over the wall, at some point the mouse
just gives up because it's just never going to happen.
And he just goes away.
Except that because even mouses can dream or mice can dream, at some point he decides,
he's not going to come back for one more try.
And he tries one more time and this time valiantly gets it over.
Isn't that very impressive?
Congratulations.
You don't have to clap.
You can clap for me at the end or clap for whoever later.
But I want to applaud the mouse there every time I see that.
But again, think what had to be going on in his brain to be able to do that.
It's a crazy thing.
And yet he formulated the goal and was able to achieve it.
I'll just show one more video that is really more about science.
These other ones are, you know, some of them actually were from scientific experiments.
But this is one that motivates a lot of the science that I do.
And to me it sets up kind of a grand cognitive science challenge for AI and robotics.
It's from an experiment with humans, again 18-month-olds or one and a half-year-olds.
So the kids in this experiment were the same age as the first baby I showed you,
the one who did the stacking.
And 18 months is really a very, very good age to study if you're interested in intelligence
for reasons we can talk about later if you're interested.
This is from a very famous experiment done by two psychologists,
Felix Wernicke and Michael Tomasello.
And it was studying the spontaneous helping behavior of young children.
It also contrasted humans and chimps.
And the punchline is that chimps sometimes do things that are kind of like what this human did,
but not nearly as reliably or as flexibly.
Okay, so not nearly in his, and I'll show you a particular kind of unusual situation
where human kids had relatively little trouble figuring out kind of what to do
or even whether they should do it.
Whereas basically no chimp did what you're going to see humans sometimes doing here.
So the experimenter in this movie, and I'll turn on the sound here if you can hear it.
The experimenter is the tall guy and the participant is the little kid in the corner.
There's sound but no words, right?
And at some point he stops and then the kid just does whatever they want to do.
So watch what he does.
He goes over, he opens the cabinet, looks inside, then he steps back
and he looks up at Felix and then looks down, okay, and then the action is completed.
Now, I want you to watch it one more time and think about what's got to be going inside the kid's head
to understand this, to understand, like, so it seems like what it looks like to us
is the kid figured out that this guy needed help and helped him.
And the paper is full of many other situations like this.
This is just one, okay?
But the key idea is that the situation is somewhat novel.
People have seen people holding books and opening cabinets,
but probably it's very rare to see this kind of situation exactly, right?
It's different in some important details from what you might have seen before.
And there's other ones in there that are really truly novel
because they just made up a machine right there, okay?
But somehow he has to understand causally from the way the guy is banging the books against the thing.
It's sort of both a symbol, but it's also somehow he's got to understand
what he can do and what he can't do and then what the kid can do to help.
And I'll show this again, but really just watch,
the main part I want you to see is, I'll just sort of skip ahead.
So watch this part here.
Let's say I'll just jump right when he, watch, right now he's about to look up.
He looks up and makes eye contact and then his eyes look down.
So again, he looks up, he looks up and then a saccade,
a sudden rapid eye movement down, down to his hands, up, down, okay?
So that's, again, that's this brain OS in action, right?
He's making one glance, small glance, at the big guy's eyes to make eye contact,
to see, to get a signal, did I understand what you wanted
and did you register that joint attention?
And then he makes a prediction about what the guy's going to do,
so he looks right down, he doesn't just like look around randomly,
he looks right down to the guy's hands to track the action that he expects to see happening
if I did the right thing to help you, then I expect you're going to put the books there, okay?
So you can see these things happening and we want to know what's going on inside the mind
that guides all of that, all right?
So that's this sort of big scientific agenda that we're working on over the next few years
where we think some kind of human, understanding of human intelligence and scientific terms
could lead to all sorts of AI payoffs.
In particular, suppose we could build a robot that could do what this kid
and many other kids in these experiments do to say help you out around the house
without having to be programmed or even really instructed just to kind of get a sense,
oh yeah, you need to hand with that, sure, let me help you out, okay?
Even 18-month-olds will do that, sometimes not very reliably or effectively,
sometimes they'll try to help and really do the opposite, right?
But imagine if you could take the flexible understanding of humans, actions, goals and so on
and make those reliable engineering technology, that would be very useful.
And it would also be related to, say, machines that you could actually start to talk to
and trust in some ways, right, that shared understanding.
So how are we going to do this?
Well, let me spend the rest of the time talking about how we try to do this, right?
Some of the technology that we're building both in our group and more broadly
to try to make these kinds of architectures real.
And I'll talk about two or three technical ideas, again, not in any detail, all right?
One is the idea of a probabilistic program.
So this is a kind of, think of it as a computational abstraction
that we can use to capture the common sense knowledge of this core cognition.
So when I say we have an intuitive understanding of physical objects and people's goals,
how do I build a model of that model you have in the head?
Probabilistic programs, a little bit more technically,
one way to understand them is as a generalization of Bayesian networks
or other kinds of directed graphical models, if you know those, okay?
But where instead of defining a probability model on a graph,
you define it on a program,
and thereby have access to a much more expressive toolkit of knowledge representation.
So data structures, other kinds of algorithmic tools for representing knowledge, okay?
But you still have access to the ability to do probabilistic inference,
like in a graphical model, but also causal inference in a directed graphical model.
So for those of you who know about graphical models, that might make some sense to you.
But just more broadly, what this is, think of this as a toolkit
that allows us to combine several of the best ideas,
not just of the recent deep learning era,
but if you look back over the whole scope of AI and as well as cognitive science,
I think there's three or four ideas and more,
but definitely like three ideas we can really put up there
that have proven their worth and have risen and fallen in terms of,
each of these had ideas when the mainstream of the field thought,
this was totally the way to go and every other idea was obviously a waste of time,
and also had its time when many people thought it was a waste of time, okay?
And these three big ideas, I would say, are first of all the idea of symbolic representation,
or symbolic languages for knowledge representation,
probabilistic inference in generative models to capture uncertainty, ambiguity,
learning from sparse data, and in their hierarchical setting, learning to learn, right?
And then, of course, the recent developments with neural-inspired architectures for pattern recognition, okay?
Each of these things, each of these ideas, symbolic languages, probabilistic inference,
and neural networks have some distinctive strengths that are real weak points of the other approaches, right?
So to take one example that I haven't really talked about here,
people in the, but you mentioned as an outstanding challenge for neural networks,
transfer learning, or learning to take knowledge across a number of previous tasks to transfer to others,
is a real challenge and has always been a challenge in a neural net, okay?
But it's something that's addressed very naturally and very scalably in, for example, a hierarchical Bayesian model.
And if you look at some of the recent attempts, really interesting attempts within the deep learning world
to try to get kinds of transfer learning and learning to learn, they're really cool, okay?
But many of them are in some ways kind of reinventing within a neural network paradigm
ideas that people, you know, maybe just 10 or 15 years ago developed in very sophisticated ways
in, let's say, hierarchical Bayesian models, okay?
And a lot of attempts to get sort of symbolic algorithm-like behavior in neural networks, again,
are really, you know, they're very small steps towards something which is a very mature technology
in computer systems and programming languages.
Probabilistic programs, I'll just sort of advertise mostly,
are a way to combine the strengths of all of these approaches,
to have knowledge representations which are as expressive as anything that anybody ever did in the symbolic paradigm,
that are as flexible at dealing with uncertainty and sparse data as anything in the probabilistic paradigm,
but that also can support pattern recognition tools to be able to, for example,
do very fast efficient inference in very complex scenarios.
And there's a number of, that's the kind of conceptual framework.
There's a number of actually implemented tools.
I point to here on the slide a number of probabilistic programming languages which you can go explore.
For example, there's one that was developed in our group a few years ago,
almost 10 years ago, now called Church, which was the antecedent of some of these other languages
built on a functional programming core.
So Church is a probabilistic programming language built on the Lambda Calculus,
or really in LISP, basically.
But there are many other more modern tools, especially if you are interested in neural networks.
There are tools like, for example, Pyro, or ProbTorch, or BayesFlow,
that try to combine all these ideas in a, or for example, Gen here,
which is a project of Vakash Mansingh's probabilistic computing group.
These are all things which are just in the very beginning stages, very, very alpha.
But you can find out more about them online or by writing to their creators.
And I think this is a very exciting place where the convergence of a number of different AI tools are happening.
And this will be absolutely necessary for making the kind of architecture that I'm talking about work.
Another key idea, which we've been building on in our lab,
and I think, again, many people are using some version of this idea,
but maybe a little bit different from the way we're doing it,
is what the version of this idea that I like to talk about is what I call the game engine in the head.
So this is the idea that it's really what the programs are about.
When I talk about probabilistic programs, I haven't said anything about what kind of programs we're using.
We're just basically, these probabilistic programming languages at their best,
and church, the language that was developed by Noah Goodman and Vakash and others,
and Dan Roy and our group some 10 years ago,
was intended to be a turing complete probabilistic programming language.
So any probability model that was computable, or for whose conditional inferences are computable,
you could represent in these languages.
But that leaves completely open what kind of program I'm going to write to model the world.
And I've been very inspired in the last few years by thinking about the kinds of programs that are in modern video game engines.
So again, probably most of you are familiar with these,
and increasingly they're playing a role in all sorts of ways in AI,
but these are tools that were developed by the video game industry to allow a game designer to make a new game
without having to do most of, in some sense, many, most of the hard technical work from scratch,
but rather to focus on the characters, the world, the story,
the things that are more interesting for designing a novel game.
In particular, if we want a player to explore some new three-dimensional world,
but to have them be able to interact with the world in real time
and to render nice-looking graphics in real time in an interactive way as the player moves around and explores the world,
or if you want to populate the world with non-player characters that will behave in an even vaguely intelligent way.
Game engines give you tools for doing all of this without having to write all of graphics from scratch
or all of physics, the rules of physics from scratch,
so what are called game physics engines, and in some sense are a set of principles,
but also hacks from Newtonian mechanics and other areas of physics
that allow you to simulate plausible-looking physical interactions in very complex world,
very approximately, but very fast.
There's also what's called game AI, which are basically very simple planning models.
So let's say I want to have an AI in the game that is like a guard that guards a base and a player is going to attack the space.
So back in the old Atari days, like when I was a kid,
the guards would just be random things that would fire missiles kind of randomly in random directions at random times,
but let's say you want a guard to be a little intelligent,
so to actually look around and, oh, and I see the player, and then to actually start shooting at you and to even maybe pursue you.
So that requires putting a little AI in the game,
and you do that by having basically simple agent models in the game.
So what we think, and some of you might think this is crazy and some of you might think this is a very natural idea,
I get both kinds of reactions.
What we think is that these tools of fast-approximate renderers, physics engines,
and sort of very simple kinds of AI planning are an interesting first approximation
to the kinds of common-sense knowledge representations that evolution has built into our brains.
So when we talk about the cognitive core or how do babies start,
ways in which a baby's brain isn't a blank slate,
one interesting idea is that it starts with something like these tools
and then wrapped inside a framework for probabilistic inference,
that's what we mean by probabilistic programs,
that can support many activities of common-sense perception and thinking.
So I'll just give you one example of what we call this intuitive physics engine.
So this is work that we did in our groups that Pete Battaglia and Jess Hamrick started this work about five years ago now,
where we showed people, in some sense,
and this is also an illustration of a kind of experiment that you might do,
when I keep talking about science, I'll show you now a couple of experiments.
So we would show people simple physical scenes like these blocks world scenes
and ask them to make a number of judgments.
And the model we built does basically a little bit of probabilistic inference
in a game-style physics engine, it perceives the physical state
and imagines a few different possible ways the world could go over the next one or two seconds
to answer questions like, will the stack of blocks fall?
Or if they fall, how far will they fall?
Or which way will they fall?
Or what would happen if, say, one color of blocks or one material, like the green stuff,
is ten times heavier than the gray stuff?
Or vice versa, how will that change the direction of fall?
Or look at those red and yellow blocks, some of which look like they should be falling but aren't.
So why?
Can you infer from the fact that they're not falling that one color block is much heavier than the other?
Or let me show you a sort of a slightly weird task.
It's like other behavioral experiments.
Sometimes we do weird things so that we can test ways in which you use your knowledge
that you didn't just learn from pattern recognition,
but use it to do new kinds of tasks that you'd never seen before.
So here's a task which many of you have maybe seen me talk about these things.
So you might have seen this task, but probably only if you saw me give a talk around here before.
We call this the red-yellow task, and again, we'll make this one interactive.
So imagine that the blocks on the table are knocked hard enough to bump,
the tables bumped hard enough to knock some of the blocks onto the floor.
So you tell me, is it more likely to be red blocks or yellow blocks?
What do you say?
Red.
Okay, good.
How about here?
Yellow.
Good.
How about here?
Uh-huh.
Here?
Okay.
So you just experience for yourself what it's like to be a subject in one of these experiments.
We just did the experiment here.
The data is all captured on video, sort of, right?
Okay.
You could see that sometimes people were very quick, other times people were slower.
Sometimes there was a lot of consensus, sometimes there was a little bit less consensus, right?
That reflects uncertainty.
So again, there's a long history of studying this scientifically.
That, you know, you could, but you can see some, you can see the probabilistic inference at work.
Probabilistic inference over what?
Well, I would say one way to describe it is over one or a few short low precision simulations of the physics of these scenes.
So here is what I mean by this.
I'm going to show you a video of a game engine reconstruction of one of these scenes that simulates a small bump.
So here's a small bump.
Here's the same scene with the big bump.
Okay.
Now notice that at the micro level, different things happen.
But at the cognitive or macro level that matters for common sense reasoning, the same thing happened.
Namely, all the yellow blocks went over onto one side of the table and few or none of the red blocks did.
So it didn't matter which of those simulations you ran in your head.
You'd get the same answer in this case, right?
This is one that's very easy and high confidence and quick.
Also, you didn't have to run the simulation for very long.
You only have to run it for a few time steps like that to see what's going to happen or similarly here.
You only have to run it for a few time steps, okay?
And it doesn't have to be even very accurate.
Even a fair amount of imprecision will give you basically the same answer at the level that matters for common sense.
So that's the kind of thing our model does.
It runs a few low precision simulations for a few time steps.
But if you take the average of what happens there and you compare that with people's judgments,
you get results like what I show you here.
This scatter plot shows on the y-axis the average judgments of people.
On the x-axis, the average judgments of this model.
And it does a pretty good job.
It's not perfect, but the model basically captures people's graded sense of what's going on in this scene and many of these others, okay?
And it doesn't do it with any learning, but I'll come back to that in a second.
It just does it by probabilistic reasoning over a game physics simulation.
Now we can use and we have used the same kind of technology to capture in very simple forms.
Really just proofs of concept at this point.
The kind of common sense physical scene understanding in a child playing with blocks or other objects.
Or in what might go on in a young child's understanding of other people's actions.
What we call the intuitive psychology engine.
Where now the probabilistic programs are defined over these kind of very simple planning and perception programs.
And I won't go into any details.
I'll just point to a couple of papers that my group played a very small role in.
But we provided some models, which together with some infant researchers,
people working on both of these are experiments that were done with 10 or 12 month infants.
So younger than even some of the babies I showed you before.
But basically like that youngest baby, the one with the cat.
Here's an example of showing simple physical scenes.
These are moving objects to 12 month olds where they saw a few objects bouncing around inside a gumball machine.
And after some point in time, the scene gets occluded.
You'll see the scene is occluded.
And then after another period of time, one of the objects will appear at the bottom.
And the question is, is that the object you expected to see or not?
Is it expected or surprising?
The standard way you study what infants know is by what's called looking time methods.
Just like an adult.
If I show you something that's surprising, you might look longer.
If you're bored, you'll look away.
So you can do that same kind of thing with infants.
And by measuring how long they look at a scene,
you can measure whether you've shown them something surprising or not.
There are literally hundreds of studies, if not more,
using looking time measures to study what infants know.
But only with this paper that we published a few years ago,
did we have a quantitative model where we were able to show a relation
between inverse probability in this case and surprise.
So things which were objectively lower probability under one of these probabilistic physics simulations
across a number of different manipulations of how fast the objects were,
where they were, when the scene was occluded,
how long the delay was, various physically relevant variables,
how many objects there were of one type or another.
Infants' expectations connected with this model.
Or another paper that we published, that one was done,
the experiments there were done by Erno Teglas and Luca Benotti's lab.
Here is a study that was done just recently by Sherry Liu in Liz Spelke's lab
there at Harvard, but they're partners with us in CBMM,
which was about infants' understanding of goals.
So this is more like, again, understanding of agents and intuitive psychology,
where, again, in very simple cartoon scenes,
you show an infant an agent that seems to be doing something,
like an animated cartoon character.
But it jumps over a wall, or it rolls up a hill, or it jumps over a gap.
And the question is, basically, how much does the agent want the goal
that it seems to be trying to achieve?
And what this study showed, and the models here were done by Tomer Omen,
was that infants appeared to be sensitive to the physical work done by the agent.
The more work the agent did, in the sense of the integral of force applied over a path,
the more the infants thought the agent wanted the goal.
We think of this as representing what we've sometimes called the naive utility calculus.
So the idea that there's a basic calculus of cost and benefit,
you know, we take actions which are a little bit costly to achieve goal states
which give us some reward, that's the most basic way,
the oldest way to think about rational and intentional action.
And it seems that even 10-month-olds understand some version of that,
where the cost can be measured in physical terms.
I see I'm running a little bit behind on time,
and I wanted to leave some time for discussion.
So I'll just go very quickly through a couple of other things,
and happy to stay around at the end for discussion.
What I showed you here was the science, where does the engineering go?
So one thing you can do with this is say,
build a machine system that can look not a little animated cartoon
like these baby experiments, but a real person doing something,
and again, combine physical costs and constraints of actions
with some understanding of the agent's utilities,
that's the math of planning, to figure out what they wanted.
So look in this scene here, and see if you can judge which object
the woman is reaching for.
So you can see there's a grid of four by four objects,
there's 16 objects here, and she's going to be reaching for one of them.
It's going to play in slow motion,
but raise your hand when you know which one she's reaching for.
So just watch and raise your hand when you know which one she wants.
So most of the hands are up by now.
And notice, I was looking at your hands not here,
but what happened is most of the hands were up
at about the time when that gray, or the one that dashed line,
shot up.
That's not human data, you provided the data, this is our model.
So our model is predicting, more or less,
when you're able to say what her goal was.
It's well before she actually touched the object.
How does the model work?
Again, I'll skip the details, but it does the same kind of thing
that our models of those infants did.
Namely, but in this case, it does it with a full body model from robotics.
We use what's called the Mujoko physics engine,
which is a standard tool in robotics for planning
physically efficient reaches of, say, a humanoid robot.
And we say, we can give this planner program a goal object as input.
We can give it each of the possible goal objects as input
and say, plan the most physically efficient action,
so the one that uses the least energy to get to that object.
And then we can do a Bayesian inference.
This is the probabilistic inference part.
This program is the Mujoko planner.
But then we can say, I want to do Bayesian inference
to work backwards from what I observed,
which was the action, to the input to that program.
What goal was provided as input to the planner?
And here you can see the full array of four by four possible inputs
and those bars that are moving up and down,
that's the Bayesian posterior probability
of how likely each of those was to be the goal.
And what you can see is it converges on the right answer,
at least, well, it turns out to be the ground truth right answer,
but also the right answer according to what people think,
with about the same kind of data that people took.
Now, you might say, well, okay,
sure, if I just wanted to build a system
that could detect what somebody was reaching for,
I could generate a training data set of this sort of scene
and train something up to analyze patterns of motion.
But again, because the engine in your head
actually does something we think more like this,
it does what we call inverse planning over a physics model.
It can apply to much more interesting scenes
that you haven't really seen much of before.
So take the scene on the left, right,
where again, you see somebody reaching for one
of a four by four array of objects,
but what you see is a strange kind of reach.
Can you see why he's doing a strange reach?
Up there, it's a little small,
but you can see that he's reaching over something, right?
It's actually a pane of glass, right?
You see that?
And then there's this other guy who's helping him,
who sees what he wants and hands him the thing he wants.
So how does the guy on the foreground see the other guy's goal?
How does he infer his goal and know how to help him?
And then how do we look at the two of them
and figure out who's trying to help who?
Or that in a scene like this one here,
that it's not somebody trying to help somebody,
but rather the opposite, okay?
So here's a model on the left of how that might work, right?
And we think this is the kind of model
needed to tackle this sort of challenge here, right?
Basically, it's a model,
we take this model of planning,
sort of maximal expected utility planning,
which you can run backwards,
but then we recursively nest these models inside each other.
Okay?
An agent is helping another agent.
If this agent is acting apparently to us,
seems to be maximizing an expected utility,
that's a positive function of that agent's expectation
about another agent's expected utility,
and that's what it means to be a helper.
Hindering is sort of the opposite
if one seems to be trying to lower somebody else's utility, okay?
And we've used these same kind of models
to also describe infant's understanding
of helping and hindering in a range of scenes.
I'll just say one last word about learning
that everybody wants to know about learning,
and the key thing here,
and it's definitely part of any picture of AGI,
but the thought I want to leave you on
is really about what learning is about, okay?
It'll be just a few more slides, and then I'll stop, I promise.
None of the models I showed you so far
really did any learning.
They certainly didn't do any task-specific learning, okay?
We set up a probabilistic program, and then we let it do inference.
Now, that's not to say that we don't think
people learn to do these things, we do.
But the real learning goes on when you're much younger, right?
The other thing I showed you in basic form,
even a one-year-old baby can do, okay?
The basic learning goes on to support these kinds of abilities,
not that there isn't learning beyond one year,
but the basic way you learn to, say,
solve these physics problems is what goes on
in the brain of a child between zero and 12 months.
So this is just an example of some phenomena
that come from the literature on infant cognitive development.
These are very rough timelines.
You can take pictures of this if you like.
This is always a popular slide because it really is quite inspiring, I think,
and I can give you lots of literature pointers,
but I'm summarizing in very broad strokes with big error bars
what we've learned in the field of infant cognitive development
about when and how kids seem to at least come
to a certain understanding of basic aspects of physics.
So if you really want to study how people learn to be intelligent,
a lot of what you have to study are kids at this age.
You have to study what's already in their brain at zero months
and what they learn and how they learn
between four, six, eight, ten, twelve, and so on,
and all that beyond that, okay?
Now, effectively what that amounts to, we think,
is if what you're learning is something like, let's say,
an intuitive game physics engine to capture these basic abilities,
then what we need, if we're going to try to reverse engineer that,
is what we might think of as a program learning program.
If your knowledge is in the form of a program,
then you have to have programs that build other programs, right?
This is what I was talking about at the beginning,
about learning as building models of the world.
Or ultimately, if you think what we start off with
is something like a game engine that can play any game,
then what you have to learn is the program of the game
that you're actually playing,
or the many different games that you might be playing over your life.
So think of learning as programming the game engine in your head
to fit with your experience and to fit with the possible actions
that you seem like you can take.
Now, this is what you could call the hard problem of learning
if you come to learning from, say, neural networks
or other tools in machine learning, right?
So what makes most of machine learning go right now,
and certainly what makes neural networks so appealing,
is that you can set up basically a big function approximator
that can approximate many of the functions you might want to do
in a certain application or task,
but in a way that's end-to-end differentiable
and with a meaningful cost function.
So you can have one of these nice optimization landscapes.
You can compute the gradients and basically just roll downhill
until you get to an optimal solution.
But if you're talking about learning as something like search
in the space of programs,
we don't know how to do anything like that yet.
We don't know how to set this up as any kind of a nice optimization problem
with any notion of smoothness or gradients, okay?
Rather, what we need is instead of learning as, like,
rolling downhill effectively, right,
a process which just, if you're willing to wait long enough,
you know, some, you know, simple algorithm we'll take care of,
think of what we call the idea of learning as programming.
There's a popular metaphor in cognitive development
called the child as scientist,
which emphasizes children as active theory builders
and children's play as a kind of casual experimentation.
But this is the algorithmic complement to that,
what we call the child as coder,
or around MIT we'll say the child as hacker,
but the rest of the world, if you say child as hacker,
they think of someone who breaks into your email
and steals your credit card numbers,
we all know that hacking is, you know, making your code more awesome, right?
If your knowledge is some kind of code,
or, you know, library of programs,
then learning is all the ways that a child hacks on their code
to make it more awesome.
Awesome can mean more accurate,
but it can also mean faster, more elegant,
more transportable to other applications or their tasks,
more explainable to others, maybe just more entertaining, okay?
Children have all of those goals in learning,
and the activities by which they make their code more awesome
also correspond to many of the activities of coding, right?
So think about all the ways on a day-to-day basis
you might make your code more awesome, right?
You might have a big library of existing functions
with some parameters that you can tune on a data set.
That's basically what you do with backprop or stochastic gradient descent
in training a deep learning system.
But think about all the ways in which you might actually modify the underlying function.
So write new code, or take old code from some other thing
and map it over here, or make a whole new library of code,
or refactor your code to some other, you know,
some other basis for it that will work more robustly
and be more extensible, or transpiling, or compiling, right?
Or even just commenting your code,
or asking someone else for their code, okay?
Again, these are all ways that we make our code more awesome
and children's learning has analogues to all of these
that we would want to understand as an engineer
from an algorithmic point of view.
So in our group, we've been working on various early steps towards this.
And again, we don't have anything like program writing programs
at the level of children's learning algorithms.
But one example of something that we did in our group,
which you might not have thought of being about this,
but it's definitely the AI work we did
that got the most attention in the last couple of years from our group.
We had this paper that was in science,
it was actually on the cover of science,
sort of just hit the market at the right time, if you like,
and it got about 100 times more publicity
than anything else I've ever done,
which is partly a testament to the really great work
that Brendan Lake, who was the first author, did for his PhD here,
but much more so just about the hunger for AI systems at the time
when we published this in 2015.
And we built a machine system that, the way we described it,
was doing human-level concept learning for simple concepts,
very simple visual concepts.
These handwritten characters in many of the world's alphabets.
For those of you who know the famous MNIST dataset,
the dataset of handwritten digits 0 through 9,
sorry, that drove so much good research in deep learning
and pattern recognition,
it did that not because Jan Lacoon, who put that together,
or Jeff Hinton, who did a lot of work on deep learning with MNIST,
they were interested fundamentally in character recognition,
that they saw that as a very simple test bed
for developing more general ideas.
And similarly, we did this work on getting machines
to do a kind of one-shot learning of generative models,
also to develop more general ideas.
We saw this as learning very simple, little mini probabilistic programs.
In this case, what are those programs?
They're the programs you use to draw a character.
So ask yourself, how can you look at any one of these characters
and see, in a sense, how somebody might draw it?
The way we tested this in our system was this little visual-turing test
where we showed people one character in a novel alphabet
and we said, draw another one.
We paired nine people, like say on the left,
and nine samples from our machine, say on the right,
and we asked other people,
could you tell which was the human drawing another example,
or imagining another example, and which was the machine?
And people couldn't tell.
When I said ones on the left and ones on the right,
I don't actually remember,
and on different ones you can see if you can tell.
It's very hard to tell.
Can you tell for each one of these characters
which new set of examples were drawn by a human versus a machine?
Here's the right answer, and probably you couldn't tell.
The way we did this was by assembling a simple kind of program learning program.
So we basically said, when you draw a character,
you're assembling strokes and substrokes with goals and sub-goals
that produce ink on the page,
and when you see a character, you're working backwards to figure out
what was the program, the most efficient program that did that.
So you're basically inverting a probabilistic program,
doing Bayesian inference to the program,
most likely to have generated what you saw.
This is one small step, we think,
towards being able to learn programs,
to being able to learn something ultimately like a whole game engine program.
The last thing I'll leave you with is just a pointer to sort of work in action.
So this is some work being done by a current PhD student
who works partly with me,
but also with Armando, Solar Lasama, and CSAIL.
This is Kevin Ellis.
It's an example of what's now, I think, again,
an emerging, exciting area in AI
well beyond anything that we're doing,
is combining techniques from where Armando comes from,
which is the world of programming languages,
not machine learning or AI,
but tools from programming languages
which can be used to automatically synthesize code.
With the machine learning toolkit,
in this case a kind of Bayesian minimum description-length idea,
to be able to make, again,
what is really one small step towards machines that can learn programs
by basically trying to efficiently find the shortest, simplest program
which can capture some data set.
So we think by combining these kinds of tools,
in this case, let's say, from Bayesian inference over programs
with a number of tools that have been developed
in other areas of computer science
that don't look anything or haven't been considered
to be machine learning or AI, like programming languages.
It's one of the many ways that, going forward,
we're going to be able to build smarter, more human-like machines.
So just to end then, what I've tried to tell you here is talk,
first of all, identify the ways in which human intelligence
goes beyond pattern recognition
to really all these activities of modeling the world.
To give you a sense of some of the domains
where we can start to study this,
like common sense scene understanding, for example,
or something like one-shot learning, for example,
like what we were just doing there,
or learning as programming the engine in your head.
And to give you a sense of some of the technical tools,
probabilistic programs, program synthesis, game engines,
for example, as well as a little bit of deep learning,
that bringing together, we're starting to be able to make these things real.
Now, that's the science agenda and the reverse engineering agenda,
but think about, for those of you who are interested in technology,
what are the many big AI frontiers that this opens up?
So the one I'm most excited about is this idea
which I've highlighted here in our big research agenda.
This is the one I'm most excited about to work on
for the rest of my career, honestly.
But it's really what is the oldest and maybe the best dream
of AI researchers of how to build a human-like intelligence system,
a real AGI system.
It's the idea that Turing proposed when he proposed the Turing test,
and Minsky proposed this at different times in his life.
Or many people have proposed this, right?
Which is to build a system that grows into intelligence
the way a human does, that starts like a baby and learns like a child.
And I've tried to show you how we're starting to be able to understand those things.
What a baby's mind starts with, how children actually learn.
And looking forward, we might imagine
that someday we'll be able to build machines that can do this.
I think we can actually start working on this right now.
And that's something that we're doing in our group.
So if that kind of thing excites you, then I encourage you to work on it,
maybe even with us.
Or if any one of these other activities of human intelligence excite you,
I think taking the kind of science-based reverse engineering approach
that we're doing and then trying to put that into engineering practice,
this is not just a possible route,
but I think it's quite possibly the most valuable route
that you could work on right now to try to actually achieve
at least some kind of artificial general intelligence,
especially the kind of intelligence, AI system,
that's going to live in a human world and interact with humans.
There's many kinds of AI systems that could live in worlds of data
that none of us can understand or will ever live in ourselves.
But if you want to build machines that can live in our world
and interact with us the way we are used to interacting with other people,
then I think this is a route that you should consider.
Okay, thank you.
Hi there.
So, early in the talk you expressed some skepticism about whether or not
industry would get us to understanding human level intelligence.
It seems that there's a couple of trends that favour industry.
One is that industry is better than that academia at accumulating resources
and plowing them back into the topic.
And it seems at the moment we've got a bit of brain drain going on
from academia into industry, and that seems like an ongoing trend.
If you look at something like learning to fly or learning to fly into space,
then it looks like the story is one of industry kind of taking over the field
and going off on its own a little bit.
Academics still have a role, but industry kind of dominates,
so is industry going to overtake the field, do you think?
Well, that's a really good question,
and it's got several good questions packed into one there, right?
I didn't mean to say, this wasn't meant to say,
go academia, bad industry, right?
What I tried to say was the approaches that are currently getting
the most attention in industry, and they're really,
because they're really the most valuable ones right now for the short term,
you know, any industry is really focused on what it can do,
what are the value propositions on basically a two-year timescale at most?
I mean, if you ask, say, Google researchers to take the most prominent example,
that's pretty much what they'll all tell you, okay?
Maybe things that might pay off initially in two years,
but maybe take five years or more to really develop,
but if you can't show that it's going to do something practical for us
in two years in a way that matters for our bottom line,
then it's not really worth doing, okay?
So what I'm talking about is the technologies which right now
industry sees as meeting that specification,
and what I'm saying is right now, I think that's not where the root is
to something like human-like, but not the most valuable promising root
to human-like kinds of AI systems, all right?
But I hope that like in the case as you said, you know,
the basic research that we're doing now will be successful enough
that it will get the attention of industry when the time is right.
So, you know, I hope at some point, you know,
it won't, at least the engineering side will have to be done in industry,
not just in academia, but you're also pointing to issues of like brain drain
and other things like that, that I think these are real issues confronting our community.
I think everybody knows this, and I'm sure this will come up multiple times here,
which is, you know, I think we have to find ways to, even now,
to combine the best of the ideas, the energy, and the resources of academia and industry
if we want to keep doing basically something interesting, right?
If we just want to redefine AI to be, well, whatever people currently call AI
but scaled up, well, then fine, forget about it.
Or if we just want to say, let me and people like me do what we're doing
at what industry we consider a snail's pace on toy problems, okay, fine.
But if we want to, you know, if I want to take what I'm doing to the level
that will really be, you know, paying off the level that industry can appreciate
or just that really has technological impact on a broad scale, right?
Or I think if industry wants to take what it's doing and really build machines
that are actually intelligent, right, or machine learning that actually learns like a person,
then I think we need each other now and not just in some point in the future.
So this is a general challenge for MIT and for everywhere and for Google.
I mean, we just spent a few days talking to Google about exactly this issue.
In fact, this was a talk I prepared partly for that purpose.
So we wanted to raise those issues and it's just, I mean, really, I don't know what,
I mean, rather I can think of some solutions to that problem
of what you could call brain drain from the academic point of view
or what you could call just narrowing in into certain local minima in the industry point of view.
But they will require the leadership of both academic institutions like MIT
and companies like Google being creative about how they might work together
in ways that are a little bit outside of their comfort zone.
I hope that will start to happen, including at MIT and at many other universities
and at companies like Google and many others.
And I think we need it to happen for the health of all parties concerned.
Okay, thank you very much.
Thanks.
I'm curious about sort of the premise that you gave that one of the big gaps missing
at determining intelligence is the fact that we need to teach machines how to recognize models.
And I'm curious as to what you think sort of non-goal-oriented cognitive activity comes into play.
There are things like feelings and emotions and why you don't think
that might not necessarily be like the most important question.
The only reason emotions didn't appear on my slide is because there's a few reasons,
but the slide is only so big.
I wanted the font to be big, readable for such an important slide.
I have versions of my slide in which I do talk about that.
It's not that I think feelings or emotions aren't important.
I think they are important.
And I used to not have many insights about what to do about them,
but actually partly based on some of my colleagues here at MIT, BCS,
Laura Shultz and Rebecca Sacks, two of my cognitive colleagues who I work closely with,
they've been starting to do research on how people understand emotions,
both their own and others, and we've been starting to work with them on computational models.
So that's actually something I'm actively interested in and even working on.
But I would say, and again, for those of you who study emotion or know about this,
actually you're going to have Lisa coming in, right?
So she's going to basically say a version of the same thing, I think.
The deepest way to understand, she's one of the world's experts on this,
the deepest way to understand emotion is very much based on our mental models
of ourselves, of the situation we're in and of other people, right?
Think about, for example, all of the different, I mean, if you think about,
I mean, again, Lisa will talk all about this, but if you think about emotion,
it's just a very small set of what are sometimes called basic emotions,
like being happy or angry or sad or, you know, those are small number of them, right?
There's usually only a few, right?
You might not say, you might see that as somehow like very basic things
that are opposed to some kind of cognitive activity.
But think about all the different words we have for emotion, right?
For example, think about a famous cognitive emotion like regret.
What does it mean to feel regret or frustration, right?
To know both for yourself when you're not just feeling kind of down or negative,
but you're feeling regret.
That means something like I have to feel like there's a situation that came out
differently from how I hoped and I realized I could have done something differently, right?
So that means you have to be able to understand, you have to have a model.
You have to be able to do a kind of counterfactual reasoning and to think,
oh, if only I had acted a different way, then I can predict that the world would have
come out differently and that's the situation I wanted,
but instead it came out this other way, right?
Or think about frustration, again, that requires something like understanding,
okay, I've tried a bunch of times, I thought this would work,
but it doesn't seem to be working, maybe I'm ready to give up.
Those are all, those are very important human emotions.
We have to understand ourselves, we need that,
to understand other people, to understand communication,
but those are all filtered through the kinds of models of action
that I was, just the ones I was talking about here
with these say cost-benefit analyses of action.
So what I'm, so I'm just trying to say I think this is very basic stuff
that will be the basis for building, I think,
better engineering-style models of the full spectrum of human emotion
beyond just like, well, I'm feeling good or bad or scared, okay?
And I think when you see Lisa, she will, in her own way,
say something very similar.
Interesting, thanks.
Yeah.
Thanks, Josh, for your nice talk.
So all is about human cognition and try to build a model to mimic those cognition,
but you don't, how much could help you to understand
how the circuit implement those things?
I mean, like the circuit's in the brain.
Yeah, and what's the...
Is that what you work on by any chance?
Sorry, what?
Yeah, I know.
I'm kidding, yeah, yeah.
So in the center for brains, minds, and machines,
as well as in brain and cognitive science, yeah,
I have a number of colleagues who study the actual hardware basis
of this stuff in the brain, and that includes
like the large-scale architecture of the brain,
say like what Nancy Camuscher, Rebecca Sacks,
study with functional brain imaging, or the more detailed circuitry,
usually requires recording from, say, non-human brains, right,
at the level of individual neurons and connections between neurons.
All right, so I'm very interested in those things,
although it's not mostly what I work on, right?
But I would say, you know, again, like in many other areas of science,
certainly in neuroscience, the kind of work I'm talking about here
in a sort of classic reductionist program
sets the target for what we might look for.
Like if I just want to go...
I mean, I would...
What I would assert, right, in my working conjecture
is that if you do the kind of work that I'm talking about here,
it gives you the right targets
or gives you a candidate set of targets to look for,
what are the neural circuits computing, right?
Whereas if you just go in and just, say, start poking around in the brain
or have some idea that what you're going to try to do
is find the neural circuits which underlie behavior,
without a sense of the computations needed to produce those behaviors,
I think it's going to be very difficult to know what to look for
and to know when you've found even viable answers.
So I think that's the standard kind of reductionist program.
But it's not...
I also think it's not one that is divorced from the study of neural circuits.
It's also one, if you look at the broad picture of reverse engineering,
it's one where neural circuits and understanding the circuits in the brain
play an absolutely critical role, okay?
I would say when you look at the brain at the hardware level as an engineer,
I'm mostly looking at the software level, right?
But when you look at the hardware level, there are some remarkable properties.
One remarkable property, again, is how much parallelism there is
and in many ways how fast the computations are, okay?
Neurons are slow, but the computations of intelligence are very fast.
So how do we get elements that are, in some sense, quite slow in their time constant
to produce such intelligent behavior so quickly?
That's a great mystery and I think if we understood that,
we would have payoff for building all sorts of, you know,
basically application embedded circuits, okay?
But also, maybe most important is the power consumption
and again, many people have noted this, right?
If you look at the power consumption, the power that the brain consumes,
like, what did I eat today, okay?
Almost nothing.
My daughter, who's, again, she's doing an internship here,
literally yesterday, all she ate was a burrito.
And yet, she wrote 300 lines of code for her internship project
on a really cool computational linguistics project.
So somehow she turned a burrito into, you know, a model of child language acquisition, okay?
But how did she do that or how do any of us do this, right?
Where if you look at the power that we consume, when we simulate
even a very, very small chunk of cortex on our conventional hardware,
or we do any kind of machine learning thing,
we have systems which are very, very, very, very far from the power
of the human brain computationally,
but in terms of physical energy consumed,
way past what any individual brain is doing.
So how do we get circuitry of any sort, biological or just any physical circuits
to be as smart as we are with as little energy as we are?
This is a huge problem for basically every area of engineering, right?
If you want to have any kind of robot, the power consumption is a key bottleneck.
Same for self-driving cars.
If we want to build AI without contributing to global warming and climate change,
let alone use AI to solve climate change, we really need to address these issues,
and the brain is a huge guide there, right?
I think there are some people who are really starting to think about this.
How can we say, for example, build somehow brain-inspired computers
which are very, very low power but maybe only approximate?
So I'm thinking here of Joe Bates.
I don't know if you know Joe.
He's been around MIT and other places for quite a while.
Can I tell them about your company?
So Joe has a startup in Kendall Square called Singular Computing,
and they have some very interesting ideas including some actual implemented technology
for low power approximate computing in a sort of a brain-like way
that might lead to possibly even like the ability to build something, this is Joe's dream,
to build something that's about the size of this table but that has a billion cores,
a billion cores and runs on a reasonable kind of power consumption.
I would love to have such a machine.
If somebody wants to help Joe build it, I think he'd love to talk to you.
But it's one of a number of ideas.
I mean Google X, people are working on similar things.
Probably most of the major chip companies are also inspired by this idea.
And I think even if you didn't think you were interested in the brain,
if you want to build the kind of AI we're talking about
and run it on physical hardware of any sort
and understanding how the brain's circuits compute what they do,
what I'm talking about with as little power as they do,
I don't know any better place to look.
It seems like a lot of the improvements in AI have been driven by increasing
like computational power.
How far would you say...
I mean like GPUs or CPUs.
How far would you say we are from hardware that could run a general artificial intelligence?
Of the kind that I'm talking about.
Yeah I don't know, I'll start with a billion cores and then we'll see.
I mean I think we're...
I think there's no way to answer that question in a way that's software independent.
I don't know how to do that, right?
But I think that it's...
And I don't know, like when you say how far are we,
you mean how far am I with the resources I have right now?
How far am I if Google decides to put all of its resources at my disposal,
like they might if I were working at DeepMind?
I don't know the answer to that question.
But I think what we can say is this.
Individual neurons, I mean again this goes back to another reason to study neural circuits.
If you look at what we currently call neural networks in the AI side,
the model of a neuron is this very very simple thing, right?
Individual neurons are not only much more complex,
but have a lot more computational power.
It's not clear how they use it or whether they use it.
But I think it's just as likely that a neuron is something like a real you, right?
Is that a neuron is something like a computer.
Like one neuron in your brain is more like a CPU node, okay?
Maybe.
And thus the ten billion or trillion, you know,
the large number of neurons in your brain,
I think it's like ten billion cortical,
pyramidal neurons or something,
might be like ten billion cores, okay?
For example, that's at least as plausible I think to me as any other estimate.
So I think we're definitely on the underside with very big error bars.
So I completely agree that,
or if this is what you might be suggesting,
and going back to my answer to your question,
I don't think we're going to get to what I'm talking about,
anything like a real brain scale
without major innovations on the hardware side.
And you know, it's interesting that what drove those innovations
that support current AI was mostly not AI.
It was the video game industry.
When I point to the video game engine in your head,
that's a similar thing that was driven by the video game industry on the software side.
I think we should all play as many video games as we can
and contribute to the growth of the video game industry.
Because, no, because I mean, you can see this in very,
there are companies out there, for example,
there's a company called Improbable,
which is a London company,
London-based startup, a pretty sizable startup at this point,
which is building something that they call Spatial OS,
which it's not a hardware idea,
but it's a kind of software idea
for very, very big distributed computing environments
to run much, much more complex,
realistic simulations of the world
for much more interesting, immersive, permanent video games.
I think that's one thing that might, hopefully,
that will lead to more fun new kinds of games,
but that's one example of where we might look to that industry
to drive some of the, you know, just computer systems,
really hardware and software systems
that will take our game to the next level.
Josh, understanding on the algorithmic level or cognitive level
is just to understanding the meaning of learning
would be how to predict,
but on the circuit level it's different.
On the circuit level?
Well, of course it's different, right?
But already, I think you made a mistake there, honestly.
Like, you said the cognitive level is learning how to predict,
but I'm not sure what you mean by that.
There's many things you could mean,
and what our cognitive science is about
is learning which of those versions,
like, I don't think it's learning how to predict.
I think it's learning what you need to know to plan actions
and to, you know, all those things.
Like, it's not just about predicting.
Because there are things we can imagine
that make the world different.
So generalization, sorry, you're not predicting.
When your model could generalize.
But especially in the transfer learning that you are interested in.
A few hundred of neurons in prefrontal cortex
they could generalize a lot.
But not kind of a Bayesian model could do that.
You said, but a Bayesian model won't do that?
Or they don't do it the way a Bayesian model does?
For sure, because that's in the abstract level.
Well, I mean, how do you really know?
Like, and what does it mean to say that some neurons do it?
So maybe another way to put this is to say,
look, we have a certain math that we use
to capture these, you could call it abstract
or I call it software level abstractions.
I mean, all engineering is based on some kind of abstraction.
But you might have a circuit level abstraction,
a certain kind of hardware level
that you're interested in describing the brain at.
And I'm mostly working out or starting from
a more software level of abstraction.
They're all abstractions. We're not talking about molecules here.
We're talking about some abstract notion
of maybe a circuit or of a program.
Now, it's a really interesting question.
If I look at some circuits, how do I know
what program they're implementing?
If I look at the circuits in this machine,
could I tell what program they're implementing?
Well, maybe, but certainly it would be a lot easier
if I knew something about what programs they might be implementing
before I start to look at the circuitry.
If I just looked at the circuitry without
knowing what a program was or what programs
the thing might be doing or what kind of
programming components would be
mappable to circuits in different ways,
I don't even know how I'd begin to answer that question.
So I think we've made some progress
at understanding what neurons
are doing in certain low-level parts
of sensory system and certain parts
of the motor system, like primary motor cortex,
like basically the parts of the neurons
that are closest to the inputs and outputs of the brain,
where we don't...
Well, you could say we don't need
the kind of software abstractions
that I'm talking about or where
we sort of agree on what those things already are
so we can make enough progress
on knowing what to look for and how to know
when we found it.
But if you want to talk about flexible planning,
things that are more like cognition that
go on in prefrontal cortex,
at this point I don't think
that just by recording from those neurons
we're going to be able to answer those questions
in a meaningful engineering way.
A way that any engineer, software, hardware, whatever,
could really say, yeah, okay, I get it.
I get those insights in a way that I can engineer with.
And that's what my goal is.
So that's my goal to do at the software level,
the hardware level, or the entire systems level
connecting them.
And I think that we can do that
by taking what we're doing and bringing into contact
with people studying neural circuits.
But I don't think you can leave this level out
and just go straight to the neural circuits.
And I think the more progress we make,
the more we can help people who are
studying at the neural circuit level.
And they can help us address these other engineering questions
that we don't really have access to,
like the power issue or the speed issue.
Okay, thanks.
That was great.
Thank you.