The video you're watching now is in 360. Resolution is not great but we wanted to
try something different. So if you're on a desktop or laptop you can pan around
with your mouse or if you're on a phone or tablet you should be able to just
move your device to look around. Of course it's best viewed with a VR headset.
The video that follows is a guest lecture on machine learning that I gave an
MIT Sloan course on the business of artificial intelligence. The lecture is
non-technical and intended to build intuition about these ideas amongst the
business students in the audience. The room was a half circle so we thought why
not film the lecture in 360. We recorded a screencast of the slides and pasted it
into the video so that the slides are more crisp. Let me know what you think and
remember it's an experiment. So this course is talking about the broad context
the impact of artificial intelligence. The global. There's global which is the
global impact of artificial intelligence. There's the business which is when you
have to take these fun research ideas that I'll talk about today. A lot of them
are cool on toy examples. When you bring them to reality you face real challenges
which is what I would like to really highlight today. That's the business part.
When you want to make real impact. When you're going to make these technologies
a reality. So I'll talk about how amazing the technology is for a nerd like me but
also talk about how when you take that into the real world what are the
challenges you face. So machine learning which is the technology at the core of
artificial intelligence. We'll talk about the promise. The excitement that I feel
about it. The limitations. We'll bring it down a little bit. What are the real
capabilities of technology. Where for the first time really as a civilization
exploring the meaning of intelligence. It is if you pause for a second and just
think you know maybe you have many of you want to make money out of this
technology. Many of you want to save lives help people but also on the
philosophical level we get to explore what makes us human. So while I'll talk
about the low-level technologies also think about the incredible opportunity
here. We get to almost psychoanalyze ourselves by trying to build versions of
ourselves in the machine. All right so here's the open question. How powerful is
artificial intelligence. How powerful is machine learning that lies at the core
of artificial intelligence. Is it simply a helpful tool a special purpose tool to
help you solve simple problems. Which is what it currently is. Currently
machine learning artificial intelligence is a way if you can formally define the
problem. You can formally define the tools you're working with. You can formally
define the utility function where you want to achieve with those tools. As long
as you can define those things we can come up with algorithms that can solve
them. As long as you have the right kind of data which is what I'll talk about.
Data is key. And the question is into the future can we break past this very
narrow definition of what machine learning can give us which is solve
specific problems. To something bigger. To where we approach the general
intelligence that we exhibit as human beings. When we're born we know
nothing and we learn quickly. From very little data. The right answer is we
don't know. We don't know what are the limitations of the technology. What kind
of machine learning are there. There are several flavors. The first two is what's
really the first is what's achieved success today. Supervised learning. What
I'm showing here on the left of the slide is the teachers. Is the data that is
fed to the system. And on the right is the students which is the system itself
from machine learning. So there's supervised learning. Whenever everybody
talks about machine learning today. For the most part they're referring to
supervised learning. Which means every single piece of data that is used to
train the model is seen by human eyes. And those human eyes with an
accompanying brain label that data in a way that makes it useful to the machine.
This is critical. Because that's one. The blue box. The human. It's really
costly. So whenever every single piece of data that's used to train the machine
needs to be seen by a human. You need to pay for that human. And second you're
limited to just the time. There's the amount of data necessary to label what
it means to exist in this world is humongous. Augmented supervised learning
is when you get machine to really to help you a little bit. There's a few
tricks there. But still it's still only tricks. It's still the human is at the
core of it. And the promise of future research that we're pursuing that I'm
pursuing and perhaps in the applications if we get to discuss or some of the
speakers here get to discuss. They're pursuing in semi-supervised and
reinforcement learning. Where the human starts to play a smaller and smaller
role in how much they get to annotate. They have to annotate the data. And the
dream of the sort of wizards of the dark arts of deep learning are all excited
about unsupervised learning. That has very few actual successes in application
in the real world today. But it is the idea that you can build a machine that
doesn't require a human teacher. A human being to teach you anything. It fills us
artificial intelligence researchers with excitement. There's a theme here.
Machine learning is really simple. The learning system in the middle. There's a
training stage where you teach it something. All you need is some data.
Input data. And you need to teach it the correct output for that input data. So
you have to have a lot of pairs of input data and correct output. There'll be a
theme of cats throughout this presentation. So if you want to teach a
system difference between a cat and a dog, you need a lot of images of cats. And
you need to tell it that this is a cat. This bounding box here in the image is a
cat. You have to give it a lot of images of dogs and tell it, okay, in these
pictures there are dogs. And then there's a spelling mistake on the second
stage is the testing stage. When you actually give it new input data, it's
never seen before. And you hope that it has given for cat versus dog enough data
to guess is this new image that I've never seen before, a cat or a dog. Now
one of the open questions you want to keep in mind is what in this world can we
not model in this way? What activity? What task? What goal? I offer to you that
there's nothing you can't model in this way. So let's think about what in terms
of machine learning can be, so let's start small. What can be modeled in this
way? First on the bottom of the slide left is one to one mapping where the
input is an image of a cat and the output is a label that says cat or dog.
You can also do one to many where the image, the input is an image of a cat and
the output is a story about that cat, a captioning of the image. You can first of
all, you can do the other way, many to one mapping where you give it a story
about a cat and it generates an image. There's many to many. This is Google
translate. We translate a sentence from one language to another and there's
various flavors of that. Again, same theme here. Input data provided with
correct output and then let it go into the wild where it runs on input data
that hasn't seen before to provide guesses. And it's as simple as this.
Whatever you can convert into one of the following four things. Numbers, vector of
numbers, so a bunch of numbers, a sequence of numbers where the temporal
dynamics matters, so like audio, video, where the sequence, the ordering matters,
or a sequence of vector numbers, just a bunch of numbers. If you can convert it
to numbers and I propose to you that there's nothing you can't convert it
to numbers. If you can convert it to numbers, you can have a system learn to
do it. And the same thing with the output. Generate numbers, vectors, and numbers
sequence of numbers or sequence of vectors and numbers.
First, is there any questions at this point?
Well, we have a lot of fun slides to get through, but I'll pause every once in a
while to make sure we're on the same page here. So what kind of input are we
talking about? Just to fly through it. Images, so faces, or medical applications
for looking at scans of different parts of the body to determine if, to
diagnose any kind of medical conditions. Texts, so conversations, your texts,
article, blog posts, for sentiment analysis, question and answering, so you
ask it a question where the output you hope answers. Sounds of voice
recognition, any kind of, anything you can tell from audio. Time series data, so
financial data, stock market, you can use it to predict anything you want about
the stock market, including whether to buy or sell. If you're curious, doesn't
work quite well as a machine learning application. Physical world, so cars or
any kind of object, any kind of robot that exists in this world. So location of
where I am, location of where other things are, the actions of others, that
could be all the input. All of it can be converted to numbers. And the correct
output, same thing. Classification, a bunch of numbers. Classification is
saying it's a cat or a dog. Regression is saying to what degree I turn the
steering wheel. Sequence is generating audio, generating video, generating
stories, captioning, text, images, generating anything you could think of as
numbers. And at the core of it is a bunch of data agnostic machine learning
algorithms. There's traditional ones, nearest neighbors, Naive Bay support
machine, support vector machines. A lot of them are limited, and I'll describe
how. And then there's neural networks. There's nothing special and new about
neural networks. And I'll describe exactly the very subtle thing that is
powerful. That's always been there all along. And certain things have now been
able to unlock that power about neural networks. But it's still just the flavor
of a machine learning algorithm. And the inspiration for neural networks, as
Jonathan showed last time, is our human brain. It's perhaps why the media, perhaps
why the hype is captivated by the idea of neural networks, is because you
immediately jump to this feeling like, because there's this mysterious structure
to them that scientists don't understand. Artificial neural networks, I'm
referring to. And the biological ones. We don't understand them. And the
similarity captivates our minds and we think, well, this approach is perhaps as
limited, as limitless as our own human mind. But the comparison ends there. In
fact, artificial neuron, their artificial neural networks are much simpler
computational units. At the core of everything is this neuron. This is a
computational unit that does two very simple operations. On the left side, it
takes a set of numbers as inputs. It applies weights to those inputs, sums
them together, applies a little bias, and provides an output somewhere between zero
and one. So you can think of it as a computational entity that gets excited
when it sees certain inputs and gets totally turned off when it gets other
kinds of inputs. So maybe this neuron with a 0, with a 0.7, 0.6, 1.4 weights, it
gets really excited when it sees pictures of cats and totally doesn't care about
dogs. Some of us are like that. So that's the job of this neuron, is to detect
cats. Now what, the way you build an artificial neural network, the way you
release the power that I'll talk about in the following slides about the
applications, what could be achieved, is just stacking a bunch of these together.
Think about it. This is, this is a extremely simple computational unit.
So you need to sort of pause whenever we talk about the following slides and
think that there's a few slides that I'll show that say neural networks are
amazing. I want you to think back to this slide that everything is built on top
of these really simple addition operations with a simple nonlinear
function applied at the end. Just a tiny math operation. We stack them together
with it in a feedforward way so there's a bunch of layers and when people talk
about deep neural networks it means there is a bunch of those layers and then
there's recurrent neural networks that are also a special flavor that's able to
have memory. So as opposed to just pushing input into output directly, it's
also able to do stuff on the inside in a loop where it remembers things. This is
useful for natural language processing, for audio processing, whenever the
sequence is not, the length of the sequence is not defined. Okay, slide number
one in terms of neural networks are amazing. This is, this is perhaps for the
math nerds. But also I want you to use your imagination. There's a universality
to neural networks. It means that the simple computational unit on the left is
an input and the right is the output of this network with just a single hidden
layer. It's called a hidden layer because it sits there in the middle of the
input and the output layers. A single hidden layer with some number of nodes
can represent any function. Any function. That means anything you want to build in
this world. Everyone in this room can be represented with a neural network with a
single hidden layer. So the power, and this is just one hidden layer, the power
of these things is limitless. The problem, of course, is how do you find the
network? So how do you build a network that is as clever as many of the people
in this room? But the fact that you can build such a network is incredible. It's
amazing. I want you to think about that. And the way you train a network, so it's
born as a blank slate. Some random weights assigned to the edges. Again, a network
is represented. The numbers at the core, the parameters at the core of this
network are the numbers on each of those arrows, each of those edges. And you
start knowing nothing. This is a baby network. And the way you teach it
something, unfortunately, currently, as I said, in a supervised learning
mechanism, you have to give it pairs of input and output. You have to give it
pictures of cats and labels on those pictures saying that they're cats. And the
basic fundamental operation of learning is when you compute the measure of an
error and you back propagate it to the network. What I mean, everything's easier
with cats. I apologize. I apologize. Too many cats. And so the input here is a cat.
And the neural network we trained, it's just guessing. It doesn't know. So I don't
know. It's guessing cat. Well, it happens to be right. So we have to, this is the
measure of error. Yes. You got it right. And you have to back propagate that error.
You have to reward the network for doing a good job. And all you do, what I mean
by reward, there's weights on each of those edges. And so the node, the individual
neurons that were responsible that back to that cat neuron, that cat neuron needs
to be rewarded for seeing the cat. So you just increase the weights on the neurons
that were associated with producing the correct answer. Now you give it a picture
of a dog and the neural network says cat. Well, that's an incorrect answer. So no,
there's a high error. It needs to be back propagated to the network. So the weights
that were responsible with classifying this picture as a cat need to be punished.
They need to be decreased. Simple. And you just repeat this process over and over.
This is what we do as kids when we're first learning. For the most part,
we're also supervised learning machines in the sense that we have our parents and
we have the environment, the world, that teaches about what's correct and what's
incorrect. And we back propagate this error and reward through our brain to learn.
The problem is, as human beings, we don't need too many examples. And I'll talk
about some of the drawbacks of these approaches. We don't need too many
examples. You fall off your bike once or twice and you learn how to ride the bike.
Unfortunately, neural networks need tens of thousands of times when they fall off
the bike in order to learn how to not do it. That's one of the limitations.
And one key thing I didn't mention here is when we refer to input data,
we usually refer to sensory data, raw data. We have to represent that data in
some clever way, in some deeply clever way, where we can reason about it,
whether it's in our brains or in the neural network. And a very simple example
here to illustrate why representation of data matters. So the way you represent
the data can make the discrimination of one class from another, a cat versus dog,
either incredibly difficult or incredibly simple. Here is a visualization of the
same kind of data in Cartesian coordinates and polar coordinates. On the right,
you can just draw a simple line to separate the two. What you want is a system that's
able to learn the polar coordinate representation versus the Cartesian
representation automatically. And this is where deep learning has stepped in and
revealed the incredible power of this approach, which deep learning is the
smallest circle there. It's a type of representational learning. Machine learning
is the bigger second to the biggest. So this class is about the biggest circle,
AI, includes robotics, includes all the fun things that are built on learning.
And I'll discuss while machine learning I think will close this entire circle into
one. But for now, AI is the biggest circle, then a subset of that is machine
learning and a smaller subset of that is representation learning. So deep
learning is not only able to say, given a few examples of cats and dogs that
discriminate between a cat and a dog, it's able to represent what it means to be a
cat. So it's able to automatically determine what are the fundamental
units at the low level and the high level. We're talking about this very Plato.
What it means to represent a cat from the whiskers to the high level shape of
the head to the fuzziness and the deformable aspects of the cat. Not a cat
expert, but I hear these are the features of a cat versus that are essential to
discriminate between a cat and a dog. Learning those features as opposed to
having to have experts, this is the drawback of systems that Jonathan talked
about from the eighties and nineties where you have to bring in experts for any
specific domain that you try to solve. You have to have them encode that
information. Deep learning, this is simply the only big difference between deep
learning and other methods is that it learns the representation for you. It
learns what it means to be a cat. Nobody has to step in and help it figure out
that cats have whiskers and dogs don't. What does this mean? The fact that it
can learn these features, these whisker features, is as opposed to having five
or ten or a hundred or five hundred features that are encoded by brilliant
engineers with PhDs, it can find hundreds of thousands, millions of features
automatically. Hundreds of millions of features. Stuff that can't be put into
words or described, in fact it's one of the limitations in neural networks is they
find so many fundamental things about what it means to be a cat that you can't
visualize what it really knows. It just seems to know stuff. It finds that
stuff automatically. What does this mean? The critical thing here is because it's
able to automatically learn those hundreds of millions of features, it's able to
utilize data. It doesn't start, the diminishing returns don't hit until well we
don't know when they hit. The point is with the classical machine learning
algorithms, you start hitting a wall when you have tens of thousands of images of
cats. With deep learning, you get better and better with more data.
Neural networks are amazing slide two. Here's a game, a simple arcade game where
there's two paddles, they're bouncing a ball back and forth. Okay, great. You can
figure out an artificial intelligence agent that can play this game. It can,
not even that well, just kind of, it kind of learns to do alright and eventually
win. Here's the fascinating thing. With deep learning as opposed to encoding the
position of the paddles, the position of the ball, having an expert in this game,
there's many, come in and encode the physics of this game. The input to the
neural network is the raw pixels of the game. So, it's learning in the following
way. You give it an evolution of the game. You give it a bunch of pixels.
Pixels are, images are built up of pixels. They're just numbers from 0 to 256. So
there's this array of numbers that represent each image and then you give it
several tens of thousands of images that represent a game. So you have the stack
of pixels and stack of images that represent a game. And the only thing you
know, this giant stack of numbers, the only thing you know is at the end you
won or lost. That's it. So based on that, you have to figure out how to play the
game. You know nothing about games. You know nothing about colors or balls or
paddles or winning or anything. That's it. So this is, why is this amazing? That
it even works and it works, it wins. It's amazing because that's exactly what we do
as human beings. This is general intelligence. So I need you to pause and
think about this. We'll talk about special intelligence and the usefulness and
okay, there's cool tricks here and there that we can do to get you an edge on your
high frequency trading system. But this is general intelligence. General
intelligence is the same intelligence we use as babies when we're born. What we
get is an input, sensory input of image sensory input. Right now, all of us,
most of us are seeing, hearing, feeling with touch and that's the only input we
get. We know nothing and with that input, we have to learn something. Nobody is
pre-teaching us stuff and this is an example of that. A trivial example, but
one of the first examples where this is truly working. I'm sorry to linger on
this, but it's a fundamental fact. The fact that we have systems that, and now
outperform human beings in these simple arcade games is incredible. This is the
research side of things. But let me step back, these again, the takeaways. That
previous slide is why I think machine learning is limitless in the future.
Currently, it's limited. Again, the representation of the data matters and if
you want to have impact, we currently can only tackle the small problems. What are
those problems? Image recognition. We can classify, given the entire image of a
leopard, of a boat, of a mite, with pretty good accuracy of what's in that image.
That's image classification. What else? We can find exactly where in that image
each individual object is. That's called image segmentation. Again, the process
is the same. The learning system in the middle, a neural network, as long as you
give it a set of numbers as input and the correct set of labels as output, it
learns to do that for data it hasn't seen in the past. Let me pause a second and
maybe if you have any questions, does anyone have any questions about the
techniques of neural networks? Yes.
How do you represent data, as you mentioned, to us anyways, as well as
coordinate the recent coordinates? How do you represent these two different
kinds of data?
That's a great question. In a couple of slides, I'll get to it exactly. The
data representation, I'll elaborate in a little bit, but loosely, the data
representation is for a neural network is in the weights of each of those arrows
that connect the neurons. That's where the representation is. I'll show to
really clarify that example of what that means. The Cartesian versus polar
coordinates is just a very simple visualization of the concept. You want
to be able to represent the data in an arbitrary way where there's no limits
to the representation. It could be highly nonlinear, highly complex. Any other
questions?
We touched on it earlier. Generally speaking, in our current state, when we talk
about machine learning or AI, it's simply statistical models that are able to
recognize the trends or things of that nature where they're not necessarily
thinking, but simply recognizing. I'm a little confused about how the current
system differs from deep learning. Whether you think that there is a
possibility of transition from recognizing to actually thinking.
I have a couple of slides almost asking this question, because there's no
good answers. One could argue, and I think somebody in the last class brought up
that is machine learning just pattern recognition. It's possible that reasoning,
thinking, is just pattern recognition. I'll describe sort of an intuition
behind that. We tend to respect thinking a lot, because we've recently as human
beings learned to do it. In our evolutionary time, we think that it's somehow
special from, for example, perception. We've had visual perception for several
orders of magnitude longer in our evolution as a living species. We've
started to learn to reason, I think, about 100,000 years ago. We think it's
somehow special from the same kind of mechanism we use for seeing things.
Perhaps it's exactly the same thing. Perception is pattern recognition.
Perhaps reasoning is just a few more layers of that. That's the hope.
That's an open question.
The concept of neural network itself is not very new. Is there any
technical innovation breakthrough to expand the use of neural network?
I think more it's just the increase of the result of computational
innovation. Yes, that's a great question. There's been very few
breakthroughs in neural networks, since through the AI winters that we've discussed,
through a lot of excitement, in spurts, and even recently, there's been
very few algorithmic innovations. The big gains came from compute,
so improvements in GPU and better, faster computers. You can't underestimate
the power of community, so the ability to share code and the internet,
the ability to communicate together through the internet and work on code
together, and then digitization of data, so the ability to have large data sets
easily accessible and downloadable. All of those little things.
I think in terms of the future of deep learning and machine learning,
it all rides on compute, meaning continued, bigger, and faster computers.
That doesn't necessarily mean Moore's law in making small and small chips.
It means getting clever in different directions, massive parallelization,
coming up with ways to do super-efficient, power-efficient
implementations in neural networks, and so on.
Let me just fly through a few examples of what we can do with machine learning
just to give you a flavor, I think, in future lectures as possible.
We'll discuss different speakers, different specific applications,
really dig into those. As opposed to working with just images,
you can work with videos and segment those, I mentioned, image segmentation.
We can do video segmentation through video segment, the different parts
of a scene that's useful to a particular application. Here in driving,
you can segment the road from cars and vegetation
and lane markings.
You can also, this is a subtle but important point.
Just go back to that one slide. How do they see the light?
It's such a critical piece. The more I listen to you
and read your stuff, it seems like this critical, these very small
piece of information that we know are important, like there is a red light.
I have to stop, I have to slow down. How does it filter that out
and pick out that?
It's got to be 100% reliable on that.
Hello.
Oof, hard question.
The question was how do you detect the traffic light
and lights.
How do we do it as human beings? First of all, let's start there.
The way we do it is by
the knowledge we bring to the table. We know what it means
to be on the road. There's a lot of the huge network of knowledge
that you come with. And so that makes the perception problem much easier.
This is pure perception. You take an image and you separate different parts
based purely on tiny patterns of pixels.
So first it finds all the edges and it learns that
traffic lights have certain kinds of edges around them and then
zoom out a little bit. They have
certain collection of edges that make up this black
rectangle type shape. So it's all about shapes. It kind of build up
knowing this shape structure of things. But it's a purely
perception problem and one of the things I argue is that if it's
purely a perception approach and you bring no knowledge to the
table about the physics of the world, the three-dimensional physics and the temporal dynamics,
that you are not going to be able to successfully achieve
near 100% accuracy on some of these systems.
So that's exactly the right question is
for all of these things, think about how you as a human being would solve
these problems and what is lacking in the machine learning approach.
What data is lacking in the machine learning approach in order to achieve
the same kind of results, the same kind of reasoning required to
that you would use as a human. So there is also image
detection. Image detection, which means
the subtle but important point. The stuff I mentioned before, image classification
is given an image of a cat, you find the cat,
sorry you don't find the cat, you say this image is of a cat or not, and then
detection or localization is when you actually find where in the image that is.
That problem is much harder but also doable
with machine learning, with deep neural networks.
Now as I said, inputs-outputs can be anything. The input can be
video, the output can be video, and you can do anything you want with these videos,
you can colorize the video. You can add, take an old black and white
film and produce color images.
Again, in terms of
having an impact in the world using these applications,
you have to think, this is a cool demonstration, but how well does it actually
work in the real world? Translation,
whether that's from text to text or image to image, you can translate
here dark chocolate from one language to another.
Class, global business of
artificial intelligence, there's a reference below there, you can go and generate
your own text. You can generate the writing of
the act of generating handwriting. You can type in some text
and given different styles that it learns from other handwriting
samples, it can generate any kind of text using
handwriting. Again, the input is language, the
output is a sequence of writing
of pen movements on the screen. You can complete sentences.
This is kind of a fun one where if you start
actually you can generate language, and you can generate
language where you feed the system some input first. So in black
there it says life is, and then have the neural network complete
those sentences. Life is about kids.
Life is about the weather, there's a lot of knowledge here
I think being conveyed, and you can start the sentence with the meaning of life is.
The meaning of life is literary recognition,
true for us academics, or the meaning of life is the tradition of
ancient human production. Also true.
But these are all generated by a computer. You can also
caption, this has become very popular recently, is
caption generation. Given input as an image, the output is
a set of text. The caption is the content of the image.
You find the different objects in the image, that's a perception
problem, and once you find the different objects, you stitch them together in a sentence
that makes sense. You generate a bunch of sentences, and classify which sentences the most
likely to fit this image.
And you can, so certainly in the
I try to avoid mentioning driving too much, because it is my field
that is what I'm excited about, but then
the moment I start talking about driving it'll all be about driving.
But I should mention of course that deep learning is critical to driving
applications, for both the perception and what is really exciting to us now is
the end-to-end, the end-to-end approach.
So whenever you say end-to-end in any application, what that means
is you start from the very raw inputs that the
system gets, and you produce the very final
output that's expected of the system. So as opposed to in the cell driving car case
as opposed to breaking a car down into each individual components of
perception, localization, mapping, control, planning
and just taking the whole stack and just ignoring
all the super complex problems in the middle and just taking the external
scene as input and as output produced steering and
acceleration and braking commands. And so in this way, taking this input
is the image of the external world, in this case in a Tesla
we can generate steering commands for the car.
And then input a bunch of numbers that's just images,
output a single number that gives you the steering of
the car.
Okay, so let's step back
for a second and think about what can't we do
with machine learning. We talked about you can map numbers to numbers. Let's think about
what we can't do. At the core of artificial intelligence in terms of
how we can impact on this world is robotics. So what
can't we solve in robotics and artificial intelligence with the machine learning approach?
And let's break down what artificial intelligence means.
Here's a stack starting at the very top is the environment, the world
that you operate in. There's sensors that sense that world. There is feature
extraction and learning from that data and there's some reasoning,
planning and affectors are the ways you manipulate
the world. What can't we learn in this way?
So we've had a lot of success as Jonathan talked about
in the history of AI with formal tasks, playing games,
solving puzzles. Recently we're having a lot of breakthroughs with medical
diagnosis. We're still
struggling
but are very excited about in the robotics space
with more mundane tasks of walking, of
basic perception, of natural language written and spoken.
And then there is the human tasks which are
perhaps completely out of reach of this pipeline
at the moment is cognition,
imagination, subjective
experience. So high level reasoning, not just common sense,
but high level human level reasoning.
So let's fly through this pipeline. There's sensors,
cameras, LiDAR, audio,
there's communication that flies through the air
or wired or wireless or wired. IMU measuring the movement
of things. So that's the way you think about it.
That's the way as human beings and as any kind of system that you design, you measure the world.
You don't just get an API to the world.
You need to somehow measure aspects of this world.
So that's how you get the data. So that's how you convert the
world into data you can play with. And once you have the data,
this is the representation side. You have to convert that raw data, raw
pixels, raw audio, raw LiDAR data. You have to convert that
into data that's useful for the intelligence system,
for the learning system to use to discriminate
between one thing and another.
For vision, that's finding edges, corners,
object parts and entire objects. And there's the machine learning
that I've talked about. There's different kinds of mapping
of the representation that you've learned to an actual outputs.
There is, once you have this, so you have this idea
of, and this goes to maybe a little bit of Simon's question,
is reasoning. This is something that's
out of reach in machine learning at the moment. This is going to your question.
Then we can build
a world class machine learning system for taking an image
and classifying that it's a duck. I wonder if this will work.
Wake you up.
So we could take, this is well studied,
exceptionally well studied problem. We could take audio sample
of a duck and tell that it's a duck. In fact, what species
of bird? It's incredible how much research there is in bird species
classification. And we can look at video and we can tell
that we can do actual recognition that it's swimming. But we
can't do with learning now, is reason. That if it
looks like a duck, it swims like a duck and quacks like a duck,
it's very likely to be a duck. This is the reasoning problem.
This is the task that I personally am obsessed with
and that I hope that machine learning can close.
And then there is the planning action and the effectors.
So this is another place
where machine learning
has not had many strides. There's mechanical issues here that are incredibly
difficult. The degrees of freedom with all the actuators involved,
with all the just the ability to
localize every part of yourself in this dynamic
space. Where things
are constantly changing when there's degrees of uncertainty, when there's noise. Just that
basic problem is exceptionally difficult.
Let me just pose this question. We talked
about what machine learning can do with the cats and the duck.
We could do that. Given representation, it could predict what's in the image.
But one of the open questions is, and deep
learning has been able to do the feature extraction, the representation
learning. This is the big breakthrough that everybody's excited about.
But can it also reason? These are the open questions.
Can it reason? Can it do the planning and action?
And as human beings do, can it close the loop entirely
from sensors to effectors? So learn not only
the brain, but the way you sense the
world, and the way you affect the world.
So the question was about the pond game. Thank you.
Let's get to talk to it for a little longer. It doesn't
get punished when it doesn't detect the ball. This is the beautiful thing.
It gets punished only at the very end of the game for losing the game, and gets
rewarded for winning the game. So it knows nothing about that ball.
And it learns about that ball. That's something you need to really sit and think
about. Because like, as human
beings, imagine if you're playing with a physical ball, how do you
learn what a ball is? You get hurt by it,
you like squeeze it, you throw it, you feel the dynamics of it,
the physics of it, and
nobody tells you about what a ball is. You're just using the raw
sensory input. We take it for granted, and maybe this is what I can
end on, is this is what something Jonathan
brought up, is we take the simplicity of this task for granted.
Because we've been, we've had eyes
we broadly speaking as living
species on planet Earth. These eyes have been evolved
for 540 million years. So we have 540 million
years of data. We've been walking for close to that
by petal mammals. We have been
thinking only very recently. So 100,000 years
is 100 million years. And
that's why we can't, some of these problems that we're trying to
solve, you can't take for granted how actually difficult they are. So for
example, this is the Marvex Paradox that Jonathan brought up,
is that the easy problems are hard. The things we think are easy, actually really
hard. This is the state-of-the-art robot on the right playing soccer,
and that was the state-of-the-art human
on the left playing soccer. And
I'll give it a second.
The question was, you know, there's a
fundamental difference between the way we train neural networks and the way we've trained
biological neural networks through evolution by discarding through natural selection a bunch of
the neural networks that didn't work
so well. So first of all, the process of
evolution is, I think, not well understood.
Meaning, sorry, the role,
careful here. The role of
evolution in the evolution of our cognition, of
our intelligence. I don't know if that's, so this
is an open question. So maybe clarify this point. Is neural networks
artificial neural networks are fixed for the most part in size?
This is exactly right. It's like a single human being that gets to
learn. We don't have mechanisms of
modifying or revolving those neural networks yet.
Although you could think of researchers
as doing exactly that. You have grad students working on different
neural networks and the ones that don't do a good job don't get
promoted and get a good job. There is a natural selection there, but other than that
it's an open question. It's a fascinating one.
Stay tuned and keep your head up because the future I believe
is really promising. And the slides will be
made available for sure.
I think a lot of the explorations of
what it means to build an intelligent machine has been in sci-fi movies. We're now beginning
to actually make it a reality. This is Space Odyssey to keep with that theme
in the previous lecture that we had. This is
as opposed to the dream like monolith view
when the astronaut is gazing out
into the open sky at the stars. We're going to look at the practice of
AI today and how we go, if you're familiar with the
movie, when this new technology appeared before our eyes
and we're full of excitement, how we transfer that into
actual practical impact
on our lives. To quickly review what we
talked about last time, I presented the technology
and asked the question of whether this technology merely serves a special purpose
to answer specific tasks that can be formalized or whether it can
be through the process of transferring
the knowledge learned on one domain be generalizable
to where an intelligent system that's trained in a small domain can be
used to achieve general intelligent tasks like we do
as human beings. This is kind of the stack of artificial intelligence
going from all the way up to the top, the environment, the world
the sensors, the sensor data, the intelligence system, the way
it perceives this world. Then once you have this, you convert
the world into some numbers, you're able to extract some representation of that
world and this is where machine learning starts to come into play. And then there's
the part where I will raise it again today is can machine learning
be doing the following steps too that we can do very well as human beings is the
reasoning step. You can tell the difference in a cat and a dog, but can you
now start to reason about what it means to be alive, what it
means to be a cat, a living creature, what it means to be this kind of physical object
or this kind of physical object and take what's called common sense, things we take
for granted, start to construct models of the world through
reasoning. Descartes, I think therefore I am.
We want our neural networks to come up with that on their own.
And once you do that, action.
You'll go right back into the world and you start acting in that world. So the question is
can machine learning, can this be learned from data or do experts need to encode
the knowledge of reasoning, the knowledge of actions, the set of actions.
That's kind of the question, the open questions I raise. It continues throughout the talk
today. And so as we start to think
about how artificial intelligence, especially machine learning
as it relies itself through robotics, gets to impact the world, we start thinking
about what are the easy problems and what are the hard problems. And it seems
to us that vision
and movement, walking is easy because we've been doing it for millions
of years, hundreds of millions of years, and thinking is hard.
Reasoning is hard. I propose to you that it's perhaps because we've only
been doing it for a short time and so think we're quite special
because we're able to think. So we have to kind of question of what is easy
and what is hard. Because when we start to develop some of these systems
and you start to realize that all of these
problems are equally hard. So the problem of walking that we take for granted,
the actuation and the physical, the ability to recognize
where you are in the physical space to sense the world
around you, to deal with the
uncertainty of the perception problem. And then
so all of these robots, by the way, this is for the most recent DARPA Challenge
which MIT was also part of.
And so what are these robots doing? They
don't have any, they only have sparse communication with human beings
on the periphery. So most of the stuff they have to do autonomously
like get inside a car, this is an MIT robot unfortunately,
that they have to get in the car in the hardest tasks, they have to get out of the
car. That's walking. So this kind of
raises to you a very real
aspect here. You want to build applications that actually work in the real world.
And that's the first challenge and opportunity here.
The many of the technologies we talked about currently crumble
under the reality of
our world. When we transfer them from a small
data set in the lab to the real world. For the computer vision
it's perhaps one of the best illustrations of this. Computer vision is the task
as we talked about of interpreting images. And so when
you, there's been a lot of great accomplishments on interpreting images.
Cats versus dogs. Now when you try to create
a system like the Tesla vehicle
that I've often, that we work with and
I always talk about is, it's a vision
based robot, right? It has radar for basic obstacle avoidance
but most of the understanding of the world comes from a single monocular camera.
Now they've expanded the number of cameras but for the most time there's been 100,000
vehicles driving on the roads today with a single, essentially
a single webcam. So when you start to do
that you have to perform all of these extraction of texture, color,
optical flow. So the movement through time, temporal dynamics of the images
you have to construct these patterns, construct the understanding of
objects and entities and how they interact. And from that you have to act
in this world. And that's all based on this computer vision system. So it's no longer
cats versus dogs, it's
detection of pedestrians. Where the wrong
classification, the wrong detection
is the difference between life and death. So let's look at
cats, where things are a little more comfortable. So computer vision
and I would like to illustrate to you why this is such a hard
task. We talked about, we've been doing it for 500 million years
so we think it's easy. Computer vision is actually incredible
so all you're getting with your human eyes is you're getting essentially pixels
in. There's light coming into your eyes and all you're getting is the reflection
from the different surfaces in here of light and there's
perception, there's sensors inside your eyes
converting that into numbers. It's really very similar to this.
Numbers in the case of what we use with computers, RGB images
or the individual pixels that are numbers from
255 to 256 possible numbers and there's just a bunch of them.
And that's all we get. We get a collection of numbers where they're spatially
connected. The ones that are close together are part of the same object so
cat pixels are all connected together. That's the only thing we have to help
us but the rest of it is just numbers, intensity numbers. And we have to use those numbers
to classify what's in the image.
And if you really think about it, this is a really difficult task. All you get
is these numbers. How the heck are you supposed to form a model
of the world with which you can detect
pedestrians with really 99.99999% accuracy.
Because these pedestrians or these cars
are cyclists in the car context or any kind of applications that you're looking at.
Even if your job is on the factory floor to detect
the defective gummy bears that are flying past like 100 miles an hour
your task is you don't want that bad gummy bear to get by
that your product and the brand will be damaged. However
serious or not serious your application is, what you have to be
you have to have a computer vision system that deals with
all of these aspects. Viewpoint variation, scale
variation, no matter the size of the object is still the same object.
No matter the viewpoint from which area you
look at that object is still the same object. The lighting that moves
we have lighting consistently here because we're indoors. But when you're outdoors
or you're moving, the scene is moving, the lighting, the complexity
of the lighting variations is incredible. From the illumination to just
the movement of the different objects in the scene.
Now that we've had these conversations, I think about this every time
I drive. I think about you at this point and how hard it is to see these things.
Particularly when I'm driving at night and particularly when it's twilight and the light is changing
I think almost every time I drive
there's one or two things that I see that I'm drawing
like 200 million years in order to be able to figure out. It's a guy who's
open his car door and I can't see him but I can just see the light doesn't look quite
right on that side of the road and somehow I know in my
mind it's a person. But it seems like an almost
impossible problem for the machines to get right with sufficient accuracy.
I will argue that the pure perception task is too hard.
That you come to the table as human beings with all this
huge amount of knowledge. That you're not actually
interpreting all the complex lighting variations that you're seeing.
You actually know enough about the world, enough about your commute home,
enough about the way, the kinds of things you would see in this
world, about Boston, about the way pedestrians move, the
certain light of day. You bring all that to the table that makes the perception task
doable. And that's one of the big missing pieces in the technology.
As I'll talk about, that's the open problem of machine learning.
It's how to bring all that knowledge, first of all build that knowledge and then bring that
knowledge to the table as opposed to starting from scratch every time.
And so, cats, I promise cats.
Okay, so to me, occlusion, for most of the
computer vision community, this is one of the biggest challenges. And it really highlights
how far we are from
being able to reason about this world. Occlusions are
what an occlusion is, is when the objects you're trying to
detect, something about, classify the object, detect the object,
the object is blocked
by another object in front of them. This is something
that you think is trivial, perhaps. You don't even really think about it, because
we reason in a three-dimensional way. But the occlusion
aspect is, makes, makes perception
incredibly difficult. So we have to design, think about this.
So this image is converted into numbers. And we, for the task of
detecting, is there a cat in this image? Yes or no? You have to be able to
reason about this image with that object in the scene. Most
of us are able to very easily detect that there's a cat in this image.
We're able to detect that there's a cat in this image. Now think about this.
There's a single eye and there's an ear.
So you have to think about what is it part of our brain that allows
us to understand, to, to suppose that with some
high degree of accuracy that there's a cat here in this picture.
I mean the degree of occlusion here is immense.
So this is for most of you.
Some of you will think this is in fact a monk
eating a banana. But I would venture to say that most of us are
able to tell it's never the last of cat.
You'll watch this for hours.
And so let me give you another, this is kind of a paper that's often cited
or a set of papers
to illustrate how difficult computer vision is.
How thin the line that we're walking with
all of these impressive results that we've been able to show recently in the machine
learning community. In this case
for deep neural networks are easily fooled paper.
The seminal paper at this point shows that when you apply
a network trained on ImageNet, so
basically on detecting cats versus dogs or different categories inside images
if you're, you can find
an arbitrary number of images that look like noise up in the top row.
Where the algorithm used
to classify those images in ImageNet of cat versus dog
is able to confidently say with 99.6% accuracy
above that it's seeing a robin or a cheetah
or an armadillo or a panda in that noise.
So it's confidently saying given this noise that that's obviously a robin.
So you have to realize that the kind
of, this is patterns, the kind
of processes it's using to understand what's contained in the image
is purely a collection of patterns that it has been able to
track from other images that has been human, annotated by humans.
And that perhaps is very limiting
to trying to create a system that's able to operate in the real world.
This is a very, so this is a very clean illustration
of that concept. In the same you can confidently predict
in those images below where there's strong patterns, it's not even noise.
Strong patterns that have nothing to do with the entities being detected.
Again, confidently that same algorithm is able to see a penguin,
a starfish, a baseball, and a guitar in that noise.
And more serious for people
designing robots like myself on the
sensor side, you can flip that and say
I can take a image
and I can distort it with some very little amount of noise.
And if that noise is applied to the image
I can completely change the confident prediction about what's in that image.
So to explain what's being shown. So on the left, the column in the left,
and again here, what's
the same kind of neural network is able to predict
accurately, confidently, that there is a dog in that image.
But if we apply just a little bit of noise to that image, to produce
that image, imperceptible to our human eyes, the difference between those two,
the same algorithm is saying that there's confidently an ostrich
in that image. So another thing to really think about
that noise can have such a significant impact on the
prediction of these algorithms. This is really, really
quite honestly out of all the things I'll say today and I'm aware of
one of the biggest challenges of
machine learning being applied in the real world is robustness.
How much noise can you add into the system before
everything falls apart? So how do you validate
sensors? So say a car company has to produce a vehicle
and it has sensors in that vehicle. How do you know that those sensors
will not start generating slight noise due to interference of various
kinds? And because of that noise, instead of seeing a pedestrian
it will see nothing. Or the opposite, it will see pedestrians everywhere.
So of course the most dangerous is when it will not see an object
and collide with it, in the case of cars. There's also spoofing, which a lot of
people as always with security, people are really concerned about.
And perhaps people here are really concerned about this issue. I think this
is a really important issue, but because you can apply noise and convince the system
that you're seeing an ostrich when there's in fact no ostrich,
you can do the same thing in an
attacking way. So you can attack the sensors of a car and make
it believe like with lidar spoofing. So spoof lidar, radar, ultrasonic
sensors to believe that you're seeing pedestrians when they're not there
and the opposite. To hide pedestrians, make pedestrians invisible
to the sensor when they're in fact there.
So whenever you have indulgent systems operating in this world
they become susceptible to
the fact that everything, so much of the work is done in software and based on
sensors. So at any point in the chain if there's a failure
you have to be able to detect that failure and right now we have no mechanisms for
automatically detecting that failure. So on the data side
so one challenge is that we're constantly
dealing with is
we, the algorithms in machine learning algorithms
that we're using are need labeled
data and we have very little labeled data.
Labeled data again is when you have pairs of
input data and the ground truth, the
true label annotation class that
that image belongs to or concept. And it doesn't have to
be an image, it can be any source of data. It's a really costly process to
do. So because it's so costly
we rely
every breakthrough we've had so far relies on that
labeled data and because of its cost we don't
have much of it. So all the problems that come from data can either
be solved by having a lot more of this data which I believe is
and most people believe is too challenging. It's too challenging to have
human beings annotate huge amounts of data or we have to develop
algorithms that are able to do something with the unlabeled data.
It's the unsupervised, semi-supervised, sparsely supervised
reinforcement learning. As we talked about last time I'll mention again
here. So one way you understand
something about data when you don't have labels is you reason
about it. All you're given is a few facts. When you're a baby
your parents give you a few facts and you go into this world with those facts
and you grow your knowledge graph, your knowledge base, your understanding of the world from those
few facts. We don't have a good method of doing that in an automated, unrestricted
way. The inefficiency of our
learners. The machine learning algorithms I've talked about in neural networks need
a lot of examples of every single concept that they're given in order to learn anything
about them. Thousands, tens of thousands of cats are needed to
understand what the spatial patterns at every level
the representation of a cat, the visual representation of a cat.
We don't, we can't do anything with a single example. There's a few approaches
but nothing quite robust
yet. And we haven't come up with
a way, this is also possible, to make
annotation, this labeling process, somehow be
very cheap. So leveraging, this is something been called
human computation. That term is falling out of favor a little bit.
One of my big passions is human computation is using
something about our behavior, something about what we do in this world online
or in the real world to annotate data automatically.
So for example
as you drive, which is what we do, everybody has to
drive and we can collect data about you driving in order to train self-driving vehicles
to drive. And that's a
free annotation. So here are the annotated data sets
we have. The supervised learning data sets.
There's many, but these are some of the more famous ones.
From the toy data sets of MNIST to the large, broad
arbitrary categories of images data sets
which is what ImageNet is. And there's
in healthcare, there's in audio, there's in video, there's
a huge number of data sets now, but each one of them is usually
on the scale of hundreds of thousands, millions, tens of millions
not billions or trillions, which is what we need to create
systems that operate in the real world. And again
these are the kinds of machine learning algorithms we have. There's five listed
here. The teachers on the left
is what is the input
to the system that requires to train it. From the supervised
learning at the very top is what we have all of our successes. And everything else is where the
promise lies. The semi-supervised, the reinforcement
or the fully unsupervised learning, where the input from the human is very
minimal. And another way to think about this, so
whenever you think about machine learning today, whenever somebody talks about machine
learning, what they're talking about is systems that memorize.
That memorize patterns. And so this is one of the big
criticisms of the current machine learning approaches, where all they're doing is
you're providing, they're only as good as the human annotated
data that they're provided. We don't have mechanisms for actually
understanding. You can pause and think about this. In order to
create an intelligent system it shouldn't just memorize. It should understand
the representations inside that data in order to operate in that
world. And that's the open question.
One of them. And one of the challenges and opportunities for machine learning
researchers today is to extend machine learning
from memorization to understanding. This is that
duck. The reasoning
if you get information from the perception systems that it
looks like a duck, from the audio processing that it quacks like a duck,
and then from video classification that the activity recognition that it
swims like a duck, the reasoning step is how to connect those
facts to then say that it is in fact a duck.
Okay, so that's on the algorithm side and the
data side. Now this is one of the reasons
computational power, computational hardware that is at the core
of the success of machine learning.
So our algorithms have been the same since the 60's, since the
80's, 90's depending on how you're counting. The big
breakthroughs came in compute. So there's Moore's law.
Most of you know the way the CPU
side of our computers works for a single CPU is that it's
for the most part executing a single action at a time
in a sequence. So sequential. Very different from
our brain which is a massively parallelized system.
So because it's sequential the clock speed matters because that's how fast
essentially those instructions are able to be executed. And so
where we're leveling off, physics
is stopping us from continuing Moore's law.
Intel, AMD are aggressively pushing this Moore's law
forward. But, and there's
some promise that it will actually continue for another 10 or 15 years.
Then there's another
form of parallelism, massive parallelism. It's the GPU.
This is essential for neural networks.
This is essential to the success, recent success of neural networks is the
ability to utilize these inherently parallel
architectures of graphics processing
units, GPUs. The same thing used for video games. This is the
reason NVIDIA stock is doing
extremely well, is GPUs. So it's
parallelism of basic computational processes that make
machine learning work on the GPU. One of the
limitations of GPUs, one of the challenges is
in bringing them to, in scaling and bringing them into real world applications is
power usage, is power consumption. And so there is
a lot of specialized chips specialized just
from the neural network architectures coming out from Google
with their tensor processing unit from IBM, Intel and so on.
It's unclear how far this goes. So this is sort of the direction
of trying to design an electronic brain, so it has the efficiency.
Our human brain is exceptionally efficient at running the neural networks
in our heads. Or does the magnitude more efficient
than our computers are? And this is trying to design systems that are able to
go towards that efficiency. Why do you care about
efficiency? For several reasons. One, of course,
I'm sure we'll talk about throughout this class is about the thing in our
smartphones, battery usage. And this
is the big one, community. I think
it could be attributed to the big
breakthroughs in machine learning recently in the last decade is
the, you know, compute is important, algorithm development
is important, but it's the community
of nerds, global. This is global artificial intelligence
and I will show in several ways why global is
essential here is tens of
hundreds of thousands, millions of programmers, mechanical
engineers, building robots, building intelligence systems,
building machine learning algorithms. The exciting nature
of the growth of the community perhaps is the key
to the future to unlocking the power of machine learning. So this is just
one example of GitHub as a repository for code and this is showing on
the y-axis at the bottom is 2008 when GitHub first opened and this is
going up to 2012. Quick, near exponential
growth of the number of users participating and the number of repositories. So these are
standalone unique projects that are being hosted on GitHub.
So this is one example I'll show you about this competition
that we're recently running and then I'll challenge people here to participate in this competition
if you dare. So this is a
chance for you to build a neural network in your browser
so you can do this on your phone later tonight of course.
On your phone you can specify various
parameters of the neural network, specify different numbers of layers and the depth
of the network, the number of neurons in the network, the type of layers and it's pretty
self-explanatory, super easy in terms of just
tweaking little things and remember machine learning to a large
part is an art at this point. It's
more perhaps than even, you know, more than a well understood
theoretically bounded science which is one of the challenges but it's also an opportunity.
Deep traffic is a chance, so we've all been stuck
in traffic. There you go, Americans spend 8 billion hours stuck in traffic every year.
That's our pitch for this competition. So deep neural network can help
and so you have a neural network that drives that little car with an
MIT logo, red one, on this highway and tries to weave in and out of traffic to get
to his destination and trying to achieve a speed of
80 miles an hour which is the speed limit which is the physical
speed limit of the car. Of course the actual speed limit of the road is 65 miles an hour
but we don't care about that. We just want to get to work as quickly as possible at home.
So what the basic
structure of this game is and I want to explain this game a little bit and then tell
you how incredibly popular it's gotten and how incredibly
powerful the
networks that people have built from all over the world. The community has built
of this over a single month is incredible and this happens for
thousands of projects out there. Now another challenging
opportunity. Okay so you may have seen this, this is kind of ethics.
Most engineers, I personally don't like, I
love philosophy but this kind of construction of
ethics that's often presented here is one that is not usually
concerned to engineering. So what is this question? You know when you have a car
and you have a bunch of pedestrians, do you hit the larger group of pedestrians
or the smaller group of pedestrians? Do you avoid the group
of pedestrians but put yourself into danger? These kinds of ethical
questions of an intelligent system. It's a very interesting question.
It's one that we can debate and there's really no good answer quite honestly
but it's a problem that both humans and machines struggle with and so it's
not interesting on the engineering side. We're interested with problems that we can
solve on the engineering side. So the kind of problem that I'm obsessed with
and very interested in is the real world problem of controlling a vehicle through this space.
So it happens in a few seconds
here. So this is a Manhattan-New York intersection, right?
This is pedestrians walking perfectly
legally. I think they have a green light. Of course there's a lot of jaywalking too as well.
Well this car just, it's not part of the
point but yes, exactly, there's an ambulance. And so there's another car that starts
making a left turn in a little bit. Let me admit that hopefully not.
But yeah, and then there's another car after that too that just illustrates
when you design an algorithm that's supposed to move through this space
like watch this car. The aggression it shows. Now this isn't
a trivial example for those that try to build robots. This is the real question
is how do you design a system
that's able, so you have to think. You have to put
reward functions, objective functions, utility functions under which
it performs the planning. So a car like that has
several thousand candidate trajectories you can take through that
intersection. You can take a trajectory where it speeds up to 60 miles an hour and doesn't stop
and just swerves and hits everything. Okay, that's a bad trajectory, right? Then
there's a trajectory which most companies take, most
Google self-driving car and every company that's concerned about PR is
whenever there's any kind of obstacle, any kind of risk that's
at all reasonable that you can maybe even touch an obstacle then you're not going
to take that trajectory. So what that means is you're going to navigate through this intersection
at 10 miles an hour and let people abuse you by walking in front of you
because they know you're not going to stop. And so in the middle there is
hundreds, thousands of trajectories that are ethically questionable
in the sense that you're putting other human beings at risk in order to
safely and successfully navigate through the intersection. And the design of those
objective functions is the kind of question you have to ask
for intelligence systems for cars. There's no
grandma and a few children you have to choose who gets to
die. Very difficult problems, of course. But
the problem of what I'm very interested in in streets of Boston
and streets of New York is how to gently nudge yourself
through a crowd of pedestrians in the way we all actually do
when we drive in New York in order to be able to safely
navigate these environments. And these questions come up in healthcare, these questions come up
in factory, in robots, in armed and humanoid robots
that operate with other human beings.
And that's one of the big challenges. Another sort of
fun illustration that folks at OpenAI use often
to illustrate, well let me just pause for a second, the gamified version
of this. There's a game called Coast Runners and you're racing against other boats
along this track. And your job is, there's your score here
at the bottom left, number of laps, your time, and you're
trying to get to the destination as quickly as possible while also collecting
funky little things like these green
these green little things along the way. Okay, so
what they've done is a build intent system, the one, the general purpose one that we
talked about last time that learns, oops, that learns
how to navigate successfully through the space. So
you're trying to maximize the reward. And what this boat
learns to do is instead of finishing the race
it learns to find a loop where
it can keep going around and around, collecting those green dots
and it learns the fact that they regenerate with time.
So it learns to maximize this score
by going around and around. Now these are the kinds of things
this is the big challenge of reward functions, of designing systems
of designing what you want your system to achieve is
not only is it difficult to, the ethical questions are difficult
but just avoiding the pitfalls of local optima
of figuring out something really good that happens
in the short term, the greedy, what are those, those psychology experiments of the kid
eats the marshmallow and can't wait for, you know, can't
delay gratification. This kind of, the idea of delay gratification
in the case of designing intelligence systems is a huge actual serious problem
and this is a good illustration of that.
So we flew through a few concepts here
is there any questions about
the compute and the algorithm side we talked about today?
So the question was, yeah you highlighted some of the limitations of
machine, computer vision algorithms, machine learning algorithms, but
you haven't highlighted some of the limitations of human beings and if you put those in a column
and you compare those, are machines doing better
overall or is there any kind of way to compare those? I mean there is actually
interesting work on ImageNet, so ImageNet is this categorization
task of where you have to classify images and you can ask the question
when I present you images of cats and dogs, where are machines better than humans
and when are they not? So you can compare when machines do better,
what are the fail points and what are the fail points for humans and there's a lot of interesting
visual perception questions there. But I think overall it's certainly
true that machines fail differently than human beings, but
in order to make an artificial intelligence system
usable and could make you a lot of money
and people would want to use, it has to be better for that particular task
in every single way. In order
for you to want to use a system, it has to be superior
to human performance and usually far superior to human performance.
So on the philosophical level it's an interesting thing to compare
what are we good at, what are not, but if you're using
Amazon Echo, your voice recognition
or any kind of natural language, chatbots, or a car,
you're not going to be, well this car is not so good with pedestrians, but I appreciate the fact
that you can stay in the lane. Fortunately you have a very high standard
for every single thing that you're good at and it has to be superior to that. I think
maybe that's unfair to the robots.
I'm more of the nerd that makes the technology happen
but it's certainly on the self-driving car aspect
policy is probably the biggest challenge and I don't think there's good answers
there. Some of those ethical questions that
come up, it feels like, so we work a lot with Tesla
so I'm driving a Tesla around every day and we're playing around with it
and studying human behavior inside Tesla and it seems like there's so much
hunger amongst the media to jump on something and it feels like
a very shaky PR terrain, a very shaky
policy terrain we're all walking because we have no idea how
we coexist with intelligent systems and then of course
the government is nervous because how do we regulate this shaky terrain
and everybody's nervous and excited.
That's a perfect transition point if that's okay.
That same kind of question to Jason in a moment. Thanks a lot Lex for another great session.
Thank you.