The following is a conversation with Ray Dalio, his second time on the podcast.
He is a legendary investor, founder of Bridgewater Associates, author of a book
I highly recommend called Principles, and also a new book called Principles
for Dealing with a Changing World Order that looks at the geopolitics of the day,
especially U.S. and China, to the lens of history, providing a fascinating
model for the rise and fall of empires that can be applied to the analysis
of our world today.
This is the Lex Friedman podcast.
To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now here's my conversation with Ray Dalio.
When you look at the history of the world, as you have done in your new book,
Principles of Dealing with a Changing World Order, what is more important,
more impactful, money or power?
They go hand in hand.
They support each other and they compete with each other.
Those who have money have power, a certain type of power.
That power has to do with all that they can buy, but it also has the ability
to influence those with political power.
So, and so you see this throughout history, this symbiotic relationship.
You know, for example, between the royal families, the nobility and the church.
So, you see that group of people supporting each other in various ways and
then wrestling around with each other for the money and power among that group.
So, the dynamic that's quite classic is you could look at the parties in power.
Back in, you know, the 16th, 17th centuries, you would look at royal families,
nobles and the church, if you're in Europe.
And then you would look at agricultural land and there was a certain dynamic.
And that varies over time.
It changes as those people get thrown out and technology changes.
So, when we evolved, when the society evolved, so that it would produce goods
and services and you have something like the industrial revolution, the first
industrial revolution, they have machines and you have the talent of people
that are off the farms and then you have a struggling for power.
You see that power mix change.
And so, we don't see that same power mix anymore, but you still see the same dynamic.
You see those with money dealing with those who have political power around
those assets that are considered most valuable to particularly the productive
assets that produce money.
And political power is usually centered around nation state.
So, the major locus is the powers, the nations.
Yes.
In 1668, after 30 years of war, there was the development of nation states.
Before then, we had, it was really the development of the countries as we know
it, that there were borders and that within those borders, those who had
control got to control it and there would not to be intrusions in those
borders and that's how we established the nation state.
And then, of course, within each country, there is levels.
There is a central level and then there is a typically a province or state
level down below and then there's a municipal level.
So, they each have different levels of power and it's the coordination of those
that determines how the country is run.
You write that the quote archetypal big cycle governs the rising and declining
empires and influences everything about them, including their currencies and markets.
The most important three cycles are the ones you mentioned in the introduction.
The long-term debt and capital market cycle, the internal order and disorder cycle
and the external order and disorder cycle.
Can you describe this big cycle?
There are two orders.
There is an order by a order, I mean a system, how the system works.
So, there's an internal order that is the internal governance system and that's
usually set out in a constitution or some agreements and then there's the world
order, how the world system.
So, for example, in 1945, at the end of a war, which is basically a fight for
determining the world order, the winners of the fight got together and created
the world system as we now know it.
44, they created the Brenton Woods monetary system that determined the money
pretty much and because the United States won and had 80% of the world's money,
gold was money then and has 80% of the world's gold and it was half the world
economy and it was the great military power.
The order was built around an American world order so that the United
nations was in New York, the World Bank and the IMF were in Washington and they
built that new order.
So, classically, you have a war to determine whose rules were following and then you
have the new order being constructed.
After that, there is usually period of extended peace and prosperity.
Peace suits prosperity and so there's not, and the reason you have the peace is
because no one wants to fight with the dominant power.
You know you're going to lose, you've surrendered, there's been the surrendering.
They carve up the world, they say what it's going to look like, who's going to
control what and then you come into that period of peace and then prosperity where
then there's a working together.
Usually, at that point, you've wiped out a lot of the debt, you've wiped out a
lot of the issues, the class warfare and so on and then there's good working
together so those great periods, such as the industrial revolution in the late
1800s or what we've experienced in the post-World War II period are peaceful and
prosperous periods led largely by the dominant world power.
Over a period of time, since really 1500 and maybe before, but really 1500 when the
Dutch invented capitalism and what I mean by that, they invented the first
capital markets, the first stocks and the first stock market, that since then
capitalism has been an effective tool for building wealth because it got resources
into the hands of inventive people.
That's when we move from agriculture to the importance of inventiveness of people.
They got resources and then they built that prosperity.
In that process of doing that, they create wealth gaps naturally.
Those who make a lot of money make a lot more and then those that don't.
And it also produces opportunity gaps because, for example, those who earn a
lot of money have that wealth, they have the power to educate their children in a
way that others don't and the gaps grow and also the debts grow at that time.
When they go around the world with their competitiveness, they earn a lot of money.
So for example, the Dutch, the Dutch Empire, learned how to build ships and that
would go around the world.
A key ingredient of this improvement in this cycle is the improvement of education.
And by education, I mean the skills that come from education, but also civility,
the ability to deal with wealth together.
So the Dutch invented ships that could go around the world and they had military
power, but they were also very inventive society.
25% of the world's new inventions came from the Dutch.
And so as they went around the world, they also brought their currency and they
brought their military.
They needed the currency, they paid for things and that currency.
And then the more that happens, the more that becomes a reserve currency and then
they have their military.
So they need their military strength.
And so you see it evolve in all of those ways.
But over a period of time, as they become more successful and more expensive, they
become, they become more expensive and newer countries come along, like the UK,
then be, learn to build ships from a lot the Dutch and could do that less
expensively and also when they become more expensive, so less competitive.
And also the work ethic begins to change.
They believe that since they're richer, they can enjoy life more.
They don't have to work quite as hard.
And so you start to see the tilt.
Now you start to see the development of the top.
And when you have a world reserve currency, that allows you to borrow a lot of
money because those who want to save want to hold your money.
And that means that they'll lend you money.
And so those countries get deeper into debt.
So you see that they gradually lose their competitiveness and they get themselves
into financial circumstances, which are not good.
And they have large wealth gaps, which set the stage for downturns.
And when they have downturns, the first question is, do they have enough money?
And traditionally, you know, money is, is resources.
So you classically see that the coffers are bare, that they're spending more money
than they're, than they are earning and they run out of money in the coffers.
And their granaries are empty rather than stocked so that they give them the buffer.
And as that deteriorates, that's that worsens conditions.
And if they have a rival power that's also challenging them, they see greater
internal conflict over wealth.
And then they have the problems internally and the problems externally, which usually
results in an internal war or an external war that leads to the change
in the, to the new world order.
And to you, the Dutch empire is a good example of that.
The British, what are some of the key examples that you think about in the book
of this process that follow the big cycle?
Well, the leading reserve currency empires, but it applies to all the empires,
were the, the Dutch, the British, the American and the Chinese.
But you could follow the same pattern.
In the book, it was very important for me to not just use words and concepts
because that's subjective.
It was very important for me to use actual measurements.
So as you see in the book, you can see every level of this.
You can see, where's the education level?
What is the military power, each one of those.
And you could see them back going over the 500 years.
And so you can see the arcs and the composition of those arcs.
And what you see is really in most countries and most dynasties, you can see that.
But you also can see through those numbers, the health of those countries.
Today, there are, there are statistics that you could, that are in the book that show
what is the level of education?
What is the level of economic output?
What is the level of military strength?
What is the level of a number of different measures of strength so that you can then compare that?
And I think that because they're objective measures of strength that you could see change,
that shows the picture of where we are today.
And I think one of the most important things about the book is that it allows people to monitor
how those things are transpiring.
I think for policymakers, you know, are your policymakers doing a good job?
And there's so much subjectivity in that.
But I think it's very simple.
If those lines on the chart are improving, if your health index is improving,
then you're moving toward a better life.
So that's what the book works like.
Also, it was used to create a model for the future.
In other words, there are cause-effect relationships.
Everything that happens has reasons, causes that preceded it, that made it happen.
And so by having all those in numbers, one can see the probabilities of certain things happening.
So that's what you see in the book.
It's not just, you know, raise interpretation.
I didn't want to make it raise interpretation because I don't know if I'm right.
Yeah.
So one of the fascinating things in the book, see, I've listed these 18 measures and there's
like a little scorecard for the countries of the world today.
So let's say US, China and Europe and what it was 20 years ago and looking at the change
from 20 years ago, and that's another indicator to change itself to see where things are headed.
Maybe can you comment on, from a score perspective, how is US and China doing?
And in the 18 measures, what are some measures that stand out to you as particularly important
to think about today for the United States, for China?
Well, there are a number.
Financially, what you see in the United States is that we're borrowing a lot more money,
creating a lot of debt, and we're printing a lot of money.
And our capacity to do that is very much is limited, first of all, because when you,
when there's a sale of a bond, when the government borrows more than it borrows money
because it spends more than it takes in, you have to sell a bond.
And the world right now has a lot of US dollar denominated bonds because as the world's reserve
currency, they sell, so on them, and they have very bad returns, negative real returns,
negative real returns significantly and so on.
So that means that more bonds has to be sold than are bought.
And that means that the Federal Reserve has, is faced with the choice of having to raise
the interest rate to curtail borrowing, which slows the economy and hurts the markets,
or by filling that difference and producing money, the debt monetization, which produces
an inflation in goods, services, and financial assets.
So in that regard, that's our, the United States' position.
In China's case, its balance of payments is better.
China has displaced the United States as the world's largest trading country,
in other words, more exports to other countries.
And as a result, it's economically competitive, but it doesn't have the world's reserve currency.
It's a real blessing.
So the United States, it has the world's reserve currency, but it is risking it because of this
imbalance. So if you look at history, you see that those go slowly, but when they go
eventually, they go quickly. So there's a risk of that financially.
Then there's the issue of internal order.
So I'm just giving you the major ones, but I'll get into some of the other ones too.
Right now, there's a lot of internal conflict in the United States,
which affects how well it works.
In China, there's less internal conflict because it's a more autocratic state,
but also they've created this bifurcation of what is political and what is economic
in terms of producing that prosperity. So if you stay out of the politics pretty much,
and then you're seeing entrepreneurship, you're seeing the finances of new businesses,
and so on. And so that internal working, that's subject to different people's interpretations,
whether they like it or not, but the internal conflict in terms of those kinds of measures
is less. Sorry to pause on that for a second.
So these measures, I guess you don't want to romanticize anyone measure or something like that,
overinterpret anyone measure, but is internal conflict always a bad thing? Is it a complicated
calculation, or do you kind of, the way we think about these measures that you've presented,
we should be thinking like the higher, the better, the lower, the worse, or of course,
depending on the... Well, in many cases, the conflict that produces the revolution
produces revolutionary changes that lead to resolutions and lead to new starts.
And so their short-term, a short-term civil war is a hellacious experience,
and at the same time, it can be the transition to a new beginning. Also, there are different types
of conflict. Competition, which makes everything better, is a productive conflict, whereas
destructive conflicts are not good over the short time. So that's how those go.
So within each measure, the story is complicated?
Yeah, but my measures are sort of clear, meaning how much political conflict, how much
social conflict. In other words, you can measure conflict, you can measure fighting,
you can measure crime rates, you can measure lots of different ways of conflict. So the measures
are a composite of different types of internal conflict.
What are some other interesting measures, maybe you can also mention that for me in particular,
interest is education and innovation. Yes. The classic cycle, the most important
leading indicator is the quality of education. Most importantly, broad-based education,
drawn from the largest population, because you can never tell who the talent is going to be,
where they're going to come from. So for example, if you look at the great Chinese
dynasties and the Confucian approach, it was meritocratic of everybody could sit for exams
and so on, broad base of drawing in the populations. And you see that if you go across societies,
because that draws on the largest number of population to get education. And that creates
a reality and a perception that the system is fairer, equal opportunity, not just one of privilege.
And that helps to create social stability. But education is not just education in understanding
facts and so on. It is education in civility of how to behave together. And so if they're smart,
they understand how to be productive, because they work well together and they're productive.
And then that leads to the next stage. You could see in the lines in the charts,
I plotted these, so that you could see in a typical cycle, you could see that education is the long
leading indicator. And then you could see, as you mentioned, that what you see is inventiveness
and technology measures then follow. And you see then also competitiveness and world markets
follows. For example, in the early stages of a cycle, the industries that they go into tend to
be very basic industry, because they have cheap labor, something like textiles and simple manufactured
goods and so on. But as the education rises, then they move up the value chain to greater
technologies and so on, which raises incomes and raises productivity. So yes, those, and as you say,
there are 18 different measures like that, but education and then civility and the inventiveness.
So you see it reflected in who's inventing what. And that corresponds then who's trading with,
who's a big trading country, and where's the value of economic output and what are per capita incomes.
They all follow those arcs. Yeah, like you said, the fascinating thing about your book,
so there's philosophy, there's wisdom, but there's plots. Yeah, you could see it.
So it's not just your opinion. It's kind of like you can interpret it in any way you like,
but you're just giving a lot of your own insights along with the numbers.
If you were to look at the American nation, the American empire, and the trajectories looking
into the future, given these measures, what is the trajectory that leads to the collapse of
the American empire based on these measures? What are the concerning indicators? And if
those break down further, what does that look like? Well, all of those indicators are concerning,
maybe except for one, which is technology, the technology niche, although even in that area
the United States is improving at a slower rate than is China for various advantages that they
have there. They put out about eight times as many computer engineers, they have free data,
and so on. But if you look at them, so the financial is a concern, the internal order,
disorder is a concern. Then if you look at education levels, the United States
is in many ways, is losing its educational advantage. If you were to look at, compare it with China,
if you take general public education in the United States, it's deteriorated tremendously,
even in comparison to developed countries. There are scores, pieces scores, and so on,
and it's something like 38th in the world or something, and that was a big plunge,
average public education. If you look at the best universities in the world,
the United States is unique in having the best universities in the world, so there are these
privileged spots that are excellent, uniquely excellent. So when you look at the comparison,
education in China is improving rapidly, and the quantity is a quantity of educated people
in the areas that they're moving in are, is greater, and the resources that they're putting
behind it is greater, and so you see the results are greater. But it's sort of a long line that
I'm dealing with. If you were to follow through in terms of actual productions, I think you know
in terms of technologies, there are some areas that the United States is in a lead. At the moment,
there's some areas that China's in a lead, but China's gaining very quickly. When I first went
to China, 1984, I would bring $10 calculators, and I gave them away as gifts to high-ranking people,
and they thought they were miracle devices. Right now, in terms of areas like quantum computing,
and AI, and you know, many areas, you have a race going on, and so if you take the trajectory
of the competitiveness, not just look at the current level, you have a situation where they're
improving at a much faster rate. This is all good for the world if the world can get along.
And the main thing I think is, in just how do you have a healthy world, and how do you have a
strong economy, and how do you have a strong situation, is be strong. The United States's
war is with itself. That's the main war. You know, it's very simple in history.
Be financially sound, earn more than you spend, and be strong in these ways, and pretty much
everything will take care of itself. But you make it sound simple, of course,
because there's a momentum when things degrade. When the education system degrades, when you
start borrowing, when, I mean, all of these indicators, once they start going down,
there's a momentum to it, right? So it's hard to reverse it.
Right, and there are circumstances that you're then in. For example, indebtedness,
you know, it's politically desirable for those to borrow money and spend, because their
constituencies only look at what they get. And when they get a lot, they don't pay attention
to the balance sheet and how much debt is on the books. So it's always better to borrow, spend,
and then leave the cleanup to the next guy. And so you inherit a lot. You inherit it as
a new president enters in, or new legislators. They have a lot of debt. They have a broken down
infrastructure. They don't have enough money to fix that. And so that's the lay of the land that
the prior generations put you in, and there you are. And so that's right. It's difficult,
because when you start to think, okay, what's healthy? Well, spend, earn more than you spend.
Well, that's not so easy, because, you know, what does that mean? Go earn more? I mean,
okay, that's not so easy. Spend less? That isn't going to work. So now what do you do? Okay,
you have this debt that you then monetize, and that's why it's classic. So yes, that's why these
cycles occur, because what has created before, what happened before created the lay of the land
that is then increasingly difficult to deal with. So what can great leaders do in this moment? I mean,
maybe my sense is leadership is crucial here. So for example, to do very large projects that
invest in the education system, that sort of try to fix the fundamentals, or maybe invest more and
more into the innovation and the development of new technologies and so on. It feels like that
just doesn't happen organically. So you have to have strong leaders that
convince the populace of the importance of these ideas.
Well, I completely agree with your list. What we have is a situation where everybody
has their opinions, and they have to sort of get them exactly right, and they all fight with
each other about whether their opinions. So the most important thing is that we become bipartisan
so that we don't, and we get over our differences. I would have a bipartisan cabinet. I would draw upon
both members of both parties, the moderates, who are going to be able to work together.
So as then we have one country, and then we deal with those in a means that works for the majority
of the people in the middle, rather than the polarity. I think our greatest risk is in not
being able to do that. So I would say that's a paramount importance because we have the resources,
wealth, real wealth, and science, and everything has never been better than it is.
But the notion is that it has to work for the majority of people, and we have to keep it
being productive. So that group has got to calmly and knowledgeably work together so that they
increase the size of the pie, and they create broad-based prosperity. So that is a paramount
importance. Whatever they do, if they do it that way, I can say I'm happy about because that other
alternative is the really scary alternative. The scary alternative, the different ways it has
evolved throughout history, some of it has led to wars. What are the future trajectories that
lead to a potential war with China? Cold war or hot war? Is this something you think about?
Is this something you're worried about? Yeah, I'd like to talk about both wars. So the war
with China, as I say, there are five kinds of wars. There's a trade war technology war,
geopolitical influence war, capital war, and military war. As far as military war goes,
I think it's only a Taiwan issue, but that's a big issue, and we could talk about that for a minute.
But those others, they'll be rough competitions, and we'll have that type of evolution over a
period of time. That's what that war looks like. Taiwan has been, for a long time,
a sovereignty issue to China, and it has its roots in what's called 100 years of humiliation.
From the 1840s to 1949, foreign powers came in, took advantage of China. They had the Opium
Wars in such times, and that represented the 100 years of humiliation. Taiwan represents
their sovereignty and their important thing. And 50 years ago, starting 50 years ago,
there was an agreement that there is one China, and Taiwan is part of China, and that there would be
peaceful reunification. The peaceful reunification hasn't happened, and in their view,
that's a very big issue. And so it's a big contentious issue, and that could produce a
military war, could produce a military accident, it's a very tense situation. And if we had a
military war, God help us because of the capacity in all different new ways to inflict harm on each
other. But anyway, that's that. If you don't have that military war, you'll have the competition
between those other kinds of wars, and whoever is strongest in those areas will win.
Where do you put cyber war within the five?
Well, cyber war is a military war. I'm assuming the type of cyber war that you're
referring to is that which it's used to inflict pain on the other party through cyber. So cyber wars,
you'll see cyber war, you could see space war, you can see drone warfare,
you, new types of warfare, not just the traditional and nuclear type of warfare,
but you could see any of the above.
What are the defining characteristics? What are the interesting things about
Xi Jinping, the president of China, as a leader on the world stage?
His father was a early leader. He was himself
in the Cultural Revolution in times, treated brutally. And during that period of time,
it was very, very difficult. And he came up through the ranks and is a very intelligent man.
When he first came to power, as you know, they have two five-year terms, and we're now coming to
the end of the second of those five-year terms. When he first came to power, he felt that there
should be a lot of reform, and reform meant moving to much more of a market and open economy.
When that happened in him coming in, I had some contact with economic policymakers, but in the
circumstances then, were that five major banks lent to state-owned enterprises and local governments
with implied government guarantees. And so there was not control of that and the movement to aim
more of a market economy. And the development of markets was a primary. And also the dealing
with the corruption issue. There was a lot of corruption prior to that, and that was viewed
as an existential threat to the system. So that became the primary objective. And then as time
progressed over those 10 years, there was a lot of changing in the world, their financial
circumstances, opening many, many other markets. They particularly getting money to small and
medium-sized enterprises and developing a lending system and then establishing controls on it.
So right now, there's a vibrant capital markets. You can raise capital, you can be an entrepreneur,
you can become a billionaire in the capital markets. And they developed the markets to be
the second largest capital markets. At the same time, they had to deal with their rising debt issue,
which they began to deal with really about four years ago, when the second term began.
And then Lou Ha became the vice premier responsible for that and to deal with those issues. So
you see right now that what's happening is the dealing with the real estate bubble.
There was a development in real estate, a bubble, which produced a lot of unproductive lending.
And Xi Jinping said, houses are meant to live in, not to speculate on. And so that was wasteful.
So they established what they call three red lines, which are financial ratios,
that the property developers had to live within. And that is then causing the adjustments that are
going on now, which in my view are very healthy because whenever there's bankruptcies and so on,
the most in the public think, okay, that's a problem. It's in many cases really a cleaning
up of bad debts and bad practices. And so that's what's going on. So that's, let's say economically.
At the same time, there is the changing relationships, the changing world order,
the changing relationships with the United States and other countries, which is becoming
much less cooperative and much more warlike, much more confrontational. Those two things,
the domestic debt problem and the domestic has led to what's called core, what they call core
leadership, which means a leadership more around him that is less challenging because they believe
in history that during very difficult times, a more centrally controlled decision making process
lends itself better than to a more fragmented political contentious project. And that's basically
what's going on now. You said it very eloquently, but you mean the leadership is surrounded by yes men
and there's a lot of centralized control. That characterization is much more black and white
than it really is. But it leans towards that direction.
Like, for example, of the standing members of the Politburo, four are more alleged,
allowed him, three are less so. You have to understand that it's kind of a collective
leadership at the top. And then, of course, there's just jockeying for power in a highly
political sense at the top. But no one leader can be successful against all those powers at
the top. So it's very politically negotiating. It's very much more like, if you put in the
United States, the Democrats and the Republicans, and they had to be in the same government and
they work it out, it's kind of something like that. And so that's that struggle, but it's an
internal struggle. Where do you put the importance of some of these ideas at the founding of the
United States when then, now we're talking about that at the context of China, the freedom of
speech freedoms. What China is doing with the central management of a lot of things, it's
enabling a lot of growth, but it's also limiting people on the very basic level in terms of freedom,
the kind of freedom that I think can lead to entrepreneurship, to starting new businesses,
to having big dreams and chasing those dreams, and then creating totally new things in whatever
the space, maybe in technology, in business and whatever. How important is that as a metric for
society? Well, they have a view which is the idea of a dialectic, which means that two things are
that everything comes with pros and cons, and two opposites exist. And you want the benefits of
those two opposites, and how do you deal with the benefits of those two opposites? So let's say
you want the capital markets because it gets money into the hands of the entrepreneurs who are
motivated, they build fortunes, and that drives an economy to do very well. And at the same time,
it produces the other problems, the wealth gaps, the other problems, then the debt cycle that we're
talking about and so on. And Deng Xiaoping, how do you reconcile communism and the market economy
and the capital markets? And he famously said, and it doesn't matter if it's a white cat or a
black cat, just as long as it catches mice. In other words, if it works in making the country richer,
then that becomes the objective, and then they move that along. So there are these conflicts,
and one of the leaders described it to me as follows, because it's confusion and it goes back
over a period of time. There's a hierarchy, and it's an extension of the family he described it.
And he said, the United States is a country of individuals and individualism,
and that is its vibrancy that we see. The individual rights to speak up, the individual
protection of the individual, individual property rights, and all of those things
is of paramount importance. And we build our organization. That's why democracy is from the
bottom up, or even a company will get together and we'll be partners to prosper together. That
is the American approach. He was describing that in China, it's an extension of the Confucian family,
essentially. And so it's almost like there's a hierarchy. And so what they think about is
the common good, not the individualism. So for example, if they want a high-speed rail to go
from one place to another, and that's best in the common good, then the individual protections that
would stand in the way of doing that would be of secondary concern. So that notion of controlling.
So for example, what they're doing with video games, they control what type of video games
and how many hours a day kids can be on video games operating in that way, because they believe
that that's good for the society and that's very controlling. In the United States, I think probably
most parents would say, leave it to me, and it's a matter between me and my kids. The same thing
has to do with data. In other words, in the United States, who controls the data? Does the company
control the data? Do you individually control the data? And so the inclination would be to figure
that out, but nobody would say that the government is going to control the data because of our
inclination of really anti-government control. In China, it would be that the government will
control the data because that's going to be best for the society and it depends who you trust.
So that difference in philosophy is very much at the heart of that. As far as your question in terms
of effectiveness, it really is, in China's case, it's how you balance the things. So what they're
attempting to do is to create a lot of freedom and creativity in areas that are not political, let's
say. And so you see a lot of entrepreneurship, you see a lot of product development, you see a lot
of creativity happening in that way. So the stereotype that you don't see creativity happening
is an old stereotype. There's a lot of creativity certainly happening and the system can work well
if they can achieve that kind of balance. It's proven to work well. Since I started going there
in 1984, real per capita income has increased by 26 times. The longevity rate has increased by 10
years. The poverty rate has fallen from 88% to less than 1% in terms of basics like starvation
and things. And if you read history, Plato's Republic, he talks about the cycles, democracy
and autocratic and the benevolent despot and all of that. Each has their own vulnerability. The
vulnerability of democracy, which has been a remarkable, remarkable system and I don't have
to extol the benefits of it. But the vulnerability of it has always been the internal conflict that
produces itself as anarchy. In World War II, four democracies chose to be autocracies
because there was internal disorder and there was the belief will somebody bring about order
and get control of the situation. That was in Germany, Italy, Japan and Spain.
They were parliamentary systems that turned themselves over to that. So, both systems
have vulnerabilities. I think the main thing that we need to think about is those vulnerabilities.
Democracy is an amazing system because the adherence to the rules and the system
and the checks and balances is quite amazing and it gives it a flexibility to change without
civil wars. But there has to be the respect of the rules. And when you see something like
they will not accept elections or they will not accept rules, history has shown when the causes
that people are behind are more important to them than the system. The system is in jeopardy.
So, we have a situation that's very much like that in terms of, let's say, the 2024 elections.
I believe that there's a very high chance that neither side will accept losing, for example.
And so, we have that kind of a situation. So, one would hope that one could rise above the
disagreements and rely on the system for resolving disagreements because if that doesn't happen,
then we have our own chaos. So, the kind of the trend that started in 2020,
or I suppose it's been growing. One representation of this internal disorder has been
the growing trend of being skeptical about the results of the election.
Well, it started before that. There was the emergence of population
before President Trump was elected. He was basically elected as a populist because there
was a large percentage of the population that felt that the system didn't work for them,
and he tapped into that, and he was largely elected as a populist leader, first populist leader
in a developed country. And so, populism began then, and that was a battle of one group against
the other group. And so, since then, it's been like that, and it continued to grow.
You've mentioned the vulnerability of democracy, the internal disorder is the
vulnerability of democracy. What's the vulnerability of a system like China? Maybe one way to
say is put China aside and look at history, look at Soviet Union.
What's the vulnerability of a communist-type system?
Well, I'll call it both communist and autocratic, depending on how much autocracy,
is that it lacks flexibility. It lacks the ability, but I should deal with them differently.
In other words, there's the economic system. The economic system threatens motivation
and productivity. So, communism or socialism has to be done in a way where you can threaten
productivity. Capitalism has, and what I mean by that, I mean free markets and capital markets.
I've been an effective way of allocating resources and also creating the incentives
and the resources, providing the resources for the inventiveness of new ideas. And so,
if I compare that, what the Chinese have done, to a large extent, is to recognize that and have made
a move, that's why the seeming dialectic or the conflict between those two things exist. But
anyway, that's it. As far as an autocratic system, rather than one man, one vote from the population
up, the risks of the autocratic system is that there's enough discontent that arises,
that the system doesn't have the flexibility, and that rather than bending, it breaks.
That's the big risk. The notion of trying to control a population, if there's that, rather
than giving it the flexibility. So, that would be the big risk of the autocratic system.
What's the human, because you mentioned like the top gets bigger with the empires,
and you start taking things for granted, is some of this just human nature. So, the concern with
China, with autocratic nations, the concern with the Third Reich, the Soviet Union, was that
fundamentally, at the individual level, the humans involved at the top, they start becoming,
they're starting to lose touch with the reality, in a way that no longer makes them. I guess that's
the representation of the flexibility that you're referring to. Well, I mean, in a democracy,
you could change. You can go as far left or as far right. You can change the leaders easily,
and so the people don't become, they pretty much only have themselves to blame.
One of the problems of that is they may not choose the best leaders, but they have that
flexibility. So, vote and you get what you wanted. In the case of the autocratic, let's say, leaders,
and then the movement from democracies to autocracies, what you see normally, that movement,
is that one of the systems is not working. Let's say the democracy is not effectively. Everybody's
arguing with each other, and nobody's getting anything done, and you know, like Mussolini,
the trains are not running on time, and that would be the example. Geez, this place has gotten
chaotic. Well, somebody gets to control, and then you get the autocratic, and then he's
autocratic enough to boss people around, and then you follow those kinds of orders, and it's like
maybe a CEO in a powerful company ordering around, and that could work well or it could work badly.
Most companies are run as like autocracies, in a sense. There's the hierarchy and the command
economy and that kind of thing, and that can work well or not, but then quite often when you get the
populist autocratic, their personality is something that they want to fight, and they become more
nationalistic, and they tend to become more militaristic, and human nature at that stage
lends itself to fighting. There's an arc here that when we think of a country,
and we say we, and we think of a country, it's not true, it's not like that. There are individuals
who change. One generation dies, and another generation comes along, and one of those arcs
is that the ones who have been through war don't want to go to war and are more happily willing to
abide by whatever the rules are. As you get farther along into that cycle, and you get a new
generation, and they forget about wars and the horrors of wars, then they want to fight,
and so you're seeing right now the emerging of fight for right, and what that means is you see
it internally. Fight, where are you in fight for that thing, and they mean fight, and then
externally, fight, are you going to be the strong one who will fight and win,
and that develops on both sides, this fight and win, and they side is cheering each other on
into a war, but that comes by those who really have not experienced war because it comes
in their part of their lifetime. Humans are fascinating.
Humans are fascinating, and by the way, human nature has not changed over the thousands of years,
so it's so interesting because like in doing this study, and it comes across in the study,
it's like watching the same movie over and over again. You see the arc, and you see it happen
over and over again. The only things that seem to change are the clothes people wear and the
technologies they use. Yeah, and then somebody probably will disagree with you about the clothes,
maybe there's also cycles within fashions. Maybe we're not even creative there. What do you
make of Russia and Vladimir Putin? What do you think about Putin as a leader,
as a human being on this world stage, within the context of the cycles of empires that you think about?
Well, Putin came to power at the failure of Russia's last order, so there was the end of
communism, and there was the development of the market economy, the collapse of the Soviet Union,
and at that time, he was appointed by Yeltsin who was an alcoholic and had problems
managing and was put into power. The conditions in the Russian, there was anarchy,
there was no money. It had the classic end of cycle ingredients. It was broke,
it was people fighting with each other, it was the anarchy, and that's when he came to power.
And there were not institutions, the whole thing had collapsed. It was not effective ministry of
education, ministry of anything. And so the idea was that they needed 25 years of stability,
and they needed a democracy, and they needed the improvement of capital markets.
So he's been in that position as a, I guess I would call him a semi-autocratic leader in that,
from all indications, he would respect the democracy, and he's very popular. He's won
democratic elections because he's been a strong leader, and he's brought peace and stability
to Russia after the breakup of the Soviet Union. And he's a strong leader in pursuit of
the country's interests in a way where Russia is not a significant economic power,
but it is a significant military power. So the issues, and then there's a strong alliance between
Russia and China now. So that's kind of the lay of the land. And then there are sensitivities. The
Ukraine issue is a sensitivity because there are a lot of Russians who live in the Ukraine,
and there's also the issue of NATO on their border. So there are those kinds of things,
and he has military power, and he has a strong alliance with China. And I guess that's my best
summary of what his position is. Strong leader, popular. These are not subjective interpretations.
These are objective interpretations. Yeah, it's interesting. Just in this conversation,
you're not sort of doing the usual criticism of any one particular system. You're looking
at these systems from the perspective of history. You're just describing how they work. It's often
times when you talk about what Russia is today, or what the Soviet Union was, or what China is
today, is you start to criticize. Well, they do this kind of censorship, or they do this kind
of they limit freedoms in this kind of way. But you're just kind of describing this as a nation
with ideas, what they think is right. This is how they hope to get it to work. This is why
it's working. This is what's not working. Here's metrics that show that it's not working. I think
that's a refreshing way to think about it. It's easy though. I mean, you got some criticism
saying that I think China is a strict parent.
You know, some people criticize these countries for violating human rights. I suppose there's some
people that criticize the United States for violating human rights. But what are your thoughts
on the world stage today about some of the behaviors it has governed in terms of respecting
the rights, the basic rights of human beings? You described accurately how I just tried to look
at things in a non, I don't want to impute my values on anybody. I mean, there are intolerable
things, so I'm not saying there aren't intolerable things. But one of the great things of being an
American here is that I grew up with all different nationalities, having all different points of
view and all different religions and all different ways of operating. And I've come to treasure the
fact that what's their business is their business. And then the question is, where do you cross the
line under what circumstances that others have got to do it my way? And then when you do it
internationally, the issue of what is a sovereign state, you know, which as I say in the piece of
Westphalia, and you have borders, and then when do you cross the line, that my way of doing things
has got to be their way of doing things or what are the various rights? And so that's a very
delicate question or a very difficult question. And we all have responsibilities to different
parties, and we all have different levels of knowledge about those particular things. So
for example, as an international investor, I have a responsibility to my investors.
Those who run companies have a responsibility to theirs of how do they run that. So if you're
taking Nike or Sinkers and so on, and Americans can decide whether they want to buy Chinese products
or not buy Chinese products, we are all faced with those types of choices. So you have what do
you want to do in your constituency, and you have your choices. And then beyond that, in many cases,
the issues are quite complex, like there are geopolitical questions that enter into it. So
and then I believe that if you disconnect it, if all those
if entities like myself, the businesses doing business with China disconnected,
I think that that would be disastrous, economically disastrous. And it would also be
reduce the understanding that comes from working together that helps to reduce wars.
And so these are all complicated. So what we do is and who makes it my opinion matters the most.
Why should it be my opinion that matters the most in making that decision? So I largely look at
the government guidance that I get not only from my own government, but from the other governments.
And I follow the rules. I'm in 40, we invest in 40 countries. And we want to do that in the best
way to provide the diversified portfolio. And we sort of need that. Every one of those countries
has similar complexities. There are always one issue or another. And there's only so much
that we really understand about all of those issues. So we rely largely on the guidance that we get.
Yeah, you have to empathize and show respect to the culture, the place, the way things are done.
You don't necessarily, the way you heal relationships between nations is like you said,
you work together. And that requires kind of to listen maybe more than you talk. And I think people
in the public sphere talk a lot about China without really listening, without understanding much
about China, without one of the things that makes me really sad because I know how to speak Russian
and I can, I know how much is lost in translation. It makes me sad that I'll never really get to
know the Chinese culture because like I'll never really get to know the language, the literature,
the just talk to regular people. It's not just the government or officials or scientists,
just regular folks get the culture. I think if you don't understand the culture,
just the basics of the human nature of what people love about their country, about their
family, what the kind of hopes they have, what kind of values they have without that,
you're not going to be able to fully connect with them. And you have to do that first,
to have a chance of building a good world. I couldn't agree with you more. I was very lucky
because as I say, since 1984, so for more than half of my life, I've been going there and the
common people and all sorts of people and I've got to meet them. I don't speak the language,
but a combination of through translators or them speaking English and being in situations,
I had my son go to school, a local school and we developed those kinds of understandings.
I think that but the not wanting to know the other perspective is the thing that's most
scary. Like I'm right now in the middle and all I want to try to do is to help a mutual understanding.
You're right. If there were questions probing me, asking me, what is it? I'm not on one side
or another. I don't want to be on one side or another. I believe that each has their right
within there to approach their different culture in their own way. So many ways you gave an example.
If they're not doing harm to others, but that issue of trying to understand is so much better.
That doesn't mean agree with. If you are wanting to out-clever and out-compete somebody, it still
pays to understand what they're thinking. So to achieve understanding of what they're thinking,
even if you want to go to war with them, that understanding is the best thing to have.
What we have now is a situation in which there's an enemy mentality. That means that anything
that seems to be like understanding or conveying understanding seems to mistakenly create the
notion of I'm on their side in a war. That's a dangerous thing because there's a momentum here
to fight. Henry Kissinger praises your new book and you thank him in it in the dedication.
What's your relationship like with him? What makes him interesting? Maybe what makes him
controversial? What makes him such a central figure in history? First, most importantly,
he's unique about seeing things through all the other's eyes.
It's like there's a chess game. I think geopolitics is like a chess game, but with
multiple chess players playing the same game. So imagine there are six people around playing
the chess game and he could sit in each seat and he could know how they see it
and see it in a calm way of how they see it. He's unique in that way. He's 98 years old
and he's equally able to do that. He has a background in which he's a historian, so he
really understands history super terrifically. He doesn't understand economic history as much,
so that's why, to some extent, we enjoy having a conversation because he's interested in the
economic piece he doesn't know and I'm so interested in the geopolitical piece that I
don't know as well. But anyway, he's able to do that, but not only a historian, but a practitioner.
So when you go from an academic to a practitioner who has that talent to see things through other's
eyes in an objective way and to be strategic rather than just tactical, that's a very special
person and that's why Henry is, to me, a very special person. Yeah, he's lived a fascinating
life. Just all of the world events he's been involved in is fascinating and, like you said,
that's such an interesting skill to have to consider what are the concerns, the hope, the dreams,
the fears of all the people at the table. What are they thinking? I find that people don't,
once again, don't do that enough when it's the obvious thing you should be doing, whether it's
business deals or political negotiation or geopolitical negotiation. I'm often surprised
again, sorry, to go to the Russian thing because I hear Putin talk in Russian and you start to
infer certain intentions, not the trivial stuff, like the human being. What is that human being
hoping for himself, for his country, for his close in a circle, for the bigger,
and I just see that that's often just lost in translation. I just see American leaders
talking to Putin and there's not a connection. Absolutely. I know exactly what you're talking
about. It has never failed that in my listening to a conversation or even reading a speech
or, and you see then it reported. Inevitably, the reporter picks some
headline characterization that has very little to do with what was really happening,
but might be a headline grabber that's at some kind of distortion and there's a lack of understanding
of really what's going on. If it's okay, let me ask you a couple of questions about cryptocurrency.
You've had a few opinions about Bitcoin over the years. What are your thoughts about Bitcoin today?
Its role in the global financial system and just in human society in general?
Well, the evolution of Bitcoin over the years is one of the things that has
influenced changes in my view. It has proven itself. Something like 10, 11 years ago, imagine
the programming of this and here's the, you throw it out and that's the idea. It has not been hacked.
It has operated, it has built, it has come an amazing way over that 11 years to be
maybe probably the most excited topic among a lot of people and has been used and is now
has obtained the status of having imputed value. At the same time, it is one of those assets
that is an alternative money. I think we're entering an era where there's going to be a
competition of monies because of the printing of fiat money and the depreciated value. There will
be a competition of monies and Bitcoin is part of that competition, but there'll be many monies,
not just crypto monies, but there'll be central bank crypto monies, but there'll be different
kinds of monies. Even monies are things that you buy and sell. NFTs can become a money,
a type of money. You own it and it's an investment and you could say, I'd rather own it than own
Bitcoin. Has Ray Dalio bought any NFTs? Not yet.
But only just because I definitely want to buy NFTs to just experience them. I think I should
produce one. I should have asked that. Have you minted an NFT? You probably should just to know
what it's like. Yeah, that's right. This stuff is happening. This stuff is real and how it operates,
but like all new real things, some are going to go and it's like in the internet in the year 2000,
pets.com could have been a great, but maybe pets.com doesn't make it and who knows. That's
the beauty of the competitive system that it'll evolve and some things will be treasured and some
things will be trashed. But when I look at it, I think we are in an environment of what is an
alternative money. Money has two purposes, a medium of exchange and a storehold of wealth.
We are looking for and it's portable and it's best if it's recognized in other countries.
Gold is one of those. I look at it as an alternative gold, but I look at a number of things as an
alternative gold. Gold is still my favorite because of certain qualities. For example,
you can't trace it. In Bitcoin, you can trace who owns it, where it's going and so on. Governments
can have that ability to trace it and so on. A gold piece of coin, it's not connected.
I think not connected has benefits, particularly in a world where maybe connections can be more
risky. Gold has been, for many thousands of years, universally recognized as a source of money
and central banks. It's the third largest source of money in central bank reserves.
I don't think Bitcoin is going to serve those types of purposes and so on. For various reasons,
I prefer gold to the other, but it's a little bit part of my mix.
But then you look at it, it hit I think 69,000 this year is the high Bitcoin hit. Do you think
it's possible? You mentioned gold. Do you think it's possible it reaches very high numbers like
one million that some people talk about? I don't think that's possible because the way I look at it
is there's a certain amount of it and there's a certain amount of gold. I'll use gold as a benchmark.
The amount of it is worth about $1 trillion. Total crypto is about $2.2 trillion,
but let's say Bitcoin. It's $1 trillion. If you take the amount of money that is in
gold that is not used for jewelry purposes and not used by central banks, and I assume
Bitcoin won't be used for jewelry purposes or central bank purposes, that amount in gold is
about $5 trillion. Right now, if you were to have a portfolio that has gold and crypto,
gold and Bitcoin, it's worth about 20% of the value of gold. Do I think it's going to be
worth more than gold in terms of that mix? I don't think it'll be worth more than gold,
but let's say it became worth as much as gold. I don't believe it will be. I think the 20%
sounds kind of about right. I really don't know what the right answer is. Then there's the question
of what is all of that pool of money that let's say gold and gold equivalents relative to everything
else. Does it go from let's call it $6, $7, $8 trillion to $16 trillion? Maybe it could double.
It depends what it is in the world environment, but basically, if you use gold as a measure,
it just makes no sense that it's going to be used that much more. Am I sure about that?
I'm not sure about anything, but logically, it seems to me that there's a limitation on its price
in relationship to other things that are like it.
Let me ask for your deep financial analysis on a very important issue. I just talked a couple
days ago with Elon Musk. He wants to put a literal Dogecoin on the moon. What are your
thoughts about Dogecoin? Do you think it'll be the official currency? Maybe reserve currency on
the moon and on Mars? My reaction is, that's cute. I remember Elon when he first got his money from
PayPal. I think he said to me, he got $180 million, $90 million. He decided to say,
why aren't we going to outer space? He wanted to take a spaceship that would be modified
using Russian technology to put a plant and a watering can on the moon or on Mars, I think it
was. He said, first life on Mars or first life on that as an inspiring notion. Then,
there's always what's behind it. I have a lot of respect for Elon's ability to do other things
behind it. I would take that as symbolic and I'd be asking him, what's behind it? What's next?
I'm also just on the topic of Dogecoin and Memecoin. There's some aspect of humor and
lightheartedness that's really interesting about the way we communicate, what ideas become viral,
how to captivate people with ideas. There's something about taking things too seriously
that somehow slows it all down. It's interesting. You're right. That's part of human nature
somehow. Humor is part of this whole thing. You've talked about the importance of writing ideas down
and you have- Principles in particular. Principles. You have this really nice thing in your book where
you actually, I think there's such a brilliant way of highlighting which parts are extra important
and you make them bold. That's a brilliant idea. Let me just ask the high level question of what's
a good system for taking notes? Well, I find that almost everything happens over and over again.
We're in the blizzard of these things happening. What I found is that if I'm making a decision
that after I make the decision usually or right at the time, if I pause and reflect and I write my
principle down, in other words, principle is sort of a recipe, how would I make that decision
and what are the criteria around it? I find that I make it much more clear. It becomes clear
and it applies to the next thing that comes along. It'll be that way because everything
happens over and over and over again. I think people make the mistake of looking at just the
one like it's the first one. I don't know. They have the first problem of this sort of the first
child or whatever it is. This has been happening plenty of times. If you have the principles,
I found that that helped me think more clearly about it and it helped me communicate better
like why. Over the years, over the last 30 years or so, that's what I've done. I did it originally
to communicate very well with the people I work with. I set up my company and it was very important
to have good communication. Then we could debate the principles. That's the process.
I urge people to do that. There are many excellent decision makers and I just wish that
they wrote down their principles when this set. For example, we're talking about Henry Kissinger
and his new book is going to come out with a book on leadership. Don't just describe the leaders.
Describe then what about them were the essential elements to make a good leader under what
circumstances. If we think about that, then you begin to think in a principled way. Then
when you start to think in a principled way, life becomes so much easier to make decisions and it's
so much less confusing because it's like coming up on a species and you say, okay, well, what
species is it? Not just another, it's a thing. What species is it and how do I deal with that
species effectively? That's what that is. I encourage people to write it down. I wish
anybody who's successful wrote down their principles or their recipes for making those
types of decisions. The events of interest here happens over and over and over in similar ways.
As you're looking for the patterns and you're defining the process, that's right to respond
to those patterns and you call that the principles. That allows you to deal with the
future effectively. That codifies the lessons from the past to be able to deal with the future.
What advice do you have for young folks today in high school, in college, thinking about how to live,
have a career they can be proud of or maybe have a life they can be proud of?
Know yourself, follow your passion. Make your work and passion the same thing
while considering the money part because money will get you freedom and choice and be able to
beg that. If you know yourself, feel the pull and pursue that passion. Along those lines,
by the way, I found that using personality profile tests has been very helpful. I've used
those for about 25 years for people to help to understand themselves and understand each other.
I created a free one that is called Principles You. It's online. It's had remarkable,
loving people who've taken it learn about themselves, but also you can put in somebody else
and it'll tell you about your relationship with them. That's like 30 minutes is a quick discovery,
but the main thing is to understand on your journey, your hero's journey,
that you will have mistakes and you will have weaknesses and to understand those,
not fight those because by understanding mistakes, you will learn not to make mistakes again.
I have a principle which is pain plus reflection equals progress. That reflection is important to
know yourself, know your pulls, know your weaknesses. When you also know your weaknesses and the
strengths of other people, there are people who have strengths where you're weak and you have
strengths where they're weak. To be able to work well together is the most effective way of
achieving success. It's that journey and there's a life arc and there's a journey and you want to
make it the best that you can make it. It's like a video game. It has the challenges and the
obstacles and the learning experiences and the temptations and all of that. The maximizing
learning to go where you want to go to achieve the life you want is the most important. That's
kind of maybe a long-winded way of seeing it. I'll try to say it simply. There's a five-step
process. Step one is know your goals. Know what you're going after. You could have almost anything
you want, but you can't have everything you want. You have to prioritize and you move in
that direction. On the way to your goals, you're going to encounter your problems and your obstacles.
Step two is understanding your problems and your obstacles. Identify them. Step three
is to diagnose them to get at the root cause of the problem. That could be many root causes,
but it could also be your weaknesses or weaknesses of others, but you have to be objective about them.
Once you diagnose them, then you go to step four, which is to design a way to get around them.
Then, after you have that design, you implement that design. You have to follow through and do it.
That will then produce its new results, which should be better results. I call this the looping
process. It's the evolutionary looping process. You just keep doing that and you learn over a
period of time and you move in the direction that you want. Last question, and you only have one
minute to answer it. You dedicate the book, quote, to my grandchildren and those of their generation,
who will be participants in the continuation of the story. May the force of evolution be with you.
Let me ask, where is this force of evolution taking human civilization and what in this story
that evolution is writing gives you hope? Evolution is a direction toward improvement.
The greatest force is man's capacity to adapt and invent. You see in the charts in the book,
you see that this upward movement, life expectancy, health, all the things that we
think are better, there's a chart and it shows that over a period of time. You barely see
the downturns from depressions and wars in that. That is the greatest power. Man's ability to
invent and adapt is evolution and that's the greatest power and that is what
gives me justifiable hope. A continuation of that, like we mentioned with Elon,
maybe we'll become a multi-planetary species. Not only will we keep creating amazing things here
on earth, we'll keep expanding out into the cosmos. My time horizon isn't going to have me
analyzing that yet, but I hope so and I agree that that would be in the natural.
So I'm not going to ask you for the best financial system on Mars. I think we'll
focus on earth for now. Thank you so much for your brilliance, for the books you've written,
for the works you've done, for the inspiration of millions. And thank you for spending your valuable
time here with me today. Thank you. Thanks for listening to this conversation with Ray Dalio.
To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now, let me leave you with some words from Ray Dalio himself. Every time you confront something
painful, you are at a potentially important juncture in your life. You have the opportunity
to choose healthy and painful truth or unhealthy but comfortable delusion.
Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.