slaves produces surplus which the master gets, serfs produces surplus which the lord gets,
employees produces surplus which the employer gets. It's very simple. These are exploitative
class structures because one class produces a surplus appropriated, distributed by another
group of people, not the ones who produced it, which creates hostility, enmity, envy, anger,
resentment, and all of the problems you can lump under the heading class struggle.
The following is a conversation with Richard Wolff. One of the top Marxist economists and
philosophers in the world. This is a heavy topic in general and for me personally given my family
history in the Soviet Union, in Russia, and in Ukraine. Today the words Marxism, Socialism,
and Communism are used to attack and to divide much more than to understand and to learn.
With this podcast I seek the latter. I believe we need to study the ideas of Karl Marx as well as
their various implementations throughout the 20th and the 21st centuries and in general we need to
both steal man and to consider seriously the ideas we demonize and to challenge the ideas we
dogmatically accept as true, even when doing so is unpleasant and at times dangerous.
This is the Lex Friedman podcast. To support it, please check out our sponsors in the description
and now dear friends, here's Richard Wolff. Let's start with a basic question but maybe not so basic
after all. What is Marxism? What are the defining characteristics of Marxism as an economic and
political theory and ideology? Well the simplest way to begin the definition would be to say it's
the tradition that takes its founding inspiration from the works of Karl Marx. But because these
ideas that he put forward spread as fast as they did and as globally as they did, literally it's
140 years since Marx died and in that time his ideas have become major types of thinking
in every country on the earth. If you know much about the great ideas of human history,
that's an extraordinary spread in an extraordinarily short period of historical time.
And what that has meant, that speed of spread and that geographic diversity,
is that the Marxian ideas interacted with very different cultural histories, religious histories
and economic conditions. So the end result was that the ideas were interpreted differently
in different places at different times and therefore Marxism as a kind of first flush
definition is the totality of all of these very different ways of coming to terms with it. For
the first roughly 40-50 years Marxism was a tradition of thinking critically about capitalism.
Marx himself, that's all he really did. He never wrote a book about communism,
he never wrote a book really about socialism either. His comments were occasional, fragmentary,
dispersed. What he was really interested in was a critical analysis of capitalism
and that's what Marxism was more or less in its first 40 or 50 years.
The only qualification of what I just said was something that happened in Paris for a few weeks.
In 1871 there was a collapse of the French government, consequent upon losing a war to
Bismarck's Germany and in the result was something called the Paris Commune. The working class of
Paris rose up, basically took over the function of running the Parisian economy and the Parisian
society and Marx's people, people influenced by Marx were very active in that commune and the
leadership of the commune and Marx wasn't that far away. He was in London, these things were
happening in Paris, you know, that's an easy transport even then and for a short time, very
short, Marxism had a different quality. In addition to being a critique of capitalism, it became
a theory of how to organize society differently. Before that had only been implicit, now it became
explicit what is the leadership of the Paris Commune going to do and why and in what order,
and in other words governing, organizing a society. But since it only lasted a few weeks,
the French army regrouped and under the leadership of people who were very opposed to Marx,
they marched back into Paris, took over, killed a large number of the of the communards as they
were called and deported them to islands in the Pacific that were part of the French empire at the
time. The really big change happens in Russia in 1917. Now you have a group of Marxists,
Lenin Trotsky, all the rest, who are in this bizarre position to seize a moment. Once again,
a war, like in France, disorganizes the government, throws the government into a very bad reputation
because it is the government that loses World War I, has to withdraw, as you know,
Brest-Litovsky and all of that, and the government collapses and the army revolts. And in that
situation, a very small political party, Russian Social Democratic Workers' Party, splits under
the pressures of all of this into the Bolshevik and Menshevik divisions. Lenin Trotsky and the
others are in the Bolshevik division. And to make a long story short, he's in exile. His position,
Lenin's position, gets him deported because he says Russian workers should not be killing
German workers. I mean, this is a war of capitalists who are dividing the world up into colonies and
Russian working people should not kill and should not die for such a thing. As you can expect,
they arrest him and they throw him out. Interestingly, in the United States, the comparable leader
at that time of the Socialist Party here, as you know, there was no Communist Party at this point,
that comes later, the head of the Socialist Party, a very important American figure named Eugene
Victor Debs, makes exactly the same argument to the Americans should not fight in the war.
He has nothing to do with Lenin. I don't even know if they knew of each other, but he does it
on his own. He gets arrested and put in jail here in the United States. By the way, he runs for
president from jail and does very well. Really, very well, remarkable. And he's the inspiration
for Bernie Sanders, if you see the link, although he had much more courage politically than Bernie
has. That's really interesting. I'd love to return to that link maybe later. History rhymes.
Yes, the complicated story. Anyway, the importance in terms of Marxism is that now
this seizure of power by a group of Marxists, that is a group of people inspired by Marx,
developing what you might call a Russian, even though there were differences among the Russians
too, but a Russian interpretation, this now has to be transformed from a critique of capitalism
into a plan at least. What are you going to do in the Soviet Union? A lot of this was then trial
and error. Marx never laid any of this out. Probably wouldn't have been all that relevant
if he had, because it was 50 years earlier in another country, etc. What begins to happen,
and you can see how this happens then more later in China and Cuba and Vietnam and Korea and so on,
is that you have kind of a bifurcation. Much of Marxism remains chiefly the critique of
capitalism, but another part of it becomes a set, and they differ from one to the other,
a set of notions of what an alternative post-capitalist society ought to look like,
how it ought to work, and there's lots of disagreement about it, lots of confusion,
and I would say that that's still where it is, that you have a tradition now
that has these two major wings, critique of capitalism, notion of the alternative,
and then a variety of each of those, and that would be the framework in which I would answer,
that's what Marxism is about. Its basic idea, if you had to have one, is that human society
can do better than capitalism, and it ought to try.
And then we can start to talk about what we mean by capitalism.
Fine. So we'll look at the critique of capitalism on one side, but maybe stepping back,
what do you think Marx would say if he just looked at the different implementations of the ideas
of Marxism throughout the 20th century, where his ideas that were implicit were made explicit?
Would he shake his head? Would he enjoy some of the parts of the implementations?
Like, how do you think he would analyze it? Well, he had a great sense of humor. I don't know if
you've had a chance to take a look at his writing, but he had an extraordinary sense of humor. So
my guess is he would deploy his humor in answering this question, too. He would say some of them are
inspiring, some of the interpretations of his work, and he's very pleased with those.
Others are horrifying, and he wishes somehow he could erase the connection between those things,
and the lineage they claim from him, which he would, there's a German word, I don't know if
he's like, if you speak the other languages, there's a wonderful German word called Verzichter,
and it's stronger than the word refuse. It's if you want to refuse something,
but with real strong emphasis. Verzichter is a German way of saying, I don't want to do that.
And he would talk then, you know, in philosophical terms, because remember,
he was a student of philosophy. He wrote his doctoral thesis on ancient Greek philosophy
and all the rest. He would wax philosophical and say, you know, that the ideas you put out are a
little bit like having a child. You have a lot of influence, but the child is his own or her own
person and will find his or her own way. And these ideas, once they're out there, go their own way.
And as you said, there's a particular way that this idea spread, the speed at which it spread
throughout the world made it even less able to be sort of stabilized and connected back to the
origins of where the idea came from. The only people who ever really tried that were the Russians
after the revolution, because they occupied a position for a while, not very long, but they
occupied a position for a while in which, I mean, it was exalted, right? There had been all these
people criticizing capitalism for a long time, even the Marxists ever since mid-century.
And these were the first guys who pulled it off. They made it. And so there was a kind of presumption
around the world. Their interpretation must be kind of the right one, because look, they did it.
And so for a while, they could enunciate their interpretation, and it came to be widely grasped
as something which, by the way, gets called in the literature, official Marxism. The very idea
that you would put that adjective in front of Marxism or Soviet Marxism or Russian Marxism,
there were these words that where the adjective was meant to somehow say, kind of, this is the
cannon. You can depart from it, but this is the cannon. Before the Russian Revolution,
there was no such thing. And by the 1960s, it was already, it was gone. But for a short time,
30, 40 years, it was a kind of, and the irony is, particularly here in the United States,
where the taboo against Marxism kicks in right after World War II is so total in this country
that I, for example, through most of my adult life, have had to spend a ridiculous amount of my time
simply explaining to American audiences that the Marxism they take as canonical
is that old Soviet Marxism, which wasn't the cannon before 1917 and hasn't been
since at least the 1960s, but they don't know. It's not that they're stupid and it's not that
they're ignorant. It's that, well, the ignorance may be, but I mean, it's not a mental problem. It's
the taboo, shut it down. And so all of the reopening that, in a way, recaptures what went before
and develops it in new direction, they just don't know. Nevertheless, it's a serious attempt at
making the implicit ideas explicit. The Russians, the Soviets at the beginning of the 20th century
made a serious attempt at saying, okay, beyond the critique of capitalism, how do we actually
build a system like this? And so in that sense, not at a high level, but at a detailed level,
it's interesting to look at those particular schools maybe. Right, because for example,
let me just take your point one step further, you really cannot understand the Cuban revolution,
the Chinese revolution, Vietnamese and the others, because each of them is a kind of
response, let's call it, to the way the Soviets did it. Are you going to do it that way? Well,
yes and no is the answer. This we will do that way, but that we're not going to do. And the
differences are huge, but you could find a thread, I can do that for you if you want,
in which all of them are, in a way, reacting to the originals. Yes, very much so. Like maybe most
of rock music is reacting to the Beatles and the Stones. That's something like that.
Well, can you speak to the unique elements of the various schools of that Soviet Marxism? So we
got Leninism, Trotskyism, Stalinism, maybe even let's expand out to Maoism. So maybe I could
speak to sort of Leninism and then please tell me if I'm saying dumb things. There's a, I think
for Lenin, there was an idea that there could be a small, so the Vanguard party, like a small
controlling entity that's like wise and is able to do the central planning decisions. Then for
Stalinism, one interesting, so Stalin's implementation of all of this, one interesting
characteristic is to move away from the international aspect of the ideal Marxism to
make it all about nationalism, the strength of nation. So Maoism is different in that it's
focused on agriculture and rural. Then Trotskyism, I don't know except that it's anti-Stalin. I mean,
I don't even know if there's unique philosophical elements there. Anyway, can you maybe from those
or something else speak to different unique elements that are interesting to think about
implementation of Marxism in the real world? Probably the best way to get into this is to
describe something that happened in Marxism that then shapes the answer to your question.
In the early days of Marxist writings, and you know, his life spans the 19th centuries,
born in 1818, dies in 1883. So literally, he lives the 19th century. And you might, I mean,
to make things simple, you might look at the first half of the first two-thirds of his life
as overwhelmingly gathering together the precursors to his own work. Marx was unusually
scholarly in the sense that partly because he didn't work a regular job and partly because
he was an exile in London, most of his adult life, he worked in the library. I mean, he had a lot of
time. He got subsidized a little bit by Engels whose family were manufacturers. And you might say the
first half to two-thirds of his life are about the critique of capitalism. And that was what,
in a broad sense, the audience for his work, Western Europe more or less, was interested in.
That's what they wanted. And he gave that to them. He wasn't the only one, but he was very,
very effective at it. By the last third of his life, he and the other producers of a
anti-capitalist movement, people like the Chartists in England, that's a whole other movement,
the anarchists of various kinds, like Proudhon in France or Kropotkin or Bakunin in Russia,
and so on. You put all these together and there was a shift in what the audience,
let's call it a mixture of militant working-class people, on the one hand,
and critical or radical intelligentsia on the other. They now wanted a different question.
They were persuaded by the analysis. They were agreeable that capitalism was a phase they would
like to do better than. And the question became, how do we do this? Not anymore,
should we? Why should we? Could we maybe fix capitalism? No, they had gotten to the point,
the system has to be fundamentally changed. But they didn't go, you might imagine, they
didn't go and say, well, what will that new system looks like? They didn't go that way. What they
did was ask the question, how could we get beyond capitalism? It seems so powerful. It seems to have
captured people's minds, people's daily lives, and so on. And the focus of the conversation became,
this was already by the last third of the 19th century, the question of the agency,
the mechanism whereby we would get beyond. And again, make a long story short, the conversation
focused on seizing the government. See, before that, it wasn't that the government was not a
major interest. If you read Marx's capital, the great work of his maturity, three volumes,
there's almost nothing in the state. I mean, he mentions it, but he's interested in the
details of how capitalism works, factory by factory, store by store, office. What's the
structure? The government's secondary for him. But there's also humans within that capitalist
system of there's the working class. That's what he's interested in. Think of it almost
mechanically like the workplace. In the workplace, there are some people who do this and other people
who do that. And they accept this division of authority. And they accept this division of
what's going on here, particularly because he believed that the core economic objective of
capitalism was to maximize something called profit, which his analysis located right there in the
workings of the enterprise. And the government was not the key factor here.
And he was looking at ideas of value. How much is the, how much value does the labor of the
individual workers provide? And that means how do we reward the workers in an ethical way?
And so those are the questions of... Right, we'll get to that.
But the government was not part of that picture.
So it's very significant that towards the end of the 19th century, Marx is still alive when this
begins, but it really gets going after he dies. Is this debate among Marxists about the role of
the state? They all agree, nearly all of them agree that you have to get the state. The working
class has to get the state because they see the state as the ultimate guarantor of capitalism.
When things get really out of hand, the capitalist calls the police or he calls the army or both of
them. And so the government is, in a sense, this key institution captured in Marxist language
by the bourgeoisie, by the by the other side, the capitalists, and yet vulnerable because of
suffrage. If suffrage is universal or nearly so, if everybody gets a vote, which in a way
capitalism brings to bear, part of its rejection of feudalism in the French American Revolution,
is to create a place where elected represented. So the government being subject to suffrage
creates the notion, aha, here's how we're going to... We have to seize the state.
And then that gets agreed upon, but there's a big split as to how to do it. One side says,
you go with the election. You mobilize the voter. That gets to be called reformism within Marxism.
And the other side is revolution. Don't do that. This system, if I may quote Bernie again, is rigged.
You can't get there. They've long ago learned how to manipulate
parliaments. They buy the politicians and all that, and therefore revolution is going to be
the way to do it. Revolution gets a very big boost because the Russians, they did it that way.
They didn't do... I mean, they fought in the Duma in the in the parliament, but they didn't.
And this focus on the state, I would argue, goes way beyond what the debaters at the time
and if you're interested in the great names, there was a great theorist of the
role of the state in a reformist strategy to get power in Germany named Edward Bernstein.
Very important. His opponents in Germany were Karl Kautzke and Rosa Luxemburg, two other huge
figures in Marxism at the time. And they wrote the articles that everybody reads, but it was a much
broader debate. And by the way, that debate still goes on. Reformism versus revolution.
And in terms of not all that different, I mean, it's adjusted to history, but in terms of different.
Can you comment on where you lean in terms of the mechanism of progress,
reformation versus... I'd rather tell you the historical story. Over and over and over again,
in most cases, the reformists have always won because revolution is frightening, is scary,
is dangerous. And so most of the time, when you get to the point where it's even a relevant
discussion, not an abstract thing for conferences, but a real strategic issue, the reformists have won.
I mean, and I'll give you an example from the United States. In the Great Depression of the 1930s,
you had an extraordinary shift to the left in the United States. The greatest shift to the left in
the country's history before or since. Nothing like it. Suddenly, you created a vast left wing
composed of the labor movement, which went crazy in the 1930s. We organized more people into unions
in the 1930s than at any time before or any time since. It is the explosion. And at the same time,
the explosion of two socialist parties and a communist party that became very powerful,
and they all worked together, creating a very powerful leftist presence in this country.
They debated in a strategically real way reform or revolution. The reformers were the union people,
by and large, and the communists were the revolutionaries, by and large, because they were
affiliated with the communist international, with Russia and all of that. And in between,
you might say, the two socialist parties. One that was Trotskyist in inspiration, and the other one
more moderate Western European kind of socialism. And they had this intense debate. And they ended
up, the reformists won that debate. There was no revolution in the 1930s here. But there was
a reform that achieved unspeakably great successes, which is why it was as strong and remains as
strong as it does, because it achieved in a few years in the 1930s, starting around 1932-3,
social security in this country. We had never had that before. That's the same one we have now.
Unemployment insurance never existed before, that you have till today. Minimum wage for the
first time, still have that today. And a federal program of employment that hired 15 million people.
I mean, these were unspeakable gifts, if you like, to the working class.
So that's the 30s and the 40s.
30s, not much in the 40s anymore, but in the 30s. And here's the best part. It was paid for by
taxes on corporations and the rich. So when people today say, well, you can tax the government,
the joke is, I have to teach American history to Americans because it has been erased from
consciousness. We'll return to that. But first, let's take a stroll back to the beginning of
the 20th century with the Russians. Right, with the Russians. So their interpretation goes like this.
Everybody was right. The state is crucial. We were right. We were the revolutionaries. We
seized the state here in Russia. Now we have the state and socialism is when the working class
captures the state, either by reform or revolution, and then uses its power over the state to make
the transition from capitalism to the better thing we're going toward. And again, make a long
story short in the interest of time. What happens, which is not unusual in human history, is that
the means becomes the end. In other words, Lenin, who's crystal clear before he doesn't live very
long, he dies in 23. So he's only in power from 17 to 22. But at that time, he has his brain
in trouble. 1923, by the way, not at age 23. 1923. Yeah, he's only there for four or five years.
He's very clear. He even says, I've done work on that. I've published, so I know this stuff.
He says in a famous speech, let's not fool ourselves. We have captured the state,
but we don't have socialism. We have to create that. We have to move towards that.
With Stalin, Lenin dies and there's a fight between Stalin and Trotsky. Trotsky loses the
fight. He's exiled. He goes to Mexico. Stalin is now alone in power and does all the things he's
famous or infamous for. And by the end of the 20s, Stalin makes a decision. I mean, not that he
makes it alone, but things have evolved in Russia so that they do the following. They declare that
they are socialism. In other words, socialism becomes when you capture the state, not when the
state capture has enabled you to do X, Y, Z, other things. No, no. The state itself, once you have it,
is socialism. So when a socialist captures the state, that's socialism. Exactly. That's exactly
right. I feel like that's definitionally confusing. Well, it shouldn't be because I'll give you an
example. Yeah. If you go to many parts of the United States today and you ask people, what's
socialism? They'll tell you, they'll look you right in the face and they'll say, the post office.
And you know, when I first heard this as a young man, you know what? The post office. It took me a
while to understand the post office, Amtrak, the Tennessee, all the examples in the United States
where the government runs something. This is socialism. See, capitalism is if the government
doesn't run it. If a private individual who's not a government official runs it, well,
then it's capitalism. If the government takes it, then it's socialism. So what is wrong with that
reasoning? So the idea, I think... There's nothing wrong with it. It's a way of looking at the world.
It's just got nothing to do with Marx. Well, there's Marx, there's Marxism. Let's try to
pull this apart. So what role does central planning have in Marxism? So Marxism is concerned
with this class struggle, with respecting the working class. What is the connection
between that struggle and central planning that is often... Central planning is often associated
with Marxism. So a centralized power doing allocation. So that has to do with a very specific
set of implementations initiated by the Soviet Union. Has nothing to do with Marx. How else can
you do... I don't think you can find anywhere in Marxist writing anything about central planning
or any other kind of planning. Again, fundamentally, then Marx's work has to do with factories,
with workers, with the bourgeoisie, and the exploitation of the working class.
You still have to take that leap. What is beyond capitalism? Right. So maybe we should
turn to that. Focus on that. Okay. We've already looked historically at several attempts
to go beyond capitalism. How else can we go beyond capitalism? Let me push it a little further.
They didn't succeed in my judgment as a Marxist. And I'm now going to tell you why they didn't
succeed because they didn't understand as well as they could have or should have
what Marxist was trying to do. I think I would have been like them if I had lived at their time
under their circumstances. This is not a critique of them, but it's a different way of understanding
what's going on. All right. So give you an example. Most of my adult life, I have taught
Marxian economics. I'm a professor of economics. I've been that all my life. I'm a graduate of
American universities. As it happens, I'm a graduate of what in this country passes for its
best universities. With another conversation, you and I can have. So I went to Harvard,
then I went to Stanford, and I finished a Yale. I'm like a poster boy for elite education.
They tried very hard. By the way, I spent 10 years of my life in the Ivy League, 20 semesters,
one after the other, no break. In those 20 semesters, 19 of them never mentioned a word
about Marxism. That is, no critique of capitalism was offered to me ever with one except one
professor in Stanford in the one semester I studied with him. He gave me plenty to read,
but nobody else. So that's really interesting. You've mentioned that in the past, and that's
very true, which makes you a very interesting figure to hold your ground intellectually through
this idea space where just people don't really even talk about it. Perhaps we can discuss historically
why that is, but nevertheless, that's the case. So Marxian economics, did Karl Marx come up in
conversation as a kind of dismissal? The best example, yeah, he came up only as an
object of dismissal. For example, the major textbook in economics that I was taught with,
and that was for many years, the canonical book, isn't quite anymore, was a book authored by a
professor of economics at MIT named Paul Samuelson. And people kind of, you know, a whole generation
or two were trained on his textbook. If you open the cover of his textbook, he has a tree,
and the tree is Adam Smith and David Ricardo at the root, and then the different branches of
it. He's trying to give you an idea as a student of how the thing developed. And it's a tree,
and everybody on it is the bourgeois. And then there's this one little branch that goes off like
this and sort of starts heading back down. That's Karl Marx. In other words, he had to have it
complete because he's not a complete faker. But beyond that, no, there was no. Nothing in the book
gives you two paragraphs of an approach. But that's cold war. I mean, that's really,
that's really neat to hear. That's the craziness. Yeah, that's the cold war in this country. My
professors were afraid. Anyway, let me get to the core of it, what I think will help.
Marx was interested in the relationship of people in the process of production,
that he's interested in the factory, the office, the store. What goes on, and by that he means,
what are the relationships among the people that come together in a workplace?
And what he analyzes is that there is something going on there that has not been adequately
understood and that has not been adequately addressed as an object needing transformation.
And what does he mean? The answer is exploitation, which he defines mathematically in the following
way. Whenever in a society, any society, you organize people, adults, not the children,
not the sick, but you know, healthy adults. In the following way, a big block of them,
a clear majority, work. That is, they use their brains and their muscles to transform nature.
A tree into a chair, a sheep into a woolen sweater, whatever. In every human community,
Marx argues, there are the people who do that work, but they always produce more chairs,
more sweaters, more hamburgers than they themselves consume. Whatever their standard of
living doesn't have to be low, it can be medium, it can be hard, but they always produce more
than they themselves consume. That more, by the way, Marx, when he writes this, uses the German
word mehr, M-E-H-R, which is the English equivalent of more. It's the more. That more got badly
translated into the word surplus. Shouldn't it have been? But it was. By the way, by German
and English people doing the translations. What's the difference between more and surplus?
Is there a nuanced? Yeah, because surplus has a notion of its discretionary, it's sort of extra.
He's not making a judgment that it's extra. It's a simple math equation.
Yes, very simple. One minus the other. Yes. x minus y minus.
x is the total output, y is the consumption by the producer, therefore x minus y equals s the
surplus. Exactly. Now Marx argues, the minute you understand this, you will ask the following
question. Who gets the surplus? Who gets this extra stuff that is made but not consumed by
those who made it? And Marx's answer is, therein lies one of the great shapers of any society.
How is that organized? For example, who gets it? What are they asked, if anything, to do with it
in exchange for getting it? What's their social role? For example, here we go now. If you get this
and you get the core of it anyway. And I don't charge much. The workers themselves could get it.
Western lawyers. That's right. The workers themselves could get it. That's the closest
Marx comes to a definition of communism. Communism would be if the workers who produce the surplus
together decide what to do with it. So this has to do not just with who gets it, but more
importantly, who gets to decide who gets it? Well, who gets it and who gets to decide what to do with
it. Right. Because you can't decide it if you don't have disposition over it. So the logic of the
word sequence, it's produced, Marx uses the word appropriated, in other words, whose property,
who gets to decide, if you like, what happens, all that property ever meant,
is who gets to decide and who's excluded. That's a clean definition of communism.
Right. And that's it. By the way, it's not just clean. It's the only one.
So what's, can we just linger on the definition of exploitation in that context?
Easy. It becomes very easy. Exploitation exists if and when the surplus that's produced
is taken and distributed by people other than those who produced it. Slaves produce a surplus
which the master gets, serfs produce a surplus which the Lord gets, employees produce a surplus
which the employer gets. It's very simple. These are exploitative class structures,
because one class produces a surplus appropriated, distributed by another group of people,
not the ones who produced it, which creates hostility, enmity, envy, anger, resentment,
and all of the problems you can lump under the heading class struggle. I use a metaphor,
simple metaphorical story. You have two children, let's assume, and you take them to Central Park,
a few blocks from here. It's a nice day and the children are playing and in comes one of those
men with an ice cream truck comes by, ding-a-ling-a-ling-a-ling, your children see the ice cream,
daddy, get me an ice cream. So you walk over, you take some money and you get two ice cream cones
and you give them to one of the children. The other one begins to scream and yell and how,
obviously, what's the issue? And you realize you've just made a terrible mistake. So you order
the one you gave the two ice cream cones to, give one of those to your sister or your brother or
whatever it is, and that's how you solve the problem. Until a psychologist comes along and says,
you know, you didn't fix it by what you just did. You should never have done that in the first place.
My response, though you understand, all of the efforts to deal with inequality in
economic, political, cultural, these are all giving the ice cream cone back to the kid you should,
you should never do this in the first place.
The reallocation of resources creates bitterness and populace.
Look at our, we've, this country is tearing itself apart now in a way that I have never seen in my
life and I've lived here all my life and I've worked here all my life. It's tearing itself apart
and it's tearing itself apart basically over the re-division, the redistribution of wealth,
having so badly distributed in the first, but that's all in Marx. And notice as I explain to you
what is going on in this tension-filled production scene in the office, the factory, the store.
I don't have to say a word about the government. I'm not interested in the government.
The government's really a very secondary matter to this core question and here comes the big point.
If you make a revolution and all you do is remove the private exploiter and substitute
a government official without changing the relationship, you know, you can call yourself
a Marxist all day long, but you're not getting the point of the Marxism. The point was not who
the exploiter is, but the exploitation per se. You've got to change the organization of the
workplace so there isn't a group that makes all the decisions and gets the surplus vis-a-vis
another one that produces it. If you do that, you will destroy the whole project. You will,
not only will you not achieve what you set out to get, but you'll so misunderstand it that you,
the Germans again have a phrase, it's get chief. It goes crooked. It doesn't go right. The project
gets off the rails because it can't understand either what its objective should have been and
therefore it doesn't understand how and why it's missing its objective. It just knows that this
is not what it had hoped for. I mean, there's a lot of fascinating questions here. So one is
to what degree, so there's human nature, to what degree does Communism,
a lack of exploitation of the working class naturally emerge if you leave two people together
in a room and come back a year later? If you leave five people together in a room,
if you leave a hundred people and a thousand people, it seems that humans form hierarchies
naturally. So the clever, the charismatic, the sexy, the muscular, the powerful, however you
define that, start becoming a leader and start to do maybe exploitation in a non-negative sense
a more generic sense starts to become an employer, not in a capitalist sense, but just as a human.
Here, you go do this and in exchange, I will give you this, just becomes the leadership role.
So the question is, yes, okay, it would be nice. The idea sort of of Communism would be nice to
not steal from the world. It's nice in theory, but it doesn't work in practice because of human
nature. Because of human nature. That's, thank you. So what can we say about leveraging human
nature to achieve some of these ends? There's so many ways of responding in no particular order.
Here's some of them. The history of the human race, as best I can tell, is a history in which
a succession of social forms, forms of society, arise and as they do, they rule out some kinds
of human behavior on the grounds that they are socially disruptive and unacceptable.
The argument isn't really then, is there a need or an instinct? Is there some human nature
that makes people want to do this? Well, whatever that is, this has to be repressed or else we don't
have a society. And Freud helps us to understand that that repression is going on all the time
and it has consequences. It's not a finished project. You repress it. It's gone. It doesn't
work like that. So for example, when you get a bunch of people together at some point,
they may develop animosities towards one another that lead them to want the other person or persons
to disappear, to be dead, to be gone. But we don't permit you to do that. We just don't.
Every economic system that has ever existed has included people who defend it
on the grounds that it is the only system consistent with human nature and that every
effort to go beyond it has to fail because it contradicts human nature. I can show you
endless documents of every tribal society I've ever studied, every anthropological community that
has ever been studied, slavery wherever it's existed. I can show you endless documents in
which the defenders of those systems, not all of them of course, but many defenders used that
argument to naturalize a system is a way to hold on to it, to prevent it from going,
to counter the argument that every system is born, every system evolves, and then every system dies.
And therefore capitalism since it was born and since it's been developing, we all know what the
next stage of capitalism is. Looking in fur. The burden is on the people who think it isn't going
to die. Okay, so it doesn't mean they're wrong, but what you're saying is if we look at history,
you're deeply suspicious of the argument this is going against human nature because we keep using
that for basically everything including toxic relationship, toxic systems, destructive systems.
That said, well let me just ask a million different questions. So one, what about the argument that
sort of the employer, the capitalist takes on risk? So the versus the employee who's just there
doing the labor, the capitalist is actually putting up a lot of risk. Are they not in sort of
aggregating this organization and taking this giant effort hiring a lot of people? Aren't they
taking on risk that this is going to be a giant failure? So first of all, there's risk almost
in everything you undertake. Any project that begins now and ends in the future takes a risk
that between now and that future something's going to happen that makes it not work out.
I mean, I got into a cab before I came here today in order to do this with you. I took a risk. The
cab could have been in an accident, the lightning could have hit us, a bear could have eaten my
left foot. Who the hell knows? Should I reward you for the risk you took? No, hold it a second.
Let's do this step by step. So everybody's taking a risk. I always found it wonderful. You talk about
risk and then you imagine it's only some of us who take a risk. Let's go with the worker
and with the capitalist. That worker, he moved his family from Michigan to Pennsylvania to take
that job. He had, he made a decision to have children. They are teenagers. They're now in school
at a time when their friendships are crucial to their development. You're going to yank them
out of the school because his job is gone. He took an enormous risk to do that job every day,
to forestall all the other things he could have done. He was taking a risk that this job would
be here tomorrow, next month, next year. He bought a house which Americans only do with mortgages,
which means he's now stuck. He has to make a monthly payment. If you make a mistake,
you capitalist. He's the one who's going to, you're a capitalist. You got a lot of money,
otherwise you wouldn't be in that position. You've got a cushion. He doesn't. If you investigate,
you'll see that in every business I've ever been in. I've been involved in a lot of them.
So you think it's possible to actually measure risk or as your basic argument is there's risk
involved in a lot of both the working class and the bourgeoisie, the capitalist, and it's very
difficult. The worker would never come and say, because he's been taught right,
I want this payment, a wage for the work I do, and I want this page, this payment,
for the risk I take. Well, there's some level of communication like that. You have acknowledgement
of dangerous jobs, but that's probably built into the salary, all those kinds of things.
But you're not incorporating the full spectrum of risk.
You don't believe that. This country is now being literally transformed from below by an
army of workers who work at Amazon, fast food joints. You know what their complaint is? It's
killing us. We get paid shit and it's killing us. There is no relationship except in the minds
of the defenders of capitalism between the ugliness, the difficulty, the danger of labor on
the one hand and the wage. Let me give you just a couple of examples, because this is my job.
This is my life, what I do. The median income of a child care worker in the United States
right now as we speak is $11.22 an hour median. So 50% make less, 50% make more.
The median income for car park attendant is several dollars per hour higher than that.
What does the car park attendant do? He stares at your car for many hours to make sure that nobody
comes and grabs it. Maybe he parks it and moves it around to get it in and out. By any measure
that I know of that makes any rational sense, being in charge of toddlers, two, three, four
year olds who are at the key moment of mental formation the first five years, to give that a
lower salary than you give the guy who watches your car. Come on, I know how to explain it.
Gender explains all kinds of issues. The car park people are males and the day the child care
people are females and that in our culture is a very big marker of what, but the one who said
only the economics professor, nobody else says this stuff because in economy, I don't know if
you are familiar with our profession, but we have something which we call marginal product.
This is a, this is a fantasy. I was a mathematician before I became an economist. I loved mathematics.
I specialized in mathematics. So I know mathematics pretty well. What economists do is silly,
is childish, but they think it's mathematics. But think for a minute what it means to suggest
that you can identify the marginal product of a factor of production, like a worker.
In the textbook, when it's taught, I've taught this stuff. I hold my nose, but I teach it.
Then I explain to students what I've just taught you is horseshit, but first I teach it.
What is the marginal product if it might be useful to say?
The notion is if you take away one worker right now from the pile, what will be the
diminution of the output? That's the marginal product of that worker.
Measured by- The amount of the output that diminishes-
Output of the raw product, of the product.
Usually in real terms, so physical, not the value. You could do a value,
but it's really more the physical you're at.
I mean, there is a transformation thing. I'd love to talk to you about value. It's so
interesting. What is value?
I'd be glad to talk to you about value and price and all of that, but I just want to get to the
that Hegel, who is Marx's teacher, has a famous line. You can't step in this in the same river
twice. The argument is you and the river have changed between the first and the second time.
So it's a different you and it's a different river. You can choose not to pay attention to that.
Just you can't claim you're not doing that. You can't claim that you can actually do that,
because you can't. There is no way to do that.
So the meaning that you can't just remove a worker and have a clean mathematical calculation
of the effect that it has on the output. That's right, because too many other things are going on,
too many things are changing, and you cannot assume, much as you want to, that the outcome
on the output side is uniquely determined by the change you made on the input side.
Can't do that.
Even in the average, it's not going to work out.
You can take, look, mathematics is full of abstractions. You can say, as we do in economics,
Keteris Paribus, everything else held constant, but you have to know what you just did.
You held everything. You know why you do that? Because you can't do that in the real world.
That's not possible. You better account for that. Otherwise, you're mistaking the abstraction
from the messy reality you abstracted from to get the abstraction.
As a quick tangent, if we somehow went through a thought experiment or an actual experiment
of removing every single economist from the world, would we better off or worse off?
Much better off.
Okay. Economics, and I'm one. I'm talking about myself. See, economics-
We're going to ship all the economists to Mars and see how the world works off.
No, but the serious part of this is that economics, you know, it's really about capitalism.
Economics as a discipline is born with capital. There was no such thing.
When I teach, I teach courses at the university, for example, called
History of Economic Thought, right? And I begin the students with Aristotle and Plato.
And I say, you know, they talked about really interesting things,
but they never called it economics. It made no sense to people to abstract
something as central to daily life as economics broadly defined. It made no sense.
That's a creation much, much later. That's capitalism that did that, created the feeling.
So when I give them Plato and Aristotle, I have to give them particular passages.
By the way, footnote, because your audience will like it, Plato and Aristotle talked about markets
because they lived at a time in ancient Greece when market relations were beginning to intrude
upon these societies. So they were both interested in this phenomena that we're not just producing
goods and then distributing among us. We're doing it in a quid pro quo. You know, I'll give
you three oranges. You give me two shirts, a market exchange. And both Aristotle and Plato
hated markets, denounced them, and for the same reason, they destroy social cohesion. They destroy
community. They make some people rich and other people poor, and they set us against each other,
and it's terrible. And that's what they agreed on that. Here's what they disagreed on. One of them
said, okay, there can be no markets. That was Plato. Aristotle comes back and says,
no, no, no, no, no, no. Too late for that. The disruption caused in society by getting rid
of this institution that has crawled in amongst us would be too devastating. So we can't do that.
But what we can do is control it, regulate it, get from the market what it does reasonably well,
and prevent it from doing the destructive things it does so badly.
So the fundamentally, the destructive thing of a market is the engine of capitalism. So
it creates exploitation of the worker. It facilitates it, and it is an institution
that Plato and Aristotle feel is a terrible danger to community. Which, by the way,
is a way of thinking about it that exists right now all over the world.
Look, the medieval Catholic Church had a doctrine, the prohibition of usury.
And this was that God said, if there's a person who needs to borrow from you,
then that's a person in need. And the good Christian thing to do is to help him,
to demand an interest payment rather than to help your fellow man is God hates you for that.
That's a sin. Jesus is crying all the way to wherever it is he goes.
But would Jesus be crying when you try to scale that system? So that has to do with the
intimate human interaction. The idea of markets is you're able to create a system that involves
thousands, millions of humans. And there'd be some level of safe, self-regulating fairness.
There might be, but it's hard to imagine that charging interest would be the way to do that.
I wonder what... I guess...
Suppose you were interested in having, suppose you took us your problem,
we have a set of funds that can be loaned out.
People don't want to consume it. They're ready to lend it. Okay.
To whom should they lend it? Well, we could say in our society,
we're going to run this the way professors in institutions like MIT work this.
They write up a project. They send the project in to some government office
where it is looked at against other projects. And this office in the government decides we're
going to fund this one and that one because they're more needed in our society. We're in
greater need of solving this problem than that problem. And so we're going to lend money to
people working on this problem more readily or more money than we lend over here because we're
going to... But instead, what we do is who can pay the highest interest rate? Whoa, what do you do?
What ethics would justify you do it? It's like a market in general. Something is in shortage.
All markets are about how to handle shortage. That's one basic way to understand it.
And so if the demand is greater than the supply, which is all the word shortage
means, has no other meaning. If the demand is greater than the supply, okay, now you've got a
problem. You can't satisfy all the demanders because you don't have enough supply. You have
a shortage. Okay, now how are you going to do it? In a market, you allow people who have a lot of
money to bid up the price of whatever's short. That solves your problem because as the price
goes up, the poor people can't... They drop out. They can't buy the thing at the exalted price.
So you've got a way of distributing the shortage. It goes to the people with the most money. At this
point, most human beings confronted with this explanation of a market would turn against it
because it contradicts their Christian, Judaic, Islamic, all of them would say,
what? You know what that means? It means that a rich person can get the scarce milk
and give it to their cat while the poor person has no milk for their five children.
There it is. Do you want to mark it? Why?
Over the fundamental thing that seems unfair, there's the resulting inequality now.
Or death. Well, that's the ultimate inequality. Yes, it is.
What about, and we're going to jump around from the philosophical, from the economics,
to the sort of debate type of thing. What about sort of the lifting ties raise all boats?
Meaning, if we look at the 20th century, a lot of people, maybe you disagree with this,
but they attribute a lot of the innovation and the average improvement in the quality of life,
to capitalism, to inventions and innovation, to engineering and science developments
that resulted from competition and all those kinds of forces.
Not looking at the individual unfairness of exploitation as it's specifically defined,
but just observing historically. Looking at the 20th century, we came up with a lot of cool stuff
that seemed to have made life easier and better on average. What do you say to that?
I have several responses to that, but I do disagree pretty fundamentally with what's
going on there. But let me give you the argument so that you can hear them and then you can evaluate
them as can anybody who's listening or watching. Marx was a student of Hegel, and one of Hegel's
central arguments was that everything that exists, exists, quote, in the contradiction.
In simple English, there's a good and bad side if you like to everything,
and you won't understand it unless you accept that proposition and start looking for the good
things that are the other side of the bad ones and the bad things that are the other side of the
good one, et cetera. The dialectic. Yes, exactly. Marx very attentive to that explicitly agrees
with this on many occasions and applies it, of course, to the central object of his research,
capitalism. This is not a simple-minded fellow who's telling you all the bad things about capitalism
as if there were nothing that this system achieved or accomplished. One of the things he
celebrates a lot is the technological dynamism of the system, which Marx takes to be profound,
because he lived at the time when major breakthroughs in textile technology, in mining,
in chemistry, and so on were achieved. But as to the notion that capitalism is therefore responsible
for the improvement in the quality or the standard of living of the mass of people,
Marx now comes back and says, oh, wait a minute here. Number one, capitalism as a system
has been mostly represented by capitalists, which makes a certain sense. And those capitalists
with very few exceptions, some but very few, have fought against every effort to improve the lives
of the mass of people. The goal of a capitalist is to minimize labor costs. What that means is
replace a worker with a machine, move the production from expensive U.S. to cheap China,
bring in desperate immigrants from other parts of the world, because they will work for less
money than the folks that you have here at home. Every measure to help the standard of living
of American workers had to be fought for for decades over the opposition of capitalists
from the beginning to right now. The reason we have a minimum wage, which was past 19,
middle of the 1930s, when it was proposed, it was blocked by capitalists. They got together,
they don't want, and today, just a factoid for you. The last time the minimum wage was raised
in the United States, federal minimum wage, was in 2009, when it was set at the lofty sum
of $7.25 an hour, which you cannot live on. Over the last 12 years or so, whatever it is,
not 11, 12, 13 years since then, we have had an increase in the price level in this country
every year, and in the last year, 8.5%. During that time that the prices went up,
the minimum wage was never raised. What? This is a time of stock market boom,
of growing inequality. This is the nerve of the defender of capitalists who wants now to get
credit for the improvement in the standard of life of the workers that was fought by every
generation. You know, it takes your breath away. It's an argument, whoa. But I take my hat off if
I had one, because that is one of the only ways to justify this system. Long ago, let me get the
heart of it, long ago, capitalism could have overcome hunger, could have overcome disease,
could have, I mean, way beyond what we have now, but it didn't. And that's the worst
moral condemnation imaginable. How do you justify that when you could, you didn't?
Look, let me get at it another way, because this may interest you anyway.
The issue is not that capitalism isn't technologically dynamic, it is. And along the way,
it has developed things that have helped people's lives get better, no question.
But the notion that the mass enjoyment of a rising standard of living is somehow built into
capitalism is factually nuts and is such an outrageous, and I can give you a, because you
do math, you'll understand it. Think of it this way. Imagine a production process in which you have
$100 that the capitalist has to lay out for tools, equipment, and raw materials,
and $100 that he has to lay out for workers, hire the workers, and he puts them all together,
and he has an output. And let's say the output is 100 units of something at one of the prices,
and that's his revenue. And when he takes his product and sells it and gets the revenue,
let's say the revenue is, it doesn't really matter, it's 120, for lack of a better word,
220, sorry. And he takes 100 of it and replaces the tools, equipment, and raw materials he used up,
another 100 to hire the workers for the next shift, and the other 20 is his profit and he puts
that aside. Now along comes a technological breakthrough, a machine, a new machine. And the
new machine is so effective, you can get the same number of units of output with half the workers.
So you don't need to spend 100 on workers, you only need to spend 50. You can do it with half
the workers. And so the capitalist goes to the workers, by the way this happens every day,
and he says to half of them, you're fired. Don't come back Monday morning, I don't need you.
It's nothing personal, I got a machine. Why does he do that? Because the 50 he now no longer has
to spend on labor, because it doesn't need half of them, he keeps. Everything else is the same,
the machine, everything else is just to make their math easy. So he keeps as his own profit
the 50 that before he paid for those workers. Because when he sells it for 220, that 50 he
don't have to give to the next job until he has a new machine. So that's what he does. The technology
leads, he's happy. He's become more profitable. He's got an extra 50, which is why he buys the
machine. The workers are screwed. Half of them just lost their job, have to go home to their
husband and wife, tell them I don't have a job anymore. I didn't do anything wrong. The guy was
nice enough to say it was nothing wrong with me, but he doesn't need them. So I'm completely screwed
here. I don't know what I'm going to do about the debts we have, the house on mortgage, my children's
education or whatever else he's got going for himself. All right, now, now the point. There was
of course an alternative path. The alternative path would have been to keep all the workers,
pay them exactly the same that you did before for half a day's work.
You would have got the same output, same revenue, same profit as before.
But the gain of the technology would have been a half a day of freedom every day of the lives
of these workers. The majority of workers would have been really helped by this technology,
but instead they were screwed so that one guy, the employer, could make a big bundle of more money.
You want to support a system like this? Well, to go back to Hegel, the good and the bad.
So you just listed the bad and you also first listed the good, the technological innovation of
this kind of system. The question is the alternative, whatever, as we try to sneak up to ideas of what
the alternative might look like, what are the good and the bad of the alternative? So you just kind
of as a opposite by contrast showed that, well, a nice alternative is you work less,
get paid the same, you have more leisure time, opportunity to pursue other interests,
the creative interests, family, flourish as a human being, basically strengthen and
embolden the basic humanity that's under all of us. Yes, but then what cost does that have
on the deadline fueled, competition fueled machine of technological innovation
that is the positive side of capitalism? It slows it down. It slows it down and the question is
which is more important for the flourishing of humanity? I agree with that and I'd love there
to be a democratic mechanism. So let's discuss it, let's debate it and then let's decide what
mixture, because it's not either or, the math problem I gave you is either or we could mix it,
you could have a third less of a working day instead of a half less and then the other part
would be extra profit for our employer, et cetera. So let's have a democratic discussion
of what is the mix between the positive and we have no such thing. All of this is decided by
one side in this debate, which not only we know what they do, they always choose the one that
maximizes their profit because that's what they were told to do in business school where I've
taught. So not only is it an undemocratic decision, but it's lopsided to boot. So we don't have the
opportunity, but I would love for us to be good Hegelian Marxists and say let's take a look at
the plus and the minus and make the best decision that we can. We'll make mistakes, but we'll all
make them together. It won't be one of us making a dictatorial decision. Marx developed the notion
of the dictatorship of the proletariat, not as a notion of how government is not, I'm sorry, not
Marx, Lenin did that, not as a notion of how the government works, but as a notion of what the
practical reality is. The dictatorship of these key decisions is not made by some sitting council,
it's made by each little capitalist in his or her relationships with the workers in the workplace,
which is why Marx focused his analysis on that point. And by the way, I can sketch for you right
now so it doesn't lurk in the background what the alternative is. Let's go there. Okay. It goes
right back to what I said earlier. The workers themselves, the collection of employees together
appropriate their own surplus and decide democratically what to do with it,
which includes the decision of whether or not to buy a machine and whether or not
to use the machine and the savings it might allow to be handled by more leisure for themselves
or as a fund for new developments in technology or new products or whatever they want. And you
this is an old idea in human. Marx loved that. Toward the end of his life, he
started reading extensively in anthropology. And one of the reasons he did that toward the end of
his life was because he kept discovering that in this society and that, including here in the
United States, that there were examples of people who organized their production in precisely this
way as a collective democratic community in which everybody had an equal voice. So we all
together decide democratically what to produce, how to produce, where to produce, and what to do
with the output we all help to produce. So let's do it in, you know, in this country where democracy
is a value nearly everybody subscribes to. Think about it this way, the stunning contradiction
that there is a place in our society where democracy has never been allowed to enter. The
workplace, in the workplace a tiny group of people, unaccountable to the rest of them, the
employer, whether that's an individual, a family, a partnership, or a corporate board of directors.
Tiny group of people controls economically a vast mass of employees. Those employees don't elect
those people, have no, nothing, there is no accountability. It is the most undemocratic
arrangement imaginable and this society insists on calling itself democratic
when it has organized the minor matter of producing everything in a way that is the direct,
it's autocratic. So to push back on a few things. So one is the idea of this society calling itself
democratic is that the government is elected democratically and the government is able to
pressure the workplace through the process of regulation. You pass laws of the boundaries of
how, you know, minimum wage, all those kinds of things. That's the one idea. The other is there
is a natural force within the capitalist when there's no monopolies of competition being the
accountability. So if you're a shitty boss, the employee in the capitalist system has the freedom
to move to another company work for a better boss. So that creates pressure on the employers and
the bosses. That's at least the idea that you there's two boundaries of you not misbehaving.
One is the law. So regulatory regulations by passed by the government, democratic. And the second
is because there's always alternatives in theory, then that puts pressure on everyone to behave
well because you can always leave. So I mean, that's kinds of accountability. But what you're
saying is that does not result in a significant enough accountability where the employer
that avoids exploitation of the worker. Absolutely. I mean, whatever accountability you get
in those mechanisms. And let me respond to that. And then I'll counter argument. First, competition.
Here again, we have to be Hegelians just a little competition destroys itself. It doesn't
need any out. The whole point of competition is to beat the other guy. If I can produce the same
product as the other guy, either a better quality or a lower price or maybe both, then I win because
the customers will come to me because my price is lower or my quality is better. And they'll
leave the other guy, he'll go out of business. Now let's follow. When he goes out of business,
because I won the competition, he fires his workers. I hire them because I'm now going to
be able to serve a market. He can't serve anymore. So I'm going to buy the used equipment. I'm going
and thereby many become few. Monopoly is the product of competition. It's not the antithesis.
It's the product. Well, let's see. That's where it comes from. There's another element to the
system where there's always a new guy that comes in. There isn't. Well, that's the dream. The
entrepreneurial spirit of a free, of the United States, for example, of a capitalist system is
you can be broke and one day have a strong idea and build up a business that takes on Google and
Facebook and Twitter and all the different car for GM, which is what you look at Tesla, for
example. That's the American dream. One of the many ideals of the American dream is you can
move from dirt poor to being the richest person in the world. It can happen.
It can happen, but you're against it. That's like you can win a lottery.
No, that's not quite. No, the lottery is complete luck. Here you can work your ass off if you have
a good idea. The odds are better in the lottery. That's not true. There's a lot of new businesses.
How many Teslas do you know? Tesla is a really bad example because the car company, the automotive
sector is so difficult. They operate as such a thin margin of profit. They're probably a good
example of capitalism just completely coming to a halt in terms of lack of innovation.
That's a very complicated industry because of the supply chain. They have their uniqueness as
you're quite right, but so does every other industry. The one thing that's common is that
many become few. What you can also have is when you have a few, they jack up the price. They make
an enormous profit. In the irony of capitalism, Marx would love this, they begin to incentivize
people to break into this industry because the few remaining are making a wild amount of profit
because they are a few and can jigger the market to make it work like that for them.
The reason every small capitalist is trying to build market share, that's a polite way of
saying they want to become a monopolist or to be more exact, an oligopolist, one of a handful
of firms that dominates. That's what they're there for. To push back a little bit also,
because this is a question also, do you think we're in danger of oversimplifying capitalism?
It completely removes the basic decency of human beings. If you give me a choice to press a button
to get rid of the competition, but that's going to lead to a lot of suffering. There's a lot of
people at the heads of companies that won't press that button. It's not in the calculation,
it's not just money, it's human well-being too. You think?
Yes. You and I don't live in the same place then.
You're saying that the forces of capitalism take over the minds of the people at the top,
and then they seize being human. No.
The basic, okay. I wouldn't, I wouldn't.
Depending on your model of humans, but they lose track of the better angels of their nature,
and they just become cogs in the machine, but they just happen to be the cop at the top.
I would put it differently, that the system is so set up, it's a little bit like natural selection.
The guys who may, I could say the women too, it doesn't matter. The people who make it up through
the layers of the bureaucracy and get to the top in these things have had to do things along the way
that becomes selective. If they can't stand it, because they have that human quality,
and there are people like, I've known them. They're the ones running an Airbnb in Vermont.
They went there and they said, I'm not doing this anymore. I'm not going to treat people like that.
I'm going to make a lovely place in Vermont with my husband or my wife or whatever, and I'm going to
be enjoying the people that come by and be a decent human. Of course, of course, but the system
selects the firm. If you don't do what has to be done to make the profit go up,
you're toast there anyway. The rest of the people who vote for you are going to kick you out.
You can tell them all day long what a lovely person you are. They're going to look at you and
wonder, what happened to you? How did you even get this far with the lovely person horses?
It's not necessarily just lovely person. Maybe, I'll just say my bias is the people I know are
and especially at the top of companies are in the tech sector where innovation is such a big
part of it. I think a lot of the things we're talking about is when there's not much innovation
in the system. Innovation usually comes in the history of capitalism, innovation comes in spurts.
There's the electric period, the chemistry period, the nuclear period. There's now whatever you
want to call it, the artificial intelligence or robotics or computer. It comes and then there's
a flurry as everything is reorganized around whatever the newest technology is and then you
have a period where you can get excited about that and the very rich people who come to the top
can talk endlessly as they always do about innovation.
But again, you know, it really is, this is a recurring kind of debate and a recurring kind
of issue. For me, how do I put this in a way that, you know, I don't mean to offend, so please,
please. No, no, no, I don't want to. But
the problem with capitalism is, and maybe you'll like this, the problem with capitalism is
not that it is the one thing that's consistent with human nature. That's what its defenders
would like to have us believe. But if anything, I would argue the opposite, that it is such a
contradiction to parts of our nature, not other parts, that it can never quite make it.
There's always going to be the people who don't go along with it, people you're talking about,
who do quit along the way, or maybe a few of them actually make it to the top. By God knows
what hook or what crook that they did it, but most of them go, and you know why? Because
their humanity is contradicted by what it is they're being asked to do. I mean, the corporate
sector this year, just to give you an idea, CEOs are jacking up their wage package. They're already
out of whack. I mean, the average CEO pay is now 300, 300 times what the average worker pays,
but they're jacking it up even more. Why? Because that's what's happening in their universe. That's
what they're all doing it, and they have to do. Each one of them justifies that I have to do that,
otherwise I'd lose my guy to the next one, which of course is true, but is no comfort for the mass
of people who aren't CEOs, for whom this argument isn't very exciting. So they're doing that at a
time when the American people can't cope. They've just gone through the COVID disaster. They've gone
through the worst, second worst economic crash of capitalism in our history. After two years of this
one-two punch, they got an inflation, a third punch, and we are now predicting rising interest
rates and a recession at the end of the year or early next year. You can't do this to a working
class. When this was done to the German working class in the 1920s, Hitler was the result.
You keep doing that in this country. We're already watching it. You're going to get that too.
You're already getting bits and pieces. You can't keep doing this.
So there's a quiet suffering amidst the working class that's growing.
Taking out on it. That can turn to anger.
Some little 18-year-old kid who has to go three hours in his car and blow away people in a supermarket.
What? And it happens every day in this country. Every day.
So that anger rises up in those little ways now and bigger, potentially.
By the way, there's one more thing on the rationality, and this goes to Elon Musk.
If you're interested, 49,000 people were killed in automobile accidents this last year. The number
was just released yesterday. 49,000. Automobiles are the single largest pollutant in the country.
They use up an enormous amount of energy. They use up enormous in our resources.
There is a way to make transportation much more rational, and we've known it for decades.
It's called mass transportation. It's a really beautifully maintained crystal clear,
clean, frequent system of buses, trains, street trolleys, vans. It could easily be done in this
society. In fact, I once did a project that I estimated cost $30 billion. That's less than
we're sending to Ukraine to do this, to reconfigure it. A public transit system where?
Everywhere in this country. All the major metropolitan. This country's overwhelmingly
metropolitan area. Well, it surely has to be more than $30 billion. Well, it was a few years ago.
You're saying it's not a number that's insane. Right. It's not crazy stuff.
It's a reasonable number. Let me just finish the point.
Sure, yes. Okay. So I'm trying to be rationally here.
If we have a climate crisis, which everyone tells me we do, if it's got a lot to do with
fossil fuels, which everybody tells me it has to do, and with the use of the fossil fuel,
particularly for the automobile, then the solution to the problem would be mass transit.
We don't, we're doing nothing to make that happen. Nothing.
Well, there's, you know, on, you could argue that autonomous vehicles is a kind of public
transit because it's going to be reasonable vehicles. It will end in theory car ownership.
So you just have a more kind of distributed public transit system.
If it happens, but you know that that's a side effect. His major goal and the major goal of
the other companies that are busy squeezing to get his share by smaller, so they have some,
four General Motors Toyota, all of them are making electric cars. So what they've done is
they've replaced the individual car with fossil fuel with another individual car.
That's fucking nuts. What are you doing? That's one of the things they're doing,
but automation is also another one. But on the Elon side, there's also
a hilariously named boring company, which is working on tunnels, which is actually expanding the
flexibility you might have to start playing with ideas of public transit. I think, listen,
I'm now partially living in Austin, Texas, that I don't know if they know what a public
transit system is, period. There's F-150 pickup trucks. Well, there's, this is an interesting,
so the older, by the way, footnote, the older the city, the more likely it has public transportation.
So you're saying Boston is the best example? Yes.
Have you been, you know? Yeah, yeah. Of course. Yeah, I have a place in Boston.
Boston with the street railway. Boston is your case study of how to do this,
because they've been doing it all along. New York's pretty good too.
There's a trade out. Yeah. New York, I would say, is better than Boston because
there's, you know, their technology also helps you out to do the public transit better.
It's almost like Boston is a little too old, but yes, I get your point. But there is a,
the Ford F-150 pickup truck symbolizes something about America. And there is a practical nature to
the fact that in order to do public transit, in order to do some of these things that you're
talking about with the working class, there has to be a central planning component,
or there has to be a centralized component. And America is very much based on the idea of,
at least in recent times, I would say from the founding of individualism,
of respecting individual freedom. Are you worried that in order to bring some of these ideas of
Marxism to life, you would trample on individual freedoms? No. Can you respect both? Sure. For
me, Marxism is a way to enhance the individual freedom of the mass of people who have had
that freedom eroded under the capitalism. That's a motive for my Marxism. It was for Marx too.
He loved the French Revolution. He loved the libert, galit, fraternit, the great three,
and then democracy, the American contribution, if you like. He believed in all of that. His critique
of capitalism was it promised it and then never delivered it. And the reason you have to go beyond
it is because it didn't deliver what it had promised. So for me, it is the fulfillment of
a gender. But again, I'm a Hegelian Marxist, so if you want. Individualism, for me, is not the way
it's set up in this society. Some sort of antithesis to the government. I think an immense con has been
pulled on the American people. And the con works like this. You know what's bad and what's dangerous
and threatens you? It's the government. The government's going to come in and tell you what
to do. The government's going to run your life. The government's the problem. There really is no
other way to explain the following in American politics. Large numbers of people lose their
homes in a downturn, like the so-called Great Recession of 2008. Who do they blame? The government.
Large numbers of people go unemployed. And what are the media all about? The government.
If I were a capitalist, I'd love this. I kick the workers by throwing them out of their home,
and they don't get angry with me. They get angry with the government. I fire large numbers of people.
I have no responsibility for what happens to them as a result of having no job and no income.
And they get angry at the senator. I'm laughing all the way to the bank. This is a genius stroke.
In theory, but if you look at government, because you said accountability in the
capitalist system has no accountability. There's some pushback I give on the accountability. I
think there is some accountability we can discuss in a Galilean way. There's more accountability
for, I would say, that in theory, government is perfectly accountable. That's the whole point
of a democratic system, is you vote people in. In practice, there's a giant growing bureaucracy
that is accountable only on the surface. There's two parties
that seem to be, are the same media somehow integrated into making the same two parties
that are just wearing different colored shirts to seem like they're very opposed and are arguing
and bitterly arguing and calling each other's names, nasty names and all those kinds of things.
Okay, but that's government. So who exactly is worse here? Government or companies?
Well, why are we asking that question? These are twins. Look, what you were able to say about
Republicans and Democrats just now, with which I agree, I would say the same thing about corporations
and the government. This is the same people, literally. But let's go to Churchill. Which one
is the, which one is worse? Let's go to Churchill, like democracy is the worst formal government,
except all the other ones or whatever. So this kind of same idea, which one exactly is worse?
Because to me, it seems like, which one between what government and industry and companies?
It's because government is plagued by, I will call it corruption because the corruption of
bureaucratic paperwork and then because they're, but they're not accountable. There doesn't seem
to be a serious accountability. Again, we're not see, we're not living on the same planet.
The greatest practitioners of central planning are corporations. Elon has an operation like
General Motors, Ford, IBM, or any of the other mega-corps. They have to plan. They buy up companies
because they don't want to deal in the market. They don't want the insecurity, the uncertainty of
having to buy their inputs or sell their outputs to somebody they don't control. They want the
professor to teach the genius of a market. They hate the market. And when they grow to be big,
they keep buying whoever they were dealing with before so they could better control them,
which requires them then to plan the production and distribution of goods inside rather than buying
them in the market. The model of the government is a private corporation. I have spent my life,
give you an example, in American universities, big ones, famous ones, not just as a student,
but as a professor. I teach now at the new school here. It's another one, right?
They will model themselves after businesses. You can attack the bureaucracy of universities,
good reason, it's a mess, but they're proudly modeling themselves on organizing their bureaucracy
in a business-like manner. So you're looking at a difference which isn't there. The government
and the private sector are partners and both of them wouldn't have it any other way. The corporations
want that from the government and the government now knows that to please the corporations is the
number one objective they have because that's how they keep their jobs and keep their system
going. And so for all practical purposes, this is the same people.
But there's important differences that I don't know if they're fundamental or just a consequence
of history, but if you have government, they're accountable in a different way than companies.
Companies are accountable by, especially if you have a consumer, they're accountable by sort of
the consumer spending or not spending their money on whatever the heck the company is selling.
The government is accountable by votes and it seems like government, unlike companies,
for most of companies, history is always too big to fail, meaning it can always just print
money. It can always save itself and that creates a bureaucracy. You rarely pay the cost of having
made bad decisions if you're in government. You distribute the blame and it's very unclear
who's responsible for bad decisions. So bad decisions in government accumulate. So you become
more and more and more inefficient and more and more poor in your decision making in terms of,
you said public transit, should we build a public transit system in this city or not?
That's a difficult decision. That's an interesting decision. I would say it's very often a very good
decision, but whoever makes that decision should be accountable for a good or bad decision and it
seems like companies are more accountable. They feel the pain of having made a bad decision more
because they can go bankrupt. There's much more day-to-day pressure to make good engineering
decisions. Government doesn't seem to be under the same level of pressure. Do you disagree with
that? I disagree with that. Everything in my history pushes me. You may be living... I may be
living in a different... Who knows? A planet or taking a different sort of drug. I won't mention
the name but I personally had a lot to do with a very large company here in the United States,
here in the New York area and it involved two brothers and a family who built it up into a
huge corporation. One of the brothers was kind of the dynamo of the family and he was more responsible
than anybody else building it up. But he took care of his brothers. He had a nice feeling about his
brother so the one brother who could not, you know, without help tie his shoes became a vice
president, got an enormous salary, got a beautiful office in a skyscraper, not that many blocks from
where I'm sitting right now and that was the way that family handled that company and all of his
relatives that were somewhere in this company doing a variety of whatever because in my experience
with this and because I went to the schools I told you, all my experiences with that group of people,
corporate execs, full of those stories, you know, they made mistake after mistake which they would
tell you about, didn't undermine there. They were always able to blame somebody else, something else
that scraped them through and had they not been able to they would have been replaced by another
person who did the same thing for as long as they could and they knew it. They would talk about it
at family events, that's how I know. I understand that you want the outside world to look at it
this way but it's not my experience. But again, that kind of thing at the risk of saying human
nature again, I wonder what kind of system allows for that more versus less. This is the question
of, I would call that, let's put that under the umbrella term of corruption, which system allows
for more corruption. But remember that the way I defined the different system is not more or less
government, it's more or less allowing a democratic workplace, reconfiguring it. What happens when
everybody has a vote, when you have to explain what the strategies are, what the alternatives are
to a larger number of people than a board of directors or major shareholders or whoever it is
that most companies are responsible to and now you've got a whole different universe. It's not
a small group of people, can't be hidden the way it's normally hidden, most of it on and on and on.
This is, you know, worker co-ops is what this is called in many parts of the world. So it's not
that I'm advocating something that's never been seen before, not at all. The Marxism I understand
is to pick from historical precedents the things that we think will work better. And I think if
all the people in an enterprise, just to drive the point home, democratically decided, they would
never give two or three individuals $100 million while everybody else can't send their kid to
college. If they can do that. So just to return, just to address this point about the particular
implementation of Marxism that was the early days in the Soviet Union, why did Stalinism,
for example, lead to so much bloodshed, do you think, in human suffering? Is there any elements
within the ideas of Marxism that catalyzed the kind of government, the kind of system
that led to that bloodshed? I don't think so. I think there are many things that led to the
bloodshed and so all that Stalin's regimes did. And, you know, I spent 10 years in my life
with another economist writing a book about that to try to explain from a Marxist position
the rise and fall of the Soviet Union. You might want to take a look at it sometime, but
there, I'm going to say a few things now, but all of those things are spelled out
in great detail with loads of empirical evidence, etc., in that work. Let me start with, you know,
playing a little bit with Hegel. The biggest impact that Marxism had on the Soviet Union
was really not so much what the Soviet Union did, but what the rest of the world did.
I mean, you had a really interesting move, and I'll give you a parallel from today.
The move was that the old Russian regime collapsed. World War I just, it fell apart.
The Tsar and all of that, it couldn't survive. It had already been in trouble. There was a
revolution in 1905. There was the loss of the war to Japan. I mean, if you know Russian history,
which I assume you do, you'll know that there was a lot leading up to the collapse in 1917.
And in some ways, it was fortuitous that the political group, very small, that could seize
the opportunity of that collapse, happened to be Marxists. You know, earlier on with Karensky,
the first government that tried, it wasn't people all that impressed by Marxism. It was people more
skeptical and would not have been called Marxists, probably, by history. They couldn't, they tried.
They couldn't. Lenin and his associates were able to take over from them later in that same year.
The rest of the world, though, was horrified. The rest of the world saw Marxism having taken this
immense leap from being a political party, a movement, critical of capitalism, yes,
but still not challenging the power. Now it had the power and in a big country. And they freaked out.
If you know American history, this country, the leadership of this country, went completely berserk.
I mean, we had a repression of the left, the likes of which we had not seen before. The 20s
were a time of palmerades in Boston, the Sakhal Vanzetti trials, really grim hostility. And you
had the four countries agreeing to invade the Soviet Union to try to crush the revolution. The U.S.,
Britain, France, and Japan all attacked 10,000 American troops. So what you had right away was
a notion in the West that this was, this was unthinkable. This was, there was a great professor
at Princeton, Meyer, forget his first name, who wrote this wonderful book about all American foreign
policy since 1917 has been obsessed with Russia. Even now, this fight with Ukraine is half about
Russia as if Russia still was the Soviet Union, as if people haven't figured out. That was a big
change back in 1989 and 90, you know, Yeltsin and Putin are not what you had before, or at least
they're not lending. They may not be so different from some of the other, but in any case.
So you had one factor was the utter isolation, the utter condemnation, the global, I mean,
Rosa Luxemburg is, I mean, I assume you know the, Rosa Luxemburg is hunted down in the streets
of Berlin. She's a critic of Lenin's, by the way, but she's a leftist, hunted down and hacked into
bits, killed. So you are attributing some, some of the bloodshed to the fact that basically the
rest of the world turned away. Turned against. Turned against, sort of, you turn against is the
better way. Very, yeah, I mean, not in order of importance, but it's, it's a very important part
of the psychology of being, you know, it's what you would call paranoid if there weren't quite
as much evidence that indeed there was a lot to be afraid of at that time. Nobody had ever done it.
Look, you could see the effects of it by Stalin inventing the idea, which had no support at first,
that you could have socialism in one country. That was thought to be
ridiculous, that socialism was internationalism. Marx was, Marx was against capitalism everywhere.
It was, you know, workers of the world unite, not workers of Russia unite, workers of the,
he had to go through a procedure of kind of coming to terms with the fact that the
revolution he had in Russia, which was tried in Berlin, was tried in Munich, was tried in
Budapest, was tried in Seattle here, they all failed. They all failed, and he's left. So,
the French would say, tout a, right, you know, all alone. That's one. The second thing is economic
isolation. Russia's a poor country and it needed what it got before the war, which were heavy
investments from the French and the Germans, particularly, but others too. Now this was all
cut off. And you can see the replay with the sanctions program. It's, we're gonna do it again,
we're gonna do it again. We have to do, we have, the world is different and the sanctions don't
work, but they're gonna try them. Because it's the history. But that culture was, today is
completely different. Russia's a different place today, but Russia has China and that changes
everything. And they don't get that here yet, but they will. Yeah, there's a very complicated
dynamic with China, even with India. Yep. Or Turkey. Brazil. Sorry to say human nature may
change at a slower pace than the geopolitical. That has occurred to me as well. I get that point.
So is there a, can you steel man the case or consider the case that there's something about
the implementation of Marxism, maybe because of the idealistic nature of focusing on the working
class and the workers unite, that naturally leads to formation of a dictatorial force,
a dictator that says, let us temporarily give power to this person to manage some of the details
of how to run the democracy of giving voice to the workers so that they get to choose.
And then that naturally leads to a dictator and there's naturally inhuman nature,
power and absolute power as the old adage goes, corrupts absolutely. Is it possible that whenever
you focus on Marx's ideals, you're going to end up with a dictator and often when you give too
much power to anyone, human, a small number of people, you're going to get into a huge amount
of trouble. You've put things together there that I would, I think if you, if you give,
put as a word, yeah, as German, the, if you, I remember, I told you my mother was born in
Germany. And then your dad is French. Yeah, but he was born in Metz, if you know you're European.
It's a city on the border of France and Germany. If you come from, Alsatians, Alsace in Germany.
So they're German speaking. Yeah, they're both. It's bilingual because it's been back and forth
so many times in medieval days already that it literally, you go from one store to another,
the proprietor here is French and the proprietor there is German, but they all speak both languages
because you don't speak either of them. I speak Russian. Russian, but not German.
Ukrainian, no, it took French for four years in high school, but I've forgotten all of it.
I remember the romance and the spirit of the language, but not the details. I'm sure I can
remember. If you allocate power unequally, undemocratically, and you do it for a very long
period of time and you do it on many levels of ideology, it is not surprising that it sticks
and it stays and you can make a political revolution or even an economic revolution
and you will discover it has a life of its own and it's going to take a long time before people
don't. If you have a religious tradition, Christianity, that prides itself on its monotheism
and that it doesn't want to have anything to do with the old Greek mythologies when there was Zeus
and Diana and all the others and they were very human like, but instead we have one who is the
absolute beginning and what are you doing? You're teaching people an authority line
that comes from the individual. If you have a sequence of kings, if in your feudal manner
the Lord sits called to the landlord, he has unspeakable power over everything that goes on
and you do this for thousands of years, you can make a Russian revolution in 1917,
but if you imagine you've gotten away from all that people assume without ever thinking about it,
you're going to have trouble. Stalin is figured here as the originator of his situation. He
wasn't. He never had that power. He may have thought that, but I don't. He's the product.
Look, the Cuban people made Fidel, who really wasn't that kind of guy. You know, he's a
baseball playing lawyer. That's what he was, but they made him into Tala. You're the product of
history. No, no, no. It was the systems, feudalism, the literature. It was the structures and
institutions that cultivated in people a mentality that has its own rhythm and doesn't follow the
calendar of a political revolution. That's the fundamental question. Is there something about
communism that creates a mentality that enables somebody like Stalin or Mao?
No, I think it's the social issues and problems the society has that make them then go to what
they find familiar to what seems to make sense and he's the guy. Look, let me give you an example
from American history. The Republican Party has traditionally in this country been the party
of private enterprise and minimum government. Income Trump runs for office in 2016, is elected.
Okay, what does he do? He commences the most massive tax increase and the most massive
government intervention in the worlds of economics that we've had for decades. Nobody says anything.
The Republicans cave and the Democrats largely too. They cave. He can throw a tariff on anything.
He gets up in front of the American people and he says the Chinese will pay the tariff.
That's not what a tariff is. It's not how a tariff works. He would flunk a freshman
course in economics, which everybody knows. Everybody who teaches these courses knows.
It doesn't matter. He's still calling the shots. What is going on here is that a society has come
to a point where it can't solve its problems and it begins what? To tap into older forms and all
of the laissez-faire and all of the individualism. Suddenly the Republican Party is gone and now
they're going to make an abortion illegal. The government is telling you what you can do with
your uterus. What? What? The government is being given more and more and more and more power.
They're hoping what? Do they like the government? No. They're desperate. This is not a pro-government
and it wasn't in Russia. They were in a desperate fix. He took advantage.
To which degree would you say Marx's ideas led to the creation of the
national socialism party of German workers, hence the Nazi party, the fascist party in the 30s
and the 40s at the head of whom was Hitler, which had just recently learned he was
employing number seven of the party or whatever, the seventh person to have joined the party
and have created one of the most consequential and powerful political parties in the history of
the 20th century? What degree did Marx's ideas, Marxism ideas have to play? It is the national
socialist party of German workers, workers. National socialist German worker party.
Worker party. National socialist German worker party. Here's the history. Did he care about the
workers or did he just use the workers as a populist message? The only thing that Marxism
did for Mr. Hitler was provide him with his stepping stone to power, but had nothing, no
other. He didn't know anything about it, didn't care anything about it, nor did the people around
him. Here's the story of what happened there, which I know largely through my own family and
plus my own history of the work that I did. The most successful socialist party in Europe
was the German party. It started around 1870. Marx was still alive. Some of his own family were
leaders, Ferdinand LaSalle and other his daughters. By the end of the century, it was the second most
important party in Germany. Nobody understood it. It was over. It was almost as big a shock to the
Europeans as was the Russian Revolution in 1917. Here was a political party that was now in
every German city, in every German town, powerful and enjoying its rise up. That's my family is
involved in this. I mean, I really do know the story. It meant that starting around 1968,
if you wanted to have any kind of presence in the German working class, you had to use the word
socialist. You had to. Otherwise, they wouldn't pay attention. The other parties called themselves
Catholic. Germany is divided. The northern two thirds is Protestant. The southern third is
Catholic. Munich and Bavaria is Catholic and every other part of Germany basically is Protestant.
You could be in the Catholic party. That was the south. Or you could be in various conservative
Prussian. If you wanted to have a presence in the working class, which was growing in Germany,
a very powerful capitalist country, expanding like crazy at this time, Germany was the major
competitor to Britain for the empire. The United States was coming up too, but it was Germany and
US taking over from Britain's empire. The German working class was it. Anybody who wanted to approach
the working class in whatever way had to come to terms and be friendly to socialism.
Other parties did this too, just like Hitler. They put the word socialist in their party,
but they wanted to make it clear that they weren't anything to do with the Soviet Union
or anything to do with Marxism. So they put the word national. Nazi is the first four letters
of national, national in German, and they ZI's how you spell national in the German
national socialism, but definitely not communists. That's right. They killed communists. They fought
communists in the street. They had pitched battles. They literally threatened each other's existence
and their life. And the first people that he arrested and put in jail were not Jews and Gypsies
and all the other people he eventually killed. It was communists. They were the number one
and socialist right behind them. Why? Because up until he takes power, January of 1933,
that's when Hitler takes power. The last elections, two of them in 1932, the socialist and communist
to vote together, 50% of the vote in Germany. So he appealed to the German manufacturers,
the German capitalists, and he said, the communists and socialists are going to win.
And you're just the capitalists. You have too few people. You need a mass space,
and I'm the only one that can do that.
So it was just the populist message that he used.
That's right. But it was explicitly done as a deal. The ruling group said to Hindenburg,
the old Prussian man who was in charge of the German government at the time,
you have to invite Hitler to form a new government. Otherwise, he would never have done it. He had
called Hitler nasty names before. The Prussian aristocracy looked down on Hitler as a little
funny man with a mustache who was Austrian, wasn't even German, for them that mattered.
So he comes in as the enemy, the smasher of socialism and communism, which he immediately does.
Only people who don't know or care about the history pick up on the word.
You know, it's like there are people here in the United States who like to say,
we are not a democracy. We are a republic, which is like saying, I'm not a banana. I'm a fruit.
You have to explain to these people a banana. So you have to explain to people, yes,
we're a republic, but we have a commitment to democracy as a way to govern the republic,
because to say you're a republic doesn't imply what kind of government you have to go through
that with people, so they kind of get it. And certain words have power beyond their actual
meaning that's used in communication, whether it's negative, like racist or positive, like freedom
of speech or Democrat or Democrat with a D. Yeah. And then you use that to mean something.
Who knows? Or negative, what, stop Donnie, stop being a socialist or something, whatever that
means that's not even used as any kind of philosophical or economic sense.
So let's fast forward to today. You mentioned Bernie Sanders.
There's another popular figure that represents some ideas of maybe let's call it democratic
socialism and maybe let's try to start to sneak up on a definition of what that could possibly
mean, but AOC, Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez, she's from these parts. So maybe if you can comment on
Bernie Sanders or AOC, are they open to some ideas in Marxism? Are they representing those
ideas well in both economic and the political sense? Okay. Where do I begin? The socialist
movement predates Marx was always larger than Marx and has gone on to develop separately after
Marx's death. So can we pause on that actually? Is there a nice way to delineate, draw a line
between Marxism and socialism? Or if Marxism is kind of a part of socialism, can you speak to
maybe try to define once again what Marxism is and what socialism is?
Right. Marxism is a systematic analysis heavily focused on economics and as I said earlier,
devoted to mostly a critique of capitalism and that's its strength, how it does that,
how it poses the questions, how it analyzes the way capitalism works, that is really the
forte of the Marxist tradition. Socialism is a bigger, broader tent within which Marxism
figures it's there so that people who aren't Marxist are nonetheless aware of Marxism,
like it more or less, study it more or less, but it's a broader notion that I like to use
this sentence to describe. It's a broad idea that we can do better than capitalism, that really
there are all kinds of things about capitalism that are not what we as modern citizens of the world
think are adequate. We are in a tradition that goes back to all the people who thought they
could do better than slavery and all the people who thought they could do better than feudalism.
We've made progress. Fuedalism was a progress over slavery. Capitalism was a progress over both of
them and progress hasn't stopped and we are the people who in a variety of ways want the progress
to go further and are not held back by believing that capitalism is somehow the best beyond which
we cannot go or even think. We find that to be, in the worst sense of the word, a reactionary way
of thinking and we're that large community. Many of us are not interested in economics all that
much. We don't think that's the focal area. We are socialists, for example, because we want to do
something to deal with climate change. We think the world is about to kill itself physically
and we want to take steps with other people to stop that, to fix that, etc. So that's for me
a kind of difference. It's a little difficult to say because there's no other figure like Marx
that has an equal impact, an equal place within the broad socialist tradition.
The only tradition that comes close might be the anarchist tradition, but that's very specialized
and that's a whole other kind of conversation. Whatever you say, the influence of the great
anarchist thinkers, Kropotkin, Bakunin, Sorrell, and others still doesn't amount to the impact that
Marx and Marxism have had so far. That could change, but up to this point that's a way of
understanding the relationship. Yeah, that's interesting that some of the ideas within
anarchism, and of course it's one of the more varied disciplines, because there's such,
maybe by definition, such variety in their thinkers, but they kind of stand for a
dismantling of a power center and that, if not equates, tends to rhyme with some of the ideas
of socialism. Absolutely. So where you have the... There's a whole train of thought in socialist ideas
and in Marxist ideas that uses the phrase, quote, the withering away of the state. That's a quotation
from Lenin. People should understand that's a quotation from Lenin and it was made by Lenin,
positive. In other words, Lenin was saying, that's a good thing. That's something we stand for.
We want to create the conditions under which there is a... Because you remember, the
communists or whatever, they wouldn't call that at first in Russia before the revolution. They
were just socialists. They were hunted down and persecuted by the government left and right.
They had no love for the government. The government was their literal everyday enemy and
being critical of government didn't just mean this particular government, but of the whole...
Being a Marxist, you always ask the questions of the social constitution of whatever it is
you're struggling against. So there was this interest, why is the state so important? Especially
because if you understand feudalism, particularly early feudalism, it didn't have powerful states.
One of Lenin's greatest books is called The Economic History of Russia and he goes back centuries.
It's a huge book, three or four inches thick and I'm one of the few people who've read it.
He's very good about the absence of a strong central government in many parts of feudalism,
including inside Russia, but also in other parts of Europe. The development of a powerful central
state comes towards the end of feudalism as it is desperate to hold on, which ought to be suggestive
that maybe the turn to powerful governments here in the United States or in Europe is maybe also
because this system is exhausted and can't go on and has to marshal every last bit of power it can
not to be lost in history. It would be interesting to see what the Soviet Union
would look like if Lenin never died. A lot of people have asked that question over the years,
a lot of people. The area is stalling, sliding in in the middle of the night,
erasing the withering away of the state part. Yes, exactly. So just to return briefly back
to AOC and Bernie Sanders, what are your thoughts about these modern political figures that represent
some of these ideas and they sometimes refer to those ideas as democratic socialism? Right.
The crucial thing about Bernie and about AOC, and it's particularly true about Bernie,
because AOC is much younger and Bernie's an older man. Bernie, being roughly my age,
has been around formatively as a student, as an activist, then coming up through the ranks in
Burlington, Vermont as a mayor and all the rest. He lived through, for lack of a better term,
I would call Cold War America. And the taboo in Cold War America, running from around 1945-6
to the present, I mean really never stopped, was a Manichaean worldview. The United States is good,
it defines democracy, and the Soviet Union is awful, it defines whatever the opposite
of democracy should be called. Good here, evil there. It was taken so far that even among the ranks
of academic individuals, it was impossible to talk, have a conversation. I mean,
I can't tell, just make it very personal. The number of times I would raise my hand in my classes
at Harvard or Stanford or Yale, and I would ask a question that had something to do with Marxism,
because I was studying it on my own. There were no courses to teach this to me, except by people
who trashed it, other than that, and I didn't want that. So I would ask a question, and I would see
in the faces of my teachers, both those I didn't much care for, and those who were good teachers
that I liked, fear. It was just fear. They didn't want to go there. They didn't want to answer my
question. And after a while, I got to know some of them, and I found out why, because you don't
know how the rest of the class is going to understand this. Either they would have to say,
I don't know, which would be the honest truth for many of them, but a professor does not want to
say in a classroom, I don't know, that it's not cool. Or if they knew, they'd have to say something
that indicated they didn't know really much, and they weren't even going to do that.
Or they would know something, and maybe that would be because they were interested. They did not want
the rest of the students to begin to say, oh, you know, Professor Smith, he's interested.
Mm-mm. This is not good for your career. You don't know how this is going to
play out. Who's going to say what to whom? And I could see in their faces what I later learned,
because they told me, don't come to my office hours. We're in the office. We can talk about it.
But that's how bad it was.
Is it not still?
Pretty much. In my field, the great so-called debate. I mean, I find it boring, but the great
debate for my colleagues is between what's called neoclassical economics and Keynesian economics.
Neoclassical, the government should stay out of the economy, less a fair or liberalism.
And the Keynesian saying, no, you crazy neoclassical. If you do that, you'll have great depressions,
and the system will collapse. You need the government to come in to solve the problems,
to fix the weaknesses. And they hate each other, and they throw each other out of their jobs.
One of the very few things they can do together that they agree on is keeping people like me out.
That they can find common ground to do. So I had to learn it all on my own.
Why am I telling you this? Because this taboo means that all of the complicated developments
within Marxism and within socialism of the post-World War II period,
the vast bulk of all of that is unknown, not just to the average American person,
but to the average American academic, to the average American who thinks of himself or herself
as an intellectual. I mean, I have had to spend ridiculous amounts of my time explaining Soviet
history to have no idea. Or saying, there's this man, Lukacs, a Hungarian Marxist. He really had
interest in, or to explain that Gramsci was not a great literary critic. He was head of the
Communist Party of Italy for most of his adult life. What does that mean? Why, you like Gramsci
as a literary critic, but they didn't even know. They don't even know. It's been erased.
It's a little bit like stories I've heard about Trotsky and his influence kind of erased in the
Soviet Union because he obviously fell out of favor. And so somehow all of his writings,
many of which are very interesting and complicated. Anyway, so what you're going to have in this
country is a slow awakening of socialism from a long hibernation called the Cold War.
I never expected, to be very honest with you, that I would live to see. I knew it would come
because of these things always do, but I didn't expect to see it. So I have been surprised
as have a lot of us that when it starts to happen, it happens fast.
So you see Bernie as an early sign of the awakening from the Cold War to accept the ideas.
Always a socialist. We all knew. And everybody who paid attention, he denied it.
But 2016, he makes a decision, momentous, to run for president. He's just a senator from Vermont.
Vermont is one of the smallest states in the Union. People who live in Vermont love to tell you
that there are more cows than people in Vermont, etc. etc. So here from this little state,
this elderly gentleman with a New York City accent runs for all and says, I'm a socialist.
And when they attack him, he doesn't run away. I'm a socialist. I'm a socialist.
Now he had been. It wasn't a secret that suddenly got out. But the great question, and I don't mind
telling you because I went to the right schools, I know a lot of people, you know,
Janet Yellen was my classmate at Yale and stuff like that. So I was speaking with a high official
of the Democratic Party and I said, well, what do you think about Bernie entering the race?
Makes no difference. They get 1% of the vote. He was wrong. They had no idea what was coming.
But the truth is, I didn't either. It wasn't just that he didn't get it. I thought his 1% was probably
right. So we were both wrong. Yeah, change can happen fast. Do you think AOC might be president
one day? Yeah. Possible. Possible. But two things. Number one, it's fast. Number two,
it's going to go in the following direction, I would guess. You begin with the most moderate,
calm, non-confrontational socialism you can imagine. So not AOC or Bernie.
No, no, they are not confrontational in my judgment.
In terms of the ideas of socialism. I mean, they're both very feisty.
They're feisty personally. But not ideologically. You know, she is, Bernie is also,
you know, in honest moments, and they're both really are pretty honest folks,
at least in my experience. In honest moments, Bernie will tell you that what he advocates
as democratic socialism is pretty much what FDR was in the 1930s. It was a kind of popular
government tax the rich a lot more than you do now to provide a lot more support for the working
class than you do now. That's not a fundamental change. That's what he means by socialism.
When he talks about it, and he's asked for examples, he mentions Denmark a lot. Okay,
that's consistent. That's the softest kind of socialism. And that's where we're going to
start in a country coming out of hibernation. Pretty soon, it's already happening. There'll
be people who need and want to go further in the direction of socialism than Bernie and AOC are
comfortable with. You can already see the shoots of it now. You know, AOC voted together with
most of the others to support the money for Ukraine. Okay, that lot of people in the socialist
movement do not support that. And that's going to have, you know, I don't know exactly how
that's going to work out. But that should give people an idea. There are disagreements and they're
going to fester and they're going to grow. People in the socialist sphere don't support money
from the United States in the large amounts that it is being sent to Ukraine. Is it because of,
it's a fundamentally, the military industrial complex is a capitalist institution kind of thing?
No, there are some people for whom that's the issue. Then there are people for whom
this is, you know, it's guns and butter and why are we, why are we over there when we have such
needs at home that are being neglected? And then there are people who, well, go back to what we
talked about at the beginning, who are more like Lenin and Debs. This is a fight between
Western capitalism and Russian oligarchs and wannabe oligarchs in Ukraine and what are we
doing here? We have to insist that these forces sit down at the bargaining table and negotiate
a settlement, don't kill large numbers of Ukraine. I mean, everybody's willing to fight
to the last Ukrainian is a little strange here. What are you doing? You're supposed to be in
favor of peace, you know, and for the United States, which just finished invading and occupying
Afghanistan and Iraq to be against another country invading. I mean, who in the world
is going to take this seriously? This is crazy. You know, I invade, it's good and you invade,
it's terrible. What? You know, what are you doing? Why are you doing that? What's going on here?
All of these questions are being active, by the way, not just by socialists,
by lots of other people too, inside the Democratic Party and also inside the Republican Party.
You watch that Tucker Carlson or people like that, they are against the stuff in Ukraine. They
don't want the money spent there, they don't want the weapons sent there, they don't like the whole
policy and Trump wobble. So, Mr. Biden's policy has got all kinds of critics on the left and the
right and every day that this thing lasts, these criticisms get bigger. Anyway, the point is that
AOC and Bernie should be, I think, evaluated as the early shoots after a long winter of Cold War
isolation from the whole, you know, when I explained to people the contribution made,
for example, to modern Marxism, I'll give you an example, by the French philosopher
Louis Althusser, I don't know if the name means anything to you. Okay. He was the rector of
the cole Normale Suprieure in Paris. That's the equivalent. Imagine in this country if there
were a university that combined Harvard, Yale, Princeton and MIT. It would be the university.
Well, the cole Normale in France in Paris is the. He was a tenured professor who became the
rector. The rector is like the president of the university. An active member of the French
Communist Party, most of his adult life. That was possible in France during the Cold War.
That was unthinkable in this country. You could not in a million years, right?
So Althusser, as a philosopher, tried to bring a version of postmodernism
into Marxism with enormous impact all over the world when he traveled, not just in Europe,
all over, right? So if you want to look him up, I'll spell it out for you.
Althusser, Luis, Althusser. Look him up. You'll see tons of stuff.
By the way, MIT Press is a major publisher, if I remember, of his works in English.
By the way, the textbook I wrote in Economics, in case you're ever interested,
was also published by the MIT Press. And the title? Contending Economic Theories,
Neoclassical, Keynesian, and Marxian. That's an MIT. Marxian. Yeah, that's right.
And by the way, when we think, I don't know if there's an interesting distinction between
Marxian economics and Marxist. I suppose Marxism is the umbrella of everything that.
I only use it because Marxist uses a noun. A person is a Marxist. Marxian uses an adjective
to qualify, but I don't mean some great difference. There's a last point I would like to make about
AOC and Bernie. That's also general. I'm a historian too. And I know that the transition
out of feudalism in Europe to capitalism was a transition that took centuries and that occurred
in fits and starts. So for example, a feudal manor would start to disintegrate, serfs would run away,
then run into a town. How would they live in the town? They had no land anymore because they had
run away from the feudal manor. A deal was struck without the people involved in the deal understanding
what they were doing. A merchant would say to one of these serfs, I'm in the business of buying and
then reselling stuff and living off the difference. But you know, I could make more money if I produced
some of this stuff myself rather than buy it from somebody else. So I'm going to make you a deal.
I'm going to give you money once a week. I'll give you money what we would later call a wage.
And you come here and under my supervision, you make this crap that I'm going to then sell.
And this all works out. In other words, there were efforts unconscious, not self-aware,
to go out of feudalism to a new system. Some of them lasted a few days and then fell apart.
Some of them lasted weeks or months or years, but it took a long time before the conditions were
ready for a kind of a general switch. And once that was done, it grew on itself and became the
global capitalist system we have today. That's the only model we have. So for me, that's what
I see when I look at socialism. I see the Paris commune was an event, an attempt. It lasted a
few weeks. I see Russia. That was an attempt lasted 70 years. Then I see, and you will fill in the
blank, I see these are all early experiments. These are all you learn things to do, learn things
never to do again. The good, the bad. What do you build on? How do you learn?
And that's what the socialist and Marxist tradition, when it's serious, that's what it does.
In your ideas, sort of capitalism was a significant improvement over the feudalism.
And we are coming to an age and over slavery, and we're coming to an age where capitalism
will die out and make, it's not that capitalism is how fundamentally broken. It's better than
the things that came before it, but there's going to be things yet better and they will be grounded
in the ideas of Marxism and socialism. Is there just a linger briefly on the way Marxism is used
as a term on Twitter? There's something called, I'm sorry if I'm using the terms incorrectly, but
cultural Marxism or the criticisms of universities being infiltrated by cultural Marxists.
I'm not exactly sure. I don't pay close enough attention, but it's woke. There's a kind of
woke ideology that I'm not exactly sure. What is the fundamental text? Who's the Karl Marx of
wokeness? All I do know is that there's certain characteristics of woke ideology, which is
hard lines are drawn between the good guys and the bad guys. Basically, everyone is a bad guy,
except the people that are very loudly nonstop saying that they're the good guy.
That applies for racism, for sexism, for gender politics, identity politics, all that kind of
stuff. Is there any parallels between Marxian economics and Marxist ideology and whatever
is being called Marxism on Twitter? No, not much. One of the consequences of the taboo
after World War II is that Marxism, like socialism and communism, become swear words.
It's like calling somebody, well, I won't use bad language, but using a four-letter word to
describe somebody. So instead of calling them this or that, you call them a Marxist. In many
circles, this is even worse than whatever other adjective you might have used, but it doesn't
have a particular meaning that I can assess. The closest you get is your little list. It is
somebody who is concerned about race and sex and sexual orientation and gender and all of those
things and wants there to be transgendered bathrooms and I don't like any of these people,
so I slap the word Marxism or the phrase cultural Marxism because it isn't Marxism about
getting more money or controlling the industry or all those things that dimly we know Marxists
somehow are concerned about. So this is odd since they don't know much about Marxism. I've always
been interested in culture. I mean, Lukacs, the man I mentioned to you before, Gramsci,
that's what they're famous for, the analysis of what Marxism particularly has to say about culture.
Gramsci writes a great length about the Catholic Church about theater and painting in Italy and
on and on. I mean, this is just ignorance talking. They don't know anything about that. They wouldn't
know what the names are. It's a label that summarizes kind of a shorthand. I'm against all of this. I
don't want to be told that there's ugly racism in this country and it always has been or sexism or
phobia against gay people or whatever it is that's agitating them, Marxism or socialism. I mean,
it's just, it's like socialism is the post office. It is a mentality. Well, but I don't blame them.
I mean, it's childish. It's mean-spirited, but it comes out of the fact no one ever sat them down
and said, here is this tradition. It's got these kinds of things that people kind of share and
these big differences. Look, an intelligent society, which this country is, could have and should have
done that. It was fear and a kind of terror that made them behave in the way they did and we're now
seeing it. Having said that, there is such a thing as cultural Marxism. What that is is simply those
Marxists who devoted themselves to analyzing how it is that a particular culture is on the one hand
shaped by capitalism and on the other hand, it becomes a condition for capitalism to survive
and grow. In other words, how do we analyze the interaction between the class struggle on the job
and attitude towards sexuality or movements in music or whatever else culture. And there are
Georg Lukacs, this Hungarian, great name in there, the greatest of all the names, Antonio Gramsci,
and a modern name just died a couple of years ago, a British intellectual named Stuart Hall,
H-A-L-L. If I were teaching, which I have done, a course in cultural Marxism, those would be three
major blocks on the syllabus. I would give you articles and books to read of their stuff,
because it has been so seminal in provoking many, many others.
So there is something to be said and understood about the kind of culture that capitalism creates
and the kind of culture that enables capitalism. Yes. And Marxists are particularly those who like
to look at that interaction. In other words, they're interested in how capitalism shapes culture
and how culture shapes capitalism. There's another name, I forgot. Stuart Hall is British,
Gramsci is Italian, Lukacs is Hungarian. The German is Walter Benjamin, B-E-N-J-A-M-I-N.
He was a member of the Frankfurt School, which is a huge school of Marxism that developed in
Frankfurt, Germany, and that has a lot of people, many of whom were interested in cultural questions.
It was a bit of a reaction against the narrow Marxism that was so focused on economics and
politics. There were people who said, you're leaving out very important parts of modern society
that are shaping the economy as much as they are shaped by it. And it was that impetus to open
Marxism to be more inclusive in what it deemed to be important to understand that this cult,
and they call themselves cultural Marxists, but they had a completely different meaning
from this. This is just bad-mouthing. That's all. Let me ask a more personal question. So
for most of the 20th century, no, not most, but a large many decades in the United States
as a consequence of the Cold War and before being a Marxist is one of the worst things you could be.
Have you had dark periods in your own life where you've gone to some dark places in your mind,
where it was difficult, like self-doubt, difficult to know, like, what the hell am I doing when
you're surrounded by colleagues and people? You said prestigious universities, both personal
interests of career, but also as a human being when everybody, you know, kind of looks at you
funny because you're studying this thing. Did that ever get you real low?
No. I know people who had exactly what you said. I mean, your question's perfectly reasonable.
If I were you, I'd be asking me that question, too.
And what's wrong with you?
Nothing wrong with the question. And here's the honest truth. I don't know how anomalous I am.
I really don't. But the truth is, no, I have, if my wife were sitting here, she'd tell you
what she tells me, which is I have been tremendously lucky in my life, which is true.
But then again, luck never is the only explanation for things that's part of it.
What can I say? I didn't choose the time of my birth. I didn't choose
the communities in which I grew up or the schools I attended or anything else.
No, but the fact that there was no courses or extensive courses on Marxian economics.
But you know, again, I'm haggled. On the one hand, I was denied good instruction.
On the other hand, I had to go out and learn it on my own. And the motivation
when you do that is very different. I'm not the student who sits there with my notebook,
taking notes of what the great professor says and reading the text and getting ready for the exam.
I don't have an exam. I'm doing something slightly risqu, you know, kind of romantically different
and oppositional. I was able to find always one or two professors that I could talk to
outside of the classroom situation, other students who felt enough similar to me
that we could get together and read these books and talk about them. I had a number of really
fortuitous people who were kind to me and gave me of their time and their effort to teach me
along the way. And I've had the benefit that because I went to all these fancy schools,
I do know a lot of people who are in high places in this culture. And when I have been put in
difficult positions, I often waive my pedigree and it works like garlic with the devil. They're
back away. They're back away. Because Americans are very deferential to that kind of academic
prestige. But there's a personal psychological thing that seems that you have never been shaken
by this. You have just naturally somebody who just has perseverance.
Well, I would put it, I mean, I understand what you're saying, but I would put it a little differently.
I think capitalism struck me early on in my life as not that great a system.
And nothing has happened to change my mind. In other words, the development
just kept giving me more and more evidence. And I must say over the last 10 years,
what's really changed the last 10 years. I mean, I can't describe to you how big that changes.
And that may be more important than anything else we've discussed.
Up until 10 years ago, I would do a public event, an interview on television or a radio thing or
give a talk at some conference or something. Once every two or three months, I'd be invited
and I would do it. Like academics often do. I now do two to three to four interviews every day.
So does a hunger, wow, is there a hunger? It's fascinating.
And I want to be honest with you. As I say at the end of some of my talks,
I allow there to be a kind of a pregnant pause from the podium, you know,
that I lean into the microphone and I say with as much smile as I can get, I'm having a time of my
life. And that's the truth. I never expected, look, I'm used to teaching a classroom,
a seminar for graduate students with eight or nine or 10 students, or a regular undergraduate
class with 30 or an occasional introductory course with a few hundred. I've done all of those
things many times, but an audience, you know, that I can count in the hundreds of thousands
on YouTube and all of that. No, that's new. Is there advice you can give given your bold and
nonstandard career and life advice you can give to high school students, college students about
how to have a career like that, or maybe how to have a career or a life they can be proud of?
Yeah. First of all, my advice is go for it. The conditions for doing that now are infinitely
better than they were when I had to do it. And I could do it. And I can, I'm happy I did it.
Becoming a teacher is one of those decisions I made that I've never regretted.
And I've never regretted being a critic of this society. Never. I find it edifying. I find it,
I mean, the gratitude people expressed to me for helping them see kind of what's going on
is unbelievably encouraging. I mean, what can I tell you? So that feels you,
pointing out that the emperor has no clothes, it feels you, that's a life not just important.
Because most of the people who say something like that to me are people who, if they had the
vocabulary and some of them do, would say, you know, I thought I was seeing through that
outfit that I was wearing. I thought it and they did. And all they needed was a little extra,
this information or that factoid or this logic. And they have that. And I remember having that too.
When I had a teacher who made something clear that had been murky, I always felt gratitude.
And now I get that gratitude, a good bit. And yes, it is enormously gratifying. And I'm not
sure I could get it any other way. And I have learned and I'm walking proof that being a
critic of society and doing it systematically and sharing it with other people makes for a
very good life, a very good life. Speaking of which, however, one other aspect of human nature
is that life comes to an end. Do you think about your death? Are you afraid of it?
Afraid of it? No. Think about it? Yes. Yes. I'm not afraid. I've always thought, you know,
death is hard for the people that are left when you're dead, you know. I worry more about my
wife. I'm very attached to my wife. I might mention to you, I got married when I was 23
years old and that's my wife to this day. So I'm lucky because if you get married to anybody
at age 23, it's either luck or it isn't. What role has love played in your life? Enormous.
Because I came from a family, you know, if your family is political refugees, which mind
who had to interrupt their lives, moved to another continent, learn another language,
find another life income and job and the disruption goes real deep for any refugee. So
my mother and father were both refugees. They met as refugees.
So I had to, in a way, make it up to them. I had to be, I was the first child of their,
I have a younger sister, but I was the first child and, you know, there's a lot of psychological
pressure on you if you're in that situation. Nobody means you harm, but you've got to do
what they couldn't, what was shut off to them in a way they want you to do. It's the closest
they're going to get to what they had hoped and my parents were both university students.
My father was a lawyer. My mother had to leave the university to run for her life.
So I had to perform, you know. I went to high school here in the United States. I had to get all
A's. I had to be on the football team. I had to play the violin in the orchestra. I had to do all
these because everything had to be achieved. So I'm an achievement crazy person that way.
But that's functional in this dysfunctional society.
But on top of that, that's an achievement within the game of this particular society,
but then love seems to be a thing that's greater than that game. Is that something
that made you a better person? How was it made you a better Marxian and a better...
Everything because my wife, my wife by profession is a psychotherapist.
Excellent. I love it.
And I needed it. Yeah.
And so I married it. I didn't know what I was doing at the time, but I think,
as I look back on it, that was more than a little what was going on.
And she has tutored me all my life about a whole range of aspects of life
that my family never talked about, never dealt with, never, at least explicitly
engaged in any of that.
Because it was all about survival, the immigrant challenges, survival.
Survive, survive. And you're so busy that you tell yourself you can't do that.
Of course, you can. And there are other reasons why you're not going to look at those problems.
But the survival is so urgent that you can fool yourself this way. And my parents did that.
One last question. What's the meaning of life, Richard Wolff? Why are we here?
I will quote you, Mr. Marx.
Let's go.
Life is struggle. And for me, I have found that to be true, that the struggle,
whether it is to build a relationship with your child, I have two children,
whether it's to build one with your spouse, whether it's to understand a complicated argument
and simplify it so that you can share the pleasure of understanding this relationship
to a student or to an audience. These are, it's a struggle to do all those things.
But that network of struggles, that makes life interesting, intriguing, and satisfying.
And meaningful. And very meaningful.
And that latter thing, I got to say, you do masterfully. You're one of the great communicators
and educators out there today. And it's a huge honor that you have sit with me for so many hours.
Thank you. This is awesome. Thanks for listening to this conversation with Richard Wolff.
To support this podcast, please check out our sponsors in the description.
And now, let me leave you with some words from Karl Marx.
The philosophers have only interpreted the world in various ways.
The point, however, is to change it.
Thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.