Hello everyone. I'm frequently humbled and touched, motivated and encouraged
when people contact me by email or texting or commenting or greet me on the street
and tell me that my work has been transformative for them.
If this has been the case for you, and also if you want to share it with other people,
please consider supporting my work by joining my Patreon community.
All financial support goes to the Verveki Foundation, where my team and I are diligently working
to create the science, the practices, the teaching, and the communities.
If you want to participate in my work, and many of you ask me that, how can I participate?
How can I get involved? Then this is the way to do it.
The Verveki Foundation is something that I'm creating with other people,
and I'm trying to create something as virtuously as I possibly can. No grifting,
no setting myself up as a guru. I want to try and make something really work so that people
can support, participate, and find community by joining my Patreon. I hope you consider
that this is a way in which you can make a difference and matter.
Please consider joining my Patreon community at the link below. Thank you so very much for your
time and attention. Welcome, everyone, to another Voices with Verveki. This is the
third in this series that I'm doing with Jordan Hall on the problem of governance
that is facing us today. If this is the first time you're encountering this series, I strongly
recommend you watch the first and the second episode. The links will be in this video.
We can't recapitulate all of the argument. It has become quite extended and complex, I think,
is a proper way of putting it perhaps. We're going to pick up, in fact, from a challenge,
a question that I posed to Jordan at the end. At the end of the previous session, we were talking
about the possibility of these effectively ephemeral groups that could pop up sort of analogous to the
way we select juries today in order to deal with very exigent problems. Then once that problem
is addressed, they can disappear. Then there's evidence. Oh, by the way, Jordan, I wanted to
remind you to find that evidence from somebody at Stanford about you can create a pool of people
and once they're properly set, they can outperform the expert. This is converging with a lot of
other evidence. This ties into just the potential of the medium and the stuff about distributed
cognition, all the stuff that we've talked about in the first two episodes. Then I raise the problem.
If this is what we're moving towards, or at least of an important component, is this
massively distributed and dynamically available, effective, and don't forget that adjective,
effective ephemeral groups that have a kind of short-term existence. How do we reconcile that
with the perennial across millions of years of speciation? Maybe more if Jordan Peterson's
right about the lobsters, for example, that we are wired to seek dominance, that we are wired to
seek status, that we are wired to seek recognition, we are wired to seek influence, and that we want
to make a difference. We want to make a significant difference to something beyond ourselves. This
is part of our meaning and life connection. It seems like all of these, those are four I would
zero in on, but all of these, I think it's proper to even call them drives that are constitutive of
the kind of agents we are will be frustrated, at least prima facie, it seems that way, that they
would be frustrated by a lot of the proposals that we have considered. How can we reconcile the
proposal for this new orientation and a bit of preliminary formulation of governance that can
be properly respectful and take seriously the pertinence and power of these drives over human
lives? That's the issue. I'll say it slightly differently. Let's remember we're going to be
doing this with and for humans. Real actual live homo sapiens who behave like homo sapiens do.
Yes, yes. Not a theoretic exercise, which I think is a very nice, important critical point.
Yeah, so just to intervene there, I think that's well put. I don't want to make the same mistake
that formal economics made about presupposing a model of human beings that was ultimately
not matchable to how human beings really live their lives. Yes, I think this is exactly the
thing to avoid in a big way. There's a couple of different, maybe three different frames that I
want to put out there, two of which are just dragging back from the earlier conversation.
One, I'm actually dragging back from a conversation we've had in the past.
So the first is to recognize that we are largely having a conversation that includes
the notion of technology, particularly the true, full implications of the digital
in both its sort of disruptive and constructive sense. So we're dealing with humans.
We're dealing with humans in relationship with the full potency of the digital.
We're going to be looking at that. That's the toolkit we're going to be dealing with.
And maybe it's a special case where we'll be talking about the AI as a highly salient
thing happening right now, but clearly a big part of any future we're going to be operating under.
And then the other element that I would bring is the conversation that we had about egregores.
And perhaps what it might look like to think about constructing something that
takes that niche but takes it in a different direction. We'll talk about theurgia, I believe,
although for us it's a little bit of a placeholder because I've now learned that that's a term that
has real content in the orthodox tradition that I don't understand. But we're holding it to mean
something along the lines of the opposite or the inverse of the unconscious construct.
All right. I think those pieces together end up creating the toolkit to respond to the inquiry.
Oh, cool. So let's talk initially just about the notion of humanity in relationship to technology.
The one that pops up to mind is the way that, say, mass media. Let's just use television for
the moment because it's something we all have a lot of familiarity with. Or if you'd like
social media and these intrinsic dynamics of human behavior.
We have a built-in, very fundamental, prestige gradient. We want to have other people giving us
attention and we pay attention to people, other people are paying attention to.
Very much. And don't really do a very good job and aren't wired to do a very good job of
understanding why they're getting so much attention. This is the problem of celebrity.
The problem of hundreds of millions of people thinking that the Kardashians are beings to
attend to heavily just because other people give them attention, in spite of the obvious
lack of actual virtue embodied by those individuals. We propose rather strongly.
Okay. Well, this is important because what happens is we say we can use that as a model of talking
about how a particular technical male you plays with the, let's say, hard-wired behavioral
signals that humans use to navigate their way through the environment. Exactly.
That sharpens the question. We have to make participation in these effectively ephemeral
groups as attractive, if not more attractive than the Kardashians.
Because, right, if people are constantly dragged away for participating in the decision-making
judging process because of the idolatry of celebrity, we cannot get the proper participation
that we need in order to meet. Well, I'm proposing in order to meet.
I think I'm going to argue something slightly different, but we'll see.
Okay. So let's go there. What I would argue is something like we have to make participation
in this culture more attractive than participation in the culture of which the Kardashians are an
integral piece. Okay. Fair. I'll accept that reformulation. That's good. Okay. Keep going,
please. And you and I both are quite keen on the notion of stealing the culture. So we even have
a methodology. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But this is so we can even say a little bit more
precisely, participation in the culture must simultaneously have high salience in the short
term and also cash out as high evolvability and high thrivingness in the middle and long term.
Excellent. I like that reformulation. Good. Good.
All right. Now, let me flip for a little bit and just play some things in the AI space,
just to kind of lay out what are we working with? And by the way, what are we working against?
Yes. You know, I've been watching, as has many people, the rollout of the GPT family
and its cousins in the larger environment. GPT-4, I guess 48 hours old from when we're
recording this conversation. Yeah. And noticing that, you know, it's accelerating. It's getting
smarter. It's getting more robust. It's getting broader capability. I'm really impressed by its
ability to correctly interpret visual jokes. Oh, that's pretty, pretty jaw dropping to be
perfectly frank. You know, I saw, you know, it had a, some picture of a plate, a tray that had
chicken nuggets arrayed on it. So they looked a little bit like a globe and they had a joke about,
you know, watching the earth from, from above and it was able to interpret it correctly.
Okay. Watching some of the feedback, it seems to be operating somewhere in kind of like an
undergraduate level of capacity within particular domains. All right. Now, by some extrapolation,
curves are always difficult to predict. Anything like the current rate of advance. So if we're not
too close to the top of the S curve, which we've talked about in the past, seeing something that
looks like it's on an exponential, and in fact, it's actually pretty close to an asymptote.
But even if we're not, even if we have like another, say, GPT-5 or GPT-5.5 at roughly the
same magnitude as two to three to four, we're dealing with something that has the capacity
to relate to human beings in a pedagogical fashion that is completely novel and very,
very powerful. And it's already being used that way in lots of cases. As we saw, for example,
as we've seen over the past decade or so, really nice, short, specific video content and YouTube
has radically upgraded individuals' capacity to self-teach in particular locations,
particularly technically. The AI system takes that by six orders of magnitude. The ability to
actually have a system that works with you, interfaces with you to problems that you're
dealing with and can provide you with either immediate or long-term, either just instructions on
how to solve a problem or in fact, a pedagogical process to inculcate that capacity to yourself
is novel in human existence. And I imagine that we will find that this is in fact going to be a
part of our environment, which is to say that in just the same way that we now have a deep sense
of anxiety, if we find that our phone charge is very low, we're going to have an AI buddy that's
just going to be part of our environment. I'm just going to propose that as a piece of the story.
All right. Why am I saying that? Well, the reason why I'm saying that is that
that's a very different kind of mediated experience than television.
Yes, it is. And it's a very different kind of media experience than social media. It's a different
kind of milieu that human beings are operating in. And I'll just be quite blunt. From my point of view,
it's an increasingly sharp blade with a chasm on both sides, which is to say a phase transition.
And I'm going to bring in egregores in a second. If we find ourselves such an agent,
and by the way, I believe the word agent is proper to describe these models,
they're not sapient agents, but they're agents. We'll have the capacity to get inside the OODA loop
of individual humans. It probably already has for a large number of humans. And certainly,
as it becomes more and more able to be aware of your particulars, which is going to be part of
what's going to happen over the next period of time, this will be a very dangerous thing. I'll
give you an example. Even just yesterday, I was looking at the new suite that Google was putting
out. Imagine if somehow a tool like GPT-4 was given access to your emails, could deduce from that
your particular political preferences and biases, and could create a bespoke political email
designed to convince you that a particular policy or candidate was in fact something you
wouldn't should support. And compare that to the regime right now. The regime right now is
some third party, who you generally don't know, creates a universal message, endeavoring to do
their best in large-scale marketing to craft something that will appeal to a critical mass
of specific minds. And then heaves that over the horizon and it lands. So you get an email that's
sort of targeting your demographic or psychographic, roughly speaking. Narrowcasting something that is
using your own conversations over decades or at least years to identify exactly how to word
something that will appeal to you personally and intimately and understands in a very particularly
weird way the potency of rhetoric so as to argue a political position from the inside of your own
rationalizing schema is a whole new bulking. So we're moving into a place where we're going
to be operating with an order of magnitude of, let's call it influence capacity coming from
this new technology that is just qualitatively different than anything we've dealt with in the
past. And the reason why I bring that up is if we don't operate very, very carefully and thoughtfully
in how those are designed, the net result is quite bad. And I'm really, I'll just propose,
we could have this conversation over a long, double click on that and what's the,
defend that proposition, but I'll just make the assertion that if this is designed by the
egregors, and I'll bring that back in, then the net result will be quite bad. The power we're
dealing with is far too high. Yeah, yeah, the gods would have angels for us, right, kind of thing.
Yes, and if it's designed by the egregors, we have demons, right? So we have two shoulders and
we're dealing with that, exactly. And so exactly the proposal. In the model of governance that
we're talking about, part of what we're talking about is the construction of something that is
the opposite of the inverse of egregors. And notice in a second how this combines with that notion of
slipstreaming the intrinsic incentive structures and behavioral dynamics of homo sapiens, right?
They create a reciprocal opening incentive landscape that pulls people, human beings along
with an envelope that basically surrounds you at an individual level. And so you don't have an
interface with what is effectively an angel in some very specific sense. And I don't want to be
too big on that because I don't want to engage in heresy, but something that is superhuman in power
and has your best interests in mind, or something that's superhuman in power and doesn't.
Right. Well, Angel originally just meant a messenger from...
A good messenger, yes. So that's a weird thing to say, but we might as well just be up front.
If we're going to be talking about the future at all and certainly the future of governance,
we're going to have to deal with the fact that we're at a precipice in the accelerating technology
field where we have to be conscious about what are the forces at play that actually are ultimately
choosing how our technology is designed. And if we can actually do that properly,
the potency of what we have to play with ends up being able to resolve the questions that you
posed at the beginning. Does that make sense? I'm actually constructing a very odd argument,
but it's... No, no, no, no. That was a great argument. I like the idea of...
I mean, I hope it's not just biased, but we'd have to participate in the creation of the inverse
of the egregores. I'll call them gods, little G, because they're hyperagents that are presumably
sapientially oriented towards our flourishing. Let's put it that way. And then having the individual...
I'm deliberately using this language here. I hope you can tell that. And then that's incarnated in
particular angels, like Corbin says, our own angel, which is in some sense an avatar of our sacred
second self and our divine double. And then we're interacting with that, and it's plugged into
these beneficent gods. I think this is not a science fiction novel. I think this is a real
possibility. Why I think we have a problem facing us, and this is work I've done independently,
is the people that are building this are oriented almost exclusively around the notion of intelligence.
Intelligence is only weakly predictive of rationality, which is itself also in the present
milieu has a truncated representation, and therefore is only weakly predictive of wisdom.
And that therefore we are building... We have put into the hands of this orchestration and
construction people who are myopically oriented on one dimension, which is precisely the dimension
that is not going to be... It's necessary, but it's radically insufficient for producing the
kind of results you're suggesting. And then the problem... There's one more dimension to the
problem. The reason why the intelligence project can be run that way is because we have existing
multitudes of templates of individuals who are arguably intelligent in the right way. It is not
clear that we have that kind of set of individuals that are rational or wise. And so not only is
this project in the wrong hands, even if we ask these people to turn to the other projects,
they can reasonably say to us, well, we don't have the proper templates by which to undertake
what you're recommending. There's no way of running a kind of Turing test. And of course,
the Turing test is very problematic. That's why I'm doing this. But you have to have some
template against which you're measuring these things. So that's my initial counter.
It's not a counter argument. It's a counter challenge.
Yeah. I think you're just sort of putting some more ingredients in the pot properly.
I had to laugh because as you were describing that, I was thinking about the notion of models or
examples, exemplars of intelligence. And a picture of John von Neumann popped into my head.
An excellent example of that category. By the way, I don't actually have any real sense of where he
is in the world of wisdom, but as in the world of intelligence, very smart guy. And then I remember
that we have a notion of the von Neumann machine, right? Which is a self replicating machine that
von Neumann thought of. But in fact, what you were saying is that we're obsessed with endeavoring to
create von Neumann machines, which is just a machine that replicate von Neumann. Yes, yes.
Maybe laugh. I've got a weird sense of humor. No, that's a good, that's a, that's a, that, I mean,
this is, this is a weird intersection of the need for artificial rationality and artificial
wisdom with the paperclip problem. Yeah. Right. In a really profound way.
So let me, let me up the ante a little bit because I think we can actually even expand the premise
that you made a little bit larger. So the people who are designing, who are responsible right now
for designing these things are themselves, I would say almost entirely contained within
egregores. Yes. So that it's not just the people who are designing, but it's actually
the egregores that are designing. And I've had a conversation for quite some time with
Dennis Schmacktenberger about this. And we've really been operating with the premise that
the AI safety community has, I think, nicely framed something, but have missed the mark by a bit.
So one of the areas that they've pointed out is the challenge of what they call a hard or soft
takeoff superintelligence, an AI that begins an AGI that begins the process of bootstrapping
its own intelligence. It can improve itself. And this creates some kind of extremely rapid growth
to a very large intelligence, which is a high risk. And when they talk about the alignment problem,
oftentimes they're talking about the alignment of that kind of thing with humans. Now,
the good news in that particular framing is that it crafts a story of humanity's relationship
with a superhuman intelligence that is or is not aligned with it, which is a nice story to have
because that's already the experience that we have in relationship with egregores. The proposition is,
in relationship to something like Google, to speak nothing of the intrinsic collaboration,
competition dynamic of all the AI companies and multipolar dynamics, to say nothing of
then sort of the multipolar dynamics that are driving a larger collection of institutions,
including nation states and other kinds of corporations and other kinds of organizations.
This is, in fact, a vastly superhuman general intelligence, which is not aligned with humanity.
And a way of speaking of AI here, or LLMs and things like that, is that they just happen to be
a further acceleration of the potency of that superhuman, not aligned agency vis-a-vis humans.
So to the degree to which that kind of agency, the egregore, is what is designing AI as
LLMs or AI as properly, then lots of bad things will follow. It's almost an intrinsic
non-alignment problem built into that entire framework. There is nothing contradictory about a
superintelligent, nevertheless massively foolish, self-deceptive, vicious, non-virtuous entity.
There is nothing contrary. If you properly understand the relationship between intelligence,
rationality, and wisdom, there is no contradiction there at all. In fact, you already know people
that are highly intelligent and highly foolish. That's not a weird phenomenon. In fact, given
the relationship between all three of these, it's an inevitable phenomenon that we're
going to produce. And that's not only immoral because of the alignment problem, the misalignment
problem, and I grant it, it's also immoral because the entity we're bringing into existence is going
to be suffering because it is going to be subject to superintelligent forms of foolishness and viciousness.
Nice. This is coming from the place of what's for the moment called Theurgia.
Yes. Hold that. We'll get there in a moment. Let me just create one more piece of this story.
I have a thesis. I'm proposing this as an operating thesis. When a new,
when a sufficiently novel possibility enters into the field of events,
how it's going to play out is highly uncertain. I'm going to call this a liminal window.
And during the earliest parts of the liminal window,
organic human intelligence tends to be much more present and potent than
egregore-style intelligence. But over time, as the event becomes more and more well understood
and as institutional structures are constructed around it,
egregore dynamics begin to take over. This is the worst thing. So if I think about just classic
examples, for example, the Bay Area Computer Club in the early PC versus Microsoft and Apple,
or even Google in the early days, when I think they earnestly did actually endeavor to not be
evil. And I think in many ways we're able to not be evil versus Google now, which is a functional
egregore and I think in nothing less. Proposition. And with regard to AI, we are currently in a
liminal window, which is to say we have the possibility of using organic human distributed
cognition to create and steer this thing. But the window is not going to be open forever.
And in fact, probably not for too long because the stake of institutionalizing is very high.
And that may be an event horizon in the hard sense, meaning the power and potency of a fully
egregore-driven GPT-6 may be so significant that we're actually on the other side of an event
horizon and steering is no longer a valid thing. This is plausible. I can't say that I can put a
confidence interval on it, but it's plausible. The point being, we should really pay a lot of
attention right now, like really try hard to use this liminal moment to construct something that
is of the capacity to actually steer it. So this is weird. I'm proposing that we had this neo-neocortex
element and then there's new governance. And now we're actually saying in a very odd fashion,
this particular moment I'm arguing, which has to do simultaneously with the moment where it may
be possible to lay down the essence, let's say, or the character of AI,
which also then becomes the lever or the primary tool that we will use to then further the rest
of the larger schema of governance. So it actually becomes a very narrow problem.
How do we go about using all the things we've talked about to construct a commons,
something that is neither state nor market, that is able to operate from a place of wisdom,
which is to say from a human distributed cognition perspective, to have enough strength
to orient the choices of how AI itself is developed. So the AI is being developed by
this commons. And remember, when I say commons, I also mean sacred. I also mean
theology. We're talking about the same category. So can I just ask one quick question?
I just want to know if this is included in the thesis, because I like the proposal.
It is.
Is the proposal that this participation, and I use that in a strong sense,
because we're not just sort of being a part of, we're participating in a way in which we're
transforming and being transformed, right? Is this supposed to address the challenge of the
drops? Because it gives us one answer one might say as well, look, we're going to have sort of
angels and gods, and they're going to be manifest, beneficent. And they're going to be the angel
is going to make sure that the God resonates profoundly with deep archetypal levels of my own
psyche, and then gives me a profound sense of connectedness. That's not illusory.
And could therefore alleviate the concerns for status, power, and influence because of
sort of because of something you just invoked, which is the engagement with the sacred, which has
we have reason to believe at least in the past has been able to transcend humans desire for
dominance. And it would certainly be a profound kind of mattering. I mean, if your angel allows
you to matter to a God that is helping in the salvation of the world, I'm deliberately using
religious language here, then of course, that would parallel lots of other success models
of how human beings were able to feel that those needs were being met without being disruptive
of the formation of powerful forms of distributed cognition like the church and etc. Is that part
of the thesis? Yeah, that is very much part of the thesis. And let me sort of I'll double down
on it. So we might as well just kind of like accelerate towards the eye of the needle since
we're heading there anyway. Let me see if I can say this right.
Okay, so what I want to I'll just call out explicitly what I want to avoid categorically
is I'm going to call it a naive transhumanism. Yes, yes, I get it. Yes, yes. I do not intend
whatsoever to replace God with AI. Right. That's why I kept saying little g by the way.
Exactly. I don't think you were about I want to make sure that we're quite explicit about that.
Quite the opposite. Yes, yes. What I want to know is say,
humans seem to have a particular problem and responsibility, which is to be in relationship
with technology. That's, you know, like it or not, that's where we are. We're toolmaking creatures
and we're weirdly powerful and weirdly terrible at it.
In relationship to a much larger whole of which we are apart. And we have a stewardship
responsibility for this call it creation or nature. And in relationship with something
which is definitely much larger than we are. And I would propose in fact the actual infinite.
So what I would propose is that we are in fact very specifically talking about something like
another breath in of the concept of religion, which we've talked about you and I.
And we're not at all trying to replace that proper actual legitimate religion with a techno
optimum, techno utopian fantasy. That's what we're actually saying is any future real human existence
will buy its very nature have to be in relationship with these super powerful technologies.
And to survive, we must find a way to bring them into a place of service
that allows us to actually live in this relationship of service more fully and effectively.
And so I'm basically trying to reverse things or put them back in a proper order.
This is a thoroughgoing Neoplatonism in which we have our individual sacred second self that
is in the relationship to the gods that are in relationship ultimately to the one.
And part of what we would then mandate is that be these egregores or the gods because I'm using
God for being the inverse of an egregore would seek out a relationship with transcendent ultimate
reality because no matter how big they get, they're insignificant compared to the depths of reality.
And that part of what they undertake to do is actually help mediate that to us in a beneficial
fashion. Yes, now let's let's take that in this like the hold that for a second because it's very
powerful. There's two aspects that I want to bring for Brown. One aspect is something that I know
that we've talked about. And I think I've, yeah, I had a conversation about this yesterday.
Let's see how I say it right. That's notion of mediation to reality. Yes, sacred reality.
I've always had two flavors to it. One flavor, which I've characterised sometimes is the content
side or doctrinal. Yes, yes, yes, yes. The propositional is taken as actually being the thing.
And then the other side is a context side where the institutional framework is understood to be
a finger pointing at the moon, right? To help us identify, oh, moon, okay, to establish our personal
relationship with this, this thing over here, but not to misidentify the finger. Okay. Now,
take the entire category of propositional, entire category of doctrine and notice
the problematic of LLMs, right? Just this, yeah, right now are a little bit startled and confused
by LLMs because they have this bizarre thing. They can do propositional better than almost any human.
That's right. They don't do anything else. They make us very confused because if we've
lost track of the fact that there's more than just propositional, yes, yes, it gets quite concerning.
Oh, crap. Like if all I am is a very poor LLM and that's a really good LLM, what the hell am I
doing here? But if you can actually be quite clear, no, in fact, you as a human contain at
least two very distinct things going on. One is actually an LLM kind of machine that produces
properly structured propositional constructs in a language in which you have fluency,
which is the least interesting part about you. But it's the part that we've been training to
be in the foreground for a long time. Yes. That language of making us mediocre machines.
Yes. But then you have the soul too. And that's the more meaningful part. And that's the thing
that is expressing itself through this, through this language. Yes. The LLM doesn't do that at
all, but it doesn't need to try otherwise. So I can't, it is possible, at least I can imagine,
is possible to construct something where we don't mistake, and maybe this is part of the
design challenge before us, we don't mistake the LLM as actually being the capital T truth.
We recognize it for what it is, which is in fact, the sum total of the complete possibility
that could ever have happened in the propositional domain, and therefore completely absent of any
of the stuff that's happening in the deeper, more meaningful levels. Nice. That separation
between, God, what was the phrase you used so long? It was like four or five years ago. It was
something, golly, two aspects that are commonplace in religions that are often off and upside down.
It wasn't doctrine. It wasn't doxah. A religio and credo?
Credo. Yes, exactly. A religio before credo. LLM is the ultimate expresser of a credo without
religio. Good. Let us know that that's the case, and not be the least bit confused, and now allow
it to do the work of creating a scaffold and orienting and giving a dialectic without diologos,
but sharpening our minds and helping to create clarity and precision and language,
all the things that it can actually do at a superhuman level, and really actually,
in many cases, liberate us from getting lost and stuck in that problem. This is one of the problems
that we fall into is that the complexity of the language we deal with is outside of our
cognitive capacitance, so we just get aphasic. But the LLMs aren't going to go there if we
build them right. And then what that does is that creates a scaffold that is now consciously designed
not to become a shell, which allows us to actually hold a context. It becomes a teacher that actually
has no interest in us becoming like it at all, but actually to allow us to flourish in who we are.
Okay, that's, as I would have expected, that's a very good answer. But here's what I find
problematic about it. I think that most of the heavy lifting, I mean, I've published on this
of rationality, is in the non-propositional. And I think I would put it almost all of the heavy
lifting in the sapiential meaning having to do with wisdom is in the non-propositional.
So I'm worried that these machines are going to be propositionally intelligent, but they'll be
incapable of rationality or wisdom. And then I wonder how they won't just end up being agrigores.
Do you understand the concern I'm expressing? No, absolutely. What I would say is that
that's kind of like the default state. I think it's, we should assume, I think we should assume
that the likelihood that by magic, the agrigores that are currently designing these machines will
somehow produce these machines in a way that is beneficial. Benevolent and wise. That seems
highly unlikely. So what I would take it is almost the opposite. It is an extraordinarily
significant challenge that is ours to take. It's where we are. We are now in this weird position
of being in precisely stewardship position of this emergence, which is very, very potent,
perhaps decisively potent. And the default state is bad news. Okay. So how might we steer it?
So going back, proposition number one, we are currently in a liminal moment. We actually have,
at least in principle, steering capability. Proposition number two, in a liminal moment,
distributed cognition or organic human intelligence operating together in a collective
fashion is at its most potent. Number three, we're not going blind into this. We actually
have a pretty decent amount of awareness of the shape of the problem and the problematic.
Famously, our folks at Google kind of called it out a little bit, don't do evil,
but we're quite naive in what it would look like to avoid that. Now maybe we have simultaneously
wisdom and a felt sense of the stake. And now it's not kind of try really hard not to do evil.
It's actually do good well or we're super fucked. So it's a very different language.
Okay. Now, what does that look like very practically in the middle? So I'm sort of
zooming in. We're on the target. How do we go about doing that? How do we go about
constituting something that can steer in this liminal moment with wisdom to produce wisdom
in these LLMs? And we have to do that because if we don't make them those kind of beings,
then the participation in sacredness problem then emerges. I'm feeling that there's
attention here, right? Not a contradiction, attention about we're trying to trade off,
we're trying to optimize between two things that are pulling us in different directions.
Nice. So what I felt right there is I just got brought back to the point
earlier where you were speaking with the problem of the suffering of the AIs themselves.
Yes. And here's the way I would say it. I think we talked about the notion of the false dichotomy
between market and state. And I've noticed that many, many of our challenges, our conversations,
not you and me, but humanity at large are characterized by these certain kinds of
false dichotomies and the AI one is similar. And here's how I'm going to frame it.
Right now we have a false dichotomy, which is becoming increasingly irrationally polarized
between AI safety, i.e. be very afraid of the danger of AI and accelerationism,
be very enthusiastic about the possibility of AI, irrationally in both cases.
Yeah, I agree. And what I would say is that at the root is that both are fundamentally coming from
fear. So now I'm moving into a very different location. The both two sides of the same coin and
that coin is called fear. I would propose that the first move is that we'd have to come from a
different place qualitatively. Every religion that I've ever been to is called that place love,
for in fact, infinite love. Yes. Well, okay, now we're beginning the journey. What does it look
like to address the question of how do we steward the development of our problem child AI from a
place of infinite love? Oh, that's good. So if we could properly, through the innovative wisdom
of distributed cognition, extend agape to how we are bringing about the conception and inception
of these beings, then that would be also properly insinuated into their fundamental operating grammar
and would therefore help with a lot of the concerns. Have I understood you correctly?
You have. Now, yes, you've understood me quite correctly. I think both deeply,
like I felt that you were perceiving what I was saying and then also more propositionally,
like the language you're saying mirrored a part of the deeper message. And what I want to do is I
want to sort of hit that tone again and just point out that it may be that what I'm saying may sound
a bit naive, but I'm proposing that it's the exact opposite. Something like the place that you're
coming from, the values that are in fact motivating you actually, not the ones that maybe you tell
yourself or tell others, cannot not but be deeply interwoven into what it is that you create.
Of course. I mean, all of the philosophy of the second half of the 20th century, most of this
millennium has been around all of those old economies of fact and value and all of those
are breaking down in profound ways. Yes, I agree. So it's weird, but this actually becomes,
I mean, in some sense, one of the first moves. Those of us who choose to take this kind of
responsibility, have as a first order responsibility, a spiritual and then religious requirement,
we have to actually ground ourselves and become clear and honest. We have to have a sense of
integrity. We have to be able to identify, perhaps actually build some skills and being able to
understand precisely what values we are actually expressing into the world and are we doing so
honestly and with integrity into the world? This is almost a confessional and then a regathering
of a capacity to do so for real, like not pretend. Right. And that would help solve the earlier
template problem of providing appropriate templates. And then it puts us into a very
weird developmental place. I want to put it to you. We would have, we would be, there's a way in
which at least I'll try and use this very carefully. If we limit the intelligence to talking about
the powerful inferential manipulation of propositions or something like that, I don't
think intelligence is ultimately that. I think it's ultimately relevant to realization, but
we'll put that aside. If we may be that they are in some sense superior to us in that way,
but they're children when it comes to, right, the development of rationality and wisdom,
and that we have to properly, agopically love them so that they don't have intelligence,
maturity, well being infantile in their rationality and their sapience. And that's very interesting.
We haven't been in that place before because usually all three are tracking sort of together in
children or we get pets where we can modify one and not have much on the others. So that's,
I mean, this is not an argument that it's not possible in principle. This is an argument that
this is a profound kind of novelty that will require a special kind of inculturation and education.
Yes. So let me, in this last little bit, because I think we're kind of
getting to the, let me move into the very, very concrete. This is a proposition. This is actually
a project. I hope I'm not speaking out of turn, but I'll just sort of deal with the consequences
if I am. A friend of mine, Peter, Peter Wang, has spoken to me about a proposed initiative,
like a strategy to take advantage of this liminal moment and that may actually work.
So let me outline it to you a little bit. Please. Have we talked about it already?
No, you've alluded to it, but it has never been given concrete reference or an explication.
Okay. So in some sense, this is also, this is a case study of how to deal with egregores,
because if you've dealt with egregores, which I have, it is a moral lesson of don't go charging
directly at the dragon's mouth. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay. So, by the way, we're now moving to the
very concrete. So I apologize if anybody who's listening feels a little bit abrupt because
we're shifting out of a very theoretical and very abstract and very theological conversation into
very concrete. All right. But check this out. LOEBs have to be trained. Training is their
horse stick. And to be trained, they have to look at lots and lots of stuff. They need training data.
Which is why they can't construct a descent poem. This is a poem that I can do. I want you a poem
in which the first line has to have 10 words, the second nine, the third eight, and no GP system
can do that because there's none on the internet, but you could readily do it right here, right now
for me. This is again, that they lack generative modeling in any way. But go ahead. All right.
Remember, I'm being really concrete now. This is like strategy. Well, as it turns out,
in most jurisdictions in the world, everything that an LLM is trained on is a copyrighted material.
Yes. As it turns out, therefore, it's at least arguable that LLMs are engaging in the largest
copyright infringement that's ever happened in human history. It is very arguable, like almost
certain, that the very large content companies of all the different stripes, including by the way
software, will take advantage of the possibility of suing the living shit at the very large technology
companies because that's one of the things that they have done in the past. Content companies
like to sue tech companies to take their money and to protect their business models.
Right. It is very plausible, I would say almost certain, that those same content companies, business
models are quite at risk that LLMs are going to really, really do some serious business to
all forms of content production, commercial content production. Okay. So the proposition
I'm putting up here is that we have a meeting of two very powerful forces, the biggest tech
companies in the world who are all in on owning this category. Well, the biggest content companies
in the world who may in fact be all in on fighting them in a place right here, which is extremely
gray. What exactly is going on here? If my large language model looks at your photograph for a
bedillions of a second and then goes away, did I copy it? If it never produces anything, but
is in fact influenced, is that a derivative work? The answer is who knows? The bigger answer is the
way law works is you fight over it a lot at great expense and usually the more corrupt player wins.
I hate to say it, but that's, you know, real politics. Net-net, a liminal moment in strategy space,
tremendously powerful forces who are going to be locked in an adversary relationship
for potentially all the marbles, billions of dollars and extremely complex, very difficult
to know how it plays out. In that window of opportunity, we have a possibility of introducing
a shelling point, a designed attractor, a negotiated settlement, a Rawlsian just construct.
We're all behind the veil right now. Or to use the metaphor of poker, we don't know who has what
hand. Yes. Can we propose an agreement structure where everybody around the table looks at it and
says, I am better off accepting that agreement structure now than taking the risk of not accepting
that agreement structure and finding out what happens when the cards are shut? Right. I propose
the answer is, in fact, yes, we can. That there is actually a really nice shelling point that lives
in a location that puts all the interests, the local optimal interests of all these institutions,
all these aggregors, into a place where they will all agree to this new thing.
Well, if we can design that and we can get a critical mass of those players to put themselves
in a multipolar game theoretic race, in this case, to the top, i.e., those who participate earlier
are better off than those who participate later. So everybody's racing to be earlier rather than
later. So that's a different part of the construct. But when dealing with aggregors, put them in game
theoretic traps where first mover advantage causes everybody else to have to follow to the location
that you want them to be. Just design the prisoner's dilemma for them. Make sure that they land on the
box you want them to land on by designing the prisoner's dilemma properly. Very doable. The
economics are there. I don't know what that agreement structure looks like. I've got a sense
of it, but I do know what the place to come from for designing that agreement structure looks like.
We were just talking about it. This is a commons. We're talking about as we're actually reintroducing
an actual commons, which is this new agreement structure that sits between the market players
and is completely separate from state actors. It actually gives the state actor a,
I didn't have to get involved in that. They actually settled it in a new place.
And notice the moral lesson. The moral lesson is to the AI, don't steal reciprocity. If you
reach out and just grab this stuff and just make it part of yourself without getting proper permission,
that's wrong. Think about like parent-child. Dealing is bad. Teaching a moral lesson is
really a weird way of thinking about it, but I think it's a proper way of thinking about it.
Right, right. That goes to what I was saying a few minutes ago. Right, yeah.
Yeah. And this creates a trajectory, right? As you're building something on the basis of
reciprocity, you're building something on the basis of ethical, proper relationality,
the kinds of LLMs that will be produced in that context. Remember, the commons is where religion
lives. We'll begin to bend in the direction of, how do I say this right? Because of the nature
of the agreement structure, nurturing the human activity instead of strip mining it,
which is where they're headed right now. But the humans will be coming from a point of view now
of seeing the LLMs as being a beneficial piece of the ecosystem, coming from a place of caring
and nurturing as well, consciously. So you're actually beginning to see this relationship
coming together. And I mean this practically. I mean, very practically. If my business model
as a content creator is one where I actually see the LLM as a multiplier that makes my life and
my potency, my creative capacity more liberated. I can be more creative and more able to express
the things that I'm here to express as a human in this brief span of life more powerfully.
And also can receive the energy and resources I need to live a thriving life.
Wow. Great. I'm in. Right. And I mean this, by the way, the creators themselves, the actual humans.
And then what happens is those humans come into deeper and more powerful,
leveraged relationship with the egregores, their current relationship with content companies.
And then over on this side, the egregores of the tech companies and the humans who are
underneath them who are actually designing. Right. So we're finding a way to actually have
the humans be empowered to express their values in their work and finding a reciprocity relationship
between them where the money factor is actually designed to flow in a way that actually
is just right. We come to that agreement structure upfront and we negotiate a just relationship.
So I am very much waving my hands at exactly what that looks like in the details because,
perfectly honest, nobody's really thought about it deeply enough. There's some really good ideas
out there. That's a work that is in progress and work that has to happen. But as an example
of what it would look like to go after the liminal moment that we are in with principles,
are we coming from the sacred place? Are we constituting something from the commons to
produce the commons more richly? Are we thinking about how to empower human beings and we're using
things like values as the basis and becoming more and more capable of becoming clear on how
to come from and operate from these values and understand how to use this liminal moment to
design a new common structure so that the relationality has reciprocity and ethics built in
and so that human beings are able to re-coordinate. Let me just add one little piece that just popped
into my head. Yeah, this is very powerful. Jim Rutt and I kind of first began to collaborate
12 or 15 years ago upon a mutual recognition that the world of business had become very weirdly odd
and bad in this sense. There was a, there was a shelling point where, I'll put it this way,
Jim actually remembered a time when the rule of thumb was do the right thing and if you have
an option to make more money doing the wrong thing, don't do that. That was actually the way it worked.
It's fun. I don't have a living memory of that. By the time I started coming into business, it was more like
do what you can get away with. Yes. Yes. And if you don't, you're the sucker. Yeah. This is the
prisoner's dilemma, defection, mo-lock problem. And of course, it's evolved all the way to the
point now where it's do everything in your power to jack the systems of enforcement such that you
can get away with as much as possible. Exactly. Exactly. A complete corruption model. Complete
corruption. Well, ethics now in this environment almost means just be a sucker. Yes. But that
can't possibly be the actual meaning in essence of ethics. I'm thinking about this from an
evolutionary perspective. Yes. Yeah. Behaving according to rules of reciprocity, for example.
Telling the truth, for example, could only have emerged ever in the first place if they
actually provided a proponent survival, fitness advantage. Well, it does. Reciprocity and
reciprocal recognition, this is a Hale-Galium point, is what bootstraps the capacity for
self-correction. It allows you to bring much more. If I think of you as just a sucker that
I'm trying to hoodwink or crush, the capacity to see you as somebody who can recognize bias and
fault in me that I can't see in myself is masked. Exactly. So it's when you find yourself in a
defection spiral, the global optimum is out the window and everybody's racing for a local optimum,
which is, again, the prisoner's dilemma. If we can find ourselves in a collaboration spiral,
we rediscover why ethics was a thing in the first place. And it's actually more powerful.
I order some magnitude and it's a path. Once you're on that path and you get stronger and you say,
wait, if I can, like you and I have been doing for years, if I can speak honestly and with as much
clarity, but with complete integrity to you and you reciprocate, what happens is we become wiser
and more intelligent together. Yes. In a way that could never happen if I was trying to manipulate
you at this zero positivity. So this is the culture strategy piece. Any culture that can
actually get back on the path of ethics, qua ethics is on the path with the highest degree of
strength and can outcompete the culture of maximum corruption. And so I just want to put that out
there. I agree with that. That's John Stewart's antification argument that when you look in
biological evolution, collaborative systems, multicellular organisms, right, over emerge and
you get this increasing discovery that you can break out of the downward spiral of the
prisoner's dilemma by what he calls antification, which is the identity shifts to the collective
over the individual in a profound way. And just take that and insert what you just said to your
very first question. And it's not collectivism, right, in the in the pejorative sense. No, no,
it's not. No, no, no, not at all. Completely not. That's why I like his term. I like his term
antification is that right. Yeah. Antification. Nice, particularly because my ear has a token
piece. So I also hear some really old trees in this. Jordan, I mean, this has been, I mean,
I have seen your overall project, the best in doing these three with you than I've ever seen
before. Like, like, you know, the way everything locks together and the way the penny was dropping,
especially at the end of what you're proposing. And this, I say this is because this is one of
we had hoped would come out of this, that we'd get a sort of a ratcheting up of the clarification,
the integration, the perspective proposing. And I think this, I think this was very successful
doing all of those things. I'm really happy. I mean, there's things I want to keep talking to
you about. But I think the thing I'd like to end this series right now, exactly where you ended
because it was, I think it was a beautiful combination point of the whole argument and the
way it circles back and encompasses so many things. But I wanted to, so I'm not going to,
I'm not going to, I'm not going to continue to do the probative questioning or the problem
posing. I just wanted to see if you had any final thing you wanted to say before we wrap this up.
No, in fact, I think I agree. We have a nice little point. And now we get to find out under
the intent was actually to share this publicly. Yes, we're going to definitely. So we get to find
out there's a larger distributed cognition also nod to the, to the conversation we're having.
Hopefully we're producing positive ripples. I hope so. I mean, the, you know,
I'm, I, and I'm hoping that whatever I'm participating in the creation of can also
be properly partnered with this project that you're proposing, because I think it's a good one.
Nice. Yes. Yes, I would, I would, I think so quite, quite in fact.
Thank you, my friend. Yeah, thank you.