Final presentation of mine. I thought that after talking to you about specific research
topics that I've been interested in, that it might be interesting to talk about a more
general topic which is doing research in applied linguistics. And of course it's my personal
view because anyone who does research in applied linguistics at whatever level, whether that is
your BA research project or your MA dissertation or your PhD or any project beyond the PhD,
everybody is facing similar issues and of course the expectations change slightly as you progress
through your career. I would start by talk about some, I would say almost philosophical issues
about research and one of the things that always struck me was that students tend to have,
tend to believe in predeterminism. They see these libraries full of books and these journals full
of papers and they can see the publication lists of certain researchers and it's easy to think
that this was destined to happen and so that it was driven by God, faith or some unknown force
so they tend to underestimate the fact that in fact nothing is predetermined. If you're a researcher
you could go in a thousand different directions, you could ask a thousand different questions and
you have a choice between a huge amount of methods and so nothing of what actually is produced
is predetermined. It's the result of free choice, free spirits trying to do something
that they are interested in and so I would say that it's crucial to hence realize that
Lambert, Garner, Dornier to mention three of the biggest names in motivation research and second
language acquisition that they weren't destined to introduce motivation and I had a chat with
Garner and Dornier and they were kind of surprised to a certain degree by the fact that their papers
seemed to have so much impact. They hadn't necessarily anticipated it. They were also
interested in other things but it was motivation that made their name and so I quite like the little
picture there about the PhD. If you're standing at the door deciding what to do for your PhD
it may look like a maze and I totally agree and I think that in fact the first year of doing the
PhD is getting lost in the maze and getting a sense of just how big the maze is and wander around
without necessarily finding the exit straight away. So this research does not descend from heaven
that's really an absolutely crucial point so it's not like Moses coming down the mountain
with God's words. It's really the result of inspiration, hard work, sweat and resilience.
Resilience because things typically don't go right straight away and in fact any paper that
you see published in a journal typically has been rejected one or twice, has been rewritten
about 10 or 15 times and the amount of work that the authors put into it is hard to imagine when
you see a nice neat little text that looks like a perfect finished product. Also it's important
to realize that the peer review system is valuable meaning that not all good papers submitted to
journals will get to publication because reviewers or editors may think it's not a good fit with the
journal or the reviewers may not like this type of research or reviewers may have different opinions
about what is important and what is original. So it's important to realize that if you submit
something to a journal and it's rejected never take it personally. It doesn't mean that you are
therefore a bad researcher. Absolutely not. You have to develop resilience and you have to extract
useful information from the rejection letter. What is it that they didn't like? Why? Can you
address it? If you can't address it you know sometimes it's better to throw away a paper that
has some fundamental deficit. If you can adapt it and submit it somewhere else please do and sometimes
good papers can get rejected because they challenge orthodoxy. So I remember talking to
prominent researchers who Albert Costa, the late Catalan psycholinguist who was complaining that
journal editors want in fact more of the same with small variations. So you add one little
ingredient and you repeat what you have done before because they know that that's a product
that will sell, that will be appreciated and he was angry that journals rejected the new papers he
was writing on the foreign language effect and that they wanted more of the old stuff. So I guess
that researchers sometimes face the kind of issue that artists have or singers in that the public
wants the good old tunes, the big hits and they don't necessarily want to hear the
singers' latest creations. Of course if I say that papers don't descend from heaven it doesn't mean
that new theories appear out of nothing. So if you work on certain topics it's because other
people have preceded you in working on that topic that teachers have told you about a certain topic
or certain research questions so the ground was prepared and at that point you come in and you
think okay what could I do to turn this into something original? Could I ask a question that
hasn't been asked before and sometimes you do manage to do that and you end up reshaping the
trajectory of a discipline. Now this is a nice little conceptualization of doing research where
you collect data, you sort it, you arrange it, you present it visually and you explain it with
a story and I would say that the crucial final step really is the explaining with a story meaning
that I desk reject quite a lot of papers submitted to my Journal of Multilingual Multicultural
Development because the authors have been through the first four stages so they did collect data,
they sorted it, they arranged it and they did some visual representation however they did not
come up with a good story and any research paper, any dissertation, any project really,
if there is no good story then in fact it's a failure because what the reader is interested in
or the audience is interested in is a good story that is based on solid data that has
been properly sorted that has been arranged following the conventions of the discipline
and that have been presented visually in order to understand or make a point and then this needs to
be embedded in a good story and the thing is it doesn't really matter what the story is about
but it needs to be a good story. Now if you are an academic or you are a PhD researcher
you may have heard about the sentence you know publish or perish and so this is a nice book by
James Hines, it's a funny book really about a young academic, a young American academic
who faces that terrible pressure to publish in order not to perish and so I think this is an
important point because once you enter academia and you become a researcher you do realise that
there is a huge amount of pressure on you to do so many things, you have to you know first you
finish your PhD and then you have to do so much teaching and you have to do administration and
you're expected to come up with creative ideas and publish them in the best journals and then
you spend so much time writing these papers and then they get rejected and then you realise
and then you hear from your head of department that if you don't have five publications by
the end of the year we will not prolong your contract so you are under a considerable amount
of stress and too much stress risks killing creativity because you end up not sleeping
enough and not going for walks and not allow your brain to engage in the kind of deep thinking that
you can get when I don't know you go walking in the forest and you're looking at a lake and that's
where an idea might hit you so you need to create the conditions where you can be creative
and of course publications matter, the career really depends on the publication list
so when I was in selection committees at Bergbeck the threshold to be invited to an interview
for a lectureship would typically be about five papers and maybe a couple of book reviews
that would be the kind of standard entry to get invited and you need these few publications to
convince the potential employer that you have research potential. I also think that it's better
to have something than nothing so it means that at the very start of your career it's okay if you
have some publications in conference proceedings that's fine I always recommend it to my students
also to write some book reviews because that's a useful way to find your academic voice and have a
line on your CV avoid publishing crap meaning if you realize that what you have produced
isn't very good and you get advice from your supervisor telling you you know that that's not
really good material then avoid publishing it so I guess that as if you want to become a researcher
you need a strategic plan knowing what to publish where at what pace and with whom.
So how to get published I would say it really depends on your research interests and on your
field so you need to know within that field what topics are hot. It's pretty easy if you go to a
conference or you look at the conference program of a recent conference you know you you check
what topics are being discussed and what seems to be creating buzz because you don't want to
start working and trying to publish something on a topic that is considered that is no longer
considered cool or hot it needs to be something that people are currently interested in because
that's what will hand you a job at the point so it's important also to create a network of people
who have similar interests so go to conferences try to talk to the plenary speakers during
coffee breaks or during the conference dinner contact authors if there is a paper out that
you're interested in but you can't access it if you flatter them a little bit they will typically
send you the pdf also keep an eye out on calls for papers of conferences or special issues or
answer books on the topic that you are interested in so what to publish it could be a small research
project pilot studies I recommend where all my PhD students I have recommended that they try to
turn the most interesting findings of their MA thesis or dissertation into a little publication
you could also publish a critical review of literature on a topic and plenty of journals
that are interested in critical reviews you could write some critical analysis of a popular concept
or contribute to a discussion forum and and as I said before book reviews are really a good way
to get free books and these books are typically very expensive so what is you simply contact
the reviews editor of a journal tell him or her that you are a PhD student or a master student
with a huge interest in this topic and that you notice that this expensive new book came out and
that you would love to review it for the journal and that typically implies writing 2000 writing
2000 words where you point out what you liked and what you didn't like much about the book
don't be too harsh because the author of that book may be your future employer so you need to be
careful and then the book reviews editor will contact the editor and will send you a free copy
of the book and you typically have three months to write your book review then the other one is the
standard research paper typically between six and twelve thousand words there are also journals
that have options for shorter papers research in progress so that's typically somewhere between
three thousand and four thousand words and then there are also review papers where you write a review
of a particular area in the field um oh so before writing I would say that you need to come up you
need to develop an intuition or a gut feeling that something is original and is worth investigating
and that you happen to be the best person to do it and it's an intuition that you can typically
discuss with your supervisor because as supervisors we are very happy when students come up with
original ideas and I have published many papers with former bachelor students or master students
who came up with a really interesting idea and I thought oh yeah great let me supervise you properly
and let's make sure that we get good data and then they got a good grade for their BA or master
dissertation but of course these BA and master dissertations even if they have high grades they
are not necessarily publishable to turn a dissertation into a paper requires a lot of a lot of work so
we then turned it into papers and they got published so you need to formalize the intuition you need
to come up with a research design you need to develop a hypothesis based on previous literature
on previous research so you need a proper literature review then you collect the data
you as I said before you sort it you analyze it you see to what extent it confirms or disconfirms
previous research and what you do is really adding a grain of sand to the pyramid of knowledge
so I say that because
we shouldn't be over ambitious in the sense that the paper doesn't need to be revolutionary it
doesn't need to be the the 10 commandments that Moses came down with from his mountain
it just needs to be one gleaming beautiful perfectly
formed grain of sand and you add that to the pyramid of knowledge and you will have done your job
so it's good to assemble the data all the data before you start writing the paper
and I would say that when you write you write up the data do it as if you were talking to colleagues
then another question is whether you should go for co-authored or signal publications
I would say that it depends on the field in literature research most papers are signal authored
in social sciences in applied linguistics it's more common to see co-authored papers typically
between two and five authors if you look at physics for example or exact sciences stem
research you sometimes see a list of 10 authors because they are all the members of the lab
so that is rather unusual in applied linguistics it can be a great idea to co-author something
with somebody who has more experience than you because they know the ropes and they know how to
react to sharp comments by reviewers and they they know that if a reviewer recommends something
that you disagree with that you have the right to disagree and explain why you disagree and why
you will not follow the reviewer's recommendation and you may even have to appeal to the editor
saying you know reviewer three is asking me to drop this but I really think this is crucial
for this and this and this reason and so it's important to learn the practices in
publishing in applied linguistics I like co-authoring because I like working with people who have
skills that I don't have to the same extent for example I've been working with in Luis Botez
and Chen Chen Li who have amazing statistical skills there so they are psychometric specialists
so they can do things with stats that I couldn't do because I'm more self-taught
statistician and and it's great and then I help them write a good story and find some
interesting metaphors so finding the right journal that's a crucial and difficult question
do you go for the top journal or do you go for a lower ranked journal
and do you go for quantity or quality and my recommendation would be to aim for balance
where you have some quick intimate I wouldn't say low level in fact but more intermediate level
publications like conference proceedings web-based journals and then I would recommend
spending a lot of time and energy to try and get at least one paper into a really prestigious journal
because future selection committees will look at UCV and will say okay some conference proceedings
some mid-level journals but wow one paper in a really good journal and if you can do one then
the assumption is that you can do more so I would also say recommend that you send your best work
to the best journals so check whether the impact factor is high whether you know the people who
publish in that journal again ask advice to supervisors I would absolutely avoid non-referee
journals unless it's reviews or opinion pieces also avoid edited volumes with editors that don't
have a name in the field or working with co-authors that you don't trust much or you don't have much
of a reputation unless they are your students and avoid also volumes published by publishers that are
so-called pirate publishers there are a number of them and you need absolutely to avoid
publishing there so again that's something that you need to ask your supervisor and then the other
thing is that you probably need to avoid editors that work slowly because if you're at the start of
your career you don't want to wait two or three years for a chapter to come out
so as I said avoid predatory journal open access these days is becoming more
common institutions typically pay the to have the paper out in open access but you need to avoid
these so-called predatory journals so be extremely careful they typically contact you after you
presented something at the conference something that leaves a trace on the internet and then
they will you will get an invitation saying you know we we noticed that you produced this
magnificent or that you presented this magnificent paper we we think you are brilliant now will you
please submit your paper in our journal run away delete straight away because if somebody flatters
you it's probably a scam so because then there will be hidden payments the quality will be crap
and it risks in fact undermining your academic credibility so make sure you check
where you submit your paper now what to avoid in the paper and I'm saying this because as editor
I come across about 800 papers a year submitted to my journal and and I would typically reject
the ones that have very superficial literature reviews where there is just some reference
dropping but there isn't any critical engagement with the studies presented
also avoid claiming that very little research has been done in an area if you're not 100
percent sure and it's hard to be 100 percent sure because you can't know everything that has
been published and and it could be the reviewer reading your paper who happened to have produced
some research in that topic and he or she will be angry with you for claiming that very little
has been done also crucial to make sure that the text looks good sloppiness is dangerous
so make sure you stick to the style sheet of the journal that the references are in the right
format double check whether everything in the list of references is mentioned in the text and vice
versa make sure the spelling of surnames is correct because it really pisses a reviewer
of if his or her surname is badly spelled also avoid making sweeping generalizations
so always be very careful in discussing the the the results because what applies to
your particular data set might not apply to data sets collected from different participants
in different environments also avoid claims that cannot be substantiated and avoid a rhetorical
style that does not match that of the journal I would add to that avoid
taking sides in whatever argument you are presenting so you are writing an impartial
paper you are writing a paper on a topic you cannot choose a position so if you're not writing a
pamphlet to attack something or to defend something you are looking at with an impartial
pair of eyes and you may come to a conclusion that this is more correct than that or that you
prefer this to that but the paper cannot be written like it would be a pamphlet
so to get your paper accepted it's crucial to keep it simple so the story needs to be
a specific story on one specific theme so better to explain one idea in detail than too many
superficially and I would say that is a typical beginner's mistake beginner researcher want to
cram in too many ideas so my golden rule is less is more so the one idea needs to be
visible in the title must come clearly through in the abstract in the opening of the introduction
and again in the conclusion so people get it what the idea was so also follow the style and
the structure of papers published in the journal that you have in mind and if you think oh this is
also such a good idea I could also put it in there in fact my advice is split it off cut and paste
it in a separate document something that you can develop later try not to put too many eggs
in the one basket also think hard about the title when you finish the paper because sometimes you
start with a working title and then at the very end of the paper finishing the paper you realize
that in fact you need to revisit the title because the the the idea may have shifted a little bit
you may have focused on one aspect rather than what you announced in the title and and the title
really will determine whether or not your paper is cited if it's too long too clunky
it won't get much attention so also having a catchy title is good but don't there is no need to
have a catchy title but if you can come up with something catchy that that gets people's attention
that would certainly help so writing tips I would say writing a good introduction
in fact the first sentence is crucial if you don't catch the attention of the reader
and you don't convey the importance of the questions addressed in in that first sentence in
that first paragraph nobody is going to read the rest of the text so I would say that I
just reject again paper submitted to my journal if I read the introduction well I read the abstract
and I read the introduction and if halfway through the introduction I still don't know what this
paper is about I reject it because they didn't catch my attention so text can be written in
the past or present tense past tense okay if you describe results of an experiment but typically
present tense if it's a general conclusion good to write if you write in English you need to write
short sentences shorter than you would if you were writing in French or Italian for example
also avoid fluffy hermetic and complex ways of saying a simple thing so I would say that the
Anglo-Saxon requirement is really to not beat around the bush be as clear and as simple as possible
now I want to talk to you about something I find really interesting which is
comes from chaos theory and the dynamic systems theory which is the butterfly effect
namely the fact that a new idea at some point in time may feel like nothing more than the flapping
of wings and I don't know whether you know this metaphor of the butterfly effect it's the flapping
of the wings of a butterfly today in Poznan may be linked to a storm in Italy in two weeks because
it could have unexpected consequences and because the world is a dynamic system
you don't know exactly what the consequences will be in our case of a particular paper
so sometimes a paper gets published and doesn't get cited very much for a couple of years and
then suddenly there is growing interest in the area and suddenly that paper may get started to
be cited more and more and you could say that you could say that that paper was in fact
the butterfly and that it had unexpected consequences or effects on the field
and so butterflies you could refer to butterflies by famous researchers like Galileo
when he first published his rejection of the geocentric model saying that you know the earth
circulates around the the sun very few people believed him and the church was very angry
and with him for making that claim and in the end it turned out that he was right
same with Einstein who introduced relativity again something that not many people believed
could be true when it was first published and then became the dominant paradigm in physics
and then I would also say that sometimes the butterflies can be political and I'm thinking
here about Tarek el Tayev Mohammed Bouazzi who was a modest street vendor and he set himself
on fire in 2010 in Tunisia and it was an act that led to the Tunisian revolution so the poor man was
desperate and wanted to express his protest in that act of self-immolation and that had consequences
so he was a kind of a butterfly now another thing that I'm interested in is how
research develops within sciences and how it develops within applied linguistics
and how that development is typically non-linear and I recommend the book by Thomas Kuhn on the
structure of scientific revolutions so where he explains that science goes through paradigm shifts
where current theories can't explain some phenomenon someone proposes a new theory
so I would say that when Galileo came in he pointed out that the the observations did not
allow him to confirm the theory that earth was the center of the universe so more and more
observations led to the rejection of the old geocentric model and the introduction of the new
heliocentric model so that was a typical paradigm shift so this revolution occurs when the new
paradigm is better at explaining the observations offers a model that is closer to the objective
external reality and that the new paradigm is incommensurate with the old one so examples of
paradigm shifts in applied linguistics if you are a master student in applied linguistics you know
that it was behaviorism that it ended in fact when Chomsky in 1959 reviewed Skinner's verbal
behavior and where Chomsky said in fact language is not a collection of reinforced habits as the
behaviorists claimed children use language creatively so it was a kind it was the death
now for behaviorism in applied linguistics at the time also we have had a contrastive analysis
that was also inspired by behaviorism seeing language as a set of habits with second language
acquisition being the establishment of new habits where it was assumed that if there were errors in
the second language they were caused by the first language and the prediction that the
bigger the difference between a structure in the first and the second language the more errors
would occur in the second language and then Zobel was among those who pointed out that
French learners of English failed to show evidence of the predictor error but English learners of
French did so in French for those of you who know French you can say je les vois in English you
would have to put the object pronoun after the verb so you would say I see them however looking at
learner data Zobel realized that French learners of English never said things like I them see
which would be the expected pattern because then they would transfer their French syntactic pattern
yet English learners of French did produce sentences like je vois et instead of je la vois
so the interference didn't go in both directions so the transfer of habits was not consistent across
languages okay so that was until now the the general advice about doing research
in applied linguistics and about the butterfly effects and I would say that in a certain sense
we all have experienced butterfly effects meaning that we have all done certain things
that led us on to certain paths and that we could not have predicted where they would take us so
when I started my career and so I will talk about these butterfly effects and and these trigger
events in in my own career and I started doing a masters in French in Brussels and I did my
master's dissertation on a theoretical topic namely a famous French linguist called Gustave
Guillaume and I managed to publish the findings of that dissertation in Travaux de Languistique
and I was really into theoretical French linguistics at the time but then my once I
started doing my PhD it was a PhD in applied linguistics on the acquisition of French as
a foreign language and I kind of abandoned theoretical linguistics and became more interested
in applied linguistics and so my first applied linguistic paper appeared in 92 was on the omission
of Neu in French interlanguage so that was in fact a combination of social linguistics and
applied linguistics and then I published my first papers in French then realized that I would probably
reach a wider audience if I wrote the papers in English but my English wasn't that good so I had
to ask a friend to help me out and so by 2000 I was writing in English and I was interested there
also in gender assignment and gender agreement in advanced French interlanguage that was
part of my PhD dissertation and I also became interested in the use of colloquial words and
emotional words and swear words in advanced French interlanguage so I was still very much
focused on French as a second language at the start of my career and then I had
critical incidents so I encountered my colleagues when I joined Bergbeck in 1994
I realized that I had gaps in my social pragmatic competence in English I was able to understand
I was able to understand most of what my colleagues said but I didn't always understand what they
actually meant so I understood the words but I didn't always get what their emotions were
and what they really meant so I couldn't really read between the stiff upper lips of my colleague
and then I had a chat with an aunt of mine who worked in palliative care and ELSE is her name
and she asked me so what do you do I said oh well you know I teach at the university and I do research
and I had just published it was the conversation happened in to early 2001 and I said you know and
I have had just this paper out on how learners of French agree gender sometimes and sometimes they
don't and isn't that fascinating and and she looked at me and she said so you are really splitting
hairs and I thought oh that's not very kind but I laughed and I said well I guess so yeah but you
know it's my hobby and I get paid to do it but it felt a bit lame and then 9-11 happened and I felt
that suddenly as applied linguists there was an urgent need for us to promote peace tolerance of
diversity in fact the underlining the value of multilingualism and multiculturalism and
positive thinking and that it was our moral duty as applied linguists to do some good
for society that we needed to get out of our ivory towers and so I left the ivory tower and
met a huge amount of people and a few names there a picture there with Beverly Costa we got an award
for our work then bottom left is with Kasia Saito who's a great friend and then in the middle a picture
with Peter McIntyre, Tammy Gregerson and Elaine Horitz and Sarah Mercer who became lifelong friends
and to the right there holding the distinguished scholarship award from AAA L Annetta Pavlenko
surrounded by Peter De Costa and Lourdes Ortega so all these people became really good friends
and I realized that one of my early papers really had an impact we were among the first to introduce
the word emotion in applied linguistics and in a paper in 2002 and then Annetta and I realized
that the emotion was really an interesting topic that not much had been written about it
and that we could organize panels on emotions and multilingualism at different conferences
which is what we did in the early 2000s and then based on these panels we
guest edited special issues in different journals and so we attracted attention to the topic and
we invited colleagues to join us and then we developed a follow-up study we developed a
bilingualism and emotion questionnaire which was probably the first and the biggest online
questionnaire in applied linguistics it remained online for two years collected data from over 1500
multilinguals and those of you who listened to my first talk remember that it was about
language preferences to express emotions also information on proficiency on anxiety and we
found that the first language is typically preferred for communication of emotion and it's
typically felt to have most emotional resonance so once we had all those data we published papers
on that and then we realized that we both had to publish a book on it and that it would be
more helpful to each have a separate book rather than to have a co-author book so Annetta published
her book pretty soon in 2005 and then I published mine five years later with a slightly different
focus and so the mine was more had more statistics in it than Annetta and you I don't remember whether
I told you that the face the self-portrait on the cover of my book is in fact a painting that is
hanging here in my office it's the self-portrait by my maternal grandfather from 1933 and he was
a passionate bilingual so I thought right he's the perfect person and this is the perfect
cover for my book and then in 2005 I was also among the first to call for more attention to
psychological and emotional dimensions in second language acquisition research and again I didn't
know at the time that that paper would get cited quite a lot and then interesting emotion research
started to develop more gradually in applied linguistics it had been dominantly cognitive
until the time with the focus on observable and measurable units and I had this chat with John
Schumann who's one of the founders of applied linguistics and professor of applied linguistics
at UCLA in California and he said well you know it's about applied linguists wanting to make sure
that they are taken seriously that they do that they are real scientists so they use sophisticated
statistics so they can legitimately be considered as scientists and he said emotions are probably
less attractive because they have no observable physical reference in the world and they fell
outside of the traditional remit of second language acquisition so the winds of change started to come
with the introduction of more qualitative research in applied linguistics where it suddenly became
okay to look at the L2 learners subjective side that included emotion, investment, duty,
love, desire and I refer here to the work by Claire Kramsch and Anita Pavlenko and I think I also
reminded you during my first session about the metaphor about emotions being the elephant in
the room that everybody knows they are there but they are not really taken into consideration
because they are considered to be inferior to rational thought and hopefully this change now
with the prior saying that yeah there is an elephant but it's time to open the windows and
to move on and so we have had the so-called emotional term and also the effective term
in fact I guess applied linguists and authors love to coin a nice new collocation linked to
their name so emotional term effective term they are good collocation see it shows that
there suddenly is some kind of maybe not paradigm shift but mini paradigm shift
also I ran the ngram viewer to look at the use of the word emotion in written text since the
1800s and you see that there's been a sharp increase in the word emotion since the 1990s
really so I would say that my interest in emotional and applied linguistics in a sense
reflects an increased interest in that word and an increased use of that word
across different disciplines across different genres and styles so I guess there is more
publicity ads that play on our emotions today than they would have 40 years ago
also although there wasn't much about emotion in applied linguistics in fact there were
emotional journals in psychology and these three journals were all established late 20th century
early of our current century so you see that there was interest in emotion that it typically
started at that point but it took a little while before it came into applied linguistics and
the introduction in Dorne and Ryan in 2015 is telling in that the authors say that of course
the classic individual differences paradigm in applied linguistics barely acknowledges
the central role of emotions and feelings and emotions play a huge part in all our lives
they have been shunned to a large extent by both psychology and second language acquisition
literature so there is a general emotional deficit and they acknowledge
that the 2005 version of their book reflected this trend so it was an ongoing conversation
I had with Zoltan and with Steven Ryan that that emotion needed more attention and why
weren't they talking about emotion more and so I was pretty happy in 2015 when they acknowledged
that yes they should have talked more about emotion and then I also realized that of course
our research is spread over different fields that in the social psychological research tradition
motivation researchers typically had included anxiety dimensions but had never included
positive emotion dimensions if there were positive emotions there were typically item
level emotions like I like my English class but there wasn't a proper foreign language
enjoyment dimension for example and most research on emotions had focused on foreign language
classroom anxiety also looking at applied linguistics there is in fact only one journal
journal for the psychology of language learning that has the word psychology in the title and I
also added the journal of language and social psychology but that's in fact a psychological
paper so it's a social psychological journal I talked to you in my second session about
learner emotions and how the interest in learner emotions came after the introduction of positive
psychology in applied linguistics 2012 paper by Pete McIntyre and Gregerson and then a 2014
paper also by McIntyre and Mercer about what positive psychology could bring to second language
acquisition research it was followed by two edited books one edited in Poland by Danuta
Gampis Barker and her colleague Dagmara on positive psychology perspectives in foreign
language learning and teaching and also a book published by Multilingual Matters edited by
McIntyre Gregerson and Mercer on positive psychology in SNA and the publication of these two books
helped strengthen the growing interest in positive psychology in learner emotions and also later
in teacher emotions and then in my second session I presented the paper that I co-authored
with Peter McIntyre the Two Faces of Yanus where we presented the concept of foreign language
enjoyment it's been my most cited paper and then also with Chen Chen Li we published a paper in
a Chinese journal which I like because we shouldn't just publish in international
journals we should also publish in national journals where we talked about the four or
the three phases of emotions where they were first avoided because cognition was the only
thing that mattered then the second phase where there was interest in anxiety including the work
by crashing on his effective filter hypothesis and then Elena's horrid foreign language classroom
anxiety and the phase we are currently in which is a positive and negative emotions phase
thanks to the emotional turn and positive psychology where we've taken a more holistic
view on emotions and look at a variety of different emotions that learners and teachers
may experience so we conceptualized enjoyment as this complex and positive emotion that occurs
when people not just meet their needs but exceed them do something unexpected you may remember that
I cited the meta-analysis that showed that if you suffer from high anxiety in your classroom
you typically don't do as well whereas if you enjoy your foreign language classroom a lot
you are typically more willing to communicate and you typically will have better results so the
pedagogical implication of that is that teachers can create optimal positive atmosphere so part of
my research output has been the creation of new instruments and those turned out to be highly
cited although we didn't really do it to get high citation but if you develop a new instrument
to do further research on a certain topic they need to be solid and so you see I love collaborating
with Ilwis Bottes and Chen Chen Li to do this and then you know I don't want to read this out
obviously but we did a lot of work on the sources and the effects of enjoyment anxiety and boredom
how that is linked to teacher behavior how different positive personality traits are linked
to willingness to communicate and to performance how it's linked to trait emotional intelligence
we also looked at enjoyment in first language classes and discovered that it is that different
from foreign language classes and yeah and then more recently I did a couple of
studies on teacher emotions teachers who are forced to smile in front of a class when they
don't feel like smiling because they are tired or stressed and and also the the role of the teacher
in front of the class where through a process of emotional contagion a happy teacher can make the
whole classroom happy unhappy teacher can also contain you know in fact the everybody and where
everybody feels depressed so as a teacher you really need that emotional labor to keep a smile on
your face and on the face of your your students and then with Prihati Ergun we looked at the link
between well-being resilience and foreign language teaching enjoyment so that that's another
interesting concept so what what makes a teacher enjoy his or her teaching and and to what extent
is it linked to teacher internal variables like well-being and resilience and then I did a lot of
work thanks to a PhD student of mine on emotion recognition and so how do we recognize how a
multilingual feels when we watch or an audio when we watch a video recording or when we listen to an
audio recording and and this turns out to to to be an area of research that that really caught my
attention and and it was thanks to this PhD student Pernell Lorette and a number of other
lovely colleagues and then I think also in my first lecture that I mentioned how my interest in emotion
developed into the more specific context of multilingualism in psychotherapy
where we discovered that very often multilingual clients feel that their multilingualism and
multiculturalism is not sufficiently addressed in therapy and that there are also differences
between monolingual and multilingual therapists in how they deal with their with their clients and
that research won us a reward an award from the British Association for Counseling and Psychotherapy
so it was clear that we had been doing something original that had practical implications and
the practical implications we worked on them trying to raise awareness about multilingualism
and the issues that this implies for the psychotherapist and we published a couple of papers
on that topic also thanks to Beverly Costa we try to disseminate our findings to a larger audience
and Beverly Costa not only did she train about 3000 trainee therapists in a program called
Improving Access to Psychological Therapists in the UK training also a clinical supervisor
but she also had the brilliant idea to hire an established author to turn to
turn our research findings and her case notes into a play so Andrew Weir wrote the session
based on an original idea by Mother Tong and it's about a Polish woman married to a British man
and they have communication problems and he doesn't value her cultural background enough and
there is some trauma about the child and so it was performed at the Soho Theatre and about
3000 people came to see that play and so the play was really about the issues that we had
found in our research and that was a nice way to disseminate the findings also our research
had an impact in that the British Association for Counseling and Psychotherapists clearly
added the importance of being aware of unconscious linguistic bias assumptions
and privilege if you work with multilingual clients the crucial need to offer linguistically
sensitive supervision acknowledging the role of language and identity development processing
of trauma memory recall and emotional expression so that was in fact clearly linked to the work
I had been doing with Beverly Costa and that applies to the UK but it implies in fact it
applies to other contexts also of course so to conclude I would say that research doesn't
emerge in a vacuum that emotion research emerged against the odds that was kind of inevitable
that intense academic socialization collaboration needs to join development and new ideas
I think it really helps to write in English to reach a wider audience I think it's also crucial
to talk to people from neighboring disciplines for cross-fertilization and that doing research is
just fantastic it's exhilarating intoxicating unpredictable and I would say that it is absolutely
worth the effort and because there were so many words I want to finish with some pictures so the
top left picture you will recognize the face of Zoltan Doge at the conference dinner in
grass in 2014 and beneath that is a Jew who is sitting on the floor during a triple AL conference
being in a packed room and being a bit tired and at the bottom left there I was at an emotion
conference with my then current PhD and former PhD students and then the other pictures again
walking going to conferences having dinners and top right is my friend Lee Wei giving a
plenary at conferences meaning what I'm saying here is that research happens because you are
collaborating with absolutely lovely people and if somebody turns out not to be lovely you just
drop them and you work with the ones that you appreciate and that keep their word and that
have the integrity and honesty and friendship and if they can bake banana breads when you
go to a conference and they give you a bit of banana bread that's even better that's a hint
because that's what Jakub did at the last euro slot conference so many thanks and I hope you will
have some questions for me encouraged by all means and the priority goes to the people in the room
you know that you can approach this place anytime you are not seen because the camera is off
so all you need is a bit of courage we had that happen before so if you think of asking a question
now is the perfect opportunity first of all the people in the hall
especially those people who are thinking of doing perhaps further research and applied linguistics
I can see that there is a question in the chat
all right
yes let me start with the first hello hello Joe Mark can you hear me okay go ahead yes
it's Jace Krisevich
I decided to to write you to write a question or rather not a question but a comment
so if you if you don't mind I will just I would just read the read those out so
I have two comments to make first of all I'd be cautious to take to advise young scholars
in the first half of your lecture here to better publish something than nothing
even though you immediately done played this with the recommendation not to publish crap
what I think is that unfortunately in in the majority of cases the urge and the pressure
on young people to to publish and the imperative to do so especially nowadays in what I call mass
university culture where we have dozens and dozens and dozens of phd students
taking interest in second language acquisition first language acquisition god knows what
and they are really pressed not maybe not that pressed in poland as they are in in in uh in your
country or in the west in general so this leads to unfortunately this leads to this something
that is better than nothing it leads to this something being of rather low both intellectual
as well as methodological piece of pseudo research yeah my second comment is the first one first
okay so so when I say something is better than nothing I meant in fact book reviews
write book reviews and write them for good journals so um because writing a book review
might not be what you originally would love to have which is a research paper but I would say
I would argue that that is the crucial first step right a couple of book reviews and after
that you will have acquired the skills to write research papers so don't run before you can walk
I would say although on this point I would also disagree with you you know I I can't
frankly speaking I can't somehow imagine a beginning phd student to write let's say a review of
of Derneis wrote on Derneis the psychology of language learner book review with well this little
experience in research very little experience in in in methodology in teaching in what really
the job is about the review okay the review might be a kind of review which you a student
might be encouraged to present in his seminar or something but I would I would be very cautious to
advise this for him to publish this because I mean this is this is my yeah my my opinion okay I
agree with you that writing a really good book review is difficult but it is feasible for someone
who's starting a phd because it shows an ability to synthesize so they need to to say okay this
book has three parts it's a part about this it's a part about that it's a part about that
so so that is not too difficult right if you are if you have a masters you can do this and
the final part then you don't need to have huge research experience to say that you really enjoyed
this and that that that you you you felt the author could have said more on that and that
and and so you you don't say anything obviously wrong or anyway the reviews editor would say well
you know you're a bit too negative or maybe you're a bit too positive or maybe you should do a bit of
that so you get some feedback but it's not too hard to produce a book review if you don't have too
much research experience but of course I mean we could discuss this further over a glass of beer
it's a huge topic but I would like to comment here too so my case my story is a bit different
and I think there are quite a few people like me who did their phd not as young people but in my case
after about 20 years of teaching experience and for me conceptualizing a topic in my case
how to facilitate self-regulated learning in a foreign language classroom
was a kind of literature review I did not use any data and I also did that like some other reviews
first because I was at the very early stage of my career and second we had a covid pandemic
so there was a limited opportunity to produce any sort of research so I just published to publish
something I'm not fully happy with the publication because there is also this thing that you know
year after year you become more critical of your own work which I think is quite natural
but I think it's not wasted effort so I had to think I had to conceptualize it
it had a revolving theme and it also gave me an opportunity to grow
mm-hmm so I'd say there is there is some positive thing about writing reviews
yeah
yeah we have one more comment one more comment and question from Dr Rusevich go on
so my my second point is about the neglect of affect so I don't think that affect has been I'll
just read through this has been neglected in second language acquisition at least not from
crashans affective filter theory I think that the problem with the affective factors is not that
the effects are unobservable as you said but that they are difficult to operationalize and tease out
from the intricate interplay of the whole array of emotional influences that are at play in second
language acquisition consequently the relative difficulty of identifying the affective effects
in second language acquisition following the difficulty in their operationalization leads
an ever-increasing number of young scholars to fall victim to some pre scientific and
straightforwardly bogus ideas which have been flying around for decades in second language
acquisition and particularly in teacher training okay and here I mean ideas like multiple intelligences
for example flow by jigs and mihi okay matching learning styles with instruction
nlp neuro uh neuro didactics uh the the pre preoccupation with totally unresearchable
ideas unoperationalizable ideas like boredom and so on and this simply takes the whole attention
of the real factors involved in second language acquisition which are researchable
to those on which scholars can sort of float without really doing anything serious in that
matter this is my comment Jean-Marc okay you know I've been always I've been always critical of
this kind of things okay uh what do you say about that I my my reaction is don't throw the baby out
with the bathwater that yes of course there are things that are over the top in in second language
acquisition research as in any area of research and that you need to discern what what is useful
and what isn't I mean that that's your responsibility as a researcher I kind of smile
because you don't like flow and I just inserted a reference to a paper that came out in a plot
linguistics earlier this week on flow and I talked about it in my session I don't think flow is
um a useless concept I think it's a very very interesting concept now the thing is
it's a metaphor this is a metaphor well no it describes something but sometimes you can
describe things that aren't necessarily always directly measurable in the sense that we
although in fact in the paper we do refer to neuro research that shows that specific areas
of the brain are in fact more heavily involved when people reach a flow state so this is not
esoteric stuff this is based on on solid science
the answer to the interesting affect in fact in a 2019 paper published in the modern language
journal I checked how often the word emotion and affect had been used in the modern language
journal on average and it turned out that before 2010 it was like an average of 8.5 times
a year that that word had been used after 2010 it went up sharply it went I think to 25 times
also before 2010 whenever there was talk of affect or emotion it was anxiety
after 2010 that that range increased so there is definitely increased interest
in in emotion and I totally agree with you that we need to avoid bogus ideas and there are bogus
ideas you know things like the lizard brain and and and stuff but we we think we I think we need to
be both critical but also courageous in trying to do solid research in areas where other people
may have had doubts so can you address the doubts can you convince them that this is solid
that you can actually measure this that people will agree with you
can you get your stuff published in the top journals if you can that's a kind of a validation
that flow is not just a bogus idea thanks I enjoyed I enjoyed your lecture
so hopefully we'll see each other in Sturck again I'm looking forward to that okay
right thank you very much both of you I think slowly time comes for a bit of round up
so I'm going to rely on my nose I really liked this metaphor I don't know how it is with you
guys but metaphors work with me so I like being able to hold into a metaphor and I really like
this one about the grain of sounds which you add to the pyramid of knowledge so we actually
build something huge and then when I was working with my boss professor Vishniewska on a very recent
paper I used another one which is in a way similar that's because that was about self-regulation
in the use of linguistic landscape and self-regulation is in general about being able to
use endless opportunities to learn worldwide and you spot the world as the endless stock of
knowledge and the first and most basic form of self-regulation is choosing the opportunity
you want to learn from so I think a lot of people are attending these lectures and I'm looking at
the people in the hall but also are relating to the people online have used this opportunity a lot
and I think it was a very wise choice using the opportunity of having Jean-Marc with us
I would also like to say that okay my boss has already mentioned one conference in 2025
uh to which she has invited Jean-Marc as a plenary speaker and we'll be honored
indeed if he appears but there is another one so I can officially say that we as a the Institute
of Applied Linguistics are going to apply for the organization of the Psychology and Language
Learning and Teaching Conference 2026 so we're going to go for the organization and hopefully
we can also meet here for that conference before that I'm pretty sure we're going to see each other
in Madrid in May so there will be time to talk about that too to round up thank you very much
for your for all your talks very inspirational and thank you very much indeed for being with us
and looking forward to seeing you again Jean-Marc thank you thank you very much it was a pleasure
talking to you all and I wish you all well in your academic careers and yeah it was a bit strange to
be only online but I'm looking forward to being in Poznan again at some point all right thank you
very much indeed and looking forward to seeing you here in the future in person thank you and
hello Camilla good to see you in person yeah thank you thank you so much thank you bye okay bye bye