Welcome to this brief introduction to TiddlyWiki.
TiddlyWiki is a powerful note-taking tool that helps you collect and structure any kind
of information and work with it to get stuff done.
It's like a hypertext card index system from the future.
TiddlyWiki deals with information in bite-sized linked chunks called Tiddlers.
Tiddlers are the fundamental units of information in TiddlyWiki.
Tiddlers work best when they are as small as possible so that they can be reused by
weaving them together into different narratives and perspectives.
You can create relationships between Tiddlers with links.
They are typed with double-square brackets so that linking becomes part of the punctuation
of writing.
Tiddlers can also include formatting.
Formatted text is typed with special codes like this.
TiddlyWiki is not just for text.
Images are first-class citizens too.
TiddlyWiki even lets you edit images.
TiddlyWiki also supports audio.
Audio is a first-class citizen alongside images and text.
Tiddlers can be further structured with tags.
The Tiddler can have any number of tags to assign it to categories.
Each tag is shown with a drop-down menu that lets you view and navigate to other Tiddlers
with the same tag.
Transcluding a Tiddler inserts a copy of its content, allowing you to reuse the same text
or image more than once.
In this example, we're using the same picture of a cat stored in a Tiddler called MottovenJack.svg
in two different places.
We can also weave Tiddlers together into lists.
Here's an example of a list of all of the Tiddlers that carry a particular tag.
TiddlyWiki is flexible, but it can be extended in new ways with plugins.
For example, the KTex plugin uses an open-source library to typeset mathematical notation.
TiddlyWiki also has translations into several languages that have been created by members
of the community.
So, to find out how to get started, go to tiddlywiki.com slash hash getting started.
Thank you very much.