Ja, einen wunderschönen guten Abend. Ich darf Sie herzlich heute Abend hier begrüßen
im Affirmengrat. Wir haben einen sehr illustren Gast, der heute hier zu uns zu Ihnen zu mir
sprechen wird. Mein Name ist Sebastian Braunes. Ich darf heute ein bisschen durch den Abend
führen. Freue mich, dass Sie so zahlreich erschienen sind und schon in großteiligere
Plätze eingenommen haben. Das Ganze heute am Abend wird sich in einem kurzen Überblick
für Sie ungefähr so gestalten. Ich rede jetzt da mit Ihnen bis alle da sind und versuche
die Zeit ein bisschen zu überbrücken. Und dann begrüße ich Herrn Schischek, der kommt
dann auf die Bühne, wenn Sie wollen, applaudieren Sie. Und danach spricht Herr Schischek zu Ihnen
und ein bisschen auch zu mir. Und danach wird das Ganze ein Gespräch und das Schöne an
dem Gespräch ist, dass wir hier so ein großes Forum haben und dass es unbedingt wichtig
wäre und auch gewollt ist, dass ich dann vielleicht mit einer oder anderen Frage oder
mit einer oder anderen Ergänzung zu dem, was der Herr Schischek so von sich geben wird,
einmengen. Es ist nur eine weitere Sache wichtig. Das Ganze endet um 19.30 Uhr und es findet
danach ein Konzert statt. Deswegen würde ich Sie bitten, geordnet und ruhig, aber rasch,
den Saal zu verlassen, weil die Sessel auf denen Sie sitzen, die müssen dann auch noch
raus und weil die keine Beine haben oder beziehungsweise die haben vier Beine natürlich, aber die können
nicht selber gehen. Die müssen dann von dienstfertigen Helfern und Helferinnen entfernt werden und
das dauert ein bisschen und deswegen wäre es gut, wenn wir pünktlich Schluss machen.
Ich werde mich jetzt auch nicht so lang darin erschöpfen, den Herrn Professor Schischek vorzustellen,
weil ich bin fast 100%ig überzeugt, dass Sie alle deswegen da sind, weil Sie in Kennen
sich vielleicht eine andere Meinung zu im Bilden wollen oder was er sagt, bzw. in Kennen
lernen wollen, aber sich ein bisschen informiert haben vorher, zum Beispiel im Internet. Also
da gibt es die ärgsten Sachen und ja, wirklich schwer, ich bin auch manchmal dort. Und deswegen
glaube ich, muss ich jetzt nicht ausführlich alle Buchtitel aufzählen bzw. sagen, an welchen
Instituten er Professorinstühle hält und mit welchen Markanten und Markigen und vielleicht
auch kontroversellen Äußerungen er bis jetzt schon aufgefallen ist oder dass er sich sehr
viel Kritik gefallen lassen musste, weil er fast kaum seine eigene These aus sich selbst
herausentwickelt, verteidigt, sondern meistens referenziert, aber es ist das Feld der Philosophie,
Gott sei Dank ein Weites und gerade in Zeiten wie diesen vielleicht auch wichtig, dass
wir auch heute hier gemeinsam den Gedanken einer Kommunikation und eines Vorurums miteinander
hochhalten. Das Elevates Festival stellt diese Begegnung hier auch ein bisschen unter den
Gedanken der unlikely Alliances, also zu Deutsch vielleicht etwas untypischen Allianzen und
ich hoffe, so eine kann heute hier auch unter möglichst der Negation dieser Rampe, die
immer leider auch ein bisschen segregierend ist zwischen ihnen und dem, was hier passiert,
stattfinden. Markig gesprochen wird es wohl um Katastrophen gehen, das ist ja prinzipiell
nichts Schlimmes, kann man sich auch oft im Internet anschauen, wo es wie gesagt die ärgsten
Sachen gibt und sie sind ja auch quasi auf eine gewisse Art und weiß es sich auch der
Kit, der uns irgendwie alle zusammenhalten, wo wir zusammenrücken können, wenn wir wollen
und gemeinsam was meistern und vielleicht auch was schaffen, was wir alleine gar nicht so
schaffen können. Aber auf der anderen Seite beinhalten sie natürlich auch die Gefahr,
dass das Individuum vielleicht ein bisschen zurückstecken muss und das ist gerade in Zeiten
wie diesen und an einem Tag wie heute. Vielleicht gar nicht so eine angenehme Sache. Es ist auch
irgendwie interessant, dass 90 Jahre in der Vergangenheit von genau heute aus die 1. Republik
Österreich sich zum ersten Mal verabschiedert hat und der ständige Staat übernommen. Das Parlament
hat sich ausgeschaltet und jetzt ist es 90 Jahre später und wir haben noch immer trying times,
vielleicht sogar noch mehr, liegt vielleicht auch daran, dass wir alle viel besser informiert sind
oder vermeintlich besser informiert sind. Also ich freue mich sehr, dass ich jetzt hier auf der
Bühne Professor Slavoj Sijek begrüßen darf. Begrüßen Sie ihn mit mir, bitte.
Charles Chaplin, das ist ein Great Dictator, er stopps die Applaus.
Ok, ich muss mich erst entschuldigen, ich verstehe deutsche Sprache eventuelle Fragen.
Sie können die Fragen natürlich auf Deutsch stellen, nur ich kann nicht flüssig Deutsch sprechen
und eine kleine Kritik an dir, was habe ich dort gehört, das bin ich nicht, Herr Professor Doktor.
Was habe ich dir zu dir gemacht?
Hast du deine Mutter geschraubt oder was?
Eigentlich, eigentlich, ich habe genau das Opposite gemacht. Ich habe gesagt, ich möchte nicht auf
deinem Doktor und Professor Kajos erledigen. Das ist gut, ja, weil ich mich für diesen
Backtaste spielen will. Du bist braunisch, ich bin braunisch, ich bin blühig.
Ich bin blühiger als du.
Ok, ich bin sorry, jetzt ist es seriös.
Wenn du mich erlaubst, ich werde nicht zu lange versuchen.
Bitte, wenn du dir fühlst, dass etwas provokative ist, es ist aufgrund der Perfektivität,
nicht zu beleidigen dich, nicht zu kürzen dich, sondern einfach zu bringen aus der realen Debatte.
Weil ich denke, dass auf beiden Seiten der sogenannten Gewöhnung, liberalen Seite und den sogenannten
neuen Fundamentalisten, Rechtesten der Debatte weniger und weniger möglich ist.
So, lasst mich beginnen.
Ich war so glücklich zu lernen, dass der generalte Titel dieser Event Unholy Alliances.
Weil das schon die Antwort zu meinem Titel, nur eine Katastrophe, was uns zu sagen kann.
Warum? Weil wir in einem Zeitpunkt Unholy Alliances leben.
Ich werde es versuchen, und dann gehen wir auf einen freien Dialog.
Ich werde es versuchen, diesen Dialog zu holen, auch wenn es manchmal lustig ist.
Es ist sehr schwer und seriös.
Ich denke, dass wir heute wirklich leben.
Es ist nicht eine empty Phase, in einem komplexen Zeitpunkt.
Nicht komplex in diesem empirischen Sinn.
Ja, die Situation ist immer komplex.
Also, zum Beispiel, um einen Schritt zur aktuellen Situation zu machen.
Ich bin, natürlich, in dieser Welt pro-Ukrainian.
Und ich liebe, wenn meine Freunde mir sagen, aber Sie wissen, dass die Ukrainien nicht so gut sind.
Die Situation ist sehr komplex.
Wobei, die Situation ist immer komplex.
In World War II, es war nicht einfach Demokratie gegen Nationalismus.
Weil ich sorry, Stalin war nicht Demokratie und so weiter.
Und wir mussten zusammen mit den Fortschreitern.
Aber ich werde mich direkt mit einem großen Unholy Alliances beobachten.
Was Putin, nicht nur Putin, ist zu Ende geäußert.
Ich weiß nicht, wer Putin ist.
Und sie hat mir gesagt, was Putin macht, ist interessant.
Auf der einen Seite ist er auf der Orthodox-Church-Support.
Die, wie man es nennt, Patriarch, oder sowas von der Orthodox-Church in Russland.
In Russland, Kirill.
Er ist ein alter KGB-Fellow von Putin.
Aber nicht nur das.
Putin hat etwas sehr Interessantes gemacht.
Er hat Kontrolle.
Eine Gruppe von jungen leftistischen Marxisten.
Und sie sind diejenigen, die ihm hissen wollen.
Er ist fast offen.
Eine konservative Art der Argumentation.
Western Europe ist der Realum von Satanismus.
Kirill, Patriarch, hat auch den größten Exorzisten der Zeit geklärt.
Ich habe eine wundervolle Debatte auf Russland.
Ich folge es.
Ich meine, um eine ideologische Bedeutung.
Wenn jemand die Pro-Putin-Figur betrifft und sagt,
aber bist du wirklich sicher, dass die Ukrainien die Nazis generieren?
Und der Mann sagt, okay,
wenn du abstrakt bist, ignorierst alle anderen Dinge,
und du bist in Kirill, wie der größte Horror.
Aber was machen die Marxisten?
Sie geben...
An dieser anderen Art der Argumentation,
ist, dass wir für alle dritten Menschen
gegen die imperialisten, neokolonialisten,
sowas wie die Westerndominanz haben.
Und die dritte Sache ist, wie?
Diese beiden Aktien,
die ersten, anti, gay, LGBT, Westerndekadenz,
und die anderen, wie die Western-Imperialisten und so,
bekommen zusammen,
das ist eine Katastrophe.
Das ist die erste unruhige Allianz.
Check in your newspapers.
It happened a day or two ago in Uganda.
The parliament passed a terrifying law,
that if you are caught in homosexual relationship,
it's not just you are a little bit ostracized.
You can even get death penalty,
but at least ten years of prison and all that.
And then when a Western journalist protested,
this happened two days ago.
A member of Ugandan parliament told him,
you are either with us supporting our anti gay legislation
or you are with the Western world.
This is a terrifying unholy alliance,
that you address third world nations,
but at the same time playing this sexually conservative,
anti gay rights, anti LGBT plus and so on logic.
And so can you imagine for so called,
I hate the term, but I will use it as an abbreviation,
for so called non binary people.
You use the general term.
You know what's the bad news that to fight for gay rights
in all this is perceived in many countries
as part of Western imperialism.
This alliance had to be broken somehow.
Now I go to another example of this unholy alliance.
I think maybe you know more like two weeks ago or three,
when there were big pro freedom,
pro peace demonstrations in Berlin and in Dresden and so on.
I mean, I almost cried.
It's so sad.
Part of the linke Partei in Deutschland,
Sarah Wagenknecht, gave a speech,
all this false pacifist stuff.
Why should we get involved?
This is not our war blah blah blah.
And then you know what she got next day.
Not ironically an invitation from a high ranking member
of alternative für Deutschland.
But you speak like us, like join us and so on.
And this is not a joke.
This is now happening in my own country in Slovenia,
in England, in United States and so on,
that the pro Russian attitude is adopted by extreme left
and extreme right.
Why?
Well, maybe you know this joke,
but what came to my mind is this,
I even wrote a book with this in the title,
the wonderful simple,
but nonetheless a joke by Freud from his book on Witz,
on jokes, where he quotes this joke,
where you give too many arguments for a thing,
but they are mutually exclusive,
like the book I wrote against the Iraq war,
American attack on Iraq has the title,
the broken Iraqi, this cap or whatever.
Like I borrow from you a cap or an a vase,
and I return it to you broken.
And you of course accuse me.
And my answer is A, I never borrow a vase from you B.
I return it to you full,
and C, it was already broken when you gave it to me.
I notice that this pro sympathy for Russia argument
has exactly the same structure.
Did you notice that there are three arguments?
First is generally pacifist.
Wars are madness.
We shouldn't give arms because of the general wisdom.
If you give arms, you only prolong the conflict.
This is, I think, a terrifying notion.
Because at the same time this pacifist's claim,
but now there is a situation more or less,
how to call it, stable position on front,
to push for peace.
Yes, but how did we arrive at this position?
By supporting Ukraine.
Can you imagine what would have happened there without?
And then I draw a comparison,
for which I got much hatred,
that I draw a parallel between today's Pisonics
and some crazy communists.
At the beginning of World War II,
when on the West they had that phony war,
who claimed this is imperialist conflict.
We should stay neutral and fraternized
with German soldiers.
This is not our war and so on and so on.
So, the first reasoning is this abstract pacifist.
I disagree with it, not because I like war.
But I think it's absolutely clear that Russia is engaged
in the long-term geopolitical rearrangement.
And it's clear, not by any sinister hermeneutics,
but they say it, the Russian, that they want to go on.
Moldova, now they officially claim to have real peace.
We have to push the borders of Poland a little bit to the West.
We already have Georgian Georgia.
We already had Crimea and so on.
So, I think that's the paradox.
I accept that.
Yes, we shouldn't aim at destroying Russia.
That's unacceptable.
But Habermas Jürgen,
who we don't like each other personally,
but he put it very nicely almost a year ago,
where he says we shouldn't speak the language of destroy Russia.
But simply negatively, Ukraine must not perish.
It's in our interest.
Especially, again, in view of this more and more crazy,
directly male-Sovienist ideological foundation,
which is Western Europe is the reign of Satan,
unholy orgies and all that stuff.
Now, here again,
there is unfortunately a moment of truth
that the West is still engaged many times in some kind of
neo-colonial, post-colonial exploitation.
But my answer to this is double.
First, do you think that China is any better?
I don't know what our media report.
I know that when Chinese buy some resources,
some mines in, I think it was Zambia, when they bought them,
there was a local rebellion.
Because the local workers there wanted monthly salary of $200.
It was too much.
Chinese brought their own start people who were ready to work
for a little bit over $100 per month and so on.
So, neo-colonialism is expanding, but it's everywhere.
Second thing that makes this alliance between left and Putin unholy is,
I don't know what's the logic.
Yes, another thing, sorry, the first argument.
We want peace, peace at any price,
and usually in my country in Slovenia,
then the politicians who follow this line add something very cynical.
They say every war has to end up with negotiations and compromise.
And my answer to them is, ah, really?
Then we were thought wrong.
Do you remember in 45, there were negotiations and packed with Hitler?
No, it wasn't.
There was a clear defeat.
So again, this general pacifist stance has to be rejected on behalf of real peace itself.
Remember one thing that I repeat all the time.
Peace is always in the interest of the occupier.
I believe, I'm not anti-Semitic, I'm totally pro-Jewish.
But on the West Bank, Israel is colonizing it.
And when Israel says we want peace there, I believe them.
Because peace means they can occupy it in peace.
Of course, even Germans, when they occupied France in 39,
where they sincerely for peace, of course they were.
Peace means we can occupy it.
That's why General De Gaulle, you know what was his great statement,
which found that resistance.
No, the war is not over.
France did not capitulate.
So I reject this general line.
Then the second line of defense is, what I already mentioned, the situation is complex.
Nobody is clear there.
I know, I will not bore you now with it, but I can give you some,
once I enumerated them, some 15 to 20 points of mistakes,
stupidities committed by Ukrainians.
But sorry, this is like condemning and we should.
For example, the Allied attack in March 45, I think, on Dresden,
which was totally unnecessary militarily.
Or, for example, the Allied bombing of Hamburg with those terrible storms.
Why?
Because, as parents of my friends in Hamburg told me,
you know what they did, the Allies, they were obsessed with the idea
that it's more important to broke the morale of the working class
than to destroy industry.
So they focused their bombings on working class suburbs
and they left all the great villas and so on and so on.
But nonetheless, this doesn't change the fact who was right.
So often complexity is an excuse.
And the third argument is a vulgar pragmatic one.
It's not our war.
Why should we, because of two crazy nations fighting on the edge of Europe,
why should we pay more for electricity and so on and so on?
I find, again, I find this logic terrifying.
It's true what my friends are saying, some pro Russians,
that the conflict in Ukraine is a conflict between two visions of the world.
But their interpretation is it's western imperialist vision
and authentic multicultural vision of coexistence and so on of different both.
I don't like the coexistence that Putin stands for.
You know where you get a model of this coexistence.
You remember when Taliban took over, they immediately made peace with China.
The deal was what?
You Chinese allow us in Afghanistan to do what we want, to treat women the way we do.
But we will not mess with what you are doing with Uyghur Muslims in your country.
It tells a lot, if you look at who are Russia's direct allies today.
Iran, North Korea and so on, Afghanistan even.
It tells you a lot about how, and this is a horrible thing to accept,
yes, world imperialism and so on and so on.
But my God, can't we accept that in spite of all the horrors of western imperialism,
what Putin stands for is nonetheless worse.
And now I come to first time, I return to my title, Catastrophe Can Save Us.
You know that the latest news I got from my friends in Ukraine, give a little bit of hope.
Ukraine no doubt was an extremely corrupted country and so on with all the oligarchs.
But do you know that now the left is awakening slowly there?
They said, organizing themselves, wait a minute, half, even more of the oligarchs.
I don't know, it is here in Austria.
For example, many of them came to Slovenia and close to Austrian border, Radenska, a big spa.
They simply rented for month the biggest luxurious hotel and so on.
And people in Ukraine are asking, we are doing the fighting, they are doing that.
It's under their pressure that Zelensky is now organizing this anti-corruption campaign.
He knows that people are not simply fighting, they are raising the crucial question, which is,
but what is the Ukraine for which we are fighting?
Will it be the same extremely corrupted oligarchs system?
And that's why I wrote a text for which I was attacked.
Maybe, I don't know if it appeared in Germany, with the title Ukraine Between Two Colonizations.
Yes, Russia wants to colonize it.
But what do you think the West is doing?
Do you know that they have in the South, the black earth, allegedly the most fertile West in the world?
But do you know that one third of this best earth in the world is already owned by American agricultural corporations?
Do you know that there is all the time pressure also from the West on Ukraine,
that it should become neokonomically at least dependent on the West?
My hope is that now, maybe something will come out of it, maybe not, that Ukraine will begin to awaken.
Also, to ask the question again, again, not just free Ukraine, but what kind of Ukraine.
So, another thing, then people tell me, and I come again to this, I'm holding a lens, and so on,
other people are telling me, but these are just words, okay, putting talks against Satanism, world domination,
but he really wants just a piece of land there, a little bit.
No, sorry, this is a big philosophical even mistake.
Ideologie is never just ideology.
It has its own power, you pay the price for it.
Look at the Nazis.
The standard Marx explanation is anti-Semitism was just an ersatz for class and camp.
Really, they wanted to keep capitalism, Nazis, and so on.
Yeah, but the result was nonetheless millions of death, and so on.
And ideology gets its own efficiency.
Like, I don't know why this anecdote stuck so deeply in my mind,
when in 44 Germany was withdrawing from Greek islands.
They noticed that on one island they left 150 Jews.
And in that crazy situation where they needed every soldier, they sent a military boat back to get those Jews.
This didn't help them militarily in any way.
So again, I don't buy this story, it's really just about material interests.
No, ideology is to be taken seriously.
My next conclusion here to provoke you a little bit with philosophy.
This is why I am sick and tired of this critique of capitalism, that it's egotist.
We care only for our interests.
No, the problem of capitalism is, as Walter Benjamin knew, that it's a religious phenomenon,
a religious in the sense of radical sacrifice, a true fanatical capitalist.
He doesn't enjoy good life.
He is ready to work all the time fanatically so that capital reproduces itself.
No, we need today more egotism.
We need to ask not what about the fate of living on earth, but my God,
and my children live in 20, 30 years from now if we go on with this destruction of nature.
No, we should appeal to good egotism against this false capitalist ethics.
Now, the next point.
Ah, now things get, this was nothing to the provocation, more difficult.
The next unholy alliance that I see, trigger warning, this will be problematic for some of you.
Although I am, I cannot say it more, I have a whole school of followers among trans people, real trans people.
Not just that game, you know.
Now I'm a woman, I feel like a man and so on, but people who went through all the painful operations and so on,
and it's not just change, man into a woman, but trying to invent something third.
And you know where I agree with them?
LGBT Plus, in principle, I totally support it, not just in words, I was engaged in actions and so on.
But I don't like this anti-psychoanalytic trend.
The common place in many of these circles, in Germany, especially in the United States,
oh Freud is an old white dead man, he still thought in binary terms, eddipal complex and so on.
No, you know what's my problem?
You know this big conflict, especially in United States and United States,
between, let's call it biological determinists and LGBT feminists.
I simplify to the utmost.
Biological determinists claim that sexism, even if sex is confused, you don't know what you are,
but basically it's predetermined with your genetic structure or education or whatever,
and it's not a matter of free choice.
On the opposite hand you have non-binary, in the wrong way I claim people,
who claim people should be allowed to freely choose.
It's a matter of choice, how you feel.
I claim there is an unholy alliance here because they both behave as if Freud didn't exist.
For an authentic Freudian, of course sex is human sexuality is not directly a biological phenomenon.
It's how some Grundlage, some foundation is mediated, caught in a totally different logic
and it can even be, I have a friend, even can be demonstrated with experiments.
I have a friend who studies sexuality in apes, well-developed apes, gorillas, orangutans and men
and discovered that apes are much more rational.
Sorry for my tasteless way of saying.
Let's say you are a beautiful ape, woman.
I am an orangutans also.
I would like to have sex with you, but I see no way.
So ok, Fakoff, I turn attention elsewhere.
It's only with humans that you get this type of fix attachment,
that the more you are inaccessible to me, the more I'm obsessed.
So the whole logic changes.
Second point of Freud, crucial and some true LGBT people are well aware of it.
You know, sex is not in this vulgar sense a matter of free choice.
I feel like that.
No, the big revolution of Freud is that, one has to read him properly,
that this patriarchal symbolic order, male position, patriarchal feminine,
it's not natural, it's a long and painful process,
because we have something, we humans unique.
What Freud characterized as childhood infantile sexuality.
It's something very strange.
Animals, as far as we know, don't have it.
Because of the delayed puberty, we have it.
This idea that you get caught in crazy fantasies, how are children born?
And these fantasies can be very beautiful.
Let me tell intimate confession.
I clearly remember them, two of fantasies from my own youth.
When I vaguely knew that sex has to do something with health,
sorry, with childbirth.
With reproduction, yeah.
Yeah, with reproduction with copulation.
But I didn't know exactly how.
So one of my infantile theories was, and women liked it very much later,
that sex is long hard work.
You have to have, again and again, like you tell to your lover now again,
Orangutang and his wife, I tell you, let's screw, let's have sex today,
today we will work on the hands, tomorrow again on the legs.
You have to do it, I like this fantasy.
I think the whole body is, yes.
And then we may check, if you like the hands, and if you don't like them,
do it again, do it again.
The second one I have, I hear this story that Storks,
how do you call them, the stupid birds, are bringing babies.
And my dream was this one, that it's better if you want a nice child,
or a child, to do it with open windows.
Because Storks are observing you.
And if you make love in a nice way, you get a child, you know.
And now, this is not just a joke, because the big Freudian theory is not.
Then once we become mature, we know how it is.
No. All the time, to the end, human sexuality is accompanied by fantasies.
Freud's big question is not this vulgar psychoanalytic,
whatever you are doing, you are always thinking about F, you know.
It's on the contrary.
But what are you thinking when you are doing F?
And here, you, Austrians, published a wonderful book by my friend.
You know, they discovered Wittgenstein's Geheimer Tagebücher from World War I.
And he's brutally open.
He describes what he's thinking about when he was masturbating.
You know what he was?
Not gay sex, but discussing with colleagues philosophical questions and so on.
That's the spirit.
So what I want to say, but you see what I'm saying.
Freud makes it aware that human sexuality is a very complex phenomenon.
It doesn't emerge naturally, but through a series of traumatic cuts.
And in this sense, the process is self-contradictory, mostly unconscious and so on.
So it's not as some LGBT plus people like to simplify, you know.
Okay, I feel that I am that.
My point is, how do you know that you really feel this?
To Freud, it was clear that feelings cannot be relied on.
They often cheat.
Elementary stupid example.
You, you or me, okay, I will not blame you.
What if I am secretly gay, but I don't want to admit to myself,
so I enact this as homophobia, you know.
So, what I'm saying, and again, please, don't buy this cheap stuff.
People should be allowed to choose their sexual identity.
Yes, but it's not as simple as that, because it's not simply a conscious choice.
It's not that you sit there and think, okay, it would be nice to have a lady.
It can be funny with men, but other options.
Okay, this sounds the best one.
No, I will give you an example, which I always like, love.
Love is free, otherwise it's not true love.
I cannot tell to you, I will try not to accuse the time harassing.
I tell, you love is not.
I compare you, you and you and say, okay, you have nice legs, you have nice eyes.
You love, okay, then I make a list, you are the best, and I will choose you.
No, love has the structure of theology.
Where is Kierkegaard, my favorite guy, said.
To choose your religion, it's not that you compare different religions
and then follow, like, I compare Buddhism, which is not even a religion,
Muslim, Jews, I don't know whom.
And I said, my God, Christianity has the best arguments.
No, you get the arguments, only you understand the arguments only once you believe.
When you already believe.
Now you will say, this is religious obskurantism.
No, so Marx is saying the same.
When he says proletarian position is not, I look around,
his story, I see, oh, workers will win, so let's join them.
No, Marx's truth is a truth, which appears only from a subjectively engaged position.
So you see what's my point here.
That let's all the rights to LGBT plus, but really listen to them
and be aware of the complexity.
Like, I was now involved, some people attacked me, totally misunderstood me,
because into a polemic about so-called puberty blockers.
I don't know if you use them then, but in England they widely use them.
The idea is this one.
When you are 10, 11, if you are not sure independently of biological sex,
if you are not sure what sex you are, at that point you cannot decide,
but so that you will not be pressured under the conditions of heterosexual patriarchal domination.
They give you puberty blockers, which delay postpone for a couple of years your sexual maturation.
With a horrifying, for me, totally naive idea that in this couple of years
you will become mature enough to see what you want.
Of course, now they are discovering slowly that first these puberty blockers
do many problematic things, they disturb the whole process of your biological development,
not just sexual identity, but other things, it's very risky.
But also I think this idea is totally wrong, namely the idea that with maturity you are free to choose.
No, sexual identity is for me like love.
I appeal to your, if you were lucky enough to be in love with men, women, I'm not playing these games, anybody.
You never fall in love in the sense of, oh, now I decide to fall in love.
Beware of temporality here.
You all of a sudden discover that you are already in love.
Maybe you even hated, hated, had a problematic relation to that man or woman or whoever.
But all of a sudden you become aware, my God, really I am in love with him or her.
That's the structure of love.
And these are our deepest choices, which are precisely not experienced as simple free choices.
Love or sexual identity is not like going to a pâtisserie and oh my God, should I take cheesecake, strawberry cake or chocolate cake, you know.
No, you are chosen in some sense.
And the most radically free choices work like that, like something imposed on you, but freely imposed.
Here again, I think we need today psychoanalysis, we need psychoanalysis more than ever.
I'm talking too much so I will cut it short.
No, because then you, my orangutan will not like me if I talk too much.
As long as we can later on, you know, like work on the hands.
Oh yeah, okay.
He is my type, you know.
I discovered that behind all his friendliness, deep in him, he can be very evil also.
And I think this is the whole, the hope today, you know.
We were sitting here just like half an hour ago and I said, we have a lot of things in common.
And we will come to that.
You know what I mean.
And now you are gradually coming out of yourself and telling me that I'm telling you, but you're telling me.
Yeah, that's a very good thing.
No, because, you know, once they asked me what makes a fool, if we can talk about this in today's confused time, a full normal human being.
I said three things.
First, here my metaphysical, dedication to some serious cause, socialism, whatever, freedom, ready to work, really for it.
Point two, some kind of good pragmatism.
There are people who are principled but enjoy being principled losers.
Many left this today.
They wait for the big revolution.
But whenever something happens, Syriza, they say, no, no, that's not yet it, you know.
No, let the others do it.
Let the others do it.
Let the others do it, yeah.
And there's the whole history of the left here.
How the European left after 68 is just looking.
At some point it was Cuba, Vietnam, Venezuela.
Now we are, no, the revolution takes place elsewhere.
We want here to enjoy our academic or work job and see the revolution there, you know.
Like, what I wanted to say is that, let me go on.
Okay, I will just cover of these unholy alliances and catastrophe can save us.
Okay, another example of catastrophe can save us.
Something that worries me very, very much.
I cut off that line.
I know I said enough about LGBT plus and so on.
I wonder if you will agree with this.
A very intelligent critique from Bernie Sanders, my God.
Good old-fashioned American social democrat.
Where are my gloves?
Sorry?
Yeah, yeah.
It's complicated.
I know, I know, I know.
No, no, no.
I just said that he noticed something.
You know what's my problem with a certain time of woke suspicion?
That the good old left at least pretended to be unifying.
You addressed the people.
You say we may have differences.
But let's say even peace, justice, better health.
Let's get all together.
Well, did you notice how the woke logic is on the contrary an extremely divisive logic of suspicion?
The first thing they note is, yeah, but the expression that you use there may be misunderstood in that way.
It's very sad.
That's why I think woke logic of this universal suspicion, where are traces of racism and so on, blocks solidari.
But let's not get long quickly to the end.
Another unholy alliance, what I already hinted at, I think Zionist anti-Semitism.
It's not a joke.
We have now at a very delicate level a strange alliance between the truly crazy Zionists,
those who now want to throw Arabs out of the West Bank.
You noticed what happened, I cried in Israel now.
For one terrorist act, they want a minister of finance of them proposed this to erase the entire city of 7,500 people and so on.
They speak openly about annexing and so on.
Okay, there are more problems here, but what I want to say is that, did you notice how this radical,
zionist-Jews, who want strong Israel, are getting gradually into an unholy alliance with even anti-Semitic western conservatives, for example.
If there was somebody who was not really philosemitic, it was Donald Trump.
He was supported by a series of extreme right openly anti-Semitic organizations, but he supported Israel.
Now you will say, what's my point?
Now comes a bad surprise.
Not now looking to my books, I have a quote.
You know who is at the origin of this?
Reinhard Heidrich.
In 36 oder 7, he wrote a letter where he said, Jews are an ingenious, active people.
We would like to collaborate great with them, we just don't want them here.
We should help them to move to Palestine and so on.
And that's why, when Bibi Netanyahu some six, seven years ago called French Jews, come to Israel,
the right wing, really anti-Semitic circles celebrated it.
Yeah, yeah, you see, go there, go, just out of France, you know.
What makes me here so sad is, again, this weird alliance.
Then people tell me, but Jews suffered so much during the Holocaust.
I told them, no, this is an obscenity, what you are saying.
Because Arabs are saying the same thing, like some stupid pro-Palestinian,
not because he's pro-Palestinian, in Yubliana, in front of my house, did a graffiti.
If I were to live in Gaza, I would also deny Holocaust.
Like when you suffer, you know, this is totally wrong.
You know what is for me, I hope we'll agree, the only serious ethical position.
The struggle against anti-Semitism, unconditionally.
And the struggle for Palestinians, not the terrorists on the West Bank,
should be parts of the same struggle, point.
That's it.
That those who manipulate the memory of Holocaust to justify what Israel is today doing on the West Bank,
those are the true manipulators with Holocaust.
Because they use a mega-traumatical event to justify petty, colonizing land politics now.
You know who? I was asked at year 2000 an extremely stupid question. Naive.
Elaborate.
No, no, I have not elaborate too much, because then we can take a break, go to sleep and then come again.
Who is for you a true ethical, oh my God.
A true ethical hero of 20th century, I said Marek Edelman.
This was, remember the name, a Polish Jew, absolute hero.
He was Bundist there in Poland before World War II, fighting for workers rights, leftist.
He was among the coordinators of the Warsaw Ghetto Rebellion.
He somehow survived it.
He then organized that Warsaw uprising.
After the war, he remained there in Poland, although communists wanted to throw him out, with a beautiful argumentation.
He said, I see Auschwitz, stones there, and I think, I don't have anything to say that out of respect for the victims,
somebody has to be here to look at those stones.
And then shock.
In 67, 8, one of the last thing he did, he wrote a message to my Palestinian brothers.
He told them, as a Jew who went through all of it, I advise you, resist.
Not with terror, but resist, you have the right.
This is true ethics.
So, that we don't go on, just to conclude, I find the same problem with ecology.
You know, that's my philosophical trading.
You know how often I am totally again pro ecology.
But again, it's complex.
Eine Idee, die ich gewinnt, ist diesejenigekusche, die AWS noch Bil
Mögen wir die Umwelt so, dass wir in es leben können.
Das bedeutet, dass wir auf das fokussieren.
Es ist eine arrogantere Vision,
dass die Natur in sich ist irgendwie mehr harmonisch,
aber wir, Egotist, verabschieden die Menschen,
durch das Ausdruck.
Die erste Statement der true Eko-Equologisierung ist,
sorry, für dieses Volker-Statement, das hast du gehört,
ist, wenn die Natur unsere Mutter ist,
dass es eine dörfte Bitte ist, diese Mutter.
Eine Probe. Was ist unsere Hauptsache von Energie heute?
Öl, Kohle.
Kannst du dir sogar vorstellen,
was die Eko-Equologischen Katastrophen auf der Erde hatten,
bevor die Menschen entstanden waren,
dass wir alle diese Sorge von Energie haben?
Nein, die Natur ist schon in sich,
es ist nicht irgendwie ein harmonisches Zeichen, es ist die Erde.
Es ist sich selbst zerstört.
Es ist nicht so, dass wir Menschen das aufgerissen.
Dann sind es so...
Eko-Equologen sind für mich ambiguous.
Ich bin wiederum absolut für sie, für alle measures und so.
Radical measures,
aber nicht in eine simple Ideologie zu fallen.
Was meinst du von diesem?
Oft, meine Freundin Alen Badiu,
der Freundin, hat das sehr gut entwickelt.
Heute haben wir ein Problem von der so-called Death of God.
Es gibt keine Autorität, die uns für uns unenttäuschbar ist,
wenn diese Autorität so ist, die wir nennen.
Wir relativisieren alles.
Und ich denke, dass die Eko-Equologen oft mit dieser Unkonditionale
in dem Sinne, dass wir die Natur haben, die uns ein Limit betrifft.
Nein, ich bin nicht bei diesem.
Ich denke, dass die Komplexität wiederum ist.
Was heute ein realer Problem ist,
ist, dass es nicht nur Natur ist, die verheiratet ist,
aber auch wir Menschen als Menschen.
Ich habe es in einem Buch geschrieben.
Vielleicht wissen Sie es, Hegel in einem wunderschönen Gehirn.
Ich habe versucht, das zu beurteilen.
Ich bin nicht so viel zufrieden von all diesen falschen Stufen,
obwohl wunderschöne Dinge passieren.
Jetzt komme ich zum Schluss.
Du weißt, dass, zum Beispiel,
siehst du, wie du diese face-swappen, hart-korpsen Poren hast?
Es ist sehr einfach.
Du nimmst einen hart-korpsen Poren,
und dann musst du nur ein paar Fotografen von einer Frau brauchen.
Dann putst du es in den Poren.
Dann hat der Computer das ganze Job.
Dann hast du das ganze Poren, das alles.
Du kannst mit jedem Poren einen hart-korpsen Poren machen,
mit dem du genug Fotos hast.
Ich habe mich eröffnet.
Ich habe es für die Tastungsmessung geöffnet.
Ich habe einen mit dem deutschen Poren-German,
eine Alena Baerbock gesehen.
Das ist so verrückt.
Es ist eine face-swapp.
Dann kannst du das mit...
Wir haben jetzt so perfekte Voizimitations.
Nein, dass du es komplett machen kannst.
So, vielleicht, zum Schluss,
wir kommen nahezu zu etwas, das ich fast findet, attraktiv.
Ich werde mit einem alten Schatz mit ein paar von dir, vielleicht nicht.
Der Guardian-German hat mir vor zehn Jahren gefragt,
ist Romanz heute noch alive?
Mein Antwort war schwierig, aber vielleicht.
Was wäre heute ein wirklich schönes Romantisches Sex-Geräusch?
Man hat ihn, die es so nennt, Völger.
Staminatraining-Unit.
In Deutschland nennt man es Wagenaror.
Eine Plastik, das ist wundervoll.
Man kann die Densität regulieren, wie man sie schrägst,
und dann die Penis.
Natürlich haben wir diese Dilde, die Plastik-Penis.
Die beiden arbeiten auf Elektrizität.
So, sagen wir, ich bin eine Frau, ich bin ein Mensch,
und wir sind keine Äpfel, und wir wollen Sex.
Würden Sie es nicht so tun?
Wenn du eine Frau mit deinem Dildo kommst,
dann kommst du mit meinem Wagenaror.
Wir sitzen runter, plaggen sie beide in.
Wir haben ein Dildo in einem Wagenaror.
Die Maschinen sind gebraucht.
Sie machen es für uns.
Wir sprechen über Philosophie, wie Wittgenstein.
Wir kennen beide die Wagenaroren, eigentlich.
Ja, wir können.
Ich möchte Sex mit dir haben, wenn du eine Frau bist.
Ich will die Maschinen, aber ich will die Äpfel.
Wollt ihr das heute ein wundervoller Ding machen?
Wir machen das Gleiche.
Wir nehmen einen richtig hohen Koppel in einem schweren Pferd,
und verabschieden die Fähigkeiten.
Und dann aufs Schreiben,
und haben einen schönen Trink, und reden, und so weiter.
Vielleicht ist das die Zukunft unserer Sexualität.
Vielleicht ist es.
Danke sehr, dass ich fertig bin.
Stopp!
Du siehst das.
Es muss discipline sein.
Bevor ich dir das Mikrofon hänge,
ich möchte ein bisschen nachfragen,
mit dem...
Das ist keine Ahnung, ob du mich wie ein Ablehst oder eine Frau bist.
Ich bin nicht ein Able, ich bin ein Peek.
Das Ding ist, du hast ein interessantes Wort gesagt,
weil wir so viel mit Technologien haben.
Und in einer Verabschiedung der popularen Quote von Nietzsche,
die lange du in den Abis klärst,
die Abis startet zu klären zu dir,
ist es nicht so, dass wir lange auf das Internet schauen,
dass das Internet zu uns sieht?
So, du denkst, dass wir schon beyond that point,
wo wir starten zu sprechen, um Katastrophen zu sprechen.
Dass wir uns die Maschine, die Web, alles so educieren,
oder du denkst, dass wir die Maschine schon passen,
wo wir uns educieren.
Und es ist so, dass es ein ganz neues Feld von Katastrophen
geht, das zu passieren.
Das ist eine sehr gute Frage,
für eine simple Dogmatik-Region,
weil es sehr Lacanian klingt.
Jacques Lacan hat diese Idee im Detail entwickelt,
die ist, glaube ich, sehr profund,
dass in dem Fall, um wirklich zu schauen,
in irgendeinem Sinne, das Ding hat zu schauen,
dich zurückzunehmen.
Und du hast das als den sogenannten blinden Spot im Film erlebt.
Der Punkt, als es dich zurückzunehmen.
Und ich denke, es ist eine spekulativen Theorie,
aber es kann auch sein, dass jedes Sex-Akt
fast auf einem tiefen, unkonservten Level
diese Idee des Voyages hat.
Wenn ich Sex genieße, genieße ich es nicht direkt.
Ich imagine, dass man von jemandem geobsert ist,
usw. usw.
Und es ist eine sehr gute Frage von dir.
Was passiert mit dieser Technologie,
in der es nicht mehr eine Fantasie ist?
Aber du bist wirklich geobsert,
alles ist bemerkt, usw.
Und meine kurze Antwort,
weil ich zu lange gesprochen habe,
ist, dass vielleicht was, was wir verlieren,
genau diese tiefen Metaphysikale schauen,
wie der andere die Geist zurückzunehmen.
Es ist nicht mehr dieses mysteriöse Sex,
wir sehen einfach, wo die Maschine wirklich auf uns schaut.
Das wäre meine kurze Antwort.
Meine zweite Antwort wäre,
dass du rememberst, dass du,
ein italienischer Typ etwas gemacht hast,
und ich mag es nicht, sorry,
es war ein endloses, artificiell generiertes Debatt
zwischen mir und Werner Herzog.
Du kannst es endlöschen.
Ich hatte einen Verkauf mit dir.
Du hast den letzten Stück der Schokolade, ich glaube.
Ja, und ich habe ihm gesagt,
my God, listen,
couldn't you, like, I'm too fluent there,
there are none of my dirty tics,
none of my vulgarities and so on.
Couldn't you include, so,
the real problem with computers imitating us
or controlling us is,
the greatest thing about our human speech,
you know who knew this, didn't Kleist,
Heinrich von Kleist, wrote a wonderful,
a couple of pages short essay on Iber-Einige,
I don't know, von Benjamin,
where his idea is that all great inventions
in language ideas happened so that you misspoke.
You say something wrongly,
and then you try to save the situation
and try to include that.
Can computers do this?
I'm not so sure.
No, we're not either, but it's a good thing,
because as we talk about this failure
and these things that happen,
and then we try to cope with that,
brings us back to the topic of tonight,
and your title of your lecture,
like Catastrophe with Savers,
because what Kleist says in languages,
a little catastrophe happens
and something good comes out of it.
Isn't it that?
Even today, sorry, just to finish.
No, no, it's interesting.
That's why many Jewish friends are telling me,
you know this catastrophe now,
colonizing the West Bank,
direct racism, and so on.
It's not just hypocrisy,
when white liberal Jews are protesting it,
but this was such a shock
for the majority of half-Eight-Eys.
What I like about Jews is that, you know,
they have the greatest percentage of Eight-Eys in the world.
The Jews.
And it's this wonderful paradox,
as a Jew once told me,
we don't believe in God,
but nonetheless, we believe that God gave us the land.
We don't believe in God,
but we know that God believes in us.
Yes, yes.
Now you said something so profound,
that I'm just said that we cannot go on indefinitely,
because I think Jacques Lacan says this.
The true methodical question
is not do we believe in God.
Some people do, some not, who cares.
The problem is, does God,
God is our fantasy formation,
does God believe in himself?
And the answer of all truly profound theology is no.
No.
The problem is there.
The problem is that we made him up.
Yeah, but what does he...
Which is why I have another theory,
I wonder if you like it.
The most hit me, the most materialist film that I saw,
I've written about it, is downloaded, you get it.
Rapture, 25, 30 years old film with,
when she was younger, Mimi Rogers.
It's an incredible story,
I will condense it as much as possible.
An ordinary, short short short, an ordinary girl,
okay, he's promiscuous, then she falls in love,
her husband dies, he has a children,
and she has an obsession
that God will in Rapture call her up.
So, she goes to a desert near Los Angeles,
to a desert to wait for God.
God doesn't do, does nothing.
So, she kills her daughter, nothing.
Then she is arrested for this, now comes the miracle.
She goes, till this point, and is arrested.
Till that, this point, the movie is realistic.
Could have happened, a disappointed, crazy believer.
Then, the miracle happens.
It's the end of the world, all of a sudden,
the walls disintegrate of the prison,
she takes a car, she goes to somewhere,
to the edge of the world, where she sees up there, Paradise.
And the ending, it's incredible.
There, from the other side of Paradise,
her dead husband and daughter approach her,
and ask her, mommy, come to us,
you just have to say, I love you God.
And she said, no, I will not.
After God did, what God did to me,
with all these miracles, no.
And then, her daughter said, but mommy, you know what this means.
You know how long you will stay there.
And she says, I know, forever.
This is the end.
That's the true undermining of religion from within.
Much better than this, God doesn't exist.
Because when people say God doesn't exist,
they usually mean, but nonetheless, it's a noble idea, you know.
Like, I talk too much, please.
No, two things.
First, this reminds me a little bit,
in a very abstract way of the story of Lilium, from Mourna,
you know, the play, the play of Lilium.
Are you familiar with that?
No, I'm not.
We'll talk about it later, when we work on the hands.
And the good thing about the film or the movie
is that you can make it like a really hard cut.
So we make a hard cut now,
because I promise the people that they can ask you questions.
And we've got another 15 minutes running.
Okay?
And I will try to be stupid enough to believe me.
I will try to be...
The good thing is you are straight to the point,
you're not very elaborate, you have straight answers,
very short, it's a very good thing.
But you are right in something.
I know, I know.
The great art in books, in films, is the proper cut at the end.
Did you see the new Spielberg?
And I don't like it very much, Fableman.
Yes.
The ending with John Ford is one of the best endings of all the time.
At now, the fuck get out of my office.
Yes.
Bitte.
You know what song I will think about you.
No.
You are Sebastian.
Yes, yes.
Somebody call me Sebastian.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
You know, do you know the old De Deer from early fifties?
Pro Stalin song, Stalin Freund Genosse.
Very good.
Thank you, Sebastian Freund Genosse.
Okay.
And the song that I will sing for you from the De Deer
is Sag mir wo du stehst.
I know, but this was a pop song.
Yes, it was.
Questions.
Bitte.
I already criticized him.
I told him as a true Stalinist,
did you organize the questions?
Yes, of course.
They are all censored.
Come on.
Of course.
The nomen Katura is watching.
Bitte.
Sie können, wenn Sie wollen, auch auf Deutsch die Frage spielen.
Ja, ich hoffe, das ist okay, sehr geehrter Herr Schischek.
Ich hätte zwei kurze Fragen, und zwar zuerst.
Sie haben das ja näher ausgeführt,
diese unheilige Allianz zwischen Wagenknecht,
den Linken und der AfD, etc.
Aber wenn man sich die andere Seite anschaut,
also ich würde jetzt mal sagen, viele Linksliberale,
die sagen, es braucht Waffenlieferungen ohne Ende,
die schon diskutieren über eine Flugverbotszone, etc.
Ich stecke da nicht auch eine gewisse Ideologie dahinter,
dass man den Krieg und den Toten das Leid als etwas Virtuelles betrachtet.
Man diskutiert darüber und denkt nicht über die Konsequenzen
und auch nicht darüber, dass Russen genauso sterben wie Ukrainer.
Und ob da, meiner Meinung nach,
ein bisschen diese Struktur der fetischistischen Verleugnung dahinter steckt.
Ich weiß, dass da ein Krieg herrscht,
aber ich tue es so, als ob es diesen ganzen Toten so nicht geben würde.
Und was Sie dazu sagen?
Und meine zweite Frage wäre,
wo sehen Sie die Rolle der Philosophie in den ganzen Krisen?
Irgendwie habe ich das Gefühl, jetzt in der Pandemie hat man sehr viel,
da gab es nicht viel Platz für Philosophie.
Er wurde mit virologischen Grundbegriffen argumentiert
und jetzt im Krieg auch sehr viel mit militärischen Begriffen.
Jetzt ist er, wie Sie erwähnt haben, Jürgen Habermas,
ist auch oft angegriffen worden, für das, was er geschrieben hat,
Alexander Kluge auch.
Wo ist da die Rolle der Philosophie im Sinne einer Intervention?
Danke.
Vielen Dank. Danke.
Ich hoffe, dass ich die Frage richtig verstanden hat.
Die erste Frage.
Yes, I totally agree again.
As I already said, I can give you a whole list of crazy things
that Ukrainians were and are doing.
But nonetheless, I will tell you one thing.
First, I don't buy this argument
that it's really a proxy war between United States and Russia
and that it's just to support our military industry.
Tell this to an Ukrainian and he will explode.
And justly, he will say, do you think that we are so stupid
that we said to ourselves we could have lived in peace?
But wait a minute, why don't we sacrifice ourselves
to support the western military industry?
For them it's not a proxy war, they fight for their survival.
Russia is openly saying,
Ukrainian nation doesn't exist and so on and so on.
I know I didn't really, but what I like very much
is this how you applied to this also,
that logic didn't understand you correctly,
is vice-versaulter.
Because this, I think, is something absolutely crucial
that's happening today.
This formula, as we well know,
is the formula of, again, feticist disavable.
I know very well, but I don't really believe it.
I act as if and so on.
But today, I plagiarize here, my good friend,
you should invite her here, I envy and hate her.
This means love, because she is very bright.
I don't want to talk about it, maybe more bright than me.
Alenka Zupancic, my streaming colleague,
and she developed that today, it's not just that,
you know something, but at the same time,
you don't take it seriously, ignore it.
No, it's that the fetish becomes your knowledge itself.
I will give you an example.
How I claim more and more,
we live in an absolutely cynical era,
where the official ideology situation
can only reproduce itself by, in some sense, limited,
saying the truth about itself and doing nothing.
You know, I will give you, to make it clear,
what I mean, two examples that I like.
First, I hate this, Castle Biennale, Benedict Biennale,
because I look at the program, they always say,
even we are caught in capitalist game,
it's all colonial exploitation.
Yeah, they say this, but they function perfectly.
They are playing this capitalist game.
And why can't they play it?
Because they proclaim it, you know.
This is a new version of this old Peter Slaughter Dykes,
his early work, maybe still the best,
critique the Chinese and Fernund,
where he defines it as the vision turning around Marx.
Yeah, reflection used for Sanction, yeah.
We know very well what we are doing,
but we are nonetheless doing it.
The second example is, I really hate it.
You remember, it's now two years ago already in Glasgow, I think,
that big meeting of Prince Charles was there,
everybody for fight against global war.
Global war in conference.
Yeah, conference.
And they were saying all the right things,
but it works like, okay, now we said it,
now we can go on as usual.
So this mechanism, I'm sorry, I shouldn't talk too much,
but this is absolutely a crucial mechanism
which works in different ways.
What you said about Chris' pandemic philosophy,
I must say that, maybe I speak now in an egotist way
for saving my own profession,
but in some sense we live in a time
when philosophy is needed more than ever.
Why?
Because in the confusion in which we are today,
like, and confusion which concerns even everyday people,
you know, like Havremas, I don't agree with his solution,
but he raised the right question,
where he said, do we have the right to mix with our brains?
Yes, because then we may manipulate our psychic properties
and so on and so on.
But this is a problem for all of us.
I read somewhere, it's a horrible vision,
so horrible that I almost like it,
that now a guy with some Arab name
is opening a big clinic in Berlin,
where you will have a perfect reproduction of not vagina,
but how do you call this inside?
Uterus.
Transparent.
And you want to have with your wife, partner, a child.
You just give experiment with the feminine counterpart
and you do nothing.
Then you just fill out the form, they give you 200 choices.
How to manipulate before, even starting the process,
experiment so on, like choice of color,
color of the eye, like brown or the blue.
Ja, ja.
All that stuff, intelligence and hate and so on.
Hate, I mean, how not hate?
Ja, hate.
Hight.
Sorry.
Hot hall.
Yes.
And then they produce the child and their hope is that...
So, you know, all these things
and basically already the abortion debate
confronts us with some basic philosophical problems,
like what are we as humans, when do we exist as humans.
We live in a time of ethical confusion,
where even everyday decisions
demand from us a kind of spontaneous,
basically philosophical decision.
You know, like the use again.
Habermas was right, but I don't think the solution is right.
When he said that when we will be able to do,
that's the big task now,
to somehow implant vision, knowledge in our mind,
either through sleep, hypnosis or other way without doing ourselves.
What does this mean for our whole concept of education?
Let's say you are much more honest and bright than me.
But I get the proper pills, manipulations
and I can be more efficient than you.
What happens with ours?
Isn't it a wonderful vision that Stanislav Lamm already wrote up
in the photo-rological Congress?
That we take pills and then we virtualize our whole existence.
Isn't that happening right now already?
Like we translate ourselves much more in images than in writing.
Like all the social media, much more like an image media
than a written media.
I agree, that's why, but we don't have time for this.
That's why I much prefer Lamm's novel than Stalker the film.
Yeah, me too.
Novel is... Sorry, Solaris already.
Solaris, Solaris, not Stalker.
In the film, Tarkowski does the usual half-religious obsturantism.
The object is just a mirror of the deepest desires of our soul.
In Lamm's novel became a traumatic, external object
which simply remains non-transparent.
We know they are doing something with us,
but we never learn at the end what.
So, okay, let's not lose time.
What I am just saying is that precisely every great philosophy
always happens in the time of a crisis.
Huge crisis.
Sorry?
Huge crisis, huge crisis.
Plato, Aristotle, it's the end of Polish.
It's already the decadence of Polish.
And Hegel was quite aware.
The new boost of philosophy from Kant to Hegel and later
comes with the problems of Aufklärung and French Revolution.
So, when with terror and so on, things went wrong, then...
So, we need the crisis.
Sorry?
We need the crisis.
To think properly, absolutely.
I don't believe that to be a philosopher, you need peaceful time.
No, true philosophy is for the times of emergency.
But Kant, peaceful times, if it's so peaceful and you have no challenge at all,
can be a great burden by itself as well.
Absolutely.
So, maybe...
I'm afraid of this, absolutely.
I mean, I cannot even...
I'm an absolute workaholic, even tonight,
because I was not able to do my work.
I go back to Ljubljana and...
And you finish it.
Two hours minimum.
It's very important to have a regime.
Absolutely.
Keeps you going.
Because you need a task in life.
I will end with a few obscenities, but take it friendly.
It's not a bad joke.
When a journalist asked me what's your favorite motto,
I said, Arbeit macht frei.
And then, of course, I said, I don't mean it in that way.
But the Nazis brutally misused it.
That work certainly didn't make you free.
But the horror of the Nazis is that a motto,
which is for me at least in itself a good one, free one,
they misused it in the most horrible, imaginable way.
But it's always like that.
Sovereignty of interpretation means you control
how you propagandize for things.
So, but that's why I believe in failure, in mistakes, in mis-speaking.
That's the only way, even in love.
Don't you agree that when you declare love,
this is for me the most traumatic moment always,
when you declare love to somebody,
if you don't do it with some oscillation, stumbling,
there is something wrong.
It means you are perfectly trained to do it.
Did you see a stupid movie, otherwise I hated it,
for weddings and the funeral.
But there is a nice detail that when Hugh Grant declares love
to Andy McDowell, he gets in his typical way,
stumbles, repeats himself, that's how you declare love.
So, the thing is, we reached the end, unfortunately.
I want to ask you one last question.
Will I kill myself?
No, with the challenge attached to it,
that you have to answer it really shortly.
And we see, and if you can suffice,
you were talking about the role of philosophy nowadays times,
and we are very challenging times.
So, do you generally, like, it's more like a yes or no question,
do you generally think that the biggest challenge is
that we live in times where we have a lot of reflexes,
to counter stuff that is coming to us.
And especially in times when there is a high pressure of reflex,
that we should take our time to reflect instead of just reflex.
Absolutley.
This is why, to annoy many of my leftist friends,
maybe you know it, this is my standard answer,
like is Marxist-Physis XI.
Philosophers have only interpreted the world, we have to change it.
I claim that it's a correct phrase for today,
just we should turn it around.
In the 20th century, we wanted to change the world too fast,
now we need to interpret it more.
Exactly.
Never were we so epistemologically, with our knowledge, disorientated.
I ask you a simple question, what is China today?
It's still communism, it's authoritarian capitalism.
The basic orientation is missing.
We have to finish now.
Ladies and gentlemen, meine sehr verehrten Damen und Herren,
danke, dass Sie sich so aufmerksam zugehört haben.
Ich würde sagen, Genossen und Genossinnen.
Fertig, danke.
Danke.
Das war ein Pleasure.
Stop! Stop!
Weil mit mir, du hast immer den Preis gespielt.
Seit du das Applaus hast,
werde ich dir eine wundervolle, dörrige Joke sagen.
Das ist...
Ja, ja.
Wir müssen auf die Hände arbeiten.
Du musst auf die Hände arbeiten.
Nein, nein, aber eine dörrige Joke,
die philosophisch korrekt ist.
Eine starke Frau schenkt ihr Mann in der Sonne,
und bringt mir ein paar Zigaretten aus der Trafik auf die Strecke.
Der Mann geht raus, die Trafik ist zu nahe.
Er geht zu einer Bar, um die Zigaretten zu kaufen.
Da beginnt ein schönes Wetter, sie flirren.
Sie enden in ihrer Fläche,
schlug wie ein verrückter Tiltrin im Morgen.
Dann sagt er, oh mein Gott, ich muss nach Hause.
Was will ich zu meiner Frau sagen?
Und er findet eine Lösung.
Er sagt zu der Frau,
ob du eine dieser, wenn du einen Puder machen willst,
okay, eine Bohlinge für Bohlinge.
Okay, er setzt das an und geht nach Hause.
Be careful for the dialectic now.
Die Frau fragt ihm, wo war du?
Sucht eine lange Zeit.
Und er sagt, ich bin raus, die Trafik war zu nahe.
Ich bin zu einer Bar, ich habe mit einer Frau geflirtet,
wir haben ein verrückter Tiltrin.
Und du weißt, was ist der Effekt?
Die Frau sagt, warum bist du so miserably lieb mit mir?
Ich sehe die Puder,
du warst mit deinen Freunden Bohlinge.
Das ist die politische Art,
um die Wahrheit zu erzählen,
in eine Weise, die die Enemene zu confusieren.
Das ist für mich.
Professor, Dr. Slavo Shisha.
Danke.
Untertitel im Auftrag des ZDF, 2017