Hello and thank you for watching this AutoHotKey tutorial for beginners. In this
video we're going to cover a lot of different topics. We're going to start
off discussing which versions of AutoHotKey to use, then we're going to
cover which editor to use. There's a lot of different editors out there and I've
tried a lot of them. The one I recommend is by far the easiest to start with.
Then we're going to jump into doing some some little pre-work. We're going to use
hotkeys which is actually a tool that you can use in AutoHotKey to launch
programs and stuff, but we're going to first use them to work smarter, not
harder. We're going to learn how to use them to edit our code and make it faster
as we develop code. Then I'm going to show you how to launch programs and
scripts and load a website with them. Then next we're going to jump into using
hot strings. The hot string as you can think of is like a text expansion type
thing. So you type a couple letters and bam there goes a lot of text whatever
you want to put in there. After that I show you a script where there's about
4,000 words in a spell check. What's great about AutoHotKey is any Windows
program you're in you can have this script running and it will spell check
across all your programs. It's another just a great example of hot strings. Then
we switch back to using a few more hotkeys where we show you how to remap
codes. Let's say you're using Outlook and you don't like a hotkey to launch a new
email. I'll teach you how you can hit a different key combination and it will
send the key combination that Outlook knows. It's a great way if you don't
like the programs you're using to remap the keys. Then we work on how to send a
mouse click to given coordinates. Of course first you have to understand you
know identify where those coordinates are and then we send the mouse clicks
there. Lastly we wrap up on the programming side of being able to
compile a script and this is a really great thing about AutoHotKey. It's
super super easy to compile a script and that way you can use it on a
different computer where it doesn't have AutoHotKey installed or you can give it
to a friend and they can write it on their Windows computer. At the very end of
this script video I have a lot of resources where where to go when you
get in trouble. A lot of great sources where you have live support where people
are just willing to help you. The AutoHotKey community and forum the people
are just great and very helpful. My site I have a lot of tutorials on them but
this is places where you can go directly and get one-to-one help. In this
video you'll notice I mentioned a lot of stuff. There's a lot of pop-ups with the
actual links you know and hyperlinks of where you can go. Just make sure you
check in the description down below because I'm going to put in the time
codes of exactly in the video when it was and the URL there is too. So you don't
have to try to type the URLs right so make sure you wait for that and I
really appreciate you watching this video. Please like it if you think it
really helped you. I spent quite a bit of time on this video to make sure that it
really helps new people so I hope you like this tutorial for beginners. Cheers.
In case is the first video you've seen of me my name is Joe Glynes and I'm from
the Automator and I teach people how to automate their PCs. I love it's my
passion to help people work smarter not harder. Come to my site check it out. I
have over 600 videos on YouTube. I have three Udemy courses teaching AutoHotKey
so all these are great resources. There's also some great AutoHotKey books out
there but check us out. Also if at some point you want to get some work done for
you now I have people working for me that will automate things. So drop me a
note my email will be in this description and please like the video if you
think it was helpful and looking forward to get going here. Cheers.
Alright so the first thing we have to do is to download and install AutoHotKey.
So let's go ahead and navigate to AutoHotKey.com in any browser. When you
get there you're going to see this button that says download. Go ahead and
click it. It's going to ask you which of these three options do you want. Always
download the current version. The other two I don't want to get into it. It's a
bit advanced to why. There's a lot of logic later that you might choose on but
for now we're going to download the current version. Go ahead and save it. I
already have it here on my desktop. It's a small file here. I'm going to say I'm just
going to replace it and now once it's here I'm going to say open when done and
it's going to come up with the setup files that you want to install. Now Windows
now is trying to think that maybe this is a bad thing. Go ahead and click run
anyway. It's going to come up with this window. Now the default isn't this
express installation. For reasons I don't want to get into it's it's it's not what
I recommend right and most people say do the custom installation instead of doing
the Unicode 64 bit to the Unicode 32 bit and it just it works with more scripts
you find online so it's just safer 64 a bit isn't necessarily better it's just
different and you can install wherever you like. I'm just go ahead and hit next. I
take the defaults on this screen as well. I take all the defaults don't change
anything and basically you're done. Now that we have a hotkey installed let's
work on getting an editor or an IDE and IDE is short for integrated development
environment and I highly highly recommend you install something. I'm going to
recommend site for Auto hotkey it's written specifically for using with
Auto hotkey. Technically you could use either notepad or wordpad or almost
anything that can edit a text file because the Auto hotkey code is written
in plain text and that just means when you open it you'll see the actual
characters and words there and you can recognize them and you could save it
however there's a lot of functionality that using text pad wouldn't allow you
to do like relaunch the script or assist you in typing the code you might
want or hit F1 highlight a word hit F1 and bring up the support Auto hotkey
support all of these things site will do for you automatically. Let's go ahead
let me share my screen here and on the main page that we're working from I have
a download for Auto hotkey site for Auto hotkey here so let's go I'm going to
click this right now and we'll get it started here it's not a big program this
is from my site I just make it for convenience because it might disappear
in the form at some point that's going to download it we'll run it here in a
second but what I wanted to point out is if you come up here there's this whole
page dedicated to videos where I've taught people how to do it looks like I
have at least 18 videos there I'm doing some advanced stuff now I don't recommend
you start off here right because the great thing about site and you'll realize
this when we start programming it is it's super easy it has a nice tool bar it
has a lot of functionality it doesn't take a lot of learning there's not a
steep learning curve and yet it's very simple easy to use so let's go ahead and
install it I'm gonna I'm gonna hit Ctrl G and Chrome that'll well let's see I can
do it right here I don't have to do that I'm gonna say open right so I don't
have to navigate to it now it's gonna come up and say do you want the quick
setup install I'm gonna hit install just to see what it's doing my default
location is gonna be different than yours don't worry about that install
wherever you want it you should it'll find auto hotkeys main install file and
that's where mine is and then you're gonna click install but it's gonna come up
and just say hey do you want to run these updates there's two updates it'll
download and just say yes and that's it and then sites installed you have this
nice toolbar up here it's a clean input interface so when you have the vertical
split on this vertical split leave it off I would recommend it I think it
makes more sense to have it down here mine just happened to be closed up so
this is where you'll see output and this is where you'll see a lot of debug
information mainly the big one is like hey the scripted launch and there's a
problem like if we put something here and try to launch it it wants to save it
first well fine save hotkeys script great now if I try to launch it it's gonna
tell me hey this file has a problem specifically hey what in the world is
our EFFD it tells you where it is right often they'll tell you the line that the
problem's on but this is this little stuff that it really helps you understand
what in the world's going on with your your script so I highly recommend you
install there's also notepad plus plus HK studio which is the editor I use now
but it's more advanced and this is by far the easiest to install easiest to pick
up and use it's really a great advanced program for editing any kind of text
there's a lot of search and replace stuff you can do in it so now let's go
ahead and get into coding all right now that we have site and auto hotkey
installed let's go ahead and start working on our first script so we're
gonna jump in here and I just have a folder this folder it's in my temp
directory and it's just keeping all the files together for me so go in somewhere
right-click and say new and I'm gonna say new auto hotkey script now this is
gonna generate a little bit of code in this file see it's one kilobyte it's not
zero and we're gonna call this thing test I'm gonna hit right inner key to save
it save the renaming and now I'm gonna right-click again and say edit and
because site was installed it's the default editor it is gonna open this
script in site for us and so we can see several things here this is really
helpful is that notice this color coding if we open this file notepad this would
just all be black text and it's it's this is where having site installed is
really helpful to allow you to easily see this stuff things that begin with the
pound sign they're called directives and we don't need to get into all the
advanced stuff about that but I'm trying to point out they're a little
different than other things just no end it's it's we don't need to go into the
explanation of it you could comment it out you don't necessarily need it it's
recommended but you don't have to have it in there control Q in site will toggle
so I could I could highlight a bunch of these and it would toggle them but it
will comment them out so that's control Q we'll leave it enabled it doesn't matter
this sent now these two are commands and send mode input this is the most
reliable and it's fast so we're gonna leave that enabled we'll use send a
little bit later a send command and the set working directory that basically
says hey when I'm accessing stuff use the the directory that I'm in is the
default directory so it's a good thing to have I definitely recommend having it
notice this auto assist this is why I love site also in in notepad you wouldn't
have any of this and it's really much more complicated so I'm gonna hit it
enter to accept that comma and we're gonna say force what this does it says
hey only launch one instance of this script so if the script was already
running it would basically relaunch it for you if it wasn't running a launch
it if you'd launch it again it will say hey there's already one running don't run
two instance of this only run one I don't understand why this isn't the
default in every script it should be it's used all the time right so I use
this is 99.9% of my scripts it should be in every script as the default you
actually can go in a site you could change that or you know somewhere and
you can change that this is the default value to have in there I highly
encourage you to add it to yours and so this gets us going and now I'm gonna
stop here and then we're gonna switch to actually working with hotkeys because
we have a couple other things I want to put in this but I want to keep these
compartmentalized while we're talking about directives and settings this is
stuff that's for your script or other things you could put in here and over
time you might learn you might want to have the next thing we're gonna get into
is actually creating hotkeys to do some stuff that really helps speed up your
coding. All right so let's jump into making our first script now before we
actually do some fun coding stuff I'm gonna demonstrate a couple things to
add to your main script the one that you're working in to make it easier to
develop code so let's go ahead and start sharing here and we're gonna jump in now
to start off let me show you there's this script right now is not running I
can tell that one easy way is looking in here there's no green little green H's
in here so we're gonna say let's say message box hello world now I'm gonna
save this and when I hit this blue run it's going to or I could hit a five it's
going to launch this script so notice two things here one here's the hello
world message box this is the joseph's which script we're in and see this green
H down here right this is telling us this script is running the second I hit
okay here I also want you to notice something with this green H I hit okay
and suddenly it's gone right why is that well there was nothing else in this
script to keep it running keep it active and there are a couple things that
you could do to do that if you had a hot key or a hot string in it it would
automatically stay running you could add a single persistent a directive called
persistent and this would keep it running so if I save this we launch it the
message box comes up here's our green H when I said okay it stays running now it
wouldn't do anything because there's nothing else in this so we don't we
won't leave this in here but so we're gonna add that in our little pile of
things to keep in memory I'll just remember so this next one what we're
gonna do is let's say we wanted to be able to easily edit this script now
there's a couple ways we could do it right now because it's running and it's
down here I could right click on this and say edit so even if site was closed
yeah changes I can right click it here and say edit and it's gonna open in my
default editor which is site I could also come into the main script here and
right click it and say edit and it will pull it up but that would be really
tedious if you had closed site and you wanted to always edit it so what I love
to do and we're gonna do this with a hot key is a let's start dabbling in hot
key so there are things called modifier keys and those the main four are
control alt shift in the windows key those and auto hot key and so let's add
some comments here so the alt key is the exclamation point the the windows key
is the pound and I'm not yet the shift key is the plus sign and well control key
sorry and and this is the carrot which is above your six so these on their own
we wouldn't use these by themselves but they're called modifiers and that's
because you use them in conjunction with another letter or or or another key so
let's say every time I hit we'll do control H we want that to run message
box hello world now I'm gonna add a return here which basically tells auto
hot key to stop stop going forward after from that point on so I'm gonna save
this always remember you have to save and reload it or hit f5 so now it's
rerun it this is another reason this output window here this can tell you if
there's errors where what line the errors on so notepad doesn't have this and
this is where it's really nice so I can when I relaunch this you'll see it flash
also notice when I relaunch it you'll see it down here at blinks and so it's a
great way to make sure you understand the changes were absorbed or used so now
I'm gonna hit control H and bam there we go right and now if I hit enter it's
gonna get rid of it but look I can hit control H again and it pulls it up so
this is a hot key that's gonna launch whatever is between here and here I
could put a second let's say I wanted to do this so now it'll have two so if I
now I have to relaunch it again now this is the point of what I'm gonna show
here in a second is control H and it's gonna say hello and then world right so
we're using our hot key to use a message display a message box with a value in
it I'm not overly useful but you get the idea of I can trigger this we can also
trigger other things which we'll cover here in a minute but before we get to
that let's say I want to automatically reload this script instead of having to
come in here and launch it and then hit right click and say reload or relaunch
so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna change this to control R so it makes sense to me
this is a really powerful thing in auto hot key I think it's really under you
know you don't understood of that I can make it what makes sense to me right so
I'm gonna change this to control R and I'm gonna add the command edit now this
is a special command let me also demonstrate here if I highlight if I'm
in a word and I hit F1 it will pull up the auto hot key help and that's built
into site also so this is a really great thing here the site document I'm sorry
the auto hot key documentation is excellent you can read about it and
then usually at the bottom it'll show you an example or two of how to use the
commands so I highly recommend again using site and then using that F1 when
you get stuck and don't not sure what it is so what is this gonna do well I'm
gonna save this and relaunch it so it takes it in now you know what let's
let's add here oh I don't want that that should have been reload there we go
and let's look at reload real quick so replaces the current running instance of
the script with a new one right so that's kind of what we're doing with this
F5 we're relaunching it of course reload only works if it's already running but
I'm gonna save this rerun it now watch what happens if I hit control R it it's
funny it reloads it but it because it triggers the reload let me let me do
this a smart way so I'm gonna save this and now hit R control R and now when I'm
hitting control R so see it says it will reload now when I hit okay it's gonna
trigger that reload and notice the green H blink down here so again control R it's
gonna pull up the message box and then do the okay I just wanted the message box
to show you we're actually in here right so now if I really hit just control R
it's gonna well the first time through now it's gonna reload it right so I can
just hit control R I don't have to come up here and hit f5 f5 is hard for me on
my keyboard to reach so it's a nice handy one to be able to say hey I want to I
want to make these changes and control R will do that for us because see how it
reloads it for us so it's a super helpful one to have in here I also want to
point out if your command is more than one line then you need the return if
it's not more than one line so let me comment this out this is only one line
right we can bring this one up here and a lot of these can be put on the same
line and if we do it on the same line you don't actually need the return so I'm
gonna save this hit control R again now it's reloading for us so it's great
because I can just hit control R and have it reload for me now another one
which is really helpful to have so we're gonna say control E to edit and now
this is the one that I was started to work on earlier here so this so here are
two that I will just love having in here so now I'm gonna hit control R to
take that now if site was not open I can hit control E and it is going to edit
this file it's gonna pull it up for us so these two hotkeys in the main script
that you're working on are entity and again you don't have to use control R
right that's my example but it's super helpful for helping you speed up what
you're doing when you're coding because I don't have to come down here and right
click and say reload or come up here with my mouse or hit F5 the control R and
whatever's convenient for you are super easy to do and then what I often will
do is I will use something to trigger so this is this is often much more how
hotkeys are used is let's say I'll do control M for a message box and let's
put that on the next line so message box hello world and now because that is
going on the next line I'm pretty sure let's just test it I could have moved
this up here and I'm gonna hit control R the say see this asterisk up here that
means there's been changes that haven't been actually saved yet so now it's saved
it now control R will relaunch it and I can do control M for my hello world
control E to edit which is I'm already in it so if I was to close this I can
hit control E and they'll pull it up and control R you can see it blinking down
below in the bottom right so these are our three things now that with this
message box I want to demonstrate you can do other things with hotkeys right so
let's let's say I wanted to launch Chrome that one let's start off with notepad
because notepad is a little easier and let's do control in now control in is
already a hotkey in site right now if I don't say this I hit control in it's
gonna open a new tab for me right but I want to use control in in a different
way so I'm going to say run notepad now I don't have I'll add it here you don't
have to have the exe and notepad especially you don't need the entire
path because notepad is in the windows path and so but I wanted to start off
with it to keep it simple so I'm gonna say control S control R to reload and
then I'm gonna say control N unfortunately it launched notepad on my
other screen here but let me bring it over here close it now if I control and
again yeah it remembers where it was so I just made a hotkey to launch notepad
but let's say we want to launch something that's not in the windows path
well you could we could say well I'm gonna come down here got our properties
I'm gonna get the full path and here this to the left I have my running in
debug mode but this is the path to Chrome and so I'm gonna say and control C
would be a terrible one right because that's copy so we don't want to replace
copy so let's do alt C so I'm gonna do the alt C remember you got to use look
up here alt you know the exclamation is the alt key so alt C and then we're
gonna say run and here paste in this more often than not you don't need the
double quotes around it but let's we'll just leave them here so I'm gonna save
this reload it control R and alt C now alt C will launch Chrome for me right
and you can do this with almost any Windows program you can launch it this
way get the full path to it sometimes there's a little things what you need to
have the set a given directory can run into some headaches or if you want to
open a certain file you can add a space here and add the path to the file after
it but being able to launch programs is a great simple thing and that's it for
this one let's let's do one other one so the Windows key so Windows let's say
Windows G and what is anything that starts with G we'll just do something
run grepwin so I'm gonna go to properties this is the path to my file
there we go no that one doesn't have the double quotes but it should be fine I'm
ready this is the portable version of it so I'm gonna save this sorry save it
reload it and now the Windows key G will launch grepwin for me grepwin is a
search tool that will search across files in your computer it's free I highly
recommend it if you need to search text in inside files but anyway you just see
it now I use the Windows key the alt key let's do one more with shift so we're
gonna do a shift and shift obviously the shift with a letter would be bad on
its own right because you want to capitalize letters but we'll just do
shift T and you know I'm gonna be lazy and run calc I think it's calc.exe so if
I hit shift T oh I didn't I didn't save it save it reload it shift T just ran my
calculator so there I used the the four main modifiers shift windows alt and
control to demonstrate how you can launch programs you could launch other
scripts you could launch web pages you could you could actually you know what
let me let me let me demonstrate that I launched a browser however let's say we
wanted to and you know what this will be a good one for the Windows G is let's
say we wanted to run a certain website so here I would put in you know what I
don't like I want to save this so we have it as an example but I'm gonna
comment to that you know what let's demonstrate this I'm gonna leave those
both there I'm gonna say run
so I'm gonna save this when I hit reload notice it says hey there's a
duplicate hotkey you can't have the same hotkey in the same script because it
will cause a problem it won't know which one to run so it warns you that's
another great thing about this is it warns you so I'm just for now I'm gonna
comment this out if it was running in another script it would have launched and
it would have just used the most recently launched one so so this though
what I wanted to demonstrate was oh you know what actually I call it Windows G
because I wanted to run Google there we go so control R now it reloaded now when
I hit Windows G it launches my default browser and takes me to that web page so
this is how I could easily do a search so let's that'll wrap this up here with
dealing with hotkeys and these these ones I like to add in the just ease I I
put something similar to this in every one of the scripts I'm working on that
I'm adjusting I always have it running in that script and then when I'm finally
done with it I either comment them out or I'll remove them because I'll have
another one that I'm working on and I only put those in what the active script
that I'm trying to develop okay the next thing we're covering are called hot
strings or you can think of them as text expansion for me they are the lowest
hanging fruit the simplest thing you can learn today and be using it and be more
efficient at a computer they're so simple and important and save so much
time it was the first Udemy course that my colleague Jackie and I built on Udemy
because they just they're huge time savers they're way overlooked by
everybody and they're just one of those little things once you get them you
realize you do type the same things over and over and over and they're really
helpful so let's go ahead and start working on them what we're gonna do is
let's let's do in a little example here so let's say I I hey I type my email
address a lot right so I'm gonna put in two colons and think to yourself what
what do I want to type as the abbreviation for my email address so I'm
gonna say JTA because this email address happens to be Joe at theautomanner.com
and then you put in the two more colons and then you type what you want Joe at
the-automater.com notice you make sure you put it in the case you want like
uppercase here I uppercase my A right because I want that to come through but
I don't want it here and I want my first name to be capitalized and so I'm gonna
save this since I still have this running I'm a hit control R now it just
absorbed it now when I type JTA period now it didn't do it right then but when I
hit a space a return or a tab basically any kind of ending character it swaps
that out for me right so it's it's a very simple thing to be able to learn how
to do you can replicate this to your hearts and this will work I could open
up do I have a hot key a control in will open up notepad JTA period space
there's my email address right it's it is just the simplest thing in the world
you could put in paragraphs of text like let's say also we wanted let's say we
wanted to have it have a line break so I'm gonna do this till day which is to the
left of the number one till day in stands for like a new line feed is the
actual character for it so and make sure if you do edit your own add it into the
script here that you don't try to save it or load it because that'll cause an
error so new Joe Joe the automator is tick my tick in email to can address I'm
gonna save this I'm gonna control R to reload let's go back to notepad now when
I type JTA period space it put it across different lines right it out of the line
so if you wanted to have multiple things in here there is a character limit on
how many you can do in this structure however you can have up to like 16,000
characters in a different way you can look at the the hot strings help which on
that way at my win webpage for this beginner course I have a link to it
about how to do continuous in sections but it's really that simple and so here
let's get back I mean I'm gonna hit control D which is a hot key in site for
duplicate the line and I'm gonna get back into my email address where when I
save this control R to reload come into notepad you know what I think I can see
if I can type down here yeah I can dump it in here so see that space at the end
well often I'm using my email address or in a as the user area in username for a
form and I don't want that space at the end because that of course would break it
so it's a simple change in auto hotkey is just add an O in between the first two
colons now when I save this and reload it when I come in here and type JTA
period now watch what happens when I hit space so notice where my cursor is it's
right at that M it didn't add the space at the end and so it's a very simple
thing to adjust where if I am using a email address or maybe a password now
you know do discretion if you're saving passwords because the password will be
stored in a plain text file that's easily visible by anybody right there's
ways around it and I have a video on that somewhere but it is they're not
secure so just be careful with it but it's very convenient to be able to do
this so things like you know just some things you just don't want to space out
of the end sometimes you want to it might be plural sometimes not and this is an
easy way to do it without having a backspace to get rid of that extra
space another example that I want to demonstrate in this will wrap up the
basic hot strings is there are certain characters because up here this windows
key the the pound sign the alt key this exclamation point this carrot is
control auto hotkey interpretees is very special characters right so you can't
let's say we were doing this see the STB if you're a signfold fan you'll get
this you have to see the baby exclamation point right so I'm gonna save
this reload it now when I come in here and I'm doing it down here because if I
do it here and I save it it'll break my code right so I'm typing in here STB
period space hey it said you have to see the baby but no explanation point right
why is there no exclamation point well that's because it literally thought hey
let's send the alt key right because it's a special character so the easy there's
two ways very simple ways to take care of it there are other ways we're gonna
handle two of them right here the first way is to wrap this anytime you have a
special character this wrap it with these curly braces and save remember save
reload reload watch that green H flash now STB periods now see it has the
exclamation point so that's option one option two is you can leave this the
original way but put an R in between here so I'm gonna save this reload it
there it goes and STB period space and that works also notice here we have the
space which is perfectly fine but I could put the O in combination with the R
save it reload it come down here see the space and now we have it without the
extra space right so even though this works like looks like the word or it's
not auto hotkey you can put multiple things in here and it's a simple easy
way let me do one more one more fun one that's it's good to know is if you don't
want to wait for that tab or space you want that hotkey to get replaced right
away you can use another one here is you put in the asterisk so here is let's
say HW period oh actually you know I don't want the period here so there we
go so this is gonna send hello world save it reload it now watch what happens
right when I hit the W so H now the second I hit the W it dumps it in right
I didn't have to hit that space or a tab or return after so those are three things
you can easily adjust in hot strings again hot strings to me this may it might
to some of you seem very simple and then oh maybe I'll use that maybe I won't I
can't stress how much you realize you type the same words or same URLs or
passwords or email addresses or names of companies over and over and over or even
entire paragraphs right so there's this is a lifesaver it just saves so much
time and in a second here we're switch over to launching a spell check that
will run again this will work in any program right I could have been a notepad
and it'll dump it in right any Windows program so it's running across all of
your tools some every once in a while you have a little problem sending to it
and that's also check out my my Udemy course or just read the search and read
the help you know I push my Udemy courses little just because they give a good
guide it's not that I want to make a ton of money it's I don't mind making money
but it's it's that they give a nice flow and they cover things they give you an
order and some people really like having the structure in the order so let's get
into the next one with using a spell check
alright this spell check I found on the forum years ago and I tried backtracking
it to get the documentation where I found it but I couldn't find it anyway it
has nearly 4,000 words in it and it's great because no matter what program I'm
in in Windows as long as the script is running it is doing the spell check for
me across all of those Windows anywhere I'm typing so let's jump into it you can
get it off of this main page and I'll put a link in this video too but on this
main page down here download spell check I'm gonna right-click and say save
link as and here we're gonna save it for now I'm gonna save it let's go to the
where I have those other files saved
a lot of key for beginners here we go and I'm gonna call it spell check that's
fine save it now it's gonna save it I'm not gonna launch it here what I want to
do is let's look at that directory and I'm gonna come in here and say edit oh
gotta highlight it edit script and now this is gonna pull it up and I want to
talk through a couple of things before we launch it notice these here's the
source just so you have it here too this is where you can get it from and that no
environment we're familiar with they're ready single lessons force absolutely
send mode input great this one is basically turning off because these are
spelled properly right so it turns off the back spacing for for some of these
hot strings so because those are often people the spell check will think it's
misspelled but it's not and so we're turning it off for that in here and I
hear examples and look how big this file is right like I said it has got 4,000
words that will auto correct for you so it's a really helpful script let's go
ahead and do a demo down let's pick the one I let's do America so sometimes
apparently people forget the sea because I guess there's no seas in America maybe
few oceans but let's say America notice the star here so it's not going to wait
for us for an ending character right it's gonna do the replacement right away
and but unfortunately I haven't I haven't actually launched this yet right
and right now in the system trade we don't have anything running right now
this one has been killed for now but let's go ahead what I want to do is to
come back into where we saved it and I'm gonna get the path to this file so come
in here copy this go back to site here and this is actually going to cause a
problem but I want to demonstrate this as well so I'm gonna say run because we
wanted to run the script this is the folder and then it's what was it spell
underscore I can see it at the top there in the other tab check HK now if I was to
save this and we launched this script we see the one green H running here it's
just test right but hey why didn't that launch the other script well the problem
is we if we have a hot key or if I had a return this top part of your script is
the auto exec script and it happens up until you come down to like a hot key or
return like that so what we want to do is things that we want to launch we want
to have it at the top part of your scripts and so now I'm gonna save this
now if I relaunch this or hit ctrl R you're gonna notice over here now we have
two green ages and it's unfortunate that it always puts in that same default
icon and and this is where it gets really confusing if you have a lot of
scripts running any given time I typically have like five to seven scripts
running at a given time all the time right for this example video I've
ripped everything out so I don't confuse anybody but remember this needs to be at
the top in your auto exec section otherwise it won't it won't get to it
basically it stops it it stops before it reaches it now there's an easy quote
unquote cure for this one is at the top here again if we don't want these two
green ages well hey the spell check I want it running all the time I don't it's
rare I'm gonna edit that file so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna come in here and
that's why I've added this here is this no tray icon if I save this and you know
what I could launch it from here but let's come back in we don't even have to
be here I can just hit control R and you'll notice the the green H is gonna
go away so I'm gonna hit control R now that other green H isn't there but the
script is still running and I'll demonstrate that by coming in here
let's come back down to our America example there we go so I'm gonna start
typing AMERIA and notice it put in the C right so the script is still
running but we don't have it in the system tray there's some some major
benefits of this is that if you have a lot of scripts going it doesn't get
confusing down here the drawback of course is I couldn't come in here and
right-click and say edit so it can make it it can be a pain and I have another
script that you can use that'll it'll show you all running scripts I could go
to my task manager and I could find it from there and right-click and kill it
or I could come back in here and I could just you know go to edit it I could I
could even find it in here and right-click and say edit right so I can
get to it that way but it just won't be in your system tray and you can change
the icons like in some of my other scripts I have it where I change icons I
even have a script to automate changing the icon so Google that on my on my
YouTube channel but it's I recommend hiding you know only having one to two
in there because otherwise it just gets too confusing and so I only allow my
one script I'm playing with to be there and then I'll change it either I hide it
or I change it to a different one so let's demonstrate a couple other things
in here notice down here at the bottom they have abbreviations so I can type
SCP period that's funny it was trying to interpret that SCP period space and it
puts in September for me right so this would be a spell check or let's do this
the days of the week I see Sun space right so it has a lot of default ones of
course you could either comment these out or delete them if you don't want to
have them in there obviously the word may you know that one's gonna come up in a
lot of sentences so they didn't do it for that one but you get the idea right
this is a great easy tool to have running and it runs like let's go back to
I don't have it launched I was gonna say let's launch notepad which I just don't
recall we got rid of that hotkey I'll just turn it back on save reload control
in to launch it and I'm gonna kill it real quick because I'll forget that I
did that and if we do the SUN period space there's Sunday a M E R I know see
a America no V November right it'll run in every program so if you're like me I
actually have a couple tools allow me a text from my computer it's so easy to be
able to automate texting and be using your hot strings to help type the stuff
that you want to send right so it's super simple super fast hot strings are
there you know a really really really great tool that I highly recommend also
don't add too many the spell checks one thing because it's doing automatically but
the regular hot strings don't add too many at once baby step into it also make
abbreviation so like mine what I do is for email addresses I'll put usually
minor my own email addresses are different because I have about eight and I
do them differently but if if I knew let's say Abraham Lincoln and he had an
email address I would do Abraham Lincoln email oops and then a period so
unfortunately that one may not because it looks like that's actually a word but
and this would be Abe at gmail.com right so oh and I actually look at that I
messed up that there we go that's better and this one of course I want the O in
there so I'm gonna save this reload it a e so it's basically the first two
initial the initials the there are the first two letters followed by an e and
that way and then a period and so that helps me have a pattern and makes it
easier for me to remember all my hot strings because I have hundreds upon
hundreds of them and it can be it can be confusing but again they're super
helpful and so let's get going on the next section
okay so I want to do one more with the hot key just to demonstrate how easy it
is to remap keys in a given program let's say you know in a lot of programs
control H will do the search replace functionality and the control H to me
just isn't the most intuitive hot key so what if I wanted to send a different
you know hit a different hot key to send control H so let's say I wanted Alt R so
Alt R that's gonna trigger this now we're gonna send control H and make sure
you add the return because we're on more than one line so I'm gonna save this
control R will reload the script I saw it blink now I'm gonna hit Alt R and
notice it this came up which is the control H now control H still works in
site because I didn't replace that but on that when I hit Alt R it sends control
H which is what the active program is gonna interpret as oh hey here control H
so it's a great easy way to adjust something if you don't like the hot key
or accelerator key and the program you're in you can write it just to redo
your own now when I was actually doing this I came up with a little bit of a
problem here let's let's change the control R R R let's just comment it out
so we don't have that one for now you you could do this this works technically
so control R is gonna send you know what I want to leave that so we are we're
gonna do control R to send control H and before the control R was up here so
this technically will work so I'm gonna save this I'm gonna minimize that
reload the script I think this should we'll control I'm gonna hit control R now
that sent the control H however I got a caution you these modifier keys have to
be the same so if I was trying to hit Alt R to send control H unfortunately so
let me close this reload the script now I'm hit Alt R Alt R it doesn't work I
just hit it it doesn't work and basically what's happening is this is what
gets passed along the the control whatever modifier key was here is gonna
be the same over here it when they're the same it works fine when they're
different then you need to put it onto the next line and then add the return
right so if you just get in the practice of doing them on the next line then
you're fine right if you're gonna use the same modifier key you can have them the
same line if not then put them on different line so I hope that helps it
again just think about it if you're in a program you don't like you know the
the commands being sent it's a great easy way the hotkey that the program is
associated with it you can make your own and the other one I wanted to point out
was you can make context sensitive hotkeys and I'll have a link in the
the web page about this but basically I could have it say if I'm in site and
hit control R and do one thing if I'm in notepad and I hit control R do another
and if I'm in word and hit control R do something else so there there's context
sensitive meaning they understand what program they're in the active program and
it's gonna do something different they're not totally hard to do but be
considering this is a beginning video I didn't want to you know do too much in
this video training video to show you so that's it and then next we'll move on
to our next section okay now we're gonna work on sending mouse clicks to a given
position and before we dive into the code I do want to caution you because
windows often are you know are in different locations where they have
something in front of it and it's not the most consistent reliable way to
automate programs there's a lot of other ways I have a lot of we have webinars
and tutorials on different ways to approach this however this is easy and
if you're controlling the environment it's definitely something you can easily
do set up and let's go ahead and dive into it here so let's pretend we're
gonna click this we'll stick with the control H type thing this is the we
activate the program here so this is the replace button we want to get this down
the problem of course is we need to know the coordinates of where that button is
right so the sending of the click is easy there's a little bit of stuff we
need to figure out where we're gonna send it to so there's a really simple
command it's a get no mouse get position and it's gonna ask for the the two
variables to store it so you can see here output var x I'll part var y those
are suggestions so we'll just call this one look x comma look why look why there
we go that's all we need there and to start off let's let's do a message box
oh you know what well we'll finish this here so message box and x is at and this
is where we're gonna wrap our variable name the thing we just had look x with
percent signs and that will make the message box display the value in the
variable not the actual text that we have there so x is there and y is at
that's why here we go so unfortunately right now I could run this but guess what
we don't have a hot key to trigger it right so let's add a hot key let's say
what let's say control oh I got a control M control P sure for position so I try to
think of them as you know meaningful so it control P to get mouse position now
we're of course this is gonna change later because we're gonna swap this to
actually click in the position but for now it's fine so I'm gonna save this control
R to reload oh I disabled my control R to let's I think I I disabled it but I
didn't read restart it now control our works and this is where this I'm trying
to show you a little bit of the troubleshooting while you're going through
this right so control P is gonna get if I hit it right now it's saying x is at
384 and y is at 58 but that was down here right so we're gonna redo this come up
here now hit control P and now we have to remember 481 and 93 so actually I'm
gonna leave this up here by the way any message box and on a hotkey you can come
in here and hit control C and come down here and paste and it will have the
contents from that message box right so it's a nice easy way to get that little
insider tip there so this is gonna be the x is gonna be 481 so let's comment this
out and I'm gonna keep these numbers so x is 41 and y 93 so I'm cheating here
because the next thing is you know we'll just we'll make that a comment and I'll
have this and now we're gonna click so we're gonna say click comma and now it's
as simple we entered those numbers right so 481 comma 93 and that is that let's
add a return so it doesn't keep going so I'm gonna save this reload and now when
I hit control P notice it moved my mouse there oh look at that how did I get the
wrong thing that's it I'm you know I we can go back and watch a video I will
bet you money I was on the wrong thing when I did that so simply we will disable
this re-enable this oops well I need to reload the script make sure we're over
the correct thing and this is why you know you'd practice right walk it through
so 435 yeah look at that I was off an 87 now the y it's this way so that one
probably can say the same but the 435 this should have been 435 right because
your x is going across and the y is the up and down so now I'm a save reload and
hit control P and there we go so funny how I got distracted apparently and
moused over the wrong item that I wanted to click now again if I had a window up
in front of this it wouldn't care oops hey it wouldn't care it would have
clicked you know and right here and this is why that sending of a mouse click
just isn't that robust or if I move this to another monitor the coordinates are
gonna be different or even if I move it like this the coordinates are gonna be
different right there's a lot of reasons why this can break but this is just the
simple way of hey sending a mouse click to a given coordinates often we put our
windows up we maximize them and and the things don't move so it definitely can
work it's just not the most robust way by the way I have a script called
automate my task on my website and it it eases the pain of getting these
coordinates finding an image it actually narrows it down by the controls it's
pretty robust it'll search everywhere for you you just lock in the image and
then say go click this or go send text to this edit field so check that out if
you're interested but that's it for the sending of a mouse click to given
coordinates in this section we're gonna explain how if you want to share your
code with someone else or that you want to run your code on another computer you
don't have to install auto hotkey it's very very easy to compile a script an
auto hotkey and give it to someone else or just run another computer so let's go
ahead and get started we come in here and go to explore this is the easiest way
highlight the script you want right click and just say compile script right
that'll actually create an executable program in the same folder it takes a
couple seconds so here now I have an executable program I can take this to
any Windows computer I don't have to install anything I just put it on it and
run it and when you run it it'll you'll have the you know if it had a system
tray icon it'll it'll have it down there let's do this with the test so I'm gonna
right click say in that one compile script I'll end up here with a test dot
exe and that one because we have hotkeys in it and the icon is showing it
should show up here in the system tray and that's it right other languages this
can take a lot of work Python in particular I would compile scripts and
it was a process and it's just it's amazing that it's so easy not a hotkey
to compile script and give it to someone else and if they're running even
down to Windows XP Windows 7 Windows 8 Windows 10 it's very very consistent
there are some things with pre Windows 7 there was no user access control and so
things were slightly different so XP might be just slightly different but
generally speaking they're very stable across all versions of Windows on
different computers now the program itself might be a little different
depending if you're sending mouse clicks in the coordinates right I mentioned
that earlier but the the heart of the program stays the same so that's simple
as we wrap up I wanted to share some helpful links and resources that can
help you automate everything and let me jump over here on this so in this
beginner page right which I'll have in the resources here there's the you know
absolute documentation commands and keys these links I have these three
bookmarked on my main default home page I use them a lot that documentation and
commands those are great the keys are when you're just getting used to
understanding what keys you want to send all three of these are just must-haves
that you use in and out the forum page the overall hotkey form it's an amazing
form the people are super helpful and nice you can definitely go there you can
find a ton of things already solved for you there's different forms let's
actually let's jump to it real quickly here and show you so the main page here
breaks down into different forms so there's tutorials scripts these are
completed scripts and functions here's where you go to ask for help and then
down below you'll actually see here are the links to the other languages so if
if English isn't your first language you can actually ask questions about that in
that language which is great and so I have those here discord is also it's a
live site well I shouldn't say life I put people hang out there and they will
they're more than happy to help you with with what you're working on and then
you can share screens and so it's a dynamic way to be able to talk to people
and get some help but you do have to use this link to create an account for it
by the way I like I said I have over 600 maybe so for 700 YouTube videos on
auto hotkey now and I cover a lot of different topics so you can definitely
go there this tutorial on specific this playlist is specifically geared towards
people like you that are just starting out an auto hotkey there's not a ton of
videos in there but there is a deeper dive you know we skimmed over the
installing a editor and installing the program and discussing it I go a little
deeper in these and then there's we've given over 50 webinars on auto hotkey
and we have also I think now around yeah 65 podcasts discussing different things
with automation I did mention earlier I have three Udemy courses here and if you
click them from here there's a coupon code that you'll get a discount for so
for the basically for the intro to auto hotkey hot strings like I said it's hot
strings are just amazing and the intermediate course these are all
they're roughly are between ten dollars and thirteen twelve ninety nine so if you
come here you'll get the best deal that there is and I'll get more of the money
it's hard to explain but Udemy if you come in from other places I end up
getting a tiny fraction of the money instead of getting them from here so I
appreciate if you click these links at the same time it is going to be the
cheapest price you can get so that's why I have them here there are auto hotkey
books by Jack Dunning Jack's been writing for over 30 years and he has a
ton of auto hotkey books you can go to his blog two of the books are free and
then you can download or you know order the other ones they're very reasonably
priced usually between four to six dollars I think and if you're one of
those people that would rather have you know it it you know a step-by-step very
minutiae work it's really great because he also gives you a ton of examples of
how you might use auto hotkey and that's one of things I do a lot of my
videos as well as just talk through what I've automated because it's easy to kind
of get caught up in doing something and not realize hey there a lot of the stuff
I do daily can be automated so I hope that helps auto hotkey is a very rich
robust language we didn't even scratch the surface of what it's capable of this
is just to introduce you to you but you can do things like web scraping I have a
screen clipping tool it'll grab text you can do regular expressions it's an
object-oriented language so you can do some pretty advanced stuff but the API
calls are another great one I do a lot of automating of Excel and Outlook so
sending emails or automating reporting in Excel anything with the Microsoft
Office program you can basically connect to programmatically and really well
drive it so go ahead and check it out my site alone if you come up to the main
site here there's there's you know a lot of different things in here that you can
learn about with using functions where they so here's the functions controlling
programs with controls that's another really great one the web scraping I
mentioned with either IE or now with Chrome which you can see in here again
it's web scraping Excel Auto Hockey Studio once you get a little bit more
robust is an amazing editor it's a default editor I use now but I do have
all these videos on site on how to customize site and to do some advanced
stuff thank you for watching my video if you found it helpful please like
it now and share if you think that others will benefit from it the more you
share the more we get likes we get the more videos like this we can make and
it just helps support us also if you're interested you can go to my site and go
to sign up for our alerts basically we send out alerts of new stuff new videos
new things we've learned new concepts of how to do Auto Hockey and automation as
well as just things you might want to automate so we hope to see you there
thanks again cheers