so welcome everybody welcome back to some faces as well it is so so exciting to
be sharing the space with you again this evening or newly this evening I'm
really it's the third session today of these kind of existential offerings live
events and I'm just starting to have it as something that I really really look
forward to because each session is so different and the discussions always
leave me with so much to think about and as ever I just want to kind of bring
in that that that idea that even though we're just squares on each other's
screens we are real people in real time joining together and sharing this
experience and it's it's just so special I know that some of the people here have
bought tickets that are free some of them have donated some of them have spent
money it either way it's just so you know it's so wonderful because what we are
giving all of us is is our time and that is so valuable and I'm so grateful so
thank you so much to the people that are live and watching for sharing your time
and thank you so much for the people that will watch this in the future for
have using your time this precious time to be engaging with these existential
ideas and even though we're in the present today we're going right back to
the past to explore ancient existential ideas with none other than
Marcos Maria Mendez who is joining us all the way from Argentina so thank you
Marcos we met in Athens and I remember you were standing there kind of
improvising your talk passionately about Greek philosophies and how they're still
relevant today and I just thought right we need to have these ideas spread
further so this is the reason that Marcos shares the space with us today and I
won't chatter and take up any more time Marcos I just welcome you and welcome you
to introduce yourself well thank you it's a wonderful wonderful thing to be
here and yes in fact we met in Athens and well you might expect a little bit of
the same things here because not very much in the preparation of the
topics but of the let's say culmination of many of the years of work and of
study in these things and the basic ideas governing the centers of
the talk so well thank you all for being here and I'll say hello from Argentina
the other side of the world so thanks for taking the time to be here with us
and yeah I'm not very much for introductions I'm let's just say that
I'm a clinical psychologist and I have been for the last almost 10 years and I
find that existentialism at least those ideas and those concepts are very
helpful in the clinical practice in fact at some point I'd say that the
existential dilemmas are so central to the human experience that we can't avoid
them and it's perfectly clear that one or at a certain point we all have to face
those things so many people come to to the practice and say okay I have this
problem I have this big luggage on my back and I can't get rid of it so the
basic concept today will be that well these questions they they persist
throughout history and the idea of the existential school as a school of thought
is well let's say has some certain issues and I don't know if you if you're
all familiar with with the idea of existentialism but and I repeat that
anyone can can interrupt me if the if my words don't come clearly enough the
idea of existentialism is complex because the the basic thoughts are not
very clear why because we have existentialists that are apes that are
apes existential Christians and agnostics so the basic ideas can be applied to
many things the the the school of thought just came to be at least formally with in
France after the second world war I like that there is a lot of European public
because well you might be all very much in touch with the with the history of
of that maybe not yourself but yes only on the generations before you very
different than the experience we have here in in South America so after the
second world war at least in France the ideas just started to be and well I I
think you might have heard of Jean-Paul Sartre he monopolized the idea of the
existentialist he he just adored the word which is very different from let's say
Albert Camus which hated the word existentialism he defined himself as
absurdism the absurd sorry if my if my pronunciation is I find myself saying
some words for the first time in English because of course I've studied them in
in Spanish so I apologize in advance if some of the words don't come up very very very well
so you might have heard of the basic concept of Sartre that the existence
precedes the essence which is in a certain way I'm not trying to make a lecture
about this because there are many far better explanations for this I'm just
trying to introduce the concept so that then we can go towards the antiquity
or the ancient times I think antiquity is just for the furniture right
no okay and the the idea of of the existence precedes the essence counts
in an antagonistic way to the essentialism the the idea that Plato and Aristotle have
that everything has an essence and that everything has the thing that makes the
thing what it is not some other thing so if you if you lost that that would no longer be that thing
the the basic explanation is the knife you can have a handle that's plastic wood
no handle at all but if you take the blade it's no longer a knife so the essence
is that that characteristic which is
unsupprable from the thing itself so Sartre says you know that's not it what if what if we just
don't have any any essence and we create ourselves which is a way of thinking about it
which is a way that I don't particularly agree and that's the thing I don't agree in a way with
one of the most influential existentialists of the world and of history because well Sartre never
never did any clinical practice never studied the development of of the humankind and how we
come from a newborn to to something so there is in a sense a well a school of thought that goes
towards that thing okay no we're just a blind a blank canvas and everything it's supplied which
in a certain way has led to to many of the of the serious aspects of of today this idea that
word we're just what we what we choose to be which is maybe not the case we have certain limits and
the the development that the development of let's say the cognitive functions are of course
rooted on on the body so the the basic idea of Sartre might have been mistaken in a certain way
but but it surely has done some some good things for the for the confrontation of ideas which is in
fact the the basic concept we have here and and that we can talk about all those things
so the so the idea would be that that the that the the the existentialists of the post-war
world war focused on the let's say phenomenology of the understanding of the humankind trying to
incorporate the subjective experience of the of the of the person to the understanding of
reality which is in fact up until today the the basic framework of of existential psychotherapy
phenomenology existential phenomenology so it's a very interesting concept which changed a lot of
the of the way we thought of of the humankind and in fact it's well very unique in its perspective
I'm not saying Sartre just said no so far along he he had many many great great ideas for example
the idea of hell which is not a new idea in itself but I don't know and please correct me if I'm not
saying that the title of the name correct and in the right way it's behind closed doors
might have been or something like that in Spanish it's no exit in English no exit okay
that idea of the Sartre and hell which is not no other thing than the people others which is
very unique and I can understand why he might might be able to to to think that way
but he missed the idea that the others are also the ones that introduce us to the world so this
idea that we come in in in a blank canvas is well to say the least naive in fact he even said
towards the end of his career and his life that he he gave little importance to the material
aspects of of human of human experience which is again a very very same thing to do to be able
to see the the errors of our past but the idea would be that these questions the questions of
death meaning uh freedom Sartre is very much into into freedom this that the the whole
excess of freedom we have comes with with an angst comes with the suffering which is not
of the aspects of of this school of thought so it's all these questions have been since
the the beginning is of humankind so the the existentialism in a sense has been around
well for as long as we are here the questions are and persist so I thinking about about today
I came up with with with a question myself why did we start calling existentialism at least the
formal school of thought after the the world war and I have no good answers sorry but there
there is an aspect that that I think it's crucial that it's that the the questions went further away
from religion than before so the Greeks at least for our western traditions our focus
much more on the Greeks than let's say on on on some other parts of the world
but they they made the same the same questions we do now exactly the same ones
one one could say well we we copied them and and how can it be that we have
haven't got any answers after so so long and and it came to me also a quote from a very good
psycho psychoanalyst and sociologist that's called eric from who said that the
that the technology advances much more than the wisdom we have so the wisdom we possess now
is not at all what what we need because well we're making the same questions as Plato we're
making the same observations as Aristotle and Socrates so one must wonder if if we will ever
if we will ever find the answers and the questions for meaning well what is the meaning of it all
at least my answer is well there is no meaning which might be within the the school of thought
of existentialism that the the the branch of nihilism the nihilist nihilists say that well
there is no apparent meaning and there is no god and there is no nothing that that can
actually give the meaning there i would say there is a smaller branch that says positive
nihilism negative nihilism the negative nihilism would be the the character of of the soyelsky
if if there is no god and there is no immortality then what what well then everything is permitted
in brother scaramosov but there is also the positive nihilism which is okay there is no
meaning at all we are responsible for creating it we are the ones that that give life meaning
which is a powerful thing a very powerful concept to say that we are responsible but it's also a
burden it's also a very very harsh reality that we are responsible for ourselves
so well i think that if you're here now might be because you you you find yourself challenging
those ideas you find yourself wondering all of this because let's face it it's not a very popular
subject all of this you don't go to a party and say okay yeah but what what's the meaning of all of
this i think okay do you all know we're gonna die someday you won't be very much appreciated in the
party so there is a certain element of of uncomfortableness in all of this a very deep
uncomfortableness i would say but it's also charged with with the very profound sense of
wondering and of course i i say to you to your you can you can ask the questions you need but
i think at some point we all have the the the wondering of saying okay but why why is this
the way i live why is this the way it's suffer which is in fact one of the of the tools we use
in psychotherapy we we try and and and get the questions with with a certain sense of of weight
behind them not just the the hollow words again hollow words the words with with nothing behind
them to to find the person asking the right questions or at least the questions that
well they are able to to handle because it's very difficult to to face yourself with a question that
nobody can answer the you and the the ideas and the problems these brings are well
i would say eternal but but it's a very a very weird way of of talking about the human experience
because in fact the the human experience is finite so
i'd say they they will accompany the the the experience of for humankind but we individually
have a very different way of approaching it so i'll go back to to to the idea of the of the
ancients well i also came across i'll i'll take the opportunity to introduce all of the of the
english-speaking audience or participants to um maybe the greatest writer of of argentina which
is Jorge Luis Borges i don't know if you've known him but he's wonderful it's like reading Edgar
Lampeau for for for us by the at the at the last years of his life he was in a project of of having
the the most important hundred books so he took the time to choose each one of them he didn't
didn't complete the the all the collection but he introduced in my in my curiosity one of the
of the most ancient stories the the epic of Gilgamesh which is a very odd a very odd well choice
but in there it's the epic of Gilgamesh is the Sumerian that's a myth a story about a hero
which let's say it simply he he faced a lot of challenges of course but the the most important
aspect is he was searching for immortality and well he didn't make it of course spoilers spoilers
for for a very old book but in a certain way we can see the the question of mortality even before
the Greek civilization in fact the epic of Gilgamesh inspired a lot of the Iliad and the Odyssey so
we find there the the well even the flood yes but also the the the work on hell in hell sorry
in hell that the the hero needs to go to hell to find something
Odysseus did it in the Odyssey Gilgamesh did it in in his epic but I'd like to say that
this this is the point there is something there that that goes beyond the the the basic story
the basic narrative which surrounds it to say okay they were wondering what would it be for someone
to look for immortality in a certain poetic way he found it because well we're we're still talking
about him so good for him but the the question lies there what is mortality and how can we face it
and we're still looking for answers today there is even a whole branch of psychology that's
that that that dedicates itself to the to the people that are dying and well it's very it's very
difficult for us to to to symbolize that so we tried a lot in a lot of ways but we are creatures
of meaning we need meaning in our lives
the in in greek greece in Athens I mentioned the paraitolia and I don't know if it's
perfectly translated english if it's basically that but it's the principle of the brain to look for
patterns and to look for meaning things even if if they are not there which might have been a very
evolutionary edge for us but it's still here with us that we need to look for meaning I always
at least when I work with teenagers I give the I give them the the idea that color in itself
doesn't exist it's like what are you talking about of course it exists I mean look at look
at all the the colors we have here well in fact color is a construction of the of our brain
it's not something let's say objective different animal different eyes see different colors the
colors are the reflection of the light that our eye and our brain are able to produce
but color in itself is not a thing which is very weird but which is again a testament of the
evolutionary presence of meaning in in not only in in our lives but but surrounding us
so they of course it's the it's the strange explanation but it's in fact the way it is
even if we if our experience is nothing like it so
well these ideas go go towards mythology in mythology at least
the one I specialize in which is Greek mythology we find a lot of the of the problems of
existentialism so it's like existentialism is a new branch of of philosophy why would it be so
present over so many things so so long ago written and it's like well yeah because existentialism
has been around forever and there is a certain strange parallelism in in the idea of psychoanalysis
of conscious and conscious and in that's that's very well established in in mythology and philosophy
in the ancient world on one hand the idea of rationality as the great means of understanding
the universe and ourselves and in a certain way mythology just came around and saying that these
are the ways we we understand the world and ourselves so the the great hero of Greek mythology
might be Odysseus the only mortal one the only purely mortal that he suffered a lot and there we
find one of the aspects that I think actually defines existentialism that life is is tragedy
and there's nothing we can do about it of course we can we have all the techniques and
on all them the the technology that allows us to live quite comfortable we're not very hungry so often
we're not very cold so often we have the entertainment we have medicine yet there's
nothing we can do with the existential dilemmas and it comes to to mind now sorry if I if I keep on
bringing stuff the the the the soma of all of no sorry all no 1980 no brave new world hoaxly
where the the drug that's just
implicated let's say or decreased all the the the suffering in in oneself and it's like
if we could do that if we had a drug which we have plenty of them but none that that are so
so at least so effective should we do it should we release the world from the suffering and even
if we if we can wouldn't there be a lot of people that think okay but what if I just
bring this down if I burn this up if I punch this this person so
it's another well paradox of existentialism it's suffering something we need to avoid there is
something that makes us who we are and in a certain way psychology deals with the suffering
with psychopathology and of course I'd say that again sorry sorry Saturday that that I
that I criticized him so much he he knew nothing of psychopathology I don't know if you're aware
that he even tried to introduce a he hated Freud he absolutely detested him and
there is a movie in the 1960s Freud the secret passion I think it's called that Sartre wrote the
the first draft of the of the movie well the director said no this this just puts Freud in a
in a horrible position why would you do that that script was discarded but he tried to introduce a
psychoanalysis even called existential psychoanalysis which denied the idea of the unconscious
now the unconscious is still today debated a lot even if we at least here in Argentina
psychoanalysis is quite popular and not so in in in Europe or other countries I found myself
seeing that in Athens which I later called upon say okay you're leaving behind a very useful tool
that might be able to explain a lot of what's going on so the
the the ancient idea of of the search for meaning is later present in in religion
that the constitution of of the the big religions we have today as answers
for the the the search for meaning what does in a certain way religion do
it gives you the the certainty of what happens beyond death wonderful like now you know
this is what happens and every religion gives an answer so religion is quite useful in that way
to to to release ourselves from the the despair that can come from us
also gives you okay this is the way you live this is the way you need to to to conduct yourself
which is again very useful and even even though in psychoanalysis Freud was very harsh on religion
he recognized the the usefulness it had maybe he was too
too naive to see that it's not about rationality the the thing of religion it's about much more
and it gives much more even today of course european
and it's going a little further away from religion as people are even more educated but
the the rest of the world is another experience and we see we see it in the in the conflicts
we're having right now at least in the the middle east so these things are still present
the war is still present in in the in the in the world we we have it's like no but the the
greeks were from war to war well that's not the greeks that's humankind we just go from one thing
to another and we can even count the years in the world that there were no wars at all which are
very few so the the existential dilemmas are still here and they have practical
aspects to it there is even the the the idea of what do we do with the with the intolerance
and you you guys over over europe are much much closer to the wars than i am but there is a specific
aspect of saying okay what do we do do we fight for survival or are we able to to just talk about it
what you do and there is no no talk no talk available so there is a in these there are
also very practical aspects in fact i think of another another story
written by by camus which takes the concept or the concept of sycophers i don't know if if all
of you know who sycophers is but he's a character from greek mythology that that
cheated on death on two occasions and after that he was condemned by the gods to
to well to tartarus the hell of the of the weak world he was condemned to to carry a huge rock
onto the top of the mountain and at the end of the day exhausted he saw how it rolled over all over
again so that he was he had to to go again and again so he was condemned to meaninglessness
he was condemned to the labor and to the effort without any reward at all so
camus many many years after takes that story to talk about suicide to talk about meaning
and to talk about a very difficult aspect of reality that's saying okay why don't we kill
ourselves so he said all the questions of philosophy are on second place towards the
question of suicide because on that we find ourselves asking okay what makes me want to
live the life i have so it's a very again don't talk about suicide on parties because that's no
it's not an easy an easy subject yet it's a very important subject so it's a very very
when the the helpful organization talks about that they they they of course they give them the
thing the certain importance yet they struggle to to talk about it and just and to find the
the real reasons why people do it because it's a very difficult aspect and and a very difficult
thing to to understand it's a very personal experience so well it's of course alarming that
that's almost one million of people are committed suicide a year according to the statistics but
it's also a very important thing to talk about because that's the maybe one of the most existential
problems we have because it faces us with with with our condition and why would someone choose
that there is i remember when i was working at um at the public hospital that i i discussed this
with a colleague of mine saying all suicide is psychopathological because of course we can we
can see with someone with depression someone maybe with schizophrenia but it's all suicide like that
and it's a very at least i haven't come upon the the question any other any other place other
other myself but it's um well it's very difficult to face those those problems so
oh we tend to avoid them and we can avoid them particularly in our societies which are
meant to distract us there is a very good book of Vargas Llosa sorry another Latin American writer
and it's called the the the civilization of entertainment she's very good
very simple to to read maybe the translation should be should be good enough
but we can avoid it for so long for it punches us in the face because because we at least well
not all of us will have to face death at some point maybe not ourselves but yes and the people
we love we will have to to deal with suffering one way or another so this idea that the the world
decides a nice place where we should be comfortable might be very detrimental for us might be very
very very false which in a in a certain way comes to the to the to the to the to the fight
of of ideas very barely poorly equipped so
well i think of of the of the buddhist one of the of the four noble truths of buddhism
life is suffering and that's again we go to the antiquity we go to towards
the the these three fathers of thought which were socrates confucius and the buddha
which changed the way we understood things but none of them said that life is something
nice and something comfortable and something that that's a gift from the gods in fact they
they socrates well criticized a lot and and with good with good ideas the socratic method is still
present in us in our psychotherapy so the the the ideas of buddha and confucius all come to a
the questions of existentialism what should we do with our life how do we deal with death
how do we deal with suffering and are so inextricably linked with the with with ourselves that
we find that it's worth exploring all of these things even if we have no answer
and of course if you are here you are interested in one way or another for all of this and that
the the the the the basic idea of existentialism which in this in this sort of activities and
and channels and and the the offerings is a a wonderful place to to explore this and to
at least feel that the suffering we might have is not unique to us because that that's
another thing that within the the psychotherapy sphere we try and deal that the person comes
saying okay i suffer i suffer specifically my suffering is unique and to a certain point it is
but certain aspects of that are absolutely
shared between us so
my my ideas would be to to
to find the way of of asking this to find and to find places where we can talk about all of this
maybe there are some some very good guidance in all of these things and in fact we can even
help help other people in this network of existential branching for the for the difficult
aspects of life because i guaranteed you know someone who's struggling with all of this if not
yourself and that struggling is in a certain way the the the core aspect of of the greek idea
that there's a tragedy that's why they invented tragedy then came the romans that made them the
circus with the with the coliseum and the the entertainment of death but the greeks and i
think we have a mixture of greek and roman that's why we have i don't know the world cup and that's
fantastic as it is it's so it's purely entertainment and but also we have the tragedy
we have the the movies and we have the the the art that connects us with that part of of ourselves
so i hope nobody nobody has has fallen into a silent despair but yes that we can we can
hear you and see what what you have to say about all of this of course there's a lot to
to to learn about ancient times and i think those three figures are a wonderful way of starting
i also recommend um uh called jaspers then that he talks about all of these three figures uh no no
i think he changes socrates for jesus so he talks about the figure those those three figures us and
as um as a way of understanding who we are so uh i think it's uh it's later over there but i hope
everyone's uh wondering at least my idea would be that we we share questions not the the answers
because of course this is not a lecture that i have the the absolute truth and in fact it's
more of the of the experience we have and the and the the the ways we have of understanding
ourselves and our lives and the and the spaces we we uh we're in even if it's work family
and the these sort of places but how can we apply certain things of this towards the the
the concrete aspects of our lives
i think if any if anybody if anybody um
um uh finds finds yourself uh wondering how can we connect over this of course it's a very good
thing if you if you can talk and and say um i hope nobody's uh dizzy with all the the the
concepts and the ideas sorry if i if i branch too much
no it was exciting to follow all of the different branches and go on such a journey
in in my own thinking and our own thinking but then throughout history and just um i'm gonna
reiterate what what marcos is saying let's make this a discussion let's make this a questioning
a shared questioning together um and i think the question that comes for me or the kind of
discussion that exploration that comes for me is what you say about clients coming to us or
people coming to us or even for ourselves that in that moment our suffering feels like the most
unique and extreme experience of suffering that could exist and even as therapists even as coaches
even as reflective and intelligent beings that know that statistically historically that's not
the case but still somehow there's that sense that big sense if we're being approached or
confronting something in the future or in the moment or in the past that's incredibly difficult
for us that we are isolated in it um i suppose i don't want to speak for ages i would love for
other people to jump in can i can i ask yeah yeah tony go so lovely to see you and thank you so
much for doing these things awesome i mean i've had um i've in my life i've had five suicide
friends which i think is an exception of suicide friends and um the impact of that is may and i
you know i'm a deep absurdist or existentialist and you know my my question on a daily basis is
really is about resilience and opposing forces to this absurdity because i mean if you know i think
we all get that it's absurd um i think that you know every time i read lots of stuff i resonate
more than you can ever believe but i think the question is how to live an absurdity in a way
that um is nourishing and uh as a you know i'm a pathologist by training so so i mean you know
i'm a hard-nosed scientist so the question always is is you know we know we know what we know if you
like the complexity of of of these questions but what's the antidote
two things come come to mind of course sisyphus and and the and the absurd
but
the the the existential branch of thought comes a bit against the idea the rationality can can
read us of all the problems we have so that that's where the the subjective aspect comes from
and in a certain way there is no antidote at least not an antidote that can work for everyone
because meaning is a very personal experience so nobody can well you can try and impose meaning
on others you can try and say okay look this works for me try it but that doesn't assure you that
that it will work so it's a very very close relationship you have with with suicide the
absurd i don't think many people acknowledge the absurdity of all because it's a very difficult
thing to to digest it's it's very it leaves us very naked onto the world so that's where the
the subjective tools come in at least my faith goes towards the person goes to work towards
the individual so one question just because then i'll i'll chat up because i could talk for england
um nisha our lovely nisha who we love so much um the famous camel hypothesis you know you know
which i i pretty much love actually i i use it every day i mean i suppose my question is is is
the camel a desensitized absurdist and tony can i ask you to explain the camel for people that don't
well yeah sorry sorry i mean the camel is you know in in um nisha thought and it's quite
close to go to actually the the camel um you know he believed that four metamorphosis of man was the
camel first then the camel becomes a lion the lion slays the dragon and the dragon becomes the child
so he he basically said that uh and i know it's very interesting because you use the word all
dyshuxley who i love um i mean and you you use the word who i mean was it all dyshuxley or was it
the the other guy who came up with the term the proletariat so let's use the word the proletariat
that nisha came up with the idea the proletariat were camors and that they had desensitized themselves
to this absurdity and then in came the lions that were trying to transform who were absolutely
naked to that absurdity tried to slay the slay the dragon and then became the child so i mean you
know there there is a question i have on a daily basis in my own world of which so many people seem
to be happy and absurdity that distresses me really but i'll shut up on that one maybe otherwise
i might talk for england well remember that the the camel needs to give way to the lion the lion
then to the child uh we're talking about the spoke saratustra which is a very good book
very recommended possible but yeah might might be difficult but but it but but within it the
all the concepts of nature and
in a certain way he needs to talks about the camel as as a metaphor for the animal that's
that's very very harsh and able to to support a lot of weight in fact that's the the idea
that the camel carries the weight of of the hump onto itself which gives him or if sorry
the the chance to survive the desert would give him the chance to to to live but then it needs to
change uh the the it was a very very accurate idea that the last metamorphosis of the child
because the child plays because the child creates and because the child is in a certain way
all potential so the idea of of getting rid of of god was not in in
talking about this idea of god is dead and we have killed him
and to be able to create and to create our own morality our own way of living makes us the
the ubermanche makes us the ultra ultra man i don't know in english um yeah the ubermanche
the ubermanche uh if if um i would say that i i agree in a certain sense with with barter and
rassel one of the of the great um the philosophers of great britain uh he says i i think in an
in an essay about nature that we should we should always listen to him but be very careful to follow
him because the idea of the government doesn't consider the idea of others with us doesn't
consider the idea that we can build our own morality for ourselves because we we're never
on us alone i i go to to add his total again the only ones who don't need others are the beasts
or the gods all of us we need we need the other and that's also the the the idea of
but why but why i would love to go to a dinner party with all of you and talk about suicide
but why why are we so different to the camel
we meaning who this group who are here is a representative of existential
thinkers or behaviors or whatever
what makes you think we're we're so different from the camel well maybe we are firing things
the reason i i think is because i'm a biologist and i i see that groups of societies have such
clusters of different if you like types who are there with a different job our job is to
agitate society really and that's well i'll go i'll go back to the
do you remember the the the cave allegory of Plato yeah yeah the
do you remember why they chose to stay chained and and to see the shadows no because
because seeing the truth because facing all these things is extremely difficult and not all of us
are prepared and well one would say also with with the haxley idea why would someone
uh anesthetize himself and we do it all the time we're not we're not exempt of the suffering
these entails so it's a very difficult thing and we try and be children in a certain way in
in an extreme way but it's difficult and might be that at some point we are camels and some
point we're lions and some point we're children and some points we are we are just too tired to
face all of this so um it's it's a a a strange way this idea of of facing all of this that's why
well in many ways religion is still very very disseminated across the world
um very helpful in many ways because it's uh i would not say impossible but extremely hard
to think of everything ourselves we need to rely on the on to to to stand on the shoulders of giants
umberto eco has a very good book about that that's called on the shoulders of giants
no i need to us because we need we we rely on on on the ones that came before
and that's why the idea would be they can still teach us a lot but we need to look further and if
we can't see further it's because they made the the much of the hard work i don't know what the
world would be without the greeks i think i mean um i can't remember the author but
but he talked about the the battle of marathon as uh maybe the the most important event on the
history of western civilization because if they if the Athenians had lost that battle the world
would be a lot different and democracy would have would have let's say um died in its infancy
so uh yeah i i think i got i got carried away but um why people thank you for not to thank you for
the dialogue i'd love that no but but the but i i i'd say i find it much more interesting
why would someone face these things rather than than be anesthetized it's it's uh i think that
question is much more uh much more relevant why would someone choose to face all of this
when they can just immerse themselves in i don't know football politics even religion
that gives you the answers there is a in psychoanalysis we we talk about uh sorry if the translation
is not correct uh not the fault and how would you say if when something is missing in you
um devoid devoid yeah it's not exactly void uh it's like the the castrate castrated when
and something is missing let's just call it the the missing fanaticism and and Freud makes a very
good case of this fanaticism compensates the missing so you um and and the missing might very well be
the meaning in life and that's a a missing that cannot be undone cannot we cannot um we cannot
uh successfully um equilibrate equilibrated or balance it so of course the the fanaticism
supports in religion remember the thing of of the void it might be the void i have to look
for the translation i've never read Freud in english which would be a very interesting experience
and the the fanaticism is the compensation of that we we we feel that void with with that
with our team with our church with our values and much of the artistic aspects of the of the child
goes towards that children find themselves playing with with let's say an empty box
and they have have a wonderful time but adults we say but it's just a box
that doesn't matter the children create in in the void in the absence of and maybe that's
where we at least the ones that approach these ideas go towards we create where there is none
we we make ourselves answers where there is no answer at all and that's very difficult that's
might be uh very very harsh on on or heavy but in a certain way these places are wonderful for that
to say that we all are asking the same questions what can we do with that
so i don't know if it's i i don't have a very optimistic answers for this at least not in the
in the existential department um but but yeah um i hope it answers a little bit of the question
yeah thank you welcome you're welcome
can i ask you something where do you place the human encounter
in encounter meeting of two persons the social encounter yeah yeah in in this
uh in this difficult process of of trying to deal with existence or yeah
or the void or whatever or so yeah you say the child creates in the absence of things you know
so and maybe that's easier than than to create by means of the human relationship
that's that's why it's so difficult to relate maybe you know
maybe there's the truth in there or something i don't know so the topic of of human encounter
does it has a place in this in this existentialistic position uh yeah
i think the i think it was in the in the 80s or the 70s in tokyo there was um a very big problem
with suicides of young men so the government consults with a group of psychologists and the
psychologists suggest that uh as the as the means of suicide was the train to jump onto the train
that they put mirrors on the other side of the of the train of the of the of the
the the place where the train of the rails yeah the idea was that that would give the the man
like a shock of narcissism to say okay no i look at myself and and i choose not to jump
well that didn't work of course why because the mirror is never the mirror literally
the mirror we see ourselves by other relationships we have at the others at the encounters
and the it was like a very literal way of understanding humankind
so the encounter is not only necessary is the thing that makes us who we are
if if nobody was there to receive you when you were a newborn you would die or even if
he if they give you the food and the shelter you would still die because i think it's called white
death um the the that happened i think it was started in poland uh at a certain war
where many of the adults when were killed and many babies were left at the care of very few people
and they gave them the shelter and the warmth and the and the food but they gave them no more
attention than they needed there was no let's say sorry for the word erotic eroticization of
the subjectivity of the of the psychic apparatus so there wasn't like no will to live
so yeah the the encounter is is what makes us who we are that's why sartre says that the hell is
others because they are very capable of torturing ourselves but they are also capable of saving
and that's where he missed he just saw the the the negative aspect of the encounter
and yeah existentialism is always about people never in solitude we we might suffer in solitude
but dilemmas are shared the the problems are uh well very much uh faced together that's at least
one of the the core ideas of psychotherapy but another an encounter can help you face things
that you could not face before that's why they approach us or or anyone and that's a
a very powerful encounter at least when you click when you have the
for chemistry with your with your therapist it's a wonderful experience
so yeah the encounter is uh central it's like the antidote we found the antidote
it might might be for for tony i like that one
yeah well we need it we need it my friend we need it i begin to like tony yeah
well we'll we'll be there together okay well that that's uh well that that came from an encounter
so yeah the the answer in action
and anna says in the chat all we need is love and a smiley face
well yeah
i don't know if he was so catchy all we need is meaning snub so
yeah not so so phonetically attractive
if frankle was in the Beatles that was his thing
so uh it's um of course the the ideas would be uh would forth uh very very well in much more
time and much more uh uh deep analysis of of the the Greek culture and of the
Buddhism and the ideas they have and there is a lot of analysis we can make of all of this
even the the bible has a lot of extension uh aspects to it it's after all well very very
inspired in in Greek ideas but that's the the the the the book that
the western civilization was built upon so of course it's in a certain way
filled with ideas we can connect not because of the of the truth of the idea i don't know if
i don't believe adam and eve are a literal and a literal story about how we come to be
but yes that it has a certain metaphors we must remember that we are symbolic creatures
the words we use are metaphors if i speak of a tree the word tree means nothing
if we have the meaning shed that's where the metaphor applies and and we understand each other
so through metaphors and through the stories as well as and i think that's the idea of the Greeks
they understood that that the metaphors on the on the myth and the philosophy uh could coexist
and in fact did in there but and as as tony said well biology and science is so wonderful too
the problem is and i find it's a very very funny question for me that can science answer all the
questions it's a question that can't be answered but by science because science can't deal with
everything i think that's a tremendous question um but i mean one just one one with this thing
do you think that many humans are suppressed existentialists
what do you mean what what do you mean by suppressed
well conformity has has erased their questioning
well that's that's education for you formal education because i mean i i have a children's
book that my grandchild had and i think that the modern children books are moving away from
metaphor to literal so it's a bit like you know oh i i agree and and it's you wonder whether what's
going to happen is that we're going to suppress a lot of it in um in banality which i think is a
very interesting word well i see it as well i i um in this couple of years of days i saw news
that in the simpsons um the new episodes of the simpsons will not have a Homer strangling Bart
yeah because oh no you can't show this because the children and i was like
that's that's uh an interesting take on that that that that we we lose the idea of that that's
a cartoon that's not that the people go struggling people because they see Homer uh so it was like
that's like going towards the most literal of the of the readings you can make of that
and and in a certain way the most simplistic and superficial idea of that of course it's a
it's a funny example but i agree that we are losing metaphor we are losing the idea that words
are complex things they're not defined they're not um they're not written in stone like saying
okay god means peace well it depends on where you are and what context and what place and and
how you use the word so uh yeah i i agree with the diagnosis that we are we are becoming more
literal at or at least they they are trying to they like who they are i think it's a lot based on
ideology and a way of thinking of people and our children specifically but it happens over there
and happens here in in argentina as well uh literality is quite uh i would say it's like they
they don't give the child the chance to to fall it's like everything everything is controlled and
and uh it's it's um no good that they struggle because when you introduce something to a child
well they can repeat the word but they don't quite understand the concept the abstract idea
yet uh it's a struggle they have to make to to to keep incorporating things
so the the idea of the literality is is very yeah i would say it's poisonous enough
as it is to not make people think very very deeply thinking has never been easy
has never been economically friendly uh in the in the in the in the sense of the of the brain the
brain itself it's quite lazy it tries it tries to deal with with everything even information
as as efficiently as possible so it's it is going against the current against the the the the the
waves but i think it's a fight that's worth giving to try and think i don't think it's a
very good very good pathway not to think about things and not to connect with things because
it's not only that you lose the the the capacity to think abstractly of complex ideas but you also
lose the ability to connect with the emotions to go within so and and that's even more difficult to
to counter weight and because they they they chop off the the possibility of um well of connecting
with with the high emotions and powerful emotions but also with harsh emotions so uh that's part of
life the both extremes i hope everyone leaves here with many questions
it's it's interesting because we came in thinking about ancient existential thinking and kind of
following it questioning its trajectory but this part of the conversation is quite disturbing to
think of where that future will go you know it can we get to the point as if if existential ideas
started at the start of human civilization is the trajectory that we're following that eventually
we won't question are we are we questioning less deeply i mean it's it's kind of mind blowing to
think that i think generally speaking the the like you've been saying the the value in storytelling
the value in myth the value in arts the value in performance all of this has been replaced by other
value systems that have just been you know really really shoved into the the faces and the psyches
of the population and uh you know it's it's not a comfortable thought it's quite an oppressive
thought to think where does that where does that go from here but you you might want to think what
what are we doing here today aren't we uh trying to to deal with with some aspects of the of the
human reality in a in a deep way and in a deep uh and and uh yeah maybe disturbing idea that's why
the the the dystopian authors are so so interesting to me because they show a part of the of the
reality which could come to be i mean i i love the t-shirt that's saying of orwell that says
i told you so i think that's brilliant i i warned you guys not with with much anticipation
and we we have a constantly news about the state of of um double thought i i i i i saw in england
those uh interesting news that police goes to your to your place if you don't have the
right idea if you protest against something that's not you should not be protested against
so it's well that's orwellian all right and and that's why thinking has always been problematic
but uh at least in a in a in a community way this is a very powerful thing but also in the
in the in the psychotherapy department is okay think about uh about yourself and who you are
who you want to be who you can be uh so yeah i don't find that that it's more disturbing now
than it was before we've seen atrocities uh all over the the history of humankind
and maybe the the shock comes with the idea that life should be easy peaceful and and with a
with a with a soft music behind you know life is and and the events of the world have shown that
life is difficult and life is many times unexpected but we need to fight for the
the ideas we stand for and for the things that makes us who we are so yeah
of course it's disturbing but it's only disturbing if you look at it
the thing is it's difficult to look and to understand what what do we see that's why people
who was it Pascal
that says something like this like it's easier or i don't know it's easier for
for people to to trust what they see in their eyes instead of thinking about it
because one is seeing beyond what you see maybe a little bit connected with the
literality we talked before so it's always been difficult but it's a fight that
uh at least gives meaning at least to me to to keep on with the with the ideas
that and that these things deserve the the time and deserve our energy
and i think in one way kind of thinking what Tony was saying at the beginning it
there's something you know unified there's something almost courageous to be spending
your life specifically dedicated to exploring these ideas and you were speaking about this
kind of this group of existentialists collecting together today whether that's live or you know
in the in the future viewers but it another side of that argument is everyone to to an
extent everybody is questioning these ideas in their own way and actually finding a community
like we have created and are creating there is there's something a lot easier to be able
to to question in this collective community and have the resources that we do and i think
you know everybody's thinking but where it's almost easier we're almost fortunate to have
to be thinking about it in this community rather than just flailing around you know
isolatedly and a lot of my clients come to me because they have been questioning these
questions alone and it's incredibly scary and painful whether that's finding a community within
an existential philosophy and having those resources or whether that's in music and
collaborating in that way or arts in that way but i remember naturally there was one of your
that lovely thing you did was it last year when you interviewed all these people and
there was a guy who said um you know that he would go to a dinner party and never leave
not leave if we were talking about this subject i can't remember the name of the guy but it but
it's very it's almost irony isn't it that we would um we as a group would love a dinner party around
this we would drink all night you wouldn't we wouldn't leave whereas most parties i go to
i want to be there under 30 seconds and i'm on to delete so isn't it ironic
the remember that not everyone is ready for those questions but once you start it's very
difficult to believe that once you start is almost like there is a point of no return
yeah i love that i love that what what is your drive to continue questioning
my drive
at some point why do you why do you look at the disturbing
why do i look at that it's disturbing at the disturbing i mean looking at things
things are disturbing only when you look at it and you said
yeah so what's your drive to open yourself to the disturbing
i remember there was a writer that was was asked why does he write
and he answered because i cannot not do it
and and and i think once you go towards these questions you can't stop you can't i mean it's
very difficult to to uh very difficult or even impossible without any uh huge defense mechanisms
might be crippling defense mechanisms to see something to not see something that you saw
so um i if i can't i cannot stop looking at things but that doesn't mean that
that i can't appreciate the the wonderful things that are down here look at the the space we have
we have today it's a wonderful thing to be able to communicate from two sides of the world
and to talk about these things of course they are difficult of course they are uncomfortable
but the the alternative is much worse at least for me that's why it's a choice
and it's a difficult choice and it's a choice that might not be for all
remember that these things are and and the the struggles we have are the same the same as the
ones that uh the Greeks had the the the cave the allegory of the cave is exactly that many
will choose to remain in the cave and there is nothing we can do for them because they they
have to choose and that's the freedom that's the the exercise of freedom they have even if it's not
for the for the their their benefit that's of course we can we can lament we can we can
we can suffer the idea of them of everyone not seeing something we can't impose that thing on
them that's why at least in psychotherapy it's no use if someone says oh no you should go to therapy
and and and i'll take you because there is not something personal that the person chooses to work
there i remember in in the public hospital and we had a specific team that dedicated themselves to
to to traffic yeah so so the people that that came to to renew their licenses need to make a
a psychic test and and have a certain space and i would say no i i don't want them because they
are not patients they don't choose to be there they are forced by the circumstances of their work
and in fact that's the the case they didn't work in therapy they they just it was just a
part of the of the functionality of the the demands that the the the the government made
that's why it's first the desire desire to go there desire to work that's a very good first step
to therapy
i've got my eye on the time and uh just like you say it's once you start it's very difficult to
stop i think we've all proved the case that it's very difficult to stop this and even when we close
today today's session we'll all be thinking because we really can't stop um but in terms of actual
time we we definitely have to bring it to a close unfortunately but i want to thank absolutely
everybody thank you so much for for taking the time to come and thank you for everyone that
contributed either just by your presence or just in the chat or or part of the conversation to make
this event what it is it's so nice to have a community i think that's what comes for me today
one of the many things it's so amazing to have this community to explore these questions and um
it wouldn't exist without everybody that makes it so so thank you so much and of course a huge
thank you to marcos um from all the way from argentina it feels funny all the way but we're
we've all the way but thank you so much um thank you so much thanks thanks everyone for being here
thank you hope hope you you live with many questions and of course thanks to natalie for
for the space and and to keep on making these these sorts of things that are very helpful
so thank you all thank you natalie ciao ciao okay bye ciao bye
you