Best guess is that China only has 1.3 billion people now the population probably peaked more than 10 years ago
And by 2030 there will be more retirees than workers and by 2050 the entire population of China will have dropped below
650 million
That's wild. It's beyond terminal
How real has the progress and prosperity of the last century been in your opinion? Oh, it's been fantastic
This has been the greatest time to be alive the combination of the American security umbrella plus globalization
Has changed the way we lived. It's allowed everyone to benefit from global trade
Before we had that if you didn't have oil locally
You didn't have transport fuel if you didn't have coal locally you didn't have electricity if you didn't have good food
Locally you didn't have a population
globalization safe globalization enabled anyone to trade anything that they could produce
Even if it wasn't a commodity and join the system. It was like everyone had one World War two all at once
It's it's been a great ride
And now it's ending
Was it inevitable that it was going to end if you'd gone back a century ago and being able to change
Policy globally could you have done something differently back then?
A century ago probably not there's a there's a couple problems here
So first of all when globalization really got going in the 50s
We started moving off the farms and into the cities to take manufacturing jobs now when you live
On a farm kids are free labor. You have a whole scat of them
But when you move into a condo kids are just really loud expensive mobile pieces of furniture and adults aren't idiots
So we had fewer you play that forward for 70 years
And it's not that we're running out of children that happened 40 years ago
It's that we're running out of mature adults
And so the economic model of globalization is consumption based and it just doesn't work without people
So we've always known we were going to get here in the end just happen
The Americans forced the issue at the end of the war
We told everyone that we would patrol the global ocean so that anyone could send any cargo ship anywhere to trade in any product with any partner
That's what made globalization work now. We didn't do this because we were nice
We didn't do this because it was a trade program. We did this as a bribe
This is what we gave everyone so that they would join us against the Soviets
Soviet Union collapsed in 1992
So Americans have been electing ever more isolationist and populist leaders ever since
So for you to believe that globalization can continue you have to believe that a it doesn't require consumption anymore and
Be that the Americans will continue to bleed and die so that the Chinese can get
You know, that's a bad bad
Before we start talking about where we're at and what that means for the future
Is there anything else that we need to understand about how we got here about any of the fundamental principles that we're going to be talking about?
We'll bring them up as we go
But those are the two big things the demographic flip well past the point of no return and the Americans have largely checked out
You said that 2019 is the best that the world will ever be what was particularly special about that one year
so think of your demographic profile as a pyramid children on the bottom retirees at the top
mortality built it into a pyramid as we
industrialized and urbanized it became more of a column and then and eventually an inverted V with more mature adults than children in
2019 was the last year before the baby boomers really got into retirement in a big way
So we had this massive post-war generation throughout the Western world that were all on average
so
They hadn't retired yet and all of their investments and all the retirement savings were churning along providing capital for the whole system
We still had a huge amount of consumption out in the world, but you fast-forward three years this year on average they turn 66
So it's over we've lost their consumption. We lose their investment
They have to liquidate all their stocks and bonds and go into T bills and cash because they won't have the ability to recover from a crash
and we're also seeing some of the fastest demographic aging in human history throughout the
Developing world with China being the far most advanced. So we're losing the investors. We're losing the workers
We're losing the consumers all at the same time
On top of that we had Trump and we had COVID and now we've got Biden
And then we had Brexit and everything that used to tie it all together has been broken apart either on purpose or just because of the
Strategic trends that were already in play. We're never going back
consumers
Investors and workers those are the three main things that people of working age and above school age give us
Absolutely, and we're running out of all of them and you need those to continue to grease the system
They're the people that drive not only creativity in terms of pushing technological progress forward and bits and pieces
But they also inject capital into the system. They're the ones that are spending on consumer goods so on and so forth
so they just provide lubricate like financial lubrication and also the
Worker power the employee employee power, right?
You can kind of split it into two general categories for people roughly aged 18 to 40 maybe 45
Those are your young workers relatively low value add
Relatively low cost, but they're at the height of their consumption because they're raising kids and buying homes
So that's where most of the economic activity that drives a modern system comes from
Once you passed 45 up until 65 the kids are moving out the house has been paid down
But your income keeps going up so the delta between your income and your expenses gets very very large
And that's where all the financial heft comes from
but these are also our most productive workers because they literally have decades of experience and from roughly
1985 until
2015 the world was in kind of the perfect balance because we had a lot of those countries with the mature worker
Demographics and then a lot with the younger worker demographics
What's happened is that countries who joined globalization in the second wave in 1990s mostly the developing world
They urbanized and aged out much faster than the rich world did
So when we hit 2015
That big chunk of developing world workers the experienced workers the productive workers the ones who saved
They're now moving into retirement. We're losing their money. We're losing their skills
But because the developing world is aging so much faster
They're moving into their 40s in their 50s, but they haven't been able to build up the skill set because their systems were not as established
But their birth rates dropped faster than the West's did
So they actually have lower birth rates in many cases in most of the advanced world
So we've lost children on both sides of the ledger and now our new mature workers
Just don't have the skill set to keep it up. And even if they did they wouldn't have anyone to sell to
When old people die, do they not pass their money down as either inheritance or inheritance tax?
Does that not go back into the system in one way? They do and if they died at age 66, that would be great from an economic
Unfortunately, if that's the right word
This people continue on for 20 25 years after retirement now. This is gonna sound really weird
But in the United States, this is less of a problem
Number one, our baby boomers actually had kids. So we do have a replacement generation. We know them as millennials
We can talk about them later in all their faults, but ultimately they're there and that's a good thing
Second
We have a really high mortality rate among people over age 55 in the United States
The the delta between the average age of mortality in Europe versus the United States is in excess of 10 years
So we will get that churn a lot faster than Europe will
That's interesting
okay, so
What which countries at the moment have got the worst demographics which countries should be yeah
Which countries should be very concerned about the ratio of young to old?
The worst in the world is China
They've been in the process of updating their data over the course of the last couple years and they're now starting to publicly admit
That they over counted by a hundred million people
All of those people would have been born since one child so age 40 and under the young worker demographic that
Childbearing demographic and two-thirds of them are probably women
So we best guess is that China only has 1.3 billion people now
The population probably peaked more than 10 years ago and by 2030
There will be more retirees than workers and by 2050 the entire population of China will have dropped below 650 million
That's wild it's beyond terminal yeah, so the Chinese system collapses this decade for sure
I
Assuming nothing else goes wrong, and there's plenty other competitors to put the bullet in China's head
Dude, that is crazy. Okay, so
Yeah, all the way from pre-industrial to post-industrial collapse in 45 years
Just for the people that don't understand about how the one-child policy and the preference for boys over girls and stuff created this landscape
What's the what's the high-level view of that sure? Well, there's two things
First of all of course is one child Mao was concerned that they had a young upcoming generation after World War II that was going to eat the country alive
So they went to a two-child policy ultimately to a one-child policy, and that was not loosened until 2015
But by that point the damage was already done because there was a second factor
Remember countries that industrialized later can follow the path of those who came before they can skip some steps
So China was the fastest ever industrialization experience
What the United Kingdom did in seven generations the Chinese did in one?
And so they crammed seven generations of economic growth and development into one and that's why their growth rate has been so impressive
But you can only do that once and now it's behind them and now they have no children and they have very few people under age 45
Mmm
Is this is
Population growth and collapse similar to an r-naught number in a way that more people
Allow you to have more children which gives you more people to have more children
But if the reverse is happening then it causes a nose dive
You're absolutely right there now. I don't want to say that
Unchecked population growth is necessarily the way to go. That's not what I'm after here
I mean you require a balance between children young workers and mature workers
If you don't have enough mature workers, you don't have the capital
You don't have enough young workers. You don't have the consumption. You don't have the children. You don't have a future
China is already out of those last two categories. And so we know where this leads. It leads to zero
Given the fact that
Humans are being I think it's every three generations lives for another generation at the moment around about every generation lives eight years
Longer than the generation before increased health care health span
Better access to that is only true in the shift from pre-industrial to industrial so you get that once
Well depends upon how you apply the lessons to your system in the case of Europe. I'd say they got it three times
But there's definitely an upper limit one of the things to keep in mind especially when you're talking about European demographics
Is that Europe in Europe people are not living longer?
Overall lifespan has not improved. What's improved is we've gotten rid of a lot of mortality
So the things that used to kill you when you were zero to sixty five don't kill you anymore
Right, okay
That is going to change the shape of demographics as well
Right the fact that young people are able to get old more easily say more safely more safely
Yeah, precisely, so I guess there's just a lot over the last hundred years. We've seen such change
It's not just been technological change, but downstream from that is what's happened
Demographically and how that's how that's influenced the demography. Okay, so if I'm medicine electricity sewage
Yeah, if China's got the worst who what are some of the areas that have got better-looking demography
The three countries in the world in the in the advanced world actually in the advanced and in the developing world
New Zealand France United States
And largely for the same reason there are countries that have a little bit more physical space
So their cities tend to be more of a sprawl
You're more likely to have a backyard more people can live in the countryside and be economically viable
So when these three countries urbanized they did it at a slower rate
And they remain the three advanced countries with the lowest urbanization rates in the world
In the advanced developing world the closest one was is going to be Mexico and for similar reasons
I'm in central Mexico, which is on a highland massive is just one giant suburban sprawl
And that means that people can have more children now all of these countries still have their own demographic hiccups
They all have the baby boomer problem. It's just that they all have replacement generations
I saw I had a conversation with Jordan Peterson about this at the start of the year and I did some research before is the
country with the highest
current birth rate per
Family Chad be somewhere in Africa. I'm gonna guess probably somewhere in central Africa. Yeah Chad, Nigeria that cluster
But I'm gonna guess that just lots of children isn't necessarily a good answer either because you then lock yourself into potential futures
You can't birth any more or fewer five-year-olds now. It's what whatever happens this year is now. Yeah, yeah, precisely
Precisely, so in the case of sub-Saharan Africa, and you know, this is a very broad array of countries
It's very difficult to make a generalization
They've started to industrialize and so they're going down the same path that everybody else did and the first step of that path is
lowering infant and child mortality and so when one out of three children don't die
You have an explosion in your birth rate
But if you play that forward 10 15 years
Then you start having adjustments and family planning and you get smaller and smaller families as urbanization kicks in
The danger for countries that are in this category who've taken the first but not the second step is
That they've imported a lot of the technologies of industrialization
Which has helped them out, but they have not developed the systems to sustain that
Themselves so if something happens to the outside environment, they lose all of the benefits what like
Healthcare medicines
fertilizers
It's very easy for me to see a lot of these countries facing famine in the not too distant future
Because if you break down globalization, you know, yes, that means it's difficult to get oil or manufactured goods
I'm more concerned about agriculture
Agriculture is by far the most
Delicate and vulnerable of the economic sectors because it needs the equipment it needs the finance and needs the fertilizers
It needs the trade options you break any of those the whole system falls apart
And with the Ukraine war we are seeing massive disruptions to the fertilizer sector with some of the decisions the Chinese have made same thing
So we're already looking this year at losing
Roughly a third of global fertilizer supply. That is going to haunt us for a decade
Wow, okay
so for the people that maybe haven't been able to work out why it is that increasing urbanization and
Education and development causes a reduction in birth rate. Can you just explain that for sure?
It's a wide array of factors
So when you move into a city you have less room and that just changes the mechanics of raising kids
When you move off the farm kids are no longer free labor. You have fewer of them when you urbanize when you have electricity
You've generated time and so people can do things after sunset
This is important for everything in terms of economic development, but it's most important for women
Because if a woman moves off the farm into the city and all of a sudden can do something after hours
You have the opportunity for mass education and freeing them from doing more than just being mothers
Nothing wrong with being a mother
But it's a full-time job on the farm in the city
You're gonna have fewer kids that's less time allotted and you have a greater chance to you know read
And so the entire women's right movement is basically linked indelibly to electricity and
Once you have it women have fewer kids because they now have other things going on in their lives that compete for attention
They can go and get jobs. They can pursue careers. They can do research. Yes interest
We absolutely so I mean the the British example with the the cotton mills was probably the best example
The first group of people to urbanize weren't the men. It was the women and we saw the impact on birth grades
Going back to what you said there about food shortages and the delicacy of agriculture
I'm seeing a lot of videos come out shaky phone videos come out of China at the moment. Just how bad is there any
Reliable information about how bad food and the future of food will be in China
It's getting difficult to get good information out of China. It's really demand
Devolved into a cult of personality state even stricter than what Mao Zedong had
I don't think that the Chinese having a food crisis that is impacting their ability to have calories at the moment
Chinese land is among the worst in the world
And so it requires a huge amount of fertilizer to grow anything specifically phosphate for rice
By far the world's most phosphate hungry crop in the Chinese traditionally
Because of that have been the world's largest producer and exporter of the stuff
The problem is actually with Africans swine fever. Now, you may have heard of that a few years ago
They had a big outbreak. They ended up culling more hogs from their farms and the rest of the world's commercial
farms have hogs
Just give you an idea of just how lopsided the pork market is. It's two-thirds of it is China
They went to rebuild their herds, but they never abrogated the debts for the farmers who went out of business
They just offered subsidies to bring in new people. They thought that would be cheaper
Well, you have now two million new hog farmers in China who have no idea what they're doing
And let's just say that phyto sanitary does not
Translate into Mandarin well in the first place. So we're probably in the early stages of a second wave of ASF
That'll probably be just as bad if not worse than the first one
So pork just like it did two or three years ago is about to fall off the market in China completely
That just leaves rice
So the Chinese have banned the export of phosphate fertilizer in the short term
This is causing massive problems in agricultural producers in East and South Asia Australia, especially Western Australia is probably the part
That's getting gotten hit hardest
Brazil is feeling the impacts because these are Western Australia and Brazil basically can't grow without fertilizer
They don't have soil on the way that we think at the term. It's a weird geology
But you interrupt the input flows
And it's very difficult to grow food at volume
And China in the best of times is on a razor's edge in terms of food sustainability
And they use about three to six times as much fertilizer as is used in the global average just because their land is so poor
Luckily phosphate they've got covered
They produce that themselves, but the nitrogen is all made with imported natural gas
and the uh
The phosphate half of i'm sorry the potash half of that comes from a different continent
so
Yeah, china demographic collapse
unavoidable
food collapse
highly likely
And that's before you start talking about things like energy manufacturing and trade
Does this not make china unbelievably dangerous?
The question is what would you do if you're china? Where would you go to get what you want?
If you go into kazakhstan fine, but you know, what does the winner get?
You can't go to india
Nabila is on the way
You could go into vietnam, but when the vietnamese when the um, sorry when the chinese did that last in 1979
They got treated just as well as the americans were and so that was a quick war
They don't have the navy to push out
Japan and taiwan could go nuclear in a month. Hang on that just leaves russia. We heard this
China are taking over the south china sea
There's all of these small islandettes that they're putting together. They've got this scary big armed
Forces that's going to come and take over everything in the is that not the case
So they're not as strong militarily as they have been have we been told really not
Um, they have made significant strides over the last 30 years
I don't mean to belittle that
But everything they're doing in the south china sea was designed to intimidate vietnam and the philippines into
Cowering and it had the opposite effect and both countries just ran to japan and now have defense packs
It doesn't really allow the the chinese to project power very far either
They do have a lot of ships. They've got like a 650 ship navy
But 90 of them are really small and can't sail more than 1500 kilometers from the coast
And that assumes they're going slow in a straight line and no one's shooting at them
In actual combat conditions. They can maybe make it 600k
So it's they don't have the power projection
And they're the country in the world that is most dependent on reaching the world in order to reach markets
and resources
Okay, so that's demographics. How does globalization play a role?
well
If the chinese can't reach europe, they lose their largest market if the united states throws a trade war
They lose their second largest market if they can't reach africa. They lose raw material resources
If they can't reach the persian golf the lights go out
They're completely dependent on globalization as maintained by the americans for the entirety of their economic and cultural system
What do you mean when you say as maintained by the americans?
The united states is the country that guarantees freedom of the seas or traditionally that has been our role since world war two
That's what we're getting out of
And we're there's going to be this little fun thing with ukraine war that's about to happen
So i don't know how much you've been following that but the europeans have done an insurance ban
Which has dissuaded most reputable carriers from taking russian crew to china
So the chinese and the russians rented a bunch of super tankers
Alashed them together into a raft off the coast of portugal
And they're bringing shuttle tankers from russia's ports, which can't take super tankers and doing sea to sea transfers in the middle of the atlantic
I can't wait for somebody just to do
And just grab it
It could be portugal the chinese don't have the naval capacity to put anything that far out neither to the russians
But someone soon is going to do that and that's going to shut down the entire energy trade out of russia
I'm a little surprised it hasn't happened already, but it's going to be a fun day when it does go down
Dude, that's wild. I mean how much how much oil are you talking about here? Because presumably if someone was going to
Do a small act of war in order to take it it would have to be a worthwhile amount of
Well, you wouldn't you probably wouldn't do it just because you wanted the oil
You would do it because you want to disrupt the russian financial system because this would destroy it
One super tanker the insurance policy on one super tanker is going to run about a billion dollars
The russians only have five billion dollars put aside for this
So not only would you disrupt the immediate transfer, which probably would affect
I'm just spitballing here because the russians aren't talking but let's call it two to three million barrels immediately
But anything else that was in the chain going back to the russian ports probably another 10 or 15
Million, I'm sorry. I said billion early two to three
Million barrels. There's probably another 10 to 15 million barrels on shuttle tankers on their way there now
And then all of a sudden the ports get clogged and then the pipes get clogged
And the pressure builds up into Siberia into the permafrost and the wells freeze
And that's it for russian energy for 30 years
Dude everything is so interconnected
Mm-hmm and fragile
Okay, so that's globalization for china you mentioned that the us was kind of like the police of the sea
And they're getting out of it. What does getting out of it mean and what did police of the sea mean?
Well part of globalization was making sure that everybody's commerce could go anywhere in the pre-world war two environment
Unless you were an empire with a navy you didn't trade
You couldn't because the empires were in charge
When the empires died in world war two and the americans took over the global structures
We decided that rather than having a single american-led structure that was designed to siphon off
energy and food and resources and money to the united states as an empire would we would instead
Prioritize security versus the soviets and so we provided the economic backdrop the security backdrop
That was necessary for everyone to play
And that's the world we know that's what we've been living in the americans make sure that piracy is under control
They make sure that hostile countries can't rage commerce and they generally provide policing actions
Not to say that we've done it great in any given day, but that that's been the plan and it's broadly worked
Since 1992 we've been backing away from that. We've been closing down our overseas bases
We've been retooling our military so it's not destroyer heavy and designed to patrol
It's carrier heavy and decide to and design to hammer things
So we now have 11 super carriers by the end of this decade. We'll have 14
one of them
Is more powerful than all but nine of the air forces on the planet
And that assumes a fair fight and the whole idea of a navy is it's never a fair fight?
Because chips move, you know, we learned this from you
Uh, and so it's really one of our new super carriers can take on any but one of three
Air forces in the world and we have you're gonna have 14 of them
Uh, so that's great if you want to knock off a country
If you want to patrol the global oceans, no, no, no, no, no
Because you can only be in 14 places at once and that assumes they're all at sea, which never happens
So we no longer even have the military structure
That is necessary to guarantee global commerce. No country in the world does
So the most likely outcome of this is we'll get a series of regional powers
That have military force that is capable of kind of making a bubble a little sphere of influence
And there will be trade within those bubbles
But the trade between the bubbles is going to be very very sketchy
Difficult to regulate difficult to protect and by definition can't really be very long distance
That eliminates a lot of what's out there
What are you protecting?
The seas from is this
Criminals and people that are going to steal ships is is that the risk that happens?
I'm trying to work out the difference between the current state and the state where there are few destroyers
patrolling the seas
Well pre-world war two is usually imperial competition
If you didn't have something that you thought you needed you went out and you took it and if somebody else had it
You have a nice little war with a naval component
During the cold war it has been i'm sorry just during the post-cold war era piracy has come back in a very big way
It's
more an irritant
But if you look back to pre-world war two privateerian was all kinds of fun
And the idea that you didn't have to go out and raid your opponents shipping yourself. You get as high or someone to do it
I expect to see a lot more of that. Oh, so that was what I was thinking. I was thinking this sounds very
primitive
very medieval that
countries that
publicly are at peace and
have their
Diplomats going to visit each other and conversations and they're sat around tables together agreeing about stuff that they would try and steal
Shipments of potatoes or whatever it is that's going on or metals that seemed a little bit unlikely
but what you're saying is that
There are ways around committing outright acts of naval war
By I mean you can have state piracy basically using your military to grab things direct
You can have privateering where you rely on third parties to do it and provide safe harbor
And then you can have flat-out piracy
We've dealt with all of them in the past. We're going to have to deal with all of them in the future
Do you think that's is that realistic though in the current state where?
Information is able to be pushed around the world super quickly and
sanctions and public
lambasting and so on and so forth would someone really come out and try and steal some ships whether under the cover of
A bunch of guys that rush has been doing it for six months
Okay, yeah, yeah
They are at war though, right when you break down the rules of action and when you remove the security guarantor
Countries do what they feel they need to whether it's out of opportunity or desperation
Interesting. Okay. So that's globalization globalization. Let's say that it does
Start to slow down. What are the knock-on effects of that? Oh, dear god. Okay
So I just wrote this book
The book split into six big chapters based on the various economic sectors so transport finance energy industrial commodities agriculture manufacturing
Everything that we understand
About all six is dependent upon the idea of global security
And so you remove the global security and all six of them have to unwind and reform in different ways
So really it's kind of pick your poison with transport long haul goes out the window
That's an end to among other things super tankers. So if you are getting your oil from 3 000 or more miles away
You're out of luck
Ships are going to have to be smaller and go faster because the concentrated risk that a giant container vessel has
You lose one of those and the shipping company goes away
If you're doing smaller tankers or smaller ships that are going faster, they can't carry as much
You just lost most intermediate goods trade. That's an end to electronics manufacturing in its current form
So you can play this on really any topic that you want
But the structures that have all held it together and made it work are dependent upon the ceiling not falling
And it's falling
It seems to me like the current way that the world's setup has got most people myself included
To believe that everyone's just a bit nicer now
Than we were for most of human history
Do you understand what I mean that it's uh, how would you say?
it's
global policing masquerading as
virtuous human nature
We established penalties for people who didn't play
And because the americans started with europe, which was the headquarters of most of the empires
It's stuck
The only non european empire that mattered at the time was the soviet union, which was the target of all this
And japan, which was subjugated
So everyone who in the past had been a bad actor if you want to use that very loaded term
All of a sudden was on the same side everyone who had ever had a projection based military throughout human history
Was in the same coalition
It worked
for a while
You've said that energy is one of the sub components of globalization
Presumably because in order to get the energy you need to move it around the world in order to take it from where it's taken from
To where it needs to be used
Is just how crucial of a port a point is energy because alex epstein's been on the show nate haigans been on the show
Richard betz from the ipcc has been on the show
I understand that they have their priors with regards to where their research lies
But obviously their focus is that especially with nate, you know energy is is absolutely everything
What are your views on the current sort of state of the energy climate and then moving forward to climate change as well?
I would say that there's not a lot of light between me and those names
I mean obviously when you get into the details analysts can quibble about everything
And they can they do absolutely
But the the core idea that without energy none of this works is solid
We've spent the last 70 years bringing the energy from where it's produced to where it's consumed which means primarily from the middle east
To europe and east asia north america is more or less the self-contained component even was before the shale revolution now
It certainly is
That was one of the prices the americans paid in order to get their alliance is making sure the energy would flow
In the environment we're in now
We're at a risk of losing all russian crude
Now i've always thought this was going to happen eventually. I didn't think it was going to happen this soon
Russian crude is what has largely fueled
The global economic expansion since 92
Because when the soviet system collapsed their energy production did not and all of their commodities were just dumped on the international market
And that has kept prices relatively low for 35 years
That period is now closing and so we're going to lose
Five percent of global crude which doesn't sound like a big deal
Until you remember that energy demand is inelastic
And a five percent loss in crude can easily generate a tripling in price
So an energy induced depression that is broadly global in scope
Will start because of the ukraine war at some point
And this is probably the reason that no one's gone after that raft yet
Because that would be the death blow for the russian energy sector. So that would kind of be like have you seen a
Margin call the movie
Not recently now, but do you remember what it was about? Was it a 2008 financial crisis?
And it's it's semi-fictional and they bring everybody in overnight
And they say look if you decide to do this if you decide to dump all of everything into the market you are choosing to begin
The most armageddon like financial situation that anyone's ever seen. So that that's interesting
That for somebody to go and do that. They're aware that downstream
Five degrees of separation. There are a bunch of externalities that are basically going to ruin everyone the whole system. Yeah now
The math is going to be different for everybody
Like take take latvia latvia has the capacity to do this
All they have to do is grab one shuttle tanker as it's leaving st. Petersburg
That would do it and the latvians have already managed to wean themselves off of russian crude
And while it would crush most of the european partners
They would see the destruction of the primary income stream for russia as an unalloyed good
Or consider the americans. We're self-sufficient. We have the capacity of putting a wall around our energy exports
So they stay at home
So we could actually see energy prices in the us go down because of this
But then the rest of the world would lose access to russian and american crude at the same time
So everyone has their own math to run
And a lot of it is going to depend upon how everyone interprets the loyalty or the actions of their allies
So i mean look at germany the russians are in the process of jerking with the
Germans on natural gas and you know for those of us and the rest of the world like yeah natural gas
It's an energy source. Whatever. No biggie. That's not what it is in germany
The entire german economy is based on taking a cheap russian gas
Processing it to petrochemicals and then using those inputs in the entire manufacturing sector
If they lose that gas, it's not just that the electricity prices go off. It's that the german manufacturing model fails
So the germans are being presented with the choice
Leave the coalition
And keep the lights on
Or lose your gas and no longer be modern. So what's more important to the germans being western or being modern?
That's a that's a shit choice
But it has consequences and people will judge them down based on what they do
Peter you need to give me something positive here, man. I'm just i'm
Terrified this this doesn't sound like a very good situation
At all. What are the bright lights? What are some of the bright lights?
There are countries that were damaged by globalization
The empire specifically if you were a country that had a pretty good geography at the start of this
Then when the americans came through and changed the rules so that everyone can play you saw a massive drop in your overall power
If you are one of those countries
and
You have a positive demographic structure
You could actually make a lot of hay out of what's coming because you could I don't want to use the word imperial narrow imperial might be the right word
You can definitely make a bid for your own neighborhood
So the two countries that are on the top of my list is regards that are turkey and france
decent demographics good manufacturing base largely not integrated into their neighborhoods economically
The french actually trade less with the eu than the brits do
Fun fact
And I can see part of western europe becoming part of a french fife toman obviously parts of the middle east
For turkey. I would have put japan on that list
But the japanese managed to cut a deal with both donald trump and joe biden
Which makes the japanese the only people who have been able to get on with both sides of the american spectrum of elate
So I think they've basically agreed to partner up with the us rather than go the wrong way
Which I think will be the best for everyone in the long term unless you're chinese, of course
How's the uk gonna do?
That's up to you. Uh, you really need to figure out this brexit thing
I mean, it's just yes, you've left, but you still don't have any plan for what's next and that is really hurting you
Uh with every day that that is pushed off
Your negotiating power with whatever the structures of the future
End up looking like are going to be weaker and weaker
And you're very rapidly getting to the point where the only option you're going to have is a trade deal with the united states on america's terms
There are worse things that could happen
but uh, we will be as um
It's best way to phrase this
We believe be as gentle in the negotiations as we were during the lend lease talks
Where you basically had to give up half of a hemisphere of military presence in exchange for 40
destroyers that you're used to laugh at because they were so bad
Not good it doesn't seem no, it's not a good negotiating position. That's for sure
Okay, you think that mexico is going to be a big part of america's future. Also, canada's good because it's able to
Yeah, uh, because it's able to do good immigration. It's able to keep its demographics pretty well
What's the future for america look like in your opinion?
Well, the united states is starting this process with very little trade exposure to the wider world outside of
manufacturing in asia, uh, a net energy exporter of all forms
A the largest refining power in the world the largest agricultural power in the world
So a lot of the things that every single country in the world is just going to have to stress about us
It's just kind of a no brainer. It's already there. Uh, in addition
successful manufacturing requires
proximate
Labor that is at different skill sets and price points. So the person who's doing the injection molding is not the
Same guy who's making the microchip
With mexico, we've got that already
So for us a lot of the hard work has already been done
And while i'm not a huge fan of donald trump by any measure his renegotiation of nafta was a stroke of genius
And it got ahead of a lot of these issues
um
Because of that north america's a unit looks pretty strong and we're already seeing
Established linkages to other powers that might be useful. So we for example already have free trade deals with columbian chile
Which are in my opinion the two most dynamic south american economies
We already have a long-term agreement with both the koreans and the japanese
The australians have a free trade deal with the united states and we're in league with the australians and the japanese
Really starting to become engaged with southeast asia, which is another part of the world where the demographics and the geography line up
so that kind of
greater american co-prosperity sphere
Is about as good as it's going to get
I mean, you'll have to deal with the americans when you tend to be a little twitchy sometimes
But we're twitchy in a different hemisphere for most of the partners, which most people really like
In your neck of the woods, france is just going to be completely insufferable
Because they're going to become the broker for the germans
They're going to become the the first power in iberia and in italy
And they're probably going to make a bid for the low countries too
And the longer it takes the uk to become a self-sustaining power again
The more advantage the french are going to have in rewriting the local rules
So a good example is that, you know, you've you've built these two super carriers. They're top-notch pieces of equipment
But between budget cuts and austerity and the financial crisis
You let the rest of your navy die
So you've got these two fantastic vessels with no defensive rings
Which means the only way that you would ever let them leave port is if they're sailing as part of an american battle group
Again, not a good negotiating position
What ways could america mess this up? Oh, so many so many
We're in one of our once in every generation or two politically shufflings and as long as that is going on
We really don't have eyes for the rest of the world
So there's a huge strategic and economic opportunity here for the long run if the united states would chose to leave and kind of
Define what the new world was going to be
What i've outlined here is probably what's going to happen on autopilot and in many cases because the australians
And the canadians and the japanese are doing most of the diplomatic heavy lifting. Thank god. They're there because it would be a mess otherwise
One of the great things to keep in mind about the united states
Is because the population is so big and so young and because the land area is so huge and so fertile
We've never had to be at the top of our game
We can rely on geography and demography to do most of the heavy lifting for us
And that allows our politics to be completely batshit
And that's where we are now there are many degrees of freedom that you can mess up within yes
This this isn't france where if you screw up you have to pay for it for two generations
If the us population is big and young
Does that not mean that downstream from that you need to have an even bigger younger
population in order to not end up with that inverted pyramid shape on your
Demographics it's definitely possible um our our
What while most of europe and japan and korea have that v shape in their demographics ours is more of a double hour glass
because we've got a bulge where the boomers are and then a bulge where the
Millennials are but then a big cut out for gen x and a big cut out for the zoomers
The ins and outs of that are going to dominate our economic and our financial world for forever
So right now we're about to go through a capital crunch
In 15 years when the millennials are in their 50s, we will be going through a capital boom
As a rule large generations make large generations and small generations make small generations
So we would expect this
wave to continue
What that means is that the american propensity for
Overdoing things and then over correcting
That's just part of our dna now and it's backed up by our demographics. That will take us
All number of bizarre directions and we will drag along a lot of other countries with for the ride
I was with jonathan height a few months ago. It's the heterodox academy conference and he was talking about the
dangers in the dating market for gen z at the moment the high levels of social anxiety the fact that you've got
One third of people aged 18 to 35 is still living at home with their parents the number of 18 to 30 year olds
Reporting no sex is tripled in the last 10 years from about 10 to 30 percent
A bunch of things that are causing young people to be less socially out there
Presumably to have children later. I think it's 2019 that for the first time ever more women had children over the age of 40
Than under the age of 20 for the first time ever in history more women at the age of 30 were childless
Rather than with child. So all of these things
seem
Like they would predict a ever aging gen generation or an ever-ranging demographic
What your suggestion is that you have this sort of hourglass shape and there will be some sort of inflection point presumably with the
15 year capital boom
Probably that would should hopefully encourage
More families more children more population
Offset this going from an hourglass into a inverted pyramid. That's what the data we have today suggests
But I've got to underline. We're in uncharted territory here
The world has never had a population bust without having some sort of massive endemic disease or war event
So when I say, you know, the chinese collapse has to happen
You know, I don't know how you make it work without kids or young adults when I say that the americans are going to experience a
Another baby boom as the millennials really come into their own
History and data suggests that but we've really never seen this combination of factors before
The zoomers
I have concerns
They are not like millennials. Millennials are very outgoing. They're very social
Because they were raised by the baby boomers and they were always told that they were special
That's one of the reasons why a third of them still live at home
The zoomers were grazed by gen X my generation
And we took a very different view of things, you know, we kept track of the score at the soccer game
We wrote it down. We showed it to him before each game
We read it to him to bed so that they wouldn't forget and when they turn 18, they're the hell out of the house
Uh, they're they're insular. They're competitive
They don't like relying on anyone for anything
And so the whole group dynamics and managerial dynamics that the millennials are positively known for and recognized for
They're the antithesis their dream job is to code alone in the dark in a closet
And that makes it hard to have kids
So I think we can guarantee that when it's the zoomers time when they're in their 30s
That their birth rates are going to be low their marriage rates are probably going to be the worst we've ever had
Their suicide rates are already the worst we've ever had
Which just means that the millennials will save us all
Okay, right. You're relying on you're relying on me and my heart fantastic
Given given the current state and obviously there's lots of
Contributing different countries. What's going on with demographics people talk about a population collapse overall globally
What is your view of global population?
uh
Before we start talking about de-globalization so assuming that globalization continues from its height onward
We were already in the process of revising down our estimates
So it used to be 15 years ago that we thought by 2050 we were going to have 11 to 12 billion people
That number is now under 10 and as the data continues to get upgraded will probably
Assuming nothing goes wrong peak at just below nine and then start falling back gently
If i'm right about de-globalization
We're going to have a significantly sharper drop-off and as soon as globalization hits agriculture at large
Which may be in the fourth quarter of this year
population peaks
Wow, okay positive stuff
Looking at the ways in which
Population collapse and the reduction of that could be tied in with automation
Is there any technological savior that can come through and assist us with the problems that we're facing at the moment?
There's always unknown unknowns when it comes to technology. I'm aware of that, but
Are there things that you can foresee if we get particular advancements that may alleviate some of this absolutely so pros and cons
Uh, there are a lot of technologies with automation AI and robotics that look really good now
AI the whole idea of general AI and skynet
Decades away from that. So I was put that in a box. I'll let Ian must talk about that
AI is all about image recognition today
And getting it so that machines can recognize different things and then
Do pre-program tasks? There's no there's no real autonomy, but it's automated
That allows manufacturing to reshape, but it also requires massive economies of scale
The most expensive thing a country can do isn't industrialize. It's to automate
And it's not a one-off cost
You have to constantly update it because every time there's a change to the production line
You more or less have to start over with the programming. So it's a very expensive way to go
It does use different labor and less labor
But it's not clear to me that it really moves the needle in a huge way
And if we're breaking down
global transport and intermediate goods trade, then we're losing the economies of scale that make that model work
In north america where you've got one third of global consumption
We'll probably still be doing that, but I see that broadly leaving the east asian sphere
Which combined with their bad demographics are awful
We also have the baby boomers leaving so that we know that the capital crunch is coming
That means less money is available to do this sort of upgrading
The technology I was most interested in are the combination of automation and agriculture
We're very close to having facilities that you can latch on to a tractor
That identify each individual plant
And identify if it needs water or fertilizer or pesticide or if it's a weed or whatever
And then it gets a squirt of whatever is appropriate
So you do like six passes of stuff in one pass and each plant gets individual attention
That suggests that we would be able to reduce fertilizer and pesticide use by 80 percent
And maybe even double yields
But again economies of scale
It only works on mega farms where you can afford the equipment cost
So if you've got giant farms in the united states or the netherlands or argentina or australia
Sure
Doesn't work for most of the world
Talking about technology. I've heard that we are unbelievably reliant on getting cheap technological parts out of china
Silicon chips and other such stuff
How much of an issue is it going to be if china is facing demographic collapse and then can't make anything anymore?
How much is that going to have downstream effects for the rest of the world's technology?
Well, we've been a little bit lucky that the chinese have kind of become a bag of dicks and really
Encouraged everyone to outsource and resource everything that they can
It's that's bought us a lot of time
Now in the united states everyone is paranoid about
Semiconductors and we all see that 12 percent number that the us now only produces 12 percent of global chips as a panic point
But that's by number
By value we produce 60 percent
So all the chips are designed in japan and the united states
They might be manufactured somewhere else if they're further down the the scale
But in terms of cell phones and server farms the important stuff that that's already safe
The problem is going to be the mid and the lower land the mid ones are usually malaysian thailand the lower ones are almost certainly china
So when you're talking about the lower tech stuff the internet of things
Yeah, that's just going away
But i'd argue that i don't really need a meat thermometer that is going to tell my phone what the temperature of the meat is
I mean we can get by without that. I think
It's overall electronics manufacturer. That's going to be the big issue
As remember differentiated labor forces is what makes manufacturing work
China is a huge place
It's got a lot of that internally and then it has access immediately to taiwan japan korea and southeast asia
That's what's breaking down that whole ecosystem
Uh, we can't rebuild all of that. I mean just just to serve
Electronics needs for north america probably would require a workforce of four million people in manufacturing
We're already in labor shortage
And the mexicans are kind of tapped out already. So there is going to be a huge amount of pressure
americans do well at the really high-end manufacturing
And the very low end because we're energy rich
It's the part in the middle that we're really reliant on the mexicans to save us for
What ways could you be wrong about all of this stuff?
You know, like I said, this is perspective. We're dealing with an environment that we've never been in before
uh
The way I would like to be wrong
Is that the americans would actually do what george herbert walker bush wanted to do back in 1991?
And have a conversation with ourselves about what sort of world we wanted to live in and how to get there
We weren't interested then I would argue that we're really not interested now
So the risk here from my point of view is that globalization does manage to persist because of some
Green american commitment
I'm not seeing that. I'm certainly not seeing that with the ukraine war. Yes. We're seeing nato having a new lease on life
But the whole guns for butter deal that we made during the cold war
None of the economic stuff is on the agenda all the sanctions that the trump administration enacted are still there with one exception
that the airbus case
uh
I don't see it's very likely and then on the demographic front
That's just math if you want more 30 years 30 year olds. You had to start 31 years ago
What difference would it make if china invaded taiwan?
Uh, that would probably lead to the end of the chinese system as an industrialized economy in less than a year
Um, why that's fascinating
It's an open question of whether or not the chinese could pull it off
And with the ukraine war, we finally got some good signposts of what it might look like
The chinese have always assumed
That the war would be a walkover
That no one else will get involved and that china is such a big place that everyone will just suck it up and move on
Well, that clearly hasn't happened with ukraine and the united states and the west have a much tighter relationship with taiwan than they do with ukraine
ukraine was only preparing for this war for eight years taiwan has been preparing for 60
Uh ukraine can you can walk to ukraine from russia? It's a bit of a swim to get to taiwan
The sanctions that are in place against russia would absolutely devastate china because well russia has a lot of faults
It's a major exporter of food and energy
china imports those things
75 percent of their oil is imported from a different continent
Uh, and 75 percent of the oil is imported
And then i think it's really the boycotts that have really scared the chinese the most
The idea that individual citizens might have any say on policy
They had they did not see that coming. They have no way to process that in a one-man state
Because it's so different to the setup that they have. Yeah, exactly
So every assumption that they've based the last 40 years of military planning on is proven to be wrong
And then of course there's the question of whether they could actually do it
If they did a slow-motion mobilization like the russians did took three months
The taiwanese would see that
they built a few nukes and so
The cost of capturing taiwan would be losing shanghai and beijing
That doesn't seem like a good plan
So the only battle plan that i've seen that might work is if they just text every member of the army and say go to a port
Get on a fishing boat and sail
You'd lose a million people in the crossing
Just to get to the beaches
So there's nothing about this that works
And if they did pull it off even if they do capture taiwan
They are now cut off from global manufacturing global investment global energy and global food
Truck stop running within a couple of months the lights go out in less than six and that is all she wrote
Remember agriculture is an industrial sector. So you're talking about mass famine in under a year
dude
Now normally i'd say the chinese aren't stupid they wouldn't do this
But it's a one-man show now
And nobody wants to bring ji any information because they don't know how he'll react
He's shot the messenger literally so many times that everything is a surprise to him
Yes, I understand what you mean
I suppose
There's a lot of criticisms around the fact that the vote of a stupid person is worth as much as the vote of a
While educated person in a democracy
But the problem is if you condense all of that
Power down to a single individual the decision of an angry or grumpy
Individual is the same as them on a good day or them if they were less idiotic or somebody else had got to power
So yeah, I suppose it's a
Forcing function that condenses all of these things down to one individual human that is just as fallible as the rest of
Maybe even more fallible human is perfect
Every time okay
But even a minor mistake just cascades through the system and it's a full cult of personality
So, you know, we've got basically people who are zealotously trying to do what they think ji wants them to do
And just one of the more inane ones is seeing teams of people in hazmat gear
disinfecting airport runways
Because they think that's what you have to do for covid
Just that people talk about the americans now in a fact-free zone. That's nothing compared to what's going on in the chinese system
Okay, so what do you think uh for most of the people that are listening to this uk us some in australia
What is life going to be like? What is the quality of life going to be like over the next 10 to 20 years?
What can people expect?
Well, the next five years are going to be rough. We basically in the west need to at least double the size of our industrial plant
Um, let me correct that in the west minus germany
Germany is its own special case
Everyone else has largely hollowed out their manufacturing as part of globalization
We focus on the really high end stuff in the design
But a lot of the middle and the lower stuff is now done in other countries. That's got to change
If you are part of a network where you can access lower skilled labor like the americans are with the mexicans
Great, if you're not you either need to attach yourself to another system
Or find some way to go without
Now if you are in that kind of friends and family network of the americans
energy is covered
Food is covered
Investment will be tight but available
And there's a degree of security that you won't have in the rest of the world
So the biggest problem is going to be building out that industrial plant
That means we should expect inflation in the us of maybe nine to 15 percent for the next five or six years
Is that's what it's going to take to get through this?
And if we do succeed at building that industrial plant over that time frame
Then that inflation rate will come down and we'll have supply chains that are shorter
simpler
Cheaper and closer to the end consumer so better all around
So if you're part of that network
And you can get through over that hump it looks pretty good
If you decide to go your own way
Things are going to get a lot tougher
Unless you are one of those regional powers who actually has the geography and demography to make it work
France
After the financial collapse of say the euro might not notice the rest of the world going to hell
Uh, their manufacturing is already in place their energy system is fine. They've got oil just across the Mediterranean
They're going to have subsidiary economies in spain in italy. It's a fairly good setup
That means that cost of living is going to increase that means cost of energy is going to increase quality of life going to go down
I mean, are we going to see civil strife in your opinion? What's going to go on?
I think we'll see a lot of governments collapse
But again, it depends upon where you are
The americans will always complain more than what the problem is worth
Uh, and the fact that we're going through our political transition at the same time we're doing this is, you know
Awkward to say the least
We're going to blame a lot of things on a lot of things that have no direct connection. That's very american
Uh, if you're talking about britain, that's up to you guys
Because like, you know, if you can figure this out and figure out a relationship with the united states or the french
Before the break that would be your best bet
Is that because after the break bargaining power goes through the floor? Yeah, exactly
Now is the time to cut a deal. You've just had a change in government. The ukraine war is hot and heavy
If you were going to have a lead or take the country in a more sustainable direction now is the time
If people want to keep up to date with the stuff that you're doing with the work with
Keeping themselves abreast of all of everything that's happening at the moment. Where should they go?
The website is z e i h a n dot com and if you go to that slash
Newsletter you can sign up for our video logs and newsletters. They're free. They will always be free
Peter, I appreciate you. Thank you. What's happening people
Thank you very much for tuning in if you enjoyed that episode
Then press here for a selection of the best clips from the podcast over the last few weeks
And don't forget to subscribe
peace
You