No scientist who actually wanted to retain any credibility would claim that the correlation between rising CO2 and
Rising temperature at this very tiny piece of time is proof of causation
Correlation is not proof of causation
Patrick Moore welcome the show nice to be with you Chris
What is your background? How did you come to be involved in the environmental discussion?
Well rather checkered I have to admit
I grew up on a floating village on the north end of Vancouver Island with no road to that area
It was a west coast inlet. So we were like
Outlanders there and
Everything was by boat the freight came on a boat once a week
to a village of about a hundred people and
in 1965 when the road came finally a
75-kilometer gravel road from Port Hardy on the other side of the North Island
Vancouver Island is the largest island on the west coast of the Americas from Alaska to Argentina
So it's a 300 mile long Island
and I was born on it and still live on it in a slightly more civilized part now
but I have a home on the beach where I grew up so I'm really lucky that way and
When the road came we thought wow now this place is just gonna explode half the people used the road to get out
so we learned something of human nature that day and
I then ended up being sent to boarding school because the one-room school
I went to till grade 8 only went to grade 8
So I was sent to Vancouver to st. George's school, which is modeled after the English public school and
There I excelled in science and particularly life science
Went to the University of British Columbia in an honors bachelor of science in biology and forestry
Which is the industry I grew up in and it's what we have almost on the entire province is trees and
much of which is in parks and much of which is in places where you're allowed to cut them and make lumber and paper and
So I then discovered the word ecology before it had been in the popular press and
realized it was an obscure branch of science going back to the late 1800s which basically dealt initially with soil forming processes and
When you when you understand soil science you understand that all life
emanates from soil on the land that is not it not in the ocean of course
But it it then led me to realize that ecology was about the interrelationships among all the factors on earth
Especially with relation to life, but life is made of rocks and air and water
So it includes those two and all those factors that come into effect
So it's almost like infinity the number of interrelationships there are and infinity is kind of a spiritual
Concept because none of us can actually fathom it and so as an agnostic in my family
My whole family was not particularly religiously oriented. I suddenly discovered religion in a
Non-religious sense in a way in science I
discovered the wonder of the infinity of
life and the universe and
Realized it was unfathomable at a certain level, but that we could know more about it
By studying it and that's where I got my beginnings and then I learned about while doing my PhD
I learned about this little group that was beginning to meet in the basement of the Unitarian Church in Vancouver
to plan a protest voyage against US hydrogen bomb testing in
Alaska taking on the world's most powerful organization at that time
a bunch of hippies and
But we were actually all professionals of one sort or another
It just that of course we looked like hippies because it was the hippie era in the early 70s and we sailed on that boat
12 of us and
John Cormack and his 12 disciples as we called ourselves and
We caused quite a ruckus and got on Walter Cronkite's evening news in the United States and
Help change the course of nuclear weapons
Development it was the cusp of the Cold War when they stopped increasing the number of nuclear weapons
And we stopped those nuclear tests on Amchitka Island in the Aleutians
Then went on to campaign against French atmospheric nuclear testing
France was still detonating hydrogen and atomic bombs in the air in the southern hemisphere in French Polynesia and
The French people didn't even know this was happening because France controlled all the media including Le Mans and we got in
We got this issue in Le Mans for the first time in France and the campaign against that began
domestically as well as internationally and
Oh just
The rest is history. We stopped the killing of 30,000 whales per year in the North Pacific when we turned from the nuclear issue
having one two major victories
And then three four years of campaigning
Against the ocean killing of whales by big factory fleets. It took that long, but we ended that by 1981
Deep Sea whaling was banned in all the oceans of the world by the International Whaling Commission
which is a branch of the UN and
So we lobbied at the UN and we went out on the ocean and got in front of the harpoon. So we had footage of people actually
Trying to save the whale from being killed by a harpoon
that's what made made it and that made us famous and then we started making a lot of money and
Then we hired a lot of people and then we had a payroll to meet and then as
Time went on the left sort of I guess realized that there was money and power in this new
Environmental movement that we had helped create along with many other groups, but we were the only ones at one point
We're talking about Greenpeace
Specifically is the movement here at what point did it become Greenpeace?
It became Greenpeace right at the beginning at the hydrogen test when you went up to Alaska
Yes, when when one of the people in the church basement meetings said as we were breaking up the meeting someone said see you later
and said peace because peace then meant sort of see you later and
Someone's he said why don't we make it a Greenpeace?
And so it started there. So we named our boat the Greenpeace
We nicknamed our boat that we went to it was named the Phyllis Cormack after the captain's wife
but we put a big sign saying Greenpeace on the front of it on the cabin and
By the middle of next well early next year the same
1972 we changed our name from what it had been that don't make a wave committee to the Greenpeace foundation
That's much better. That's much better as it goes. Yes
Foundation wasn't because we were wealthy like foundations are it was because of the Asimov trilogy
About the small group of people on the opposite side. What star what Star Wars is fashioned after
that that took on the Empire and
We were taking on the Empire indeed and succeeded. What about your exit?
My exit was unfortunate, but it was caused by the fact
That as we became more well-known and powerful and political
The we were basically hijacked by the left in the end who were more clever at politics than we were
as that was their game and
So I ended up being the only
Director of Greenpeace International during the last six years from
79 when we created Greenpeace International, and I was instrumental in the negotiations that brought that about
And until 86 when I left I
Was the only director with any formal science education and we were now dealing with toxic waste and issues of chemistry and
You don't need to be a PhD
Marine biologist to know to save the whales or you don't need to be a nuclear physicist to want to stop hydrogen bombs
But if you're going to get into the issue of toxicology and now where they're calling plastic toxic, right?
And calling carbon dioxide toxic
Which is complete BS?
you've got to know some chemistry and you've got to understand toxicology and
Because toxicology is not just about something being poisonous
It's about how much of it does it take to be poisonous which is known as the poison is in the dose
Which is basically the first rule of toxicology such like do no harm is in medicine
The poison is in the dose is and like for example table salt is one of the best examples
It is an essential nutrient sodium chloride right with chlorine in it is an essential nutrient you die without it
That's why Gandhi made salt at the sea so they didn't have to pay a tax on something that was essential for life
well at a certain point it
Gets to be too much and if you actually ingest four or five tablespoons of
Table salt all at once
You're likely to die because it becomes toxic at those higher levels and you also have you at four or five tablespoons
Sitting on the counter isn't harmful to you
It's only harmful if you're exposed to it
So there's a lot of issues in toxicology
That just got ignored in the whole thing and then suddenly I find my other five directors in Greenpeace
Agreeing that we should have a campaign to ban chlorine worldwide that would be our next big campaign and
It was based on the fact that chlorine was a constituent of dioxins DDT and
Other chlorinated hydrocarbons
Chlorinated hydrocarbons are a very common group of
Molecules because carbon is the basis of life and chlorine is essential as in sodium chloride salt
So there's lots of chlorinated hydrocarbons around and not all of them are toxic
At at at low levels and some of them are
But banning chlorine specifically
Was such a stupid idea
Seeing as though it is the most important element for public health adding it to drinking water
Swimming pools spas as we use bromine also these days
There was a time when iodine which is another one of the halogens in that group along with chlorine
Was the most important thing in your in your medicine cabinet as it was when I was a child if you got a cut
You put iodine on it to stop infection
And so there's that reason for chlorine the other reason is that 85% of our pharmaceuticals are made with chlorine chemistry and
25% of them actually have chlorine in them if you look at the ingredients in your cold or flu medicines
Just for an example, you'll see a little cl after a lot of them. That's chlorine
so at a purely
Scientific perspective, I couldn't stay in a group that was going to launch a campaign to ban chlorine worldwide
But that was just the sharp end of the stick for some years
After a long evolution 15 years for me from the beginning of being involved in the beginning of the environmental movement or the modern environmental movement
We actually had a fairly strong humanitarian orientation in the early years
we were trying to save civilization from all out nuclear war and
So that must means you care about people as
Well as the environment which was the green part of Greenpeace
But the peace part of Greenpeace was to end nuclear war or the threat of nuclear war and we did a pretty good job of helping with that and
But by the time I had to leave the environmental movement
Now controlled largely by the political left
Had basically changed the tune to humans are the enemies of the earth
Humans are the enemies of nature as if we are the only bad or evil species on the planet
And everything else is either benign or good or whatever you want to say, but they're not evil
Right just so this is original sin reinvented for environmentalism as it is in
extreme Christianity and I suppose other religions
I don't know much about other ones, but I do know that in Christianity
There's a wing of it that considers humans to be born with evil in them
Not that they don't have some good in them, but I don't believe that one iota
I just think we're it's not even an irrelevant thing to discuss. Why do you think that transition happened?
From it being about peace to this Alex Epstein calls it human racism
Yes, it's the same reason why Americans now think America is evil even though they are Americans
I it's self loathing is another way of expressing it
It is a deeply
Destructive mental condition to believe that you are evil even when you're good and
So I what it is. So why is it?
Why did it happen fear of death? I think is at the root of it
That's why doomsday
Predictions are made throughout history is because people believe that when they die the world will end
Because they think they're so bloody important or something
I don't know what it is
But it is it is the fear of owns one own one's own death projected on the universe or or on the world
End times apocalypse they keep saying it's going to happen
They've been saying it for 10,000 years or more this little guy standing on a street corner with a sign saying the end is near
Well, they used to say the end is nigh
But I think that's an English term that nobody knows what it means anymore
But the end is near right and that's what aOC is saying and that's what
Greta is saying and that's what the ice IPCC is basically saying. That's what the World Economic Forum is saying
That's what Biden is saying. They're all saying the end is near
Because of climate change now now it used to be because of the devil or witches or something like that
But now it's because of climate change that the end is near and I'm sure it's a projection of one's own fear of death
One of the reasons I'm sure of that is that I don't think that way and I'm not afraid of my own death
I have absolutely no fear of it because there's one thing that you must do in life is not to worry about things
You can't do anything about because then you'd be worrying about way too many things and you'd never get anything done
and so I only worry about things that I can do something about and
As as far as I can see I can't do anything about the fact that I have a
Short life on this earth short meaning under a hundred years or so
it definitely does feel like
there's a narrative at the moment of
human racism of
the
descriptions of humanity being a scourge on the earth people are made to feel guilty about the cars that they drive or the flights that they take or
You know, you have Greta Thumberg going back from conferences on a
Rowing boat and it's taken a six months to get back across the Atlantic. I
Don't know I
Think I'm unconvinced that
all of this
Can be attributed to
The denial of death, you know, Ernest Becker might agree
But I'm not sure that all of it could be but I don't know where else it could come from
It's definitely a you know fear is a very good control mechanism for people. So there are other
There are other powers at play there
However, I don't understand why people would take it and imbibe it themselves and then start to push it back out
Because if it's something that is that makes you feel uncomfortable
I even most people tend to shy away from it, but it really does feel like
People have become their own torturers with this, you know
It's almost
Part for the course that humans are damaging the earth that we're causing harm and that we shouldn't be here
You said it and I I too
Don't know if I have the whole picture, but I think that's part of it now fear and guilt
You see those are the two that when they're combined
Are so powerful in controlling people the way I put it is you're driving your SUV down the road
You're afraid that you were killing your grandchildren
By putting out the toxic co2, which is actually the main food for all life on earth why they can't get that
I don't know but it is it is a fact and it is not toxic
Etc. But there is a fear and then that makes you feel guilty because you're killing your grandchildren
right so fear and guilt that's why I call the chapter in my book climate of fear and guilt and
Michael Crichton used the word fear in his book on climate change as well. I
Forget the whole title, but the word fear climate of might have been climate of fear, but
the the the fear
That is put into people about the end times, you know
And if people would just think straight they would realize that people have been predicting the end times since practically the beginning of time
And they have never once been right
They are batten zero on
End times right so why should we believe the new end times story?
Well because this one's backed up by science and it's got all of these people around the world
They all agree with each other. There's research. There's studies that have been done and you have 80% of scientists say that climate change is real
well
This is because lying has become acceptable to a lot of people
bald-faced lying
It the 80% thing or the 97% thing is a lie
It's been shown to be a lie in the they you know
This one study that said it was 97% done by a psychologist from Australia
And not a sign not really a scientist. That's a soft science at best and
He came up with this 97% number when analyzed and this Christopher Moncton was involved in this reanalysis
along with a couple of other really smart people on numbers and
Statistics and it turns out to be 0.3% not 97% who actually in their paper
Declared that humans
Will cause a climate disaster basically
Many of them said humans have a role in climate change
But they didn't say it was going to be a disaster
so
That if you break down what people actually said or even inferred
You will not find that many climate scientists who will outright come out and say this is a climate emergency
The scientists are hiding behind the politicians who fund them
That's where they get all their money. They get their money from politicians through bureaucrats in the deep state in the United States
I don't know what you have as equivalent to the deep state, but having watched Boris rise to fame
I can't fathom what caused that
So it must have been some kind of weird political good hairdo. That's what that's what yeah, right
Let's not talk about that anymore
Is my attitude towards it because I just watched these things somebody came out today and said that polar bears are inbreeding
Right and that's because there's not enough ice for them to find each other anymore. Is that same? Oh
Yeah, right
That's so weird is that true that it well first what is inbreeding, right?
Is it beyond cousins or second cousins anything closer than that genetically? That's our definition of it
Yes, but in plant breeding for example and animal breeding in breeding is commonly used in
In order to maintain characteristics that are desirable
But I've seen I've seen tigers that have got down syndrome from too tight inbreeding
Yes, but inbreeding is absolutely necessary like you're not going to start breeding with snails
right so
How far out does it go?
Well, it needs to be within your own species, but not within your own hereditary genetic pool
Yeah, but it should it should always be someone of another race, right because that's the most outbreeding you can get
Right, it should never be anybody in your own race because that's inbreeding
You see inbreeding and outbreeding are flexible terms in that sense
There's extreme inbreeding
And there's extreme outbreeding
right
If you outbreed you water down
The genetics if you inbreed you concentrate them
A combination of those two things is always essential in species evolution
and
So therefore they're just using the word inbreeding as a political term rather than a scientific term
There because inbreeding is bad period
Right
That's that's how they're getting away with that and the idea that they aren't finding enough of each other
The the population of polar bears has grown by four or five times since the treaty
Do you know about the treaty on polar bears?
So you do but nobody else does because they never mention it. They never mentioned that in 1973 on the advice of wildlife biologists
Because too many people were now able to go to the Arctic in planes and hire Inuit guides and get polar bear rugs
There were too many people doing that it was had become too easy and rich people were able to easily do that
So the polar bear population was declining due to over hunting
So the all the nations with polar bears signed a treaty international treaty to and the unrestricted hunting of polar bears
In other words, there had been no restrictions
On killing polar bears up till then because there didn't seem to need to be any
Because there was lots of polar bears and hardly anybody ever went up there and killed one
Besides which they're really mean and horrible and they'll kill you if you don't watch out
But with a high powered rifle the odds are turned in your favor
So they signed that treaty and since then the polar bear population has grown from somewhere between six to 10 000
to somewhere between 30 and 50 000
those are the
accepted figures by all the people involved in this except for
Uh fakers, which are not scientists, right? They're political activists
Give me your thoughts on extinction rebellion
They're really really stupid and bad
Elaborate on your thoughts about extinction rebellion
Well, because you you come from right you come from greenpeace co-founder of greenpeace and extinction rebellion
There there seems to be people could see some sort of lineage or progression or connection, you know, it's an environmentalist movement
No, there's no lineage or progression. We didn't dress up like cult
teams of a cult movement like all dressed in
Really stupid looking red uniforms that are somewhere but across between the inquisition
and uh a cartoon uh
And spraying blood on buildings and this sort of thing actually
I signed off when people started chaining themselves to other people's stuff
Peace peacefulness pacifism
Is non-violence, right?
but
It doesn't include inciting other people to violence against you. That is not pacifism
in other words
By you making the first blow or you chaining yourself to someone's tractor who is trying to make a living with it
That is not peaceful
And yet
They they were basically saying that anything short of killing the other person is peaceful
Almost, you know, it it's not peaceful
To interfere with other people's livelihoods in a way that threatens their livelihood. That's not peaceful
But they think that they think that this is a really important and just worthy cause they need to get attention and people aren't looking
So they need to do more
So why don't they go with the Taliban?
That would be good. They then they'd have machine guns and they could kill anybody they wanted and have mass murder
To destroy the human race, you know, that's more or less what they're
Recommending as far as I can see
Uh, so I think they are I think they are evil
There are good people and bad people and people that are sort of in between like actually most people are a little bit good and a little bit bad
But these people are evil
That's what I think of extinction rebellion. What about Greta Thunberg the other one of the other horsemen of the
environmental apocalypse
Yeah, well, it's funny that people didn't notice right away that she is a young girl with pigtails
Because uh, that's what Stalin and Mao
And hitler all used young girls
with pigtails
In their photographs that's all been well documented
um, I don't know what the pigtails has to do with it, but uh
dictators all
Often it seems almost always use children
As as a front to make it look as though
They're nice
I suppose. I'm not sure what they're Danish though. Is there someone someone in Denmark sending her over
Is there some totalitarian leader in Denmark trying to get Greta Thunberg to?
No, the movement is totalitarian right and the movement the movement controls her
Uh, green she she's she's there's all kinds of photographs of her on trains with the head of Greenpeace
Etc. I mean and and of course Al Gore and
The list is endless
And her speeches are written for her obviously
And she doesn't know anything much about climate change or science
So what what is she then she's simply a tool?
Right. She is just a tool nothing more. She is not a wise person
Telling us what we should be doing
She is being used by Hollywood actors and phony politicians like Al Gore
Uh, none of none of whom actually have any science
What scientist is behind Greta Thunberg?
Thunberg I should say
It sounds like you've got a problem with the delivery mechanism, especially for
Extinction Rebellion and I can absolutely agree with you there. I don't think that going and
Hammering and chiseling the front door of banks or trying to erect structures in the middle of London Bridge
I don't think that that's a a fantastic way to get people on side simply from a human psychology perspective
If you want to compel people to be a part of your cause you need to convince them not terrorize them
Terrorize them that being said
Yeah, yeah, but I mean gluing your breasts to the street for example. Has that happened?
Yes gluing gluing
Your breasts what like so lying face down
And and gluing your breasts to the concrete so that you can't be moved so that you're blocking the traffic or whatever
Okay, right
So that that's the kind of thing they do and I agree that it's very sensational and everything
But it has absolutely nothing to do with the issue whatsoever whatever the issue is
I don't even know what their issue is. Is it that humans are should be exterminated?
It seems to be that would be basically their issue
and
So I recommended that a man glue his penis to the top of a of a
subway car
And somebody did a cartoon of it on twitter as a result of my suggestion
Right, so as you can disagree one of the five
Unacceptable words either no no
You can disagree with their methods, but there is an awful lot of
Well-known people who appear to have credentials saying that we are in a climate emergency, which we are aren't we?
No, we are not
in a climate emergency
I don't know people say to me well all you have to do is look outside
To see that it's a climate emergency
I I'm looking outside and I see a beautiful green mountain with a glacier on top of it where I live
And a whole mountain range right next to me and the whole of vancouver island is as healthy as can be
And yet they say it's been stripped mind of all its trees. No, it has not
What do you think they mean when they say climate emergency?
I
Think they mean the end times are coming. It's just another way of saying we're all doomed
Right because if there was an emergency
It means that if you don't do anything about it, you're doomed
We got upgraded right it was climate crisis and then within the last couple of years it is now climate emergency
Precisely, and I can't imagine what more extreme word they could now invent
after they've come from
you know
Crisis to emergency change crisis emergency. Yeah, there isn't you are right. There isn't much left, but there's there's so many
differing
Critiques around what the impact is that humans have had on the planet
So the world getting too hot for instance increases in the temperature. That's something that's happening. Is it not?
The world has been warming ever so slightly since about 1700 when the little ice age
Stopped getting colder and started getting warmer
There have been these thousand year cycles for the last 6,000 years of the interglacial period known as the Holocene
Which we are in now, which is about 12,000 years long
Since we emerged from the last major glaciation which peaked 22,000 years ago
Which was one of 45 major glaciations that have occurred during the place to see an ice age over the last 2.6
million years, which is the first ice age in 250 million years since
The previous ice age
Ended after a hundred million years
From 350 million years ago to 250 million years
There was another ice age the previous one to this one
Since the last 250 million years until recently
Which was 2.5 million years ago
It was warmer than it is now at all times
It is now colder than it has been even in this interglacial period
During this place to see an ice age
Which has gone up and down and up and down and up and down
In cycles of 41,000 years for the first 1.6 million years and in cycles of 100,000 years for the last
1 million years in concert with the two molankovitch cycles
Related to the tilt of the earth changing and the orbit of the earth changing shape
This is caused by the gravitational attraction of jupiter on our earth
And so these people want us to think that the world began in 1850
When we started using fossil fuels
But for 150 years before that it was also warming and during one of those warming spurts because
When the earth warms it just doesn't warm continuously
It goes up and then down and then up and then down and then up and then down but net warming
Net cooling looks like this down and then up down and then up down and then up
There's cycles within cycles within cycles
We understand very few of these cycles
We certainly don't know what causes the onset of an ice age
Such as the one we are in now and we have no idea when it will end
Because actually at the bottom level it is still getting colder
And until we came along
Only 150 years ago
We started restoring a balance to the global carbon cycle
By putting some of the carbon back into the atmosphere that had been taken out by life
And drawn down co2 to the lowest level it has ever been in the history of the planet
Which is 4.6 billion years
So when was the lowest?
22 million years 22,000 years ago
co2 sank to 180 parts per million
Due to the cooling of the glaciation
Causing the oceans to absorb carbon dioxide from the atmosphere
Liquids hold more gas when they're cold and when they're warm
Air holds more humidity
In other words gas
When gaseous forms of what can be liquids
Holds more of it when they're warm like warm air holds more water than cold air does
That's why fogs form when the air cools because it condenses. So it's the exact opposite
water
And in particular holds more gas when it's cold
So when the earth cools
The oceans absorb co2 from the atmosphere and the the total co2
There's nearly 50 times as much co2 in the oceans as there is in the atmosphere today
That wasn't always the case
Because the atmosphere had a lot more co2 in it in the past
Going back 200 million years
It had about 2,000 ppm
Today it's 400 because of our
Increasing it from when we came along it was 280
So you do agree that we as humans have had an impact on the climate
No, just producing co2 doesn't mean you're having an impact on the climate
The primary impact of increased co2 is more plant growth
And that's called the greening of the earth and nasa has verified this with
Maps on the internet and so has csiro in australia, which is the one they're the one that broke it
in in 2014 or I think it was
When they showed a map showing up to 30 increased photosynthesis
Due to increased co2 in the atmosphere. So that is the main known fact
From what has happened as a result of more co2 in the atmosphere
There is zero evidence that the co2 increase in the atmosphere is the cause of rising temperature
None whatsoever because it was already rising as I was about to say during the first 150 years of rising out of 1700
There was a period of over 40 years
Where the temperature increased more and faster than it has done since 1850
Especially since 1950 when we were actually starting to put a significant amount more co2 in the atmosphere post war
And today
It's exponential. There's a wonderful graph. It's in my book which shows
The temperature record in central england
From 16 60 or so when the first first thermometer existed. So this is this is the longest
thermometer record of temperature in the world because they were invented in england
And so that shows a very steady continuous rise in temperature of a little over one degree celsius
in 320 years
It's not a big deal
Certainly compared to previous like they they keep saying it's never gone this fast. It's never risen this fast
That is a lie. It has risen this fast many times in the even recent past
Especially from about 1690 to about 1730
It rose faster and longer than it ever has done since
It's all in the record. Now, they'll say, oh, that's just a local measurement. Well, all measurements are local measurements
But not if you aggregate them across multiple, right? No, that's called the climate
If you aggregate them across global except global is really badly skewed by there being by far the most
Measuring centers in north america and europe and hardly any in many other places, especially africa. So
It even that is skewed badly in terms of localism, but never mind that
The fact of the matter is is climate is a 30 year average of each weather
Event, right?
Whether it's hurricanes or tornadoes tornadoes are almost non-existent in the united states this year compared to previous years
For some reason the conditions just didn't happen
Because united states has 90 of the world's tornadoes
There's a reason for that. It's geographic. It's because from the arctic to the gulf of mexico
There are no mountains in the way because that was an inland sea
The prairies in other words of the united states
Were end of canada that was that was the sea bottom at one point
And so it's a straight shot for arctic air to come all the way down to the gulf of mexico and for hot
Gulf of mexico air to come all the way up and they combine and boom
And that's how hurricanes are formed too is the convergence of cold and warm air masses and that's why when the earth warms
The tropics
hardly changes when the earth warms the warming is is
What's the not inadvertently is greater anyways the warming is always greater towards the poles when the earth warms
It wasn't that long ago when all the arctic islands of canada were covered in forest
And there was giant camels roaming there five million years ago. That's not very long ago
That that's five million years is like an eternity to these people. They don't even know what it means
right, so if we have
Most of the effects of global warming or of any warming that occurs at the poles
Presumably that is going to increase the melting of those ice caps. Is there a concern whether it is
man-made or otherwise cyclical in nature or simply a trend over time
Should we be concerned about increased warming rising sea levels?
We have a lot of coastal cities. We have people who live there who may not be able to move very easily
Is that a danger
People who can't move very easily. Do you have some of those are the in wheelchairs or what?
You have people who may I say I say two things about this
number one
You won't have to run
Right, this is happening very very slowly and always will happen very very slowly. It doesn't happen quickly
number two hire the dutch
Right 25 of holland is below sea level
And they're growing most of their food there
On this land that is below sea level. It is not difficult to build dykes
around pieces of land
Especially if the land is steep
Sorry, especially if the land is flat
You can save a lot of land by building a foot of dyke or two
If the land is steep
You have to decide whether it's worth it or not
To build a wall because you're only going to lose a small amount of land if it's coming steep out of the water
So those are the basic situations the sea level has always been rising and falling
We should not weep because we happen to be victims to this
eternal factor in the earth's
climate
and sea level
Right the earth sea level has been 40 meters higher than it is today in the past and it's been
100 meters lower
So it goes up and down
But if you look at the islands at the equator in indonesia, which are made of limestone from ancient coral reefs
They're all undercut sometimes up to 12 feet
Undercut they've got this angle undercut. They look like mushrooms, right?
You may have seen them in photographs. Vietnam has them too
They're all through that part of the world where the islands are made of limestone, which is more erodible than granite by waves
now
If if the sea was constantly rising for the last 10 000 years or whatever
Because it stopped rising pretty much around 7 000 years ago when the glaciers melted coming out of the last glaciation
The most recent glaciation. It's not necessarily the final one
As people think the last glaciation means the final glaciation. It just means the more recent
Yes, the most recent one of 45 that have occurred in the Pleistocene
So we have no guarantee that anything is going to change
Another one should be here in 80 000 years according to the last million years of cycles all which is
Thoroughly documented by ice cores from Antarctica
So this sea level rise and up and down has been happening forever
And people in the last 10 000 years have adjusted to it
It's not going to like they're they're they're making it seem as though it will be a flood
Like an inundation, right?
That's the climate emergency
Scenario that all of a sudden our houses will be under water
It's not going to work that way
And that's why Obama is perfectly happy to buy a 14 million dollar house right on the ocean
in Cape Cod
Because he also knows this
That he's safe there
there's some inland
harbors in the uk
isn't there and there's some
Ruins of of roman
Shipping places that are actually miles inland from when the sea level was higher
Precisely and that was 2 000 years ago when the romans built docks on all across the south of britain
And uh lewis
You know where lewis is no
Well, it's one of those castle towns
On a river that flows south
It's way inland
It was on the sea
Also, there's a place in france
Called something sir lemare
it's like
Many many kilometers from the sea today. It used to be a harbor
so it appears as though
The sea level is lower today
And that would be worldwide
than it was 2 000 years ago
and
That is because the world was warmer 2000 years ago during the roman warm period
That's why they have a name for it
Because it was the roman warm period and in the roman warm period 2000 years ago
It was warmer than it is today
In addition during the medieval warm period 1000 years ago
Interestingly a thousand years a thousand years a thousand years. This has been the trend
There was also a thing called the minoan warm period before the roman warm period
The earth has been cooling for 6 000 years net cooling
We are in a slight upward tick now. It's just an upward tick in
A downward movement. Do you think that we've got further to go down?
Yes, 80 000 years further
The malankovitch cycle so 100 000 years so you think that
realistically
We are seeing this upward tick
What has happened is it has coincided with an increase of releasing carbon dioxide
Which has led some scientists to associate the increasing temperature with the increase in carbon dioxide
Which justifies blaming it on humans, but that if you were to roll it forward by another
500 years
You are going to see the crest of that thousand year cycle actually
diminish
And we're going to start to cool again and then cool again to a lower level
Than we would have seen previously at the previous low
You got it
If things continue on the same pattern they have for the last 6000 years
Which is typical of an interglacial period through the Antarctic ice cores
We have a really good picture of the last 800 000 years and now they're starting to go back more than a million years
Into the times when there was a 41 000 year cycle
Right now we only have really good information for the 100 000 year cycles
Especially going back through four of them. They all have names. The previous one was the emion
I'm forgetting the other two right now, but they have names on a chart
And they were a hundred thousand years apart
In quite perfect synchronization
We know the co2 levels and the temperature
At the Antarctic during those cycles because we can measure
proxy measurements of isotopes and actually the co2 is measured directly from bubbles in the ice
down
400 000 years in ice
And so we've got that and we know
that the interglacial periods
come out in
10 000 years
Whereas and then there's a 10 000 year these these are not all equal exactly right, but approximately
10 000 year interglacial period
Where the temperature remains higher for a period of time and then a gradual 80 000 year
Decline into the next major glaciation
So it appears as though and the and the interglacial periods are virtually always warmer at the very beginning
Of them in other words as you come out
Of the previous
glaciation
It goes up
To what we call the Holocene climatic optimum
Meaning it was warmer then
For the first 6 000 years
Of the Holocene interglacial period and since then it has been cooling. This is well documented the graphs are in my book
They're from Iceland and Antarctic ice cores
And they're also from marine sediments marine sediments can take you back half a billion years
Because stuff has been falling on the bottom of the sea from all the life in the ocean
And the stuff and the sediments flowing into the ocean
In addition so the life that dies falls to the bottom and is embedded in the sediments that come from the land
And that record is in layers and we can date all of that with radioactive techniques
So
We've got that
What do people mean when they say that we've got 50 harvests left?
Is that like 50 years of crops apparently yeah, I think so
I don't know why they wouldn't just say 50 years of crops as opposed to 50 harvests because
That's just confused me but yeah, let's call it 50 years of crops left. What do they mean? Is that
Something to do with soil microbiome stuff or biome stuff and virum stuff
No, it's it's simply a cult doomsday prediction
Is what it is
They have absolutely no reason to say that
Topsoil degradation none of this
Oh, yeah topsoil degradation. It's happening everywhere. No, we're our farming methods are
So improved now that soil conservation is so improved now
That we're not losing soil like they say we are and yes soil gets washed into the sea by rivers, right?
New soil is created. It's not as if soil creation has ended
And people think that trees use dirt to make themselves
And therefore if you take the trees away over and over and over again by harvesting them
The soil will eventually go away, right? No, the soil is made by the bloody trees
That's how soil gets there if there was no trees that would be rocks there no soil
Soil doesn't just happen by itself
It happens because of the leaves falling and the branches falling on the ground and decaying
And some of it turns into soil
soil forming processes was the beginning of ecology in the steps in the ukraine
Studying the grasslands of the ukraine, which are very productive deep churnizem soils have been created by grass
Doesn't it's not just trees that make dirt. It's all plants
make dirt and
When you look at a tree and you see this huge say at a big mature tree you see this huge solid thing
It's hard to believe that it's 99% made from air and water
Right the carbon and the hydrogen and the oxygen in that tree, which is over 99% of that tree's biomass
Came from carbon dioxide and H2O water
That's what made it trees are basically carbohydrates. So are we except for our bones
And so
The knowledge of of life is so poor
Science has progressed so far and yet the average person's knowledge of science has degraded
Because they're being told all these lies
That carbon dioxide is poison when in fact it is the primary food for all life
And there isn't enough of it right now
And there certainly wasn't enough of it when we first started putting some back
It's important to note that all the carbon that we are releasing was made by life
In the form of fossil fuels and much more importantly in the form of carbonaceous rocks
Now have you heard of carbonaceous rocks? I have not of course you have it's called limestone
Yes, and limestone is what we make cement with
And limestone is calcium carbonate
It is a carbonaceous rock
The carbon in limestone came from co2 in the ocean
And the co2 in the ocean came from the air
So as
The shelled creatures evolved what we call the marine calcifying species
All life in the sea was microscopic
Invisible and unicellular
Until about 600 570 600 million years ago
Then the Cambrian explosion occurred
Which was the advent of multicellular life in the sea
And large creatures this big
Came into being if you read
Stephen
ghouls
Book a wonderful life. You will see the history
Of early life as discovered through the Burgess Shale
Which is a fossil deposit in the rocky mountains at Yoho national park in canada the chinese have a parallel one
Where soft bodied organisms were preserved
That because most fossils are bones or shells
Because they were hard parts
And they could be preserved more easily soft parts would normally decay
But because of mudslides which immediately ended oxygen exposure
Ancient creatures that were only soft like jellyfish
Were preserved as fossils
So there's a record of these species evolution in the early times of the Cambrian
At a certain point many different species somehow from a common thread
Developed the ability to combine calcium and carbon dioxide
calcium like sodium and
potassium is in the salts in the sea
And
Combined calcium with carbon dioxide to make calcium carbonate
to form shells
Armor plating around their soft bodies like oysters and mussels and crabs and barnacles and shrimp
And tiny coccolithophores, which are a plant phytoplankton and a little bit larger for eminifera, which are about
They're an animal they're about the size of a very tiny grain of sand
And they are all marine calcifying species
coral reefs are actually
The predominant one which is about 50 of all the calcification going on in the world and was much more before
When coral reefs were much more widely spread when the earth was warmer. They've been reduced to basically
Small places where the ocean is still warm enough
For the high biodiversity of corals the particularly indonesian coral triangle
and so
today
We have a situation where these coral species and other calcifying species are still
Using the carbon dioxide out of the ocean and it's raining down on the bottom
As dead shells right as shells from dead creatures and that has built up and formed all of the
All of the limestone in the world over the years and that's where most of the carbon dioxide has gone
90 approximately only about 10 of it has gone into fossil fuels
Now the fossil fuels are also the result of forest being buried and turned into coal
Of species sinking to the bottom the the soft parts of species turning into oil and gas
In and now we find them on the land in places like texas, which was once a sea bottom
and and the fracking
Deposits all were at one time a sea bottom
Whereas the coal deposits were a terrestrial environment where forests
But all of the fossil fuels were made with photosynthesis. They were all created by solar energy
They were all created by carbon dioxide being drawn out of the atmosphere and locked away
For hundreds of millions of years where the plants on the land and in the sea could no longer use it because it was gone
Into these locked up sediments. They call it sequestration
Or sequestered carbon it is out of the cycle
That's why co2 came down to such a low level
At the last glaciation when the oceans cooled and pulled it out of the atmosphere to 180
Which is 30 parts per million above the death of plants
Plants don't just need co2. Just like us
They need a certain level of co2 just like we need a certain level of oxygen
If you have an an atmosphere with 5% oxygen you die
Actually, you die at 10% oxygen
I think it's even higher than that whereas oxygen is around 20% in the atmosphere
But you go up to the top amount Everest
And you've got to be a sherpa who's been doing it for their whole life before you can breathe up there
And successfully live
So that these are true true isms about life
That they need a certain level of their essential nutrients and carbon dioxide being the key
Essential nutrient for all plants
They need it at one one third one fifty and they start to die
And it is believed that during some of the last major glaciations because of ash layers that are associated
With the peak of those glaciations that high altitude plants did all die and burn
Because they were dried out
And that would be because when you run when you the higher you go the thinner the air gets
So even though co2 is still at the same parts per million
Compared to the other gases. It's more dispersed
And therefore more difficult for plants to obtain that
Everything i'm saying is thoroughly documented on the internet
The and the most important point is that no scientist
Who actually wanted to retain any credibility?
Would claim that the correlation between rising co2 and rising temperature at this very tiny piece of time
Is proof of causation
Right correlation is not proof of causation
Correlation just means two things are going in the same direction
And very often the reason they are is because of a third common factor and let me give you an example
The relationship between ice cream consumption and shark attacks
They are perfectly correlated
When ice cream consumption goes up shark attacks go up ice cream consumption goes down
Shark attacks go down. It's a perfect annual cycle
Do ice cream consumptions cause shark attacks? No. Do shark attacks cause ice cream consumption? No
This is a correlation which is not an example of causation because temperature
A third factor is the cause of both of them going in the same cycle
When the temperature gets warm people go to the beach
Eat an ice cream and go swimming and some of them get attacked by a shark
In the winter neither happens
So this is correlation is far more common than causation and there's a a website called
Something correlations spurious correlations. Yeah, that one. It's very very good
Yeah, yeah, yeah, like Nicholas Cage
Correlated with the number of people that die by being caught up in their bedding every year
There's a statistically significant. All right, so what's the third? What do you think is the third?
Factor in that case. Is there something that there doesn't have to be one? Yep
There doesn't have to it's just that they're both right
There could be a a separate factor causing temperature to change and a separate factor
Causing co2 to change and the fact that they're both going up at this time
But they're not going up in sync
If you look at there's one graph in in my book that shows that in this interglacial period
We came before humans started emitting we came to a point where co2 was at 280
And temperature was at a certain point. I don't know what exact Celsius it was
And then suddenly co2 just shoots up off the chart if you put it in a hundred thousand years graph
this little bit of time right now
150 years and really only the last 60 or 70 where it's been substantial 60 years of
Radical increase in co2. I won't
You know say that's wrong. It is a radical increase. We don't need to do it this quickly
And that is why in my book
I make it very clear that reducing fossil fuel consumption would be an excellent strategy
If you had something reliable cost effective to replace it with
Right and that is nuclear energy
With nuclear energy we could easily take out half the fossil fuels being used today
Not because of climate change, but because they're precious and should be conserved because they're
Non-renewable they don't they're not being made as quickly as we're using them by orders of magnitude
Right, so we should be conserving fossil fuels for the essential things like flying airplanes
It's not easy to fly an airplane with anything else
Besides a liquid fuel and liquid fuels are hard to come by as our gaseous ones like methane natural gas
so
electricity
Is mostly being made by fossil fuels today not just in china
It's only in france that more than 50 of the electricity is being made by nuclear energy
And they they diss france for this and they hold up germany as a shining example of green
When in fact germany is emitting nearly two times the co2 per capita of france
And their only reason france is emitting less co2 is because of nuclear energy
Why is the world so averse to nuclear energy?
Because they're idiots
And they're they're brainwashed and whatever else, right? I have nothing but
Contempt for people who just
Reject nuclear energy when almost no one has ever been killed by it except chernobyl
Which was a stupid reactor design that the russians made
From their plutonium production reactors to make nuclear weapons. They just cookie-cuttered the same
cheap reactor all across
The former soviet union all of which have been shut down in any of the former satellites
They still have 10 running eight or 10 running in
In russia, but they have modified them so that can't happen again
They should have done that in the first place because they had a negative void coefficient or a positive void coefficient
I never get them right, but one is good and the other is bad
and
Their reactor was a design that could theoretically
Go critical in other words
Become a nuclear bomb
And that a slow one
That was a slow nuclear bomb that explosion
They happened faster in real nuclear bombs
And do more damage than that one did but it blew a 2000 ton lid off itself a concrete lid and then burned because they had a huge
Carbon moderator in there. That was 2000 tons or something
To I mean there's big numbers involved in Chernobyl
And that burnt for 10 days while firefighters tried to put it out spewing
More and more radiation into the atmosphere the whole time
Whereas Three Mile Island wasn't even worth talking about
It was a bad accident to cord a core meltdown, but it didn't cause any damage to anything or any one
And no one died in Fukushima from radiation and no one will because no one received a sufficient dose to cause any harm
And this is confirmed by the radioactive effects research foundation in Hiroshima and Nagasaki
Formed after the second world war by macArthur and the japanese to study the life history
Of people who were exposed to the radiation and survived aren't there some tuna or some fish in the sea
Who are showing higher levels of radiation and ten eyes to yes ten eyes imagine that
No, there are not
there's higher levels means
Infantesimal higher levels if that's what they mean
They did have a ban on fishing in the region because a lot of liquid was going into the water that was contaminated as they say
Had radioactive substances in it. There are radioactive substances in you and me
Potassium 40 in particular if you eat a banana
Which is radioactive we have radiation stuff wasn't from a banana was it that was from something much more dangerous
Well, what do you mean what was more they nuclear reactors are not inherently dangerous they are if you eat them
Yeah, but we we we don't eat them and nobody ate anything from Fukushima because they stopped
Taking crops from the land nearby
I mean they took the Fukushima was one of the stupidest accidents that ever occurred in the world and the japanese are so insular
In their culture that they did not take the the lessons that were learned
From other accidents that occurred
They just didn't and the the difference in culture can be explained this way in the united states or britain
When a reactor has a problem
The operator phones the prime minister and tells him what the problem is and what he's doing to try to fix it
In japan the operator phones the president asks the president what he should do
Right because he's the president
And he doesn't know what the heck to do so those three explosions that happened one day after another i think
Approximately at Fukushima could all have easily been prevented even after the meltdowns occurred
Because they were hydrogen explosions people think those were explosions in the reactor
They weren't they were explosions of hydrogen gas that was not released as it should have been to prevent it from becoming concentrated at eight percent
hydrogen almost spontaneously
Ignites with any spark and causes a huge explosion
So and then they evacuated
All the people even though they were not subject to sufficient radiation to require evacuation and over 2000 people died from the evacuation
Because they evacuated five intensive care wards into gymnasiums in other communities where they did not have the facilities to keep them alive
So that that's the kind of overreaction
That happened to in Fukushima, which was a bad accident
It was a huge industrial accident that it did not cause death what caused death of almost 20 000 people was the tsunami
And I saw on cnn
A headline written across the screen during the Fukushima disaster
Which said nuclear crisis deepens
As bodies wash ashore
That's what it said
And that was to me the beginning of fake news all the way when they started showing
smog and calling it carbon dioxide basically
And showing backlit
chimneys of factories with black
smoke coming out of them supposedly but no it was water vapor and that's what water vapor looks like when you backlight it
so the
And you know and the same with the inbreeding polar bears
I mean they are just making up one story after another now and floating it in the media
And it all comes back to the fact that the politicians
Are funding the scientists to give them what they want, which is something that they can instill fear
And guilt into the population about in order to have power
And then the media and the activists are the bullhorn right the megaphone
That puts that into just a giant global story and nothing else matters
The truth doesn't matter one bit anymore in this discussion
What about the people that say we're seeing the beginning of the next big extinction event?
It's so stupid
We're not seeing the beginning of the next big extinction event
Okay, if a big extinction event was happening and it was being documented
I could get it but read the chapter in my book on extinction where I appeared before
a committee of the u.s. House of Congress
With three people there claiming to be united nation scientists
Saying that yes
We only know of 1.7 plus million species which have been identified named photographed written up, etc
But there are very likely 8.7 million species
That's what they said
There's probably 8.7 million species and this is our best estimate
Where did they get that estimate?
In air there's no way you can turn 1.1.7 into 8.7
Without having any actual observation of any real thing
So they were saying there's about 7 million
Unreal species that we don't know about and then they say and a million of those will go extinct in the next few decades
Right, how many of the how many of the observed creatures?
Have they seen go extinct?
An ever decreasing number as humans in around 1920 when the passenger pigeon became extinct
suddenly
The general population took an interest in the issue of extinction
Prior to that which wasn't very long ago 100 years
Nobody cared about extinction. They thought it was a normal thing except a few naturalists who
Bemoaned the extinction of the dodo bird or other species that went extinct as a result of human activity
And most people don't realize that the the main cause
Of species extinction is not hunting
Right it it is actually agriculture
And the changing of habitats so that is why most
Species recovery programs are based on habitat and making sure that there's a place for these species to exist
That's key
but we have not like overrun 90 percent of the world's habitat and much of the
Area that we are using especially for forestry
Is perfectly suitable for most of the species that always lived in the forests
agriculture is different
Agriculture creates a monoculture on purpose and that's pretty hard to get away from
People who preach that you should have 17 different species of plants growing on the same plot of land
I'd like to see them do it successfully. It's not possible
So they the farmer wants to get rid of every insect every animal
You know everything other than every other plant all other all other plants are weeds
in this case
And so agriculture is is where you have to really
Look at what you're doing in the landscape and make sure that in that landscape and it usually happens naturally if you fly across the
Whole agricultural area of the united states. You see lots of forest
Burst among the agricultural land because and and in europe too
I mean most people don't realize that
200 years ago 250 years ago less than 10 percent of europe remained forested
Because the trees were being used for everything to do with fuel
They were being used to heat all the buildings to to smelt all the iron and copper to do the glass works
And steam engines everything was fueled by wood and all the building of everything
So forests started to disappear in central europe initially and then spreading out over the whole of europe
The first time in the history of humans where forests
Were disappearing if we were cutting them faster than they were growing back
That's why agriculture was invented 10 000 years ago and forestry wasn't invented until about 1750
In central europe because they realized they had to start planting some trees
And then silviculture otherwise known as
As as forestry scientific forestry came into being and now there's 43 forest cover in europe
Well speaking of trees. I thought I thought the amazon rainforest was wrecked
10 percent of it has been modified
That's quite a lot that could be quite a bit. It's a fair big forest, isn't it?
It's a huge forest and it's not in any way endangered
The the problem with the you know my book is titled fake invisible catastrophes and threats of doom for a reason
I put the word invisible in there
Because to most people the amazon is invisible they show you a picture of a fire that takes up the whole screen
Right, it might be about 10 feet
Of the you know of the amazon which is almost as big as the continental united states brazil itself
Is almost as big as the continental united states and amazon is a huge part of brazil
And there are parts of the amazon
That have been developed
But most of it is intact
And even where it's been developed it is only small areas if you just look at a satellite photograph of it
You can see it. I've flown over it in an airplane at
Fairly low elevation and you go for five hours and you hardly see any people
It's called a human desert by people but even
You know the the leader of brazil now is under attack over the amazon
from the left
And one of the reasons you can get away with that is almost no one in brazil has ever been to the amazon even though it's in their own country
People don't go there. What would you do there?
It's got manouse, which is basically a manufacturing hub for electronics. So it's a sort of a
Tax-free zone of some kind
You've got bay lamb at the mouth of the river, which is i've been to that city. It's not very interesting
It's just a city at the mouth of the amazon and there's not much else to do there
You can go on a boat up and down the river
Then you see all you see is trees the whole way and the amazon
Is 300 miles wide during the flood period. It will never have a bridge over it
It doesn't have a road anymore
Because the road the plants grew up through the pavement and destroyed the road within 10 years when they did build one to manouse
And i'm going to guess that if we continue to increase the concentration of carbon dioxide that's just going to happen quicker
Yes, the amazon is is growing faster, but interestingly it's the drier places that benefit most from increased co2
because
Increase co2 has two effects one more co2 for growth
like
I'll give you the second one in a minute
But first i digress to say that i used to laugh at people who said their plants grew better when they talked to them
As if plants have ears and can hear you and are empathetic or whatever
And i saw i sort of chuckled at that
Then i realized that when you're talking to your plants you're breathing 40 000 parts per million co2 on them
That's our breath
Is 100 times the level it is in the air
So you're basically breathing super concentrated fertilizer onto your plants when you're talking to them
And they do grow better because of that because they would like to have more co2 than exists in the natural world today
The second thing that increased co2 does is it makes most plants more efficient with water
Because now it's easier for them to get the carbon dioxide they need because it's more concentrated in the atmosphere
And therefore they don't need to make as many holes in the bottom of their leaves. They're called stomata
It's where they take in the air with the co2 in it, but it's also where they lose water through transpiration
So the fewer of those holes there are the less water they lose
Therefore the more efficient they become with water and gives them ability to survive in places that have less water than they could before
That's why trees are marching out onto grasslands in many parts of the world the southwest of the us for example and australia
the very eastern part
of
Sorry the very western part of australia western australia as it's known
Is the driest part of australia the nalabar desert is there too
Which doesn't have much of anything growing on it because it's so dry
But in the in the west like around perth and down to albany
The the trees are growing much faster now and so are the crops because
You know if if you're a farmer
Today and you are giving your plants all the water and all the fertilizer they need the mineral food
The limiting factor to the plant's growth is carbon dioxide because of how low it is in the atmosphere even today
And the the proof is in the pudding here because all commercial greenhouse growers
in the world
Inject carbon dioxide into their greenhouses because they haven't enclosed space
Where they can increase the level of co2 and they generally go up to between 800 and 1200 ppm
Which even above that the plants grow faster, but there's a curve because economics is involved
They have to buy the co2 so at this level at right somewhere in the curve
They say okay 1200 is optimum for us because above that buying more co2 has an ever decreasing increase in yield
And so 1200 works really well in greenhouses
That's four times sorry three times what it is today in the global atmosphere and that is
We should not even be concerned
Until co2 gets up to 20 000 ppm
Because that's what submariners survive in for three months under water
and the the the people who uh had the trouble on apollo 13 where the co2 was building up it went up to at least 20 000 in there
See we our breath is 40 000
We have 40 000 ppm co2 in our lungs
Just before we breathe out. I don't want to be breathing that in though
Yes, you do
But the same air that I breathe that well in that case you can no no just once just once
Yeah, yeah, but you don't want to be a closed system of breathing that back in when you put your mask on
You are breathing a significant portion of the air. You just breathed out back in again
so
We we can survive at a whole different bunch of levels of co2 just fine and plants are happy with it at
10000 ppm or they wouldn't be here because that's what it was back
500 million years ago one of the things that I decided to fact check you on or internet check you on
was photos of the great pacific garbage patch
And photos of birds with plastic inside of their stomachs
Now I'd seen these floating around on the internet and when I was reading your book and listening to you
I found that you'd said try and find me a photo of a big patch of garbage
That doesn't have mountains in the background
Because in the middle of the pacific there aren't any mountains that are nearby
So if someone was to take a photo of it something that's supposed to be
Didn't someone say it was nearly the size of texas or something like that size of texas and growing faster than anyone ever predicted
Yes, and I thought well if this thing's so big
That seems ridiculous
I'd seen photos of big clumps of plastic floating together bottles and and and stuff
In the middle of the ocean
So I did a search and I kept on looking in the background and people have re cropped numbers of different photos
And twisted them so that they look like they're at different angles
I thought oh, that's
That's kind of interesting because I thought I was pretty sure that that was there and then the other thing that you mentioned was
Birds that birds don't have teeth so the way that they digest their food is actually by putting little stones or nuts into their stomach
And they kill it and then they use that to grind up the food
And then they eject the little bits of plastic back out
So I thought well I'll have a bit of a read about that and I'll have a look and I'd seen a photo
It's sort of a carcass of an albatross and it's laid on the floor and it's really just sort of
bones and some feathers
And it's got like a thimble like a full reel of string inside of it and other stuff
And you'd mentioned that a lot of these might be staged and I thought yeah
Not a lot of them not a lot of them chris all of them. Okay. I looked and I thought with a skeptical. I was like
Yeah, I mean that that one does look a bit ridiculous and then a few of the other ones do and I read an article from
I want to say it was a bbc
one of david attenborough's documentaries about life or something
And it's one of the write-ups that's a partner to one of the episodes and the episode you see one of the birds eating plastic
And I was like, right, okay. Well, maybe they're doing this thing. Maybe they know you don't not in his episodes
You don't see a bird eating plastic. Oh, it might have been it's definitely a documentary on the bbc
And he's holding up a plastic bag next to a chick in a nest
Okay, and saying and saying
Adult birds are feeding plastic to their chicks. There's no pick. I've I've searched the internet thoroughly
He's actually removed one sequence that sequence where he's holding up the plastic bag
It no longer is available on the internet. I don't know why that's interesting
Yeah, it why did you say it the first time if about a year ago if sir before I wrote my book
I I think he's on to me
uh, and
He's he's an absolute liar in many many cases and I've made three of them in the book
One of them is that albatross adults are feeding plastic to their young
Mistaking it for food greenpeace says the same thing the smithsonian institute in the united states is saying the same thing
They are pushing this lie
That albatross can't tell plastic from food
Sir david attenborough never mentions the word gizzard anywhere
He wrote the bloody secret life of birds book
He did a ten part series on bbc on birds
Right and he doesn't know that birds all have gizzards that need to have solid objects in them to grind their food
Because they have no teeth and therefore have two stomachs all birds every bird in the world. That's why all land birds
Take pebbles into their stomach and when their chicks are in the nest and can't go and get pebbles for themselves
They put pebbles in their chick
So if you have a more convenient pebble that is made of plastic
And it's able to do the same job then
No, the land birds do not feed bits of plastic to their chicks as far as I know because there's plenty of pebbles
But out in the ocean where birds are actual marine animals that
Nest on rocky islands barren rocky islands where all there is is a bit of grass
Right, there's no pebbles there either. Yeah, so traditionally their favorite. Well, naturally they feed their chicks squid
little squid
In those squid is a beak
That beak is retained in the gizzard as part of the digestive aids
Right, it's like a ball mill in mining where they put steel balls into a mill to grind the ore
It's exactly the same concept in many ways, but in the in the gizzard
It's a muscular motion where they go like this with their gizzard and grind the food with these solid objects in there to help with it
And so the other thing they'll take is pumice
Which is volcanic lava from undersea volcanoes and because it's spongy it floats
It's got air in it or gases in it. So it floats so little bits of
Pumice will come to the surface sometimes in huge layers when a undersea volcano goes off
But they're not it's not always there
So they have to resort them to hard bits of wood and nuts that have dropped off a plant
In a river or by the seashore and come out in the ocean
So it they have to work really hard
To find enough digestive aids that are suitable in size and and hardness
It's not easy for them. And when plastic started showing up in the ocean 60 years ago
They started choosing pieces of the right size not plastic bags not cigarette lighters
Not spools of yarn. That's all staged
They don't feed them those kind of things and they're actually they're not feeding the plastic bits
They're giving it to them to ingest so they can put it in their gizzard. That's where it goes
They know how to decide which goes in which stomach
So the story that I read had this lady explaining about the situation and that the parents she'd used the word feed
She'd parents would come back and given the chicks these plastic pebbles
And I can't remember the word that they used
To describe what happens as they're just about to fly the nest some bird word
They the bolus
Maybe they cough up most of the hard objects in there. Yeah
The reason they have so much in their gizzard is because they will digest their food even faster
Then and the parents won't have to feed them for the rest of their lives
Right, so they want them out of the nest as soon as possible
So they put a lot of plastic which weighs a lot plastic and but plastic is never
A majority of what's in a young bird's gizzard never like it's shown in those staged photos is like all plastic
What this lady said was just as they were about to leave. I saw them
Eject the the the plastic back up and throw it back up just as they were about to leave the nest
And you think it's not just the plastic not just the plastic
But all the other items they have in there to do the same job
And it's all plastic is always a minority of it
And she's got all these plastic bags and big plastic plastic cloths and things that's all staged
Yeah, well, that's not going in there. It's not going to fit in a small bird. Is it?
No, well, they're not they're actually quite big because albatrosses are big
But it's not gonna it's not gonna work
They only if you see the photo in my book the only photo I know of of a adult albatross
Giving plastic to its chick you can see it in its beak going into the chicks mouth
And it's all nice little pieces of colored plastic
That are just the right shape and size. It's not plastic bags. It's not
Cigarette lighters like they show in the staged pictures
But when you read that when you read that article what you see is if you didn't know that
The birds needed the plastic to break up food in the stomach
If you didn't know that that was something that aids them with that digestion
And that it is common for them to throw up the plastic plus presumably all of the other stuff
That's been in there helping them to break up their food
You would read that article and it is it is accurate
What she says is correct, but the things that have been purposefully omitted
And the understanding about why some of the inclusions have been put in there and why biologically that might still be natural
That creates a situation and that was the moment I was reading it and I thought
This really is
This really is quite sinister. It does feel like it's quite a
Manipulative way
To tell people what has happened but frame it in such a manner that makes us again hate our own existence
You could say evil
as a synonym of sinister
And I believe it is because sir david attenborough
Also lied about the walruses committing suicide due to a lack of ice
That's the final chapter in my book. They committed suicide. Was this a harry carry thing?
Yes, they jumped off a cliff to their death in order
To avoid an attack by 20 polar bears. Oh
He didn't mention that part and that is well documented
There are photographs of the bears the people who live in a nearby town
Know that the reason the walruses left off a cliff was because they were being
About to be attacked and eaten by polar bears. What was the proposed reason?
Not enough ice as if you can put those two things together
It's sort of like polar bears are inbreeding because there isn't enough ice as if those two things are connected somehow
Right and he made it seem as though it was connected that there was because he said the reason the polar bears have come on the land
and got to a place
Where they could jump off
They did because there was no ice for them in the sea below
Which is always the case on the north shore of russia the ice recedes in the summer
And funny enough he says that the he says the ice is their home
No, the sea is their home
That's where the walrus lives and fishes. They don't fish actually
They dig clams on the bottom
And when the ice recedes away from the coast
And they are coming out of the water to haul out they come on the land
There's a reason why it is an officially designated walrus sanctuary this piece of land
And he implies that it's unnatural that they are coming on the land because there's not enough ice for them to get onto
When in fact they cannot exist they are a coastal species
They cannot exist deep sea
So if the ice recedes to where it's 600 feet deep or 1000 feet deep
It's no good to them
Because they are bottom feeders and as I say in my book
They are bottom feeders much like sir david attenborough and his tv crew on the planet earth or whatever our planet
right they they too are bottom feeders in this case
And they are lying because the reason the walruses left to their death
Fell to their death
They didn't walruses can't actually leap
But they plummeted to their death because a pack of polar bears was going to eat them
And instead the polar bears just walked down to where all the dead walruses were and ate them while they're dead
And i'm sure the walruses would rather be eaten while they were dead than while they were alive
So that's the deal there and he is bald face lying to the whole world about this and he continues to do it
He had people in davos in tears
Recently telling this story even though he now knows that I have busted him and so has
Susan crockford the polar bear expert
Who's also an expert in all arctic animals has busted him publicly
And he sticks to this story because bbc lets him
right
Patrick more ladies and gentlemen fake invisible catastrophes and threats of doom
Will be available on amazon in the links of the show notes below if people want to keep up to date with all of the other
Stuff that you're doing where should they go?
You will perish in flames. That's what I have to say about that
There's a little man on the front. Who's the little man? Who's the guy who was he supposed to be made up guy made up guru
Right, but you will perish in flames is I stole it from the ghostbusters. I don't know if you remember the scene where
The the short guy maranus
Approaches the horse and buggy in central park and first goes up to the horse and says
Are you the key master or something like that right to the horse and then runs off with his eyes blazing
Screaming at the driver. You will perish in flames
So, uh, that's a little guy. How many people have got how many people have got donald trump
Quoted on the back of their book talking about no, no, no, he's not quoted. He's quoting me
Yeah, yeah, but it's he that's him on the back of your book talking about your work. There's not many people that must have had that
Uh, I was very pleased that he recognized that I was telling the truth
About carbon dioxide being the primary element for all life
Etc and that there was no climate emergency or crisis as it may have been called at that time pretty impressive
That was an appearance on tucker carlson. Uh, yeah, what have you got a website? Do you have a twitter or anything like that?
Yeah, I got a twitter. It's ecosense now
Uh, and it's it's I got nearly a hundred thousand followers. They dropped back about ten thousand when a lot of people quit twitter
Uh, and but I've stayed on and I just recently I said I'm quitting twitter finally because the taliban is on it
and they're kicking all these other people off who who aren't the taliban
and uh, people I had about a thousand people come back and say stay man stay so
Because we need you here. And so it's very difficult these days to know when you should like with the the uh,
vaccine
issue
Uh, I I know that in law and in medicine
Informed consent has always been the rule that nobody is required to consent to any medical treatment surgery
needles
Uh pills
Right without their own consent
Everybody has a right as an individual to refuse treatment in other words
And they're trying to turn that on its head by threatening people with their livelihoods
And with their ability to be a normal person they might as well stamp a a brand on their forehead, right?
and
and make them second-class citizens is what they're doing and so
People are saying to me. Well, why did you get vaccinated then and
It's a trip. Well, because I want to be
But I respect the right of other people not to want to be and actually on gutfeld
uh, he had trump on the last two nights
And trump made that same point because his wife doesn't want to be vaccinated
and uh
Gutfeld and trump came to the conclusion that that was perfectly her right
That is the truth if we don't if we allow
Society to force us into medical treatments. Maybe next they'll want our skin to make lampshades, you know
So you this is a fundamental principle in medicine is informed consent and in law
And they're trying to bust it down so that they can have control over everybody
To say what they should have to have injected into their bodies
And personally, I believe the vaccines are efficacious. I also had covid was in the hospital for six days
Really sick
After I had my first vaccination it had not yet taken effect or I was one of those people who gets it anyways
but it's
normally
After two vaccinations at least you're 95 percent
Immune and now I'm
Must be close to 100 percent immune because I survived covid
But they don't take that into account. So the the fact that they're not taking covid survivors as
Equivalent to vaccinated people is also another travesty in this whole thing. So I it's like climate. It's like the climate issue in some ways
um, but it's even more
bizarre from a
Political control point of view because they're really pulling the levers here, you know and trying to make it so that
all all of their subjects are
Are subject to their whims
And we got to fight that
And so people are blaming me for not fighting it because I've got it vaccinated
So it's really complicated that way from an intellectual point of view as to I should should I join
Even though I've been vaccinated should I join the anti-vaxxers in a march? You know, no, I'm not anti-vaxxer
right
And neither is trump. He's vaccinated
Well, he brought us the product apparently
Maybe a conversation for another time patrick. Thanks so much for today
Thank you very much chris. Nice to be with you. Thank you very much for tuning in if you enjoyed that
Then press here for a selection of the best clips from the podcast over the last few months
And don't forget to subscribe makes me very happy indeed
peace