Okay, great. I'm seeing lots of people into the room. Fantastic.
Okay, welcome everyone. This must have been a parallel session with two papers. Unfortunately,
our second presenter has fallen prey to this thing that's going around and is unable to join us.
Our second presenter is not well. So we will have only one paper in this session.
If you wish to, after the half hour is over, investigate the other parallel sessions and
join for the last two papers in the middle of the session, that's completely fine. That's what I'm
planning to do. Okay, also to note that this session is being recorded.
Just to emphasize that, I know you've had to click for your permission, but I do feel I should
note it at the beginning. Okay, so to introduce our last speaker standing, Helen Hooper from
Northumbria University, who will be talking about enhancing university mentoring practice
directly theory analysis of lived experiences of learning and teaching mentors.
So Helen, handing over to you now.
Okay, so I'm just sharing my slides. We did a tech check, so hopefully this is yes.
So I'm assuming unless somebody shows, they can't see anything. I'm assuming the slide is still okay.
So I'm absolutely delighted to be here and unaffected by the seasonal thank goodness.
And for the next 20 minutes or so, I'll be presenting on behalf of my wonderful collaborative
team members at Northumbria University. And what I'm going to be aiming to do is to discuss
some initial findings of an ongoing collaborative project. And my wonderful collaborative team
members are all from across the university, from different faculties, different departments,
including staff from a central quality enhancement team. But we've got this shared goal of really
trying to dig in and explore the experiences of staff across the Institute who mentor their
colleagues to develop their teaching activity. And we've got to share this shared goal, this
shared interest, because we're really motivated to try and improve the support and recognition
for teaching and learning mentors. It builds on a previous project and I can dig into that as we go
through the presentation. So in terms of some kind of general scene setting, I don't think it would be
too controversial to say that mentoring to help colleagues develop their teaching and learning
practices is considered pretty important, pretty essential. And there are a number of studies
which have really attempted to look at the impacts of mentoring colleagues to support
their teaching development. And those research studies which have focused on looking at the
impacts, there's a general consensus that really mentoring those colleagues really enhances
the quality of the learning and teaching that results. Too many ways and there's a
various studies that have dug into various aspects. So they help colleagues to develop
their understanding and their knowledge about learning and teaching in general. But also and
importantly, it facilitates that knowledge transfer. So does that knowledge and understanding of
how learning and teaching best practice works, does it facilitate that to be actually incorporated
in colleagues practice and it does. And if anybody is interested in this, in the citations here,
I've put in a really useful systematic review of the literature looking at how mentoring for
teaching and learning enhances the quality of learning and teaching that results. Now in
complete contrast, there's a real gap in the literature and there's very little research
that actually focuses on their mental experiences and their perceptions about mentoring. So
what motivates people to become a learning and teaching mentor? What are the values and
depending engagement? Do learning and teaching mentors perceive existing supports effective?
Do they perceive their learning and teaching mentor enrolers valued within their team,
within their discipline, within the department or across the institute more generally? And I
suppose our starting point for this is mentoring is really underdeveloped as a pedagogical approach
for enhancing teaching. The literature out there suggests that mentoring really does enhance
teaching. But if we know very little about what mentors experiences and perceptions are, then
that's a real kind of target I suppose for us as academic developers and educational
developers more generally to try and target in and enhance support and enhance recognition
for our mentoring colleagues. So that's our shared goal. So in terms of setting the scene then,
I'm just one of a larger group of 11 brilliant colleagues and we've come from all faculties
at my institute, a wide range of departments including colleagues in the central quality
enhancement team. So it really is an interdisciplinary group. We're all really, really quite experienced
learning and teaching mentors. We provide training across the institute and within
our department as well as acting as mentors ourselves. And this builds upon a previous
research project which focused on trying to improve the support for new academic staff
being inducted into learning and teaching. And what came out of that project were a whole range
of things which did result in improved practice and process. But what came out of that in particular
was the central role that new academic staff perceived mentoring to have on an effective
induction into teaching and learning experience. And the other thing that came out of this side
by side, so mentoring is really important for a new staff member to feel really happy and supported
for that induction process to be effective, but also how inconsistent it was and how uneven and
how different the experiences of new academic staff were across the university in terms of the
mentors they were given, in terms of the type of mentoring and all sorts of things. So that always
remained with us and we thought right the next project we really need to try and do is to dig
into the mentor and aspect to really get that improved as well. So in terms of research James
then we want to really dig in and understand the perceptions of learning and teaching and mentoring
amongst mentors themselves, to identify contradictions, inconsistencies and evenness
in mentoring across the institute and to use these findings as a good evidence basis for proposing
changes to both policy and practice across the institute to improve the support we give to
mentors and to really make sure that their excellent mentoring activities is properly recognised.
Now I mentioned this project builds upon a previous project exploring the induction
experiences of new academic staff and we've utilised the same methodological approach because
it is so good and it always surprises me how the chat, so collaborative historical activity theory
in my opinion, should be used far more widely especially for collaborative research projects
in higher education. It is just so useful and it just fits the bill so brilliantly if your aim
is to really try and drive forward change. So it's a theory which encompasses expansive learning
amongst the collaborative team so it really challenges collaborators to question the notions
of your academic agency in terms of suggestion improvements as a basis for change and it's
all about transformation through collaborative reflection. Now this might sound a little bit
complicated if you've not come across this before. So chat, cultural historical activity theory,
it focuses on socially situated learning so thinking about everyday tasks so in this case
we're focusing on the experiences of learning and teaching mentors to try and identify ways to
improve support for them and to increase recognition for the brilliant role that they do
and we do that by setting out and mapping a specific activity system for mentoring. So an
activity system is defined through six interconnected elements which are listed on the bottom of the
slide here so this is a bit of a busy slide. The next slide shows this in terms of an image so if
it looks a bit confusing here hopefully it'll be a little bit clearer in the next slide. So there is
a subject of any activity system and we sat down as a collaborative team and mapped this out for
learning and teaching mentoring so the subject of our activity system is the learning and teaching
mental. The subject engages in an object of activity so here the activity is effective,
we defined it as effective mentoring for learning and teaching in higher education
and obviously that activity occurs within some kind of community so is that predominantly
within a department or a discipline or do actually effective mentors rely in part or predominantly
on interdisciplinary or institutional networks or communities of practice. These are very
sociocultural in nature and the remaining three elements of the activity system on the right
hand side of the bottom of this slide are much more structural or institutional in nature so
you've got a mentor engaging in mentoring in the community but that is mediated often by
institutionally dictated tools and resources so for example what training or CPD is available
for new mentors is there any further training available for experienced mentors and so on.
There are rules defining that activity so for example many institutions have targets for
new academic staff to achieve fellowship of advanced HE and there's a formal process of
allocating that new staff member a trained mentor to guide them through that process
and obviously then there's lots of conflicts and contradictions in terms of how many things
do people have to do so the division of labour for example is there a workload allocated
for that formal mentoring and how is all of the excellent informal mentoring that occurs
allocated for in terms of division of labour so if that previous slide was a little bit busy
maybe this slide makes it a little bit clearer so you can see two triangles there's a large one on
the outside and a smaller one on the inside the sociocultural elements of this activity system
the subject a mentor engaging in the object of the activity system which is effective mentoring
for to support colleagues develop their learning and teaching and that's within a community so it
might be a departmental or institutional community and then that sits within this outer triangle
the three remaining most structural elements of the activity system so what are the rules what are
the tools and resources and you know this contradiction in terms of time available so how
do you spend your time what's the division of labour so we sat down as a collaborative team
we mapped out the activity system and then in terms of generating data and how we progressed
with the analysis each individual team member spent quite a lot of time writing an individual vignette
about how learning and teaching mentoring occurred within their team or their discipline
but i'm from the development of an online survey we use the JISC online survey to
that contain both quantitative and open-ended questions so for example the quantitative questions
you get a workload how much of a workload you get and then open-ended questions such as do you
perceive your mentor learning and teaching mentoring role as valued what are the challenges
or the benefits associated with it and so on and in terms of the analysis it's very intuitive back
and forth between the data the activity system to make sure that the theme codes were organized
around the nodes of the activity system and really focusing on surfacing typical patterns
and contradictions because then we can use those as the basis for improvements to institutional
policy and procedure just checking the time oh i want to spend some time on the findings so again
this might be a little bit of a busy slide and i'll give you a little bit of time to to read
these kinds of typical themes and contradictions that the our team my team has come together
to consider and let's start at the left hand side here not one respondent to the survey
had ever been asked so these are really experienced mentors from across the university and i'm sure
us hopefully i'm well i'm i'm guessing that some people in in the audience today have engaged in
mentorship for teaching and learning have you ever been asked yourself as a practitioner
is the support for mentoring effective and do you think your role is valued do you get a work
load not one of our participants had ever been asked the basic questions about that really
valuable role before now on the flip side i was really surprised by how happy and collegiate
people were to engage in this kind of role and there was some conflict and and contradictions
in terms of respondents and perceptions about whether or not you should be mentoring for a
whole academic at my institute at many institutes mentoring mentoring for learning and teaching
is separate and distinct including a separate person for learning and teaching as opposed to
research and there are various reasons for that and conflict and contradictions in terms of whether
or not that's perceived to be effective or whether on balance mentoring for for the whole
academic is an ideal that we should maybe be trying to work towards um uh then this is an
interesting one there is some assumption and i think i was guilty of this myself that if you're
good at something so if you were if you're an effective teacher then you'd be an effective
mentor in helping colleagues develop their teaching practice and that is probably not so
true and in terms of the institutional support for uh mentor training it's very much focused
on helping new and relatively inexperienced colleagues gain fellowship or granted cheap
because that's the institutional kpi associated with with um with activity very little uh development
for example for colleagues who need to be working in professional practice
so lots of really rich data coming in from both the vignettes and the surveys for mentors across
the university now just just in order to spend a few moments on some initial reflections and
learnings again the the chat theory it really has promoted expansive learning amongst our
collaborative team and at the moment we're sitting down and we're in the process of thinking
through the implications in terms of suggestions and things we want to take forward to really try
and improve the institutional support and the recognition for our brilliant uh learning teaching
mentors so something we really need do need to work on is to get to a reasonable level of
recognition and reward especially in formal processes and procedures so for example promotional
processes appraisal process process and things like we've got an institutional scheme for professional
recognition by advanced hg can we embed some criteria therefore senior fellowship or principal
fellowship and we're kicking around ideas as well for a more celebratory approach so can we give some
kind of institutional prize or can there be a small pot of funding for cpdo research and so on
and surprisingly i'm i'm guessing for some of you would be inconsistent mental workload so
some people had to workload others were completely unaware if they did and if they did it was hidden
in some kind of workload spreadsheet so there's not even a line on the workload spreadsheet so i
think there is a real need to increase mental workload and to get that implemented a bit more
consistently a really strong feedback in terms of this this really crucial role basically being
invisible especially the informal kind of mentoring that goes on every single day so a reliance on
ongoing above and beyond and professional generosity and something we hadn't thought about was what's
the best mentee and mental pairings should they actually be set determined discipline based into
discipline based and that's something that we're going to think about and i really like colleagues
feedback and ideas on any of these so if there's an opportunity for me to to steal some good practice
i'm definitely going to do that and take it back to to um my colleagues at Northumbria um there's
definitely an unmet need for a little bit of extra training especially for mentors who are helping
colleagues develop their practice for professional practice rather than just teaching at a university
kind of standard approaches and what also came out of this was how much mentors gain from mentoring
mentees who have brilliant knowledge to share and especially things like digital literacy so i'm
currently mentoring a relatively new staff who has very little teaching experiences but absolutely
fantastic on generative AI an area which i know very very little about so i think we do have capacity
here to promote the benefits and to capture the benefits of reciprocal mentoring regardless of
status or prior experience or anything along those lines so i think with just maybe one or two minutes
left i'm probably going to end there and i really really welcome any comments or questions or any
good practice that you'd like to share
i'm getting my screen back um thank you very much that was a really interesting presentation
um if anyone has any questions in the uh who in the attendance list here please do let me know
pop it in the chat or just raise your your hand electronically i was really interested Helen in
that last slide um where you were talking about um the uh the potential benefits um and you were
talking about the the mentor mentee pairings and how these might be rethought how the organization
of those might be rethought and i was wondering if you could speak a bit more about how those are
currently arranged at Northumbria does it vary across department or yeah so it'll be really
just again to get other people's kind of perspectives on this so at Northumbria even
though it's a reasonably large and quite complex kind of organization and my own faculty is split
on two different campuses really quite large deeper mental and discipline based teams
we still have this kind of one we have this notional one university approach
but then when you actually dig in and actually go and have a look at what happens in departments
and discipline teams it's clearly not a one university approach so what's really nice about
doing these kinds of projects is to actually find out what happens in reality regardless of the
notional one university approach to processes and practices so in my own department i allocate
formal mentors to new academic staff and what i generally tend to do is to allocate a mentor from
outside the direct program or disability team because then there's no kind of conflicts of
interest in terms of a bit of teaching practice going on and you also get opportunity to share
good practice across the department more generally it also gives new academic members of staff a wider
network outside their initial disability team because they can draw on expertise and they get to
know people from other programs or other areas but that's very different to other departments
and disciplines so in some of the more professionally oriented departments and programs there's very
much an allocate from that specific discipline area because there's niche knowledge that's really
helpful for the new academic staff member to to get on board with and to understand so
i'm not so sure that there's a correct answer to that but it's not something that i ever thought
about before and what i did after thinking about this because this came out of the data analysis
was take this back to my own departmental teaching and learning enhancement team and say
look we've always done this in the past but there's these other ways of thinking about
things and doing things shall we try something new or actually if it's not broken shall we not fix it
so i think what's good about this approach and what's good about this method
is it stimulates that discussion and that collaborative reflection and it also i find
this so valuable myself it's about the academic agency you are the captain of your own destiny
what are we going to do as a team to try and make things a bit better for everybody
so that was that was a bit of a long winded answer did i answer your question
no it's all it's just all really interesting isn't it i mean um yeah that that perspective is
is really interesting um i see that richard davies has his hand raised would you like to
post your question and yeah thanks very much um my question really is about um the design of the
chat system and i i guess my question is is to what extent the data confirms this kind of
setting out of it or whether there are multiple ways in which the activity system could be laid
out in relation both i think to the different kinds of communities and different rules um
but also whether or not um how you think about what the um the object is and the output of them
and to what extent it feeds into the activity um system of teaching and learning itself
um and i just i just wondered where you had thoughts about whether this was a
where this was a kind of a strong activity this theoretically strong activity system or
whether it was it was a kind of a heuristic and there were alternatives that might also
fit the data thanks yeah richard so i i think this is this i think we could talk about that for
probably about an hour or something so um this is the second project that i've been involved with
with which utilised the activity system and this chat approach and i come from a kind of hard
science background so my background is a molecular biologist um and a colleague of mine
Sue Matheson who's in the central quality enhancement team is an educational developer
by practice and by research so she really led on on teaching us and um developing our knowledge
and understanding of this approach so that's the caveat to what i'm going to say i've been
involved with it for about five years we've done a couple of projects but i don't really consider
myself to be an expert in the field i'm kind of more of a practitioner i put it in putting it
into practice i think i think about it as a really valuable tool both for data generation
and analysis but also for personal and practitioner educational development so i think i gain as much
out of it as what we learn from the participants responses and so on so to try and answer your
question a bit more focused so um with this activity system the one i presented is probably
about both iteration so we go away we have a thing we come back and we draft it out and
then we talk about it and then we go away we have a thing about it in practice we come back
and we talk about it and so um we get to a stage as a collaborative team so there's 11 of us from
all four faculties from eight different departments um 10 different disciplines on a central team
and we've got that breadth so i suppose a weakness if you can call it a weakness is i think it would
be much more tighter and focused if i define that within my department but i think that weakness is
also a strength because if you're trying to develop and improve support and recognition
for colleagues who engage in mentorship across the university you do have to have that that kind of
the breadth so i if i remember correctly that's about the fourth iteration that we agreed upon
where it was general enough to reflect everybody's practice and understanding but tight enough
to be useful as a tool for data analysis and then reflection and the focus of this i think is to
identify those common experiences and contradictions because that's the basis on which then you say
this is what we do reasonably well and we should fight and argue to keep that going but actually
these are things that are unhelpful because they're different in different departments and
there's unmet need for training or it gives you some ideas for things that you haven't tried out
before there could be a bit better in your own department um so i think if you take that here's
my feeling i think if you take that and maybe try and apply it at your own institute you plan
i'm guessing that you would come to something pretty similar if you did it across your institute
if you did it in a tighter team it might be a bit different does does that make sense does that answer
your question or not have you experienced of it or would you would you say something different
it'll be really interesting to find out no i think i think i think i guess uh no timber and you can
be similar in the sense that we have quite centralized teaching and learning um policies
and framework so i guess across the institution um i i would think it would be interesting to see
what it would look like at say some of the you know that's based at one of the kind of more
entrepreneurial universities that's um uh where um departments are actually quite distinct in terms of
their culture and activity um and potentially more driven by um the academic discipline than
perhaps many of our schools are because they're primarily driven by more vocational occupational
concerns um so i guess there would be similarities i think might i think where we might look at
differently is is whether we're actually whether we're trying to provide if whether the outcome is
providing effective mentoring or whether it's about providing effective teaching learning
within particular schools so um so that we that so that the effective mentoring will be a kind of
mediating uh feature i think for us as opposed and that's partly because we're driven by as many
are by rfs requirements in terms of theory of change and impact upon student metrics and so
quite a lot of what we do see the kind of work with staff as as mediating the actual goal which is
the improvements of learning and to some extent teaching kind of almost drops out as a as a final
so what you're doing what you're doing there is is i'm getting deja vu that was our first conversation
so how tight should be the relationship between the subject and the object
and we ended up as quite a tight relationship because if it's mentors it has to be support for
mentoring and not everything else because that's a bit too broad um so so that's that's that but
you go through those cycles as a team to say and to divine it so it's quite a time consuming process
but it's very valuable because it really makes you unpick and think about things that you might
either haven't thought about since you were a new mentor or you'd never thought about before
hey thanks
um was there a question in the chat player i've not been keeping an eye on no um one of the
questions just want to leave yeah yeah and we're thanking you for for a great session um
were there any other questions in the room otherwise i think we can all exit and go on
through another session but um Helen thank you very much that was really interesting uh you're
your perspective on that um i think it's really interesting work so we'd love to hear back from
you again yeah well thanks for listening and thanks thanks for the input it's fantastic
excellent okay and we'll see you again soon yeah brilliant thanks very much bye everybody
bye now