This week we will be looking at the creative practice of sequencing sound using our digital
audio workstation.
This will allow you to order your musical events over time whilst layering and blending
them together to realise your creative project.
The key concepts we will explore are time, sequencing, tracks and channels, volume, panning
and effects.
The first thing I need to do is create, set up and save a project file.
So I will go file, new.
It brings up the familiar project window.
Note, we have used this window before, but before we used it simply to edit, process,
manipulate and export audio.
We never actually saved a project.
This time we are going to save a project file which contains all the various settings
and media that we need to use.
I will go file, save project as, give it a name and click save.
The next thing I need to do is ensure Audacity has the correct settings that I wish to use
for sequencing.
To do this I go to Audacity, Preferences, Quality and make sure it is 48,024 bit.
It is a bit higher than probably what we need, but it will ensure the quality is good.
The other thing I need to do is ensure the tracks are set up to edit in a particular
way.
One of the things that is useful is ensuring when you are sequencing that the various events
or clips don't move about when we edit, add and modify.
So I am going to uncheck this option here, editing a clip can move other clips.
Click OK and we are done.