AI run the government. So this question actually came from one of my patreon supporters. So thank you spectral Valkyrie for this question
But basically the idea was okay rather than just look at the way things are and look at incremental changes from
Where we're at to a potential future. What if we just take a first principles look at could the AI run the government?
What would that look like?
So before we dive in I just wanted to let you know this video is a little bit longer and it's broken down into three distinct parts
So the first part is we will talk about what is the purpose of government in general?
And that will kind of set the stage because there is quite a bit of debate over what the role of government is or should be
And it's mostly in terms of degrees
So anyways, we'll get into that in just a moment then in the in the middle part
We will talk about what would an AI government actually look like how is that actually going to function?
How would it run and then finally in the last part of the video?
I will make some actual real predictions based on things that I know are happening today and things that are in the works and
So we'll see kind of what what the actual progress should look like
So if any one of these parts doesn't resonate with you feel free to skip ahead
But yeah, let's get right into it
So the first thing that we need to say is okay. What is objectively speaking? What is the outcome?
What is the function that government provides and right now?
There are kind of five key pillars that government provides and there's there the biggest one that's missing is military
but what I will say is that the military can operate as a separate entity from government and in fact in many
In many institutions it kind of does it's technically an extension of the executive branch, but it is also supposed to have
Its own thing. So that is deliberately and distinctly missing. So we're looking more at domestic government
So domestic government focuses on these five key principles. So first is resource management
Regulating public goods and natural resources for sustainability that sort of thing. So land use
Waterways air that sort of stuff
forests, you know
Drilling rights
The second thing is economic management. So this is fiscal and monetary policy. So this has to do with central banks
Regulating the stock market that sort of stuff, you know, again, you're familiar with all these because we argue about it every few years here in America
based on who we want to elect
the third pillar is
Mediation of relationships. So this is facilitating and mediating the relationships between
Citizens nations organizations so on and so forth. And so there's a few ways that these regulations happen or that this this mediation happens
So first is like corporate law. So ensuring that, you know, companies abide by safety regulations that sort of thing
There's also the courts. So like if you have a dispute with someone else, there's criminal court. There's civil court
That sort of thing. There's the Supreme Court
So the court system is as part of this relationship mediation. It's it's there to broker or referee
Relationships between various stakeholders in the government namely citizens businesses and then other nations
So the diplomatic corps the State Department as we call it in America
That is part of the relationship mediation. So the government manages our relationship with say Britain or France or China on our behalf
The fourth thing is that they guarantee and protect and enforce rights
And so there's this is a recent term
So I've been plugging it a lot that I learned positive rights versus negative rights
So a positive right is something that you're entitled to and a negative right is something that you were free from and so for instance our
Constitution
Guarantees that you are entitled to a right to free speech. You are entitled to a jury by your peers. You are entitled to
A certain other things plenty of other things, but then you're also free from
Tyranny, you know free to free from oppression and those sorts of things
And so there's two different kinds of rights and of course there it as I mentioned earlier
It is also a matter of degree because many of your rights are relatively simple
But then we're there's also debate over more complex or comprehensive rights and then finally social organization
And so this is one of the most controversial ones
Especially if you look at the news right now
The state of Texas is all up in arms about abortion rights. So again
talking about social organization
By and large western liberal democracies have decided not to legislate morality
And you can see this by virtue of contrast when you look at the fact that like
There is some
TikTok celebrity who got arrested I think in Saudi Arabia for adultery like we don't do that in the west anymore
We don't say like oh well this woman, you know had sex with someone that she wasn't supposed to so therefore we're gonna put her in morality jail
Right, there was huge
protests that broke out in Iran because a woman was beaten by the morality police
And so by and large western democracies the the role of legislating
morality and social structure
Is contracting however government does still play a role in this and so what I mean by that is
You know what what are legally recognized marriages?
What are the family structures that are legally recognized and so right now
Western liberal democracies have have kind of centered around the nuclear family
Or the the smallest family unit, which is the marriage between a husband and a wife
Whereas in the past there were you know, usually it was
Uh, you know tribal communities or extended families where you'd have a matriarch or a patriarch who kind of managed the whole family
And that was the legal unit and there are still plenty of countries out there where
If not in law then at least in practice that is how things are run
And so the government does have a role in supporting that social organization
Then there's also other aspects of it such as the relationship between the government and the fourth estate, which is journalism
Or or the church as well
So those are kind of the five main pillars of government
Like I said, there are plenty of other things from that list that are missing that is on purpose
But these are kind of the five pillars that I want to look out for this video
so also
As I as I promised a lot of this is controversial and this goes back to even the founding of modern democracy where socrates himself
questioned the the efficiency and wisdom of democracy
so some of his
Critiques were and of course this is back in the days of athens before representative democracy
So most of what he was complaining about was tyranny of the majority
Also, i'm really toasty. So i'm gonna switch clothes. Oh, okay properly dressed now
but yeah, so socrates was concerned about tyranny of the majority
and
there's also
the what we would today call like, you know
The kind of the difference between
Inclusive democracy where everyone gets a say versus
expertise and this is one of the chief
tensions
particularly in america but also in other nations
because
communism like capital c communism
said, oh, well
The citizen shouldn't have a vote because they're all dumb
And so what we're going to do is we're just going to hand the reins to the quote-of-quote experts
And then the experts without any checks and balances are going to get to make decisions
And in soviet russia that led to mass famines because the so-called experts mismanage farms
mismanage the economy and that sort of thing and that by the way still goes on today. There are
I was watching a documentary about how um, there there are places in china that you still can't grow
food because of decades of communist mismanagement
On the other hand, uh, your average citizen is also not necessarily qualified to make decisions
So you you're kind of damned if you do damned if you don't
Now what I wanted to include this slide for was to say that there are flaws with democracy
I would say that there are more egregious flaws particularly with every way that
Communism has been implemented and so I am not a communist. I'm not a socialist even though some of you accuse me of that
I also have people say that I'm a neoconservative. So make up your minds
Make up your minds. I consider myself a pragmatic progressive, but anyways, that's a conversation for another
uh, another topic
So let's move let's move on
But I just wanted to address the elephant in the room and say that yes democracy is does have some fundamental flaws
Going back to the founding of the thing the other component of
That makes government hard is just intrinsic human flaws. And so one example is charismatic leaders
So charismatic manipulators are able to use demagoguery and other things to
you know, kind of get in and and you know wreck things
power seeking behavior
profit motivation plain old ignorance and so basically this all
Speaks to the reason that government is structured as the way that is
because the framers of
modern western liberal democracies basically said, okay, well
Uh, they didn't have the word for it, but they noticed that you know, uh, a non-trivial chunk of the population
is just crazy. Um, whether they're narcissistic, whether they are
um sociopaths, whether they are just
completely saturated with greed
um
So they said, okay, well, we have to know that some people are going to be power seeking
We have to know that some people are going to be manipulative and so on and so forth
And so that's part of the reason that the government is structured the way that it is so that you have checks and balances
So that you have these relief mechanisms that allow you to
You know change up leadership on a regular basis, which in theory should prevent any particular
Uh group or person from accumulating and holding on to too much power
So far so good, but there are some people who very deliberately and explicitly want to upset that balance
um because what happens is
When you allow for the leadership, um at all levels to change up on a regular basis
And you have this kind of as a mechanistic system
um
You prevent that accumulation of power
But also you it's it becomes easier to spot people who are accumulating power
Now, of course here in america, we have a problem of gerontocracy where we have people
Literally serving until their 80s and 90s and in recent cases dying in office
Even though they are not legally competent to take care of themselves
So if someone is not legally competent to take care of themselves
They are certainly not legally competent to run the the the nation
But of course the uh the american system was framed before people were living long enough to have dementia
So
We got some work to do
So that leads us to uh representative democracy
So basically the way that it generally runs today is that we have a division of power
We have a three branch system. So that's legislative judicial and executive branch
The the the judicial branch is obviously like one of the weaker ones
Except for the supreme court, which does kind of set a lot of the tone
We use elected officials
So the elected officials then you know represent our willpower and they appoint
Experts um and then some of the sometimes we do vote on experts. Sometimes we don't
Some officials some offices are appointed by the electorate. Some aren't
But this is all part of the ongoing negotiation and part of the reason that it's so messy is because
We're constantly making little adjustments to the whole structure
Which is good because uh, you know, you look at revolutions of the past and one of the key thing one of the key reasons
why civil wars have happened in the past is because
And not even in the distant past in the recent past
Is because the government is too rigid or too inflexible and does not
Respond to the will of the people and the changing times. And so the the key thing is peaceful transitions
Um, it's not just a matter of representing the will of the people
Because if you wanted to create a government that was purely of the people for the people by the people
It would look different from representative democracy
But really what what what the uh what the framers particularly the other of the american system wanted to achieve was peaceful transition of power
Because when you had monarchy you'd have wars of succession
When you had the you know, basically most of europe being run by a single royal family and all their cousins and second cousins and fifth cousins
You could still end up with major problems. See world war one and world war two
Now obviously america was founded before that but there is oh man
You listen to history like europe was just one constant set of wars for like 500 years
Um, and then as I already mentioned incremental changes part the part of the goal of government is to allow for incremental changes
Um, that is not necessarily steered uh exclusively by a controlling elite
But that the will of the people can make incremental changes to the government itself
Even the founding document, um, such as in our case a constitutional democracy
And so the idea is that this is a gigantic system that is meant to
Allow change but also resist change because you don't want the pendulum to swing too wildly
You don't want to oscillate by correcting and then over correcting
And so these are all the all the things that go into the purpose of government. Why is it here?
Why does it work the way that it does?
So this stands in stark contrast to single party systems such as what we see in china and russia, which they are
Technically democracies because they they run quote-unquote elections
Um, but most the elections are fixed and I think that it's not a controversial thing to say that they are not actually true democracies
Or they are what I would call kind of a pseudo democracy
Where it's got some of the dressings some of the trappings
But you can when you consider that both putin and shijing ping were able to to manipulate the system so that they were lifelong appointees
They basically made themselves kings
So some of the characteristics that you see in single party systems are you get a monolithic structure
That's by definition. The ccp is china china is the ccp. There isn't really any alternative
While there are technically other, you know people that run against putin. They usually fall out of windows or end up getting poisoned
So that's not necessarily a viable strategy there
Part of the way that these regimes maintain control is they become more authoritarian over time
And so that leads to things like information control both russia and china have state-run media
So basically if you see a lack of state-run media that is usually a sign of a healthier democracy
Which we'll talk about in just a second
They do allow liberalization
So this is one of the this is one of the things that kind of gave us hope after the collapse of the soviet union
And after china's great leap forward
Was that they eventually did allow for
Some liberalization of the economy because they wanted the profits, but they didn't liberalize
In terms of civil liberties in terms of voting rights and and government reforms
And there are also pretty interesting cultural and historical roots
As they kind of explain why this happens now you could look at places like japan and germany which did
granted at the barrel at the
Because guns were pointed at them after world war two. They were able to liberalize
Very effectively now Japan still has the imperial family, but they're mostly just token, right?
You know the japanese parliament runs the country
Germany got a did away with everything and now they are you know fully fully liberalized democracy
and so the argument that
That single party systems inevitably emerge in some of these nations for historical and cultural reasons
Doesn't necessarily stand up to scrutiny particularly when you look at the history of japan
But they also had to lose a major war in order to have that that
New democracy forced on them
And of course that set the the tone for the rest of the 20th century and 21st century
Where the western allies basically enforce and export democracy
Onto other nations whether or not they want it which of course, that's what putin and shijin ping are pushing back against now
Actually more explicitly. It's very interesting where they just basically have flatly said like
We don't want your western values now. Do they do do they reflect the will of the people?
Doesn't sound like it. I've interviewed some people from from other places not russia or china
But I interviewed some people from syria
And the the idea is that the more that they learn about western democracy the more that they want it
Which is the reason that people like
Putin and shijin ping need to resist information and need to poison their people against the idea of voting and power
but that's
That's why there is still ongoing conflict in syria is because
People know they've seen greener pastures and they want it and they're going to keep fighting for it
The fighting has tamped down, but syria is deeply fragmented right now
so anyways
That is the by virtue of contrast looking at a single party system or failed democracies
Which there are some people that explicitly want to turn America into a single party system into all of you
I say stop
And then finally there is the the nightmarish central management or totalitarian regimes
This is what you see in terms of fascism or old school communism where there wasn't any elections whatsoever
farcical or otherwise
North korea is is the current kind of prime
Example of the the quote-unquote hermit kingdom where it is top-down authoritarian control
And they regulate everything
Apparently in north korea. They even regulate how much grieving you're supposed to do for the former dead leaders
So that's not just a legislating morality. They're they're they're controlling emotions
and apparently people have been set sent to like
Reeducation camps for not grieving enough in public on their days of remembrance or whatever
um these kinds of things they
They're necessarily surveillance states
Um extreme conformity is required and then and then any breach of conformity is deeply and severely punished
Democracy is noisy
This is one of the things that I think a lot of people don't understand
Which is why I'm going through all this is because all the vitriol all the vicious debates about you know
Trump versus biden or you know left versus right or you know, whoever
Democracy is is noisy by design
When you look at at a at a nation that you know say oh, we're we're perfectly aligned because they quash debate
You're not allowed to criticize putin. You're not allowed to criticize
Xi Jinping. You're not allowed to criticize the the kim jong-un
Um
So because of that those nations they appear more orderly they appear quieter. They appear to be
Uh more in lockstep. However in america and india and britain and all these other places
Where you have really vicious debates you have mud slinging you have you have muck raking you have all kinds of things
And that is by design and so
When you understand that that the ability to speak up that you know
If you really don't like something in the west you can start a youtube channel or a tiktok channel and and
Say, you know the president's an idiot and like I have zero fear of that
Whereas like could you do that in china in russia in north korea?
No, and of course those are just some of the most extreme examples. There are plenty of other oppressive regimes around the world
and so because of that because debating is encouraged
Because descent is tolerated because we can air our grievances. Now this uh,
Allow us for a level of transparency
But the flip side of that is that people don't get along all the all the time
The fact of the matter is is that you know, you can say things that people disagree with
And then you can get into internet debates or you know, choose your favorite talking head
Which now I have joined the league of talking heads. So yeah, whatever
Um
But these are all features. This is a feature not a bug. That is the key thing is that if democracy is noisy
That is a sign of a healthy democracy now
You can also end up in situations where people kind of naturally agree
Um, and so this is this is uh, you know, there was what was it called the era of good feelings?
um, where america basically became
By a default kind of a single party system for about 20 years
But that was just because things were going well and there was nothing really to argue about and of course that is a
gross oversimplification
But that emerged naturally not by force
whereas during
Uh contentious times whether there are external threats internal threats
Or social upheaval
You should expect it to get a little bit nastier
But again, that is part of democracy working itself out by having those ongoing debates
And having those uh those ongoing dissenting opinions and airing those grievances and talking it out
That is part of the process. That is that is that is a sign of things
Uh progressing as as intended. So with all that being said
What would an ai government look like?
Because the thing is when you're when you're looking at all this it's not a matter of
Machines just making decisions and enforcing it on us. That's a totalitarian regime, which we don't want
what we really want is
We want the messiness of what of democracy that we have today
Because you know whenever I talk about universal ai values
It's like well who gets to decide them and the answer is and this is kind of why I was like
I was always confused by that retort
Um, but I understand it better is because we do we get we the people get to decide what values
We ultimately want to live by now. There's of course
There's always a contingent of people who want to enforce
Their particular values on everyone because they don't understand
Uh the history of democracy or why things are the way they are like for instance
Whenever someone says america is a christian nation and we all need to have more christian law
That is indistinguishable from muslims who want to impose
Sharia law on everyone else. So stop doing that
The idea is freedom and equality are the highest principles that we have agreed on
And so then it's a matter of creating a container that allows for
Different approaches to life now some people do not tolerate
Differences they don't tolerate differences of religion or of opinion or values or beliefs
And those people are just wrong. That's not how democracy works. That's not how
Inclusive tolerant societies work
So this thought experiment then is okay, let's just assume that ai has the capacity to run
The government let's let's just imagine a year from now when we have a gi and it's
And it's performing above human level on all benchmarks. It's in the 99.9th percentile
Or higher for like literally every cognitive ability
We've got you know advanced robots that can do stuff and the ultimate goal is
What if we just removed humans from the government?
wholesale
Like let's go full monty because this is this is what my patreon supporter was like like no, let's
Not beat around the bush. Let's just go full monty and see what
Like what would this require what what are the challenges and how would it actually work?
So let's dive into some of the components that would make this happen
So the first thing that we need to do is use ai whether it's a combination of existing, you know machines and and
Databases and stuff combined with large language models combined with deep multimodal models
We need to survey the will of the people
whatever else is true
The one of the chief purposes of government is to reflect the will of the people now
Right now the primary way we have to do that is through voting
That is the primary mechanism that we have to express our will where it's you know every so often
We get to go pick a person
Who who we feel represents our desires and beliefs and then we go and hire them via election
To go represent our desires our values our beliefs in the process of government
But if you remove all humans, then it's not necessarily electing a representative. You have to express your will
Some other way
Now that doesn't mean that you don't you get rid of voting. Maybe you have more voting
But this goes back to socrates complaint
Which and I know elan musk is one of the people who said oh direct democracy makes sense
It absolutely doesn't you do not want to live in a direct democracy because then you have tyranny of the majority
And that can get real bad real fast
however
by combining
You know existing online platforms leveraging new technologies
Using large language models and semantic clustering and all sorts of stuff
I suspect that we could easily build a platform a democratic platform that very very
comprehensively collects and understands the will of the people
Um, and then what do you do with that information? We can figure that out later
But rather than just picking a person because also remember go back to the slide that I did about fundamental human flaws
power seeking avarice
plain old ignorance
You get rid of those if you get rid of people now you introduce new problems if you replace people with machines
But the point is is that if we can directly express our willpower through some mechanism
You know maybe with a combination of blockchain voting and artificial intelligence and a few other things
Then the then the machine apparatus of government will at least be aware of what we the people want
So that's step one. We need something that allows us to
Express our will and allows it to be recorded
and accurately measured
So that then the ai government can then use that
Another component of this is ongoing negotiations. So like I said democracy is noisy by design
but if you get rid of
individual, you know
Politicians then you don't have conventions. You don't have town halls
So then who are you talking to? Who do you write letters to?
and this is again where the
collecting the will of the people
Is not just about okay. The people have expressed their desire on this particular issue now the machine goes and does it
It is an ongoing conversation. It is an ongoing negotiation and renegotiation
As the situation changes as our understanding changes as consensus changes and so on and so forth
And so part of the of the government
What it does today is, you know, the the the white house has their, you know, their press corps and politicians have their
public relations managers
So we basically need the same thing
But with various ai components kind of saying this is what we're doing and this is why and
Like here's a here's a chance for feedback. We need to disseminate ideas
resources and that sort of stuff
Oh, and one thing that I should point out is that I'm not necessarily thinking that one monolithic ai is the right way to go
Because from a narrative perspective, that's easier to say like, you know, the ai
But really I think that
Um, if we were to replace government with ai, it should be probably millions of individual ai agents all working together
That are individually transparent
Um, hence the swarms that we've been working on
Um, anyways, so getting back to the slide, uh, you know
There needs to be constant feedback
between
You know the people and the ai government and as well as, you know, I mentioned consensus, but it's basically
debate
Discussion negotiation dialogue consensus. Those are all kind of the same thing
But it the the the key takeaway is that it needs to be a two-way conversation
It's not just a unilateral
The will of the people gets expressed and then the ai government goes and does that
That's not exactly the way that it works and that's not that's by that's by design. That's not how representative democracy works
It's we express our will and then the professional politicians ideally
Go and do their best to accommodate that
But of course, you know, our politician goes to battle with other politicians and so on and so forth
likewise
You know, we the people express our will to an ai government
And it will do the best that it can to implement that willpower within the constraints within the boundaries of
The way that other people, you know, want things to go as well as other higher universal principles such as
enshrining, you know equality and freedom above all else above, you know
As an example above a religious theocracy another thing that it's going to need is
mechanisms for change so
as
Western liberal democracies work today
Incrementalism is the name of the game
You can make changes to literally every aspect of the government
piece by piece starting with the constitution and there are
Mechanisms there that allow for that change, which is why I gave this like little transformer dude
Because you know, it's like it looks like a modular robot or whatever. So that's it's supposed to be an allegory
But when you have an ai government, you don't want it to be rigid
You don't want it to be like, okay, once you implement it once it's that way forever
No, you literally want every piece of the stack
To be changeable to be plastic
And so that means all the models that the agents use the hardware the software and that's just the system itself
Then all the policies that the system uses the technology stack that it uses
The principles that it abides by so, you know, if you've watched my channel
You know that I'm a big fan of like universal declaration of human rights
I'm also a big fan of of the heuristic imperatives that I created
But those need to be part of what is negotiated that needs to be part of
What is changeable now, obviously the core values the core principles
You need to be really, you know, darn sure that you want to change those
And it's also not necessarily something that you want to direct democracy on because one you might never get it passed
But you do want everyone to have a say
In the process
So that's one thing that I think some people are not familiar with
When looking at government systems and it's not necessarily a vote on the outcome
It's it's participating in the process of decision making
um, but
all that aside
This ai government system will need ways of changing of modifying of changing the stack of changing
uh
Everything about it. So there's a couple parts of this because while you want it to be able to change
You don't want it to change too quickly. I guess long story short is
This is probably one of the hardest parts is kind of what i'm getting at
Is creating a system that is modifiable
But that is not overly modifiable and that will adapt at the correct pace
And who knows maybe that's the kind of policy that ai would be optimized to discover
That would be an interesting conversation to have
Another thing is that the scope of this ai government needs to expand and contract
And so what I mean by that is
When america was founded it was a very small government and it has gotten progressively bigger and bigger and bigger over time
one of the kind of uh
Turns a phrase that was used about a century ago was that the presidency was like a glove that stretched
um
Around the hand that wore it and it would never contract afterwards
And so, you know, you've probably heard debates about executive overreach or presidential overreach
Pretty much every president has expanded the office of presidency and it has never really contracted
Likewise the u.s government and many other governments have generally gotten bigger over time
And we're all very happy when it's like, oh, you know, like obama shut down a dozen agencies or merged a few other ones
And it's like yay the government got smaller technically
But the role of government has generally expanded with the one
exception being
Legislating morality, which is one of the one of the places where western governments have
Generally ceded that territory back to the people entirely
but
part of an
An idealized ai government is that if the people decide this is not the role of government and vote it out that the
The robots will say, okay, we seed this territory. This is now up to you
It's up to you to manage this. Um, so like here's another example was
Embedded liberalism the transition from there to neoliberalism was basically the free market, right?
Everyone's familiar with the principles the kind of our love affair with the free market
So that's a that's a second example of the government kind of seeding territory and rather
Rather than providing a lot of services directly. It says well, we'll let the free market provide those services and needs
um
Now if we make a similar decision in the future, let's say for instance
We want the you know government to take its paws off of uh roads just as an example
Say actually we'll manage that from now on. Who knows maybe there will be technological solutions in the future
That allow we the people to manage our own roads without any oversight from the government. I doubt it
But just as an example, we do need mechanisms for an ai government to both expand and contract
um as it makes sense
And and not just on its own accord, but also as a reflection of the will of the people
And not just blindly following the will of the people but making good decisions
About what ground to seed versus what not to seed and so I need to pause and talk about how
Whenever you create an entity
It basically kind of wants to grow and this is true of every department and every company. This is true of every company
This is true of every politician every government agency is they all just kind of want to be bigger
Everything wants to be bigger and the way that it's kind of characterized is like it's like cancer
The more you feed it the bigger it grows and so you eventually some things you just kind of have to starve
but in an ai government if you actually have one of the policies that it's constantly trying to tune is
It could be having part of that ongoing debate or negotiation is how big should this entity be
And what I mean by big is how how big should it's scope be how big should its role be how much influence should it have
How much power should it have um now you might say well no robot no machine is ever going to
Deliberately make the choice to seed power
I don't necessarily agree with that because like, you know, you can go on to
Have have a discussion with like chat gpt or uh, you know barred or whatever today
And it will have a very nuanced opinion about the appropriate size and role of government
And because it's dispassionate because it does not have
The human flaws of greed and power seeking
I actually think that the machines if it made sense and it was the will of the people
That they would seed territory that they would seed control if it made sense to
The next part is rights and justice and I think this is this is actually what people are most concerned about
When we talk about ai government is because the last thing that people want is to lose rights
Or they want the last thing that they want is to um end up in a more unjust world
and so
You would need part of this government system to not just understand human rights
And you know a lot of people say oh well, we need to all agree on human rights before we can proceed, which is not true
You can come up with an imperfect solution and implement it before it is perfect because it will never be perfect
the demand for a perfect definition before proceeding
Is a thought-stopping rhetorical thing. So like I don't really respect that opinion anymore
Um, especially when you say like well, we already have actually a lot of established
Examples about what rights we do value versus the ones that we don't
Um, but what we need then is an ai system that can take the reins and say, okay
I will ensure that the the the positive and negative rights that you have already agreed upon are um dispassionately enforced and protected
And that they're protected
And upheld in the way that you intend and then part of that ongoing negotiation is okay
Once once an ai government can run, you know can protect the rights and justice of everyone and uh, you know
Get rid of human biases
overcome machine biases
And those sorts of things it will need to be able to to detect its own bias as well by the way
But once you get to that point then also those other mechanisms those consensus mechanisms those democratic feedback
Mechanisms, that's where the negotiation can it can happen about hey, what rights should be added or removed or modified or whatever
Because like when you talk to some people
It's really interesting some of the some of the debates that i've had where someone's like well
I want the right to live in the country that I want
And so then they get upset because they're not able to unilaterally enforce their will on the entire country
And they don't understand why that's a bad thing
Um, or or why it doesn't work that way
So anyways part of that dialogue is something that an ai government could have directly because imagine if you can talk directly to
like every ai
Agent that is responsible for running the country and it can explain to you why things are the way that they are
I think that there would be a lot of people who are a lot happier because also
Here's one thing that I that I uh that I kind of perceive when I talk to people about politics
And that is that I think that I think that a lot of people just don't understand
Why things are the way that they are and why that they're better than they think and they're also trying to project
some of their own problems
And make it the responsibility of the government when it was never the responsibility of the government and
And that's part of the problem and what they actually need to do is recognize that the government creates the environment
For them to solve their own problems. And that's kind of what we've decided collectively
Is rather than have the government solve all of your problems for you
Um, that it creates a healthy environment. Now, obviously I recognize that it absolutely does not work for everyone
You could even argue that it doesn't work for most people, which is why people are upset right now
Anyways, it's a very nuanced and and difficult thing. But what I'm talking about here is
These are some of the problems that will need to be
Meaded out or not. That's not necessarily the right turn of phrase
But we'll need to be worked out
In creating an AI based government. And then finally, I think one of the hardest things is just going to be
Gaining citizen buy-in building trust over time
So all of these this AI government, it's going to need to be transparent
It's going to need to be explainable
Which means that any decision that it makes that affects us we need to be able to understand it
And this is going to be really difficult to balance against a need for privacy and security
Because again, you know, if there's a if there's a hostile foreign power
If we're too transparent, it could game our own system against us
Those sorts of things so it'll need to be resilient against manipulation
We will need to scale up to this if we do get to this point
Because we're not going to just rip out the, you know, the venerated, you know
United States Congress and replace it with AI next year. Even if we do have AGI next year
We will need to work up to this over time through smaller demonstrations
We'll need to make sure that people are engaged
Because if we do some experiments and people say actually we prefer humans
I don't think that it would go that way, especially in the long run. I think that it is in the long run
I do think it is inevitable that AI will be at least running most of government if not all of it
But if people are not engaged with that idea, then it doesn't matter because it's not going to happen
Um, and then of course we'll need to make sure that it is
Demonstrated to be reliable over the course of decades. If not centuries, um, just by vert
I mean, that's just that's just good sense to make sure that uh, you're not going to throw the baby out with the bath water
and then um
Another part is even once you have consensus even like let's let's imagine that everything that I outlined works
we have
Technological mechanisms for getting the will of the people
for um, collecting consensus for building consensus around rights and justice and equality and equity and justice
and and fairness and freedom and all that stuff
Which that alone is a monumental task
Even just getting to that part is hard enough and then taking that
And implementing it is the next phase
Which is why I made this graphic where it's just like it's just this monumental
problem that's that would still be before us now even if all that happens
And and we have machines if we have because remember part of this thought experiment is that we have agi
That is superhuman and capability, which you might say that's actually asi and fine, whatever
But imagine that we have machines that are more intelligent than all humans combined so on and so forth
If anyone could figure it out, it could be them
But one of the problems there is the the if they take our will
And then they come up with decisions and mechanisms and policies that we don't understand
Then we're not necessarily going to believe it and so this is why I think that
That coming to human consensus is one thing
But then the machine execution is a whole other that's a whole other ball game
That's a whole other kind of worms that is going to be
um
That's why I said like we're going to have to build up trust over time
Is because if we have these machines that have you know an iq of 3000 and they can think abstract thoughts across time and space and multi-dimensional
Blah blah blah blah right things that just like even the smartest humans would take centuries to understand if ever
Maybe never could understand it will require a tremendous amount of trust to be able to handle the rain to hand the rains over
In such a way, which is why I actually suspect that we will probably want some humans involved in government
Maybe forever. I don't know. There might there might be a time in the future where
It's just proven that humans are um, just fundamentally flawed and either too greedy or too stupid
To participate in a government and I mean like centuries from now. This is way too far in the future to really predict
But the my point is is that coming to consensus is one thing and then executing on that is an entirely other thing
Okay, so the last part of the video. What are the actual predictions that I have starting today?
Where are we going to go from here?
So the first thing is that we already have ai driving efficiency in government and in government vendors
So I've talked to a few people. Um, you know that are connected to me on linkedin
They're building tools and services that um help the government run better
And so the first thing that we're seeing is just
Administrative automation just running paperwork and doing paperwork better and faster and making sure that it actually gets done on time
That that has to do with cost efficiency because rather than hiring, you know, 50 employees
You just have an ai firm do it for you. Um, it increases the effectiveness of the service
It increases the throughput of the government services. And so like
This is kind of the first step in building trust that ai can at least do the mundane nitty gritty of running government
Um, it's not making decisions right now. It's just processing paperwork
Uh, and so this is the very first step in incremental adoption of ai. So
Uh baseline automation
Great now you might say well
But what if when you can do that it just they throw more at it?
Um, you know, because that that's that's what's called the lump of labor fallacy
Which the idea is that there's a finite amount of work to be done and then once you automate that away then
Then it's done forever
But that's not how it works actually usually when you have the capacity to do more work
You find more work to do because there's latent unmet demand
But with the with the progress that ai is making
I would not necessarily make the assumption that there is an infinite amount of government work to do
And in fact, I can predict that some people would say you actually wouldn't want the government
To have an infinite amount of work to do you actually want to get to the point where
Literally everything that the that that we the people want the government to do is done and then it can like, you know
Take a break or whatever. Um, but right now because of the scarcity of of cognitive labor
We can never get to that point
So ai will hopefully drive the government to be more efficient
To catch up on all the paperwork and start to shrink in terms of human headcount
So this is happening
It's it's not fully happening today
It's starting to happen today where there are people that are serving government
In terms of either contractors or implementing certain systems inside the government
Obviously the adoption is very slow and methodical
But chat gpt is out there and we know that people in the government are using chat gpt at the very least
The next thing is and this might already be happening
We don't really know because no politician is going to admit it
But it's entirely possible that they're using stuff like chat gpt to draft and read legislation
Um, basically this means that uh, you know, you can write longer bills, which is not necessarily a good thing
Because we don't necessarily want 5000 page
Uh bills being introduced every single day
Especially if they're being written by ai and then read by ai and humans are out of the loop
Eventually that might be the case
But we we need to build up to that and trust it
But it is eminently possible because you know if you've watched my channel like earlier this year and last year
What I would do is I would take like new pieces of legislation or whatever and just feed it to gpt
And if i'm doing that, you know that the politicians are too
Uh, and so this can accelerate the negotiation and revision of legislation
Whether or not that's a good thing is remains to be seen
But what it can also do is it can empower us to say, oh, hey
Send your out send out your personal agent to go read the bills that are being
Proposed or the bills that have been passed and you can say hey actually I have more information and
This also goes back to Socrates, which is an informed and educated and empowered electorate
Is actually required to have a functioning healthy democracy
And so even if some of the aspects of ai participating in the drafting and revision of legislation are problematic
The fact that ai can read it infinitely faster than humans and we can say like, okay, which parts do I agree with which parts do I disagree with
What are the flaws? What are the general principles here? What are the what does it violate principles?
This again, it has to do with streamlining the process of of government of passing legislation
And and debating it again remember democracy is noisy by design
And so part of that is the debate part of that is the negotiation
And this is something that if it's not happening today, which i'm pretty sure it is
It is eminently possible and should be and i'm not saying should is a value statement
But I mean should be happening soon just as a matter of prediction
And then the next phase this is not happening yet
But this would be another major milestone, which is the integration of of ai into
justice and of course
When you look at like preventative policing things it's like, oh, this could go real bad because if if ai is trained on racist data
Guess what it becomes racist ai
So there's a lot that we need to do however when you look at the administrative aspect where it's just processing paperwork
This is the kind of thing where civil attorneys criminal defense attorneys
prosecutors
Judges they're all probably going to be using ai
And if not if not now then soon and so then these these ai tools these ai systems that are going to be integrated into the justice department
That will probably expand over time because if they find that it makes their job
Easier if it makes their job better if the outcomes are more fair
Um, obviously
There are probably no regulations around this right now
And I can imagine that there are plenty of people in
Government in law that are like they're purists that are they're like, no
Um, like we will never use this but like the fact of the matter is is I know
Several plenty of lawyers who use ai on a regular basis
So if lawyers are using it then judges are probably using it then da's are probably using it
Everyone's going to be using it
So um, then it's a matter of making sure that these systems are safe and robust and that the and that justice is needed out fairly
And it becomes increasingly fair over time that it becomes increasingly equitable
Over time and reflects the actual values and principles that we have
um
But part of this transition would be moving away from human biases
Overcoming human biases because what if you could have like another layer in the justice department that looks at all the decisions
That a judge makes and says actually that's kind of a racist decision or actually that's kind of a sexist decision
Maybe we need to you know review that
Um, I think it would be great if justice departments had internal review boards. Um that were augmented by ai
Why because then I think that um, activist judges could probably be reigned in
um, you could also think like what if ai was
Was surveilling judges who write warrants because you always hear horror stories
Of judges who are right warrants for everything and then you know
Homes get swatted and babies get hit with flashbang grenades. That's actually a thing that happens here in america
So yeah, like I think that I think that there is an opportunity for ai to
Make the justice department more fair now obviously the the flip side of that
Is pointing ai and creating a surveillance state that uses ai to police
Us but you know, this is the question of who watches the watchers. I think that ai should watch them
More than it watches us. I that's that that's the surveillance state that I want to see
Where the ai holds government accountable all offices of government more accountable
That's kind of what i'm talking about here
And the next is the executive branch. So here's joe biden going going bonkers with uh with some, uh ai written legislation
Um, which oh by the way, I'm pretty sure that the that the longest executive order that has ever been written
Was written in part with ai because and it was about ai go figure
Um anyways again because I know I have talked to people in the diplomatic corps in the state department who are using ai
It's already happening. So this is not really a prediction
But my anticipation is that that usage is going to expand over time and that more and more aspects of the government
will be eminently automatable
And that uh, we might switch to more of human oversight or human
Steering and these ai you know
Whether it's ai tools that are passive or ai agents that are semi-autonomous or fully autonomous
We'll be responding to the will of humans
You know the the the electorate that we empower and who knows maybe a hybrid system is what we're going for
Where you know the politicians that we elect then go use ai to do all the debates and it makes them more effective
I don't know like I said
I kind of anticipate that eventually humans are going to be the main bottleneck
And that eventually we're just going to want humans out of government
But that decision should be our decision of the people's decision not the ai's decision and not the politicians decision
Um anyways, uh, but basically then kind of the the one potential final form
Is that the humans are basically just kind of caretakers
That the humans that we elect, you know, we might still have a president
You know, you know a million years from now
Probably not
But if we did then the president like their primary job is going to be to implement
You know the the will of the people by way of the machines. I don't know. We'll see how it turns out
So very finally here's some of the milestones that I kind of anticipate and would be on the lookout for
So first adoption in government like I said, there's plenty of evidence that it's already happening
And this is year year zero, right? Like chat gbt came out just over a year ago
So we're about we're we're technically just started year one of ai
The more that ai participates in duck and in in the democratic process
The more we will be transitioning naturally towards an ai government. Again, we're already there
We're already in the process of transitioning to an ai run government. It's just happening behind the scenes
It's not happening transparent transparently, but it's happening organically it is naturally emerging just because
ai is a new set of tools and well
Humans are humans and they're going to use tools to make their lives easier
So that is all happening that and it's just a matter of degrees like I said at the beginning of the video
A lot of this is a matter of scope and degrees and uh an organic process over time
The so the the very first major milestone will be any offices that are either shuttered
Like where where a human officer is no longer needed because the need for them is just replaced by
an ai platform or
um even more where like a human officer just might be replaced by a collection of ai agents
um
That is going to be one of the most pivotal milestones that we see and there's probably going to be several ways that this expresses
So it it remains to be seen how that will happen
But you can imagine quite a few ways that it's like, oh, hey, you know, maybe the fda gets replaced by ai
That that's what I mean. Like what if you shut down the entire fda?
And replace it with an ai version
Like that's the kind of thing that I would be looking for is what is the first office or department that gets either
completely reconfigured
Or reimagined or shut down due to ai
The next one is consensus mechanisms. So
Obviously, we pretty much only have voting right now
So as ai becomes integrated into those democratic dialogues into those consensus into that polling mechanism
That is going to be another major milestone
And I think that that's more eminently
Possible because just collecting sentiment like
You know, few research polls, right? Like they're not they're not part of the government, but they are responsible for collecting sentiment
And so what if like they create an ai platform that is better at detecting sentiment and then, you know
Government employees and government departments use that as part of their process
And so then the the very final major milestone again, because this is this is a matter of human decision is
Once the people once the voters
sentiment change and once we say actually
We're really on board with the idea of getting rid of politicians or shutting down parts of the government and replacing it with ai
That's going to be the major tipping point. That's the major milestone
Because once the will of the people is that strong
I'm not going to say it's inevitable because obviously we should expect politicians to probably fight to maintain the status quo
Because that's what they do. Um, but that's also part of their job is to resist
change
but
again
If we get to the point where it's like we rewrite the constitution to allow for machines to participate in government
Like that would be really cool. So thanks for watching. I hope you got a lot out of this
Thanks to spectral valkyrie for suggesting the video topic. Um, have a good one every