I think we're ready to begin um you saw me look at the camera used to be over
there now you're over here okay so I ran a poll 17 hours ago I asked if y'all
wanted me to do a video on the EU AI Act man god names gotta get better with
names I'm good with acronyms come to me for acronyms Gato Gaia ages okay anyways
so y'all were confused about what I meant by Haas which is something from
here in the south basically Haas means just something big right it's short it's
a southern dialect for horse or in particular a big horse so this document
is a Haas because look how freaking long it is it just keeps going so I plugged
it in over here and it is 70,000 tokens long so even if I had access to GPT-432
K which I did briefly and then they revoked it I think they got overwhelmed
because I used it I tried to use GPT-432 K on a couple things and it was just
like server is overloaded servers over anyways so hopefully I get that back but
the idea what there would be I could read it and you know chop it up into maybe
four sections three or four sections and read the whole thing but we don't have
that and I do have GPT-3.5 turbo 16k 0613 so this model is actually super
steerable it is actually better than original GPT-4 add a lot of things it's
still kind of dumb especially if the instructions are too complex but as long
as you give it just one task GPT-3.3.5 turbo 0613 the June 13th model is more
than adequate for most things now that being said because I'm interpreting
and I'm doing summarization I'm gonna use 04613 so the instructions that I gave
it just now and I know that I'm ready to start the video primary purpose zoom in
a little bit the primary purpose or the following is a chunk of legislation your
job is to summarize this legislation with two primary goals one drastically
reduce the word count and two retain enough context that it will still make
sense the reason for this is the current AI technology can only read chunks that
are so big method the user will give you a chunk of legislation via chat your
response must only be the summarized version do not chat with the user engage
with them or offer any other commentary summarize only so I copied the first
hundred lines of the legislation in you here and this is what it spit out so it
took all that and just said okay this is what it means so the first hundred
lines which you can see here so we've got 344,000 characters 3665 lines of
stuff to go through I'm not going to read the whole thing I'm not AI explained
that dude just like you all are impressed with how much work I can do I'm
impressed with how much that dude can read just honestly I'm maybe he uses
chat GPT I don't know anyways if you're watching it's just a joke okay so
anyways so ultimately basically that that first hundred lines was summarized
and condensed down to the European Commission proposes a regulation for
harmonized rules on artificial intelligence aiming to balance the
socioeconomic benefits of AI with potential risks the proposal seeks to
ensure AI systems are safe respect fundamental rights provide legal
certainty for investment and innovation enhance governance and prevent market
fragmentation so it has says nothing about existential risks or prevent AI
from killing everyone it's sort of implicit because like if AI kills
everyone you can't have investment in innovation but I would rather see
legislation that is explicit it proposes a risk-based approach prohibiting
certain harmful AI practices and setting requirements for high-risk AI systems
okay cool we'll see how they define that later the proposal also establishes a
governance system at member state level and a European artificial intelligence
board at union level okay cool so this is this is going to be an
international regulator great it is consistent with existing union
legislation and policies including data protection consumer protection
non-discrimination and gender equality so these are all very low-level risks
none of this is actually talking like when they say high risk they're probably
meaning like the social credit system that is used in China which that is a
high risk but it is not the highest risk the proposal is based on article 114 of
the Treaty of the Functioning of the European Union Union the TFEU which
ensures the establishment and functioning of the internal market okay so this is
mostly a market-oriented piece of legislation great so we know that this
works so let's go ahead and save this out I'm gonna walk you through the whole
process and then I'll yeah so this is this is how this is how we're gonna
proceed for those of you that are newer to my channel this is actually the
original format that I used where I would where I would walk you through the
entire process so just watch that on 2x and you'll see the whole process of how
I approach these things so we'll call this system summarize yes dot text and so
basically I give it a system a system message up with very very clear
instructions and and what I expect and and what it should expect and then it
gives you very clear consistent results so then we come over to do to do to do
to do step one simplify so this is I'm just re I'm borrowing code which I
always do so we've got this so this is what we're gonna use to do that this is
this is this is a KB service that I'm working on so I'll show you that in an
upcoming video but you don't get to see that yet we don't need KB functions so
delete that flask routes we're not gonna do a flask app so that's also fine
actually I guess I just delete most of it okay cool so we get rid of flask
cuz we're not gonna do that we're not gonna do threading we're not gonna we
don't need flask or logging or JSON or YAML okay clean it up I probably should
have done that before I started the video but it's good to it's good for you
to see how messy my process is I am the first person to tell you I am not a
professional developer I never was my professional background was I was in
virtualization and automation so I'm an automation engineer which is why I
approach things the way that I do which is creating discrete steps so you notice
the thought the title of this is step one simplify okay cool so basically what
we're gonna do is we're going to ask this handy dandy coding chatbot that I
built which you can use this it is available over here I had a bunch of
people submitting pull requests and they kept trying to like change the way that
this thing works so I just said it to public archive so here's the thing is I
welcome pull requests that are like simple fixes or small improvements don't
refactor my code just fork it right like there's 19 forks if you want to if you
want to fundamentally change how it works fine but I got tired of people
messing up my code so I just said it to public archive and guess what like
people you can still do whatever you want with it anyways so we're gonna use
this as a co-pilot tool because I got frustrated with GitHub because they're
co-pilot customer service whatever documentation is garbage okay let's see
I have here let's just write a function that accepts a gigantic string and
returns now let's see and let's see splits it by lines and then chunks 100
lines together and returns those chunks as strings so the final result will be a
list of strings each string represents 100 lines of the original okay so this
is this is my coding chatbot assistant that it uses it also uses GPT for you I
tried it you can actually switch it to oh it's using the old one hold on now I
need to update that hold on hold on that's the wrong model coding chatbot
assistant see this is what I mean is someone someone updated it oh no my
local one uses the right one so someone updated it with the wrong model and made
a bunch of other assumptions and I was just like no this is not this is not
what I wanted okay so here we go here's the function Python chunk strings line
lines equals split oh wow I did it in two lines cool this functions first splits
the string into lines using the delimiter then it uses a list comprehension
to create chunks of 100 lines each the range yep the result is a list of strings
cool excellent excellent excellent so I'm gonna go ahead and copy this out oh and
another good thing is that uh like well yeah you see how it works all right so
we'll go ahead and do that so chunk strings so first we want to just act
equals open file and I've got it named as act text just right here yep oh and
also this excuse me this this uses a scratch pad so what I can do is I can
actually populate the code that I'm working on over here so now it's aware
of what I'm working on so this scratch pad is a holdout so rather than giving it
the code in sequence the the coding chatbot actually has a it has here let me
show you the system message so here's the instructions your Python coding
assistant you know me turn on word wrap your Python coding assistant etc etc
scratch pad so basically tells you the scratch pad is usable you know so that
you know what the user is working on so that you can talk about this and this is
passed to the chatbot every time so whatever the conversation is like that
that is in the past I don't know if I'm explaining that well anyways point being
is that it see it can see the code that you're working on as long as you keep
this updated okay so that's the first hundred lines let's go ahead and see
where did it go step one simplify cool so act equals that and then we'll say
chunks equals see chunk string chunk string act all right so that this
basically creates the chunks that we're gonna be working on and that is that
let's see I'm gonna need to watch this because mmm well here let me just show
you something real quick so the first hundred lines if we take that over to
playground and paste it in here you see that a hundred lines is about 4,000
tokens so that would obviously be too big for text of inchio 3 but with with
GPT-4 we have 8,000 tokens and then with 3.5 16k we have 16,000 tokens so we
could actually probably do more but the thing is is that again 3.5 turbo is
actually you know it let's try it real quick heck with it heck with it while
we're here let's go back over to chat let's give it this chunk because if it
can if I can do it faster and cheaper why not why not and then we need this is
our system message we need to make sure that we're gonna use 3.5 turbo 16k so
that it's got enough space okay turn the temperature down we do not want you to
be creative thank you very much all right and then let's see how well it
summarizes it yeah so it's not this summarization is not nearly as elegant
or as concise but just glancing at it it's okay I think I'm gonna stick with
four but I'm glad I did this side-by-side so the the the GPT-4 it's a much more
elegant summary and it's also less worthy even though so it's not quite as
fast and it's not quite as cheap because we need to capture the essence of
something that's really important let's use the smarter model now that being
said again 3.5 turbo the the June 13th one plenty plenty good for a lot of
things okay cool so I'm glad I ran that test where are we what am I doing I don't
know I'm lost I'm always lost there's this meme it's like a pug in a field
with a wizard hat and it says that the meme is like not all who wander are
lost except Dave Dave is lost as fuck and that's me I'm the pug with a wizard
hat does that make any sense I need more coffee
okay all right I hope you find this entertaining because I just woke up and
I was like my brain's like hey we should work on this all right now we're back
here all right we've got our chunks so now what we need to do so this is this
is where it gets fun so four chunk in chunks this is super straightforward
let's see messages equals this is gonna be a list and then the role will be
user and the content wow I know how to type I promise it's just getting it from
my head to the to the hands on the keyboard to the screen that's too many
steps right now content equals chunk okay cool so basically what we're doing
right here is we're setting it up to look exactly like this so I'm putting
the chunk in here and then we also need to load the system message so what we're
gonna do is we're gonna do system equals open file system underscore
summarize so this is this is the instructions dot text so system message
is the new prompt engineering all right cool so then we'll do role system and
content is system all right so now we're ready to pass it up to our model right
here so then we'll just do response equals chatbot messages ta-da is that
simple so it's ready and so this response is going to be the summary and so
now I need to figure out how I want to save this save these summaries out in a
way that makes sense let's see let me ask my chatbot assistant okay cool great
now I want to pass a list of strings to a function and have that function save
them to a specified folder as a parameter and I want it to serialize
those files like so so it'll be like file 001 dot text file 0002 dot text and so
on let's see you should see the script I'm working on all right cool so then
we're gonna we're gonna have summaries equals list and then summaries dot
append response so now basically we're gonna have the summaries all in order
and what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna copy and paste this into my scratch pad so
that the chatbot knows what I'm working on and I'll show you how that it says oh
okay cool I probably should have told it that I'm gonna do that with the summaries
it's usually pretty good at making the inference okay cool let's see def save
strings if os path exists or if it doesn't exist make it otherwise enumerate
strings so as long as I've been using Python I'm not entirely sure how
enumerate works maybe I should ask all right but let's go over here let's go
back to my script save strings cool file I05 interesting yes see I'm not even
sure how that works fantastic let's see if it let's see if it works though the
function first checks that the specified folder exists excellent then it uses it
to make it then then iterates over the list of strings using enumerate which
provides both the index and the value okay so that's what enumerate does the
index is used to generate the file name with I colon O5 in the f string
ensuring that the index is zero padded to five digits well that was easy cool
right and then it uses the right method yeah so instead I want I was hoping it
would use my save file but that's fine so let's go to here and we're gonna do
summaries and so instead we're going to assume that that is already there and
then we are going to do file path equals I was path join folder yeah that works
and then we are going to do save file because this so my save file function
encodes it in UTF-8 so just reuse something rather than do it here because
you see this doesn't do it in UTF-8 you want to make sure that you have a nice
standardized thing that's what I'm doing here file path and s so that should be
good fine all right so save strings so then we do save strings we'll do
summaries no I need to do yes summaries and then summaries that should work now
that being said I want to print the response as I get them there we go and
then response all right let's give this a whirl and see if it works CD what is this
EU AI act zoom in a little bit Python step 01 this will probably take a while
because we've got 3,000 line 3300 lines there we go cool hmm hold on oh right
right right I forgot about this okay so this is an important thing what I started
doing and I forgot to integrate this so what I started doing is I when I whenever
I call the chatbot I return the text and the token use so because this is
actually really helpful if you just go ahead and return the tokens so that you
know when to summarize it so instead what I need to do is response tokens
because I don't need to save I don't need to save a tuple out here but this
otherwise looks good and then what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go grab something
to make the the printout look a little bit better
to do to do to do to do reflective journaling tool this one has this one
has good pretty output so we're gonna do formatted lines yep so take the formatted
lines here and then we'll do print new line new line new line and formatted
lines all right so that will that'll make it that'll make it prettier and then
we'll also use so this this is this is why I appreciate when people add feedback
is we added someone added the halo which is a little like thing that shows that
it's thinking so I'm gonna add that real quick as well and the way that you use
that is down here
and so once once this is running I'll pause the video so you don't have to
watch the whole thing so you're actually probably closer to the end if I had to
guess
oops spinner start so we'll say summarizing next chunk and then spinner stop
okay so let's try this make sure it works
summarizing next chunk hey look now it gives us some output better user
experience it tells me what it's doing text wrap is not defined whoops what do
you mean I need to import everything that you use import text wrap try that
again third time's a charm all right and if this works then I'll go ahead and
pause it and then we'll come back once the whole video is or once the whole
thing is done why is it in hold on hold on that's not right why are you giving
me this garbage that's not correct oh right I need to print out formatted
text my bad
don't give me this nonsense because basically what you want to do is you
want to have it formatted in such a way there we go see so now we have this nice
little block it's easier to read all right cool so this is working we'll watch
it just a couple times you see how fast it is the the June 13th update is much
much faster let's see excellent excellent excellent so we will I'm gonna pause the
video and we'll come back and and take a look at the final result cheers okay and
we're back so after running it all here let me just show you what the results
were we've got 37 files each with a summary and I wrote a really quick I
hacked together a really quick script that merged them all and so the merged
result is 34,000 characters long so we reduced it by a factor of 10 to 1 just
just shy of 10 to 1 which when you plug that in over here that's 6,000 tokens so
we went from from 60,000 or 70,000 tokens I don't remember exactly to 6,000
tokens one of the reasons that we had a more drastic reduction reduction of
token count is because we removed all the serial numbers and stuff because
that's kind of superfluous if you if you remove symbols and stuff like this
these are high token things if it's ordinary words like AI and each system
these are easy for the model to tokenize so that means what we can do now is we
can just take this whole thing and come over to chat and say let's see main
purpose here turn it believe that you are a chatbot tasked with discussing the
following legislation with the user make sure to well hell but I mean that
that's all it is use the legislation summary below to conduct the conversation
and that's it and so then we say a legislation summary and we'll copy paste
it here and so then we move over to we could do 16k because that'll be that'll
be faster actually here let's try that real quick let's try that temperature
there okay give me a high level overview of this legislation blah blah blah
okay cool we're new after five years how is it funded let's see the funding and
implementation of this legislation comes from the multi-annual financial
framework blah blah blah the financial impact includes allocation of resources
and having watched it go through how many employees will it cost there we go
ten full-time equivalent employees all right so we can clear that out just
because it ultimately is superfluous so some of the questions let's see will
this legislation hamper research and innovation let's see the legislation
aims to balance the benefits of AI research and innovation with the need
for safety and respect for fundamental rights it includes measures to support
innovation such as AI regulatory sandboxes and reducing the regulatory burden
on SMEs and startups so the SMEs are going to be subject matter experts like
UNI as well as startups the goal is to provide legal certainty and prevent
market fragmentation which can actually foster innovation by creating a level
playing field for AI developers however it imposes certain requirements and
obligations on high-risk AI how does this legislation define high-risk AI
let's see this legislation categorizes AI systems into three risk levels
unacceptable high and low or minimal high-risk AI is based on their intended
purpose and usage while the specific criteria may vary high-risk AI generally
include those use the safety components of products covered by union
harmonization legislation as well as AI used in critical infrastructure
management education vocational training employment and workers
management these high-risk AI systems are subject to requirements what are
unacceptable types the legislation prohibits certain AI practices that are
considered unacceptable due to their potential to violate fundamental rights
while the specific types may vary some examples include manipulate human
behavior exploit vulnerabilities or enable social scoring by public
authorities right so as I mentioned social credit system these practices are
deemed harmful freedom dignity democracy equality and fundamental rights okay
cool does this legislation address existential risk at all does it address
autonomous AI the legislation does not explicitly address existential risk or
autonomous AI systems wow okay now one thing that I will say is that if you look
at the legislation it does talk about like basically human supervision yeah
so like AI regulatory sandbox by one or more member stages no like here where
was it and talked about not supervision of the sandboxes but like AI systems
basically need to be steerable it's in there somewhere okay but let's see it
does not specifically address the potential risk associated with highly
autonomous or super intelligent AI systems that could pose existential
threats however the legislation's emphasis on risk management human
oversight oh that's what it was oversight not supervision and robustness
requirements for high-risk AI systems indirectly contributes to addressing the
safety concerns associated with AI technologies it is important to note
that addressing existential risk related to AI may require further research
discussions and potentially additional regular to regulations in the future okay
cool so there you have it this file is saved on as merged dot text let me go
ahead and send that up to get so you can all use it let's see get status I get
add get commit AM all done get push all right so there you have it you have a
much condensed version of the EU act here and merged you can plug it
into the playground and ask questions to your heart's content if you have access
to it but otherwise you can at least just read it here yeah I think we're all
done thanks for watching