Ladies and gentlemen, it is my great privilege on this occasion to present Edward Whitten
for his plenary address, string theory, and geometry.
As you may have noticed, the program of this Congress, the Berkeley Mathematical Congress
of 1986, differs from its predecessors in the much greater emphasis given to the relationship
of mathematics to the sciences, both natural and artificial, to physics and to computer science.
This is true particularly of the plenary addresses, but also of the remainder of the
program. And it reflects in my view a profound change which has taken place in the
structure of mathematics at its cutting edge, what has been described by some of my equativeness
as a profound reconvergence of mathematics for the sciences. Edward Whitten epitomizes this
tendency in his sharpest form. By training in profession, he is a physicist, he is a professor
in the Department of Physics at Princeton, and by achievement, he is physicist at the highest
level, and a mathematician at the highest level. He has been one of the leading workers in recent
years in the ongoing development of string theory. He has been one of the, perhaps, the leader in
introducing ideas of conceptual originality and mathematical sophistication and that theory.
And he has also used those ideas in a very remarkable way to get important mathematical
results of a high degree of originality, both in concept and execution. In their lectures,
both Richard Schoen and Izzy Singer have referred to some of these results.
Another one to which they have not referred is his highly original proof of the Morse inequalities
using the eigenvalues of Laplacians on manifolds, the first original proof of that set of ideas
in 50 years. The material of which he is going to speak reflects one of the most powerful trends
in contemporary mathematics and the most powerful and sometimes controversial trend in theoretical
physics. The development of fundamental ideas concerning the unity of the theory of fundamental
particles and of gravitation in a highly sophisticated and elaborated mathematical form.
We welcome him here as a symbol of this movement, which will continue, I am sure,
in even sharper forms in the decades to come. Professor Whitten.
Professor Whitten.
In 20th century physics, there have been two really basic ingredients,
which are first of all general relativity, which is Einstein's theory of gravity,
and secondly quantum field theory, which is the basic framework for our understanding of
essentially everything else in physics other than gravitation.
Though they both play a role in a description of the same natural world,
these two theories enjoy their successes in very different realms.
General relativity has its successes in the realm of astronomy, and quantum field theory
is the framework for successful descriptions of many aspects of the properties of atoms,
molecules, and subatomic particles. Most of the really important developments
in fundamental physics since about 1930 have been developments in quantum field theory,
or certainly in quantum mechanics, and for much of this time physics and mathematics
had relatively little interaction compared to that in many previous epochs.
One obvious reason for this perhaps is that in the 20th century mathematics advanced into
seemingly abstract realms unrelated perhaps it would seem to the humdrum world of the theoretical
physicist, but I think in large part the reason that the interaction of mathematics and physics
was more limited in the last half century than in previous epochs was because the physical
problems that arose in quantum field theory, which was the central framework for most
progress in physics, did not seem to give rise to many interesting mathematical structures.
By the mid-1970s this changed mainly because of developments in physics. By the mid-1970s
the quantum field theories which had emerged to play a central role in physics were the so-called
non-abillion gauge theories, theories in which one of the main ingredients is a vector bundle
over space-time with a non-abillion structure group. These theories raised more interesting
and significant issues in geometry and topology causing a more significant interaction of physics
and geometry starting about 10 years ago perhaps than had been possible during most of the epoch
in which quantum field theory played its central role in physics. In fact one of many strands leading
to Donaldson's work, which we heard about a couple of days ago, originated from this interaction
of physics and geometry. Now progress in quantum field theory led by perhaps a decade ago to the
beginning of an enriched interaction of physics and geometry, but I believe that all the same this
interaction would remain relatively limited if it were only a question of quantum field theory.
It's really in trying to go beyond the limits of quantum field theory that physicists have come
upon mathematical frontiers. Perhaps the fundamental limitation of quantum field theory
is the one I've already alluded to. It's only one of two fundamental theories in physics
and in fact quantum field theory turns out to be incompatible with that other basic ingredient in
20th century physics which is general relativity. You can attempt formally to combine these two
theories by so-called quantization of general relativity, but this leads to all kinds of
nonsensical formulas. Now in the early days of quantum field theory it was not at all obvious
that this was a central problem. Quantum field theory faced many problems in its early days.
It wasn't even obvious at the outset that the quantum theory of electricity,
quantum field theory of electricity, which was the original quantum field theory,
really made any sense. In time though the other difficulties of quantum field theory were overcome
and it became clear that quantum field theory was an adequate framework for describing all
of the forces of nature except gravity. Though in the course of learning how to do so,
physicists were led to develop quantum field theories with a richer geometrical contents,
such as the non-ability engaged theories I alluded to previously. As the other difficulties
of quantum field theory were overcome the incompatibility with general relativity emerged as
the limitation of this framework. Now general relativity is based of course on Riemannian
geometry which is certainly one of the richest frameworks for our understanding of ordinary
geometry and asserting that general relativity which is based on Riemannian geometry is incompatible
with quantum field theory. It must mean that some proper physical theory which will successfully
generalize general relativity and reconcile it with quantum field theory must in some way
be based on some generalization of Riemannian geometry compatible with the requirement of
quantum mechanics. Now experiments can only provide us with indirect clues about how we
should go beyond ordinary Riemannian geometry as a framework in physics and the reason for this is
that to our great regret gravitational effects are unmeasurably small in experiments that probe
quantum field theory and the same is true the other way around. There is actually only one example
in the previous history of physics in which a theory was invented even though the experimental
clues were only indirect. The one other success of that nature was general relativity itself
it was discovered in what we might call a logical way Einstein first beginning only with the very
general clue which was that special relativity was incompatible with gravity. Einstein first
formulated the physical ideas for reconciling two inconsistent theories then found the right
mathematical framework which was general Riemannian geometry and finally he invented the theory.
Now of course we'd like to emulate this history but that is easily said than done many ambitious
physicists and mathematicians have gone off into the wilderness in search of some fundamental
generalization of geometry that would reconcile gravity with quantum mechanics but generally
speaking they've come back empty handed if at all. While direct assaults on this problem have yielded
little progress seems to have fallen from the sky essentially through the largely chance discovery
of something called string theory. Now the people who invented string theory beginning in the late
1960s weren't aspiring to reconcile general relativity with quantum mechanics they weren't
hoping to generalize Riemannian geometry in fact the ambitions were not in the realm of our
discussion at all. String theory was originally developed as a theory of the so-called strong
interactions the nuclear forces that keep nuclei together despite the electric repulsion among
protons. Even as a theory of strong interactions string theory was discovered largely by accident
following its discovery which essentially occurred when one of the formulas in string
theory was written down by Veneziano with very slender motivation in 1968. Following the essentially
accidental discovery it was vigorously developed in this early period drawing which upwards of
500 papers were written led to an extremely rich mathematical structure which fascinated people
by its richness yet never advanced toward solving the original problem which motivated this work of
strong interactions and in fact this whole line of development was abruptly abandoned by most
physicists around 1974 when it became clear that it was not the correct approach to strong interactions.
While it was generally abandoned because of not being the solution of the original physical
problem the structure retained its fascination provoking work in various areas and eventually
being revived in the 1980s as an approach to quantum gravity. Now this subject has already
an extremely long and complex history and I fear that if I tried to survey even the high points of
this history it would take the rest of the lecture. I've written here some of the dates and
names of some of the main developments but it would be impractical to explain even a few of them
completely. I will be talking about some ingredients from some of these developments
but I'm not going to attempt to explain this history.
Now as I've indicated string theory essentially fell from the sky by chance
with some special formulas of this theory being discovered with a rather strange motivation
and it gradually being learned that these formulas were special cases of a richer structure
in which one has penetrated in times deeper levels but probably not very far toward the
deepest levels that underlie this theory. The situation in string theory is roughly as if
Romani and geometry had been sorry it's roughly as if general relativity had been invented without
having first invented the logical framework for this theory which is Romani and geometry.
Einstein happens to have followed Riemann but it's imaginable to have conceived of a planet
where the problem that Einstein posed of reconciling gravity with special relativity
would have existed on a planet where general relativity was unknown. Conceivably on such a
planet general relativity would somehow be invented in some obscure way without its logical
underpinnings Romani and geometry being clear. Whether or not that's happened on some planets
in the universe in which theoretical physics may have been developed it certainly has happened
on planet earth in the case of string theory. Because of the peculiar way that string theory
has been discovered I cannot do what I would dearly love to do and a lot of hope will be done
by some speaker at some future congress of the international congress of mathematicians
which is to explain the basic concepts of curvature connections and Romani and manifolds
which should play in string theory the role that Romani and geometry plays in general relativity.
I can try to explain some of what presumably are the preliminaries for this theory
and in sketching what I mean by these preliminaries perhaps I'll give you an
analogy with general relativity. In Romani and geometry one has some curved manifold
and if you consider at a point the tangent space to this curved manifold of course the
tangent space is a linear space and one thing you certainly have to be able to do in order
to work with Romani and geometry is to understand a little bit of elementary linear algebra
so that you can carry out linear operations in the tangent space. Roughly speaking our present
understanding of string theory was as if we were trapped in the tangent space of Romani and manifold
not understanding the basic frameworks that we would need the basic logical concepts that we
would need to go coherently beyond linear operations in the tangent space.
So the analog and string theory what the role which is played by linear algebra as a preliminary
to work in the tangent space of Romani and manifold that role the analogous role is played
in string theory by much richer mathematical structures which are the theory of Riemann
surfaces modular forms and what I will loosely describe as infinite dimensional representation
theory. Roughly speaking just as one needs a little linear algebra before trying to learn
Romani and geometry so one needs to know something about Riemann surfaces and infinite
dimensional representation theory before trying to learn string theory. So we could say that
general relativity requires linear algebra for its linear approximation but the fundamental ideas
in the theory are really connections curvature and Romani and geometry. String theory requires
Riemann surfaces and infinite dimensional representation theory for its linear approximation
and what should really belong in the lower right hand corner of that square is I think to my thinking
and the thinking of many other physicists really the central problem in theoretical physics.
Now I've stressed the incompatibility of quantum field theory with gravity but in fact there are
certain other problems in our understanding of physics that we would like to overcome
and one of the most fundamental problems is simply that there are too many conceivable
theories permitted by the general principles that we have. Quantum field theory would permit
an infinity of theories and the logical framework of general relativity would also permit an
infinity of theories of which Einstein's is only the prototype. Of course if you try combining
these two frameworks you have not an infinity of theories but zero which is the assertion
that they're incompatible but if you could have combined quantum field theory with general
relativity with no particular difficulties then you actually would have had an infinity of possible
descriptions of the natural world which certainly would mean some basic gaps in your understanding.
So in a sense the blessing there might be a blessing in disguise in the difficulty of
reconciling these two frameworks either would separately permit an infinity of theories together
they seem to permit none and hopefully the proper understanding will lead to a finite set of theories
that reconcile them. To briefly illustrate what I mean in saying that the general ideas of
Romanian geometry would permit an infinity of theories the basic concept in general relativity
is really that spacetime which I'll call m is a pseudo-Romanian manifold it has a metric tensor g
and Riemann tensor the Ritchie scalar is what I've called r. Einstein's basic principle
was to describe nature by some geometrical action principle some geometrical integral
over spacetime was to be the action of this theory and while he wrote the simplest action
there are an infinity of more general action principles more general geometrical
invariance integrated over m that would give conceivable generalizations of general relativity
within the logical framework in some sense you might consider this to be the most
elementary member of the clan but when you consider another point which I'm about to
allude to presently in fact what has an infinity of theories without a evident most elementary example
so apart from the inconsistency of quantum field theory and general relativity we would
certainly like to overcome the fact that either of those separately leave us with too many theories
in fact with an infinity of conceivable theories to illustrate the other deficiency of general
relativity let me briefly discuss almost flat solutions of this theory of course in everyday
life we don't notice that spacetime is curved spacetime is flat in everyday life and of course you
can do a better job of probing for curvature if you measure over larger and larger scales
every romanian manifold is almost flat on a small scale gauss as many of you know measured the
angles between three high mountains and found pi as the sum confirming that one mount on the scale
of the alps spacetime is roughly flat and astronomers do much better on even larger scales
so we introduce as a good approximate description the flat metric eta the diagonal metric with these
eigenvalues we imagine a small deviation h from a flat metric we write the spacetime metric
as the min-count metric plus a small fluctuation
well if we insert this form of the metric in the Einstein equations we'll get a non-linear
equation but since spacetime is nearly flat let's linearize it if we linearize it we will get some
linear equation for h which will be some perturbation of the Laplace operator acting on h giving zero
well this equation has wave-like solutions the simplest being the plane wave I've written here
and these wave-like solutions are quite analogous to the corresponding wave-like solutions of Maxwell's
equations which are light waves so in this way we learned that general relativity permit predicts
gravitational waves a prediction of that theory which emerged clearly when the theory was formulated
in 1915 though it had been conjectured by Poincare some 10 years earlier and incidentally a prediction
which was finally tested indirectly by observations of radio waves from pulsars just a few years ago
now when this prediction was made it was a prediction of a new type of wave not a new
type of particle but in fact in quantum mechanics waves and particles are two facets of the same thing
so this prediction of a new kind of wave is actually a prediction of a new kind of particle
Einstein merely aspired to reconcile gravitational forces with special relativity
but in trying to do so he actually predicted a unified
not just a theory of gravitational forces but a unified theory of gravity and matter
gravitational forces were unified with this peculiar new kind of matter which was predicted
namely gravitational waves the Einstein wasn't satisfied with his unifications since he eventually
hoped to unify gravitational forces not with some exotic form of matter that he predicted but unknown
at the time but with the forms of matter that were known about so this is often described by
saying that Einstein didn't succeed in unifying gravity with matter but a better statement would
be to say that on a logical plane he unified gravitational forces with matter but wasn't
satisfied with the form of matter that the resulting theory predicted
so on a conceptual plane it's a great triumph that merely trying to describe gravitational
forces finding the logical framework which is romanian geometry writing down the simplest
equations in that framework which are nonlinear equations one then found that one had not merely
a theory of gravitational forces but a unified theory that unified gravitational forces with matter
however this wonderful unified theory has a couple of flaws it's incompatible with quantum field
theory that of course wasn't known at the time since quantum field theory was invented later
but evident even at the time was that the forms of matter predicted in this theory
were less rich than those that we observe
now I would next like to give a heuristic account of why string theory might what string theory is
and why it might be hoped to improve upon general relativity the framework for this really does
require some preliminaries about quantum field theory and I do hope to give a brief
comment about quantum field theory later
but without developing all the requisite preliminaries of quantum field theory
I would like to at least explain heuristically how one stumbles upon some generalization
of general relativity in the form of string theory
and in doing so I will be explaining conventional things in quantum field theory
in a way which is closely related essentially to the viewpoint introduced by poliakov some years
ago well in quantum field theory the scattering of particles such as the gravitons of general
relativity are described by Feynman diagrams now a Feynman diagram is a spacetime history of a
scattering process in this transparency I've sketched a scattering a spacetime history
time runs vertically on the diagram space or one of the space dimensions at least runs horizontally
particles have been emitted and absorbed at these points a b c and d the solid lines are actually
curves in spacetime along which a particle traveled and x y z and w denote points in
spacetime at which one particle split into two or in which two particles recombined into one
so this actually is a sketch of a sequence of events in spacetime
and if you start with some theory like general relativity
then the rules of quantum field theory will give you
algorithms for associating probabilities with spacetime history such as that one
actually you start with some abstract graph gamma and then you imagine some map of gamma
into spacetime which i'll call capital x x denotes a map of gamma into spacetime
of course this graph gamma is a collection of intervals if we map such an interval into
spacetime we can compute its arc length and the sums of those arc lengths is what i'll call i of x
the length of the image of this map graph gamma in spacetime under some map in which gamma is
mapped into x of gamma so let omega of gamma be the space of all maps of the graph gamma into
spacetime now in conventional quantum field theory of the last 50 years
even though this isn't quite the conventional way of describing the usual structures one almost
injured way to describe the usual thymine diagrams is as integrals over this path space omega of gamma
so we have an abstract graph gamma we map it into here i've sketched the image of that graph
such a map omega gamma is the base of all such maps i is the length of the image of the graph
under that map we try to integrate over omega of gamma e to the minus the length of the image of the
map times some facts i'll explain presently the local factors at the branch points in the graph
now one thing you'll note here is that infinite dimensional integral the integral over the
space omega of gamma of all conceivable maps of this graph into spacetime all conceivable
continuous maps of gamma into spacetime that's a characteristic infinite dimensional integral
that appears in prime and path integral formulations of quantum mechanics in quantum field theory
now one thing which we'll notice here is that when we're mapping this graph gamma into spacetime
gamma is not a manifold it's almost a one-dimensional manifold but actually it's a
one-dimensional manifold with singularities p q r and s and the ills of quantum field theory
all come about because gamma isn't a one-dimensional isn't a manifold but has singularities
we're taking this graph which is a one manifold with singularities we're mapping it into spacetime
and two bad things happen because of the fact that gamma isn't a manifold
first of all well we have to define this infinite dimensional integral and in fact
there is a there's a lot of experience and even some theorems in constructive field theory
about defining such infinite dimensional integrals and one thing we know about it
is that it will work a lot more nicely if you tried mapping a smooth one manifold into spacetime
rather than a graph with singularities when we map such a graph into spacetime we encounter
the possibility that the image of p q r and s in spacetime make coincide and in fact after
we've learned to define such infinite dimensional integrals in the first place we learned that
this integration is badly behaved near the region where x of p x of q up to x of s all coincide
this bad behavior makes all quantum field theories difficult to define but actually
impossible in the case of general relativity so our first problem in quantum field theory
its overall mathematical difficulty and in particular its incompatibility with gravity
arises because gamma isn't a manifold secondly because gamma isn't a manifold we have these
special points p q r and s and uh we had a nice simple factor in the integrand the exponential
of minus the area minus the length of the image of gamma in spacetime but since there are these
special points p q r and s it makes sense as those points are singled out to take some local
functional of the behavior of x near one of those points phi here is a local functional of x of p
and the derivatives of x near p
it makes sense to pick such a local functional and introduce a factor in the integrand at each of
those singular points p q r and s and in fact with certain very simple limitations each choice of
this local functional phi of p gives you a different quantum field theory the infinity of quantum
field theories corresponds to the infinity of local factors that can be introduced at those branch
points well of course you might think that we're straining things a bit and that there would be
a minimal model where we don't introduce these factors but one of the surprises perhaps is that
that isn't true if you take a nice geometrical theory like general relativity and yang mills theory
and transform it into this framework you'll definitely need some suitable local factors
at those points and on the contrary the theories that wouldn't have those local factors or would
have simple local factors turn out to be quantum field theories that don't have interesting
geometrical content so this is a freedom not only it exists in principle but we have to use it and
we do use it for the quantum field theories that are of most interest in physics so we have a variety
of problems which have their origin in the fact that gamma isn't a manifold suppose though that we
wish to ask an engineering shop let's say to make a physical model of the graph gamma well we probably
to find this graph as consisting of mathematical lines but the craftsman doesn't have mathematical
lines at his disposal so perhaps if we're lucky he uses thin tubes
and if he uses hollow tubes and joins them smoothly as a plumber does
then we can replace this graph by something for which it's more easy to make a physical model
which looks very similar from a big distance and that is actually why string theory if you'd
coarsely looks rather like quantum field theory but there's a fundamental difference in replacing
these mathematical lines with little tubes we've replaced the one manifold with singularity gamma
by the smooth remun surface sigma now in some sense in some sense the graph gamma
may be an approximation to sigma but the fundamental difference is that sigma is a smooth
manifold which gamma isn't and as a result in replacing gamma with sigma we will we in fact
overcome both the infinities in quantum field theory and also the lack of uniqueness the lack of
uniqueness came from the ability to attribute special factors with these points upon losing
those special points we in fact encounter a situation in string theory where we replace gamma
with sigma in which there are very few theories that can be formulated
now
the other main occurrence which arises when we replace gamma with sigma
let's take a close-up of this picture which I won't draw completely
remember this is actually a picture of a process occurring in spacetime
so time is running upwards in the picture and this graph gamma which I've drawn is actually
happening in spacetime it actually describes the propagation in spacetime of point particles
which for general relativity are the quantum counterparts of the waves that I sketched earlier
so I'm going to take a blow-up of a little piece of that picture
our blow-up is the propagation of a particle in time in spacetime if we take its locus at given
time we get a single point or at most a finite set of points the fact that we might get a finite
set of points instead of a single point leads to the fascinating story of creation of matter and
antimatter or perhaps it would take us too far afield to discuss it so I'll imagine that we find
the locus at a given time to be a single point and that corresponds to saying that this graph
is a theory of a point particle propagating in spacetime if in the same way we take the locus
at fixed time of one of these tubes it consists of a circle or perhaps a finite collection thereof
so we've actually replaced the point particle of field theory with
the oscillating circle you see I remarked that on a conceptual plane Einstein had unified
gravitational forces with some kind of matter but the matter in question wasn't rich enough
and it wasn't rich enough essentially because that point particle which was the locus of a
curve at given time didn't have enough freedom when we replace our graph with a Riemann surface
sigma the locus at given time isn't a point or finite collection of points but consists of
circles and one of those circles or in that case closed strings will be rather like a
violin string except without fixed endpoints physically it will oscillate in time and like
a violin string it will have an infinite set of harmonics which will correspond to different forms
of matter so in fact replacing gamma with the Riemann surface sigma means that one is dealing
with a theory with much richer forms of matter it's not at all obvious from what I've said that
these richer forms of matter will be at all like what we find in the real world but upon closer
investigation it turns out that they are so the seemingly innocent step of replacing gamma by sigma
leads us to a more unique theory with also a much richer form of matter
and it leads us at the same time into the world of Riemann surfaces and modular forms
and representation theory of certain infinite dimensionally algebras such as diff s1 the group
of difumorphisms of s1 which will act on this circle now I have another transparency which aims
at recapitulating what I've been saying so in a theory like general relativity we have really
basic formulas like the geometrical action principle the integral over spacetime of the
Ritchie scalar the beauty or lack of beauty of such a theory should be judged by the beauty of
its fundamental principles our aspiration would be to generalize this elegant action
geometrical action principle to some richer structure that will be compatible with quantum
field theory a direct and even indirect attempts to do so haven't been successful on the other hand
if we consider not the really fundamental formulas of Riemannian geometry but some drive formulas
such as the ones I've been discussing involving maps of graphs gamma into spacetime
then it turns out that some of the drive formulas can be generalized
now of course if at the top of everyone's mind was that we think of general relativity in terms
of maps of graphs into spacetime then this generalization would be more obvious and perhaps
would have happened sooner what makes it less obvious is that although this is closely related
to standard descriptions of what one gets from quantum field theory it's not the most standard
description by any means I haven't explained the steps in quantum field theory which lead from
fundamental formulas to less fundamental formulas involving these graphs it's possible to explain
it but would have taken an excessively long exposition if we work on this less refined plane
we find we can generalize the less fundamental formulas of quantum field theory getting something
called string theory which overcomes many of the difficulties for instance the lack of uniqueness
of quantum field theory which in this framework arose from the fact that the Ritchie scalar is
only one of many possible geometrical action principles in this less refined framework
is associated with the fact that gamma isn't a graph sorry gamma is a graph but not a manifold
and that is eliminated in going to Riemann surfaces and so on with other points I've already
illustrated so what has happened in the invention of string theory is that in a peculiar process
of trial and error with many historical stages one has succeeded in generalizing not the truly
fundamental formulas of older physical theories but some of the derived formulas
now just as
this picture with the graph gamma is to be derived from some much more fundamental viewpoints
the same ought to be true with our generalization of it involving Riemann surfaces
and elucidating what lies above the Riemann surface in the sense that general relativity
lies above these graphs is what I've alluded to as the mystery of unraveling the logical structure
behind string theory and I personally believe that it's a very fundamental problem for both
mathematics and physics one peculiarity is that ordinarily the beauty of a theory is to be judged
by its fundamental principles and not to be looked for in these derived formulas derived formulas
like the ones involving graphs and maps of graphs into spacetime are necessary tools if you want to
determine the quantitative predictions of a beautiful theory like general relativity but
they're not the basic formulas and they're not necessarily beautiful in fact they're ordinarily
not beautiful one of the surprises in string theory is that the Riemann surface generalization
of the theory of those graphs is very beautiful involves fascinating properties of Riemann surfaces
modular forms infinite dimensional representation theory algebraic geometry some of the many
beautiful aspects of this were described in a marvelous article by manin which was submitted
to this conference but which regrettably he wasn't able to deliver here because of not being allowed
to attend the conference but singer presented them very elegantly in a talk on tuesday afternoon
it comes one shouldn't expect beauty in trying to generalize a secondary formula
but actually in the case of string theory one finds that the generalization of this picture
with the graphs leads to very fascinating and beautiful mathematics and I personally would get
conjecture that what lies above here will in some sense stand in the same relation to general
relativity that the marvelous automorphic forms and algebraic geometry that enters in Riemann surfaces
uh path integrals Riemann surfaces compares to the Euler Feynman diagrams of field theory
now I haven't uh been able to explain how one goes from here to here that would be
rather too time-consuming I do want to use the remaining terms to the remaining time
to explain briefly a little bit of the flavor of what it means when we talk about the maps over
into infant dimensional spaces that are involved in dealing with these graphs gamma or the Riemann
surface sigma in their own terms so in the rest of this talk we're going to be working on this lower
half of the page without discussing how this one is associated with conventional field theory
now in doing this I will be giving a very brief uh introduction to quantum field theory
since I will have to attempt to extract one or two ideas in about 15 minutes
you see quantum field theory exists on the upper half of this page because
we started with quantum gravity or attempted quantum gravity in going here but quantum field
theory lives again at the lower half of this page because these infinite dimensional integrals
are really formulas in quantum field theory now quantum field theory has been for most of its
60 years almost the private preserver physicists and even now it has not yet emerged as a mathematical
tool but there are reasons to believe that quantum field theory might emerge as a mathematical tool
in the near future reasons independent of string theory for believing that because there are at
least two areas where progress in mathematics has come to the brink of quantum field theory
that is areas of mathematics where some characteristic features of quantum field
theory have begun to be recognized as significant one of these is the representation theory of
affine lee algebras which frankle reviewed yesterday and which is closely related to the
hamiltonian picture of certain quantum field theories and the other involves recent work in
arithmetic geometry which we will hear about in the next lecture where the derock determinant
which is one of the really fundamental characteristic ingredients in quantum field theory
has begun to play an important role
so in a choice of topics for an extremely brief comment on quantum field theory i'm going to
talk about points that are in string theory but might prove to be related in further developments
to the areas of mathematics i've just mentioned let then sigma be a Riemann surface perhaps with
boundary let phi taking sigma into the real numbers r be a real valued function and then let's define
an action very natural action which is called the action functional of free boson field theory
the integral over sigma of this two form del phi wedge del bar phi where del and del bar are the
del bar the natural operators associated with a complex structure on sigma
that f be a real valued function on the boundary of sigma and that omega sub f of sigma
be the space of real valued functions on sigma whose restriction to the boundary coincides with f
now we didn't need a Riemannian metric on sigma in defining the action i but if sigma
is endowed with a Riemannian metric and not just with a conformal structure then this affine space
omega f of sigma likewise has a natural metric which i've defined here by giving the distance
between two functions phi and phi prime now in finite dimensions a Riemannian metric certainly
induces a measure the so-called square root of the determinant if you wish to write it in formulas
and hoping that that works in infinite dimensions we might try to define what i call z sub f of sigma
which is the integral of e to the minus the action over the space of functions whose
restriction to the boundary coincides with f that's what i call it omega f of sigma
the integration measure is the one which we hope was induced by that Riemannian metric on sigma
well how are we going to integrate in infinite dimensions well physicists actually deal with
infinite dimensional integrals that are very difficult to define mathematically in which you
can't write explicit formulas but i happen for practice to have given you one for which we can
write an explicit formula i in this case was a quadratic functional of phi so we're integrating
the exponential of minus a quadratic functional that's a Gaussian integral and we know that
Gaussian integrals are integrals which are easy to evaluate in finite dimensions let a be a
quadratic form in finite dimensions if we're integrating in finite dimensions the exponential
of minus a quadratic form we can carry out that explicitly in terms of the square root of the
determinant of a or if we have a natural basis in phi so it makes sense to speak of eigenvalues
of a we can write the answer in terms of eigenvalues of a so we can try to interpret
Gaussian integrals in infinite dimensions in a similar way first consider the case where the
boundary of sigma is 0 the same action i wrote earlier can be written like so in a way that
makes the conformal invariance less obvious but some of the differential geometry more obvious
perhaps what the operator that appears here is the ordinary Laplacian
and delta plays the role of our quadratic form in finite dimensions so we should study the eigenvalue
problem delta phi equals lambda phi it's a nice eigenvalue problem a nice discrete set of eigenvalues
and formally we would like to define our integral as the product of the minus half powers of the
eigenvalues well of course this has a zero eigenvalue which we should throw away and it also is a
little bit divergent because of the infinite factor but nonetheless there are many natural ways of
regularizing this one elegant way of doing it is so-called zeta function regularization
we introduce the zeta function as sum over eigenvalues lambda to the minus s and then we
write a formula which would be correct in finite dimensions if this were finite sum
with an infinite set of eigenvalues the zeta function converges for a large enough real part
of s and we take here its analytic continuation to s equals zero this would be our zeta function
definition and there are many other definitions such as the polyvlar's method used in quantum
field theories some 40 years ago if now the boundary of sigma is not empty and we're given
a real valued function on the boundary we'd like more generally to define the integral not
over all maps of a segment of spacetime but only maps of segments are but only maps which coincide
with f on the boundary well for f equals zero what we've already said is quite adequate
for f equals zero we're still integrating a Gaussian integral on a linear space
we study the eigenvalue problem with boundary conditions that the eigenvalue vanishes on the
boundary and we make again the same definition
if f isn't zero then by classical theorems we find some unique there's a unique minimum
of this functional subject to the condition that the boundary value is equal to phi
let phi not be the extremizing function and that our integration variable phi be
phi not plus m correction
then we can easily work out by manipulations that would be valid in finite dimensions
the appropriate formulas it turns out in this case that the action because it's quadratic
for phi is the sum of the separate pieces and if phi has boundary value f then phi prime has
boundary value zero show shifting the integration variable from phi to phi prime we would work out
a formula now in reaching this point we've needed a metric on sigma we needed to claim that these
spaces um omega of sigma had had measures and we induced the measures from Riemannian
structures on sigma so since we need matrix on sigma to reach this point
these formulas are actually not conformally invariant if we make a conformal rescaling of
the metric of sigma which of course won't change its conformal structure as a Riemann surface then
this formula won't be invariant however it's possible to work out simple formulas
for how it transforms under conformal transformations to physicists those simple formulas involve the
so-called theory of anomalies and to mathematicians they involve the theory of the determinant line
bundle as it is entered in the work of faultings deline and the tn singer and more recently freed
in bismuth and others i've given a case um uh well more generally uh if one considers simple
generalizations of this one will be led to generalizations of these formulas whose behavior
under conformal rescalings of the metric involve a quite rich theory which involves the theory of
certain homomorphic line bundles over the modular space of Riemann surfaces in its mathematical
exposition but it wouldn't be practical to enter into that here i'll contend myself simply with
saying that i've tried to give a prototype of um some of the manipulations by which were led
to investigating determinants of operators such as the lapossian and for surfaces without boundary
such that we wouldn't have that factor here this is a simpler prototype of some of the things they
enter in the next lecture now i'd like to conclude by uh returning to our more general themes
i suppose it would be plausible to conjecture that in some suitable sense
the number of really fundamental problems in mathematics is infinite
but i personally believe that the number of really fundamental physics problems is finite
and therefore by definition a physicist who has the privilege of working on such problems is lucky
since in the course of time progress will slow either by solving them or by failing to make
further progress if it's true that the number of really fundamental physics problems is finite
then the number of episodes in the future in which there will be really fundamental
interaction of mathematics and physics will likewise be finite however there are reasons
for believing that the next few decades will be one of those epics
so
so let us begin informal seminar on which professor witten will speak on gage theories and
john's polynomials uh professor witten's work was already introduced to you in the first day
so he need no more introduction so i give floor to professor witten please thank you
i'm very glad this is an informal talk as a result of which my wife hasn't required me to wear a suit
so i will be describing
a particular three-dimensional quantum gauge theory which
puts the john's polynomial and it's in a manifestly three-dimensional form exhibiting
its symmetries which are not obvious from the original definitions and also although i won't
have a chance to talk about this exhibits its formal analogies to modular moonshine that is
moonshine in the theory of the monster group and the theory of our finely algebras modular invariance
in those theories a donaldson theory and other things and also gives a context in which the quantum
group uh quantization of an ordinary league group arises from ordinary geometry for special gauge
groups this theory is also related to some other things including three-dimensional quantum gravity
the castan invariant and some of the fashionable models of high temperature superconductivity
so i thought that uh well i'd begin the talk with a little bit of the end just uh as an
inducement so remember that on the first day in explaining von jones's work
john burman explains a bit about skein theory and also indicated the history of the skein theory idea
that i'm about to summarize and the people who contributed to it so this is a very pretty picture
where you have three pieces of knots these pictures are meant as pieces of very complicated
knots which i won't draw but you have some complicated knot and inside the dotted line it
just looks like this this or this and you consider three knots which are the same outside the dotted
lines of some projection but inside a little sphere which has been projected onto the plane
you have these three different pictures and you have three complex numbers alpha beta and gamma
and you define an invariant of a knot by saying that the invariance of three pictures that are
the same outside and look like this inside weighted by complex numbers alpha beta and gamma add up to
zero by an elementary induction it can be seen that this property uniquely defines a knot invariant
if it exists but the fact that it does exist is considerably deeper and in a way is this part
of the surprise of the jones polynomial and its generalizations the humphly and patricki
tragic and colvin polynomials and others now the explanation we will get for this beautiful picture
is as follows you see the boundary of this sphere has four mark points where the knots pass through
the sphere and we will find a natural way to associate a two-dimensional vector space which
i call h sub s to every sphere s with four mark points it's a two-dimensional vector space and
that's why there are three terms in this scan relation the association of the vector space to
every sphere has the property that every bordism determines a vector in this space now by a bordism
i mean a three manifold which has for boundary this sphere and in which the mark points are
boundaries of bits of knots the knot these lines are only permitted to end at those four points
so this picture here we had the same boundary in the three cases but the interiors are three
different bordisms and in this theory every bordism determines a vector in h sub s
and we will have in this theory a knot invariant in which the details of the interior of s don't
matter all that matters from the mess that might be inside s is this vector size of b in the
Hilbert space on the boundary now a simple fact of linear algebra is that any three vectors in a
two-dimensional space obey a linear relation alpha psi one plus beta psi two plus gamma psi three is
zero for some complex numbers alpha beta and gamma in this case we make the three vectors
determined by these three bordisms and they base on linear relation and if you glue them into some
more complicated picture so that these are little pieces of knots which are constant outside this
sphere and look like this inside then this relation is a relation between the values of the invariant
for three different knots so the existence of this theory now the characteristic of the theory
will be the values of alpha beta and gamma and such a theory predicts the validity of scheme
theory that is the ability to define a knot invariant this way for a particular value of
alpha beta and gamma to explain scheme theory in general we need a two-parameter family of
such constructions so that the ratios of alpha beta and gamma are variable
so that's the answer we will eventually get although perhaps not completely explained today
for the validity of scheme theory it comes fundamentally from the existence of a knot invariant
which can be computed well where the details of what's inside any little sphere don't matter
all that matters is the vector that that bordism determines in the two-dimensional vector space
now put this way
it's an elementary topological idea but its geometrical realization will bring us into
matters that may seem either far afield at first sight in the realm of quantum field theory
while we will be doing quantum gauge theory so we pick a gauge group g
g is a v group which for economy of exposition we take to be connected and simply connected
this simplifies the it's not essential but it simplifies the discussion because then every g
bundle on a three-man hold is trivial we don't necessarily assume that g is compact although
we will sometimes assume it again for simplicity only we assume that g is simple in that case
up to a scalar multiple there is a unique invariant quadratic form on the le algebra of g
and we denote it as the trace we denote the pairing of two elements as the trace of their product
the motivation being that it can actually be realized as the trace in some representation
and the normalization I'll give in a second is such that for SUM this scalar product is the
trace in the n-dimensional representation now a g bundle e on a four-man hold x has a characteristic
number which can be computed by taking the curvature of any connection and integrating trace of f
wedge f and our normalization of the trace is such that this is integer valued
so that's an in a topological invariant or in a four-man hold the corresponding secondary
turn simons invariant isn't a topological invariant but is in an invariant that depends on a connection
if we have a three-man fold m and a g bundle over it and a connection on that bundle then
there is a corresponding secondary invariant so the bundle is called e we extend the the bundle
on the connection over some four-man hold b and we define the three the three-dimensional secondary
invariant is the integral over the bounding four manifold of the object which on a closed four
manifold would have two pi times integer periods the fact that for closed manifolds the periods are
two pi times integers means that for a manifold of fixed boundary this depends on the extension only
up to a multiple of two pi integral multiple of two pi so this is well defined with values in
real numbers modulo two pi times integers or in other words it's exponential times the square root
of minus one has is well defined with values in u one now we're going to be studying a certain
quantum gauge theory in which the Lagrangian is a positive integer k times this functional i of a
and this integer k is related as it turns out to the level in the theory of affine leochvus
now as is standard in quantum field theory the discussion has two halves one is the construction
of Hilbert spaces and in this case they will be generalizations of the jones representations of
the break group and the second part are path integrals although it's hard to explain this
just in one lecture the questions we will ask and the methods we use are not dreamed up on a
not hope basis for this particular problem there are the techniques of quantum field theory adapted
to this situation albeit a somewhat unusual situation in which some steps that are usually
relatively trivial become non-trivial now the goal of the first step of the discussion
is to associate a Hilbert space h to every two manifold sigma every closed Riemann surface
sigma and this is accomplished in general in quantum field theory this is a comp so we're in
three dimensions but in the Hamiltonian version we are in one dimension less here two dimensions
we consider manifolds without boundary and for every such we wish to find a Hilbert space
and this Hilbert space is constructed by quantizing a suitable suitable syntactic
manifold which in general is the modular space of critical points of the Lagrangian
on a particular three manifold which is the surface times R1 that being time
now floor discussed the same functional in another context and as he explained a critical
point of this functional is a fault connection or in other words a representation of the fundamental
group of m into g now since pi1 of m is the same as pi1 of sigma the modular space of such
representations is the same as the modular space of fault connections on sigma and this is the
space we will quantize now this space is often studied by people studying Riemann surfaces
but here in principle it's arising as a representation space of a certain three manifold
that happens that that degenerates to representations of the fundamental group of
sigma because m is contractable to sigma but in principle this space is originating with a
three-dimensional origin which is the beginnings in a very elementary level of the three-dimensional
explanation of the Jones polynomial now as a preliminary which is usually trivial in quantum
theory but here non-trivial we have to consider what kind of object is the Lagrangian on a three
manifold with boundary and here I will be explaining what constant and serial call
pre quantization in this context but I'll be explaining it in some detail when we actually
get to quantization I won't go into such detail so remember how we defined the action functional
we had a three manifold with that boundary then we regarded it as the boundary of some
poor manifold b and the action was defined as an integral over b so implicit in this is that
the boundary of m was zero so that m was the boundary of some b now we want to let the boundary
of m be non-zero and this definition therefore doesn't make sense and therefore we don't have any
we in fact no no longer have this turn simons functional as an r mod 2 pi z valued functional
however what is the nature of the obstruction that a curly a will be the space of connections
on the surface sigma then we can't define this exponential of the turn simons function as a
number but we will define it as a section of a line bundle over the space of connections
or more precisely a connection on the three manifold has boundary values in a and for every
point in a we have a one-dimensional complex vector space the fiber of a line bundle at that
point and this thing will not be a number but will take values in the fiber of that line bundle
so the line bundle is really defined just by asking what's the obstruction to defining this
as a number while the obstruction was that we had an open three manifold and if we knew how to
close it we could get a number again so we just exploit that systematically we have this space of
connections to describe a line bundle over the space of connections we must for every point in
that line in that space describe a one-dimensional complex vector space visa bay and we declare
that visa bay has a basis which we call a prime for every extension of a over any three manifold z
z is any three manifold and a prime is any extension of the connection over z
actually we also extended the bundle and connection over z and for every such extension
this line has a basis a prime well i need to tell you how to compare two different basis elements
and i can do this because if a prime and a double prime are too such extensions
individually they don't have a churn simons invariant but they have a relative churn simons
invariant because they have the same boundary by definition so if i glue them together with
opposite orientation we get a closed three manifold and then the connection on the closed
three manifold has a number a complex number valued invariant and we just say that a prime is a
double prime times this number so now although we have no natural basis in this one-dimensional
vector space we've defined a one-dimensional vector space for every connection on the surface
and thus as the connection on the surface values and varies in the space of all such connections
we got a line bundle l over the space of connections on sigma
now this line bundle has an actual unitary connection in fact if we're given a path in
the space of connections so a1 and a2 are connections on sigma on the surface sigma
and gamma is a path between them in the space of connections that path gives us a connection
on a certain three manifold the three manifold is sigma times the unit interval
and one sigma times the unit interval we take the connection which is trivial in the in this
direction in which in this direction is a1 at this end and a2 at this end and interpolates
between them by the given path so that's a connection on a particular three manifold
and now if you tell me and how to extend a1 over some three manifold then i know how to
extend a2 over some three manifold because the interpolation from a1 to a2 which we just discussed
can be glued on to your interpolation and that gives a unitary connection on this line bundle
in other words if you give me a trivialization of the fiber at a1 i've given you a trivialization
of the fiber at a2 which depends on this path and we interpret that as parallel transport
of the trivialization here to a trivialization here along that path
now let g hat be the gauge group of maps of this surface into g
then g hat acts on the space of connection along sigma and with a small effort that
actually requires a slight elaboration of what i've said the g hat action lifts to an action on
this line bundle preserving the connection now we have a projection from the space of connections
through connections modular gauge transformations we can ask whether the line bundle with connection
descend and they don't the standard criteria are in debate if you take a little loop downstairs
and lift it to a loop upstairs the polynomial on the loop will depend on the left and therefore
there's no way to make these things descend but if we restrict ourselves to five connections
the space of five connections on sigma then by elementary considerations you see that this
line bundle and connection do descend to a line bundle and connection over the space of
five connections divided by gauge transformations and that was the modular space of five connections
on this surface which i indicated earlier was going to enter
so we get a line bundle with connection over the space of five connections on sigma
its curvature can be computed in an elementary fashion and is the standard symplectic structure
which was first provided to gauge theories by a tia and bat in a paper that caranel and
back mentions is the standard symplectic structure on this manifold now these things
have been studied in the past in other methods and in particular this line bundle and connection
in special cases are usually constructed by picking a complex structure on sigma
and using algebraic geometry if you pick a complex structure on sigma so that sigma is
a complex Riemann surface then by the Narasimhan-Sashadri theorem this modular space is a modular
space of holomorphic bundles on sigma and then one has the determinant line bundle with its
racing or quillen metric and its curvature as computed by quillen is precisely the same
curvature as this thing so there's a holomorphic construction in special cases like the unitary
group or for any group for special values of k there's a holomorphic construction of this line
bundle that depends on picking a complex structure on sigma what we've achieved by the
construction I've given is that we've given a purely topological construction it doesn't
depend on any complex structure the mapping class group acts in a fashion which is visible
essentially and at the same time we've related the construction to three manifolds what we've
achieved is actually what constant and surya called pre quantization in this problem we've
constructed what is called the pre quantum line bundle and we've constructed it in a way that
doesn't break this topological invariance of the problem and you see the construction was naturally
related to thinking of it in relation to three manifolds which is what we want because we want
to do a three-dimensional problem now going back to the original question I raised of what is the
term simons and variant i of a if a is a connection on a three manifold with boundary well we see that
total logically it makes sense as a suction of this line bundle that we introduced or more
exactly a vector in the appropriate fiber of that line bundle because any trivialization of the line
bundle which is an extension a bounding three manifold an extension of the connection enables
us to make sense of that thing as a number so this is pre quantization in this situation
now not only have we pre quantized that is we've constructed the appropriate line bundle over the
right module space which has the right unitary connection and the right curvature and without
breaking any of the symmetries of the problem but we're in a very good situation because this
modular space is the sympathetic quotient of an affine space the affine space is the space of
connections and you see we took two steps we restricted to five connections and we divided
by the gauge group and although i won't explain it those compound steps are mathematicians call
them the sympathetic quotient and for physicists they go back to newtons use of symmetries to
reduce a problem in mechanics but anyway this rather complicated modular space of fault connections
we're seeing it in relation to an affine space a with a group action and this relation of course
between the two is what was exploited by atea and bat to compute the chronology of this modular space
but here we're seeing the same we will be using the same relation in a different way
that's appropriate to this particular quantum field theory
now we want to quantize and i won't have time to explain quantization in as much detail as i
gave for pre quantization but quantization means associating a helbert space h which should be
canonically associated with the data and the data are a modular space and the loin bundle with
connection but these data were canonically determined by the surface sigma as we saw
so we will really be canonically associating a helbert space with the surface signal
now what quantization means in general is a long story but if there were a natural
complex structure j on this mod space m obeying certain conditions most importantly that the
symplectic structure the curve the curvature of this connection should be of type one one
so that the line bundle will get a natural homomorphic structure
and in addition the symplectic structure should be positive relative to that complex structure
if there were an actual complex structure then the quantum helbert space would be you see
if we had such a complex structure then our modular space we take as a complex manifold
and the conditions mean that the loin bundle is a homomorphic loin bundle and at level k
we will take the kth power of that loin bundle and take its homomorphic sections
and that would be our helbert space for the level k theory with this gauge group
and associated with this surface sigma
while there isn't a natural complex structure on m but for every choice of complex structure
on this underlying surface sigma we have a hodge decomposition of cohomology you see the tangent
space for this modular space is the Durand cohomology of sigma with values in a twisted bundle
and if we complexify it then it has a hodge decomposition and that hodge decomposition
is really then a complex structure on this modular space in fact it's precisely the
complex structure predicted by the Narasimha and Sashadri theorem and I will call it by the
same name j so for every complex structure j on the surface we get a complex structure j
on this modular space and thus by the definition on the last transparency
for every complex structure j we can make this definition but if j is not natural then neither
is curly h so we have a definition of curly h but it depended on j so I'll call it curly h sub j
and because of the j dependence well this situation to begin with is fibrous over the
space of all complex structures on sigma but it trivially reduces to the space of complex
structures up to isotope or in other words to take more space so we really have a situation
that's fibrous over take more space we'll have this family of hybrid spaces fibrous over take more
space actually without mentioning it I started to assume a transparency or two ago that this
well I didn't prove that the hodge decomposition gave a complex structure that really at that
point was assuming the case of a compact group for other classively groups we'd get something but
not quite this so we're now assuming for the moment that we're dealing with a compact group
now we wanted a single helbert space and we have a family of them and of course to get back to the
situation of a single helbert space what we wanted is a natural flat connection on this bundle
such a flat connection since the base take more space is contractible such a flat connection
would give us a natural identification of the fibers such a connection can be explicitly and
rigorously constructed as I did along these lines with axolot and telepiedra using two facts
the first fact is that if we were quantizing an affine space such a fat connection exists
because of the stone von Neumann theorem on the unique representation of the
Heisenberg group and physicists think of this fat connection as the infinitesimal generator of
what we call bugolubov transformations and then one can push down from an affine space to a
synthetic portion by restricting to the G invariant subspace now for finite dimensional affine
spaces these two facts will give the result a priori here the affine space is infinite dimensional
only the synthetic portion is finite dimensional so what one has to do is to take the formulas
which would be valid a priori in the finite dimensional case and do a little bit of geometry
to verify them and in fact modify them slightly so that they make sense in this case for only
downstairs you have a finite dimensional story now the fault connection one gets this way
or I've written it in the plural because there were different groups and levels
these fact actions since the mapping class group acts here one really gets representations of the
mapping class group and as was first perceived by Tsuchiya and Kanya in a work that was part of
what made possible the soil development these are generalizations of the Jones representations
of the braid group to get precisely the Jones representations you would take sigma the surface
to have Gina zero and you would have to include knots and mark points in a way that I haven't
indicated moreover the equations that define this fact connection are the generalizations to
genus G of the Keynesian exam logic of equation which we've heard so much about in so many different
talks at this congress starting with Jim Bo's talk explaining part of the work of Jim Fed and
including unexpected applications to number theory that were mentioned in one of the primary
addresses yesterday now this construction of this particular file connection for compound G
has been obtained in other ways where the original results came from conformal field theory about
six years ago by Konishnik and Samochikov and Gina zero and Aguchi and Ugari some years later
at genus one and these authors were studying the well what's sometimes called the West
Amino Novikov-Witton model of conformal field theory and then these constructions were formatted
rigorously at an arbitrary genus by Tsuchiya at all Tsuchiya talked about it yesterday
and there was a simple argument well this a simple sketch of an argument by Siegel in the
Swansea proceedings from two years ago also it's possible to construct this connection by pure
algebraic geometry and this has been done by Hitchin and by Balanson and Karzhan
the construction I've indicated
is natural in relation to three dimensions in the sense that it's the one that arises naturally
as the solution to a quantization of this pre-quantized symplectic manifold and
it extends to other classes of gauge group which we hope is may also be the case for some of the
other approaches ultimately in fact with some minor modifications relatively minor modifications
of what I've said it's possible to carry out a similar construction if G is a complex semi-simple
e-group now perhaps I'll devote one transparency to a site digression so far there are no results
about this problem for other classes of e-group which were like to study and notably for non-compact
real forms even in the simple case of SL2R now in a very precise sense which would take us far
field to really explain this subject is a generalization of representation theory and from that
point of view the facts I've stated aren't too surprising so in representation you know well
that compact groups are the easiest followed by compact scripts and that the non-compact
real forms are an order of magnitude harder and difficult to study in a unified fashion
so I've told you that again in this context I had a transparency alluding to different
approaches for the compact groups and the corresponding problem for the complex groups
is definitely harder and is much less well understood but it is tractable it's the next
case after the compact groups it leads of course to infinite dimensional helbert spaces just as
in representation theory where the unitary representations are infinite dimensional
and the solution of this problem for complex groups is related to compact groups
much as in the case of representation theory since there are no results for the non-compact
real forms one doesn't know what will happen but either there's some reasonable way to solve
this problem which might well lead to some new viewpoint in representation theory or this problem
might be affected with more elaborate versions of the usual difficulties in representation theory
well we now come to the deeper part of the story and while I wish to emphasize that what I've said
up until this point is very precise mathematically in proceeding we will have to base ourselves
for a while on the massive experience in theoretical physics in the last 40 years
but at the very end we will get back to the realm of
precise rigorous mathematics as of our period so
I might say as a general role I'm explaining a particular quantum field theory and in this
particular quantum field theory the deeper results are based on the ideas that I will indicate
but that's there's a similar statement that can be made about
other quantum field theories of geometrical interest for instance if one is interested in
what was called by Conway and Calbert as monster moonshine in the theory of the monster
simple e-group the quantum field theory explanation for it is based on the same
Feynman-Pathens a goal that I'm about to tell you about together with the conformal field theory
constructed by Frank Lepasky and Merman so in general I'm about to tell you the aspect which
Fadeev stressed in his lecture on the opening day the aspect of quantum field theory ideas
which is perhaps most indigestible mathematically but which usually leads to the deepest results
so the heuristic motivation for this well we've made an association of Hilbert's bases with
surfaces by picking a gauge group on a level k and quantizing and this association is somewhat
analogous to the association of a surface with its let's say complex cohomology first cohomology
in each case a diffeomorphism of surfaces induces some map on these spaces
and in the case of cohomology if you pick a bound in three manifold that actually determines
a Lagrangian subspace in the first cohomology group namely the subspace of things that extend
over the three manifold and you may ask whether there's some analog here
a surface is sitting there with its first with its h1 but if you give a three manifold
suddenly that determines a subspace a preferred subspace of h1 you can ask what's the analog here
and now just for fun let's guess what it might be of course I'll make a slightly biased guess
if for every connection on sigma we had a natural extension a prime over m so we're given a three
manifold sigma and we construct we're given a surface sigma and we constructed a helbert space
by quantizing the space of connections on sigma and if for every connection on sigma we knew how
to extend it over m so if every connection had a natural extension then since an extended connection
has an a churned simons invariant not as a number but as a vector in some line then if we had a
natural extension of every connection then we could define a natural section of this line bundle we've
been talking about well there's no natural way to extend connections in fact there isn't even a
continuous engaged invariant way to extend the connections but in what many regard as his greatest
insight Richard Feynman taught us more than 40 years ago what to do since there isn't a natural
extension we average over extensions and every extension determines some vector in the corresponding
line so the average over connections is a vector in the line and as the boundary data vary so we
consider for a given connection on the surface all its extensions and averaging over extensions
gives us a vector and letting a vary we get a section of that line bundle that I've told you about
and this is Feynman's recipe for computing transition amplitudes
now of course I've made it sound like a possibly naive idea there wasn't a
natural extension so we averaged over them but a not very deep one in Feynman's context
the problem or prior he wasn't set up in such a way as to make that sound so much like the obvious
thing to try on the other hand what Feynman was trying to do is similar to what we're trying to
do in understanding the Jones polynomial in those days there was a theory called quantum
macho dynamics that was really a four-dimensional theory but it was only formulated with three
dimensional symmetry now Feynman was trying to exhibit quantum macho dynamics in an obviously
four-dimensionally invariant fashion here we have a theory the Jones polynomial and its generalizations
which is really a three-dimensional theory but the known formulations at most have two-dimensional
symmetry or even less in the original versions and we're trying to exhibit it as a three-dimensional
theory and we're simply following in Feynman's enormously successful and influential footsteps
now I'll in a bit try to make the notion that there is a way to average over this infinite
dimensional space of extensions sounds a little more palatable but first let's indicate a few of
the consequences well first of all if you believe you can average over connections you can do it
even on a three manifold without boundary or at least you can try to consider the case where the
boundary is empty so if we're given a closed three manifold well we consider the space of all
connections or really connections modular gauge transformations on M and we want to average
over connections modular gauge transformations or more conveniently we usually average over all
connections including the Fadenov-Paprov ghosts to account for the volume of the gauge group
anyway we want to average over all connections and now since we have a closed manifold the
churn assignments invariant is really a number so the answer is a number and it's a numerical
invariant of the three manifold now this is a very big integral and maybe it's too big for one
graduate student to do but we might have two graduate students so we split the problem into
two pieces we take what's called a Higard splitting of the three manifold so we have a three manifold
x now i've called it i've regarded as a union of m and n m and n are three manifolds with a common
boundary with opposite orientation so they fit together to make a nice three manifold x and
we fix the boundary values of the connection on sigma and we ask one student to integrate over
connection extensions here while the other student integrates over extensions here and one student
gets one functional of the boundary data and of course the other student gets the other functional
of the boundary data and of course if we fix the boundary data and integrate overall extensions
then we've integrated over everything except the values of the connection on sigma and maybe the
student's advisor who should do at least part of the work will then do the final integral over that
so the two students have constructed these two functionals of boundary data and then
perhaps the advisor integrates over the boundary data and that final integral means that we finish
the job and we have the invariant of this three manifold but we've obtained that invariant by
pairing two pieces one functional of boundary data obtained by one student and the other
functional obtained by the other student now these two functionals were sections of our
favorite line bundle so what we found is that while each three manifold determines a vector in
this space or the other one because of opposite orientation determines a vector in the dual
the pairing of the vector in the dual vector is our desired three manifold invariant and therefore
we have learned that we are dealing with invariants that are computable from e-guard splitings
and more general considerations along these lines
lead to a nice formula for the behavior under game surgery
so I haven't quite explicitly introduced not invariants but not invariants are introduced
similarly by considering a three manifold with knots and considering holonomies of connections
around those knots and after formulating the problem for the not invariants then one can push
a little farther on this formula by which we compute from e-guard splitings and get a formula for
the behavior under game surgery and that formula is really what makes the theory computable because
any two three manifolds are related by game surgery
and for instance if you want you can use game surgery to reduce anything you want to know about
any three manifold to knots in s3 or in some ways it's even simpler to reduce them to braids in s2
times s1 because if you get to the braids in s2 times s1 then you really have reduced this more
general picture to the original Jones representations of the braid group essentially and their cousins
for higher representations and groups and so ultimately you get combinatorial formulas
based on game surgery and these formulas have been adopted as the definition in combinatorial
approaches uh rachatecan lectured on the um work that uh rachatecan and trev did to rigorously
justify the combinatorial formula you get this way by checking the generators and relations
of essentially curvy calculus in an elegant fashion that depends on the relations involving
quantum groups of course the uh tool that they used uh well the ingredients that come in and
doing so are the so-called quantum 6j symbols and the quantum 6j symbols themselves have a natural
representation in three dimensions in terms of these path integrals which again is related to
the essential properties and is another side of what i mentioned earlier when i noticed that we
were getting the kinesian exam logic of the question which one knows is related to uh
quantum groups so different ways of looking at this make different aspects of driving quantum
groups from quantum filter you see i might remark that to physicists quantum groups are
rather funny things because you might say that the name quantum makes it sound like physics
and perhaps it does but what quantum is here being used in a rather loose sense quantum means
that an algebra in this sense context quantum is being used to mean that an algebra which
is commutative or commutative is being deformed so that it doesn't have those properties anyway
but quantum mechanics is really a little bit more specific than just deforming commutative
algebras to non-commutative algebras quantum mechanics really has to do with quantization
of symplectic manifolds the algebra which is being deformed is the uh algebra of functions
on a symplectic manifold and it's deformed to a non-commuting algebra of operators on Hilbert's
base quantum groups as formulated so elegantly uh involve the deformations of a cross on
manifold but not of a symplectic manifold and as such there really a bit outside the
conventional framework for quantum mechanics and quantum theory if you wish to uh take the
quantum group and reduce it to a more standard object which is quantization of symplectic
manifolds or once a complex structure is picked algebraic geometry sections of line bundles
over that modular space m sub j this much bigger story with the space of connections and the three
dimensional quantum theory puts the quantum group in a framework that really is quantum mechanics
and quantum theory of course the drawback is that we're in a much bigger picture which is
less obviously computable as so often happens in mathematics and physics the more computable version
which is the quantum group doesn't exhibit all the symmetries which are exhibited in the three
dimensional story one should think of this as one of many instances where there is a invariant
definition which is the definition involving quantum theory on three manifolds and there's a
computable definition a manifestly computable definition that doesn't manifestly have all
the symmetries which is the one that involves the reduction to quantum groups and the combinatorial
approaches now i think i should spend the last few minutes to give you a favor of what path
integrals are on here i shall be following as i should have said at the beginning in the first
steps of albert schwarz who considered the abelian version of this theory many years ago in the 70s
writing it to write a monster racing retortion so i want to say something which is mathematically
precise about path integrals though it doesn't give the complete story and it's a challenge to give
the complete story so what i'll tell you is if you give a physicist satan seeing a quantum theory
that was found behind a bush and has no particular redeeming virtues i will tell you all that can
be said about it that that path integrals based on general ideas so the only general thing that you
can say in terms of really computing their money so of course even if you've reduced an integral
to quadrature and finite dimensions you usually can't compute it and you look for some asymptotic
expansions and we will make an asymptotic expansion here which is an expansion in powers of 1 over k
so the situation we're in is we have a big infinite dimensional manifold
and we're integrating something and the same thing we're integrating is the exponential of i times
something else times k so the prototype for this problem um i'm going to simplify it so
we really have the gauge group and we should worry about the ghosts the idea of proper of ghosts
but pretending they weren't there the prototype is a finite dimensional manifold
what they measure and a morse function it doesn't have to be a morse function in general it's a
larger class of functions but let's think for simplicity of a smooth function with isolated
critical points and then we have a real number and then we want to compute this integral and
of course we can't compute it in closed form we can prove it exists but we can't compute it
but we can't compute it in an asymptotic expansion in powers of 1 over 2 and that's
essentially classical the asymptotics of such an integral is given by stationary phase
in fact if f were not a function but were had values in r mod 2 pi z and t was an integer
so there were no critical points this would vanish exponentially for large t because of oscillations
so the failure to vanish exponentially due to oscillations comes because of critical
points where there aren't oscillations the asymptotics are given by stationary phase
if pi are the critical points then this has a systematic expansion involving a sum over
critical points where the leading term is the value of the integrand at the earth critical
points times a power of t that depends on the dimension and then multiplied by a local expansion
determined by local data at the critical points so these are the coefficients here are local
invariants at the i-th critical point and for instance if near a given critical point you
make an expansion so i pick some local coordinates and i want them to be adapted to the measure
so that d mu is dx1 up to dxn and then since it's a critical point the function has its value
and then the next term is a quadratic term involving the so-called Hessian
then by studying the integral the idealized integral we find that the leading term
is this animal and that animal involves the determinant of the Hessian while this thing
has a determinant because of the existence of a measure here and the condition on the coordinates
involves the determinant of the Hessian and involves the signature of that quadratic form
so the leading contribution here involves these nice endurance of the behavior near the critical
point and then you can compute the higher order corrections involving local behavior near the
critical points you need to the only new thing you'll really need is that you'll need to invert
this invertible matrix and then the expansion can be described diagrammatically in terms of what
physicists call Feynman diagrams now this can be imitated systematically in our problem in
fact that's where they're called Feynman diagrams well there's no problem with the notion of a
critical point uh for explain that a critical point of this functional is a fault connection
up to gauge transformation and for a large class of three manifolds they'll be isolated
in general we need to understand how to generalize the previous story which will involve certain
integrals of measures that you'll construct well what will happen in fact is that if the critical
point isn't isolated this determinant isn't a number but is naturally a measure on the space
of critical points so after proper understanding the finite dimensional story you can imitate it
here there's no problem with the notion of a critical point there's of course no problem
with the notion of the value of deterrence hymens functional at a critical point that's one of
these standard invariance of a fault connection well the hashen makes sense after including
the ghosts the hashen is a certain elliptic differential operator which i call al well
then we need the determinant of l but that's essentially what ray and singer defines and
schwarz interpreted in quantum field theory so that the determinant of l is the ray-singer
torsion and then we also need the signature of l well l is a quadratic form in infinite dimensions
so it has infinitely many positive and negative eigenvalues so we need to define its signature
and we need to regularize that but tia petode and singer told us how to do that in the so-called
eta invariant and in this problem the eta invariant is the right notion of the signature of l
so i've explained the leading contribution for large k to this path integral so we've actually
if you like evaluated the path integral in the leading approximation of stationary phase and
it involves invariants that are classical namely the more recent of them were defined in the early
70s but they're still fairly sophisticated things like the torsion and the eta invariant
and the corrections which are only beginning to be systematically investigated mathematically
involve what physicists call Feynman diagrams
um my student drill born out on has worked at rather precisely the through loop
correction to the not invariants and has shown that it's
equal to the again classical not invariants which is the derivative of the jones polynomial
at q equals one as was the second derivative right as was expected
so then the story is that we can carry out the Hamiltonian picture more or less rigorously
getting the jones representations and their generalizations the deeper side of the story
is certainly the Hamiltonian picture which is a challenge perhaps to understand it comprehensively
um in perturbation theory it leads in the leading approximation to these classical but
slightly settled invariants with a systematic prescription for generalizing them and computing
more elaborate corrections perhaps rather as in some fashion which
um in some perhaps rather fashion in the province primarily of experts
I certainly couldn't claim to grasp it a block explained in the first lecture
some generalizations of more classical invariants
thank you
yes thank you very much professor britain and the the inform of seminar is finished thank you for
attention
thank you
what is it
Now, the professor, Fatih Er, will speak on the work of Week 10.
It's a duty of the chairman of the field committee to ask speakers for that session.
So as soon as it becomes clear that Witten got a medal, I approached Tatia asking to speak for him.
I wanted kind of cover up from a mathematician in the very physical domain
to explain to you why it was so natural to give a field medal to a mathematical physicist.
And Tatia was very enthusiastic in this, but he told me that unfortunately he cannot come
to Kyoto in the end of August. So we decided on the following way that he will send me some text
and I will use it in describing of Witten work at this session. So I had got this text
and I will read you some excerpts out of it, but it contains no formulas at all. So just to read it
maybe it will be a little bit too dull. You have seen transparencies before.
So in a way it will be a mixture of ideas, text and some general comments which I will give to you
myself and some explanations. So mathematical physics must be considered as a legitimate,
it's my belief, must be considered as a legitimate part of mathematics. It was always stimulating,
it was always a source of stimulus and inspiration for more theoretical branches of mathematics
and we know very many classical examples. But until recent time it was stimulating mostly
analysis or in general or part of analysis such like partial differential equations,
especially non-linear equations nowadays and so on and so forth. We could call it classical
mathematical physics, but in more recent time we witnessed development, another type of mathematical
physics which could be in contradiction with previous one called quantum mathematical physics.
And this mathematical physics differs mainly, also differs from classical mathematical physics
in the use of different domains of mathematics in it or in other words also stimulating different
parts of theoretical mathematics. Algebra, geometry, topology, algebraic geometry, complex analysis,
all these traditional fields of mathematics now come to modern mathematical physics and vice versa
mathematical physics problems arising there in quantum mathematical physics are sources of new
problems for this part of theoretical mathematics. And now I read first citation from Atiyah in all
this large and exciting field which involves many of leading physicists and mathematicians in the
world. Edward Whitten stands out clearly as the most influential and dominating figure,
although he is definitely a physicist, here I would add mathematical physicist. His command
of mathematics is rivaled by few mathematicians and his ability to interpret physical ideas
in mathematical form is quite unique. Time and again he has surprised the mathematical community
by brilliant application of physical insight leading to new and deep mathematical theorems.
Now in Atiyah's text there is elaboration on this general statement and usually the reference
is to an important tool of modern theoretical mathematical physics which is called Feynman
integral. Feynman integral allows us to write down explicit in quotation marks solution of very
complicated problems arising in quantum field theory, quantum mechanics and so on. Quotation
marks means that this tool is still heuristic and not not made rigorous, rigorous to the standards
which are supposed to be used now. They would certainly satisfy I would think more mathematicians
in previous century but or even such people like Elikartan but without more standard of
more high standards of rigor they are still non-rigors of course. On the other hand as I will
try to explain with the help of Atiyah also it's really a very important tool to find out new mathematical
theorems. So the ingredient in the Feynman integral is a functional of some fields. Fields means
functions on the some manifold domain so functions could be not necessarily functions but sections
of the bundle and so on so could have geometrical origin and this functional is called action
and that function x to the i where i squared minus y times action is Feynman functional and the
Feynman integral is kind of averaging over of this functional over all possible fields
in consideration. It's significant value that is real over measure of course not measure is strict
standards. This local which is a product over all points in the domain or manifold
of differentials of these fields so to say. So the answer is a number that of course depending
on what we what problem we have in consideration for instance we have domain the boundary or we have
some asymptotical conditions then so there are some which characterize the the main
of this geometrical object we are average over the function would be also functional of this data
and so quite a rich object. So the example well of course physicists after Feynman after 48
use it mostly for their own needs and then a function a was action in the statistical theory
of mechanics of some particular Hamiltonian system but in more general use which gradually
developed in this quantum mathematical physics and especially by the influence of very modern
things there in particular what's called thing theory people began to use more
geometrical objects in these actions and fields. So examples of possible fields could be loops
or connections it's called young wheels field in physics or metrics in physics it would be
most useful in the case of gravity and so on and so forth. So Witten have shown a very
ingenious way of using functionally integral to produce purely mathematical theorems.
Now I cite from here in his paper on supersymmetry and Morse theory yes excuse me Witten's paper on
supersymmetry and Morse theory is obligatory reading for geometers interested in understanding
modern quantum field theory. It also contains a brilliant proof of classical Morse inequalities
relating critical points to homology. The main point is that homology is defined
via Hodge harmonic forms so the Laplacian will play a role of the Schrodinger operator
of quantum mechanics and you can write down Feynman integral using this action.