Good afternoon everybody. Bienvenue à tous. My name is David Eidelman. I'm Vice Principal
Health Affairs and Dean of the Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences and it's my pleasure
to welcome you all to a session on Healthcare in Deep Space, Autonomous Medicine Practical
AI in Advanced Simulation. This is the session's part of McGill Space Week as you know and it's
a signature event of McGill's bicentennial celebrations. You know, we just heard about AI,
we heard about the application of existing technologies and we heard about complexity
and space missions obviously are the prototype of highly complex systems operating in an
environment in which you have to handle lots of heterogeneous data and information sets and in
order to be successful in spaceflight you have to figure out how to do this and to do that you need
to really know what you're talking about and there you know Professor Smith's going to describe
the foundational principles necessary to integrate all aspects of complex systems including emission
systems using biologic and other data and into an information architecture that really supports the
use of advanced modular algorithms and so Professor Smith the floor is yours. I'm going to transfer
over take it away. Good so I'm not going to be able to do all of that but I will try and do at least
some samples which will give you an idea of how it could be done and I'll start with some background so
I started life as a philosopher working on metaphysics. Recently I started a whole new
line of thinking. I'm about to publish a book with a German AI entrepreneur colleague of mine on
artificial intelligence which more or less agrees with everything that Gary Marcus says
in his book but takes it further so we try and document in great detail the limits of AI when
dealing specifically with complex systems such as organisms and missions to Mars and so forth
and if we've got time I may come back to show the relevance of that to the main topic here
so which goes back to 2002 when I was awarded a prize to establish an institute in Germany to
deal with the ontology of medicine and this prize was awarded because people working in
computational ontology already then had started to use some of my ideas from philosophical ontology
so I started the institute and the first thing I realized was that I was probably going to be
spending the rest of my life studying one single ontology which was the gene ontology which John
mentioned already. Gene ontology solved a very considerable problem namely the problem of making
human genome and mouse genome and fly genome data useful for medicine and the idea was that the
gene ontology provided a systematic semantically well-grounded common consensus terminology across
all organisms and all disciplines which could be used to tag sequences whether they're gene sequences
or protein sequences or any other kind of sequence and this was a great success it was
brought to my attention very early on in working in this new institute and the first thing I realized
about it was that it was full of mistakes and mistakes of a logical nature which a philosopher
learns about in the first logic class at the beginning of their studies and so I had money for
the new institute I invited the leadership of the gene ontology to come to the institute in Leipzig
and I went through pointing out all the mistakes that they were making so this is just one example
a lytic vacuole within a protein storage vacuole is classified by the gene ontology as a protein
storage vacuole it was then this is a bit like saying that an embryo within a uterus is a uterus
it's an ontological mistake of a very simple logical sort and in those days the gene ontology
was full of such mistakes it was also doing the job of providing semantic definitions useful to humans
in a in a way which involved similar kinds of mistakes so this is a circular definition
it's not a good definition doesn't it doesn't and it cannot tell you anything about the meaning
of hemolysis because the word is used in the definition so I presented a talk at the meeting
in Leipzig entitled stop or smart terminology through ontological principles
and the the head of the gene ontology initiative Michael Ashburner at the end of who was in the room
on the front row smiling throughout he took me behind the curtain and he made a deal with me
he said Barry I will put you in charge of the logic of the gene ontology and in return you
promise never to criticize the gene ontology in public and I I sold my soul I said yes
I'm not criticizing the gene ontology today the gene ontology has improved in part I think because
of some of the things I did but more importantly I helped the gene ontology to marshal or heard the
many cats that is to say the many other ontologies which were being built in biomedicine in its
wake ontologies in areas like proteomics or anatomy or disease and some of the ontologies
mentioned by John earlier today were built precisely in this effervescence of ontology
creativity in medicine or in let's say biology to be careful which arose as a result of the
success of the gene ontology so the oboe foundry is a collection of ontologies which are built to
be interoperable from the very start so this is anticipating silos and deliberately taking
steps establishing principles to avoid the the appearance of those silos by ensuring that
everybody involved in the ontology building effort is aware of what everyone else who is involved
in the ontology building effort at the points where the ontology is overlap so that the overlap
is always such that the ontologies which do overlap are consistent in those areas
so this is a picture of the of the oboe foundry as it then was basic formal ontology is
the very top level of the gene ontology it's a reverse engineered generalization of the
gene ontology which covers everything in the universe but only at a very general metaphysical
level and we'll see a bit more about what that means later on so basic formal ontology is the key
to the unifiability of all the ontologies which are built in a way that descends from basic
formal ontology it provides the starting point for defining the terms in non-circular ways
in principle in every other ontology we've got now to 2005 now this this is a hub and
spokes model of ontology development you start with the top level and then you move to a slightly
the most specific level and then you move from there to a slightly more specific level all the
while maintaining maximal consistency in areas where ontology is overlap and this works it worked
really well and the army heard about it and in 2008 I was presenting a talk which was designed to
help the army solve problems that they had with silos in their data from Afghanistan at the time
and it was the army eventually which sponsored the proposal to make BFO an international standard
ISO IEC 21838-2 I'll come back to that well it's here actually there are two parts the first part
standardize is what it means to be a top level ontology so an ontology that can serve as a
universal general hub for the spokes which are created by domain ontologies and then part two
shows that BFO is satisfying the requirements for being a top level ontology set forth in part one
and these standards are both in the public domain you don't have to pay for them and BFO of course
is also in the public domain it's used now by some 500 different initiatives and the number
grows all the time so in 2010 my colleagues in Buffalo received a very large IR per grant to
create a set of ontologies to deal with everything in the universe these are called the common core
ontologies they they were built to satisfy some needs of the intelligence community which are
not important here but what is important is that some of the ontologies within that ecosystem
were created for space and this is just a few examples so this is the common core ontologies
ecosystem the space ontologies are down here so we have space event ontology space object
ontology is space mission ontology and stuff and we deal with things like residence space
objects such as satellites missions functions components and so forth these are the space
objects and then we have object aggregates we have orbits so this is the ontology of different
kinds of orbits you thought the idea of orbit was simple and it is not simple and then we have
missions and maneuvers we have sensors and now we get back to medicine so John made a number of
points concerning what we would need to address if we wanted to have useful medicine ontology
and it's rather easy it's probably too easy to build ontologies the problem is to build useful
ontologies and useful ontologies should be interoperable with existing useful ontologies
and so there is a certain homesteading effect in the world of ontology if you have ontologies which
are already serving a purpose and doing it very well then you should if you want to build an
ontology in a related domain you should ensure that you build your ontology by using what exists
already as your starting point this very often doesn't happen because you get paid for doing
something new and for reusing what already exists it's hard to get paid and so there is a certain
tendency to promote silo formation of the sort which John described so how do we build a useful
space medicine ontology that was in fact part of what we were trying to do from the very beginning
in the medical information science although of course we had no idea that this would become
particularly relevant in the in the space context so what we want to do is to document
medical knowledge especially as it's relevant to space travel and then we want to find an optimal
way in which relevant knowledge can be retrieved on a mission and the idea would be that you have
all the medical knowledge that there is and you have some way of finding the medical knowledge
that you need that can then find that knowledge very quickly and very successfully and the problem is
that all the medical knowledge that you have is full of garbage and this is one of the reasons why
foundation models as described by Gary are so unhelpful when it comes to mission critical
applications so why is the and totality of medical knowledge that we have full of garbage well first
of all doctors make mistakes and medical science advances doctors don't always keep pace with medical
advances some of them do some of them don't and so doctors have conflicts they have inconsistent
diagnoses sometimes for the same patient and all of this gets added to the totality of medical
knowledge all of the EMRs which exist and all of the problem lists which exist grow and get bigger
and bigger and get added to the totality of medical knowledge all records are still records
when doctors make diagnoses clinical coders have to document those diagnoses using clinical codes
and those clinical coders make errors in coding and they have certain tendencies and habits to code
in certain ways and different coders have different habits and then worst of all and that's what I'm
going to talk about next is that the coding systems change and this is good because medical science
advances but the coding systems should change gracefully and they should change in such a way
that changes then can be fed back to filter out the consequences of the older systems which have
been shown to be no longer scientifically coherent and even worse than coding systems themselves
ferment errors because some of the coding systems are to be honest badly built and and then coding
systems generate forking this is a problem that we will see in a minute all right now I could say
bad things about most medical coding systems I'm afraid I had a a long career in which I was
comparable to the little boy who says that the emperor does not have any clothes where the emperor
were was world leading medical coding systems communities it was an exciting time this is
a quote from Gary so foundation models he says are more like parlor tricks than genuine intelligence
unfortunately the the problems in medicine don't even yield the parlor tricks they're not interesting
errors they're just errors of a very messy sort now let's look at snow med ct which John already
mentioned and he mentioned Roger Cotay I will mention a story about Roger Cotay which I'm not
sure is true but certainly there's some truth to it Cotay visited the Vatican he wanted to present
the six volumes of snow med ct to the pope and so he was chatting with the pope and the pope was
looking at six volumes and then the pope raised his head and he said are you aware that this spells
demons backwards now whether that is a true story or not uh no one will ever know so this is a little
piece of snow med showing how it changed from 2016 to 2017 it's a very very trivial example but it
will show you how you get bloat so this is the opposite of silos bloat is when you get inconsistent
data because there isn't a silo in 2016 a test kit is classified as a substance which may or may
not be good in 2017 is classified as a physical object which also may or may not be good but the
fact that you have both of those classifications in your system is going to mean that data about
test kit which was entered into the record in 2016 will conflict with data about test kits
entered in 2017 and that's not good if it happens all the time now here we have 2015 2016 we see
that there is on the left a joint finding and disorder of musculoskeletal system these are both
parents of orthopathy which is a disorder now a disorder is something on the side of the patient
it's a broken leg or it's a disease a finding is something on the side of a physician it's what the
physician finds or discovers in the world one of the same thing should not be both on the side of
the patient and on the side of the clinician it's a very basic error snow med is full of that error
there are so many different ways in which that error is made in snow med that snow med generates
bloat and now this is just one term in snow med and two versions 2002 and 2010 so the term is
excision biopsy of vulval lesion this term is chosen at random you would get similar bloats
from the many terms so every single track through this monster can be found if you join snow med 2002
with so 2010 and the clinical coders are coding at different levels within this monster they're
putting down data about one and the same medical phenomenon namely the process of biopsy from a
vulval lesion and they're each coding that with a different code for how it looks is this so this
is just this is from that diagram i've just zoomed a little bit procedure characterized by action
status is a navigational concept in snow med that means it tells you how you got that concept or
something and then you have procedure carried out on subject which is what snow med calls a
situation we're also told that it's a procedure carried out which is another situation but at
the same time it's a procedure on a body system which is a procedure so we have four ontologically
different things namely navigational concept situations and procedures applied to one and the
same medical phenomenon and the reason is that snow med's top level is incoherent now it's
incoherent has been recognized for some years by what we might call the intellectual leaders of
the snow med community and each year they propose to the general snow med management assembly that
they should drop the snow med top level and re-architect snow med using bfo there is now reason
to be optimistic that they will finally achieve a majority vote bfo does not allow that kind of
forking it doesn't allow four different terms at the very high ontological level to be applied to
one and the same item it's built on good ontological principles and it's much simpler to use than the
snow med top level and it makes clear distinctions between things like entities on the side of the
patient and entities on the side of the clinician so how do we get a useful space medicine ontology
well nasa has a chief information officer and they have a an information system which is an
information system covering all of the astronauts who ever existed in in the west and all the families
of all the astronauts it's very high level it uses unfortunately multiple coding systems but all of
the coding systems could in principle be unified and focused on a revised version of snow med which
is what the nasa cio should be calling for a revised version with a proper top level it should
eliminate the errors basically where they are easily identifiable and it's here i think that ai
could play a role because we already have a large amount of data which is relevant to space missions
because the astronauts are involved it's maintained and curated by top level clinicians and it's
accessible already it just needs to be filtered to remove inconsistencies and well i just conclude so
would therefore be useful for space medicine as john explained it would be useful for everyone else
because it would serve as a kind of ground truth the equivalent of a foundation model but one which
would have been well built and i won't try and talk about deep mind i will i will stop
and i hope you're all still there