On the program it says the ontology of social services but this grew and it's become very
complicated.
So I've been working on the ontology of services for many years and with the distinction between
goods and services and I don't think it's possible to provide a good definition of either
of these two terms which will please everybody.
We have to make sacrifices at the edges but I think that I've found a way of organising
a lot of the data that we have about goods and services in a way which is interesting
and potentially also useful and I want to use the word good to mean an independent continuance.
I'll talk a little bit about the issue that Matt raised earlier about goods which are
not independent continuance but for the moment I want to focus on this case and then I'm
going to talk about services and I'm going to suggest there are really two kinds of services.
On the one hand there are what we might call pure services which are just processes but
then on the other hand there are the great majority of services which create things and
it will become clear what they create as we go along.
Now the starting point is national income statistics or gross domestic product statistics
and the official tables for gross domestic product start with these items so personal
consumption expenditures are divided into expenditures on goods that means either durable
goods like refrigerators on young durable goods like hamburgers and then services so
they are pretty clear that there are two different kinds of entity at work here and they're
interested in these kinds of entities because money is involved and I am primarily interested
in these kinds of entities also because money is involved but I think that the distinction
holds even where no money is involved so this distinction can be applied for instance to
the charitable work of a convent for instance.
Alright so goods are material entities and they're created by manufacturers and farmers
and so forth and then there are some people think there are immaterial goods I don't have
a finished view on this but my current view says in the olden days software was a material
good it was made of silicon and rubber and whatever floppy disks were made of today you
don't buy software you rent it or you buy the rights to it you pay a fee so you can
have a right to use the software and the same I think applies to insurance you pay a fee
for the right to receive payments if you have a certain kind of loss so you pay a fee in
essence to gamble and so I don't think these are good counter examples to the idea that
goods are much material but as I say I have no finished view about this.
Now one, this is a little bit of philosophy here so I apologise, one distinction that
philosophers like to make is the distinction between intrinsic goods which I'm here calling
ultimate goods which are good in their own right and not for another reason that they
serve so these are all intrinsic goods you don't eat a hamburger because you want to
bring about another effect you eat a hamburger because the hamburger is a good in its own
right and similarly for all these other things so you don't read a novel because you want
to achieve something else you read the novel because reading the novel is good in its own
right well non-ultimate goods are goods that are involved in a chain of creation of ultimately
ultimate goods so the steering wheel is a good because it's going to become part of
a car which may be good in its own right and the design for a car is a good because it's
going to be used as a design for building a car which is a good in its own right so
there are goods which are goods for something and then there are goods which are goods in
their own right and there are many on either side and it's important to keep this distinction
in mind and if you want a little exercise you might think about whether there is a distinction
between ultimate services and services which are for something else goods have an economic
value but only if they enter into buying and selling processes and buying and selling unless
you do it yourself are services so when you buy a car this is a picture taken in the max
Heidegger RG which is the BMW sales center in Liechtenstein you deal with sales personnel
who offer services what do they bring about they bring about a new pattern of ownership
basically before the transaction you have the money and they have the car after the
transaction it's reversed all right so there are buying and selling services but there
are many other kinds of what we will call pecuniary services and the document acts come
into play in a big way so billing and securing payment and registering payment and ordering
and auditing and processing claims ranking hospital services ranking rankers of hospital
services and so on all of these things are examples of services which have to do with
the buying and selling the price determining side of things all right now goods are created
but then they're bought and sold they're transported it need be to the purchaser or maybe to the
finisher or maybe to the showroom where they can be shown to potential purchase and so on
and then that maybe they're protected they're kept in a climatized garage or something and
they're maintained and repaired and restored and so on over the years and then eventually
they are demolished or destroyed or recycled disposed of in some way so there is a product
life cycle the creation is the first step in the product life cycle maybe there's a zero
step which would be designed now all of these things are services so most of what goes on
in the life of a product a good is a service or involved services one way or another so these
are services which are applied directly to material entities so that's another kind of
ultimateness they are not applied to to people they're not applied to other services they're
applied to goods and demolition is a service I get a hundred dollars for every contract
that the bunker hill service is and then we have protecting services so you keep all your
cars in a warehouse which is protected by watchmen and electronic fences and cyber security
systems and so forth so certainly in the early stages of the supply chain for expensive goods
there is a lot of protection going on and then later on there'll be more and different sorts
of protection all right so goods are continuance so they exist beyond the time in which they are
created so there's a common view which I used to embrace according to which services all of
services are occurrence and I still embrace that view the common view will come in a minute
so that process is performed by a service provider or by a company of service providers
and now the view which I used to embrace for all services says that they're all what I would now
like to call pure services which means that production and consumption coincide at least
temporarily often spatio-temporally so a medical interpreter provides a service of interpreting
and in providing that service that service is also consumed by stuff there is no left over
and it's the same for a bodyguard a haunted house tour guide provides a service but you probably
forget what you learned so there's nothing left over that may be the memories which will fade
but no nothing which has economic significance for instance from any of these pure services I
think pure services are a relatively small fraction of the entire empire of services
so now let's move to social work and general medical practice
are these pure services so they can both of them have outcomes which means that they're
not pure services so in the one case the doctor may give you a bottle of pills
in the other case the social work again may give you a script which enables you to get money and so
both of them have alienable benefits and so they're not pure services so what about
just advice so you go to the doctor or to the social worker just to get advice then there are two
cases you ignore the advice or you accept the advice if you ignore the advice it's a it's a
pure service it's a very very weak and strange kind of nugatory pure service if the advice is
accepted however then there is something which survives and this is the central thesis of the
whole talk what survives is because you accept the advice to go running every day or stop beating
your wife or something the person who receives the advice acquires a new disposition and what
that means is that something in that person's brain has changed there's a new pattern in that
person's brain which serves as the basis for a disposition to go running every day or to stop
eating chocolate or something so pure services create no issue they're relatively rare and the
common view according to which services create nothing says that all services are pure services
and we reject that common view with the view that nearly all services create specifically dependent
continuance they create patterns quality patterns in for instance people's brains so these are the
examples of services and they're all impure services in my sense so the hairdresser creates a new
pattern on your head the gardener creates a new pattern in your garden and the teacher creates
a new pattern in your brain and none of those patterns are alienable you can't sell them or
store them or rent them but they're created by services and that's why we pay money for those
services because of what they create not because we enjoy watching the gardener or because we enjoy
hearing the hairdresser's clips but because we want the pattern
all right now this fits into bfo as follows the disposition has as its material basis
a new quality which is a pattern in the brain of the person who acquires the disposition
so we have material entities which are people families goods machines for creating goods
or transporting goods a pattern which is a kind of quality complex quality capability which i'll
talk about next which is the kind of disposition the client of the social worker has the capability
to go running every day and then the service itself which is a process and and now we can
capability a capability is a disposition of a certain sort whose realization someone
or some group could be an organism of a non-human kind but we'll focus on humans here
has an interest so you all have an interest in digesting your food and so you have a capability
of digesting your food your digestive system has the function of digesting food which is also a
capability but it's a special kind of capability if you have an interest in the realization of a
disposition that disposition is a capability we can now deal with hospital administration services
in the same sort of way so this is what we have the simple services which have outputs simple
patterns and the patterns are intrinsically valuable there that's the idea and these are all
experts who have certain capabilities so that they're able to perform services which bring about
these intrinsically valuable patterns but now there are more complex services such as hospital
consulting services and now we get a two-stage process the hospital consultant bears the capability
of the first type which is realized in the consulting service which has an output a pattern
in the hospital which is the material basis of a second capability which is the capability of the
hospital itself to smoothly more smoothly run than they did before the consultant performed her service
if you're lucky now we we are going to have ultimate services and the ultimate services are
just the first the simple case this case just the one pattern step and then non-ultimate services
will be the ones which have multiple steps in the case of the consultant we have a two-step
process we could have if you're teaching consultants to teach hospital managers how to run a hospital
that's a three-step process there and another hypothesis that we I think is correct here is
that many perhaps nearly all non-ultimate services are performed to create new capabilities either
new capabilities in things or in organizations or in people that's just a hypothesis but I
I have a suspicion that it's going to hold in many cases buying and selling I said yields new
patterns of ownership now you can understand the significance of that thesis so that we're dealing
with services in general as creating patterns and buying and selling our services and they
create patterns in a very obvious way all right now let's go back to the protect restore eliminate
kind of approach so we have this approach for goods so we protect our new car we restore our new car
by repainting it and we eliminate our car by disposing of it but you can do these things
also to patterns so we may want to we may want to restore the pattern that was established in
our garden by the famous landscape designer 100 years ago and so we want to restore the same
paint pattern not the garden as a good now but the pattern that was created by the landscape
designer and we may want to protect the knowledge that acquired or the capability of our dog to catch
beans all right but now we get another level of services because these processes are services
which are applied to patterns created by prior services when they successfully restored the
Darwin Martin house in Buffalo they went for the original seeds of the same seed stock
as we used by Frank Lloyd Wright to create the bushes in the gardens and so forth and a lot of
it had been sold when the house became decrepit during the period after the Second World War I
think by the wife of the then president of the university of Buffalo she sold some of the windows
which now cost if you can find one they cost $17,000 why do you want the original windows
than the original bushes in order to create the original pattern as near as you can get
it's the same universal it's the same quality pattern as near as matters so if you want to get
the same capability to play tennis thing you have 10 years ago they can be applied to patterns
created by services but the same distinction can be applied to patterns in general so you may want
to protect an ancient forest which has never been touched by forest designers all right now we can
see how this works for different kinds of services so teaching and training the creating is the
coaching training in the gym and so on here the pattern protecting is things like follow-up exams
and promotion reviews pattern therapy is follow-up classes more more more exercise pattern restoring
is they send you back to school and pattern eliminating is brainwashing that's not a very
good example but Ryan came up with that example but I thought it was good at the time it's still
good for some purpose all right now gardening is obvious so you have anti-weed chemical spraying
tree doctor historical garden restoration and then eliminating the pattern would be weed removal
and dental that's obvious so creating the pattern is with the nears and caps that's creative dentistry
and then protective dentistry as a mouth guard prevented dentistry and training in brushing
and flossing restorative dentistry is restoring the correct pattern in your jaw through filling
and then eliminating limited dentistry is removing the tube and medical in general well we have
creative medicine which is cosmetic medicine and then protective medicine which is diet and exercise
therapy for instance therapy itself repairing in other words the curing the infection resetting
the broken arm or removing the tumor so these are all types of medical services which involve
something created like that your whole body was created in the first place by your parents
and then protecting what's created repairing what's created restoring what's created or
eliminating what's created or bits of it and so this is a picture of the high healthcare supply
chain so you want to protect the services of the hospital and that means you want to keep track of
how all the bed linen and all the pharmaceutical supplies and all the patients and all the ambulances
and all the fuel and so on are being delivered to the appropriate place in the supply chain at
the appropriate time in order to keep the hospital and the ambulance service running
not to mention the 911 service and so forth and now this is the final slide
just to get back to social services so creative social work is where the social
worker provides advice which in the successful case issued the nudist disposition on the side
of the client protected social work is where the social worker reports the case to the child
protective services that may be another partner for CBP and then prevented social work is
counseling the client on incipient family related problems with the aim of preventing them from
occurring restorative social work is social work with the goal of restoring those patterns
which is characteristic of healthy family development and then I couldn't think of an
example of eliminative social work so my name is Bart Gajdović I'm a postdoc at the University of
Toronto at the Center for Social Service Engineering and we work on essentially data
standards and ontologies for interoperability between social services and we focus on things
like measuring impact of services and service provisioning on clients and so this is really
interesting work that well that I've heard today but also that Barry has been working on and we
kind of started this discussion at the the joel workshops we had a workshop there on social
services and so yeah so this is this is really sort of interesting work in sort of defining
services for maybe a different perspective or a different use case but I really like the
the direction that this is going Barry so thanks very much and you don't have a question or a
criticism I have three questions actually if there's time one is I'm trying to understand
what a pattern is it is is it just a state that has some kind of structure
so it's basically the idea of quality in BFO arises as follows there are two kinds of attributes
that things can have one kind of attribute is what we call realizable which means that
it's not really there as something which is manifest but it can be made manifest by some
made manifest by some kind of external signal or process or some other means so and realisables
we decide divide into two parts dispositions which I've talked about just now and then roles
which Matias talked about yes Matias talked about earlier on the other hand are those attributes
which are manifest all the time to the extent that the bearer of the attribute has that attribute
and they they're called qualities and now patterns are just complex qualities that's all we mean
so the kind of pattern that I'm thinking of primarily in many of these examples is a pattern
in your brain so that would be a very very complicated electromagnetic electrochemical
magnetic pattern and whether that well we don't use the word state as a technical term in BFO
because we don't know what would be a good definition of state but I think the example
will give you a clue as to what we mean by a quality pattern okay great my second question was
so this is sort of there was leftover from the the previous workshop on social services but
you mentioned that a service is only something that is either I think I think you said a
legislative or has some kind of monetary exchange and so no no I I don't I don't think I ever held
that what I and what I said today was that I'm using examples of services which do have some
kind of commercial or pecuniary significance but I don't believe that the account I'm giving is
exclusively going to hold for those kinds of cases so I have a I think a general view of service
which is as general as your view of service okay so something like a community providing services
to or some people in a community providing like let's say meal services to yeah yeah that would
be a service in my opinion okay and the final question is this example of eliminative I was
trying to think I was trying to think if something like removing someone's addiction would be
eliminative but rereading your definitions here sounds like that would be more restorative
yeah so I said that it was that the eliminative one was sometimes hard to find examples and I
can't find even one but there is someone in the room who I think has an example I wanted to offer
a limited to could be interpreted as a non-ultimate service through the cessation of the social
service itself but that wouldn't eliminate the problem on the part of the client that and all
of the other cases have to do with the problem on the part of the client and and you're not going to
say kill the client no would it be maybe eliminating obstacles in the clients I mean if patterns are
just in the client's mind would it be eliminating sort of cognitive I think that's preventive
sounds more like preventive you're eliminating temptations for instance but as I say I don't
think that there is that I don't think it's a sound category eliminative social service
it just doesn't feel right I don't think it breaks everything but it does mean that there is a week
point yes psychotherapy in Canada um so now I'm going out on a deep end but let's suppose that you
had a kind of psychotherapy which counseled people to commit suicide and there have been cases in
history where there were such kinds of people who went around counseling other people to commit
but it's not a good thing yes pet okay good I will use it
but yes I think you're still on uh no my end I think is down and you've answered my questions
okay good