Welcome to Deep Transformation, Self-Society Spirit.
I'm Roger Walsh, and our co-host is John DePuy.
And with us today is a guest that I'm just delighted to be in dialogue with.
This is Daniel Schmacktenberger, one of the most incisive, integrative, and brilliant
thinkers about the great issues of our time.
Daniel's a polymath who has ranged across a wide variety of disciplines and has a prodigious
amount of information about multiple areas, topics, issues, concerns, and intellectual
disciplines, but not only a wide array of information, a remarkable degree of information
and integration, pulling topics together, synthesizing them in novel ways, and coming
up with creative innovations and ideas and synthesis.
He is able to and has been giving us a wide array of insights into the great issues of
our time.
And if you've searched the internet, you've probably run across Daniel and the many dialogues
he's had about the metacrisis, the term that's currently used for some total of our social
and global issues.
But what you haven't seen or heard of, Daniel, is his spiritual dimensions and the ways in
which those have touched his understanding of life and our current temporary concerns.
So we were really delighted, given that Deep Transformation is about transformation not
only of self and society, but also of spirit, when Daniel suggested that in our discussion
of the metacrisis, we focused specifically on the spiritual dimensions, which he said
he doesn't often get a chance to talk about.
And so we are just very happy to have this opportunity.
Daniel, so many people know you as someone, as a brilliant intellectual who has thought
deep and hard and synthetically and novelly about these great issues.
But you also have a deep commitment to self exploration, self actualization, spiritual
practice.
What would you like to share about that side of yourself?
First, thanks for having me here, it's good to be with you both and all the people engaging
in the podcast.
When it comes to the spiritual dimensions, and we'll probably want to unpack what we
even mean by spiritual sense, it is a pretty unprecise term often.
But the psychological, interior, sacred, whatever dimensions of the state of our world, I would
love to be in that conversation together.
I don't have a preset set of things to talk about on it, because as you mentioned, it's
not the thing I talk about all the time, but obviously very interesting.
I was fortunate in my growing up to get to study a lot of the people that might be called
great polymaths throughout history, so I have a heap of respect for them and I've tried
to learn what I can, I would not describe myself that way.
I think the connection is I would describe myself as being deeply interested in lots of
things, and I find that what people are interested in and what they find meaningful, and at the
heart of that what they find sacred are usually connected, though they might not be explicitly
aware, and the things that people are interested in and enough, they often develop some capacity
at, and if someone has some sense of the wholeness of reality, as opposed to when we think in
different disciplines, here's where biology starts and chemistry stops or physics or whatever,
those are ways we take the complexity of the world and try to divide it to make subjects
and make it easier to study, but those divisions don't exist in reality in that way.
So if we have some sense of just the integrated wholeness of reality and we're kind of interested in it,
there's some sense that reality itself is sacred, then there would be nothing that isn't interesting.
It's like, if you're really in love with your partner, what aspect of their being is uninteresting to you?
It's a weird proposition to say, oh, I don't give a shit what she thinks about, or her
talk books on fashion or whatever it is, and it's such a superficial place to be, because even if you
didn't think you cared about that topic on your own, if you really care about this being and this
being cares about it, work to understand why they care about it, because there's some part of their
being you're missing, if the fascination they have, if the care, if the love doesn't translate to,
and so if you get that, you're like, well, whatever, every aspect of them I'm interested in,
because part of love is the desire to know, because what does it mean that I love somebody if I don't
really know who they are? And if I have some love for reality, then wanting to know it more is
one of the things, right, wanting to appreciate it more wanting to be in more service to it,
and those are all just kind of natural byproducts. And so relatively young,
I had the insight that everything was interesting, that the things that I thought weren't interesting,
because at first I didn't think that, but the things I thought weren't interesting was just
because I didn't get them, I didn't understand why anyone else found it interesting, and if I
tuned in empathetically enough to them, and I could see it, I'm like, oh, there's a whole
dimension of meaningfulness and beauty and parts of the nature of reality that I'm just missing,
and when Gibran said it's in, it was in meditation upon the dew drop that I discovered the mysteries
of the ocean, right, the kind of poetic way to speak to the fractal nature or the as without so
within, when there is some understanding of the integratedness of reality, a deep insight about
anything also gives you some insight about everything else. And one of the places that I
most insight was taking some principle in thermodynamics and applying it to gardening,
or some principle in evolutionary theory and applying it to relationships or whatever,
getting that like those theories were ways of understanding the universe, but all of them
gave different insights, looking at the world through a thermodynamics lens versus an evolutionary
psych lens versus a complexity theory lens gave different insights on the same reality.
So if I could take those insights and apply them to lots of things and apply lots of different
ones, just got to see more multi-dimensionally. I mean, one of the projects we launched called
the conciliance project, and that's what the word conciliance means is the more
perspectives one can take on the thing, the more depth and richness of information they can get
about it. So, and I think, you know, the the metacrisis, this area of study of like,
what are all the problems of the world is really like came from a childhood inquiry of
what is worth doing. And there were so many things that were worth doing. And I became
kind of clear that when you focus on one, one, I just couldn't leave some of the areas out,
right? Like, it was just, I don't know how many people have this experience, some for sure.
But when I would think about really focusing on factory farms or really focusing on
the issue of how many dogs and cats are getting put to sleep every year or clear cutting or whatever
it was, the idea that I was not focusing on the other things just wrecked me. And then getting
to see that there were so many groups focusing on those things, and yet so many of those things
collectively were getting worse, not better. And I was wondering, do we just need more effort in
these areas? Or is there something about the nature of the effort that is that is off?
And the answer is both. But there was definitely something about, and people have heard me talk
other places, the way we solve problems causes other problems almost all the time, because we
define the problem too narrowly, we create a first order solution that the technology or a law or
business or whatever to solve it. But that's connected to a complex set of things, and it
produces second and third order effects somewhere else. So the dam to bring electricity to poor
people to solve the poverty issue might extinct a bunch of species downriver from the dam that
just got flooded or whatever in this, a million examples of this. So there's a, it actually became
clear that the study of the issues in the world and the siloing of the issues in the world was
a part of the problem itself, why we weren't solving them in a way that Bohm talked about very
well, David Bohm. And so the, like what is worth caring about everything, you know, how it fits
together, what is worth studying is kind of everything. The study is for itself, it's pure
knowledge of just the intimacy with universes intrinsically interesting. And it's also has
utility, it can increase the capacity to be of service to. Those are some initial thoughts.
And Daniel, did you, was there a point as a young man or a teenager, you began as you were
kind of chewing on all this and seeing it was that starting to emerge as a calling
for you that maybe that was your path to start connecting the dots and seeing how these things
mattered? I think
I think most people when they're young are enculturated in a particular way about who they are
and what life is about and what they should pursue. And then some of them continue on that path,
some of them recognize that their parents idea of what they're calling should be or their culture's
idea is not their own and then they have kind of this path change. I've had lots of path
refinements. I have had times of deep study in esoteric metaphysics and hardcore reductionist
atheism, you know, like any young person who's trying to be intellectually congruent and make
sense of stuff and not miss stuff. But they had the same spirit to them, which is funny, right?
They had the same spirit, which was like, and you can't even put words to it because you can
say it's what is true, but it's also kind of what is good, what is meaningful, what is beautiful,
and you know, something like that. But I think I was pretty fortunate in a way that some other,
but not lots of other people were in terms of early childhood exposure to the topic of what is my
path is that I had parents that were putting that question as the forefront of my education
since I was born. And so that's a pretty fortunate thing. And I went to school a few times mostly
my parents were interested in me getting some socialization, but I was mostly home school.
And they were interested in running a kind of educational experiment. And they were not
educational philosophers in any formally trained sense, they hadn't read Dewey and Montessori and
Steiner, they just had their own kind of intuitions about it. But some really good intuitions.
But the sense was rather than have a curriculum based thing have some sense of trust that the
kids innate curiosities if facilitated will orient them in the right direction. So it's kind
of constructivist. And so we had a homeschool that had no curriculum at all. And there are a few
places where this was significantly disadvantageous because like it wasn't till I was an adult and
paying attention to spell checker that I learned how to spell. It's very fortunate. I didn't do enough
of the like writing letters penmanship to actually have refined the fine motor skills enough to have
legible handwriting. I didn't get it and then let it devolve because of busyness like some doctors,
I just never even got decent penmanship. It was a good thing I can type. There were whole areas of
like American history and things that were actually important that I just didn't know were
important and I just had none of them. But then there were some areas that I got to study way
more deeply than people normally would have at those times. But because I was studying things
I was interested in, I doubled down on interest, right? And I think one of the things that happens
for a kid is when you don't facilitate their interests because you don't know how, which
so often the kids are asking questions and the parents just don't know the answers. I give these
examples a lot because they come up all the time when a kid asks why is the sky blue or why is fire
hot. You have to understand many layers of physics but then also neuroscience and then also the
philosophy of mind to be able to translate the subjective experience of hotness from sensations
that happen on the skin and what is communicated between cells and in the nervous system to what
is the thermodynamics of fire or the nature of the molecules in the upper atmosphere that create
blueness in the visual optical spectrum. Those questions, if every kid asks stuff like that
and if you know how to facilitate the interest, they end up learning everything from theory of
mind to philosophy of science to, you know, atmospherics and neurobiology. But if you don't
facilitate the things they're interested in and you force them to do shit that they're not interested
in, it can break their interest and then they become a little bit more focused on quick hits of
dopaminergic interest rather than deep learning. So I had that fortune but the other fortune other
than just kind of just hiding my own curriculum is because a kid will largely be interested in
things based on what they're exposed to and how they're exposed. I don't find that there are any
kids who aren't interested in math who had amazing math teachers or who weren't interested in art who
had amazing art teachers or history. So how they're exposed, what they're exposed to. And so
what my parents were interested in had a lot to do with what I was interested in, of course,
right? This is one of the limits of constructivism is, you know, what the reality of what the
kid is exposed to. But again, I feel like I lucked out in terms of their interest being things were
a pretty good set of things. So my, my parents were reading Buckminster Fuller and kind of design
science and they were reading David Bowman, Krishnamurti, they were reading kind of Vedanta
and Eastern philosophy for Choff Capra and the kind of emerging systems theory in the early 80s and
and they also the thought that there's no reason bedtime kids bedtime stories for kids when their
infants need to be Dr. Seuss as opposed to synergetics by Bucking Fuller because kids learning
language no matter what. And so those were like my primitive concepts and included in those were
the core existential questions of what are we, what are we here for? What is this all about?
And then the people using kind of the most advanced frameworks of the time like systems theory and
design science to think about how do we go about making a better world and like that. So I never
really had to find my way to that. That was kind of the default setting. I had to find and upon
further inquiry of like, was that a wrong default setting? Should I just
just make money or make art or something else? Like no, that didn't, that ended up continuing to be
roughly right direction, but trying to more competently answer how to understand the issues
of the world and how to be of service to them. It's a lot of content refinement.
Daniel, so you had an unusually broad self-directed education, but there's also
something else that's quite distinctive about your thinking and that is a rare degree of integration.
And how did you develop that?
I have friends who are developmental theorists who, Zach Stein, who I work with closely and
many others, who will talk about how there is an increase in the type of
complexity of what someone can process, the way they notice changes in context for processing
the same content the way they can seek and shift perspectives and then integrate them. And I think
there's a lot true and important there. I have other friends who are critics of developmental
theory because they say there's a lot of societal normative assumptions based on how people are
kind of ubiquitously trained that in a different society with different childhood development
would go differently. So for instance, if kids are being taught in school, this is math, this is
social studies, this is history, this is biology, and they're being taught a compartmentalized
universe where they're never asked how the social science is being influenced by the biology or
vice versa or how the principles co-apply, they're getting a non-integrated fragmented world
given to them and actually behaviorally trained up on thinking that way. They're not being given
any kind of integrated framework, so then we get excited when someone becomes an integrative thinker
later because it was trained out of everybody. I don't think it is actually necessary that people
learn that way. I think it's not even the case in say, pre-industrialized education, it just wasn't
even the case in the same way. And so because my education was self-directed, it also didn't have
clear delineations of topics. I was never doing math or social studies. I was doing an inquiry
about something that was interesting that might have involved some math and some, you know,
quite a few things. So if you're trying to understand integrative things like how does a
body self-organize? How does a fetus actually develop? How does that? Then you're having to
intrinsically be radically interdisciplinary. What is worth doing in the world and how do we know?
So I think the most interesting questions are at a high enough level of abstraction that to address
them well, there's the taxonomy of questions beneath them is very interdisciplinary and you
actually have to bridge across them. So I do think a totally different educational paradigm
could have analysis and synthesis or integration on a knowledge that happening simultaneously
at each level of complexity. Yeah. And pulling together some of the things you've said,
you've spoken to your education, you've spoken to the natural integrative thinking that emerges
from a problem-solving approach to education as opposed to a compartmentalized scholastic
disciplinary approach. But also underlying this was sounds like a real desire for an
appreciation of the whole and a desire to optimize service. And it seems like what I'm
hearing is that those two things led you to this in big picture integrative approach to
understanding and responding to the great issues of our time. Yeah, I'll share a few other things
that I think were significant influences that I'm grateful for and that I think are interesting
for everybody to look at is... I think there's a good bit of evidence that the
people that many of us find to be some of the greatest exemplars of human potential
were the result of developmental paths that are more accessible to everyone than lots of people
or think. Not just some weird genetic or situational anomaly. And I'm not saying that genetics plays
no role in aptitude, of course it does. The height is a real thing that's going to affect
aptitude, size, whatever, and maybe does it do that for neural connectivity? Sure. But
I believe his name is Eric Hoel, who was an academic who started a very interesting blog recently,
published this article that then has gotten a lot of traction and debate around where
of all the super genius has gone. And it's a resource I think is really interesting and worth
people paying attention to. Of course, there are problems with what we think of as super genius
because might a aboriginal tracker who doesn't solve Rubik's cubes particularly well or do the
normal IQ things be a super genius in a totally different set of dimensions on things we can't
even perceive with our normal cognitive science kind of models, sure. But if we just take what
he was meaning here, he was saying it seems that the Isaac Newton's and Einstein's and
the people that contributed novel insights to many fields that specialists in those fields
appreciated and hadn't done, that we are seeing less of that recently than we have in a long time.
And this is a whole fascinating debate. I know I'm a bit off topic, but I find this an interesting
topic and maybe relevant. Some people think the idea that there is less super genius now is just
wrong and some kind of romanticizing the past, but there's pretty meaningful data in here in
terms of how quickly do new scientific insights happen or philosophical insights or legal insights
happen that are paradigm shifting that would change a Cooney and paradigm or something like that.
Some people think it's that there's just so much more fucking knowledge now than there was that you
just can't be a polymath that you could have been a polymath before and all the stuff and
nobody can now that it takes all of your life to be a specialist in a tiny discipline and that the
only thing that can make breakthroughs now is huge teams of specialist scientists with big data
processing AIs. There's a lot of different ideas about it. Feynman famously said that he thought
he would be in the last generation of great physicists for some time based on what he saw
happening in the direction of physics and the direction of education and there have certainly
been some developments in physics since but maybe not of the type from modern physics to him.
I think there is some truth in this that has that we are actually developing people of that type
less globally independent of the increasing complexity of the world as also a factor.
I think there's a few reasons for it but one of them that seems to be pretty compelling and so this
this article about where the super genius has gone puts forth that there is a lot of data
that points to the idea that most of the great polymaths the super geniuses if you want to call
it were have one thing really clearly in common obviously not a hundred percent correlation but
a higher correlation than anything else which was that they were the result of aristocratic tutoring
high quality aristocratic tutoring and that post the kind of modernity and democratic
reformation of the world there was no aristocratic tutoring of the same kind and that it really makes
a difference so if you think about it this little boy in Tibet identifies certain bulls
in pain so we say he's the Dalai Lama from a reincarnation perspective but then how does he
get educated right yeah right the top llamas in Tibet who are the top meditators and oracles and
philosophers and historians and scholars and mathematicians are all privately training this
boy with the investment of their entire culture is the Dalai Lama the result of an educational
paradigm that doesn't really scale because how could you have the best teachers of a whole
peoples you know for everybody and is the Dalai Lama's type of consciousness and capacity
actually something that could be trained if people had access to that it's a fair question
when you read meditations by Marcus Aurelius which is also a great philosophic text the first
chapter he dedicates just to his tutors right the intact like he writes the book of stoic philosophy
as the emperor of Rome and the first chapter is just a dedication to his tutors because when
you're being raised to be the emperor of Rome during Rome's high period the best mathematician
in all of Rome is your math teacher and the best historian and there was another study I had seen
I find this theory of education stuff so deeply fascinating there's a study I'd seen that was
looking at world class or what were considered first rate mathematicians and they had some way
of defining what a first rate mathematician was and it wasn't just a field's medal it was something
some set of things but the highest statistical correlator they could find across everyone who
became a first rate mathematician to see like is there some trait that where we can predict this
is that when they were young they started to study with a first rate mathematician
and of course someone could do a correlation causation question and say was it only because
they had such exceptional ability that a first rate mathematician paid attention to them when
they were young but it does not appear that that is the direction of causation that they
got exposed to a first rate mathematician was teaching at their particular school for a while
at the time whatever because there are certain classes where a whole bunch of them came out of
that class where that teacher was and it makes sense because your average first grade or 12th
grade math teacher at a high school is not a first rate mathematician they're not even a second or
third rate mathematician the the brilliance of mathematical thinking the love of it the insight
the passion they don't have it they have something else right they study to be an educator they study
in a country that couldn't pay you all that much to be an educator so they aren't even a first
rate educator so can you learn how to think like a first rate mathematician from a normal math teacher
who is themselves someone who has never even had thought like that probably not and the same would
be true for spiritual insight or for anything else and so when you look at Marcus Aurelius you're
like it was who he was actually just the result of a good educational model and
when the modern democracies were forming the idea of feudalism was so disgusting and
were pregnant for many reasons and had to be shed away that anything that was a remnant of
feudalism had to be put away but in democratizing education to raise higher education for so many
people you also lowered the highest version of education to where the wealthy people whose
kids are getting tutoring today is to keep up with the normal scholastics of a curriculum based thing
it's not a personalized tutoring system for the most part and so I do partly why I was bringing
this up is that you know I didn't have a whole field of tutors but I had parents that were doing
that with me and then because I saw how valuable it was to have invested people be in that level
of dialogue I started seeking out tutors before I even knew this and this is like maybe the highest
thing I can recommend to young people or for parents what to do with their kids I somehow
knew because I also had stuff like think and grow rich and the kind of like tenacity of a
Carnegie to be self-directed as part of the thing but hopefully along a different set of goals than
just monetary accumulation but if you have the tenacity of a Carnegie associated with other
developmental goals which would be a really good thing whenever I found a teacher that seemed like
they knew something I really wanted to learn I figured out what I could possibly do to be useful
to them and that looked like cleaning their house and changing babies diapers and learning skills I
didn't have they needed electrical done I would learn electrical to those like whatever the fuck
it is this is where I want to study from so I'm going to figure out how to be around them and be useful
to them and so much of my learning was not what I studied in university that was cool or even just
in books on my own it was people who were really really fucking brilliant spending time with me
directly because I figured out how to partly I was a gift and partly I figured out how to make that
happen and Daniel is part of what you're saying as far as the tutor also a mentor relationship
having older people that can not only just download information but somehow impact your soul and your
being and you know it's all together see in a mentoring relationship they're not just topical
artists right they're who have because they're teaching to a whole class have to teach a curriculum
you're the kid is asking them questions that they're interested in the range beyond their
subject matter and the and the teacher in that relationship actually cares about them and loves
them and gets invested in their education so they ended up getting the benefit of something like good
parenting but multiplied by a lot more people a lot more capacities that error correct each other
and so the cognitive education shouldn't be limited to one domain separate from others it
should go across the domains but it shouldn't be limited to just cognitive education it should be
that the you know and so first the various domains of ontology need to integrate it you need to be
able to think about biology and chemistry and physics and etc together next is you have to
integrate a cross ontology and epistemology whenever the kid is learning something it's not
just here is how it works it's why does it work that way how is that discovered that this is one
of the next key insights is I never wanted to know a formula in math I wanted to know how long
people knew that that problem was interesting and didn't have the formula who discovered at first
what novel thing about their life gave them that insight what other new things they discovered
afterwards because of that you know like I wanted to know the epistemology and I find that when you
get that and you start to get what is the generator function of novel insight what is across all the
domains the the people who discovered the most important thing what was happening in them that
made them discover the most important thing you can start to develop that in yourself rather than
just a huge knowledge set in which case we're just shitty computers and so you want to integrate
all the ontologies you want to integrate ontology and epistemology and then all of that in the
cognitive domain you want to integrate to why do you care at all why do you care to want to learn so
the ethics the aesthetics the pragmatics also come in and the identity of the person in relationship
to it comes in and and and is there a developmental sense of responsibility that's transmitted it's
like I don't want to let my dad down my mom down these people that taught me I want to live up to
the the quality of the love and the gifts and the knowledge that they're imparting to me
you know
people being motivated to care about
people and animals and life forms that they will never meet and will never give them credit
like it takes some work it takes some developmental work to get there enough that
you'll make real sacrifices to care where you don't get any obvious credit for that it takes
having some sense of your identity expanded beyond your own individual self where you're
looking through their eyes right and you're and you get that they actually matter to you
reality but at first if somebody believes in a sky god that is all knowing all seeing and
internal punishment if you fuck up and they know your thoughts so you can't just virtue signal
because you can't virtue signal the god that knows it and eternal reward if you get it right so
even if you're really just a shithead who just doesn't want to get punished and wants to get a
reward you still have to be good all the way down to the level of your thoughts that's kind of awesome
right like from the point of view of just how do you get a lot of people who might still be
narcissists in a low degree of truly ethical development to do the right thing that kind of
like sky god judicial system is kind of awesome and another now it's also terrible because then
of course everybody's terrified of burning in hell forever and has to think that someone else
who's not getting it right is and they have to terrify their kids of burning in hell but
but in the same way the idea that many many traditions had that when I die I'm going to be
with the ancestors and I'm going to like and there's some glory of my of the great teachers
and will and they're still watching me right and and when I go to be with my forefathers
with the teachers in eternity and afterlife do I actually deserve to be with them
there's something in noble that can do right there's something powerfully ennobling that
old tradition can do of course we also find out that our great teachers are people that have their
failings and weaknesses and we have to wrestle with that and we're going to have our own failings
and weaknesses and we might get intellectually congruent enough to have some doubts on the
metaphysics of that thing but there is there is definitely something even if you don't go to
the metaphysics the afterlife version there is something about feeling that you received
something that you don't get to take credit for that you're fortunate that someone else was born
into a situation that if you were born into you'd be doing less well and that you were fortunate to
get to have these experiences and that you owe something to them and to the future world because
of that fortune I think that's really important anyway I've got to bring this up preparing for
this I went to your websites and I came across a blog article you've written things that I learned
from my dad I was deeply moved by this I halfway through when we got to the part how to treat women
I think I started weeping and immediately I like your father but I like you because this is what
you remembered from your father and it was so incredibly powerful and basic and I see such a
need for young men to be initiated into some sort of positive manhood and what your father laid out
I got a lot from my father but obviously he was not as articulate as your dad
that he lived a lot of these principles that you were talking about and can I read one of them
I love this the highest value for men is serving women nature and children future generations
the highest value for men
you should shout it from the rooftops that's incredibly profound
yeah my dad would say things all the time like you're either serving your family or the family
of mankind or your off-path those are the only two things that you can be doing that are not off-path
and the family of mankind was the term used but inclusive of life not just human life
yeah I mean I wrote that because my dad's health was very delicate at the time and it wasn't clear
if he was going to be around much longer or not and so often people write a eulogy of all the things
that they appreciated from their parent after they're dead and they don't get to experience it
directly and I thought that that would be a loss and so I wanted to write it for that reason
but I also wanted to write it that particular one is definitely not a full expression
of what I learned from my dad it was called things I learned about being a man from my dad
and so it was it was definitely oriented to the
principles that have to do with transfer of masculinity as opposed to just would be equally
true for all people some of them are of course that and part of the reason that I wrote it at
that time was I think I had had in conversations a rise in the week or two before of
men young men so boy into man phase who had just clearly never been fathered in important ways
and were causing pain to women they were in relationships with to people around them were
being or leaders and it was just I was like there are so many people that didn't have so many men
that are in their masculine role not having the fortune of having had a good role model of
teaching in that way and I wonder if some tiny little bit of vicarious element of it can come
through by writing about it so that's why I wrote that one in that way I think it came through for
me brother thank you for that and one of the things he said is like on your time off what you
do is you get in your pickup truck this was before cell phones and all and you drive around and find
people are having trouble with their cars getting them started you you fix their cars and send them
on their way and he said that's a good time that's the way to spend your day off and it's all
his orientation noble disinterested service and it's just anyway but it was so funny because
yeah this was before cell phones and so when someone broke down on the side of the road
pulling over to pick them up was an important thing and you know my I think part of teaching
someone about how the world works in general and also part of the ideas and I understand this is
normative like by gender normative thinking on the thing that is how it was given to me
was that for a boy growing into a man knowing how to solve problems and fix things
was a particularly important thing so anytime there was construction to do he always involved
me and it even were involving me and it took a lot more time than doing it without me because
he was not just trying to fix the thing he was also trying to raise a child who would someday
not just be an adult but would themselves be a parent and a teacher and how to
do that thing properly and whenever there was something to fix on the car it took
10 times longer to show me how to do it and you know then then not and so but then it was also
while we're fixing the car there were so many things like if a job is worth doing it's worth
doing well and well begun is half done and see the job do the job stay out of the misery these
kind of idioms and the if the job is worth doing it's worth doing well meant just no half-assing
the thing like we and so like I'll give you an example that was so beautiful I remember the
first time we're building a building from the ground up we laid the studs and then we drilled
to the studs to run the wire for the outlets and it was very important to my dad that the way the
wiring was in the wall before the drywall went on was beautiful that the holes were at the same
height that the Romex was not twisted and that it was beautiful and no one would ever fucking see it
we're about to cover it in drywall and you're like why and he's like you know you know you know
it's an incredible teaching that's and there's something where it's like the if you can do it
any of the ways do it the way that is the most integrous the most awful the most beautiful
and you will feel better about it and you'll feel better about who you are and then your
unconscious default in the moments where it matters and other things will be to do the
thing in the highest way you possibly can as opposed to asking the corner cutting questions and
um so the if it's worth doing it's worth doing well see the job do the job stay out of the misery
meant uh don't even ask if it's possible and definitely don't bitch about it just if it needs
done figure out how to do it and do it with the best attitude because you have choice over your
attitude and why would you do it any other way um and well begun is half done meant have you
cleaned the space first have you set out the tools do you know what the workflow is going to be
because the problems that are going to come up when you've opened everything up it's up on the
jacks and you realize you're missing something and you have to go to the store like that's where
the danger happened that's where someone gets hurt that's where the inefficiency happens that's
so think through the process pretty well first um and anticipate where the mistakes and the
problems and the challenges are going to happen there's so much of my work in the
metacrisis that is anticipate where the unanticipated externalities going to happen
and then internalize those future externalities into the choice making process better and uh yeah
yeah like I can see now how you are basically uh self-taught and coached and mentored into
uh into the ideals which would lead you into a life of service into a way of thinking
which would bring you into a big picture approach and into a planning mode that would allow you to
anticipate second third order complications and to think through those to uh you were honed for
the work you're doing now wait there's something that I was starting to say it's important please
remember your thought because I don't want you to forget it but I don't want to forget this
but you were you had um mentioned John the um that a fun time was to load up the tools
and go looking for people who are broken down and fix up their car because
AAA wouldn't necessarily come all the time especially if it was snowing outside they
could actually be in danger um so obviously that meant you know there I had to know some
how to fix a car type skills so I was mentioning that my dad would take a lot more time to do the
thing than pay someone else to do it and to do it with me than do it on his own because he was
wanting me to learn learning these other deeper psychological spiritual integrity lessons along
with it like well begun is half done and if a job's worth doing this worth doing well but then
also um learning the mechanical engineering of why was the screw threaded this way rather than the
other way and why was the sting built this way and then the history of internal combustion engines
and when the transmission came out and the um you know like and and then the physics of how
the explosion happens inside of the piston and so there's a very integrated set
of knowledge that was happening and that takes just a lot of investment right takes a lot of
care and a lot of investment and but then when we would do that it was like sunday father son
let's have fun um he wasn't into sports so we didn't throw a ball uh that's my my
anti-coordination at the level of ball throwing didn't develop all that much but we would uh
load the load the truck up with tools and go look for people who are broken down and fix it
up and the interesting thing was it didn't feel like some dreadful sacrifice of service that we
had to do the way that a lot of people um feel when they're doing some church activity as kids
they don't like it felt like the most fun thing we could possibly do like it was just actually
really enjoyable because one i'm getting this high quality time with my dad right he's not
trying to get me to go do the thing on my own who we're getting to be learning in the process
and then helping people where there's this immediate you know expression of these people
being delighted and surprised and so there was absolutely it wasn't just like an ethic of service
it was like a like a way to condition that as that the what i want for myself personally and
who i want to be for the world there wasn't even a distinction yeah beautiful yeah and
another thing your dad said and i'll stop parping on your dad i could go on and on this but he said
and this is so simple but so profound he said forgive just as a given you've got to forgive
and the second part is help them do better so you just don't forgive okay i'm okay i'm clear
you know i didn't bother anymore because i forgive him but the other part is help them
do better i just think that's one of my and i was a kid and there's a period where my
parents were in the tm community and built this beautiful community called lake view
estates out in fairfield and we're working on on the kind of enlightened theme park and
and a development business and there was someone that was an extremely close friend of the family
and um kind of employee and partner who had for whatever reasons um decided that he was going to
come into our house and steal a bunch of the artwork and uh because he you know had the
key to the house and all like that and uh you know but the trail like that oftentimes very easy to be
like want to be vindictive or at least totally cut ties i remember my dad intercepting him
not letting him do that and then taking him out and having this conversation like dude what the
fuck like what happened inside your head is this who you want to be and and there was still to like
help them do better um and one of the ones that really stood out to me and you know i there's
something where i feel torn about this first just as a caveat i must say the reason i didn't
write one about my mom at the time was because i don't think there is as gruesome a deficit of
mothering in the world as there is fathering currently and so i didn't have as many women
in sharing with me just like kind of abject failures of fundamental things as i had guys so
i was a little bit more motivated for that reason also her health is better but my mother is also
everybody's important in in my life and childhood and who i became and uh was the one that got me
into activism and had me going door to door with and had all the protests with pita and greenpeace
and all those things as a kid and got me studying art and introduced me to dolly and picasso and
jebron and blake and you know brought me to all the world religions churches and
but going back to my dad here my dad had a strong patriarchal line that taught him some
of these things his dad was first generation green beret and so that you know taught that way
but he also had a really fucked up childhood with a humongous amount of trauma
his dad commits suicide his sister commits suicide is many of his family members were in
and out of incarceration in mental institutions and and the violence of the childhood he was in
he's covered in physical scars from weapons you know like he had a rough go of it and so
some of what he got he got directly but a lot of it was his way to not kill himself was to say
maybe he's not crazy the entire world is crazy because the whole world he was exposed to seem
completely crazy to him and he'd rethink everything from scratch and so when you do that you come up
with a lot of good and interesting things and also are going to make a lot of mistakes and
their painful parts in the process and I didn't emphasize those in that letter because it wasn't
the purpose of the letter the article but you know my path benefited from all the extreme
gifts and it had some like quite interesting hardships as a result of the complexity of
who he was from transcending his life all those other things is what got me into therapy young
and which I'm also very grateful for because then I ended up getting a huge amount of
you know basically parenting from the therapeutic traditions
the reason I say that is so that people don't think oh well I can't do well because I had trauma
because I didn't have some of these gifts I everybody's life has some gifts and has some
fucked up stuff and the difficult stuff the healing of it is what catalyzes their gifts
and I just want to say that and some of the gifts that he had were really
fairly rare and unusual I'm very grateful for that some of the issues he had were somewhat
unusual but when it comes to one of the things on the forgive he definitely had the gift of being
physically heroic and there are military men who are trained in that a lot of people are not
in this age physically heroic in previous ages that was much more common
and there was a time here in Encinitas when I was like 20
where which is usually not a violent area my dad was in the
parking lot on thoroughfare here El Camino Real gunshots rang out handful of gunshots
from a blind store and everybody who was in the parking lot ran the other way or dropped my dad
ran straight at the blind store he figured the shooter was still alive and in there turned out
the shooter after killing the other person killed himself so by the time my dad got in there the
shooter was dead it was a husband who was going in there to suicide homicide his wife
and the but he shot himself he stabbed her and when he thought he had finished killing her
then he shot himself when my dad got there she was bleeding out but not dead and so he started
to put compression and turn the kits and whatever on you know all the areas where the ambulance
and police came but then he went to the hospital to be with her and then followed up with her
afterwards and in addition to like she would have bled out if he was not there saving her life
was him wanting to make sure that she could forgive her husband for that because of knowing how
fucked up he was and that he's no longer you know in pain himself or a risk to anybody else
but that was like it was his default mode and I mean almost too fast that it can be a bypass
but in that moment it was both and you know just a very interesting thing about him is like
thinking the shooter was still alive he thought I can keep my body moving long enough if I take
shots that I can take him out and more civilians won't get killed which means he was willing to
risk his life for people he had never met didn't even couldn't even see to know what color they were
a race or whatever this is very noble very beautiful and then the moment the harm of the
dying was out of the way the harm of her holding on to that grudging sentiment was the next one he
was focused on. What a gift to be exposed to and live with someone like that and not only an education
but a transmission of normal values and priorities and to take up a theme a question I began with a
little while ago as you've described this it's getting more and more clear how your life has been
self-developed and honed and gifted by multiple people to bring you to your life's work which has
been the metacrisis and how we as a species and a civilization can continue because clearly we're
in danger right now and presumably will be forever after because the technology is probably only
going to get more developed and greater capacities etc so you've been you've been you've had these
ideals of service transmitted to you've had attitudes of handling them schoolfully looking
for complications thinking ahead etc you've also had the multidisciplinary education so how does the
how does the to these depths the spiritual depths that and self-inquiry you've gone through not
only in spirituality but in psychotherapy and philosophic inquiry how do these how do these
depths inform you about our contemporary crises and what do you see lacking that these
these steps when these depths aren't appreciated what do we miss
I was speaking with a friend recently who does conservation work and she's a brilliant conservationist
who has kept huge important areas of high biodiversity intact and has done so at a
significant devotion including expense of her own personal life and in other areas
we're talking and she had just been in conversation with some of the world's wealthiest people
and she asked me when someone asks why should we protect nature how to answer it
because that was obviously their question and I said well there's a lot of answers that we can give
that from a you from the utility perspective of helping them get why they should care we
we look at what they currently care about and we show a rationalized argument between why
the harm that would come to nature would harm something they would care about right we draw
those connections but before getting there the fact that someone has to ask that question in
earnest speaks to something broken in them at minimum something pathologically underdeveloped
and if they had had a life where they grew up in any real contact with their own embodiment
their own kind of biology and experience of being in a body being and in any real contact with
nature and other sentient beings that question just wouldn't even arise
it would be prima facie right it would be it would be obvious and the question would simply be
how do we do a better job with it and I saw one of the in the brief look one of the questions
that you sometimes explore with guests of like what are the questions that orient their relationship
to the sacred and I think at the at the heart of it it's not even a question right it's a
something more like a perception I think if someone is perceiving somewhat clearly
then the sacredness of life is prima facie just is and I don't remember the exact quote but it was a
Joseph Campbell quote that was something to the effect of
that we think what we want is to know what the meaning of life is when what we're
actually seeking is the experience of being fully alive and I don't think that is the whole
because someone can experience being fully alive in fairly self-centered ways just doing
you know extreme sports and whatever but it is also true that in the moments where someone is
experiencing feeling fully alive they're not an existential angst about what is the meaning of life
and I think that oftentimes the actual intrinsic sacredness and meaningful of
meaningfulness of life that happens through a deep enough bandwidth of connection and sensing
the longing for that it's filtered through the mind as a desire to understand what is the purpose
of all of this what is the meaning with a whole bunch of bad assumptions about like what thing is
it building to that seems like a terminal value that then I can't then that will be a satisfying
answer where if we say well the purpose is love then I say well what is the purpose of that or
the purpose is learning well what is the purpose of it it's so we can the first the concept of
purpose and the concept of meaningfulness are not identical but the reality of them and the
concept of them are not the same either and so how to develop a deeper connection to the
a deeper connection to life and deeper ability to perceive the innate uniqueness of everything
and the interconnectedness of everything at the same time right the interconnectedness of it all
but not it's not it's not a homogenous oneness where because if it's a homogenous oneness
it doesn't matter how many of these ones die it doesn't matter if the species goes the oneness
is still oneness if it is just uniqueness but not interconnectedness well then in the service
of this one I can damage these ones it's every part unique and every part radically interconnected
in which case it is all an expression of the whole so I whatever I care about I also have
to care about all of it because it's connected and also each part is irreplaceable and those
totally precious right and it's not that is the thought it's that is the perception
from there from that base state of perception I think the right other questions and analytics
more naturally arise yes so the to the extent we can open ourselves to
the totality of experience to to life the world and to ourselves to that extent in some ways
and so in one sense one could say the questions fall away because the questions are conceptual
and we're you're now speaking to an experiential openness and directness
that give birth to understandings or intuitions which can flower into concepts
obviously I'm obviously into concepts right I'm obviously into work
you're a good company um I wrote a blog piece a while ago called the dance of the
Tao and the 10 000 things and maybe that one can be linked I'm specifically talking about that because
you know there's this concept in Taoism that every day in the practice of knowledge something is
added every day in the practice of the Tao something is dropped and but I think they are
both meaningful and I think that not only there's a way in which learning more about the 10 000
things the field of conceptuality and interfere with one's connection to the Tao there's a way
that it can also enhance it yes you don't know how they can dance together if you don't know how it
can enhance it then you have to just avoid intellect mind past future mostly the things
that are uniquely sapient uniquely adult sapient and say look at the lilies of the field look at
the little children you're like yes the things that don't have the prefrontal cortex yes the
prefrontal adult brain can cause problems but it also has unique evolutionary purposes we just
have to use it right um and two things there Daniel one one is the intention what's the intention
of using the intellect is it to get lost in the abstractions or is it in the service of the solution
and the other is the skill and capacity to integrate into a kind of vision logic say
I think those are both part of it I had a friend that I think you know Samantha Sweetwater
she hasn't been on this podcast she'd be great to be on she just left me a message this morning with
a thought she was saying the way she phrased it was that sapience is in service of sentience
if it is to be rightly guided oh I thought that was a nice way of phrasing it I um
in terms of the Greek the true the good and the beautiful triad I remember writing to an
artist friend of mine on her birthday once uh that the true and the good only matter because
the beautiful is um or no I think I said truth and goodness only matter because beauty is that
the beauty was actually the fundamental thing if reality did not have intrinsic beauty I wouldn't
actually care to be good to it or to know it or to whatever there's something that is intrinsic
that is deeper than the why Daniel I plenty yeah I have a follow-up question to all this
and I know they they threw it at Carl Young so uh I'm gonna throw it at you do you believe in God
I remember many many years ago and I wouldn't phrase it this way
any what more and there's maybe 15 years ago I wrote a poem called uh the atheist who writes love
poems to God and um it was saying do I believe in God not in any God that is believable meaning
that I don't remember where it went but the idea that what the word belief means is
the idea that a proposition about reality actually maps to reality and so belief is a
thing that can happen inside of propositional logic and propositions have to be formed in
semiotics right in in semantics and syntax do I believe that there is some sentences that I can
say that define what God is uh where I would say yes that is a description that I think is both
true and comprehensive and you know adequate and no I don't I think that's why the first verse of
the Tao Te Ching is the Tao that is speakable it's not the eternal Tao so if you believe in the Tao
you missed the whole fucking thing um if you you can have a outside of semiotics outside of
propositional experience outside of propositional knowledge experience of a kind of wordless knowing
in a connection to wholeness but you don't then try to reduce that to propositions about the world
so I think there's a lot of people that will have
real experiences that are numinous and transcendent and then try to make a belief based on that
and I think that's usually misguided so uh if I wanted to speak to beliefs do I think
that consciousness is an emergent property of brains probably not do I think that there
are things that don't have brains including other types of biology and whatever that might
have some quality or there is something that is like to be them probably yes but I'm holding all
this I say probably even though I think there's some pretty strong arguments uh because I I think
too much certainty about any of these things is really problematic um do I think that
it might not just be biology but that anything that self-organizes has some type of interiority
or self-ness in some kind of panpsychic type way yeah sure I do do I think that um
even though each cell in our brain or body is its own self-organizing thing they come together to
make something that is synergistically more than the sum of them taken separately yes do I think
that might be true for say universe as a whole or very large things within universe like galaxies
or whatever yeah I think that's interesting so do I think that um there are types of sentience
and types of intelligence that are more deep and vast by far than our imagination can think about
totally do I think that there is the possibility to in some meaningful ways
connect there and have results come from that connection yes do I think that there is an inherent
sacredness in all that is physically and metaphysically yes I wouldn't reduce all that to saying I
believe in God I rather think of it as something more respectful than the reduction to a proposition
I get that yeah um but but I was actually just talking with um a very close friend the other day
about an aspect of learning theory there are certain things
that when I learn them I have to work to implement them as effectively as I can because
I can't not I just I can't not and uh and there are many people who don't have that they um they
forget like they learn the thing and they forget and they're like oh yeah that was about I forgot
let me get back on path are they there's some different depth of the care about the thing
that is of course the result of all the exposure and whatever and I'm like yeah there is something
where it is like actually like the difference is actually believing there's a god right meaning
but it and that was the term that I used to just kind of make it simple in which if one actually
believes there's a god then they can go they can work to perfect themselves go to happily
die in a holy war whatever it is because there is some superordinate thing that is so fucking
important that everything else falls in line to that so there there is something for me and
belief in karma can do that right there is something that is like believing in a god
that is the coordinating basis of everything for me but it isn't believing in a god
and I can't do better with words no that yes I think that's a very sacred holy answer I think
you handled it really well and thank you for even even doing that means a lot yeah I'm beautiful that
certain that some of the some of the intimations in your response were
about to the uh unknowable mystery of reality bottomless fathomless inconceivable and to the
transconceptual nature of that mystery and actually of life that that the idea so the
doubt that can be named is not the eternal doubt and even more than that we can't any statement we
make is you know in fact it can be valuable but it's never fully adequate to the reality of anything
and to the extent that you think that you even unconsciously even fuzzily think of it as adequate
now it's actually harming you yes because now it deadens your perceptions now it creates
less you don't see the reality you see the frame of the reality that you expect to see it in and
you stop seeing where that model is inadequate which means you stop learning because you're
now filtering reality through that model because it's convenient so in that thing the dance of the
doubt and the 10 000 things there's one part where I say do atoms exist I'm like kind of kind of because
uh and I'm and I didn't play with it from the point of view of is there physicality at all or
is that all just an epiphenomenon of consciousness or is this a simulation I wasn't even playing
with it from that direction I was just saying do atoms exist well the periodic table works pretty
well we can actually uh do atomic level engineering and chemistry pretty well right this is it's about
as good a science as we've got there's a a lot of um good empirical things regarding atoms
but when I define an atom the formal definitions will like we can do it in terms of the Schrodinger
equation or information theory or particle physics or whatever but we'll say okay you've got nucleons
and you have electrons and you have orbitals and whatever um you can just say where in the
periodic table row and column it is and it's an ion or but does that atom exist without the strong
force does it exist without electromagnetism does it exist without the Higgs field does it exist
without the gauge bosons that mediate the connections the gluons and the Higgs boson it
doesn't exist without any of those things and yet none of them are included in the definition
when we say atom we take them all for granted so if I remove those that are not part of the
definition do atoms exist nope so if I want to define an atom adequately that it actually exists
can I do that nope and so I have to take for granted a trans finite amount of reality
to define this thing in a way that is useful but is it real kind of you've walked your way into
the buddhist shunyata and into the why buddhist wayan philosophy of the concealed and the revealed
that any perspective unveils or conceals a universe and simultaneously conceals another one
this is absolutely fascinating we could go anywhere with this but I want to I want to ask you
from this this perspective or these multiple perspectives you're bringing to bear
on your own your understanding of of everything what do you see as some of the deeper
unrecognized usually unacknowledged causes of the metacrisis and I'll just give a little context
and I think one of the beautiful things about the way the way you appreciate the metacons crisis
is you're very aware of the traps of reductionism or what I would call the single focus fallacy
which there are three a single issue fallacy the we're facing global warming that's it
a single cause fallacy it's all due to capitalism and the single solution fallacy so I love the way
you're thinking transcends those limitations and and recognize the traps of reductionism so
in asking you what you see as some of the deeper causes I certainly acknowledge that you don't
these aren't it but they are important elements and they're ones that don't often get don't as often
get spoken to yeah okay so the question as I understood is are are there
drivers or causes of the issues we face in the world and of the thing that
I sometimes call the metacrisis that we haven't defined here but I'm defining enough other places
of someone who is not already familiar they can check it out that are not the ones that we usually
talk about that are somehow deeper and I'm going to translate that to are there things in the inner
landscape of people's experience and psyche specifically just when we were saying are there
spiritual dimensions or interior dimensions the reason I want to make the distinction is because
I don't know that the term deeper makes sense just for quick point of reference I would not say
that I am a physicalist or an idealist in the classic philosophical sense of
physicalist meaning that physics comes first matter and force fields and third person stuff and
that consciousness emerges from that somewhere nor am I an idealist and that consciousness comes
first and all of the physics is an emergent property of consciousness structures of mind or
something I would say that the the subjective stuff and the objective stuff have you want to
think of that all the words have problems we can talk about first person third person we can talk
about the quality and the physics but that they are equally fundamental and co-informing
co-arising facets of an integrated reality and the relationship between them is part of that
fundamentality so I wouldn't say consciousness is deeper than physics to the nature of reality
I think that's a weird kind of dualism still I think information theory affecting physics has
already started to get a lot of people at least in this realm because if you say okay well consciousness
stuff is deeper than physics stuff and like well what is physics stuff well it's like atoms
atoms are subatomic particles and subatomic particles are some weird Heisenbergian Schrodinger
thing which seems a lot like some type of pattern of information that doesn't sound like physics
anymore right and it doesn't necessarily sound as different it's not like just some dead inert
matter it doesn't sound as different from the consciousness stuff especially as you start to
do a similar dive on what the consciousness stuff is because you say well is that information
processing on some information processing substrate what does that mean so in the same way
that I wouldn't say consciousness is deeper than physics or the other way around I wouldn't say that
the psychological drivers of the metacrisis are deeper than the technological or the economic ones
I would say that they are co-informing co-influencing and that to really address it there are necessary
things that have to happen across each of those areas and that sufficiency only happens across all
of them and I won't belabor the point because we've written and talked about it we wrote a
paper in the conciliance project called why technology is not values neutral
and it's worth people looking at and it shows just a brief overview of the work of
Marvin Harris and Marshall McLuhan and so many people in theory of technology of how
technologies change the nature of mind and psychology individually and collectively the
nature of culture in ways that are really subtle and not not obvious so I you know there's always
this question of there's the what technologies the world develops and what social systems it
develops are those the result of the consciousness and values of the people or the consciousness
and the values of the people who are born as babies being conditioned by the world that they're in
and the dominant systems and what things happen to be successful and if the worldview and the
technology creates don't win a war it just gets wiped out and so I'm framing it this way because
I think the deeper thing is actually really problematic it's you mentioned
um Roger the reductionism one type of reductionism is to say there's only one thing the other type
is say there's a handful of things but my favorite thing is the most important one um
and so being able to understand the co-arising and non-reduced process is actually really important
um if I can introduce if I can introduce the concept here Daniel I find I have a neologism
which is omnideterminism everything determines everything and I think that's what you're speaking
to yeah um yeah I might more usually talk about omni influence that everything is influenced
everything but not in a way that is absolutely deterministic because um nice refinement thank
you there are things that are outside of hard determinism still that influence the net result
of what happens also when we say omni we mean in the direction of all inclusive but we can never
actually know we're being all inclusive um so in fact we can know for sure that we aren't being
that's actually important um I can know for sure that I am not being all inclusive because
computationally it would be impossible um so the framing of the metacrisis we often talk about
involves like a frame I'll use often is um from Marvin Harris's work but to understand
its civilization you can think of it in terms of these three areas its infrastructure its
social structures and its superstructure its infrastructures all the technologies the whole
tech stack and all the modes of material development and like that the social structures are all the
collective agreement fields everything from the system of governance the law the institutions that
mediate it and the superstructure is the religion the cultural ideology the values the definition
of the good life so the the superstructure is kind of the spirituality psychology
interiority of the people at the collective level and so of course we're always talking about that
so I think seeing the top level frame of how all those fit together is worthwhile so if people
haven't um I'll just reference talked about in a bunch of places a good friend Nate Hagins who's
very good thinker on um specifically the relationship between the environment and energy and the
financial system he and I just did a five part series on his podcast and then the fourth part
we do a kind of an overview of the metacrisis that covers this the third part unintentionally
just because it came up we ended up covering how does one like emotionally psychologically and
spiritually deal with the reality of the metacrisis given that there's so much to care about beyond
what we feel like we have a sense of agency about those are ones that people might find
interesting the fifth one we talk about frameworks to think through solutions
competently so with all that prefacing I'll say some things here that I think maybe have not said
as much other places that are relevant to what in the interiority of human psyches and experiences
and cultures uh is a key or our key drivers of the problems of the world
I want to mention how many things there are that we probably have no fucking clue about
that are really critical just just to give a tiny couple examples
we know that there are a lot of species that have gone extinct at somewhere between 100 and
a thousand times the background rate of extinction since the industrial revolution as a result of
human activity those species are not just in the world externally there is a similar biodiversity
loss and species extinction in the microbiome of the human being and the microbiome of the human
being produces some of the necessary chemicals for us to work our genome doesn't actually produce
all the things some aspects of the macrophage binding protein and various things like that
are not adequately coated in the genome without a microbiome and and so extinction of some of
those is pretty humongous it's like deleting chunks of our genome right and but if you start
having ubiquitous antibiotics and chlorine in the water and pesticide exposure and all those types
of things so how much when you realize that somewhere between 50 and 80 percent of the
major mono and amine neurotransmitters like dopamine serotonin and gob are produced by the
microbiome in the gut and that how you think how you perceive what you believe how happy you are
what you your orientation towards violence will large to be or the result of that how much of
what seems like a spiritual crisis in the world is the result of the effects of the unintended
consequences of our kind of war on bacteria and biology and actually destroying part of the
code set that makes us able to be us that's not something that people often would think of when
they're thinking of the spiritual drivers of a thing but that is really important and if we
you know if we look at the Anthropocene at the human built world there are so many aspects of
the human built world that built a world we did not genetically evolve in we're not genetically
adapted to that makes us misfit to our own being in important ways um obviously for the
200,000 or 300,000 years of homo sapien history and the couple million years of hominin history
we always lived in tribes there was no such thing as not living in tribes until extremely
recently but we've been this way long enough that it seems like the nuclear family household
was the most obvious thing and the only thing that could ever be and we can't really imagine
anything else and yet it evolutionarily we evolved to fit in tribes so we so all the
shit about attachment theory we we evolved to have attachment to like 150 people like strong
attachments and where our life literally depended upon them we couldn't get our the the person who
knows medicine it's the only person who knows medicine i'm not going to interact with other
people so i can't just have a market opportunity to go to anybody so i actually need people and
they need me so i can't be a shithead to them so i and everybody's going to see what everybody
does so i can't lie and get away with it so like everything about psychology attachment theory
bonding the ideas of codependence and interdependence we're totally different and we evolved in that
setting right so then we get birth control and we're like oh sex doesn't have to equal reproduction
anymore even though forever sex always equals possibility of reproduction we evolved to have
our neural chemistry means sex equals the possibility of reproduction we put in birth
control our neural chemistry and our evolutionary value didn't just change overnight but now we're
acting in a way where it's like as if it doesn't mean that thing but a huge part of our whole
being is responding that way so the reason i bring this up is if we were to try to comprehensively list
all of the things
that are conditioning our psyches in ways that they did not evolve
to process and that are not optimal for us at an individual thriving a community thriving
or a global thriving would be this podcast would take days um and so that's a big topic
i just want to yes um if and i say that because if i say anything else first i'm
concerned that people over norm on that as the thing and then again lose observation to all
the things and complexity of all things so if i wanted to speak to something as the thing it would
be the nature of mind that makes us lose orientation to the complexity and the interconnectivity of
all the things um so if i if i was going to try to say what is the psychological generator function
of the metacrisis one i think as good a way of saying it as i could is kind of
not exactly the way david bone said it but it's derived from the way i heard him when he said the
problems of the world result from a fragmented consciousness that sees the world as a bunch
of parts and doesn't see the wholeness of things and he talked about wholeness in the
implicate order and can we perceive through that wholeness and obviously we know he was a student
of einstein's and einstein said it's an optical delusion of consciousness to believe there are
separate things there is one thing that we call universe and that we have to work to develop our
perception um so some of the problems in the world happen by be by intentionally advantaging
some things at the expense of other things we know it'll cause an expense so we're advantaging
our country at the expense of another country in a war which means our people our land our
riches or whatever at the expense of that for those people um that obviously means we're able to
separate the world enough to be able to think about this trade-off of good for these ones
and even though we know it's bad for these ones okay because we separate the interconnectedness
of everything and whether it's a country doing that to another country or in a relationship
of a person doing that to another person thinking they can possibly win a fight and someone they
love actually not get their needs met and that equals a good life for them somehow which is
fucking ridiculous idea um uh or at the level of corporations or anything else or humans with
regard to the biosphere or other animals we can advantage ourselves at their expense which
obviously a factory farm and an uh uh industrial fishing fleet are not good for those animals
are not good for the oceans are not good for the people working on them in poor conditions
the other problems in the world is where we didn't know that we're causing the harm right so we can
either benefit something at the expense of something else knowingly or we can benefit
something at the harm of something else not knowing so conflict theory and mistake theory
um and the real politic assessment of humans is the problems in the world are because we are
dumb and nasty right like roughly if you want to make it very simple dumb is we cause problems
that we didn't anticipate and nasty as we cause problems that we knew we're going to happen and
so the how do we enlighten humans has to deal with both the dumb and nasty part right if we're
talking if we're talking about how do we have the not not just how do you affect human behavior
through different rewards and deterrents and social norms and systems of law but through people
wanting something different having an internal motivational basis it would be can we expand
the circle of care where they care about more that's the even the nasty part and can we expand the
complexity of process where they can actually calculate their effects so that they are not
unintentionally harming things more that's the deal with the dumb part um but similarly there if I'm
thinking about
co2 and how critical it is to get it down but I'm not thinking about ocean dead zones
from nitrogen effluent using nitrogen fertilizer to grow more crops that will sequester more co2
seems like a good idea even though it's going to cause this other externalized issue
so again my ability to separate the ocean dead zones and the co2 is what's causing that unintentional
right or thinking about that facebook will be some cool system for people being able to tag photos
and get to know each other not thinking about what its effect on democracy will be with that particular
ad model I would say all the problems look like people all the problems come from harm happening
somewhere as a result of human choice but the choice was motivated by someone trying to benefit
something so they're all based on tradeoffs so it's either I'm trying to benefit myself now at
my own future expense addiction and compulsiveness I am uh so the parts conflict can even be within
oneself right um I'm trying to benefit my people my religion my nation my political party whatever
at the expense of the other one so great you get your political party elected you polarize the
population worse next time they'll swing back harder and you're actually not progressing anything
other than increasing polarization um or I am seeking to benefit things and the harm I'm
causing elsewhere I just didn't know I didn't know that leachate was going to cause that pollution
over there or whatever the other thing is so when bone was talking about the fragmented
consciousness it was both at the level of aware of the connectedness and care about the connectedness
and so really the key is seeing reality as parts right seeing reality as a bunch of separated parts
leads to being able to care about a part and seek to advantage it in a way that causes harm to
other things and then cascade effects of other agents doing this similar stuff and so you get
cumulative harm effects and you get escalating arms races so not being able to perceive stuff as a
bunch of separated parts but perceiving everything in relationship to everything else perceiving
everything as a part of an interconnected whole where your ability to benefit that thing had to
mean both caring about everything that it's connected to and being able to think through
everything that's connected to come up with a strategy that is omnibeneficial or as close to
that as possible and that where you made a mistake in it you're also ongoingly aware and working to
correct it I would say from the psychological perspective that's probably as deep a thing as
we can say and even stuff like but aren't people wouldn't wouldn't we say impulsiveness and selfishness
and addiction are even deeper than that because obviously all of the environmental harm is happening
because people are buying too much shit to get a keep up with the Joneses or get a hit of something
well it's still the same thing right like it's it is still the thing of that their future self is
being harmed for their momentary self because their momentary self feels fucked up enough that it
thinks that it means to get ahead of it so the parts conflict the the theory of tradeoff starts
within the self between the parts of itself the Jungian parts reconciliation then would be the
basis for being able to also have a wholeness of self in relationship with the wholeness of world
um
yeah let me let me um a couple of things uh given that and I've listened to you talk about these
issues a lot and sometimes I'm just left with just oh we are so fucked you know but given that
the solution of survivability as our current species on this our home seems to be ignorance
and just uh being bad actors uh do you feel that enough of us that there's any kind of hope or
sense that enough of us can evolve to a level where we can recognize this fractured and recognize
what we're doing enough to keep us together as a human family connected to the whole so that we
can survive this this choke point in our evolutionary history
I don't think there is much of a human family to keep together that is anything other than
an abstract idea at this point that some people hold and many people don't even hold
that's an ideal I think
the question of is it possible
to make it through the issues that the world is facing today the whole plurality of issues
that are unprecedented historically because we hadn't had centuries of industrial tech bringing
us up to planetary boundaries and we hadn't had exponential tech or even small number of actors
could fuck everything up so quickly and we didn't have a world that had so much fragility
given that we could have massive catastrophic harm from so many different vectors from synthetic
bio created pandemics and from AI autonomous drone weapons and from climate change and from
chemical planetary boundaries and from scaling war is there to make it through we have to avoid
all of those to fail we only have to have any of them happen and our crack record doesn't look good
right if you look back at the history of empires at all the history of war and environmental
destruction is a pretty big part of that story we don't seem to be really noble stewards of power
so as we're getting exponentially more power and we've usually used our power to
do power games with each other meaning destroy each other and in ways that harm the environment
is there any way that we can steward exponential power in a finite space I would say it takes a
step function like it will take something significant that is more than just the continuation of
whatever good aspects the enlightenment created or something like that
in the huge shift after world war two it was a big shift we made a whole new world system
but the answer was still
extract more from nature even faster make more money and make more tech like it the
Bretton Woods world system was a world system but in more increase for everybody was still a
somewhat easier thing to do than when you're hitting planetary boundaries and you have to say
no we actually have to reduce consumption across everybody where a lot of people are like no I
would rather not reduce my consumption go to war and have less people and I think I can win like
this it's hard the situation we're in right now is unprecedented at a global level in such deep ways
right so do I think it is possible to make it through I think the question is it possible to
make it through without great harm doesn't even make sense because we're in species extinction
and war today like great harm is happening today people are being killed in Ukraine people are
being killed in Armenia and Azerbaijan people are being killed all over because of these issues
and species are going extinct today so we're already in the great harm phase I almost know
adolescents don't have body dysmorphia in the Instagram etc world like that's
so we're already in that right now do I think we can make it through without catastrophes
where hundreds of millions of people die is one question do I think we can make it through where
there are any humans left I think we make it through where there are humans and something
that isn't just a totally scorched earth these are all different questions the answer
can we make it through without the catastrophes intensifying no no no chance so so
so given all this the the question comes up how then should we live given the truth of
well this next part is critical can we make it through without the catastrophes intensifying
no they're going to intensify because no matter what we do today there is no inactable path
to preventing the extreme weather events that climate change alone is going to mediate there's
a lot of things like that and then the human migration that's going to come from that we can
if we do the very best things we can make it less bad but there is also no we there is no we that
is a unified acting group right um the what china's interests are and what the us's interests are
what the individual with the left and right within the us's interests are what the individual us people
versus the elites in it they're not the same and so the whole like one of the biggest mistakes I made
growing up was I always thought in this royal we that like humanity thoughtfully was all reading
bucky's operating manual for spaceship earth and we're all you know thinking about un charters and
looking at the earth and the astronauts perspective and carrying carl sagan's pale blue dot and of
course we want to do the right and smart and good thing for everybody uh the thing that some people
think is really good the other people think is really horrible and when you realize that
the enactment gets really hard right is is the legality of abortion protecting women's freedoms
and rights or is it murdering infants um you'll see the most severe uh ideological differences
on what is good they create a basis for massive conflict and you see that across so many things
right so um that's why I said there isn't a human family to hang together like that's
that's an aspirational thing um do I think that if there is already a trajectory of some people who
care about not just their own political party or their own nation or their own race or even
their own species but care pretty considerably and are working in service of that that there are
increasing number of people who have both more care more capacity and more interconnectivity
and they cannot then also work with other people who maybe don't care about all of that but in
increasingly good coordination for the things they do care about yes that's happening right
there's a good thing in emergence that is happening do I think that that could be sufficient
to make it through without total extinction or scorched earth yes totally do I think it
can make it through without the catastrophes intensifying no they will intensify before even
on the best course do I think that it's a given that we make it through no which means we are no
matter what in a phase of increasing intensity ahead and with I think both the what it takes to
avoid all the catastrophes is deep enough change to the world systems that it's like that Bohmian
thing that we are neither harming each other on purpose or accident which means a kind of
more universal on the consideration or things like a human family is actually a real thing
so I think in order to not have a get much worse changes have to happen at a deep enough
level that it gets much better so I do think there's something like a pretty hard fork
and I think it can go either way and I think it is not determined and I think it is increasingly
potent and hard over the next while on in figuring that out so with that then the question how do
we live as the frame is I can't imagine a context in which one's choices could matter more
than that
indeed it gives a whole another level and depth and dimension to
the choices we make and the priorities we serve and the
how we live our lives and offer our lives and so what what are some of the parameters for an
effective contributing life that you see
a few more resources that I'll offer here another short little blog I wrote on how to live a meaningful life
which was intentionally not answering the question what is the meaning of life which we discussed
earlier but it said had a meaningful life and it's just
it's a way of talking about it there's lots of ways of talking about it that's not particularly
better than lots of other ways but I there's something that is kind of comprehensive and
kind of elegant about it so I'll offer it and it was looking at the mode of being
the mode of doing and the mode of becoming all being relevant and defining all of them in terms
of beauty and that thing we said earlier that truth and goodness matter because beauty is
so there it says the mode of being at its essence is about really deeply taking in the beauty of
reality and appreciating it giving gratitude for it honoring and loving it you know all those things
it's the essence of what the mode of being is really about
and that the mode of doing is about being in service to the beauty of reality protecting
it adding to it and the mode of becoming is deepening the capacity for being in doing
that I can appreciate ever more fully and that I can add to it ever more fully
and that a meaningful life is a recursive relationship between those three
and if what I'm doing isn't arising out of everything's fucked up so I have to fix everything
but it's arising out of perceiving working on this hunger issue because we're perceiving the
utter meaningfulness and beauty of these kids or these people in their life and the importance of
it and the and so then the doing the desire to serve and protect arises not from the perception
of all the badness but actually arises from the perception of the beauty from which the good
which also means the bad is framed at all right so the thing that really is terrible and pisses us
off is because something that is beautiful and sacred is being harmed which then brings us back
to there's something that we actually love and have devotion to so we trace it back to that and say
how do I be in service there so the doing must arise from the being
and the becoming is I don't just want to perceive the beauty I currently see I want to perceive
ever deeper dimensions of things that I had missed you know I want to ask what aspects of the
of reality are important and beautiful that I'm missing that other people are noticing that I'm
not honoring as fully as I could and then similarly with our doing where do I have frameworks for what
I'm where is what I'm doing coming from ego and trauma and wounding where have I been running a
strategy so long if I stopped and thought about it from scratch and I come up with something better
you know like I want to be deepening the doing as well so I think if one relates to appreciating
the beauty of life adding to it deepening the capacity for both that's a nice framework to start
and then there was another resource but on there called Dharma inquiry which is more personal
because that's obviously true for everybody the Dharma inquiry it's more into specific
things one is bothered by and is inspired by and has aptitude at and is called to to have a sense of
what is your unique relationship to that is your own Dharma with it I realized that
there's something both very beautiful about the kind of bodhisattva direction and something
that is incomplete about a certain direction of it I was I was incredibly influenced by
the value of the bodhisattva and the may I become whatever is needed and
when you look around and try to perceive what is needed and try to develop within yourself
what can offer something there I remember the the first time I actually read it was in Alex Gray's
art book the sacred mirrors and he had the heavy look page for the painting and then he had this
poem next to it it's so beautiful and it said something like where there is
thirst may rain fall upon the people and may I myself become that rain or there is hunger may
I be transformed into the food but near them where there is illness may I become the medicine
you know wherever there is need of any kind may I become what is needed I think that helps one to
recognize that what they love is deeper to who they are than who they think they are
beautiful because I think I like these things and I don't like these things I'm good at these
things not these things but oh I can't help with that because I'm not a legal scholar or I'm not
a construction worker or I'm not a whatever it is and yeah it's like but if that's the thing
that is most needed and would help what you care about most can you can you become something that
you are not and I've had many times where there was something that I was not good at that I actually
really identified as a thing I would never want to be good at and realized that it actually
mattered what I cared about enough that if I held that limited identity I was not in maximum
service to what I claimed to care about and I had to get like well I I care about what I care about
so long as it fits with my identity easily or I've got to transcend the identity so that's
what I like about the vow of the bodhisattva but where it's missing something is
I really am not equally good at all the things that are needed nor can I do all of the things
even if I try there's a lot of people have to do all the things so if medicine work is needed and if
economics change is needed and if care of the individual people and animals is needed as well
as macro systemic thinking about systems to do that not only what is most needed but what is most
needed that my being is well developed to be able to be in service to is important and so the
Dharma questions are trying to help hone that for people. Beautiful and and you're pointing to
the kinds of questions we need to ask ourselves in order to in order to orient ourselves
to be most effective instruments of service or for the and in the bodhisattva aspiration for
the welfare and awakening of all and I really think that probably that bodhisattva aspiration
may be one of the highest ideals in mind as human mind has ever come up with and such a beautiful
thing and you're pointing now to the questions we ask which the first question that emerges is
well what what can I do but then you're pointing to the idea that there's a there are questions
deeper than that what's the most effective thing I can do and along with that the question or the
colon actually what am I called to do and deeper still in your implication is is a question how
can I live my life so as to be an optimal instrument of service and each of those is I think better
thought of as a as a colon or a wisdom question and I would draw the distinction saying a conceptual
question is you know is it raining outside take a look no end of question but wisdom questions are
more like columns every time you ask them they have the potential for taking you deeper into the
question deeper into life deeper into yourself and so you're pointing us towards the real the
wisdom questions of our time. I would also say that almost every value or principle
lives in a dialectical relationship with another value or principle that is complementary but
they might seem almost opposite and that without holding them together the full version of just
that one thing the reducto ad absurdum of it actually becomes evil and so this is the everything
can be a medicine or everything can be a poison topic so what is
what is my unique self calling what is that which I can offer the world based on the unique
set of experiences and capacities I have that no one else could offer that if I spend my life doing
things other than that that other people could do the most novel offering that I have doesn't occur
that's a deep and important and beautiful question but taken to its extreme it'll make
you a total shithead because fucking do the dishes when you need to do the dishes no it's not your
unique self the only thing that you can do like anybody can do the dishes or take out the trash
but like damn though a lot of life is just doing the dishes out of the trash and maybe the unique
self that you have is is unexpressible infinitesimal qualities with which you show up to those things
you know so the what is uniquely mine to do that no one else can do and what fucking needs done
that nobody wants to do I'll just show up to you got to hold those together right because also on
the other side if you always just say what is nobody what is the shittiest job that nobody
wants to do let me show up to that which is an incredibly ennobling question incredibly beautiful
question you can also end up uh failing at some unique self darmism capacities you could have
because of only orienting that way and so uh every every principle and every virtue needs held in a
dialectical relationship and not over normed as absolute yeah and this is the ancient concept
of the interdependence of virtues that that they require require each other and complement one
one another and I think you're also pointing to the contextual nature of our inquiries that we
have to keep the context as well so again beautiful beautiful reflections and deepening and expanding
uh that I see you're pointing us to yeah and I've I've just felt that we've been spending
I don't know extra amount of time in the heart of philosophy and I feel a connection with
fidgety triathlons and all of that stuff has started long ago in another land and it's still
it's still churning and a universe that can produce um a you and a me I can't be all bad
and I feel deeply moved and deeply uh renewed in my commitment to do my little things you know
whatever that calling might be and I think I pretty much found that but also to shampoo my dog
and take out the trash and you know wipe the counters and that sort of thing you know and
you say it can't be all bad it's funny because so I focus on the meta crisis which is like all the
most fucked up stuff that could be all together um it kind of seems like that but it's not really
what I focus on I mean it's in appreciation and love of this world and life there's the desire to
protect it and uh so paying attention to things that need protecting but where does the motivation
come from the motivation doesn't come things being fucked up the motivation comes from the
wonder of it right from the beauty of it like I've had I know you you both talk about bringing
the philosophic concepts into daily practice on this um show a lot and you know I've had a lot of
practices throughout my life in terms of types of meditation types of inquiry and whatever
but like I wake up in the morning and the first thing I do pretty much every morning is I just
look out the window at the trees and I just watch the trees move in the wind for a little bit
and I don't I don't have to try to care about them or try to find them beautiful they're just
fucking beautiful and there's a happiness that comes just watching that and then there's a
gratitude to be alive and consciousness you know arising again and there's a happiness to be on this
planet and then there is a because of the happiness it comes from just the perception of the beauty
of it I don't need that much for myself right there's not an unhappiness it needs me to do a
bunch of stuff and then there's this gratitude that I like I was sleeping this con this Daniel
consciousness wasn't here and then it boots again and now it's here and I think about when Daniel's
dead the consciousness that will be perceiving the world and falling in love for the first time and
climbing trees and reading hafez and rumi for the first time it's all the things and I can't
not feel connected to those consciousnesses a hundred and a thousand years from it like I can't
not feel what it feels like to perceive through those eyes and I'm actually not trying to get it
to go anywhere I just want that kids get to keep experiencing falling in love with trees for the
first time and mothers get to keep falling in love with their kids and people get to fall in love and do
poetry for the first time and get heartbroken and all the things the pot like it is intrinsically
already meaningful without going anywhere and it's already beautiful and you know one of the other
things I know you'll have talked about is peak experiences and one of the things I always felt is
once you have had one of them
like for me I remember I remember discreetly I've talked about before there was this one time I
was watching a sunset and writing poetry to nature and watching a sunset as a teenager
and I remember the sunset was just so incredibly beautiful and I remember thinking
if I had the choice if there is a spirit before this life if I had the choice to come here and
incarnate and go through whatever painful things that I've went through my whole life just to get
to have this one experience of color and vision and the wind and the insects in this moment would
totally do it like I would take every pain in my whole life to have had this experience as opposed to
no experience and then I'm like I've had that I've had so many of these experiences and one of
them is worth incarnating for I've had so many of them and so it's like the fact that I will probably
have more of them is gravy and it's like a ridiculous beauty and abundance but that every
that future life gets to keep having those and that other people get to have more of those is kind
of more what I'm motivated by and they make us better persons when we experience those things
that it shifts you know something happens maybe just a little bit but something happens in a
positive thing and shifts in our soul and our interiors and maybe we behave a little a little
better or a lot better I'm not sure I think the what's in it for me thing chills out
you know and it's not that it doesn't reboot because we're complex people with lots of parts
and there will be a pain body that reboots and so it's not like enlightenment is a static thing
and you have a satori and then you never have a pain body boot again it does but there's something
about even just thinking about it and just being like I there could have been no I no experience at
all and there's experience and there've been such amazing ones and
and and I feel this pretty much with every difficulty or trauma too is like when you've
done the healing work with it you don't still feel messed up by the trauma or the pain but you do feel
ongoingly benefited by the lessons and it's kind of like a lot of people don't have the
resources or know how to do the healing so they never get the lessons and they're just always
affected by the pain and that's a bummer but if one kind of has the resources knows how to work
on it then the pain is temporary and the gifts are lasting and it's like this just beneficial
asymmetry like this beautiful asymmetry where it's like yeah I just am a yes to the whole thing
let's say yes to the whole thing and there's there's a beautiful couple of lines that came out of
San Quentin prison uh there's a project uh grip guiding rage into pain which uh the people work
very intensely with with people many of them life as many of them have been murderers and
work on life transformation their ideals the body sight for aspiration the commitment is
even if I stay in my in the prison for the rest of my life I'm going to do what I can to help people
and one and one of them after after and there's a very intensive exploration of their pain and
the trauma they've both caused and received and these are very traumatized people and there's a
video of one of these sessions in which one of the one of the prisoners some suddenly lights out
lights up and says oh I get it hurt people hurt people and healed people heal people
it's like oh oh it's so beautiful yeah they're both self-propagating
yeah I would love to explore that with you Daniel uh we've gone long and far and deep or maybe that's
the wrong word uh to explore the the darkness and the addiction and the way out of that and just
what you said um Roger uh hurt people hurt people and heal people heal people and that's uh
maybe that's a good place to wrap it uh for this evening I really enjoyed the conversation with
both of you I think that the this podcast where you're exploring these topics and sharing it with
people is uh a really beautiful service and I'm honored to be here with you oh it's such a delight
Daniel and it's such a such a gift to be able to investigate at this depth and co-explore so
thank you so much for this gift to to everyone who listens to the podcast and thank you so much
for your life's work it's truly a gift crisis we get to share this with thousands and thousands
of god knows how many people that's tremendous that's just tremendous if there is a second time
we come back to and explore that hurt people hurt people that there is some
autopoetic trauma force almost and that there is also some kind of autopoetic healing or integrative
force but if you wanted to think of the light and dark sides of the force that's actually kind of a
good way of thinking of it is the autopropagation of those things um and we wanted to explore that
sometime maybe also if the listeners have thoughts or questions or topics coming from this that can
inform it we can get to those next time too right well we hereby extend an invitation to
listeners to let us know the questions you have for Daniel and uh I think you're implicitly
suggesting you're open to coming back and we of course would love that and I know how listeners
would too so that's beautiful and again in regards to your father and mom if they're still
on this plane and if not in regards to them anyway okay tell tell them they they deeply
touch one old guy in Louisiana made a difference for him I'll send this podcast to them when it
publishes Daniel thank you so much take care