So that was the philosophical part of my talk, and I will be slowly moving towards really
more practical, I mean, practically in the sense of mathematical stuff, not so much philosophy.
But from all this talk about how our brains work, the important part is that we want to
be able to, the major tools in our arsenal are abstraction, composition, and I'm going
to add one more thing to this identity. So as I said, abstraction means we want to get
rid of the details, we want to forget about the assembly language or machine language
of what we are doing, and that's not only in programming, it's also in mathematics or
in physics, we want to get rid of unnecessary details. So once we get rid of unnecessary
details, then suddenly what happens is that things that were different, but they were
different because of unnecessary details, they suddenly become identical. Like if you
have, let's say, two billion balls of the same color, they are not really identical
if you look under the microscope, they have different maybe scratches, maybe they have
different configuration of atoms, but you can replace one with another when you are
playing billiards. So once you abstract, things that used to be different now become identical.
This is why we have this notion of identity, and this notion of identity because of abstraction
is always non-trivial. So there are things that are strictly identical, so you can replace
one with another and you won't notice any difference, but then there are things that
are identical for all intents and purposes. And in mathematics, this is a very, very important
thing, that there is this distinction between, it's really the same, or it's not really
the same, but we will look at it as if it were the same. And there is even a whole foundation
theory that's being now developed that's based on like distinguishing between what's
not identical, it's called homotopy type theory. It's a very hot topic right now in mathematics
that just tries to solve this one problem of what are things that are equal and what
are things that are almost equal, or as they say, isomorphic. Isomorphism and equality the
same, or not, should be treated the same way, or not, and so on. So composition and identity,
these two things, they just define category theory. This is all there is in category theory,
it just encompasses composition and identity. So you are now ready for the first definition,
definition of category. And I wish I could define category, what a category is, very
precisely, but I can't. So I will be using terms like a bunch. A category is a bunch of objects.
You would want me to say it's a set of objects, because a set has a precise mathematical meaning,
but it's not. So you have categories that have sets of objects and it's fine, but not
all categories have sets of objects. It turns out that there are things that are bigger than
sets. And you might think, what can be bigger than a set? What's a set? A set is something
that has a bunch of elements. A set is defined by membership. Is this element a member of
the set or not? But then you can build sets with sets. You can say, I have a set of sets
that are two element sets. And I have a set of all sets that are of this particular shape.
So elements of a set can also be sets. From a set theory point of view, everything is
a set. They have the set hammer and everything is a set nail for that. So sets are built
from sets and so on. And then you can say, how do I define a set? I will specify what
kind of elements it has. So I can say, I have a set of sets. There are some sets that are
members of themselves and there are sets that are not. A set of dogs is not a dog. So that's
one. But a set of... Well, it was a good example of a set that is a member of itself.
A set that contains only itself. A set that contains only itself. Okay.
So now if you can define a set that... So you can also define a set that's a set of
sets that are not members of itself. And then you can ask, does this set... Is this set
a member of itself or not? If it is a member of itself, then it should not belong to the
set. And if it's not, it should belong. It's like with the barber's paradox. If he shapes
himself, then he should not shape himself. If he doesn't shape himself. So you get into
these paradoxes in set theory. So if I say, okay, a category is a set of objects, then
I immediately get into this problem. And in particular, you cannot define a set of all
sets for some other reason, right? Because it's too big. It's like a power set of... It
would have to contain all its subsets as well. So it's a set that contains all sets, including
its subsets and so on. So these are the mind-blowing things that set theories that are thinking
about and they cannot sleep at night. So a category says... A category theory says, let's
not worry about it, right? Well, they do worry about it, but they have ways of doing this.
So I will say it's a bunch of objects, okay? So a category consists of objects. And then
without specifying further whether they form a set or a bunch or a class, sometimes it's
called a class, which is like less precise than the set. And these objects, I would just
draw as dots, you know? And arrows. And these arrows are called also morphisms.
I'll be sometimes saying morphisms, sometimes I'll be saying arrows. So a morphism or an
arrow is something that goes between two objects. So you have an object A and you have an object
B and you have an arrow between them and you call it F, okay? And now you might want
to ask, you know, but what's an object? Right? And I can't tell you, okay? An object is primitive
in this theory. It has no properties. It has no structure, internal structure. It's nothing.
It's like the atom. It's a point. It has no properties, okay? What's a morphism? Well,
a morphism is also a primitive. It has no properties, well, except that every arrow has
a beginning and an end, okay? So that's the important thing. So in fact, the reason for
having objects is so that you can mark the ends of arrows, okay? They don't serve any
other purpose as just being names for the ends of arrows or identifying the ends of
arrows, okay? And notice that this is like, this is really funny that we are using arrows
here. It's like going back to this, what I talked about, the primitive human beings hunting
mammoths with bows and arrows, right? This is really a very interesting thing that we
perceive the universe through these notions that were developed by hunter-gatherers, right?
They had, they described the world in terms of, you know, the sense of, you know, the
spatial relationships, right? For instance. So they, they, like when I'm talking about
category theory and when mathematicians talk about it, they will put things in space, maybe
with their hands, manipulate. So we know how to manipulate things, right? We know how to
position things in space. We talk about spatial relationships. Something is above, something
is below, higher level of abstraction, lower level of abstraction. These are all spatial
relationships, right? Now hunter-gatherers also understand movement. It comes from here,
goes here. This is movement. This is from arrow, from A to B, right? It has this little
thing here with barbs, right? So when you, when you hit the animal, it can't just pull
it because it's, okay? So, and of course we have social language. We, we, hunter-gatherers
are, we're social animals. So, so they talk about, you know, relationships between things
in terms of this guy, points at this guy and, and, and by movement, kind of, you know,
going from this place to that place, through this place and so on. So we'll be using this
language all the time and I want you to, like, realize what kind of language we are using
and how it actually constrains us, okay? But anyway, so we have objects and objects we
draw in some kind of spatial relationship usually because we are using the spatial part
of our brain. We have morphisms which are arrows, so they suggest some kind of movement
and relationship between people. So what kind of things can happen? I mean, we can have,
let's say, you know, multiple arrows going between objects. So if you have object A
and B, you can have zero or more arrows going between them. So every time you define a category
you specify, you know, what is the, what are the objects of this category and for each
pair of objects, right, you specify the arrows that go between these objects. Some objects
are not connected with arrows, other objects are connected with one arrow, other objects
are connected with infinitely many arrows, could be uncountable number of arrows going
between two objects, okay? So, like, if you have an idea that the category is sort of
like a graph, that's a good idea, right, except that you have to be open-minded about what
the graph is. It might have infinitely many nodes and it can have infinitely many arrows
between, between two nodes or it could have zero or, you know. But you have to expand
your mind around this. And of course you can have arrows going from B to A as well, right?
And you can have arrows going from B back to B or from A back to A. You can have multiple
arrows going from A to A, right? And so on. So all these are possibilities. Sometimes people
get stuck and I get questions, you know, like, how is it possible that you can have more
than one arrow? Aren't they all the same? No, they are different, you know. It's like,
you can have infinitely many or uncountable number of arrows going from A back to A, you
know, and it's okay. You just give them different names, you know, okay, this is F, this is G,
this is H, right? So this is what a category is, okay? Now that's not all. That's not all
because that doesn't, that just tells us about what are the elements of category. We haven't
talked about these two things. Composition. So composition is a property, very simple
property that if you have an arrow from A to B and you have another arrow from B to
C, so you have object A, object B and object C and you have these two arrows, then there
always must exist an arrow that's a composition of these. So if I call this one F and call
this one G, I'm using these names F and G that suggest functions, right? Because at
some point this will be one of our models for a category. So this is called G after F,
after is this little circle. So this arrow is called G after F. And here we have this
idea that going from A to B using F and going from B to C using G is identical to going
from A to C using this path called G after F, okay? So this arrow is identical to the
composition of these arrows, okay? It's very important to understand that there might be
multiple arrows going from A to C, right? But this one is a composition of these two
and it must exist, okay? So for every composable pair of arrows, composable means the end of
one is the same as the beginning of the other. And here it's important that we have these
objects to identify the ends and the beginnings, right? So the end of this is B, the beginning
of this is B. So they are composable, right? And if they are composable then there must
be a composition, there must be an arrow going from here to here. So this is called composition
check. Now when we are defining a category, the category is defined by giving us objects,
saying what the objects are and arrows. And then defining composition, which is sort of
like a multiplication table for arrows. So for every two arrows you have to define what
is their composition. It's a humongous multi-dimensional multiplication table, you know, or infinitely
dimensional multiplication table, right? For every three objects you have to define all
possible combinations in which you can compose arrows going between these objects and so
on, right? So it's a humongous multiplication table. And the whole information about the
category is in this multiplication table, okay? So remember, this is the multiplication
table for a category, it's a composition table, how you compose morphisms. And different
composition tables will give you different categories. Because since objects don't have
structures, since arrows don't have structure, they don't contain any information. But the
composition contains the information. And we just like want to encode everything, everything
absolutely in this composition, okay? Now, identity for every object, it's called A,
there is an identity arrow. We will call it ID. Sometimes ID with a subscript A. This
is identity for the object A. So there is this arrow that we call identity. There's
one per object. For every object in a category, there is an identity for this object. Now,
why am I calling it this identity? Because of composition. So, if I have an arrow going
from, well, let's call it A, let's call it B, IDB, okay? If I compose this arrow F with
IDB, I get back arrow F. In this sense, this is an identity, right? If you think of this
as multiplication table, you know, F times ID is again F, right? So this is like a one
in terms of composition. So I can write it using this notation that IDB after F, right?
So first I go F and I go IDB. It's the same as this. Equal, okay? This is one morphism,
this is another morphism. They are equal. It's the same morphism, okay? And of course
there is this symmetric thing when I have IDA and I have some, let's call it G from
A to B, right? So if I start with an ID, IDA, and follow it with G, I will get G, okay?
So these two things, they are not the same, right? I mean, this is like left identity,
this is the right identity. Sometimes they are this, well, maybe I shouldn't say it, sometimes
they are the same, but it's just like you have to have left identity and you have to
have right identity, okay? So this is one of the axioms of a category or laws of the category
that in every category, so if you think of a category as a graph, this graph has to
have some special properties. For instance, it has to have an arrow going back to the
object. For every object, it has to be this little loop, okay? Must. So that's one law
or actually two laws, left identity, right? And then identity. And there is the third
law and that's associativity. So if you have three objects, well, here you have three objects,
let's say three arrows, okay? So we have object A, an arrow F to object B, then an arrow
G to object C, right? You can combine these to have G after F, but if you have another
one going to D, right, then you have to have G after F, right? And then you have to have
you can combine these and have, so F, G, H, right? You have three arrows. Three arrows
can be composed in two different ways. So this one composition, I compose GF with G
first, G after F, and then I compose this with H. So I have H after G after F, okay?
Now I can also compose G with H first, right? So I'll have H after G, H after G, okay? Now
I can compose this arrow with this arrow, right? And I will get H after G after F, okay?
H after G after F, okay? The difference between these two is where I put the parentheses. Now
if I had to remember where to put parentheses, every time I draw a diagram, it will become
extremely complex and probably my brain would just give up, okay? Therefore, the
axiom of the category is that this and this is the same, okay? So H after G after F must
always be equal H after G after F. So this is called associativity, right? Normal thing,
associativity. You can associate it this way or this way and you get the same result.
And that's extremely important in order to make this manageable for us humans, okay?
Now you might think, okay, what if we didn't do this? Is it possible still to have a theory
in which this is not true? Well, it is possible and of course there are mathematicians who
are working with stuff that maybe not completely falls, the associativity is not completely
false, but they make associativity weak, meaning that these two ways of combining things are
not really identical, but they are isomorphic, okay? Yes?
What about real-world stuff like finite precision arithmetic? Is that the kind of thing you're
leading to, like you're multiplying flows and the order in which you multiply them,
you may end up with a slightly different result? Well, then they would not form a category
in the sense, okay, yeah. The category has to have associativity, yes?
So what do you mean by the two ways of the composition of isomorphic?
It means that there is a transformation that transforms this into this that is not an identity.
So morphisms can also, okay, this is a separate thing. You can have identity between morphisms
that is not identity, it's weak identity, right? Here I'm assuming, well, okay, so let me
for full disclosure right now, okay? I said objects don't form a set in general. If they
form a set, then this category is called small, okay, if they can form a set. If they don't
form a set, it's a large category, okay? Morphisms, on the other hand, between any two objects,
they form a set. So that's okay, right? Now is there a category here in which they don't
form a set? Of course there is, right? These are the higher-order categories in which
arrows don't form sets, they form objects in a category. But we are not going to talk about
them. So that's it, that's all, that's the category. That's the definition of category,
yes? In terms of definition, when you say the two eras are isomorphic, if they have
the same beginning and ending? What is isomorphic? Two eras, would they be isomorphic if they
have the same beginning and ending? No, no, they are different. No. Yes? Is this so much
different from a group in the other way? It's, okay, so the question is, is that different
from a group? And it has some similarities to a group, actually it has similarities to
something that's called a monoid, right? Because a group is a monoid that also has an inverse,
right? So there are two ways in which you can impose further conditions on this and you
can say, what if every arrow has an inverse, right? You can define an inverse to say, if
the arrow f and g, if they combine, compose to an identity, then one is an inverse of
an other. That's the definition of an inverse, right? So if you do this, then you end up
with something that's called a groupoid. A groupoid is the category in which every arrow
has an inverse, okay? It's still not a group. It's more than a group because a group is
really a category in which there is only one object and arrows between them. We'll be talking
about a monoid as a category and in particular a group. But this is more because now you
have transformations going between objects, so you cannot, in a group you can compose
anything with anything, right? Here you can't. They have to be composable. The end of one
has to be the beginning of another, right? You cannot compose anything with anything,
right? That's the biggest distinction. Okay, now, notice that a group is a group
of objects. So let me give you an example, okay? And this is the example that we'll be
studying a lot because this is an example from programming, right? We have a basic useful
category that we use in programming. And this is the category in which objects are
types and arrows are functions, right? Like if any single argument function takes an argument
of a type A and returns a result of type B, right? So in the sense a function is an arrow,
or a morphism between two types. So that's the category in which this is actually in
Haskell, it's almost exactly, well, maybe in ML, this is almost exactly the category
which you are working, right? Types are your objects, functions are your morphisms, right?
In Haskell, it's a little bit more complicated because of laziness of Haskell, okay? Haskell
is a lazy language. So the trick is that in Haskell, every type also contains this
undefined value, the bottom value, which means like if you try to evaluate it, you will get
into an infinite loop, it will take you forever. Because categories don't really take into
account time. It's like time really is really hard to describe in mathematics, right? Whereas
in computation, we worry about time, right? I mean if something takes too long to calculate,
that's useless for us, right? And in particular, if it takes infinite time to calculate, which
means it never terminates, okay? It's a calculation. So if you have a function that goes forever,
what's the return type for this function? It's a function that's supposed to return an
integer, but it never does because it goes into an infinite loop. So in this case, in
Haskell, we say it returns an int type, but int type contains this special value called
bottom, which means it never terminates, okay? And that's the digression I make once, and
maybe from time to time, I will say, well, of course, except for bottoms, and we are
ignoring bottoms, or we are ignoring never ending calculations and so on, right? So there's
this caveat. There's lots of caveats here in the beginning, and I just want to get rid of
them, and later we can think in simpler terms, okay? But of course you might ask, but what
are types, right? Okay, types in the programming language, what are they?
Sets of values, okay. So there is a model, a kind of simplistic model, maybe this works
in ML, it won't work in Haskell because of the bottoms, right? But the simplest model
for types is that they are just sets, sets of values, right? And so we can model programming
as in a category of sets, we can say, okay, so instead of types, we will be saying sets
of values, right? And functions are just functions between sets, okay? You can define
functions on sets, function from one set to another set, right? And that's a good model too.
So sometimes I'll be talking about sets and functions, sometimes I'll be talking about types
and functions, and of course when I say functions, I'm talking about mathematical
functions, right? So mathematical function is defined between sets. So a function is just,
you know, you take a value from one set and it gives you a value from another set, right?
So I can even draw a picture of what might mean by a function in a set. So I hope you
can memorize the definition of a category, right? I mean, it's so simple, so very elementary.
So I can erase this now. So it's like you have one set, you have another set, here you have
elements of this set, elements of this set, and the function sort of, you know, takes
elements of this set into elements of this set, and again I'm using the arrows, but these are
different arrows, these are not morphisms, right? So one function corresponds to one morphism,
right? But we can like, so this is another thing that you have to be very careful with,
this schizophrenic view of a category, right? That every category, well not every category,
okay? But a lot of categories come from some model. For instance, you take sets, set field,
right? So and you say, I'm going to represent these sets as objects in my category. This
category, by the way, is called set. This is a category of sets and functions, right?
We'll be using it quite often. So I'll be talking about the category of sets and the origin of
this category is that I started with sets, right? And I know what sets are. They have structure,
right? Every set has elements and there are functions and functions in sets, they just map
elements to elements, okay? So I know all the stuff. I'm looking under a microscope and I said I know
it has elements. I know that the functions are actually a bunch of mapping. It's a mapping from
one set to another, right? Now when I build a category on top of this, I have to forget about
the structure, okay? I get amnesia and I say this is set A. What's inside of the set? I have no idea.
It's an atom. It has no structure because now I'm putting my category glasses, right? No
structure. What are the arrows between these sets? Well, I look at what kind of sets these are, right?
I know elements of the sets. I know what kind of functions are possible, right? So I know how many
arrows, how many functions are from this set to this set and I build my category based on this.
I say, okay, this set corresponds to an object A, this set corresponds to an object B and there are
ten arrows between these objects. Fine. What are these arrows? I don't know. I forgot. I just know there
are ten of them, okay? And I call them ABCD or FGH, okay? And the next thing is, okay, so if I have
arrows from this set to this, I mean functions from this set, another function from this set to this set.
Oh, I can compose them, right? What does it mean to compose functions? Well, you apply a function to
an argument, right? You get a result. You take this result, you apply the second function to this result
and you get another result, right? So if you combine this, you start it here, you end it up here.
You get a function that goes, right? Okay? So starting some x here, it produces a y here and y goes into z here
and there is a function that just takes x directly into z and that's the composition of these two functions.
Okay? So I know how to compose functions on sets using this, right? So I use this information to create my big
infinite dimensional multiplication table, composition table for my category set and then I forget.
And of course there is an identity function, right? That just takes an x into x, takes another x into x.
This is an identity function, right? So every set has an identity function that just doesn't move the set.
It just maps the set into itself by mapping every element to itself. It's like a trivial function, right?
So, like, id of x equals x. That's what it has.
Yes?
It doesn't have to map every element itself though, right? It just needs to map the set to itself.
No, because you can map the set to itself in many different ways, right? You can interchange element if you want.
That's also a map, you know, the set into itself, right?
From a category point of view it's still...
Okay, so what we are doing here is we are studying the set and we find out that there are many functions going from the set to itself, right?
One of them is the identity function. This would become our identity morphism, right?
And, by the way, identity function when it's composed with any other function will give them back this function, right?
So it's a good identity function, I know, from set table, right?
So I know that I will get that my multiplication table that I'm building when I pick this function as my identity morphism,
it will be an identity in my big multiplication table, right?
So I'm abstracting, I'm just slashing information left and right.
I'm forgetting about what's inside the objects, what these functions do, and I end up with this category set.
And in this category set I have these objects that now I forgot where they came from.
I have these arrows, I forgot where they came from, but I have the multiplication table, the composition table for them, right?
And this composition table fulfills my axioms of category theory, right?
I mean, this composition is obviously associative, right?
The composition of functions is associative, so I get a good category.
I have identity, I have associativity, I have everything.
So I got this huge multiplication table, now I can forget about where it came from, and now I have a category set.
And in this category set, you know, I don't care about the structure of my objects or the structure of my functions or my morphisms.
I forget that my morphisms are really functions. I forgot all this.
And now I can start thinking about, you know, what can I say about these objects just by looking at morphisms?
And it turns out I can say a lot of things.
And we'll see later how you can identify, just by looking at morphisms, how you can identify, oh, this set is actually empty, right?
How do you know it's empty, right?
I mean, if you forgot the information, then it has no elements, right?
You only have morphisms.
Well, it turns out that an empty set has this property that can be expressed just in terms of morphisms, nothing else.
And I can identify an empty set. I can identify a single element set using just morphisms, nothing else.
It's not easy, but it's possible.
So the thing is that you can identify a lot of properties of sets just by looking at the multiplication table.
You don't really have to know what's inside these sets.
And that gives you a completely new way of looking at things, more abstract way of looking at things.
It's like if you think about what's inside a set, you're thinking assembly language of sets.
Thinking about elements, how they are mapped, you know, that's the assembly language.
Category theory gives you this higher level language in which you don't have to look inside the set.
You just look at how they are connected with arrows.
And this is like the ultimate in data hiding, right?
You have an object, it's a data type, it's a set, but you cannot look inside of it.
It shrunk to a point. All you have is its interface.
Its interface is how it connects to other objects.
All these arrows coming out of this object and into this object.
They define the interface.
So like if you take this idea of data hiding and abstraction, this is where it leads you, eventually.
This is the end of the road for abstraction, right?
This is the end of the road for data hiding.
This is it. You get like the most abstract language that you can think of.
And we can stop now. Next time. Two more. Thank you.