Hi, everyone. It's Tristan, and this is your Undivided Attention.
Up next, we have our unedited conversation with Daniel Schmacktenberger.
And because it's unedited, it's longer and not corrected for fact-checking purposes,
but you can find our shorter, edited version wherever you found this one.
Listen to both versions, and then come to our podcast club with Daniel and me,
and hopefully you, on July 9th. Details are in the show notes.
And with that, here we go.
Welcome to your Undivided Attention.
Today, I am so honored and happy to have my friend, Daniel Schmacktenberger,
as our guest, who works on the topics of existential risk
and what are the underlying drivers of all of the major problems,
or many of the major problems, that are really facing us today as a civilization,
be it climate change, breakdown of truth, social media, our information systems.
Those of you who've been following your Undivided Attention will hear this
as a very different kind of episode.
We almost think of it as a meta-episode about the underlying drivers
of many of the topics that we have covered on your Undivided Attention thus far.
So if you think about the topics that we've covered,
whether you've seen the social dilemma or you followed our interviews previously
on topics like attention span shortening or addiction or information overwhelm and distraction,
the fall of trust in society, more polarization, breakdown of truth,
our inability to solve problems like climate change,
well, this is really about an interconnected set of problems
and the kind of core generator functions that are leading to all of these things to happen at once.
And so I really encourage you to listen to this all the way through,
and I think that we're going to get into some very deep and important knowledge
that will hopefully be orienting for all of us.
One of my favorite quotes is by Charles Kettering,
who said that a problem not fully understood is unsolvable
and a problem that is fully understood is half-solved.
And what I hope we talk about with Daniel is what about the framework that we are using
to address or try to meet the various problems that we have has been inadequate
and what is the problem-solving framework that we're going to need
to deal with the existential crises that face us.
So Daniel, welcome to Your Undivided Detention.
Thank you, Tristan.
I've been looking forward to us dialoguing about these things publicly for a while.
Well, you and me both.
And for those who don't know, Daniel and I have been friends for a very long time,
and his work has been highly influential to me and many people in my circles.
So Daniel, maybe we should just start with what is the metacrisis
and why are these problems seemingly not getting solved,
whether it's the SDGs, climate change, or anything that we really care about right now?
I think a lot of people have the general sense that there is an increasing number
of possibly catastrophic issues and that as new categories of tech,
tech that allows major cyber attacks on infrastructure,
tech that allows weaponized drone attacks on infrastructure,
biotechnologies, artificial intelligence and moving towards AGI,
that there are new catastrophic risks with all of those categories of tech
and that those tech are creating larger jumps in power faster than any types of jumps of tech,
including the development of the nuclear bomb in the past by many orders of magnitude.
So there's a general sense that whether we're talking about future pandemic related issues
or whether we're talking about climate change or climate change as a forcing function
for human migration that then causes resource wars and political instability
or the fragility of the highly interconnected globalized world
where a problem in one part of the world can create supply chain issues
that create problems all around the world,
there's a sense that there's an increasing number of catastrophic risks
and that they're increasing faster than we are solving them.
And that when you mention like with the UN,
while progress has been made in certain defined areas of the sustainable development goals
and progress was made back when they were called the Millennium Development Goals,
we're very far from anything like a comprehensive solution to any of them.
We're not even on track for something that is converging towards a comprehensive solution.
And if we look at kind of the core initial mandate of the United Nations
in terms of thinking about how to recognizing after World War II
that nations take government alone wouldn't prevent World War
and now that World War was no longer viable
because the amount of technology we had made it a war that no one could win,
we still haven't succeeded at nuclear disarmament.
We did some very limited nuclear disarmament success while doing nuclear arms races at the same time
and we went from two countries with nukes to more countries with better nukes.
And that's simultaneous to that.
Every new type of tech that has emerged has created an arms race.
We haven't been able to prevent any of those.
And the major tragedy of the commons issues like climate change and overfishing
and dead zones in the oceans and microplastics in the oceans and biodiversity loss,
we haven't been able to solve those either.
And so rather than just think about this as like an overwhelming number of totally separate issues,
the question of why are the patterns of human behavior
as we increase our total technological capacity,
why are they increasing catastrophic risk and why are we not solving them well?
Are there underlying patterns that we could think of as,
as you mentioned, generator functions of the catastrophic risk,
generator functions of our inability to solve them,
that if we were to identify those and work at that level,
we could solve all of the expressions or symptoms.
And if we don't work at that level, we might not be able to solve any of them.
And again, people have been thinking about this for a long time,
kind of notice these issues.
They notice that you try to solve a,
like the first one I noticed when I was a kid
was trying to solve an elephant poaching issue in one particular region of Africa
that didn't address the poverty of the people that had no mechanism other than black market on poaching,
didn't address people's mindset towards animals,
didn't address a macroeconomy that created poverty at scale.
So when the laws were put in place and the fences were put in place
to protect those elephants in that area better,
the poachers moved to poaching other animals,
particularly in that situation rhinos and gorillas
that were both more endangered than the elephants had been.
So you moved a problem from one area to another and actually a more sensitive area.
And we see this with, well, can we solve hunger
by bringing commercial agriculture to parts of the world that don't have it
so that the people don't either not have food or we have to ship them food,
but if it's commercial agriculture based on the kind of unsustainable,
environmentally unsustainable agricultural processes
that lead to huge amounts of nitrogen runoff going into river deltas
that are causing dead zones in the ocean
that can actually collapse the biosphere's capacity to support life faster
than we're solving for a short-term issue that's important
and driving even worse long-term issues.
We see that many of the reasons people who oppose climate change solutions
in the West oppose them is because,
not because they have even really deeply engaged in the underlying science
and say the climate change isn't real,
that will oftentimes be what's said,
but because the solution itself seems like it'll cause problems
to other areas that they're paying attention to that seem even more critical to them.
So if the solution involves some kind of carbon tax
or something that would decrease GDP for the countries that agree to it
and some other countries don't agree to it,
and let's say in this particular case,
the model that many people have is western countries agree to it,
their GDP growth decreases, China doesn't agree to it,
and there's already a very, very close neck-in-neck fight
for who controls power in the 21st century.
Are we seeding the world to Chinese control
that many people would think it has less civil liberties
and is more authoritarian in its nature?
Or some people's answer to climate change is what we just have to use less energy,
but when you understand that energy correlates directly to GDP
and when GDP goes down, it affects poverty,
people in extreme poverty first and worst,
and wars increase because people who have desire to get more
end up going zero sum on each other,
and only when it's very positive sum does that not happen.
You see all these intricate theory of trade-off,
so we can't see that the problem is climate change.
Everybody knows the problem of climate change seems like a big thing,
but you've got to look at climate change plus the macroeconomic issues
that would affect the poorest people
and that would increase the chance of war
and the geopolitical dynamics between the West and China,
and the enforcement dynamics of international agreement.
When you start to recognize that the problem is that suite of things together,
in a way it seems, well, that's too hard, we can't even begin to focus on it.
I would say that that's actually easier
because trying to solve climate change on its own is actually impossible,
because if you're trying to solve something
that is going to externalize harm to some other thing,
maybe you solve that thing,
but you find out that you're in a worse position,
so I would say that it's impossible to actually improve the world that way,
or half the world that is paying attention to that other thing disagrees with you
so vehemently that all the energy goes into infighting
and whatever some part of the world is trying to organize to do,
the other part of the world is doing everything they can to resist from happening,
then all the creative energy just burns up as heat
and we don't actually accomplish anything.
So I would say that the way we're trying to solve the problems is actually mostly impossible.
It either solves it in a very narrow way
while externalizing harm and causing worse problems,
or it makes it impossible to solve it all because it drives polarization.
And so going to the level at which the problems interconnect
where that which everybody cares about is being factored
and where you're not externalizing other problems
while it seems more complex is actually possible.
Impossible is easier than impossible.
And so it's not just that there's a lot of issues, right?
There are a lot of issues,
and just that the issues are both more consequential at greater scope
and moving faster than previous issues
because of the nature of exponentiating technology.
That's part of it.
It's not just that the problems are all interconnected.
It's also that they do have underlying drivers that have to be addressed,
otherwise a symptomatic only approach doesn't work.
The first underlying driver that when people look at it they generally see
is they see things like structural perverse incentive built into macroeconomics,
that the elephant dead is worth more than the elephant alive is,
and so is the rhino, and so is the...
And so how do you have a situation where that's the nature of incentive,
where you're incentivizing an activity and then trying to bind it,
or keep it from happening?
And the same would be true with overfishing,
as long as live fish are worth nothing and dead fish are worth more.
There's something fundamentally perverse about the nature of the economic incentive.
And the same is true that when we have war and there's more military manufacturing, GDP goes up.
And when there's more addiction and people are buying the supply of their addiction, GDP goes up.
And when there are more sick people paying for health care, cost GDP goes up.
So it's obviously a perverse kind of metric.
So anytime someone can fiscally advantage themselves or a corporation can
in a way that either directly causes harm or indirectly externalizes harm,
we have to fundamentally solve that.
If there's something like 70 trillion dollars a day of activity happening
that is a decentralized system of incentive,
that is incenting people to do things that are directly or indirectly causing harm,
there's really nothing we can do with some billions of dollars of nonprofit or state
or whatever money that is going to solve that thing.
So we have to say, well, what changes at the level of macroeconomics need to happen
where the incentive of individuals and the incentive of corporations and the incentive of nations
is more well aligned with the well-being and the incentive of others.
And so we're less fundamentally rivalrous in the nature of our incentive.
So we can see that underneath heaps of the problems, structures of macroeconomic incentive are there.
That's kind of maybe the first one that most people see.
We can go deeper to seeing that even as an expression,
because whether it's a economic incentive for a corporation or whether it's a power incentive,
a political power incentive or a political party or for a country,
they're both instantiations of rivalrous-type dynamics that end up driving arms races,
because if you win at a rivalrous dynamic, the other side reverse-engineers your tech,
figures out how to make better versions, comes back, which creates an exponentiation in warfare
and eventually exponential warfare becomes self-terminating on a finite planet.
Exponential externalities also become self-terminating.
So if we want to say, what are the underlying generator functions of catastrophic risk?
First, maybe just to make clear, the catastrophic risk landscape.
Is this all right if we do a brief aside on that?
Yeah, let's do it.
I think what we should do, let's do that, and then let's recap just what these structures are.
People are tracking each of these components, because you've already mentioned a few different things.
The first thing is just many listeners might hear what you're sharing as an overwhelming set of problems,
and I think it's just to recap.
It's important people understand that it's overwhelming if you're not using a problem-solving framework
that allows you to see the interconnected nature of those problems,
because if you solve them with the limited tools we have now,
let's just solve the social media problem by pulling one lever and changing one business model of one company,
or banning TikTok, but then you get 20 other TikToks that come and sit in its place with the same perverse incentive of addiction,
the same rival risk dynamic competing for human attention.
We're going to end up perpetuating those problems.
And so just to sort of maybe recap some of that for listeners,
and I think maybe let you continue with the other generator function.
Let's just make sure that people really get those frameworks.
I think it's really important.
Yeah, I mean, in the case that you in Center for Humane Technology have brought so much attention to,
with regard to the attention harvesting and directing economy,
it's fair to say that it probably was not Facebook or Google's goal to create the type of effects that they had.
Those were unintended externalities.
They were second order effects.
But they were trying to solve problems, right?
Like, let's solve the problem if we're Google of organizing the world's information and making better search.
That seems like a pretty good thing to do.
And let's solve the problem of making it freely available to everybody.
And with the AdModel, we can make it freely available to everyone.
And let's recognize that only if we get a lot of data will our machine learning get better.
And so we need to actually get everybody on this thing.
So we definitely have to make it free.
And then we get this kind of recursive process.
Well, then the nature of the AdModel, doing time on site optimization and stuff I'm not going to get into because you've addressed it so well,
ends up appealing to people's existing biases rather than correcting their bias,
appealing to their tribal in-group identities rather than correcting them,
and appealing to limbic hijacks rather than helping people transcend them.
And as a result, you end up actually breaking the social solidarity and epistemic capacity necessary for democracy.
So it's like, oh, let's solve the search problem.
That seems like a nice thing.
The side effect is we're going to destroy democracy and open societies in the process and all those other things.
Like, those are examples of solving a problem in a way that is externalizing harm,
causing other problems that are oftentimes worse.
And so let's just focus on the opportunity.
And just to say, typically, this will get accounted for as, oh, this is just an unintended consequence.
But there's some other generator functions I think we should outline.
I mean, if YouTube and Google didn't personalize search results and what video to show you next,
and the other guy did on TikTok starts personalizing, they're caught in a race to the bottom of whoever personalizes more for the best limbic hijack.
And so just to sort of connect some of those things together for listeners.
So you mentioned race to the bottom, and obviously CHT has discussed this before,
and this is a key piece of the game theoretic challenge and global coordination.
And the two primary ways it expresses itself is arms races and tragedy of the commons.
And the tragedy of the commons scenario is if we don't overfish that area of virgin ocean,
but we can't control that someone else doesn't, because how do we do enforcement if they're also a nuclear country?
That's a tricky thing, right? How do you do enforcement on nuclear countries, equipped countries?
So us not doing it doesn't mean that the fish don't all get taken.
It just means that they grow their populations and their GDP faster, which they will use rivalrously.
So we might as well do it. In fact, we might as well race to do it faster than they do.
Those are the tragedy of the commons type issues.
The arms race version is if we can't ensure that they don't build AI weapons or they don't build surveillance tech
and they get increased near-term power from doing so, we just have to race to get there before them.
That's the arms race type thing.
It just happens to be that while that makes sense for each agent on their own in the short term,
it creates global dynamics for the whole and the long term that self-terminate,
because you can't run exponential externality on a finite planet.
That's the tragedy of the commons one, and you can't run exponential arms races and exponential conflict on a finite planet.
So the thing that has always made sense, which is just keep winning at the arms races,
has had a world where we've had lots of wars increasing in their scale and lots of environmental damage.
We started desertification thousands of years ago.
It's just has been a long, slow, exponential curve that really started to pick up with the industrial revolution
and is now really verticalizing with the digital revolution and the cumulative harm of that kind of thing becomes impossible now.
So basically, with the environmental destruction, with the wars and with the class subjugation things that civilization has had in the past,
pretty much anyone would say we have not been the best stewards of power, and technology is increasing our power.
Exponential tech means tech that makes better versions of itself, so you get an exponent on the curve.
We're now in a process where that's a very, very rapid.
Computation gives the ability to design better systems of computation.
Computation and AI applied to biological big data and protein folding gives the ability to do that on biotech and on and on, right?
So we could say the central question of our time is if we've been poor stewards of power for a long time and that's always caused problems,
but the problems now become existential, they become catastrophic, we can't keep doing that.
How do we become adequately good stewards of exponential power in time, right?
How do we develop the good decision-making processes, the wisdom necessary to be able to be stewards of that much power?
I think that's a fair way to talk about the central thing.
If it's okay, the thread we were about to get to, I think, is a good one, which was the history of catastrophic risk coming up to now,
is that before World War II, catastrophic risk was actually a real part of people's experience.
It was just always local, but an individual kingdom might face existential risk in a war where they would lose.
And so the people faced those kinds of reality, and in fact, one thing that we can see when you read books like The Collapse of Complex Societies by Joseph Tainter
and any study of history is that all the great civilizations don't still exist, which means that one of the first things we can say about civilizations is that they die.
They have a finite lifespan on them.
One of the interesting things we can find is that they usually die from self-induced causes.
They either over-consume the resources and then stop being able to meet the needs of the people through unrenewable environmental dynamics, and that's old.
Or they have increasing border conflicts that lead to enmity, that has more arms race activity coming back at them,
or they have increasing institutional decay of their internal coordination processes that leads to inability to operate quickly in those types of things.
So we can say that it's the fundamentally most all civilizations collapse in a way that is based on generally self-terminating dynamics.
And we see that even when they were overtaken by armies, oftentimes they were armies that were smaller than ones they had defended against successfully at earlier peaks in their adaptive capacity.
Okay, so catastrophic risk has been a real thing. It's just been local.
And it wasn't until World War II that we had enough technological power that catastrophic risk became a global possibility for the first time ever.
And this is a really important thing to get because the world before World War II and the world after was different and kind so fundamentally.
And this is why when you study history, so much of what you're studying is history of warfare, of neighboring kingdoms and neighboring empires fighting.
And because the wars were fundamentally winnable, at least for some, right? They weren't winnable for all the people who died, but at least for some.
And with World War II and the development of the bomb became the beginning of wars that were no longer winnable.
And that if we employed our full tech and continued the arms race even beyond the existing tech, it's a war where when lose becomes omni-lose-lose at that particular level of power.
And so that created the need to do something that humanity had never done, which was that the major superpowers didn't war.
The whole history of the world, the history of the thing we call civilization, they always did.
And so we made an entire world system, a globalized world system that was with the aim of preventing World War III.
So we could have non-kinetic wars, and we did, right? Increasingly you can see from World War II to now a movement to unconventional warfare,
narrative and information warfare, economic, diplomatic warfare, those types of things, resource warfare.
And you could, if you were going to have a physical kinetic war, it had to be a proxy war.
But to have a proxy war, that also required narrative warfare to be able to create a justification for it.
But also to be able to prevent the war, so the post-World War II Bretton Woods Mutually Assured Destruction United Nations World
was a solution to be able to steward that level of tech without destroying ourselves.
And it really was a reorganization of the world. It was a whole new advent of social technologies or social systems,
just like the U.S. was new social technologies or social systems coming out of the Industrial Revolution.
The Industrial Revolution ended up giving rise to kind of nation-state democracies.
The nuclear revolution in this way kind of gave rise to this I.G.O. intergovernmental world.
And it was predicated on a few things. Mutually Assured Destruction was critical.
Globalization and economic trade was critical that we, if the computer that we're talking on and the phone that we talk on
is made over six continents and no countries can make them on our own, we don't want to blow them up and ruin their infrastructure
because we depend upon it. So let's create radical economic interdependence so we have more economic incentive to cooperate.
Makes sense. And let's grow the materials economy so fast through this globalization
that the world gets to be very positive GDP and gets to be very positive sum
so that everybody can have more without having to take each other's stuff.
That was kind of like the basis of that whole world system.
And we can see that we've had wars, but they've been proxy wars and cold wars.
They haven't been major superpower wars and they've been unconventional ones.
But we haven't had a kinetic World War III. We have had increase of prosperity of certain kinds.
75 years give or take. Now we're at a point where that radically positive sum economy
that required an exponential growth of the economy, which means of the materials economy,
and it's a linear materials economy that unrenewably takes resources from the earth faster than they can reproduce themselves
and turns them into waste faster than they can process themselves, has led to the planetary boundaries issue
where it's not just climate change or overfishing or dead zones in the ocean or microplastics or species extinction
or peak phosphorus. It's a hundred things, right?
There's all these planetary boundaries so we can't keep doing exponential linear materials economy.
That thing has come to an end because now that drives its own set of catastrophic risks.
We see that the radical interconnection of the world was good in terms of will not bomb each other
but it also created very high fragility because what it meant is a failure anywhere could cascade to failures everywhere
because of that much dependence. So we can see with COVID we had what was a local issue to an area of China
but because of how interconnected the world is with travel it became a global issue at the pandemic level
and it also became an issue where to shut down the transmission of the virus we shut down travel
which also meant shut down supply chains which meant so many things, right?
And very fundamental things that weren't obvious to people at first like that countries agriculture depends upon the shipment of pesticides that they don't have stored
and so we got these swarms of locusts because of not having the pesticides which damaged the food supply
and shipments of fertilizer and shipments of seed so we end up seeing a drive of food insecurity of extreme poverty
at a scale of death threat that is larger than the COVID death threat was.
As a second order effect of our problem we were trying to solve the problem of don't spread COVID
and the solution had these massive second third order effects that are still playing out, right?
And that was a relatively benign pandemic a relatively benign catastrophe compared to a lot of scenarios we can model out
so we can say okay well we like the benefit of interconnectivity so we're not invested in bombing each other
but we need more anti-fragility in the system.
And then the mutually assured destruction thing doesn't work anymore because we don't have two countries with one catastrophe weapon
that's really really hard to make and easy to monitor because there's not that many places that have uranium
it's hard to enrich it you can monitor by satellites.
We have lots of countries with nukes but we also have lots of new catastrophe weapons that are not hard to make
that are not easy to monitor that don't even take nation states to make them.
So if you have many many actors of different kinds with many different types of catastrophe weapons
how do you do mutually assured destruction?
You can't do it the same way.
And so what we find is that the set of solutions post World War II that kept us from blowing ourselves up with our new power
lasted for a while but those set of solutions have ended and they have now created their own set of new problems.
So there's kind of the catastrophic risk world before World War II
the catastrophic risk world from World War II till now and then the new thing.
So the new thing says we have to have solutions that deal with the planetary boundary issues
that deal with global fragility issues and that deal with the exponential tech issues
both in terms of the way exponential tech can be intentionally used to cause harm
i.e. exponential tech empowered warfare and unintentionally
i.e. exponential tech empowered externalities and even just totally unanticipated types of mistakes
the Facebook Google type problem multiplied by AGI and things like that.
And so when we talk about what the catastrophic risk landscape is like that's the landscape
the metacrisis is how do we solve all of that and recognizing that our problem solving mechanisms
haven't even been able to solve the problems we've had for the last many years let alone prevent these things
and so the central orienting question it's like the UNS-17 Sustainable Development Goals
there's really one that must supersede them all which is develop the capacity for global coordination
that can solve global problems. If you get that one you get all the other ones
if you don't get that one you don't get any of the other ones and so we can talk about how do we do that
but that becomes the central imperative for the world at this time.
So you're saying a whole bunch of things and one thing that comes to mind here
if I'm just reading back some of the things you've shared
the development of the let's call it one of the first exponential technologies which is the nuclear bomb
led to a new social system which was sort of the post Bretton Woods world of trying to stabilize
that one exponential technology in the world in a way that would not be catastrophic
and even there we weren't able to sort of make it all work
and I think people should have maybe a list of some of the other exponential technologies
because I want to make sure that phrase is defined for listeners and there's a lot of different ways
that we've now not just created more exponential technologies but more decentralized exponential technologies
and I think people should see Facebook and Google as exponential attention mapping
or information driving technologies that are shaping the global information flows
or the wiring diagram of the sort of global societal brain at scales that are exponential
it's sort of a nuclear scale rewiring of the human civilization
we couldn't do that with newspapers we couldn't do that with a printing press
not at the scale speed et cetera that we have now
so do you want to give maybe some more examples of exponential technologies
because I think that's going to lead to we're going to need a new kinds of social systems
to manage this different landscape of not just one exponential nuclear bomb but a landscape
indulge me as I tell a story first that leads into it because it'll be a relevant framework
obviously the bomb was central to World War II and the world system that came afterwards
and what motivated our activity getting into it but it was not the only tech
it was one new technology that was part of a suite of new technologies that could all be developed
because of kind of the level science had gotten to
and basically like physics and chemistry had gotten to the point that we could work on a nuclear bomb
we could start to work on computation
we could get things like the V2 rocket and rockets and a whole host of applied chemistry
and one way of thinking about what World War II was
one way of thinking about it but it's useful frame and I think it's a fair frame
is that there were a few competing social ideologies at the time
primarily kind of German fascism fascism socialism whatever you want to call it
Soviet communism and Western liberalism something like that
and that this new suite of technologies whoever kind of developed it and was able to implement it at scale first would win
that social ideology would win because it's just so much more powerful
if you have nukes and they have guns you're going to win right
and Germans were actually ahead of both the US and the Soviets
because of some things that they did to invest in education and tech development
but that led both the Soviets and the US to really working to catch up as fast as they can
and when the US finally figured it out which we were actually a little bit slow to right
Einstein actually wrote a letter the Einstein solar letter that went to the US government
saying now the science really does say that this thing could happen and the Germans could get it
and you should focus on it and at first they didn't take them up on it
it wasn't until the private sector actually nonprofit supported advanced it further
that then the Manhattan Project was engaged in but then it was engaged in when they recognized the seriousness
that there was an actual eminent existential risk to the nation and the whole Western ideology and whatever
then it was an unlimited budget right it was a let's find all the smartest people in the world
and let's bring them here and let's organize however we need to to make this thing happen
and let's do it for all of the new areas of tech we're going to get the enigma machine and crack the enigma code
we're going to get a v2 rocket we're going to figure out how to reverse engineer that in advanced rocketry
we're going to do everything needed to make a nuclear bomb and then more advanced ones
it was the biggest jump in technology ever in the history of the world in record history as we know it
and it wasn't actually done by the market right it was done by the state that's a very important thing
this idea that markets innovate and states don't innovate is just historically not true here
this was state funds and state controlled operation in the same way that the Apollo project coming out of it was
and a technological jump of that kind hasn't happened since
so it's an important thing to understand but we can say though this is not a totally fair thing to say
we can say that the US came out dominant in that technological race
the US and the USSR both had a lot of capacity so that was the Cold War and then finally the US came out
and so the post-World War II system was a US led system
the UN was in the US the Bretton Wood system was pegged to the US dollar
what I would say is that so it wasn't one type of tech
it was the recognition that science had got to a place where there's going to be a whole suite of new tech
and the new tech meant more power and whoever had the power would determine the next phase of the world
and if we didn't like the social ideologies that were going to be guiding it
of course we can also think of it as just who wanted to win at the game of power
but from the philosophical argument if we didn't like the social ideologies then we have another social ideology
get it
what I would say is that there is an emerging suite of technologies now
that is much more powerful in the total level of jump
technological jump than the World War II suite was
in fact orders of magnitude more
and only those who are developing and employing exponential tech
will have much of a say in the direction of the future
because just from a real politic point of view that's where the power is
and if you don't have the power you won't be able to oppose it
and so what do we mean by exponential tech?
there's a couple different ways of thinking about it
just exponentially more powerful is a very simplistic way
and in that definition nuclear is exponential tech
but what we typically mean with exponential tech is tech that makes it possible to make better versions of itself
so that there is like a compounding interest kind of curve
the tech makes it easier to make a better version which makes it easier to make a better version
and so we see that starting with computation really in a fundamental way
because computation allows us to advance models of computation
how do we make better computational substrates
how do we get more transistors in a chip
how do we make better arrangements of chip so we get GPUs and those types of things
and so in this new suite of technology the center of it is computation
the very very center of that is AI
is kind of self-learning computation on large fields of data
the other kind of software advances like advances in various meaningful advances in cryptography
and big data and the ability to get data from sensors and you know sensor processing image recognition
that is a part of that central suite
and the application of that to the directing of attention and the directing of behavior by directing attention
which you focused on very centrally
then the next phase is the application of the tech
the application of computation to increasing computational substrate
so this is now the software advancing the hardware that can advance the total level of software
so that's not just continuously better chips
it's also quantum computing, photo computing, DNA computing, those other types of things
and the other types of hardware that need to be part of that thing
i.e. sensor tech in particular
so that you can keep getting more data going into that system that can do big data machine learning on it
then it's the application of that computation in AI specifically to physical tech
so to nanotech, material sciences, biotech and even things like modeling how to do better nuclear
and you know robotics and automation
and so when you start thinking about better computational substrates running better software
with more total data going in with better sensors in better robots
you start getting the sense of what that whole suite of things looks like
so that's the suite of things that I would say is what we would kind of call exponential tech
and the reason why the term exponential is important is we don't think exponentially well
our intuitions are bad for it because we think about how much progress was made over the last five years
and we imagine there will be a similar amount over the next five years
and that's not the way exponential curves work, right?
and so it's very hard for us, our intuition was calibrated on the past
and it's going to be miscalibrated for forecasting the total rate of change and the magnitude of change
so to link this for one much more narrow aspect for our listeners who are familiar with social media
and social dilemma and you're talking about sort of self-compounding systems that improve recursively like that
if I'm TikTok or if I'm Facebook and I use data to figure out what's the thing to show you
and that's going to keep you here for long since going to bypass your prefrontal cortex
and go straight to your limbic system, your lizard brain
well the better it gets at doing that and succeeding at that
the more data it has to make a better prediction the next time
but then a new user comes along who it's never seen before
but hey they're clicking on exactly the same pattern of anorexia videos
that we've seen these other 2 million users have that turn out to be teenage girls
and it just happens to know that this other set of videos that are more anorexia videos
are also going to work really really well
so there's sort of a self-compounding loop that's learning not just from one person
and getting a better version of hijacking your nervous system
but learning across individuals
and so now you get a new person coming in from developing countries
never used TikTok before and they're just barely walking in for the front door the very first time
it's sort of like when Coca-Cola goes to Southeast Asia for the first time
and you get diabetes 10 years later because you refined all the techniques of marketing so effectively
but now happening at scales that are automated with computation
so what you're talking about is the impact of computation
and learning on top of learning data on top of data
and then cross-referencing look-alike models and all of this kind of thing
you could apply to the domain at least that social dilemma
watchers and people who are familiar with our work might be able to tie into
Yeah, the more people you have in the system and the more data per person that you're able to harvest
the more stuff you have for the machine learning to figure out patterns on
which also means that the machine learning can provide things that the users want more
even if it's manufactured want, right, even if it's manufactured demand
which means that then more users will come and put more data in
and it can specifically figure out how to manufacture the types of behavior that increase data collection
and so you do get this recursive process on how many people, how much data, how good are the machine learning algorithms
you know, that kind of thing and this is one of the reasons that we see these natural monopoly formations
within these categories of tech
and this is another reason that's important to understand like
these types of self-reinforcing dynamics and things like network effects like Metcalf's law
didn't exist when the Scottish Enlightenment was coming up with its ideas of capitalism
and market and the healthy competition and markets and why that creates checks and balances on power
they didn't exist, Adam Smith did not get to think about those things
and so when you have a situation where the value of the network is proportional to the square of the
people coming into the network then you're incented to keep it free up front, maximize addiction, drive behavior into the system
and then once you get to the kind of breakaway point on the return of that thing
it becomes nearly impossible for anyone else to come in and overtake that thing
so you get a power law distribution in each vertical
you get one online market that is bigger than all the other online markets
one video player that's bigger than all the other video players, one search, one social network one
and that's not because of a government monopoly, that's because of this kind of natural tech monopoly
this also means that when we created the laws around monopolies they don't apply to this thing
and yet this thing still has the same spirit of power concentration and unchecked power
that our ideas of monopoly had but it's able to grow much faster than law is able to figure out how to deal with it
or faster than economic theory can change itself, right?
and so one of the things that we see is that our social technologies like law, like governance, like economics
are actually being obsolete by the development of totally new types of behavior and mechanics
that weren't part of the world they were trying to solve problems for, right?
and so the Scottish Enlightenment was the development of new ideas of how to problem solve, the problems of its time
the constitution was trying to figure out how to solve the problems of its time
I would say they were good thinking, right? they were good work
the Bretton Woods world was, none of them are adequate to solve these problems
because these problems are different in kind
and even where they're just an extension of magnitude, when you get enough change in magnitude
sometimes it becomes a difference in kind, like as you're getting more and more information to process
once you get past what humans can process, infosingularity type issues
okay, well now it's a difference in magnitude that becomes a difference in kind
which means you need a fundamentally different approach
so I would say this is where it's important to recognize that those social technologies that we loved so much
because they seemed so much better than all the other options we had at the time
like markets and like democracy
these are not terminal goods in and of themselves
the terminal goods were things like human liberty
and justice and checks and balances on power
and opportunity and distribution of opportunity and things like that
these were the best social technologies possible at the time
the new technologies both kill those things
they don't work anymore, right?
you can't have the social technology of the fourth estate
that was necessary for democracy
which is why founding fathers said things like
if I could have perfect newspapers and a broken government
or perfect government and broken newspapers, I'd take the newspapers
because if you have an educated populace that all understands what's going on
they can make a new form of government
if you have people that have no idea what's going on
how could they possibly make good choices if their sense making is totally broken
so we had this idea that the fourth estate was a prerequisite
to a participatory governance
but that was based on a very narrow limited capacity for print
and again it was the technology of the Gutenberg Press
that was one of the things that actually ended feudalism
and so the founding fathers were employing that new tech
both because it upended the previous tech and it made this new thing possible
same with guns
they needed guns and second amendments to make this new thing possible
but once we get to a internet world
where you don't have centralized broadcasts
you have decentralized and then there's so much stuff
that you can never possibly find at all in search
whoever coordinates the search
the content aggregators, which is the Facebook, the YouTube, whatever
are doing it with the types of business models we have
the fourth estate is just dead forever
that old version, there's no way to recreate that version
that either means democracy is dead forever
or anything like a well-informed citizenry
that could participate in its governance in any form
or you have to say what is a post-internet, post-social media, post-infosingularity
fourth estate that creates an adequately educated citizenry
that's thinking about the way that our social technologies
our social systems have to upgrade themselves
in the presence of the tech that obsoleted the way they did work
but we can also see and we can give examples of this
the new tech also makes possible new things that weren't possible before
so we can do something better than industrial-era democracy
or industrial-era markets
which is why I say they aren't a terminal good
they're a way to deliver certain human values that really matter
and the new technology that obsoletes those
can actually also be facilitative in designing systems
that also serve those values
but it's not a given that it does
that has to become the kind of central orienting mission
so Dan just to make sure we're linking this back to the start of this conversation
we started this conversation by saying
the way that we are going about solving problems
let's say using the legacy systems of lawmaking in a congress
or using the legacy systems of a town hall to vote on a proposition
or trying to pass laws as fast as social media as rewiring society
the lines don't match
and so what you're saying is that
and just for listeners because I know that you use the phrase social technology
but I think you're really talking about it
social systems, ways of organizing democracy
technology in the most fundamental sense of the word
of something humans design to facilitate certain kinds of activity or outcomes
like language is a technology
or democracy is a technology
social systems
and so if the kind of old world approach of
some people might be hearing this and say to themselves
now hold on a second
so we have all these institutions
we have all these structures
we live in a democracy
and we live in a system that is working the way it does
it has its courts, it has its attorney generals
it has its litigation procedures
it has its lawmaking bodies
if you're saying that we can't use those things
because they're not adequate
or they won't help us solve those problems
we need to have new social systems
maybe you could give us some hope about why that might be feasible
instead of feeling impossible
because this is actually precedented in our history
when new technologies show up
and then new social systems emerge
to make room for those technologies functioning well
you briefly touched on that
but I think it's important to give listeners a few concrete examples
there's a number of good academics and disciplines of academics
that look at the history of evolutions and physical technology
and the corresponding evolutions in
thought and culture and social systems
Marvin Harris, the cultural materialism
did a kind of major opus work here
where he specifically looked at how changes in social systems and cultures
followed changes in technology
there are other bodies of work that will
look at the social systems as primary
or the cultures as primary
and we can say they're inter-affecting
but for instance
the vast majority of human history was tribal
however much 200,000 years of humans
in the small Dunbar number villages
there was a social technology
social systems that mediated that
that had to do with how the tribal circles worked
and the nature of how resources were shared
it was a very different kind of economic system
a very different kind of judicial system
a different educational system
it had all those things
it had a way of education
meaning intergenerational knowledge transfer
of the entire knowledge set that was needed
for the tribe to continue operating
the development of certain technologies
particularly the plow
but baskets and a few other things
obsolete that thing
because all of a sudden it made possible
big amounts of surplus
that made reason for much larger populations
to emerge
those larger populations
were going to win in conflict against
the smaller populations
and so you can see that then the emergence
of new social technology
to facilitate large groups of people
empire types
civilization technology emerged
you can see
and that there were a few other shifts in technology
that evolved the types of empires that were there
and then the next one that people talk about a lot
is the industrial revolution
from the printing press specifically
and then steam engine
the gunpowder revolution was part of it
that kind of ended feudalism
and began the nation state world
and so you can see like
what is the thing that the founding fathers
in the US were doing
well they weren't trying to keep winning at feudalism
there was a game that had been happening
for a long time
and they were saying
like no we're all people who are in
of the type of people who could do well
at that system
and rather than do that
we recognize that there are
fundamentally things wrong with this system
and fundamentally new possibilities
that hadn't been previously recognized
so we're going to actually try to design
a fundamentally different system
that we think
a more perfect union
that makes life liberty in the pursuit of happiness
better for everybody
and increases productive capacity
and things like that
so that was fundamentally in advance
in social technology or social systems
that both utilized
new physical technology
and was enabled by it
in the current situation
there are groups that are advancing
the exponential technologies
and that means whatever social systems
that they're employing
are the social systems of the future
if we don't change it
and that's what I want to get to in a moment
but like who is working to
implement any of the new emerging
tech for better social systems
that are aligned with social systems we want
you've had Audrey Tang
on the show
do you want to just briefly describe
an example of what she
and what they have done there
because if people aren't aware of it
that's a pretty prime example
of for this particular iteration
sure well
and maybe just to go back briefly
because you gave this example
in one of our earlier conversations
that the printing press
could have been used by the feudal lords
for consciously reinforcing feudalism
but instead this new technology
the printing press gives way
to new ways of organizing society
so we can actually have things like
a fourth estate or newspapers
or things like that
both happen
but then the new thing theoretically
has to win out over the old thing
at least the one that we want
that holds the values that the society wants
so
I think a lot of people can hear our conversation
we've had this riff before
actually following our last episode
after my senate testimony
speaking about a frame
that you have offered and know well
which is that we can notice
that digital authoritarian societies
right now like China
are consciously using exponential technologies
to make stronger more effective digital
closed and authoritarian societies
and in contrast digital open societies
democracies like the United States
are not consciously using technology
to make stronger healthier open societies
instead they've sort of surrendered
what they are to
private technology
corporations pursuing self-interest
to shareholders and are
profiting from the degradation
and dysfunction of democracies
and so
when we say all this and we talk about
how do we build the kind of next social system
and Audrey Tang and her work
I think people
get tripped up in thinking that what we really mean
is we have to make some kind of 21st century
digital democracy in fact I probably said those words
but what we're really talking about here
is some new concept that preserves
the principles of what we meant by
a democracy
but instantiated with the new technologies
our version of the new printing press
which is networked
information environments and
all of the new capacities that we have in the 21st century
with
mobility where everyone's connected to everywhere
and everything all at once
so what is that system
that leverages the current technology
and makes a stronger healthier open society
and I think Audrey Tang's work
I mean I would probably send listeners back
to listen to that episode I think it's one of our
most listened to and most popular episodes for a reason
because in Taiwan
she's essentially built an entire
civic technology ecosystem
in which people are really participating
in the governance of their society
we need masks, we need
better air quality sensors, we need to fix these
potholes, there are processes
by which every time you're frustrated by something
you actually get invited into a civic design process
where whether it's the potholes or the masks
you can actually participate in having a better
system
complaining about the tax system and filing your taxes
and maybe it's an inefficient form
or something like that you get brought into a design process
of what would make it better
and so the system is participatory but not in that
kind of 18th century way of hey there's a
physical wooden townhouse and we're going to walk into it
and we're going to hang out there for three hours
and we're going to yell and scream about issues that are more local
within 10, 15 miles
of where we are because we were existing in a world before automobiles
we're now talking about how do you do
an open society social system
but in a world with all of the new technologies
that are not just here today but emerging
and so do you want to talk a little bit
about what
how we even navigate that challenge
and why is some new social system like that
necessary
for dealing with these problems that you've
sort of laid out at the beginning
because I'm sure people would like to feel
less anxiety about those things
hanging around for longer
yeah I think
I think what
Taiwan has been doing
and what Audrey Tang
in the digital ministry position
in particular has been leading
is probably the best example
certainly one of the best examples in the world of this kind of
process in thinking
and
does it apply in the
or could it apply in the exact same way to the US
no of course not like we know that
because
of the relatively small geography
and
high-speed train transportation
you can get across Taiwan in an hour and a half
and so when you're mentioning the small scale
of local government at the beginning of the US
where you come to the town hall in a way they have
that right like it's 23 million people
but there is
an older shared culture
there is all there also happens
to be an existential threat just right
off their border that is
you know big enough that they can't
just chill and not focus on it
everyone has to be civically engaged
with some civic identity and like that
they didn't start making
their culture in the industrial era and then have to
upgrade it right like they started
later
where they're we're able to start at a higher
level of the tech stack
so there's a number of reasons why it's different
so we're not going to naively say what you do
in a tiny country that is culturally
and ethnically homogeneous
and has a higher GDP
education per capita and whatever is the same thing
you would do but we can certainly take a lot
of the examples and say how would
they apply differently in different
contexts
so
the thing we said earlier
that this suite of
exponential technologies is so much more powerful
than all of the previous types
of power that only
those who are
developing and deploying
them will be
really steering the direction of the future
and
that there are ways of employing them
that do cause
catastrophic risk
and
the catastrophic risk is of two primary
kinds right conflict theory mediated
and
you can't
you just can't do warfare
with this level of technology
and this interconnected a world
and make it through well
not all catastrophic risk means existential
doesn't all mean nuclear
war and nuclear winter and we've killed
all the mammals on earth it might
just mean we break global supply chains
kill lots of people and regress
humanity and the quality of the biosphere
pretty significantly so
I'm not
just focused on existential risk I'm interested
in kind of catastrophic risk
at scale in general
and we can see that exponential tech
applied
as
in conflict theory and in
mistake
as externalities and the cumulative effects
could you define
conflict theory and mistake theory for people
who are not familiar with those terms
yeah there's
a very nice
discussion on the less wrong forum
if people are interested to go deeper
and it's this question of
how much of the problems in the world
are the result of
conflict theory versus mistake theory
meaning conflict theory is
we knew we either wanted to cause
that problem that harm to whomever
as in a knowingly wanted to win
at a war and
or at least we knew we were
going to cause that problem and didn't care because
it was attached to something we wanted
right conflict theory or mistake
theory we didn't know we didn't want to cause
it and we really didn't know and it was just
unintended unanticipatable consequence
and it's fair to say that there's
both right there's plenty of both
one
thing that is worth knowing is that
if I
if I'm trying to do something that is
actually motivated by conflict theory
it benefits me to pretend that it was mistake
theory benefits me to pretend that I had no idea
and then afterwards say oh it was
an unintended unanticipatable consequence
it was too complex people can't predict stuff
like that and so
the reality
of mistake theory
ends up being a source of plausible
deniability for conflict theory
and
but they're both things and we have to
overcome both meaning we have to
have choice making processes in our new system
of coordination and like this sounds
like maybe hippy stuff
until you take
seriously the change of context
oh we have to have problems of choice making that
consider the whole that sounds like
unrealizable hippy stuff
until you realize
but we're making choices that affect
the whole
at a level that
can even individually be catastrophic
and is definitely catastrophic cumulatively
so if we aren't factoring
it
then the human experiment self terminates and maybe that's
the answer to the great filter hypothesis
right and so
our
well yeah
I think people don't have an intuitive grasp of
what it means that each of us
are walking around with the power of
gods to influence huge enormous
consequences I mean
I could give a few examples every time you
enact with the global supply chain and hit buy on Amazon
you invisibly enacted
shipping and planes
and petroleum and wars in the middle east
there's a whole bunch of things that we're
sort of tied into when you are
posting something on social media and have
more than a million followers you're
influencing the global information ecology
and if you're angry and biased about one
side of the other of the pandemic is real
or it's not real or something like that you're
externalizing more bias into the commons
of how keep the rest of the world understands
things so we're walking around with increasing
power but I don't think the increasing power
that we've granted is intuitive
for some folks did you explain
some more examples of that there's both
cumulative effect and
like cumulative long-term
and fairly singular short-term
and cumulative long-term
I mean you go back to
early
US settlers coming into the
US moving west
and they're being buffalo everywhere and there had
been buffalo everywhere for a very long time
and then there's no buffalo in whole areas that
were forested with old growth forest became
deforested and it was
like no it's impossible we could never get rid of all the
buffalo like I we could never
cut down all the trees but the cumulative effect
of lots of people thinking that way we're individually
I have no incentive to leave the buffalo alive
and I do have an incentive for my family individually
to kill it but everybody thinking
that way and
increasing our
desire for how much we consume per capita
our technology that allows us
to consume more per capita
and developing more capital
more total people well
then you start getting
environmental destruction and species extinction at scale
and that's a long time ago
right like that's much lower tech and much less
people and it's
distributed action it's a
cumulative effect issue
and obviously we see that with
nobody's intending to fill the
ocean with microplastics
but everybody's buying shit that is filling the
oceans with microplastics and
so everyone is participating with systems where
the system as a whole
is sociopathic the system is self-terminating
the system doesn't exist without all the agents
interacting with it all the agents feel like
their behavior is so small
that that justifies everybody doing
that thing right so that's what we
mean by cumulative kind of catastrophic risk
but it's
also true that
whoever made
that
thermite bomb and hooked it to a drone and hit
the Ukrainian munitions factory a couple years
ago that caused a billion dollars
in damage exploded munitions factory
the effect of a bomb as big
as the largest
nuclear bomb the U.S. arsenal has an incendiary bomb
this is a home
that was a homemade little bomb in a
drone right and
so and crisper gene
drives are
cheap and easy and it doesn't take
that much advanced
knowledge to start working with them and
so that that starts to look
like
individuals and small
groups with real catastrophic ability
not long-term and cumulatively
the increase in our tech
gives us both issues via
globalization and the overall system you
get these cumulative long-term effects
and with the exponential
tech creating decentralized catastrophic
capabilities one
of the core questions we have to answer is how do we
make a world that is anti fragile
in the presence of
those kind of catastrophic capabilities that are
easy to produce and thus
decentralizable
and so
how do we do that
what are the social systems that we need
to employ to bind some of these
bad
facts and ways that the natural
inclinations of self-interested actors
will drive things in that direction just
to link this to the social media space for people
if I know that I can get
a little bit more attention and a little bit
more likes and clicks and follows and shares
and so on if I exaggerate the truth
by five percent just to use a little bit
more of an extreme adjective
you know I know that that in the long
run would be bad if everybody did that
but for me right now I can win a few hits
and I can get more influence and I'm an Instagram influencer
and I'm making ten thousand dollars a month and if I don't do it
I'm noticing everyone else's do it and if I don't use
the filter everyone else is using the filter
and so everyone ends up in this sort of another race
at the bottom sort of situation
that has that kind of cumulative degradation
or cumulative
derangement where there's increasing distance
between what is true and what people believe
because we've all been subtly exaggerating it
to make our point and gain influence and so on
and so
just to give another example
maybe for listeners in kind of the space that they're
more familiar with
but going back I mean the whole premise
of this is as we gain more
exponential technologies that have
more capacity and more hands
so instead of having just the US and Russia having this
you have
whether as you mentioned CRISPR gene drives or
some of the drone things that are out there
more and more people have access to these things
how can we bind
those kinds of forces and what are the
social systems that we need to make that happen
yeah I want to go back
as you were describing this
I was thinking about how many people
who
listen to your show
who maybe work in technology who might have
they work in technology
because they see the positive things technology can do
and have more of a kind of techno-optimist
point of view and this overall conversation
might sound very techno-pessimist and
like did we not
read Pinker and watch Hans Rosling and
you know those types of things
and
so I want to speak to that briefly
first this is a meta-point
but it's worth saying right now
particularly in on this podcast
and in the kind of post-truth
post or fake fact
world where then so much
of the emphasis has gone into we need fact
checkers and we need real
facts
obviously it's possible
to have an epistemic
error or even intentional error in the
process of generating a fact
is there corruption in the institutions
and that kind of thing but let's even say that wasn't
an issue and the things that go through the right epistemic
process as facts are facts
can you lie with facts
totally can you can you mislead
with facts yeah because nobody
is going to make their choice on one fact
they make their choice based on a situational assessment
based on a narrative based on a gestalt
of a whole thing that's lots of different facts
well which facts do I include and which facts do I not
include and
am I de-contextualizing the fact
so
the quality of life has gone up
so much because we average person lived
on less than a dollar a day in the US in 1815
and now they live on this many dollars
a day which inflation adjusted means higher quality
of life yeah but in 1815 most
of their needs didn't come through dollars
they grew their own vegetables they hunted
so I'm de-contextualizing
the facts to compare something that's really apples
and oranges so even if the fact is quote unquote
true the de-contextualization and
recontextualization makes it seem like it means
something different than it means
and the same with the cherry picking
of facts and I can very easily
say oh there's a lower percentage of people in extreme
poverty but I might also be changing the definitions
of extreme poverty I can also
rather than focus on percentage say well there's more
total people in poverty than there were total people
in the world before the industrial revolution so like
so there's the
abilities to de-contextualize
and recontextualize facts there's the ability to
cherry pick facts and there's
the ability to lake off frame facts
and put particular kinds
of sentiment and moral valence
on it and so am I talking about them as
illegal aliens or undocumented
workers and I get a very different kind
of sentiment so talking about it
as a pre-owned car or a used car
everyone loves a pre-owned car no one wants
a used car and so these
very simple semantic frames
contextual frames cherry picking
of the things means that I can
make a narrative
where all the facts went through the most
rigorous fact checker and yet the narrative
as a whole is misleading
and so fact checking is necessary
but it is not sufficient for a good
epistemic and good sense making and not
only is it not sufficient it's even weaponizable
this is a very important thing
to understand because if you are not
pursuing that
you're if you're not recognizing
that you might be believing
nonsense thinking that you're using
epistemic rigor
okay so the techno pessimists
and the techno optimists both cherry pick
and they both lake off
frame and
this is true with
all the difference in almost every
political ideology the woke and the
woke the
the pro socialist
pro capitalist you'll notice that the way
they do their arguments the
systemic racism is really really terrible
no there's not that bad the systemic racism
they both have stats
but this is actually you can almost think
of it as statistical warfare as a tool
of narrative warfare and
so this is where
a higher level of earnestness
rather than a particular
bested interest or bias a higher willingness
to look at biases a higher level of rigor
you know ends up being critical to
actually overcome any of these things
so
can I cherry pick stats that make it look like everything is getting
better totally those things are true
and nobody wants to go back to a world
before novocaine when you have to do dentistry
and
nobody wants to go back to a world before
penicillin when basic bacterial infections go around
and like there's totally good stuff that has
emerged
and are there all
kinds of
ubiquitous
mental illnesses and
chronic complex disease
that didn't exist before and
increase in the total
number of addictive type behaviors within populations
and
and a radical
increase in the catastrophic risk landscape
and negative effect to environmental metrics
so things are getting better and things are getting worse at the same time
it's important to understand that depending upon what you pick
it's just that the things that are getting worse are heading
towards
tipping points that make the whole thing no longer viable
and so that we're not
denying that there are things that are getting better we're
saying that for the game to continue
at all right to have it
be an infinite game that gets to keep continuing
there are certain things that have to not happen
and you can't have the things that are getting worse keep getting
worse at the curve that they are
and have the things that are getting better be able to
continue at all so I just want to
say that so
naive techno optimism
can actually
make you a part of the problem because
then you do things like develop
a solution to a narrowly
defined problem and externalize harm to other areas
because you weren't taking seriously enough
not doing that
but techno pessimism also
makes you a part of the problem
or at least not a part of the solution because
because the world is the future
is not going to be determined by Luddites
it's not going to be determined by people who aren't developing the tools of power
so if you aren't actually looking at
how do we develop a high
tech world that is also a fundamentally desirable
in terms of a high nature and high touch
world then you really
aren't thinking about it in a way that ends up
mattering and so we are
techno optimist but
not naive techno optimist we go through the
totally cynical phase of man tech
is a serious issue and then you go to a post
cynical phase of
if I want to be techno optimist
and not be silly
what does it take to imagine a world
where humans have that much power
and we are good stewards of it
meaning that we actually tend to each other
well and we don't create a
dystopic world that has
exponential wealth and equality
and an underclass that nobody in the upper class would want to trade places with
and that doesn't cause catastrophic risk
right now the amount
of power of exponential tech
makes two attractors most likely
catastrophic risk
of some kind
or social systems
that do not preserve
the values that we care most about
that are the ones that are currently most
working to develop and deploy that technology
and to just give a very brief
recap of the frame that Tristan
you gave on earlier as you mentioned
China is not leaving 100%
of its technology
development to the market to develop however
it wants even if it harms the nation state
they are happy to bind technology
companies that are getting too large
and in ways that would damage the nation state
as we saw with Ant Corporation
and they are doing a lot of
very centralized innovation
as well
associated with long term planning
long term planning is a key thing
in the US
term limits make long term planning very hard
as does a highly rival risk
two party system that is
willing to damage the
nation as a whole to drive party wins
so in that system
almost all the energy
just goes into trying to win
you spend at least a couple years
but even the years before that are fundraising
creating alliances to just try to win
then you are not going to invest in anything
heavily that has return times
longer than four years because it won't get you re-elected
so no real long term planning
and then
whatever you do do in those four years
will get undone systematically in the next four years
for the most part
that system of governance
will just fail comprehensively
in relationship to a more
to a system that
doesn't have that much internal infighting
and that has
the capacity to do long term planning
and there is a million examples we can look at
but just when did high speed
trains start? they started
we saw them emerge in Europe
we saw them emerge in Japan and in China
we started to export them all around the world
and the US still doesn't have any high speed trains
and it's like what happened?
and we can see
that the US innovated in fundamental
tech in the Manhattan project
kind of through the Apollo project
but then it started to privatize almost everything to the market
the market started to develop in ways that really
were not advancing the technology
in a way that increased the coherence
of the nation
and the fundamental civic values and ideas of the nation
even the World War II thing
increased our military capacities radically
but that didn't mean we actually really advanced the ideas
of democracy or those values of
do we make a better system
to educate the people and inform them
and help them participate in their governance
do we make better governance?
this is why the US military is so powerful
but the US government is so kind of inept
which is why nobody wants to fight a war
with the US, a kinetic war
but it's very easy
right now to
engage in
supporting narrative warfare
where you turn the left and the right against each other
increasingly
and where you do long-term planning
where the US can't do long-term planning of those kinds
so we can see
that the
government of the US
and not just the US but like we can see that
open societies are not innovating
in how to be better open societies
for the most part, more effective ones
where they're using the new tech to make better open societies
that's happening in the market sector
the market is making exponentially
more powerful companies
a company is not a democracy
it's not a participatory governance structure
in general, it's a kind of very top-down
autocratic type system
and so we see that
there's more authoritarian
nation states that are
intentionally doing long-term
planning of the development and deployment of
exponential tech to make better
nation states of that kind
and we can't even blame them
they look at
trying to have the benefit of getting to see both where the USA
failed and where the USSR failed
and try to make something they didn't fail in either of those ways
and there's some things that are very smart about
those approaches
so we see though exponentially empowered
more autocratic type structures
and the emergence of
one natural
monopoly per tech sector
and then the interaction of those that kind of
becomes like oligarchic feudalism
tech feudalism
neither of those
have the types of jurisprudence
or public accountability or whatever
that we're really interested in
so the two attractors right now
is
the emergence of social systems
that are deploying
the exponential tech
that will probably not preserve
the social values that we're interested in
and not be maximally desirable civilizations
probably pretty dystopic ones
or not even guiding it well enough
to prevent catastrophic risk
those are the two major types of attractors
we want a new attractor which is
how do we
utilize the new exponential technologies
the whole suite of them
to build new systems of collective intelligence
new better systems of social technology
how do you make a fourth estate that can really adequately
educate everyone
in a post
Facebook world
well the same way that we're trying to
optimize control patterns
of human behavior for market purposes
to get them to buy certain things
and to direct their attention
could that be used educationally
of course it could if it was being
developed for that purpose
and the AI tech
that can take a bunch of faces
and make a new face that is merged out of those
could it take semantic fields of people's propositions
and values and create a proposition
that is kind of the semantic
center of the space and then could we use
we can't all fit into a town hall
but can we engage in digital
spaces where we can have
better processes of proposing
refinements to the propositions
of course we can, could we use blockchain
and other types of uncorruptible ledgers
to solve corruption which is something that universally
everybody thinks is a good idea
should all government money
be on a blockchain
the movement of it so you have provenance so you can see
where the money is actually going and if someone wants to be
a private contractor
they have to agree that the accounting system
if they want government money
goes on the blockchain so we can see the entire provenance
of the taxpayer money so that
you can't have representation if there isn't
transparency of how it happens
so there's a whole
bunch of when you start to think about
attention directing technology
and what its pedagogical applications could be
when you start to think about
AI and how it could actually help
proposition development
and parsing huge amounts of information to make a better
epistemic commons when you start to think about
blockchain and could we actually resolve corruption
using uncorruptible ledgers and making
the provenance of physical supply chains
and information and money all flow
across those, totally new possibilities
start to emerge
that never emerged before, that were never possible
before
but if it doesn't become our central design imperative
to develop those, those are not
the highest marketed
opportunities for those right now
the highest market opportunity for blockchain is speculative
tokens that have no real utility
and for AI is things that actually
drive ads and purchasing
and you know, on and on
and for attention tech it is the same thing
So you've sold me on the idea that we
have two dystopian attractors
that we don't want and the third
attractor that we're trying to develop
here is some kind of open society
that is consciously using
all the modern technologies
towards the values that we care about
can you give some concrete examples
of what it would look like to
use you know, AI and attention
driving tech and click driving tech
and block chains and all these things
but in a way that would make a stronger, healthier open society
Yeah, totally
So let's say we take
the attention
tech that you've looked at so much
that when it is applied
for a commercial application
it is seeking to gather data
to both maximize time on site
and maximize engagement with certain kinds of ads
and whatever
That's obviously
the ability to
direct human behavior
and direct human feeling
and thought
In a way
that has both emerged out of capitalism
and has become
almost a new macroeconomic structure
more powerful than capitalism
more powerful than being able to
incent people's behavior with money
as being able to direct what they think and feel
to where the thing that they think of
as their own intrinsic motive
has actually been influenced or captured
So
if we
if we wanted to
apply that type of technology
and we figured out how to make
the kind of transparency
that made institutions
that were trustworthy enough
and already we have institutions that have it
that we have no basis to trust with it
could that same
tech be used educationally
to be able to personalize education
to the learning style
of a kid or to an adult to their particular
areas of interest
and to be able to
not
use
the ability to control them
for game-theoretic purposes
but use the ability to influence them
to even help them learn
what makes their own
center
their locus of action more internalized
we could teach people
with that kind of tech
how to notice their own bias
how to notice their own emotional behaviors
how to notice groupthink type dynamics
how to understand propaganda and media literacy
so could we actually use those tools
to increase people's immune system
against bad actors' use of those tools
totally
could we use them pedagogically
in general to be able to identify
rather than manufacturing
desires in people
or appealing to the lowest angels of their nature
because addiction is profitable
can you appeal to the highest
angels in people's nature
but that are aligned with intrinsic incentives
and be able to
create customized educational programs
that are based on what each person is actually
innately intrinsically motivated by
but that are their higher innate motivators
everybody can have a reward circuit
that is based on
you know chocolate cake and sloth
but the immediate spike
that comes from the chocolate cake
ends up then having a crash
and increased weight and inflammation
and whatever where the baseline of their happiness
goes down over time
even though every time they eat the chocolate cake they get a spike
the exercise reward circuit is maybe
not that fun maybe even kind of painful
and dreadful in the moment
but then creates a higher baseline
of energy and capacity
and endurance and self-esteem
and you start to actually have the process become
more fun you get a new reward circuit
and the baseline goes up
so of course I can appeal to the lower reward
circuit and say hey I'm just giving people
what they want
but if you have a billion dollar
or a trillion dollar organization
that is preying upon them
and you discuss this very well all the time
the vulnerabilities that make people's life
worse to then have the plausible deniability
to say yeah but they wanted it
but it was a manufactured demand
and a vulnerability where's the no bless
oblige where's the obligation
of having that much power to actually be
a good steward of power a steward of that
for other people where if there are
reward circuits that decrease the quality
of their life reward circuits that increase
that we're trying to appeal to one rather than the other
could we do that yeah totally we could
could we have an education system as a result
that was identifying innate
aptitudes innate interests
of everyone and facilitating
their development so not only did they
become
good at something but they became increasingly
more intrinsically motivated fascinated
and passionate by life
which also meant continuously better at the thing
well in a world of
increasing technological automation
coming up both robotic and AI automation
where so many of the jobs are about to be
obsolete
our economy
and our education system
have to radically change to deal with that
because
the core of like one of the core
things an economy has been trying to do forever
was
deal with the need that a society had
for a labor force
and that there were these jobs that society
needed to get done that nobody would really want to do
so either the state has to force them to do it
or
you have to make it to where the people also need the job
so there's a cemetery and so kind of the market
forces them to do it well when you technologically
automate those jobs and it happens
to be that the things that are the most
wrote are the least fun for people
and the easiest to program machines to do
and
so
if you keep the same economy
where if people don't produce
they don't have any basic needs met
then people want
those crappy jobs right
but if you make it to where they have other
opportunities then of course
having those jobs be automated is fine
but what does it mean to really be able to have
other better opportunities
so
if one of the fundamental like
axioms
of all of our economic theories
is that we need to figure out how to
incent a labor force to do things that nobody
wants to do
and emerging technological automation starts to
debase that
that means we have to rethink economics from scratch
because we don't have to do that thing anymore
so maybe if now the jobs don't need the people
that need the jobs can we start to create
commonwealth resources that everyone has access to
where people's access
isn't based on possession
that automatically limits everyone else's access
if you get around
transportation wise with a car
based on owning that car
where the vast majority of the life of the car
it's just sitting not being used
for you to have access to the car you have to have
possession of it which means that it's a
mostly underutilized asset I don't have
access to the thing that you possess
now what we see with Uber of course is a situation
where your access
is not mediated by your possession
so now turn that into electric
self-driving cars and now make the entire
thing on a blockchain so you disintermediate
even the central business make it a commonwealth
resource and everyone has access to
transportation as a commonwealth resource
it'll take a 20th of the number of cars
to meet the same level
of convenience during peak demand time
so much less environmental harm
it'll actually be more convenient because I don't
have to be engaged in driving the thing
and there's less traffic because of the coordination
and better maintenance and there isn't a desire
for an incentive for designed
an obsolescence in that system
you can see a situation where
can we make it to where
the wealth augmenting capacity
of that technologic automation goes back
into a commonwealth because we don't have to
have the same axioms of needing to incend the people
oh yeah but if you don't incend the people
they'll all be lazy welfare people
nonsense
Einstein didn't do what he did based on
economic incentive and
neither did Mozart and neither did Gandhi
and none of the people that we
are most inspired by through history
were doing that
and what kids will
who will spend so much
time doing where they ask questions
about why this why this why this
and building forts and whatever is intrinsic motive
it's just we don't facilitate
the things that they're interested in
we try to force them to be interested in things
that's what ends up breaking their interest in life
and then they just want a hypernormal stimuli
and play video games whatever
what if you had a system that was facilitating
their interest the entire time
now you have a situation where you can start to
decrease the total amount of extrinsic
incentive in the system as a whole
use the technology
to the automation to decrease
the need for extrinsic incentive
and make an educational system
and culture that's about optimizing intrinsic
incentive because if my needs are already
met getting stuff there's no
and everybody's needs are met through access
to commonwealth resources there's no real status
conferred that there's only status
conferred by what I create so now there is a
any status is bound to a kind of creative
imperative that's an example
we can look at blockchain
tech even more near term and say
but
but just to come back to this technological
automation thing so obviously it makes possible
changing economics and changing education
but also
what is the role of humans
in a
post AI robotic automation world
because that is coming very very soon
and what is the future of
education where you don't have to prepare
people to be
things that you can just program computers
to be
well the role of education has to be based on
what is the role of people in that world
that is such a deep redesign of civilization
because the tech is changing
the possibility set that deeply
so at the heart of this are kind of
deep existential questions of what is a meaningful
human life and then what is a good civilization
that increases the possibility
space of that for everybody and how do we design
that thing we come back to
blockchain and we say
well blockchain is an uncorruptible ledger
well
one thing that the left and right and everybody
agrees on is that we did corruption
happens and it's bad for the societies
at home we don't like it we just disagree
on who does it
is it possible
that that tech could
make possible decreasing
corruption as a whole
it actually decreases the possibility set for corruption
yeah in order to do corruption
I have to be able to hide that I did it
right I either have to
to break enforcement or break accounting and mostly
it's break accounting
and so what if
all government spending was on a blockchain
and doesn't have to be a blockchain
it has to be an uncorruptible ledger of some kind
all a chain is a good example
that is pioneering another way of doing it
but uncorruptible ledger of some kind
where you actually see
where all taxpayer money goes and you see how
it's utilized the entire thing and have independent
auditing agencies and the public can transparently
be engaged in the auditing of it
and if the government
is going to privately contract a corporation
the corporation agrees
that if they want that government money
the blockchain accounting has to extend
into the corporation so there can't be
very very
bloated corruption everybody got to see
that when Elon made
SpaceX all of a sudden he was making
rockets for like a hundreds to a thousands
of the price that Lockheed or Boeing were
who had just had these almost monopolistic government
contracts for a long time
well if the taxpayer money
is going to the government
is going to an external private contractor
who's making the things for a hundred to a thousand
times more than it costs
we get this false dichotomy sold to us that
either
we have to pay more taxes
to have better national security
or if we want to cut taxes
we're going to have less national security
what about just having less gruesome
bloat because you have better accounting
and we make the rockets for a hundredth
of the price and we have better national
security and better social services and less
taxes well that's
everyone would vote for that right
who wouldn't vote for that thing well that wasn't
possible before uncorruptible ledgers
also means you can have provenance
on supply chains to make the supply
chains closed loop so that you can see
that all the new stuff is being made from old stuff
and you can see where all the pollution is going and you can see
who did it which means you can now internalize
the externalities rigorously
and nobody can destroy those
emails or burn those files right
what if
the changes
in law and
the
decision-making processes
also followed a
blockchain process where there was a provenance
on the input of information well that would also
be a very meaningful thing to be able to
follow so
this is an example of like can we actually
structurally remove
the capacity for corruption
by technology that makes
corruption much much much harder that forces
types of transparency on auditability
what if also
you're able to record history
you're able to record the events that are occurring
in a blockchain that's uncruptible where you can't change history later
so you actually get
the possibility of real justice and real history
and multiple different simultaneous timelines
that are happening that's humongous
in terms of what it does
what if you can
have an open data platform
and an open science platform where
someone doesn't get to cherry pick which data
they include in their peer reviewed paper later
we get to see all of the data that was happening
we solve the oracle issues that are associated
and then if we find out that a particular
piece of science was wrong later we can see
downstream everything that used
that output as an input and automatically
flag what things need to change
that's so
powerful like the least
interesting example
of blockchain is currency creation
these are actually
like
the capacity for the right types of
accounting means the right type of choice making
right let's take AI
with AI we can make
super terrible deep fakes and destroy
the epistemic commons you know using that
and other things like that
but we can see
the way that the AI makes the deep fake by
being able to take enough different images of
the person's face and movements that it can generate
new ones we can see where it can generate totally
new faces averaging faces together somebody
sent me some new work that they were just doing on this
the other day I found very interesting they said
we're going to take a very similar type of tech and apply
it to semantic fields where
we can take everybody's sentiment on a topic
and actually generate
a proposition that is at the semantic
center or take everybody's
sentiment and abstract from it the
values that they care about and create
values taxonomies and say
we should come up with a proposition that meets
all these values then
can you have digital processes where you can't fit
everybody into
into a
town hall but everybody who wants
to can participate in a digital space
that rather than vote
yes or no on a proposition that was made by a
special interest group where we didn't have a say
in the proposition or even the values it was seeking
to serve so it was made in a very
narrow way that like we mentioned earlier
benefits one thing and harms something else which is
why
almost every proposition gets about half of the
vote and inherently polarizes the
population well people are so
dumb and so rival risk the process of voting
with
bad propositions and
and bad representation
process is inherently polarizing
and downgrading to people so
what if there's a process by which there's
a decision that wants to be made you start
by identifying what are the values everybody cares
about and then we say the
first proposition that meets all these
values well becomes the
thing that we vote on and then instead of just
a direct vote do we engage
types of qualified and liquid democracy
together where you have to show that you understand
the basics of
that topic to be able to vote on it
but the education is free and you can keep retesting
and the basics don't show leaning one way or the
other just shows you understand the stated pros and
cons so that massive populism
doesn't happen but if
you don't want to come to understand it you can seed
your vote to someone else who has passed that thing
these are that type of liquid
democracy that type of qualified
educated democracy where it doesn't have to
be educated across everything it can be per
issue and where you're not just voting
on a thing you're helping craft the propositions
these completely change
the possibility space of social technology
and we can go on and on in terms of
examples but these are ways
that the same type
of new emergent physical tech
that can destroy the epistemic
commons and create autocracies and create catastrophic
risks could also be used
to realize a much
more
pro-topic world
so I love so many of those
examples and I especially on
the blockchain and corruption one because
I think as you said something
the left and the right can both agree on is that
our systems are not really functional and there's
definitely corruption and defection going on
and just to add to your example
imagine if citizens could even earn money
by spotting inefficiencies or corruption
in that transparent ledger
so that we actually have a system that is
actually profiting
by getting more and more efficient over time
and actually better serving the needs of the people
and having less and less corruption and so there's
definitely more trust and faith and that's actually
a kind of digital society
that when you look at let's say the closed
China's digital authoritarian society
and you look at this open one that's actually operating
more for the people with more transparency
with more efficiencies you get more
SpaceX Elon Musk type cheap
ways of sending rockets to the moon and becoming a multi-planetary
civilization as opposed to
more bloat and more mega monopolies
defense contractors that are not taking us
to where we need to go
that's just an inspiring vision and I just hope
you share it and kind of go back because there's a lot
of different aspects there
I think the question on many people's mind right now
is going to be
how do we get from where we are
to the world that you are talking about
what are the steps that are in between
obviously I don't know
nobody knows
there's gonna like
which projects emerge
and
first and start really making success
that there's a lot of different
possible paths
I can say some of the things
that could happen and some of the things
that I think need to happen
so we take all the catastrophic
risks that exponential tech
makes possible and the dystopic attractors
and we say okay so we need to solve all those
problems but we're not doing
really good at solving those problems right now
so our problem solving processes need upgraded
and that means new
institutions
and when we say
institution we usually think of a pretty centralized
thing and with things like decentralized
governance emerging
the institution might be a decentralized one
but it's individual
people aren't going to solve all of that right
so it's new institution
centralized and decentralized that have the right
capacities to solve these types of problems
need to come about
alright well who develops those
institutions and who empowers them
and this is where
the democratic idea of
the
power of government coming from the
consent of the governed
is one of the key ideas to what
we would think of as the values of an open
society let's say that there's a small
number of people who think we understand these
problems we understand the solutions that must happen
everybody else doesn't get it so we're going to make this
thing happen and because we have the power we can
just kind of implement it by force and so
that becomes
its own dystopia right
and implement it by force might be well the people think
they need to be free so we'll implement it
by attention hijacking them so that they
participate with it or
don't even realize that it's happening and they just
keep doing whatever is next
the cultural element why we talk
about the need for a new cultural enlightenment
is
of course when we look at like the founding
of the US we can see all that was
super wrong with it right
just to mention like how when Churchill said
democracy is the worst form of government ever
saved for all the other forms
there's when when Socrates
talked about in
in the republic when Plato was
discussing it why
democracy was a dreadful idea
the arguments are good arguments right like
do you want
people who understand
seafaring to man the boat or just a general
population who knows nothing about it to man the boat
well that's not a very good idea do you want the general
population that knows nothing about it to build the NASA
rocket or do you want people that know what they're doing
well why would we think people who have no idea what
they're doing are going to be good at figuring out
how a civilization should be run what should
our nuclear first strike policy should be how should
we deal with the stability of the energy grid
against Carrington events
and so what does it take
to have a population educated enough
and yet then if we say okay
but then the other
problem is if we say the people are
too uneducated and maybe
too irrational and rival risk to be able
to hold that power so it needs to be held by
some how do we ensure non-corruption and
who is a trust
worthy authority to be
able to hold that power and not have vested
interest mess it up and so this is why I
think it was a Jefferson quote of
the ultimate
depository of the power must be the people and if
we think the people too uneducated not enlightened
to be able to hold that power
we must do everything we can to seek to
educate and lighten them not think that there
is any other safe depository
and so
even with that
we take the
US formation and
you've got some founders
who
had read most of the books of the time
read most of the books of philosophy knew the history
of the Magna Carta and the Treaty of the Forest
and all these kinds of things thought and talked deeply
spent many years were willing to die
fighting a revolutionary war were not
going along with winning at the current system
but really trying to do a fundamentally different thing
to develop a new system
not everybody who was participating in the US
was doing that thing they weren't all doing systems
architecture right
but they were all basically
saying
we agree to this kind of systems
architecture and we want to
learn how to participate with it adequately
will read a newspaper we will do a
jury duty will come to the town hall that kind of
thing so
um
in Taiwan's example I think their population
is 23 million people in their
online citizen engagement platform has something
like 5 million people engaging
that's pretty awesome right that's not everybody
and no one should be forced to be engaging
and one of the critical things
when we think deeper about is it a democracy
is it a republic
is it a epistocracy is it a
um we want to think about
the values not the previous
frames for them and the values exist
in dialectics and we need to be able to hold those
together of course we want individual liberty
but we don't want individual liberty that gets to harm
other people and other things so we want
also you know law justice collective
integrity how do you relate those things
one of the core things is the relationship between
rights and responsibilities so
there
if I have rights and I don't have
responsibilities there ends up
being like tyranny and entitlement
if I and we can see
that that's kind of rampant the entitlement
thing if I have responsibilities
and I don't have any attendant rights
at servitude neither of those
involve a healthy just society so
if I want the right
to drive a car the responsibility
to do the driver's education and actually
learn how to drive a car safely is important and we
can see that some countries have less car
accidents than others associated with better
drivers education um and so
increasing the responsibilities a good
thing we can see that some countries
have way less gun violence than others
even factoring a similar per capita
amount of guns based on more training
associated with guns and mental health
and things like that
so if I have a right to bear arms
do I also have a responsibility
to be part of a well organized militia
train with them and be willing to actually sacrifice
myself to protect the whole or
sign up for a thing to do that to have to be a
reservist of some kind those are the right
responsibility if I want the right to vote
is there a responsibility to be educated
about the issue
yes yes now
does that make it very unequal no
because the capacity
to get educated has to be something that the
society invests in making possible for
everyone and of course we would all be
silly to not
be dubious factoring the previous
history of these things but this is what we then
have to insist upon because do we want
people who really
don't understand the issues but think they do
voting now that's a dreadful system
but do we want people who know
something to have no avenue or who care
do we want people who know something to have
no avenue to input that into the system or
people who care to have no opportunity
to learn no that's also dreadful
so how do we make the on-ramps to learning
available for everyone not enforced
but we're actually incentivizing
can we use those same kind of social media
behavior and sending technologies to increase
everyone's desire for more rights
and attendant responsibilities
so that there's actually a gradient
of civic virtue and civic engagement
yeah we could totally do that
so this is where the cultural enlightenment
layer is of course not everyone is going to
be working on how do we develop AI
and blockchain for these purposes
but they can certainly be saying I am going
to make sure that my representatives are talking
about these issues I want all the
presidential candidates to be talking about these issues
I'm going to pay attention to and support
candidates who really do in earnest ways
I'm going to invest in
companies that are doing those things I'm going to
invest from companies that are doing the other things
there is a cultural
enlightenment that is needed
to be able to create the
demand and the support for
where those projects
that are earnestly working on and have
the capability start to emerge
so you've painted
a compelling vision of
some of the ways that a open
society could consciously employ
some of these technologies to
revisit and
re-fulfill some of the original
values for which they were intended
how much of this
how does this work with the
existing institutions that we have how much is
this going to rely on
transforming the existing
digital Leviathans into something new
how much is going to depend on blockchain projects
how much is going to depend on
existing institutions would be the Brookings
institution or
the New York Times can you speak
to the role of new
and future institutions in making this transition
possible
yeah
it's interesting
when we look at institutions that emerged
to try to solve some social
or environmental problems or nonprofits
in particular and some government branches
that are associated
with that there's this kind of structural
perverse incentive
that if I
am an organization which means
I'm people in an organization
that
have some that have job security
and some actual power and access and whatever
because of this position
and my job is to solve a problem
if I fully solve the problem I would obsolete my job
and obsolete myself so then there's this kind of
perverse incentive to continue managing
the problem continue manufacturing the narrative
that we're needed to manage the problem continue
manufacturing the narrative that the problem
is really hard and is hard to solve and so we got
to keep doing this thing
and so one of the fundamental
dispositions of systems is that
they want to keep existing and
so and yet they might
no longer be fit for purpose they might even be
antithetical to the purpose we have to be very
careful about this
with regard to
the new institutions we need to what degree could
existing institutions reform
themselves to what degree does it need to be new ones
it's kind of up to them like it's kind of
up to the the depth of
realization of the need and the
sincerity and then the coordination capacity of
people in current institutions
how much role they could play we can
see the way that going into World
War II coming out of the depression the U.S.
up-regulated its
coordination capacity so profoundly
so could we
have a Manhattan project like level
organization
by organization
I mean
the
capacity to organize not a
singular thing
that was oriented
to how do we
instantiate the next model
of civilization how do we instantiate the next model
of social systems and social technologies
what is the future of education what's the future of economics
what's the future of
the fourth estate of law etc
that are
that fulfill the values
that are meaningful and are antifragile
in the presence of the current technologies
and they can actually compete with the other applications
of those technologies towards
things that serve different values
and or aren't antifragile
I would
love to see the U.S.
make that a
central imperative Manhattan project level
to be able to do that not just how do we create a more
powerful military but how do we create
a more powerful a
healthier fundamentally a healthier
society that up regulates
and engages collective intelligence
in its own problem solving and innovation better
I would like to see lots
of countries do that I think there are countries
that did
not yet transition to democracy
are interested in it and completely bypass
the industrial era democracies
and go directly to better systems
I think networks
of small countries you see what Taiwan
is doing Estonia is trying to do some interesting
things I think networks of small countries could start
sharing best practices and sharing
resources so they don't all have to develop the stuff from
scratch which could start to lead
to coalitions of countries like the EU
saying let's do some fundamentally better
things I think
it will happen also not at the level of nation
states were like
decentralized groups blockchain
type groups say all right let's
really earnestly take on what these primary
problems are and work on developing
these solutions these capacities
for the tech companies
to do so would be very hard because
while
it could be
still
profitable
long term it would not be profit
maximizing short term relative
to the current thing they're doing as we said
winning at the current game
and building a new game are different things
and winning at a current game that self
terminating is a very short sighted thing
to want to keep doing so
if Facebook or Google or whatever
were to cut its ad model
it would have a hard time being able to meet
its fiduciary responsibility to shareholders a different
way but could it
in conjunction with
a
participatory
government regulatory process that wanted
to help change its fiduciary
responsibility
where it became more of a social utility
start to actually redirect its technology
and redirect its decision making process
yeah it could and that would be super interesting
so
I would like to see
as we mentioned earlier I'd like to see the UN
recognize that the
level of progress that it has made
at
the sustainable development goals, nuclear
deproliferation and other types of
international things like
economic equality
globally writ large
and
preventing arms races and tragedy of the commons that
well it hasn't done nothing
what it's doing is not converging
it's not adequate, it's not converging on
eventually solving the problem set
just more of that approach, it needs a different approach
and so to say
clearly we don't know how to facilitate
coordination of global problems well enough
so let's have the superseding focus
be innovation towards better methods of global
coordination, that becomes our new number one
goal
because we know we only get all the other goals if we get that
and you can see that during World War II
when we had to crack the enigma machine
and figure out
computation and whatever
we got touring, we got von Neumann
one of the smartest people from
countries all around the world
engaged in solving those problems
I would like to see the US, the UN
I would like to see other countries and I would like to see private sector
taking seriously the actual
problemscape we have
and innovating not for
just short-term advantage or narrow
in-group advantage
but for long-term
advantage of the whole, how do we
since we have global effect
global coordination adequate to what is needed
to me that has to become
the central zeitgeist
and whatever groups figure out how to do it
effectively will be the groups
that can direct the future
and I know that this is the work
that you are working towards with the conciliance project
do you want to talk
just about how you are working towards that
with your work and how we are collaborating?
yeah, I mean we are
we are at the very very beginning
the conciliance project
has a site up that is not even
a beta yet
because we
in just starting wanted to
work on building stuff
in association with thinking
but this talk is very
central, this conversation you and I are having is very central to the aims of the conciliance project
which is
we are wanting to
inspire, inform and help
direct a innovation zeitgeist
where
the many different problems of the world
start to get seen in terms of
having interconnectivity
and underlying drivers
and the forcing function
of the power of exponential tech
is taken seriously that says in order to become
good stewards of that requires
evolutions of both our social
systems and our culture
the wisdom to be able to guide
that power, a recoupling
of wisdom and power in that
adequate to what is needed
so how do we innovate in culture
the development of people
and how do we innovate in the social systems
the advancement of our coordination
both employing the exponential tech
and being able to rightly guide it
and so
we have
a really great team of people that are
doing research
and writing basically the types
of things we are talking about here in more depth explaining
what is the role of
the various social systems like what is the role of education
to any society help understand
fundamentally what that is
understand why there is
a particularly higher educational
threshold for open societies where people
need to participate not just in the
market but in governance
understand how that has been disrupted
by the emerging tech and will be disrupted further
by things like technological automation
and then envision what is the future
of education adequate to an open
society in a world that has the
technology that's emerging
and we don't necessarily know what the answer is
but we know examples and we know criteria
so then it's like innovate in this area
and make sure you factor these criteria
and the same thing with the fourth estate the same thing with law
the same thing with economics
and so the goal is not how do we take
some small group of people to build the future
it's how do we help get
what the criteria of a viable future
must be and if people disagree awesome
publicly disagree and have the conversation now
but if we get to put out those design constraints
someone says no we think it's other ones
the center of culture starts to be thinking about
the most pressing issues
in fundamental ways and how to think about them
appropriately and how to approach them appropriately
so fundamentally our goal
is
supporting an increased
cultural understanding of the nature of the
problems that we face a clearer understanding
rather than just there's lots of problems and it's overwhelming
and it's a bummer and so
either some very narrow
action on some very narrow part
of it makes sense just most of activism
or just nihilism
we want to be able to say actually
because there are underlying drivers
there is actually a possibility
to resolve these things
it does require the fullness of our capacity
applied to it
and with the fullness of our capacity so it's not a
given but with the fullness of our capacity applied to it
there is actually a path forward
and
so we're writing these papers
that basically would be kind of like
a meta-curriculum
for people who want to be engaged in designing the future
and
some of them have to do with current
public culture and how to be able to
change patterns of public culture that lead to
better conversation, better sense
making, better meaning making and choice making
so that there's an on-ramp into higher quality
conversations meaning higher quality process of
conversation and then some of them are things
like what are the design criteria
of the future social systems and how could
we build those things then
not everybody will read those
some people who
have the ability to help start building them
will but
we hope that other people will
take that and translate it on podcasts
and into animations and in
whatever other forms of media
so that those topics start
to become increasingly
present in people's awareness
then of course
the next part is what groups start
emerging wanting to address those
and what can we do to help facilitate
good solutions in those groups
and this is where you and I
I've learned a lot from you about
the
social media issues in particular and how
central they are to the breakdown of sense making
because obviously without good shared sense making
there is no possibility for emergent order
you either just get chaos or you have to
have imposed order if you want emergent
order that means emergent good choice making
that means emergent good sense making
and so
we've learned a lot and discussed these things for a long time
and obviously also not just you and I
there's a whole network of people that we're connected to
that have been thinking deeply about these things
that we continue to
try to think about what
adequate solutions could look like
and
I think what
CHT did with the social dilemma
took
one really critical part of this metacrisis
into popular attention
in a more powerful way than I have seen done
otherwise because as big a deal
is getting climate change and public attention is
it's not clear that
climate change is something that is making
that is driving
the underlying basis of all the problems
but a breakdown in sense making and a control
of patterns of human behavior that kind of downgrade
people like oh wow that really does make all these
other things worse
so I see that as a
as a very powerful and personal
on-ramp for those who are interested
to be able to come into
this deeper conversation
and some
of them it'll simply help them
be like okay now I know
what I was intuitively feeling somebody's put it
into words and I at least feel more oriented
and that's the extent because they don't necessarily
have the ability to build new blockchain systems
or whatever it is and they should be
doing the nursing or education or whatever really
other important social value they're doing
some people
will be able to say this actually really resonates
I can translate this to other audiences
and get more people engaged and some people say
I can actually start innovating and working with this stuff
and all of those are good
yeah I
I agree and I think
what we've essentially been
outlining here and you sort of hit it at the end
is going back to the Charles Kettering
quote which I learned from you
and I've learned so many things from you over the years
which is
that a problem not fully
understood is unsolvable
and a problem that is fully understood is half
solved and I just want to maybe
leave our listeners with that which is
I think people can look at the
long litany of problems and
feel overwhelmed or get to despair
in a hurry I think is your phrase for it
and I think that
when you understand the core generator functions
for what is driving
so many of these problems to happen simultaneously
there's a different
and more empowering relationship to that
and you've actually offered a vision
for how technology can be consciously employed
these new technologies can be consciously employed
in ways that should feel inspiring and exciting
I mean I want that transparent blockchain
on a budget for every country in the world
and we can see examples like Estonia and Taiwan
moving in this direction already
and we can see Taiwan building some of the technologies
you mentioned to identify
propositions of shared values between citizens
who want to vote collectively on something that
obviously would have driven up more polarization
so we're seeing this thing emerging
and I think what we need is to
sort of have this be seen as
a necessary upgrade to
let me do that again
I think we need to see this as
not just an upgrade but
the kind of cultural enlightenment that you speak of
that so many different actors are in a sense
already working on you know we used to
have this phrase that everyone is on the same team
they just don't know it yet
and once you understand the
degree to which we are in trouble
if we do not get our heads around
this and identify the kind of
core generator functions that we need to be addressing
once we all see that
I'll just speak to my own
experience when I first encountered your work
and I encountered
the kind of core drivers
that drive so much of the danger
that we are headed towards
I
immediately
I was kind of already in this direction already
reoriented my whole life to say
how do we be in service if this is not happening
and of creating a better world
that actually meets and addresses these problems
and I know so many other people
whose work
and whose lives and whose daily missions
and purpose have been redirected
by I think hearing some of the core
frames that you offer
and who I hope
and who are many of whom are already working on
active projects to deal with this and those who are not
are supporting in other ways
and I hope that our audience takes this as
an inspiration
for how can we in the face of
stark and difficult realities
as part of this process
gain the kind of cultural
strength to face these things head on
and to orient our lives accordingly
because I have
while bearing periods of time
hit probably low grade despair
myself
I actually feel more inspired than ever
the amount of things and the number of people
who face these challenges
and I'll just say that
I think when you face these challenges alone
and you feel like you're the only one seeing them
or you have a weird feeling in your stomach
it can feel debilitating
and when you realize the number of people
who are also putting their heads up to say
how can we change this
that's what feels hopeful
and that's where I derive my optimism
so Daniel thank you so much for coming on
it's an honor to have you
your work has touched the lives
who may not always say so publicly
but I know that you
had also a huge hand in
inspiring some of the themes that emerged
in the social dilemma which has impacted so many people
as well so thank you so much
really wonderful that we get to have this conversation
thanks just on
absolutely