Yes. Okay, great. So, yeah, let me start by thanking the organizers
for the opportunity to present my work. It's actually the first time that I'm attending
this conference and I must say that I really enjoyed it. I enjoyed a lot of talks for the
past three days. So thank you for having me here. My name is Bata Ziawin and I'm a PhD student at
the International Center for Fury of Quantum Technologies at the University of Gdańsk in
Poland. And we have a Quantum Foundations group here. The leader of the group is Anna
Bellin-Sainz and as you can see she's also a collaborator on this work as well as David
Schmidt and Mati Homan. So today I will talk about quantifying EPR, the Resource Fury of
Non-Classicality of Common Cause Assemblages. We recently put this draft on our archive so
if you find what I will be talking about interesting you can of course ask me questions
but I also encourage you to look at the paper. Okay, so let me start with a question.
Is quantum steering spooky action at a distance? Because it is sometimes called this way. So the
steering phenomena is a form of non-classical correlations that arise when one considers
measurements performed on half of a bipartite system prepared on an entangled state. So if we
try to represent the situation graphically we end up with a picture like this. Here the double lines
correspond to quantum systems and single lines correspond to classical systems. So we have
we have two parties, we have Alice and we have Bob and they share entangled states. Alice prepares
measurement on it so this represents a measurement device that takes a classical input x and outputs
classical variable a and now depending on x and a on Alice's side Bob's system can be described
by this conditional quantum state row a given x. So why is it sometimes called spooky action at a
distance? Well it is because Alice and Bob are two space-like separated parties but it seems that
Alice can somehow steer Bob's system into this conditional state. So the term steering was
actually given by Schrodinger himself and he called it that because from this scenario it kind
of seems that maybe Alice has an influence on what's happening in Bob's laboratory. But this is
not the only perspective that we can take when we talk about this scenario and a different one was
endorsed actually by EPR themselves so by Einstein Podolski and Rosen in their original work and it
is that simply Alice updates her knowledge of the state of Bob's system by performing a measurement
on a system correlated with his and of course it makes perfect sense that Alice and Bob shared
a correlated system so when Alice learned something about it she also updates her knowledge on what's
happening in Bob's laboratory. So is steering spooky action at a distance? Well not really it's
neither spooky or action at a distance and because of this throughout this presentation I will not
refer to this phenomenon as steering but simply as EPR scenario where again EPR stands for Einstein
Podolski and Rosen. So well we could say that it's just a change of name and maybe from a technical
perspective well it doesn't make much difference but from the foundational perspective it actually
makes a huge difference how we look at this scenario. So let me just recap everything that
I just said so from Schrödinger point of view he called this phenomenon quantum steering
in a sense that quantum because he thought that quantum state is a physical property of a system
and then the fact that Alice steers Bob means that there is some kind of supergluminar causal
influence. So in the modern language we would call a set of beliefs that see ontic view which basically
means that this quantum states describe distinct physical states of the world. While what EPR
interpreted it as they said well spooky action at a distance is not really acceptable so quantum
state we can take it to be a representation of one's information about the system and then in
this scenario Alice simply learns about true state of Bob's system and this point of view
could be described in the modern language as epistering sorry which is basically that quantum
states represent states of knowledge about the world. Okay so after this foundational
motivation let me go into the actual resource theory. Okay so we will talk about EPR scenarios
and what we take to be the defining features of an EPR scenario are the following. First
common cause causal structure so as I said we have two parties Alice and Bob and they share a
common cause which in this case is quantum and the second defining feature of this scenario are
types of systems that parties have access to so on Alice's side it will be a classical input
and a classical output while on Bob's side it will be a trivial input because he has no input at all
and a quantum output. And it's very usual to describe EPR scenarios with quantum assemblages
so a quantum assemblages assemblage is an object like this where each conditional state
contains information about what's going on on Alice's side so this probability distribution of
obtaining an outcome A given an input X and what's happening on Bob's laboratory so this conditional state.
Okay so we want to create a resource theory of assemblages. Resource theories allow one to
formally quantify physical resources so in our case the resources are assemblages and what we
want to quantify is their non-classic quality. The structure of a resource theory is completely
determined by the set of three operations so three operations are operations that cannot
create a resourceful object and because of this they can also be applied to different resources
for free because if we apply a free operation to the resource it will not increase the resourcefulness
of it. And now for the case of assemblages our upload follows the recent developments of resource
theories for studying non-classicality of common cost processes wherein the three operations are
local operations and shared randomness so as I said an EPR scenario is simply a common cost
process and because of this we take a lesson from some papers that were already published
common cost processes are studied with LOSR operations and in particular there is this
paper here that basically creates a new branch of entanglement LOSR entanglement in contrast
to LOCC entanglement where CC stands for classical communication and that people usually talk about
and in this paper it is shown that taking this LOSR perspective actually resolves some anomalies
of entanglement and there is also this paper here which treats common cost boxes so things like
Bell's scenario where we have a common cost structure again but here both parties just
have access to classical inputs and classical outputs and because we can study both entanglement
and bell types scenarios using LOSR it means that we can also study their interplay which is really
amazing because it means that we can have like one unified resource theory of common cost processes
with different types of resources like entanglement bell boxes or assemblages and we can study
their relative non-classicality. I would also recommend this paper if you are interested in
this stuff because it talks about a type independent resource theory which considers even more types
than just entanglement assemblages and bell boxes. In the literature it was pretty well
motivated to study LOSR for common cost processes but even from simply looking at the DPR scenario
well we can see that it is a common cost process so we have two parties it's perfectly fine to
allow local operations for each of the parties local operations can be classical or quantum
it there will be quantum on both side and because we want to study the non-classicality
of assemblages we do allow classical common causes for free so what you can see on this picture here
on the right is an assemblage where the common cost is classical so Alice gets a classical
variable lambda and she performs her measurement while Bob prepares a quantum state depending
on the value of the classical variable and we call such assemblage a free assemblage because it
can be created solely by free operations so LOSR operations and it can be decomposed like this
so on Alice's side we just have this probability distribution where lambda is the short variable
and on Bob's side he prepares this quantum state. So for now I'll just mention that there are also
different approaches to studying non-classicality of assemblages and there is one resource theory
that was developed a few years ago that the set of the free operations in this resource theory
was the hasty one-way classical communication and local operations and after I'll introduce
our approach the LOSR one I will compare it to the previous one but I'll do it later on in my
presentation. Okay so what are these LOSR operations here in black we have the original
assemblage and now the most general LOSR operation that we can perform on it as first analysis side
we have a classical prep processing of this classical variable we have a classical post
processing of the output variable on Bob's side we have this post processing of his quantum state
so this will be just a CPTP map and now the actions of of local operations on Alice's side
and the local operation on Bob's side can be correlated by shared randomness so classical
common cause so this will be the lambda that's distributed to Alice and to Bob. Okay so now that
we have a resource theory and we have the set of free operations we can study the properties of the
preorder so we can study the relative non-classicality of assemblages and what we showed is that
assemblage conversion under LOSR can be tested using a single instance of a semi-definite program
so one assemblage is said to be more non-classical than another if it can be fairly converted to
the latter so if we have the black assemblage and we can convert it into a different one the one
with primes with free operations well it means that they can be used for example for the same task
because they have this one will be at least as non-classical as this one
so we showed that checking such conversions can be tested by checking if the following program is
feasible so I have the semi-definite program here but maybe let me not go into details about it
if any of you is like interested in the details I can just we can talk about it later doing the
questions but the important lesson here is that how this program works is that you just input
two assemblages and it tells you what there one can be converted into the other and it works really
fast it's just a single instance so it's really amazing because it's a great tool to study the
relative non-classicality of assemblages and we use this to study the structure of the preorder
and one interesting result that we found is an infinite family of incomparable resources so resources
that none of them can be converted into any other and this family goes like as follows so what we
checked is that we had in scenario where we have Alice and Bob and they shared this state here so
they share a partially entangled state now Alice performs sigma z and sigma x measurements on it
so such an assemblage would be described like this so Alice performs this measurement Bob does
nothing and they share this partially entangled state but now something else that we allow is
mixing with noise so the assemblage that we study is defined here so it's parameter parameter
randomized by these two parameters theta and p where theta corresponds to this theta here in
the partially entangled states and p corresponds to the level of mixing with noise so you can see
here that with some probability we create this element of the assemblage and then we mix it with
noise and now the results of the program that I just showed you are presented in this graph here
so here each dot corresponds to one assemblage so for example this one is an assemblage created
where Alice and Bob share a state with theta being equal to pi over four so it's a so-called
maximally entangled state and they don't mix it with noise because p is equal to one and now the
arrow from here to here means that under LOS operations we can covert this assemblage to this
one where this one is when Alice and Bob share a state with theta being equal to pi over 12
and they mix it with noise with this p being equal to 0.9 so as you can see we can like
using the sdp we can check whether different converters are possible but one interesting
property that we can see here is in this family here so for p being equal one for different
values of theta no conversions are possible and we actually we checked it analytically
and we showed that this is the family of incomparable resources so for all values of theta
from 0 to pi over 4 so like up to a so-called maximally entangled state all of these assemblages
for p being equal to 1 are incomparable and yeah we also developed some new epr monotone
in order to confirm this result analytically. Okay as I promised I'll now compare it to prior
work which was a resource theory of so-called steering under so-hastical collaborations and
one way classical communication from Bob to Alice so this set of free operations is of course a
valid set of free operations for epr scenarios which means that it cannot create a resourceful
object and it goes as here so again in black we have the original assemblage and in green
we have the free operation so here Bob has an instrument that he performs on his part of the
state and as an output he gets first of all the classical variable that he sends to Alice
and also his quantum state and now Alice has a classical pre-processing of her variable that
depends on the message that she received from Bob and she also has a post-processing
so the motivation behind the set of free operations was that the authors claim that
is the most general set of free operations that does not compromise the security of one sided
device independent quantum key distribution protocols for them steering as a useful resource.
So the motivation here is a particular protocol in quantum information.
Okay so if you want to compare it to our work to LOSR approach the first thing that we can show
is a pretty big difference so the two resource theories actually have different pre-orders
which means that if we have a set of assemblages and we want to study it and we will study it with
two different approaches this one here and with our LOSR approach we can actually get
different results because the pre-orders are different. Now our LOSR approach has some conceptual
advantages over this one and one is that it has a clear physical motivation so motivation for
this approach here as one way LOSCC is this one sided device independent quantum key distribution
protocol while for our LOSR approach the the conceptual underpinning is more
foundational because it comes from the causal structure of this scenario and because of this
we have this unification of every type of non-classical correlation in bell-like scenarios
so we have a single LOSR resource theory for common cost scenarios and there are also some
technical advantages so for example our LOSR approach is simpler to characterize and study
this SDP this semi-different program is a good example that in our approaches it's really easy
to study the conversions and the other technical advantage is that our approach for the bipartite
scenario actually has some direct generalizations for example to multi-partite EPR scenarios but
also to bobov input and channel EPR scenarios where by channel EPR scenarios I mean something
that's usually referred to as channel steering and we left bobov input at channel for future work
but we did study the multi-partite scenarios so let me just say a few words about this right now
so let's go to a multi-partite setup which means that we now have more LSS for example this picture
here we have two LSS and as you can see everything just generalizes from the bipartite case so we still
have a common cost so we have the shared randomness that goes to each party and each party also can
perform local operations so we have local operations for Alice 1, Alice 2 and for Bob and what we
showed in the multi-partite scenario is that a sandwich conversion can be tested using a single
instance of a semi-definite program so we generalize the program that I showed you before
to to work for multi-partite scenarios and we also found a family of incomparable resources
so we have these two results that are very like they go in analogy to the bipartite case
but one thing that's a little bit extra here is a clear definition of a multi-partite free
assembled so again free assembled is one that can be can be created using only free operations
and since we study non-classicality the free assembled will be a classical assembled
or how people usually call it in the literature so an unsteerable assembled and actually there are a
lot of definitions of a free multi-partite assemblage in the literature the most general
that you will find is this one so it's that an assemblage is free if it can be decomposed
like this so we have this probability distribution for Alice's and we have the state for Bob
and actually in the most general definition there are no constraints on this probability
distribution here so for example this probability distribution is allowed to be signaling for each
lambda as long as the signaling average is out when we sum over all lambdas so such a thing is
usually referred to as fine tuning that we have this kind of undesired effect for for each lambda
but then it's average is out and it can be seen as problematic from some perspectives and there
are a few different problems that arise for this definition maybe I will not really go into detail
here but we don't have any of these problems in our LOSR approach so if we look at the set of
free operations again in our LOSR approach well it's pretty clear that a1 prime depends only
on x1 prime and lambda and a2 prime depends only on x2 prime and lambda so this probability
to distribution in our case will factorize so in our LOSR approach every assemblage is one
that decomposes like this so we don't really have any problems with signaling or any of the ones
that appear for this more general definition okay so that's pretty much it let me just make
some final remarks and so what I just presented to you was a resource theory of common cost
assemblages for bipartite and multi-partite EPR scenarios and it was motivated by a clear
causal interpretation of an EPR scenario that is a common cost that Alice and Bob share
thanks to this causal interpretation this notion is a unified notion of common cost resources
and it works for example for EPR scenarios but also for Bell scenarios and entanglement
we showed that testing convergence is numerically tractable which is very useful if you want to
study the preorder of resources and we use this result to show some interesting properties of
the preorder and finally in the multi-partite case we have a well-motivated definition of a free
multi-partite assemblage so thank you for your attention and I would be very glad to take any
questions okay thank you data for your talk now we have some minutes for questions or comments
if somebody makes a question please can you take this
can you check
yes um okay thank you and thank you for the talk I think it was very well
presented and I am a little confused about the general picture of what you're doing
um so okay let me try to state what I think is your project and let me relate it to some issues
that I that seem to be relevant okay so if I understand you correctly you first presented
the view of Schrodinger according to which there seems to be some type of action matter distance
in a typical EPR scenario and you said correctly that EPR themselves and in particular Einstein
had this view that well it might be that in reality quantum mechanics is not complete
and that the quantum state somehow reveals it's about the knowledge of Alice or Bob
okay that perhaps there is something more to the quantum state and in your case there seems
to be a reference to a common cause in the past of Alice's and Bob's labs okay and I just seem to
think that you can recover locality by this way of thinking and the problem I see is that well
that is precisely the starting point with Bell's work and with his theorem and his question was well
can we recover locality by doing something like whatever Einstein thought and his theorem is uh
no you cannot do it you cannot have a local theory and here's why because any theory that
that is uh non-local in this sense is going to make this uh inequalities is going to satisfy
these inequalities we go we check uh time and again we we notice that the inequalities are
violated and the the consequence seems to be that well any non-local theory is not going to work
so so let me know what am I missing and how is your yeah so you're not really missing anything
so let me start with your bell comparison so this is a bell type experiment right we have
a common cause and we have two parties and they make measurements so now if this common cause is
classical just by studying this causal structure so the fact that you have a common cause and you
have inputs and outputs you can derive bell inequalities and now if the common cause is
classical you can just like the the upper bound on the chsh inequalities too if the common cause
is quantum it's two times the square root of two and if it is allowed to be anything more but
there is still non signaling between the parties we have the pr box right so it goes up to four now
it's the same with epr scenarios so if this is a classical common cause then the assembler is free
and it's classical so as you said it kind of recovers the locality in in this sense but if
it's quantum we get assemblages that cannot be explained that's with classical physics okay but
then you must somehow be violating one of the assumptions of bell theorem right you must be
violating settings independence either by postulating some sort of common cause between
the state of lambda the the common cause and the settings of Alice and Bob or you're assuming something
like retrocausal theory in which Alice's settings somehow influence the the state of the the system
the common cause so for example here you can like put a box and you can make Bob make the
measurement and then it will be just like a standard bell scenario right so one way of looking
at an assemblage would be to see whether if Bob makes a measurement we violate a bell inequality
and like you could do so with the shared state is entangled right but if it's classical then you
cannot so you have to draw this line between what's classical and what's non-classical and
both for bells scenarios and for EPR scenarios this line can be decided based on the nature of
the common cause so if a common cause is classical then you will not violate a bell inequality but
if it's quantum so with the shared entangled state then you will get some some quantumness in this
scenario. Thank you. Does it answer your question or I'm not quite sure? Perhaps we should let other
people make questions and perhaps another time we can continue. Okay thank you. There is another
question from Federico Farlic but we have Federico. Yes thanks Beata for this very nice talk I wanted
to ask you whether there is a simple explanation of why you have a pre-order and not a partial order
or even a lattice as it happens in other resource theories? Not really so one thing is
so the structure of the pre-order here is very much inherent to the structure of the pre-order
for LOSR entanglement so for example in LOCC entanglement what you have is that
the conversions between states with an as the value of fee targets smaller you can actually
convert the states into a different partially entangled states. In the LOSR entanglement it's
not the case so it's already in the LOSR entanglement that you have family of incomparable resources
so for the case of assemblages this case is it just translates from the states to assemblages.
Okay thanks.
Okay there is another question or
it's not we thanks to Beata again for the talk and the people to participate.