It's good to see you.
Can you hear me okay?
Yep.
There was a little bit of interference there, but right now it's good.
So it's good to see you guy.
It's been too long to connect.
And I want to officially congratulate you on your new edition.
Thank you.
Oh, that's gotta be a.
Yeah.
That's right.
Yes.
All right.
Good to see you.
Can you hear me? Okay.
Yep.
Thank you.
That's gotta be a pretty exciting thing to bring,
bring another life into the world.
I know.
Three times.
Yeah.
Beautiful.
Right.
Yeah.
Three times totally.
In fact, in fact, I, I'm not,
I'm not in the place I'm normally at because.
My mother came to visit for the first time.
So she's meeting T.
And it's so.
So, so guy, guy got kicked out.
So he's, he's asking Mark.
Well, that's what happens when new ones come along, you know,
the old ones get shuffled out.
Absolutely.
Right.
We see the priority here.
Amen.
Yeah.
So one of the things I wanted to talk with you about.
Right.
And I think a lot of this has to do with.
With the way that I,
I see you really linking a lot of things together.
Right.
And, and, and I want to, I want to set some,
I want to set some frames up here and then we can just see,
see how it leads all together. But, you know,
it's precisely,
precisely your work and the way you situate.
That sense of the primate, right.
That goes then into justification. Right.
And that this,
my understanding is this primate level is the level of like attachment.
Right.
It's the level of attunement, attachment, all,
and there's of course stuff with Bowlby and couples therapy.
I mean, there's the evidence for that is just Astramont.
You know, it's so predictive how that goes.
Right.
It's very powerful force.
It's surprising anyone ever missed that.
We somehow missed that.
Right.
I'm glad we'll be picking up and others. Yeah.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
And how that goes into justification. Right.
And in the social arena,
where you become in your,
come the person, you know,
some sense you become initiated in a,
as a person in terms of socially justifying your own existence in
front of others. Right.
Exactly.
And also the way,
there's another way that you talk about it,
just to set this frame too, which I really,
I appreciate is that of course,
then of course it's in that justification where things get
really fucked up. Right.
And we end up totally split.
So in order to justify my existence,
I can't talk about this part of my existence and then I feel guilty.
Then we have the splits.
Then we see the psychologist and the psychologist is all about
helping unite these lower systems and these orders and sharing
the story. Right.
And so I think that's one of the things that I think is really
important.
And I think that's one of the things that I think is really important
is that you can open around these,
these defensiveness,
this defensiveness and adaptations. Right.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
And all of that coming together and how,
and in what way.
That in some sense is.
Is connected ontologically to things. Right.
Right.
Absolutely.
And, and so as we were talking about,
I'm just going to summarize what we talked about before we hit record.
Right.
One of the things for a while that I've been really thinking a lot
about is this notion of.
School lay.
The Greek sense of school lay,
which,
which usually translates into English is leisure.
And of course,
leisure and idleness leisure is, is, is the core.
It's kind of, it's, it's so core to economics.
Right.
And metaphorically to everything that,
that if everything's going well, people work and then they have
leisure. Right.
They work too much and they don't have leisure. That's bad. Right.
Yep.
And however, it's very different.
That sense of leisure is not,
doesn't get at the deeper sense of the way that they talked about
school lay.
Philosophically and religious.
Right.
Yeah.
The Greeks.
The Greeks saw school lay.
He uses this example.
For example,
Aristotle said that all fear,
fear,
in geometry happens in school lay.
And then in, in the apology, I think it was.
Socrates said that I actually think you guys shouldn't kill me.
I think, I think,
I think Athens should pay me to be in school lay and.
And have, and speak philosophy.
Those conversations, right?
Right. Right.
And so you get this sense with school lay that like for the Greeks,
whereas in leisure, there's a sense in which there's time.
And then you fill time.
And then if, if you work, if you work hard enough and right enough,
and the economy works well,
then you can work for a certain amount of time.
And then at the end you have free time or leisure.
And you notice that conception of time is the same throughout.
It's just a matter of if it's filled with stuff or not filled with stuff.
Yes.
But with something like, with something like theory or,
or philosophy or geometry, right?
At these higher levels of essentially contemplating being.
There's a very, very different sense of time, right?
It's really precisely the pinnacle where, where,
where means and ends come together as one thing.
Love it. Right.
And so bringing this back into me having a kid, right?
And, and everything that we're talking about was attachment, right?
Right.
Totally.
Is for the Greeks.
Skolle, the root of Skolle means holding to hold.
Right.
And that really only makes sense in relationship to time.
So Skolle in the Greek sense was that time was something for
which was of our concern.
It was an essential concern in the sense that there was a way that
if there's a way to hold time,
such that time in turn turns back and holds us.
Love that.
Right.
The Skolle was a way of being in time and holding time,
but then of revealing time, right?
In a way that they're mutually disclosive, right?
And so that was the essence of time itself.
So there's this really sense where meaning in time, right?
Being in time would, would receive their pinnacle.
And it wasn't like you were in Skolle and then not in Skolle.
No, it was more, it was more,
this was connected with the revelation of what time was, right?
Which was the direct concern for us.
And so if you look at it now though, without that sense of time,
where time now is more this kind of anatomical force in which it,
of course we're subject to it and it concerns us,
but there's no sense in which time.
It all responds to us, right?
It's like we're subject to it.
And therefore I think what,
what that's done on some level is we no longer see
meaning in time as unified, right?
Or as a couple.
So therefore time is just this force, right?
That can't really hold meaning.
It can just give lawful,
you can get a lot,
lawful like sustaining an entropy to circumstance.
Therefore,
therefore we need to find meaning in the,
the sensations of our circumstances that you will, right?
Thus the drama, but there's nothing about time that it all
responds to us, right?
And that sense that the Greeks had about it.
And so that in that,
and just this idea that in Schole,
that it's, it's this relationship to the ontology of time that,
that, that, that, that,
that the way I am comport is already a comporting or a holding
of time and that time is that which is holding me.
Right.
And now I think about that.
Now I have a baby, right?
No, I'm thinking about all this.
And now I have a baby, right?
And yeah.
And somebody asked me how Teague was.
And before I responded,
I noticed that I had this picture of Teague, right?
And that,
that I hadn't noticed that there is no Teague to simply Teague
being held, right?
At every picture, like either literally by our hands or held by
our attention or being held by the thing we set up for the crib.
In fact, if there's like a second where we don't have our eye on him,
it's like a big deal, right?
Hey, hey.
And so, right?
And so there's no such thing as Teague.
There's Teague continuous with being held.
Right.
And then if we think about that, right?
So there's something real.
I'm like, okay, what is this,
this connection between time, meaning ontology,
our vulnerability as human beings,
the fact that we primordially start like this,
like a deep vulnerability and an openness to the very holding,
right?
Which then that holding in turn,
hopefully they internalize and as they internalize it,
as he grows up, we will then let go and he will take on the whole
holding.
And so in some sense,
I'm wondering about this idea of holding.
What does that reveal about the ontologically the case with us and
human beings, right?
Totally.
All right.
So those are all the thought islands.
Let's see if we can,
we see if we can peer underneath the surface,
pull some sort of synergy out of that.
Yeah.
That's a beautiful set of observations.
Let me just say that. Okay.
I love,
I didn't know about the Greek word skole.
Can you say that?
Okay.
So we know about that word.
So let me give you just some thoughts to start to ground us in,
in relation to the holding environment that we can then cultivate.
Yeah.
Okay.
So the first thing, a couple of things that come to mind,
one is our vertical integration.
Okay.
Vertical integration of us as organisms first.
Yeah.
Into animals,
which then is the base of our feeling system.
And we can feel that, you know,
in our gut and our loins and in our gut.
Okay.
And that's the way the position of the body and whether we got pain
or emptiness in our stomach or horny and longs in the loins.
It's an appetite of desires.
It's a very platonic play-toe version.
Yeah.
And that's our animal.
You know,
our organism into animal level from a to K view.
So you're a bio physiological entity.
And then the first thing is, Hey,
you got to take care of survival.
Shit.
You know, right?
Yeah.
And then we're social primates.
Okay.
So then we move into the, what I metaphorically refer to the heart.
And the heart's the relationship attachment system.
Okay.
And there's nothing more central to an infant than this.
I mean the whole,
because the entire safety food and relational matrix are all
intimately intertwined in virtually every infant's experience.
Yeah.
And we see that in the holding that,
whether they're being prepared and connected,
they're so dependent.
And for the first six months,
they are completely dependent upon the environment in which they're
held.
Yeah. Right. Yeah.
I know they're, they're, they're absorbing stuff.
They have enormous plasticity.
They're upgrading the various models,
but they're just checking shit out basically.
Yeah.
They have a little bit of hand movement and a lot of,
they put shit in their mouth.
Yes.
And they track everything really fast with the head.
Yeah.
And they have a visual auditory learning system,
but the body is doing, you know, it's barely roll over.
Right. Right. Yes.
Right.
So they're, so the system then in what they're doing from it,
that we can, we spoke about John Bulby. Okay.
So what he noticed is we,
the early systems of psychiatry psychology, well,
the key really is food.
So, you know, we had orphanage.
We just fed them as long as they stayed alive and the temperature
was thing and they didn't have any threat and they were getting
out of bed.
They should be all right.
And then all of these kids and orphanages that weren't being,
we're all broken in some ways, you know,
they were underdeveloped.
They felt the whole socio-emotional systems was out of touch.
They got these weird attachment structures that was a fundamental
set of insecurity.
Okay.
That the,
that the environment would drop out of them at a particular level.
Yeah.
They weren't known and valued and they wouldn't be protected.
And then they had to, they were, kids would respond in certain ways.
You'd either get very hyper dependent. Oh my God.
Just try sending out alarms all the time, hyper neurotic,
sending out certain alarms to be so that they try to get what little
attention they could.
Yeah.
Or they would go avoidant, which is hyper independent.
They try to crush this need of the heart and then be,
I don't need anybody. I'll just try to suppress it.
Or they would get really, especially if they were abused,
then they get really erratic and disorganized attachments.
Okay.
Yeah.
And really this is what later attachment is about the circle.
Of security that you're actually wanting to see build,
which is a fundamental participatory dance between the caregiver.
And the infant.
Where you're tracking eye movements and building a shared attention,
intention, space.
Yeah.
So that you can then create the ground,
the socio-emotional ground that you will be cared for.
And if you have particular needs, you can signal them and I'll be able
to empathize with you and I'll meet them.
Okay.
Yeah.
This creates the ground of the secure base.
From which the infant can go at six months into the next couple of
years and start to move away from the base.
Okay.
Yeah.
And then return to the holding environment.
If it falls, if the kid falls and scrapes his knee,
runs back to mom and dad and gets immediately returned to the holding
environment.
Yeah.
Because the entire primate animal organism system is like check.
Okay.
Am I held safe?
Or am I in the dark woods somewhere by myself?
The ultimate panic, right?
Which is.
Right.
Complete.
Yeah.
You're about to get eaten by a dark man and a tiger in the woods.
Absolutely.
So that's an unbelievable, that darkness is unbelievably,
you know, concerning the poor panic abandonment and the felt sense of
worthlessness and this felt sense of insecurity, you know,
and are you, and then you get polyvagal defensiveness throughout the
system when you're getting this structure.
Yeah.
Okay.
So you're being, you're either being held in the matrix of care or
not.
Yeah.
And those are the two basic secure insecure.
And of course there's a lot in between.
Yeah.
Basically the matrix says there's actually these two equilibrium
states at a bimodal kind of distribution of being held.
And then you track the interpersonal world.
And indeed we know kids can be feel pretty safe with mom and not
with dad or vice versa, depending on the dance, the relation.
It's called the circle of security and the more advanced
simulations that then afford.
Right.
When it's there, it's a particular holding environment.
So, so the, the, when you have that,
you're going to create coherent integration in the environment,
into the body, into the animal, into the social primate.
Okay.
And that's really the first couple of years is trying to create that
fundamental secure base.
So the system can then trust basic trust to use, you know,
the world and that you're going to get your needs met or basic
mistrust.
This is the Ericksonian formulation.
Okay.
A basic trust is mistrust.
Yeah.
That says, Hey,
yes, I will get my needs met because the environment will hold me in
a particular way.
And the environment holds me because it sees me as valuable.
Yes.
Exactly.
That connection between value and holding, right?
And what that means seems to be.
Super.
Deeply, deeply central. Yeah.
And I make a very important point about my own development in this
theoretical structure called the influence matrix,
which first emphasized it from an evolutionary instrumental way,
which is totally valid, but it's incomplete originally.
And that is what I call that the social influence line.
Okay.
And social and it was to bind in sort of instrumental terms,
to what extent can you influence others in accordance with your
interests?
Okay.
If I cry, will you come help me?
Or will you ignore me?
So it's an instrumental framing,
which at a pragmatic level of survival is key.
However,
what I saw in the clinic room is that a lot of people could have
influence, but feel very empty inside.
Okay.
And they would go around and they wouldn't,
or they would feel that they were not valued.
And I realized that actually the ultimate sort of core,
even from an evolutionary perspective,
the core equilibrium safe space is to be valued,
not just to be able to manipulate others instrumentally.
Cause if the contingency of manipulation disappears,
then the,
then there's no intrinsic motive for mom and dad to love you.
Then they're out of it.
Okay.
Yeah.
But if they're totally,
if their motivational system is attached to you by its own valuing
structure,
then that at a particular level, that's really key.
The other thing that's going to get back into why this is so
important is because modern science basically thinks and economics
thinks in terms of instrumental means and relationship and trying
to maximize productive control.
Okay.
They then, in fact,
the entire social capital laborers basically,
influence and investment and return on investment in instrumentality,
modes of production and control.
Okay.
Yeah.
So the whole thing basically is like,
how do we efficiently maximize our influence and power over the
things for the least amount of money in relationship to particular
outcomes.
So now you create the doing instrumental mindset.
That then fundamentally merges as the dominant mode.
And this now brings in Eric from the dominant mode of doing that then
becomes so salient for the way in which we all think that's a
quantifiable and, you know,
many scientists see the behavioral and evolutionary sciences.
Oh, we're all just selfish anyway.
And this is what we really care about and blah, blah, blah.
Yeah.
And you know, what you can do is you, you know,
there is really any God, there's no real purpose,
but you can at least get the most toys that you have.
And get as much accomplishment.
And then that's, that's the doing of what, you know,
you get rich and you get status and you get leisure time.
And that's what you're trying to get.
Yeah.
You know, do, do, do.
Yes.
Okay.
Right.
So we'll love you, but at least we can hack it.
Yeah.
At least we can hack it.
At least I can get the most.
Yeah.
At least we can hack it.
At least I can get the most toys.
But like, at least we can hack that.
That's right.
I got a big fucking Vita that's going to substitute, you know,
for true love,
but at least I got a big fucking Vita or have a nice Lamborghini
or something or not.
And then you're on the low shit.
And you can't do, and then you fail and all of that.
Yeah.
And then it's like, well, okay, well, what am I doing here?
Well, I'm just trying to, I'm trying to,
everything's a means to an end relation.
I mean, look at money.
I mean, to the extent that then money becomes the symbol.
It's the ultimate instrumental symbol.
Yeah. For some people, they get it so confused.
I was like, I want to make more money.
You know, it's like,
as if that is some sort of quantifying in it.
That's empty calories at the core.
Yeah.
And I think that we're,
we have driven the doing mode to try to control energy and time
in an instrumental kind of way to enormous excess.
Okay.
Yeah.
And then that's not good calories for feeling,
spending time in an attached relational environment,
in nature,
feeling the oneness of the self-world modeling structure,
feeling held by that,
feeling fundamentally present and fulfilled in relationship to it,
feeling the integration between the body,
into the animal, into the heart,
into the justification, into the spirit,
mattering value purpose.
That's what I call vertical integration.
Okay.
So if you get vertical integration,
I would say then for me,
the label is wisdom energy.
And what you feel is just a massive presence,
a fundamental fit between the self-world environment
and a massive presencing of that.
Yeah.
And then that is a eudaimonic ultimate endpoint.
You are then in,
in sync,
incoherent integrative sync with the system.
Yeah.
And then finally to bring it back to kind of the leisure,
I feel like I got lucky with Socrates.
I'm a public intellectual.
I get paid.
And I tell people at the level of leisure,
it's like,
people are like, well, how often, how much do you work?
I was like, well,
I work either five or 75 hours a week,
depending on how you calculate it.
Okay.
Yeah.
Yes.
Because, you know,
I have five hours of shit I need to do that is the kind of labor.
And, you know,
here's a paperwork thing, sign this prep.
This is like,
while I'm doing it,
the only thing I'm doing is for,
for instrumental purpose to get something done.
But I'm super lucky that I'm now at a place as full professor,
blah, blah, blah.
That's like a huge amount of work like this.
Is this work?
You know, are we are, am I, I don't, I love this.
I feel that enormously just present.
I feel connected to you.
I feel our souls connected in a particular way.
And then we engage in D a logos.
And then that's a,
then my experience of being in the world is just enriched by
these things.
So yeah.
No, it's like, you know,
it's productive and in growth promoting,
but it doesn't feel like I've had to,
I'm trying to control something to get to some place.
I'm in the place of being itself.
Yeah.
And that's,
and there's somehow in some sense implicitly there.
And it's a couple of things that kind of link all of that together
all the way down to that.
Like,
you know,
I started with the first six months because the second six months,
right.
All the way is like mature professor. Right.
One is it sounds like your relationship with time is very,
very different, right.
In some sense that there is a way that you relate to time that seems
like these things,
these meetings or something like the pinnacle or express this
fundamental relationship where you're.
There is a sense in which it holds you and inspires you.
There's time disappears.
There's the flow state, Deologos, all of that.
Totally.
Now, it's interesting too that
this sense about when you talked about
after the first six months and then they start,
the child starts to venture away from the holding
and then they come back, right?
It's such a cool image of that,
because you can see that too, because they do.
They venture out, they're like,
they'll check back and then they'll go,
oh, they're gonna see what they gotta do.
And then they'll check back really quick,
are you still there, right?
Like, you're still there, I'll go out and then you look back,
right?
They're test, they intrinsically are testing something.
That's right.
And, and God, and there's so many different ways
that could get fucked up, right?
Like, cause I was thinking about that when,
if the, what happens when the child comes back
and then the mother's destroyed and angry
because the child left her, right?
Like, and then, and so there's all kinds of ways
that that dynamic relation can get all whacked out, right?
And then usually it stresses itself in all these,
you know, in broken marriages and-
Well, we're right, and then we test it all the time
for good reason.
You're like, hey, I'm gonna, I'll drop a cry over here
or I won't do other things.
And it was not with conscious justification,
but the design of the system is to know where it is.
So, and we do this with our spouses, you test them.
Yeah.
You drop little, I mean, not like very rarely,
I'm gonna adjust my, some people that,
but you do it intuitively
because you want to see where the value and attention is.
Okay?
Like, I mean, my kids, I mean, they've got five and three
and you know, you cut two pieces of cake,
hey, his cake's bigger than mine.
And I was like, and I was like, okay,
but you know, they're gonna check that
and they're gonna be like, hey, you cut it
and that reflects something in your heart, doesn't it?
You love him more than you love me.
Or you better draw attention to that.
You know, there's a little, you know,
that's a chronic state of,
is this environment really holding
and then I'll test it and see what happens.
You know, really.
Right, totally.
Like I,
well, the other thing about that that I didn't,
I think I saw as you're talking about this differently
than I saw it before,
which is this back and forth, right, relation,
that it's really, it's, it, how dynamic it is.
It's like, I know we talk about it in terms of like,
okay, is that, is the child starts to objectify, right?
Will that object hold me, right?
Is that all?
But really when we look at it this set,
they're not actually checking to a thing,
but that the stability is precisely a way
of a modal of relations happening, right?
So it's not like there's something stable
in a thing-like way.
It's a dynamic, a nexus of relations that are going on.
Totally.
Which they start to feel a certain kind of safety with.
And of course, the world is a chaotic network of relations,
right, that they're trying to tolerate
and then go back and forth.
Right.
And that, and that that's actually,
and that it's also,
it seems to me this relationship in some sense,
that seems that back and forth implies
a certain temporality, right?
Nope.
In some way.
Sure.
All right.
Is my past.
If I turn around and I look back,
will it still be there?
Right?
This future, right?
There's something drawing me in
that I don't know about yet.
Therefore it's chaotic,
but then I'll turn around this past
and this back and forth movement seems,
I would imagine that's probably one of the,
there's something there about temporality.
Right.
Well, the system starts to be able
to extend itself over time.
That's one of the first things, okay?
So then the way in which you,
I mean, at first it's pretty immediate.
And then the capacity to then,
and indeed it is the argument that John and I
and Chris were making in the elusive eye was,
it is this capacity to begin to extend the self over time
through multiplicity of possible simulations
where the environment then changes as you,
but then it is the extension of self in that time
that really starts to give this self agent environment
relation and then the self other relational matrix
that then creates the model of the self.
Okay, so that means that we start to carry
and then we extend.
So that issue of who am I across time,
basically becomes the modeling structures
that afford you the opportunity to get a grip,
on the world.
So how you build that is through the attachments
of first mom and dad need to be present
or there needs to be a security system present
at first six months.
Then all of a sudden that it begins to extend
into an autonomy versus shame and doubt.
That's the next lace title, which is autonomy is like,
hey, I can now actually start to exhibit.
I have the motor work and cognitive capacity
start to exhibit control over the world
and distance myself, okay?
But as soon as I get distance in any way out here
in the darkness and I'm still just learning shit,
it all of a sudden becomes a dark, scary world.
Now I have to quickly touch, is mom gonna be there?
You know, if I move away, you know, when I look back.
And so then you have to expand the temporality
of the field of consideration
because now the opportunity across time is increasing
and you have to start to really protect
what's going on in relationship to that.
Right.
I mean, so interesting just to kind of grok this sense of
if I turn around and if I look up and it gets scary
and I turn around, are they still there?
That there is so linked to value, right?
Am I valued enough such that people stay around, right?
It's so interesting to think about it like that, right?
Being valued is so primary.
Totally.
That's it.
The fund, that is the core of the heart soul
is to be known and valued by important others,
at least according to the unified theory.
It's the fundamental calories, okay?
Of that part of your psyche.
And it's absolutely as crucial as good calories
for the body, you know, it's a fundamental
in some ways even, you know, at the level.
So am I known and valued?
It's not just can I manipulate them
but fundamentally they care about me, you know,
and my essence, okay?
And in non-contingent ways, they care about me.
Yeah, yeah.
That's what people really track
and they desperately need.
And unfortunately, because of our humanness though,
we get to a stage where we can,
there's an access to the interior through justification,
which they need to start talking, okay?
And little kids don't have to deal with this as much
but as you start to get older,
you can then the cognitive capacities of justification
start to say, well, okay,
I know mom wants to hear shit from me
or dad wants to hear shit
or my friends want to hear shit
and they can ask me questions.
So then I find myself basically generating a persona,
public justification out here, okay?
And that creates then the opportunity
for imposter syndromes,
which then emerge in middle to older childhood,
where you actually start to then create a public face,
a persona, that's young call,
that the mask that you then wear in relation
and you realize you do that
for social influence purposes,
meaning because you wear the mask,
you avoid their judgment in a particular way
or you obtain their praise.
But at the same time,
it creates a fundamental social versus core self-split
because it's like this,
they love me now as a function of the contingencies
that I give them.
But if they really knew me, I'm terrified they wouldn't.
That way I see that all the time in a relationship
to once adolescents start to struggle with mental health
and it creates this very, very brutal dichotomy
and there's no holding environment there
that can be really generated,
that's fundamentally embodied
because you can't really,
you can't bring yourself to test if so you fake it,
but you then don't trust that you would actually be held.
I have many, many clients
who had to work through that process
to afford coherent integration along those lines.
In fact, you were just saying,
because I too, because I work with people one-on-one too
and in so many cases,
like I just started to,
it's at the point where I could just kind of almost
look for it, right?
There's something like life was fine, right?
Everything was fluid, I was loved and then we moved.
And then there was a new school
and then I had to like,
and then there's the socialization, right?
The break with something, some kind of security
and then there in a new social matrix
and then there's all these breakdowns
and on some level, right?
That's,
there, so much of their personality
has been defined in that adaptation, right?
Which has all these dichotomies in it, right?
And that's usually what we end up talking about, right?
Are issues around that fundamental break, yeah.
Totally, exactly.
And then that activates the insecurity
of not being held in the environment.
And then people struggle with various strategies,
testing, defenses, coping strategies, et cetera.
And if they are constrained and limited
and they also lead to additional problems,
you get an entrenched maladaptive problem
of a social phobia,
a fundamental sense of insecurity and inability
to articulate what's going on,
a hyper-reactivity of the vulnerability
because you're always on edge.
And then of course that makes you very difficult
to then engender the risks that are necessary
and they perceive them often as great risks
to then go out and try to find
a new secure identification matrix.
Identification matrix is the self-world identity process.
So these are the elements of the world.
It's my map of that, not necessarily conscious,
but just intuitively the way you map it.
My place in that world
and this is what's gonna happen to me
if I behave in X, Y, and Z ways.
Right, right, right.
You know, the sense about, right,
one of the things that's interesting to me about this
is this, you can see through all of this
that, you know, I often talk about it like this.
It's like, you know, do you,
I don't know about all of biology,
but like in terms of mammals,
I don't think there's anything more helpless
than the human infant, is there?
Not even close.
And what's interesting about this,
this has always struck me as like,
we all start off like that.
Like the way we start is completely dependent,
completely helpless in every dimension
that you can imagine.
Totally.
And who's going to Mars, right?
Who's on top of the food chain?
Who's, right?
Who's the one, as far as we can tell,
I mean, who knows ultimately,
but as far as we can tell,
who's the one that caught a sight of its own existence
and then can relate back with that existence, right?
Even that, you can feel a kind of vulnerability
or transparency or porousness going on.
And I think about this,
and this is where it starts to get kind of ontologically
where I want to bring this in.
And I'm just curious how this weaves together
is, so there's a deep vulnerability
that seems to afford the highest levels of theoria, right?
Of mystical realization, right?
Deep conceptualization, right?
These unitary things and abstractions
and all of that, right?
And in one sense, there's this helplessness
that also, right?
And in this relationship with that vulnerability,
in its hold-it, right?
Yes.
And it's all, so if you think about this statement,
I think it's Jesus, I think he says this in the Bible,
I'm so not up on that stuff,
but where he says, the meek shall inherit the earth.
You think about that statement, right?
Such a weird thing at face value,
the meek shall inherit the earth.
When you think about it like that, right?
Like in the terms we're talking about,
you can start to get where you're talking about.
Like that there is a way that,
and I think what he's basically saying is,
the meek, when loved, right?
That can potentuate this vulnerability
into something very, very powerful, right?
And so there's that part of it that's just,
it seems I'm wondering,
it's like there's something ontologically
about vulnerability and holding, right?
That is expressed here.
And then also, but it also strikes me that as human,
oops, sorry about that.
That's fine.
I've got to figure out a way so when it calls,
it doesn't blank out.
You know, it's like, yeah,
so that something about the essence of being human, right?
Is really, really tied with being vulnerable.
But like, I don't know anybody.
In fact, I've been teaching courses
for years and I've never had anyone sit,
not once have I ever had anybody say,
respond to me when I've said,
well, hey, maybe this is a good time to be vulnerable,
where they're like, oh, I'm so,
I was, someone had to say it, right?
Thank God.
No, it's always this sense of like, oh, like, all right,
right, that on one level,
our humanity seems to be very much
about this deep vulnerability, right?
But there's a level at which it can be,
we can also be exposed, right?
Which is I think what we're really afraid of
when we talk about being afraid of being vulnerable,
but we're really, really afraid of
is we collapse that with being,
with the involuntary sense of being subject
to something in which I'm exposed to,
which I think is really, really different.
Vulnerability seems to, at least in my mind,
has more of a sense of I'm voluntary, right?
There's some sense of I'm willing, right,
to be vulnerable, both will, positive sense,
and willing, right, and the generative sense.
And, but when that holding environment, right, breaks down,
and we develop defenses,
and so I don't wanna be human,
so what I do is I put a shell around myself.
But here's the paradox, it's like the moment,
the moment I put a shell around myself,
and this is why our psychological defense
is on one level work, but the cost to them are great.
I think it has to do with this,
is because the moment I put a shell around myself
is the moment I become brittle, right?
So, and it seems to me that this relationship to,
because on some level, you could say the mystic
realizing on the top of the mountain, realizing being, right?
You could almost see that is in some sense
a profound relationship with his own vulnerability,
such that he's so vulnerable,
that he's vulnerable to the deepest depths of himself,
and transparent to it,
such that he realizes the ultimate depth of oneness,
and then paradoxically,
in that full realization of vulnerability,
he's invulnerable, right?
Because he's everything, right?
We think about that as a symbol.
Yeah.
And this kind of, this ontological sense,
this verticality, right,
that has to do with holding time vulnerability,
bringing those things together.
What stands out for you in that?
Well, a couple of things.
So, yes, I think you're, first off,
we should highlight the vulnerability aspect of our nature.
That we're born into the world vulnerable.
And then that affords us a wonderful set
of both opportunities and serious risks at multiple levels.
And then our potentialities are structured
around trying to mitigate and navigate those risks.
Okay.
And potentially can be realized
through a huge amount of affordance.
Okay, so let's just talk this through.
So, I think the bottom line,
why are we so vulnerable from an evolutionary perspective?
I think the fundamental answer
is because we're incredibly plastic, okay?
I was just listening to Heather hiring on Jim Rutt,
and she was like, from hunter-gatherer perspective,
we're sort of the niche generalizers,
meaning that we can bounce from,
one of the things about it is we can bounce
from niche to niche, okay?
And learn strategies in a wide variety of addition niches.
I mean, that's what our cognitive language,
collective intelligence capacities,
our creative capacities afford us that.
How the hell do you, though,
get all the cognitive gadgets
and the availability to do that?
Well, super long time of development, you know?
And the other thing that probably the mechanics
of the size of the head,
then that requires to hold the brain,
and then the birthing process is like,
well, you can't stay in there forever.
We're already have serious problems at birth.
It's a hell of a process, right?
Yeah.
So you got to get the thing out of there
really before it's ready, basically.
And now all of a sudden you have this really,
neotony is the extended period of neonatal development.
And Steven J. Gould points out that this is a really,
almost certainly a central feature of our development.
So nature basically says, all right,
we're going to get systems
that can have this unbelievable cognitive learning flexibility
that they can learn repertoires
and then repertoire off a top so that they,
most animals just learn repertoires.
We earn repertoires on top of our repertoires.
They've put them all together in evolutionary new ways
through our learning.
And then now we justify on top of that.
So we are really do,
our behavioral flexibility is really in a class by its set,
okay?
To get there, the system has to have be able to download
and manipulate all that.
Plus, so then it comes out very, very vulnerable.
So now let's think about what that means about our condition.
If I am fed and held well, okay,
I can then grow and network into a collective intelligence
that is enormous amount of power
and be a part of something belonging.
Actually, my doctoral student is probably going to do
a dissertation on suicide called the ontology of belonging
and suicidal behavior in adolescence, okay?
And basically it's the ecology and ontology of belonging
in her estimation that affords coherent integration.
And what gets deviated for so many people
is the breakdown in that.
And then an internalized critical looping
that then alienates and leads to psychic
and then a crash and burn and have alienation.
And you can see then that you have this whole,
all of this potential,
first off, you might get neglected and abused.
That's horrifying, right?
Or you might get situated so that you're in a contingency
where you have to fake it,
but then you feel empty inside.
That's another sort of developmental line,
an aberrant or atypical
or less than fulfilling developmental line.
And then there's this enormous potential
to grow in connection with each other in nature
in a fulfilled way because of the enormous plasticity
and learning potential of the structure of the system.
So our developmental trajectories are enormously variable.
And so the idea that we're sort of like trying to track,
oh, guys, is this a bad sign?
Is this a good sign?
Where are we and have potentials that afford that?
The other thing that I was thinking of
when you were talking,
I hooked up with a theorist a while ago
who really centered on this core split of our potential.
He actually called his framework called the one divide, okay?
And he basically argued that birth and early events
inevitably result in trauma, okay?
And then you have the activation
of the low relational value, low social influence,
panic of abandonment, death, desertion, okay?
And that core panic is something
that you are really programmed to like void.
I was like, oh my God, am I gonna be seen
and devalued and dejected and removed, okay?
So then what happens then is the self system
begins to model what makes me vulnerable
and then how do I create a defensive self-structure
that's trying to compensate and avoid and control
in an instrumental way,
the avoidance and discovery of that abandonment.
And he argues that many, many people,
and I think this is true,
many people then live their lives essentially on the cusp.
This is really a felt sense of insecurity
you're building a defended character armor structure,
Wright talks about character armor
from a psychodynamic perspective,
you build this up and the function of that
is to avoid the terror with the fear
that if you fail to do this, you would be revealed
and you'd be rejected
and you have a fundamental abandonment, okay?
The structure of that,
if you think the vertical integration structure of that,
it's basically, it's an empty dark core
that is speaking to you constantly
and the rest of your character structure
then is a compensation to try to avoid falling into something.
Yeah.
Think about that.
Yeah, it's like, exactly.
Like, ah, you know.
And that is, and now I need to work really hard
to build stuff and then the felt sense of existence is,
how far can I stay away from it?
But everything then you're doing
is actually negatively reinforcing.
And what that means is you do shit
so that you avoid the potential horror of consequence.
And it takes a little bit of the edge off periodically
but then you have to keep doing stuff
to keep the abyss falling away.
I've met a lot of people that live their lives like that
and it is, it's pretty tragic
because the entire structure of being
then is like, it's just,
how do I avoid falling into abyss
as opposed to how do I live in the divine bliss?
Okay.
Yeah.
The fullness, not the negation.
Exactly.
It's like, oh my God.
You mean to say that I can be valued
and value that into my animal body,
into my soul and my cells and feel at oneness
with the sense of divine, with the ultimate purpose,
with the negentropic complex, coordinated,
integrated processes.
That's my spirit into my system of justification.
Then you drop into that
and you just feel a perspectival,
a heart flood with a sense of appreciation, gratitude, love,
awe, all of that, and then down into the body.
And that is, then that's the true self,
what he calls the true self integration.
And it creates the basically the stack
of an affirming belief system in spirit
that has some sense making,
that makes sense of the heart that's known and valued,
that's into the body that's felt held and secure
in the environment itself.
And then I think one of the things
that we should be really emphasizing,
my friend Rob Scott emphasized this,
calls it the fundamental shift is those moments
of being itself are the awe-inspiring glory
of being itself and to be just in the moment of awareness,
of fundamental awareness
and to cultivate the taste of that beauty,
of awareness itself.
I mean, I find that to be,
and then you get back to the whole leisure place,
is sort of like to have the opportunity to simply be,
right?
And then to be and to have that beingness
be so fill your existence in the world.
I mean, that's a beautiful thing.
And I think there's an opportunity for us to achieve that.
He certainly makes this case.
I believe this too, that we just,
we don't so, we socialize towards instrumental control
and doing, you know?
And can I do more and do more and do more and get more
and the whole, and then you can rest
and or watch your damn, you know, whatever is fun for you.
And it's like, you're missing the entire point
of being in becoming modes of, you know,
we should be working when certainly you have to
at some level, it's not like you don't do,
but the cultivation of that fundamental being in the world
and being held by the world in a moment of the infinite now
and a particular kind of presence
to be able to taste that, to be present with that.
I think that's a, I've certainly grown
in the last five years in that mode.
And, you know, even as a clinical psychologist,
we aren't socialized too much to orient to that.
I think that's a great,
many wisdom traditions do orient that way.
And I've really felt fortunate
that I've been hanging out with people over the last five years
and really shine the light on that in a rich way.
Right.
Well, one of the things that is you've been describing
all of this, it's just been,
it's a marvel to realize our pre-reflective
organismic sense knows this relationship with folding.
It's embodied, embedded, right?
There's a deep, seems super intelligent to me.
It's network of is intelligibility
that seems to somehow be oriented to this, right?
So just this idea of that,
because I've seen this over and over and over again,
where, you know, like it is, it's really true.
It's like, I think it's set up in such a way
and it says a lot to do with nihilism.
It says a lot to do with the meeting crisis,
all of this, right?
Where we're not really,
we don't even consider that we don't have
an understanding of being that isn't contingent, right?
There's not this sense of contingency,
the sense of, that there is, there are principles, right?
That in some sense govern,
you know, govern the orderliness
or make it possible for orderliness.
And in some sense, philosophy, right?
Philosophy in the deepest sense of the word
was really in some sense about getting close to
and beholding those principles, right?
That in some sense, the principle itself,
you can't, what's interesting about is,
the principle itself is like, you cannot,
it's one of those things where you cannot ultimately,
you can't put into language, right?
I think, yes, it's the way, you know,
you go to Taoism catchers, this is pretty early.
I think when they say the Tao is not the Tao,
it's a participatory, perspectival presencing
that is definitely at this animal heart,
you know, felt sense of being it.
And then, and also I think it often is,
when we have our transcendent states,
it's trans-justificatory.
So in virtually all mystic states, it's, you know,
the ego dies or dissipates that little,
the narrating regulator or seeking justification,
control and legitimacy, right?
That is crucial.
But it is a particular kind of mode
that I think our modern style is like,
way over-activated in a particular way.
Oh, totally.
And then it kind of controls the shit
and is trying to regulate and make sure everything
fits in the damn boxes that it's trying to control.
Anxious or pissed off if it doesn't, you know,
win its justification in a particular way.
And that is, that's definitely not
the coherent stacked integration.
In fact, that's just one piece of it
and you need to be underneath it and above it
rather than just trying to use it as the primary,
you know, propositional reasoning network,
which is really modernity, you know,
basically started to just said that in many ways.
It was like, wow, we're gonna reason our way
through justification and science into this.
I know Ian McGillchrist makes a number of points
in these directions and I agree.
Yeah, right.
And this sense of witnessing,
and I'm sure you've probably experienced
this being a therapist too of that.
It sounds like I would imagine
that therapy is a lot like this,
but just when you start to get real about,
people start to have these insights that,
and it's usually when their defensive strategies
don't like actually start the balance,
the benefit of that goes down, right?
Right.
Because usually I've noticed this
with like kind of psychological forms of defensiveness,
is it creates this immediate sense of safety,
but in a way that numbs you
or has you not see the long-term consequences.
And I think that thing that you were talking about,
this nemo, this emptiness inside,
in which if you fall into that, it's all over, right?
That's the felt sense.
Then you live such that you're not that,
and then you articulate a whole way of being
that's about an avoidance of that, right?
But then you're dependent on that in some weird sense.
So you go in with people and you start talking about this,
and you say, well, what would happen if you just didn't do that?
Yeah, totally.
Like in this anxiety comes up,
and then there's a way where it's like you take something
to be with the anxiety and the annihilation
because there's a deep mistake going on in there, right?
Right, exactly.
But when people can tolerate it, right,
and the conditions are right,
and they can tolerate it and they can open to it,
that and go through that initial, it's like feeling,
it's like that level of experience is so, it's so intense, right?
It's like, imagine, it's like the feeling,
it's like the most haunting, nauseating,
like everything unattractive that you could imagine
in your very pores is the recognition
that that's all that there is, that's what it feels like, right?
It's like total awfulness, right?
In the deep sense of the word,
and it takes something to even get any leverage
to be able to turn towards it, right?
Absolutely, it takes a little bit.
But when you do, there is something though,
because, and I'm kind of getting this through this conversation
in a different way,
that I don't know if I quite saw it like so congruently here,
is that we have our nervous system
is really knows how to open to that deep openness, right?
It's like something catches,
like if you can feel through that barrier, right?
And you can like, at some point, you're like,
all right, non-being, ah!
Right?
Totally, yeah.
At some point, you're like,
well, there is a lot of room.
It is kind of spacious in there.
In fact, there's like an affording spaciousness in like,
but your nervous system knows how to,
how to take in that in the most generative sense, right?
Yes.
Yeah.
If it's, yeah.
Right, it has that potential, okay?
Yeah.
It also, the reason people get all tangled up
is precisely because the way that egoic narrator
frames it all, okay?
Yeah.
If you frame it in a particular way,
and you do have a core anxiety thing,
and then you get a lot of reinforcement,
that this in structure,
because the system basically is reading this,
is that this is annihilation itself, okay?
Yeah.
And then you build all the justification around that.
And then what you, if you do it in the right way,
and afford the person to bring to bear
what that annihilation actually means,
at first it's terrifying, right?
Yeah.
But you're right.
If the opening of what this might mean
and what might be on the other side of it
is afforded to the individual,
and they can hold the egoic defenses off
or participate in a flow that don't lead
to the reciprocal narrowing
and the need to escape in safety,
but actually get present and take the step off
into sort of like what appears to be the abyss.
And then it's like, oh!
And then you're like, huh.
You know?
Here I am not meeting up my dad's standards,
and here I am not being this,
and here I am being the person that's rejected,
and here I am, and here I still am.
And here I am like so many other people,
and then here I am like living my life,
and then it's just like, and then here I am living.
And then it's like, well, isn't this fascinating
that this is all part of the drama, you know?
And then all of a sudden the relationship to this
is instead of the doer, controller, manipulator,
avoider, defender, it's just the beer, you know?
It's just sort of like, huh.
And of course that is the, that shift when I see it.
And you're like, you start noticing like, what is this am?
Yeah.
The am doesn't seem to,
if you follow me around everywhere,
what is this am, right?
There you go.
Oh, close one day.
There's the beginning of all of it.
Yeah, of the whole new vibe.
Yeah, you start to make that fundamental shift.
And then I think that, you know,
to coach people into the mode of fulfillment,
you know, what is fundamental fulfillment?
And certainly from my vantage point, you know,
it is in the now of, of, of existence in that felt sense
of beingness, being and becoming, the doing is crucial,
but it's, that's means to end shit.
This fundamentally is the eudaimonic point, you know,
that affords the particular capacity,
whether it's by some design, design,
or at least just a hell of a fortunate system
towards neg entropy that affords us what it is like to be
cohering and integrating across multiple levels.
And then to have the reflective felt sense of appreciation for
that, which to me took a little cultivation,
but is now super available.
Yeah.
And that's, that's a nice place.
I remember when you talked about, when you,
when you talked about that of,
I think part of what you mean with that is when you talk about
when wisdom energy,
would you say wisdom energy and in the way you're talking about it,
is in the way you're talking about it, is that, is that.
That felt experience.
Of all of that intelligibility coming through a, like,
you could feel it in your body from the inside out, right?
Exactly.
In a way that you.
Yes.
Yep. So it expanded my, you know, I had my framing or whatever,
but that I did reach another layer,
both above and below my justificatory narrative of expansion
and coherence integration and afforded a presencing of that.
Being this and then basically it was, I am energy.
I'm in this energy information blob.
Okay.
But it's actually the arrangement of my energy information blog
then affords a profound experience of wisdom.
And that's what I meant as wisdom energy.
It's just sort of like, yeah, you know, this,
and it feels the way, you know, it's just walking my dog.
You know, it's just, you know,
it's just the opportunity here for profound sustainability,
meaning it's like, if actually,
if I just relate to myself and the world they particular,
I don't need to, of course I need to eat a few things,
but I mean it's like the consumption and the doing and the,
you know, all of a sudden it's just sort of like, God, you know,
so I kind of know that we've really unwell balanced in this regard.
It's like, what the hell is this? Why don't I just like, you know,
I can just be in love, you know,
basically it's just being in love with existence.
It's just being in love without memory or desire, you know,
and that the ego facility sort of drops in out.
And it is a profound sense of being held.
I really do feel held by the universe.
And at one with it in a particular way in that self other just grip of the world.
And that it's a level of feeling that I think that's what I kind of,
I think I'm like reflecting back with you about this.
To the earlier part of our conversation.
Is it.
It's, it sounds like an embodied optimal grip.
Yeah.
With, with being right.
Like,
That's great.
That's, you know, being John is cognitive science.
This will tend to describe it that way. Yes.
Yeah.
In fact, in fact,
to talk to with John the other day about this about,
because he's been looking a lot more at attachment and he,
the way he described attachment, right, was.
As.
The result and demonstration of, of optimal gripping.
Right.
Of the, this whole thing about that there's, and that's,
it does make sense because it's.
We're not looking at objects, right? There's, it's,
it's dynamical relations all the way down. Right.
We're no something that's, it's, I think, in fact,
I think the mistake is often we start to relate to ourselves as a thing.
Right. That can have something. Right.
But it's really a dynamical affordance of that.
And would you say that, that, that, that you feel.
That resonance that you're talking about that embodied resonance.
It seems like your attachment systems. Right.
Our system. It's what do you feel that through the same?
I don't know if you want to call it circuitry.
That one feels.
Deeply valued.
And a parent relationship. Is it a similar.
Like.
Circus tree.
Yep. Yeah.
Well, I mean.
Yeah.
So certainly at the relational level. Yes. I mean,
I was sort of expanding beyond in terms of the entire self.
And it was, I will, as a social mammal, I'll feel it in relation.
Okay.
But so in terms of, so in terms of my attachments,
just say, let's say with myself. Okay.
Yeah.
The attachment with yourself is the internalized.
Intraject.
The interject is the ego.
Builds its model of the self.
And then build a second order justification system of.
Yeah.
I me relation.
And then starts to hold the standard of self.
Relative reflecting on the self.
The intuitive heart level and self esteem.
And self acceptance refers to the way the interject.
Treats the heart.
Okay. And that then often it's not always the parent,
the way you do it,
but to the internalized other and the normal standards are,
you've internalized the standards of society, the super ego.
So you know,
know what contingent society is going to tell you that's loved
and acceptable.
And then you judge yourself accordingly.
So you jam the shit that's not acceptable into the closet and
other people can't see it. And then you won't,
and you won't lose influence and value.
But then of course you break the structure of coherent integration
across the verticals.
Cause you're now taking a poor aspect of the self that thinks it's
an organismic value in processes like, Hey,
this is how I want to express myself.
You're like, you know,
like my friend who was gay in 1985 is like, you can't be fucking gay.
You know,
you know,
all the homophobia is like jam that shit in the closet.
And you're like, you know,
and then you had to figure out how to come out of the closet.