Excuse me guys, may I have attention please?
Yes.
As you know that guys, we are gathered here to do GD.
So, with your kind permission, may I see at the GD?
Yes, go ahead.
Well, mister.
Well guys, as you know that this is Mr. Prince Khusa from Saunpur.
And you already know that the topic has been given us to discuss about
is social media making us less social or more social.
So, it is a fantabulous topic.
So, from my point of view, is social media making us more social?
Because there are lots of reason behind it.
So, let me explain.
As you know that guys, the social media is that platform
that we connect the each and every persons of any states, any country.
Then you should already know that in this time, they are in the times of holidays.
And every persons are going to tourist place to around that place.
And you should already know that that is why that every person disconnects
with their persons where they live.
And we should already know that through the social media,
that persons connect that peoples where they are lives.
And you should already know that in this times of educations
and in this times of get result of any UP boards, any 12th, 10th result.
Then through the social media, each and every students get that result immediately.
And any information come through the social media.
And in this times, if I talk about the news, then if any events happen in our India,
through the social media, every persons know that how in whatever happened in our country.
And through the social media, we earn more and more money and also we get educations.
And there are lots of peoples who do better in their lives
and get success in their lives through the social media.
And if I talk about likes, there are lots of people say that
there are tons of downloaders of games and there are less downloaders of education channels.
Then you should already know that there are lots of persons who also do better things
and they also do wrong things.
And then if we focus better things, then we can get better.
And as we know that guys through the social media in this times,
every persons like also prime minister like prime minister Modi,
he also get the lecture online also offline.
And there are lots of peoples who doesn't go there to listen their lectures
then also they are able and live in the social media.
And through the social media, we get lots of things.
And also if we feel that the social media making us more social.
So keeping this all pointing to my account, I must say that social media making us more social.
So I invite all of you to join this GD and make this GD more and more successful.
Thank you Mr. for inviting me us in this GD.
First of all I want to say that you said that social media is making us less, means more social.
But I don't think like this. According to me, social media is making us less social.
Why I am saying so let me explain.
You know Mr. you said that due to social media means we can connect,
means each and every person.
I mean who is going anywhere means who is going to celebrate holiday.
That's why means social media is more social.
But don't you think Mr. due to social media means many peoples using in wrong way.
You already know that many peoples means don't focus their career.
Well Mr. as you said that there are lots of peoples through the social media.
They are using social media and they don't focus this career.
Then if I talk about social media then you said I don't know that there are lots of peoples
who use the social media in better way.
And if we think like better, if we think positive then we can go in positive and develop.
Through the social media as you know first listen Mr. through the social media we know current things.
Whatever happened in our country.
So what's your take on this?
But don't you think Mr. you also stated that due to social media means we are lots of money.
But don't you think now this means lots of people means one to increase our subscriber and flower on social media.
Means just like a YouTube and Instagram.
You already know that they are spending lots of money.
If they spend lots of money then absolutely it's a very...
Well Mr.
Well firstly listen.
As you said that there are lots of people spend lots of money to get the subscribers.
As you already know that in the YouTube if your subscribers increase then after some days
you get lots of money according to your views.
And according to your subscriber.
Means when your channel monetize then absolutely firstly you need to do lots of hard work.
Because you can...
Well Mr. could you please tell us that without hard work you get success.
Absolutely if you have intelligence you can get success.
Well Mr.
You already know that also children use social media.
Means they use Instagram and also YouTube for watch comedy video and entertainment.
If they use that...
Then Mr.
Well Mr.
As you said that in this times 80% students do online education.
Firstly listen Mr.
Then why are you talking about only that students who use the social media to see the comedy videos and entertainment.
So if I tell you Mr.
Well Miss
Means whatever you mention in your content sir I am totally disagree with you.
As you said that social media is making us more social.
But from my perspective social media is making us less social.
And why I am saying like this there are tons of reason.
You know Mr.
Now in this time means 99% people out of 100% people use social media.
And they are means child means children's youth is and some person who don't use social media because they are illiterate.
But you know Mr.
If means due to social media means every person disconnect with their family members.
Because you know Mr.
Now in this time every person busy in their cell phones.
And they don't means focus on what's happen in family.
But and you also
How give us in this time
In this time
You also know that means in this time means social media is a very means I want to say that social media make us.
Due to social media we have lack of confidence.
You know Mr.
Now in olden time people used to go to on stage and to share their ideas and views about any topic.
And they means share their thoughts.
And but now
Well Mr.
As you said that
Firstly listen to me.
And now in this time means people hesitate to go on stage and speak something.
They feel signs come in with each other.
Because of social media they are disconnect with their persons.
Well as you said that there are lots of people in olden times do go on stage and give their opinions about the lots of people.
Then in this time you should already know that you are also say that 80% and 100% people are using social media.
Then you should already know that if that persons go to stage and give their opinions throughout some people.
And in this time if you use social media and if we give our opinion in social media
Then there's 100% people give your opinions.
But you know Mr.
People use social media.
And also you said that it means just because of social media.
Many people are distracted from their family.
But Mr.
Now after 10 to 12 people go to other stage to do it.
And just because of social media we are connected from our family members.
And also Mr.
Now is this time of leave.
And it means every people are celebrating holiday.
And just because of that we are connected with our friends.
And then we are taking selfie because we catch the beautiful moments in our camera.
Because if we have that then we can never forget that where we go and where we mistake.
And as you already know that means just because of social media people have less confidence.
Then I would like to tell that in this time there are lots of motivational channel.
And if we see that motivational channel then also we can motivate and also we can get a lot of confidence.
But you know Mr.
You are talking about they can make videos
And share on social media.
But you know Mr.
If all the people means use social media and due to this their eyes means eye problem.
And they will go.
So if we talk about eye problem also.
So if we talk about eye problem on Facebook.
And you also suppose that means people go.
There are lots of cases.
I love accident.
And if we go to miss road then I saw the accident.
Well missed the.
And if there is lots of people gathered in any place then if that person have any enemies
then he also killed that person.
And in the social media you are safe in your home.
Well Mr.
Firstly listen Mr.
As your Mrs. said that in the social media we are lack confidence.
Then as you already said that 80% or 100% people are using social media.
Then if we give our opinions in that platform then we have we are our confidence increase
because there are lots of people.
And if we say any wrong things then lots of people comment your post that it is wrong
and it is bad.
It is bad.
And if you give better opinion then your confidence will increase.
And if you don't better then also your confidence will decrease because and you do better that
that.
Sorry point of some can I say something here.
Yeah.
Well Mr.
And you said that means due to social media means people means go anywhere means they
go with any person.
But don't you think Mr.
Means also due to social media people is going to become lazy person because they are not
going to work they are not means also children are not going to play I mean any type of game
just like you can see means they go I mean any field they play game.
If they don't play then absolutely they are not going to miss keep their body fit at the
health.
So Mr.
I don't know Mr.