If you actually look at the story of Jesus, it's an insane story because even if you know
traditional storytelling, it's like you don't have stories where someone is like a warrior and a king
and a shepherd and a worker and a monk and he's like all these categories jammed into this one
story like this doesn't make sense but that's the point. Grab all these story structures, these
aspects of the gods. It's interesting because a lot of the people that have tried to criticize
Christianity will say well Jesus is just a copy on all these old gods and it's like yeah I mean
all of them like every single one of them like he's all these weird things that would never
for a pagan be brought together and so it's like that's it so it's like you look at the image of
that person on the throne and it's like it's that that condensation and then that person he is the
source but he also ends up being the judge because he's the standard by which all the
multiple aspects get compared to or the through line.