Welcome back. I hope that our first few lectures on bonding and molecular structure have piqued
your interest in the relationship between those structures and the physical and chemical
properties that they lead to in organic compounds. Of course, observation of these properties
takes time, so we can't just rely on a static snapshot of a structure to tell the whole
story. Let me show you an example. Here I have a molecule called acrolein. Acrolein is a
potent toxin found in cigarette smoke. It's also used in commercial biocides, and its
reactivity is similar to that of formaldehyde, so it finds use as a fixative agent, preserving
biological samples. Now, in textbooks and in papers, acrolein is commonly drawn in this
configuration. And yet, something about this configuration doesn't make sense to us. There's
a carbon-carbon double bond, a carbon-carbon single bond, and a carbon-oxygen double bond
in this molecule, which means the central bond should rotate freely. Yet, when we use
the static structure like this one and try to model its behavior, we see that this kind
of rotation doesn't happen. And so the chemical properties of acrolein, like its boiling point,
its acid-base properties, are all different than the prediction based upon this model.
So we find the carbon-oxygen bond dipole here is actually larger than the structure predicts,
and that electron density around these carbons is not the same. So clearly there's something
going on here that this static model just can't explain. Now, so far we've concerned
ourselves primarily with the drawing of molecular structures, these stationary, unchanging representations
of molecules in their most ideal states. They'll have median bond lengths and angles and dihedrals
just the way that we want them. Now, as useful as it is to have these representations, showing
compounds in their most stable, ideal states, as chemists we're ultimately concerned with
materials physical and chemical properties in the real world, where bonds vibrate, electrons
move through clouds, and those bonds change. So the physical and chemical changes would
be best communicated not by a single ideal representation, but by how the molecule truly
behaves as time passes. So we need to develop a method for communicating how substances behave
and change through time, instead of just a single instantaneous ideal snapshot. We naturally
benefit from a method which is generally accepted by all chemists so that we can give one another
all the information we need to reach a common understanding of chemical processes as well
as physical processes. In this lecture I'll show you how to create drawings which depict
the transfer of electrons from one location to another in order to form and break chemical
bonds. Some of these motions will be intramolecular, meaning they take place within a single molecule,
and others will be intermolecular, meaning that they take place between two or more molecules.
In all cases, the relocation of electrons will result in the formation, alteration, or breaking
of connections between atoms. Get ready, chemistry is about to come alive.
So let's begin with an intramolecular process called resonance. Electrons within an electron
cloud are always in motion, and we've already seen in one of our previous lectures that
pi bonds have a unique ability to form and break without altering the connectivity of
atoms, and since the stronger sigma bonds can remain intact while the weaker pi bonds are
broken. So electron pairs which are not involved in bonding at all, sometimes called lone
pair electrons and pi bonding electrons, can be made more mobile within a molecule's
overall electron cloud. Now these electrons can sometimes occupy a region much larger
than just that defined by a hybrid orbital or an isolated pi bond. They can traverse
great distances across molecules using p orbitals without disrupting the connectivity of the
atoms. These long interconnected systems of p orbitals, sometimes called pi systems.
So as electrons move through the pi systems, no reaction is really taking place, but our
method of drawing an individual structure begins to fail. We're already familiar with
today's acrolein molecule, and I drew it like this just the way that I had represented it
in the model that I showed you previously. But the problem is that the pi electrons in
acrolein want more space. They want to run throughout the molecule, and if given a chance
to do so, that's exactly what they'll do. Now if you look at the acrolein structure,
you'll see many, many sp2 carbons and even an sp2 oxygen all arranged in a row. Now if
I show you the molecule on its side, it'll probably make a little bit more sense what's
happening here. I'm going to take the hydrogens away so it's easier to see, and I'm going
to turn my acrolein molecule. Now these are the p orbitals participating in pi bonding.
So even though I've drawn it here with an isolated pi bond on alternating carbons, the
truth of the matter is that pi system is completely interconnected. So when the bonds are arranged
appropriately so that all p orbitals are aligned, the electrons can run throughout the molecule.
So I need a way to represent acrolein, which is a little bit more realistic. And we do
this by breaking the structure down and drawing every conceivable extreme. For example, here
I have three duplicates of my acrolein structure, but I'm going to alter them, remembering my
rule. Sigma bonds can't break, only pi bonds can move. So let's take a look at what happens
when I do this to my first structure on the left. I'm going to move one pi bond up to
the oxygen, creating a charge separation. In my other one here, I'm going to relocate
both of those pi bonds, one to the oxygen and one to the central carbon-carbon bond,
creating a different kind of charge separation. And my third I'm going to leave exactly as
it was. So these extremes of electron motion that we draw in this type of way are called
resonance contributors. And you'll see this drawn in the chemical literature and in your
textbooks. But what happens when you see that, or at least when a trained chemist does, is
this. They mentally combine all of those resonance contributors into a single resonance hybrid,
which is essentially the weighted average of these three structures. In my resonance
hybrid, I can understand why there is no rotation or limited rotation about that central bond,
because it has a little bit of pi character, which my static structure that I drew originally
would not predict. So this is the utility of thinking more about the motion of electrons
through time than about a single instantaneous snapshot of my molecule. So in that drawing,
I had brackets and straight double-headed arrows, giving me my cue to create the best
possible approximation of acrylene structure. And I did this by mentally combining them
all into that new weighted average called the resonance hybrid. And it will help me
to predict the reactivity and properties of acrylene much better. But it's important to
remember that hybrid is a weighted average, meaning that the contributors with less charge
separation and more ideal electron positions tend to be a closer representation of the hybrid
than their charge-containing counterparts. Now, creating a static depiction of a system
changing through time can be a challenging undertaking, but one which humanity has deemed
worthy since prehistory. Just ask cave painters of Paleolithic Europe and Africa. They tried to
document their hunts with just a few simple markings on a cave wall. Or if you don't have a
time machine, ask any modern-day comic strip author. The comic strip artists try to tell
a story using a storyboard of static images, depicting different moments within the narrative.
And it's up to us as readers to combine these images in our minds to create a seamless running
story. For example, here's Garfield holding a piece of pie, and then suddenly in the next
frame, pie's gone. But where did it go? Well, as the readers, we have to rely on our experience
and our intuition to tell us how that transition occurred. I'm pretty sure I know where the
pie went. Now, organic chemistry is no different than that comic strip. I might show you the
chemical structures, for example, of ammonium cyanate and urea. But unless I give it greater
detail, it's up to you to decide how you think the transition took place, using your understanding
of how organic chemistry works. Of course, technologies progress to the point at which
we don't often have to perform this exercise anymore. Computer animation fills in all the
gaps and gives us maximum detail about how a process takes place. But even with the advantages
of modern technology, fully animating a story is not always the best choice. It certainly
leaves out most ambiguities, but it requires a great deal of effort to create, and also
special devices to view. So for the purposes of day-to-day communication, chemists prefer
to use a faster, shorthand style of depicting reactions that's developed over the centuries.
Now, last time, we took a detailed look at methods chemists use to unambiguously convey
molecular structures to one another. And in this lecture, we'll be taking a detailed
look at how organic chemists convey changes in those structures through time. Specifically,
how the chemical energy of a system changes, and how the bonding between and among atoms
changes when that chemistry takes place. So let's begin with the simplest possible illustration
of a chemical change, a reaction scheme. Now chemists often don't know or feel the need
to convey minute mechanistic details of a chemical reaction as it takes place. And sometimes
their arguments simply depends on what was present at the beginning of the reaction and
what was present at the end. For example, if we just want to give the basic details
of a reaction, we rely on something called a reaction scheme. The reaction scheme consists
of reagents on the left side, products on the right side, an arrow which indicates whether
the reaction is reversible or not, we'll get to that in a moment, and also any special
conditions which are required for the reaction to take place. A great example of this is
the reaction scheme used by Friedrich Wohler to synthesize urea. Remember, his reagent
was ammonium cyanane. His products ultimately were urea. The reaction runs irreversibly,
meaning that it completely and quantitatively converts all of the reagents into products.
And the conditions that he used were simply heating. We represent heat sometimes with
the capital Greek letter delta. So this is how Wohler's synthesis would appear if I
were to write it as a reaction scheme. I have the synthesis of urea formed from ammonium
cyanate in an irreversible process driven by heat. Now it's that last element of the
scheme that requires a little bit more explanation. See, chemists distinguish between reactions
which can be reversed from those and those which cannot. So in a reaction like Wohler's
synthesis, the product formed is so stable that once it forms, it can never go back to
the original starting materials through the reverse pathway. Of course, this means that
if we wait long enough, the reaction will eventually result in the complete conversion
of reactants to products. And as the course progresses, we'll eventually see why this
is so important to make a distinction like this when plotting out a synthesis. So now
that we have our completed scheme for Wohler's irreversible synthesis of urea, let's take
a look at a scheme for another famous reaction, which this time is reversible. Another classic
example of a reaction scheme is a Haber-Bosch process, which one might argue is not truly
organic since carbon is not involved, but it's probably the single most influential
chemical reaction of all time. And it's a critical entry point for nitrogen into the
biosphere. So I'm going to exercise the professor's privilege here and step outside the bounds
of my own discipline for just a moment. During World War I, with Germany facing dwindling
natural resources to fuel their war efforts, famous German chemists Fritz Haber and Karl
Bosch were engaged in a project to provide Germany with all the fixed nitrogen it could
ever need for explosives and crop fertilization. The scheme that Haber used looks like this.
As reagents, he used nitrogen gas and hydrogen gas. For products, he was hoping to get ammonia.
And what Haber realized was that in order to accomplish this, he was going to have some
trouble because he had a reversible process. But he could get it to go if he ran it at
400 degrees centigrade and 200 atmospheres of pressure in the presence of an iron catalyst,
which speeds the reaction but doesn't really participate in it overall. That's why we place
the iron here in the conditions rather than as a reagent. So Haber's scheme was, again,
to try to get nitrogen and hydrogen to combine in a reversible process at 400 degrees and
200 atmospheres of pressure with an iron catalyst, all to make ammonia. So you'll notice in
this case that I've placed some numbers in front of my reagents here. And those numbers
indicate a quantity. So you'll hear me from time to time refer to three moles of hydrogen
or two moles of ammonia. This is because chemists usually count molecules using a very large
quantity. It's no different than a dozen or a gross. So if I need a dozen eggs to make
two dozen cookies, you now know the ratio needed. So if I need three moles of hydrogen
to make two moles of ammonia, again, you know the ratio that's needed. So the only difference
here is that in chemistry, we're counting atoms and molecules. So a mole is tremendous
in quantity by comparison. 6.02 times 10 to the 23rd to be exact. So my reaction here
involves one mole of nitrogen gas reacting with three molar equivalents of hydrogen
to produce two moles of ammonia. And it would be a great way to make ammonia from the air
if we could convert it into this much needed ammonia. The only problem here is the reaction
is reversible. So once it's formed, the ammonia can convert back to hydrogen and nitrogen
gases, thereby completely undoing the reaction. So as the concentration of ammonia builds,
the reverse reaction accelerates until it matches out of the forward reaction, establishing
what chemists call an equilibrium. The problem that Haber and Bosch faced is that ammonia
decomposes to nitrogen and hydrogen very rapidly under common laboratory conditions, so only
a small fraction of material in the reactor will be ammonia at any given time. So equilibrium
is defined as a dynamic process in which the forward and reverse reaction rates are equal.
And it's a common misconception actually that equilibrium means equal amounts of both
products and reactants, but this is really not the case at all, much to the chagrin
of Haber and Bosch. So let me show you what I mean by that. We model equilibria as chemists
using something called an equilibrium constant, which is written as the capital letter K. Now
in the equilibrium constant we place a function of the products in the numerator, a function
of the reagents in the denominator, and we raise those functions to a power equal to
their coefficients in the reaction. So here I've created a sort of generic reaction,
one mole of reagent A plus three moles of reagent B forms two moles of product C. So to construct
the equilibrium constant K, I simply place my product's concentration, which we indicate
by brackets, raised to the power of two for its coefficient. I place my first reagent
in the denominator, raised to a power of one, and my second reagent also in the denominator,
raised to a power of three. So this is my general equilibrium constant for this type
of reaction. So Haber and Bosch were attempting to use nitrogen, hydrogen, and ammonia in
an equilibrium process, meaning that its equilibrium constant expression will look like this, concentration
of ammonia squared over concentration of nitrogen over concentration of hydrogen cubed equals
ten to the minus sixth. This is a highly disfavored equilibrium. So this reaction is capable of
producing only a small amount of ammonia once equilibrium is reached. So the scheme
that Haber and Bosch were hoping to use to create ammonia from nitrogen and hydrogen,
unfortunately at equilibrium didn't look much like this, instead it looked a little
bit like this. So the genius of what Haber and Bosch did was not in this reaction that
they used. In fact, it's a pretty simple reaction. The genius of what Haber and Bosch accomplished
was in their reactor design, which altered the conditions of pressure and temperature,
increasing both of these factors to speed the rate of ammonia formation relative to
the rate of its decomposition. So they influenced the equilibrium in a manner which suited their
needs. But even that strategy didn't produce large quantities of ammonia at equilibrium.
So in a final manipulation, they devised a way to remove ammonia from the reactor as
it formed, thereby causing the equilibrium to shift continuously in favor of their desired
products. This tendency of reversible systems to shift in ways which relieve stresses like
removal of product is known as Le Chatelier's principle. Now at this early stage, reversible
reactions may seem like a nuisance. After all, wouldn't it be great if we could just
mix some ingredients, wait for a little while, and ultimately have the maximum possible amount
of product? Sure, many times it would. But later in the course, we're going to see some
examples of reactions whose reversibility makes them even more useful in synthetic design.
So far our drawing examples have been limited in the sense that they convey a great deal
about what we start and end with, but relatively little about what goes on in the interim.
And since reaction schemes only show a list of starting materials and products, we're
often left to wonder exactly how those materials go about changing. One might make the analogy
that it's like having a pile of boards, screws, and other pieces, and then a picture of a
finished table when assembled, but our step-by-step manual is missing. So when organic chemists
want to convey a process in a little more detail, they turn to a style of drawing known
as a mechanism. And a mechanism, just like that manual for assembling their table, it's
a series of elementary steps showing not only the starting material, reversibility, conditions
and products, but also explicitly showing how electrons from each species are exchanged
to make and break bonds. So let's take a look at Wohler's Synthesis one more time
as an example, knowing that chemists now understand what happened during that happy accident.
So our scheme only showed the starting material and products, but let's see if we can fill
in some of the gaps now. So once again, here is Wohler's Synthesis. Ammonium cyanate
and forming urea. But if I break this reaction down to elementary steps, I see that there
are different compounds which form as intermediates, specifically ammonia and cyanic acid, and ultimately
a charge-separated intermediate, before it finally becomes urea. So Wohler's Synthesis,
as I showed you before, left out a lot of information. There's actually quite a few
additional species involved in the transition. But that's still not enough information.
If you look at this now, it's sort of like reading that comic strip. We might have multiple
pains in the comic, but we still haven't really clearly defined how one transition
occurs and forms the next. Now to do this, we use a mechanism. And a mechanism consists
of not only the structures of all of these species, but arrows indicating how and when
electrons move. For example, here's a representation of ammonium and of cyanate. And I've colored
the nitrogens just a little bit different shades of blue so they're easier to follow
through the process. So I could skip ahead and draw the new structures for ammonia and
cyanic acid, but that would leave you wondering how the transition happened. So to fill in
that gap, I'm going to use some arrows. When I use an arrow like this, I'm trying to show
you that a pair of electrons is moving from this nitrogen to this hydrogen, abstracting
it, forming a new chemical bond to it. As that happens, the original chemical bond breaks,
and that pair of electrons moves back to the nitrogen of the ammonium ion. Now I can draw
this intermediate in my process, and it's absolutely clear how it got that way. In a
second fundamental step, I have my ammonia reacting with the cyanic acid, which was produced,
forming a new bond between the nitrogen and carbon, and breaking a pi bond between the
carbon and the original nitrogen of the cyanic acid. This produces a charged intermediate
in which there's a rearrangement where one of the hydrogens moves from my nitrogen here
to my nitrogen down below, breaking that bond. Now I can complete my mechanism, and it becomes
clear exactly how we got from this point to this point, including each individual bond
forming and breaking. And this is the value of a mechanism. It gives us the maximum level
of detail. So we're now acquainted with the techniques used not only to draw molecular
structures, but the elements of drawings used to convey elementary steps, and the electron
transitions which take place in each one. But there's one more piece of information
which is crucial to understanding how these transitions occur, and that is the chemical
energetics of the process. You see, just like in classical physics, chemists think in terms
of potential energy. And just like a physical object, like a ball, is expected to roll down
a hill, thereby decreasing its potential physical energy and reaching a more stable state, so
will a molecular system react in a way which decreases its overall potential chemical energy,
also making it more stable. The difference is that chemical energy is a bit less intuitive
to determine. Still, to fully understand the process of a chemical reaction, we need a
quick and convenient method for demonstrating whether a particular transition increases
or decreases the overall chemical free energy of the system, and by how much. And to better
understand this concept, we should consider a simple example like that ball perched on
a hilltop. Classical physics tells us that the potential energy of that ball in its current
position is higher than that of the same ball at the bottom of the hill. So we can see from
the diagram that when we give it a small push to overcome the barrier, which would be friction
or a small hill preventing it from rolling in the first place, the ball will spontaneously
roll downward, presumably coming to rest at the bottom of the hill in the lowest energy
state available. Chemical systems are a perfect analogy for this physical system that I just
described. Just as that ball has an associated physical potential energy, which it would
like to release, so does a collection of molecules have an associated chemical free energy that
it would like to release. When a small energetic barrier is overcome by the addition of heat,
catalyst or some other perturbation, the system can then convert spontaneously to its lower
energy state. Now chemists often convey this energetic landscape for a chemical reaction
using this hill analogy, and we call it a reaction coordinate diagram. The only difference
here is that the hill is one of chemical potential energy rather than one of physical potential
energy. So the diagrams are essentially a plot of system free energy as a function of
reaction progress. So let's finish our discussion today by applying this diagram to Wohler's
Urea Synthesis, and recall that the mechanism for this process involves starting materials,
products, and two different intermediate states, which are meta-stable, and they can exist
for a little while. So we begin by defining the original energy of the system as the y
intercept of our plot, and the first step of our reaction begins with a new bond forming
to hydrogen while its original bond breaks. So this process actually increases the energy
of the system until we reach a maximum energy for the step. The structure at that local
energy maximum is called the transition state. Now at first it might seem strange to suggest
that the system is going to move energetically uphill. After all, balls aren't known to roll
suddenly uphill without a little outside help. And the same is actually true of chemical
systems, but often the help is already there. It's all around us permeating every object
in this room. Of course I'm talking about heat. At all temperatures but absolute zero,
there will be some molecular motion, bond vibration, molecular collisions, and other
kinds of motions. And so long as there's sufficient thermal energy in a system to get it over
that initial barrier from starting materials to the transition state, the reaction will
take place. Now we call that activation, that barrier activation energy as you already know.
And just as you might expect, often the addition of heat to a reaction mixture is all it needs
to traverse that barrier, thereby speeding the reaction up. Now as that first step winds
down, we see that the energy of the system begins to decrease to a local minimum. But
in this case it has a second energetic hill to climb on its way to the final product.
So we call this local minimum an intermediate. And it's distinct from transition states because
it has a small energy well there which makes it metastable so it can exist in measurable
amounts while the reaction is running. In the next step ammonia forms its bond to the
newly formed cyanic acid. Again this increases the energy of the system initially to a point
representing the transition state for that process. After that new bond formation completes
and the system reaches another metastable state. We finally conclude the reaction with
the reorganization of the product by an intramolecular exchange of a hydrogen. So we've created an
energy diagram here for the entire process of converting ammonium cyanate into urea
in three steps. Now let's review the relevance of all the features of this diagram.
Our starting materials must pass through a transition state to become the first intermediates
ammonia and cyanic acid. The diagram tells me two important things. First that the reaction
will happen quickly because the energetic barrier is relatively low. And second that
a large amount of this intermediate will exist in equilibrium with the starting material
because the intermediate is lower in energy. The second step of the mechanism reaches a
considerably higher transition state energy which tells me that this is a rate limiting
step of the reaction. Since this step is expected to proceed much more slowly than the others
by virtue of the energy change taking place. Finally the intramolecular proton relocation
or hydrogen relocation takes place quickly and irreversibly once that last intermediate
has formed. This creates a product of greater stability than the original starting materials
and my reaction is complete. So today we've taken a look at how chemists communicate chemical
transitions to one another. We do this in much the same way that a cartoonist tells
a story with pains showing punctuated depictions of a system as it undergoes changes. We started
with the phenomenon of resonance or delocalization of electrons. And we talked about how multiple
resonance contributors contained in brackets and separated by straight two headed arrows
can be mentally combined in a mathematical average to produce the resonance hybrid.
We looked at how to write a reaction scheme which communicates the four crucial details
of a reaction, the starting materials, the products, the conditions and the reversibility.
And we discussed how the choice of arrows separating the starting materials and products
give us a little bit of information about that reversibility. Then we explored the art
of depicting mechanisms in which schemes are expanded into their elementary steps and the
motion of electrons is indicated by curved arrows pointing from the original location
to their final destination in a given step. And finally we took a look at a reaction coordinate
diagram and how it shows us the energetic landscape of a chemical change making such
details as the transition state and intermediate energies and rate limiting steps all evident
to us. As we progress through the remainder of this course, we're going to rely heavily
on what we've learned regarding chemical drawing. And next time we'll put some of these drawing
skills into practice as we investigate the acid based properties of organic compounds.
I'll see you then.