Today, I'm going to show you how to do the impossible.
Okay, it's a little bit dramatic, but not entirely inaccurate.
Now what would you say if I told you that I know how to deprotonate an alkane?
Now remember, the hydrogens of an aliphatic alkane, like the hydrogens in a molecule of ethane, for example,
are the single weakest acids of any compound that we've studied to date, with a pKa of somewhere around 60.
Now that's literally trillions of times less acidic than alkenes,
which are themselves trillions of times less acidic than alkynes,
which are an extraordinarily weak acid in their own right.
But if we could deprotonate an alkane, just imagine what a powerful nucleophile the resulting carbanion would be.
It's a tempting target, isn't it? But how do we do it?
So if we were to have a go at creating such a motif using proton transfer,
we would need a base whose conjugate acid has a pKa of at least 60.
But what would such a base be? Right, the only option would be deprotonated alkane,
so we're right back at our original problem.
Okay, you've got me here. This is a little bit of a trick question.
It really is just about impossible to deprotonate an alkane under any kind of sensible laboratory conditions.
But there is a class of compounds which can be made to act like carbanions.
In order to do this, we have to abandon the safety and simplicity of the first few rows of the periodic table.
We have to use a remarkable marriage between the usual suspects of organic chemistry,
like carbon, nitrogen, and oxygen, and a newcomer to our discussion, metals.
Today we're going to investigate a small slice of a field known as organometallic chemistry.
Now, before I continue, I need to advise you that we're only going to look at a very small set of organometallic compounds and reactions.
Organometallic chemistry is used in a wide variety of applications, as we'll soon see,
and it's a science worthy of its own graduate level course when considered in its entirety.
Organometallic chemistry as a proper science got its start in a familiar place,
the lab of Alexander Butlarov at the University of Kazan in 1800s Russia.
Butlarov had noticed that dialkyl zinc reagents, or chemicals containing
two organic alkyl groups bonded directly to a zinc atom through their carbons,
could be used to produce alcohols from ketones by transferring their alkyl group
to the carbonyl carbon of the ketone.
No doubt excited about the prospect of developing a new method for the formation of carbon-carbon bonds,
Butlarov passed this project on to his protege, Alexander Zetsiv.
Zetsiv was able to apply his chemistry to several new substrates, but always with limited success.
These zinc-based reagents proved to be unpredictable and difficult to work with,
and as the sun set on Zetsiv's career, he seemed no closer to developing
reliable methods or rules for their use in synthesis.
It would appear that this particular line of research was destined for obscurity.
Then, in 1900, a young French graduate student by the name of Victor Grignard
blew the lid off of organometallic chemistry when he devised a powerful,
versatile, and adaptable organometallic reagent for use in the reliable production
of carbon-carbon bonds, which had eluded Butlarov and Zetsiv.
Grignard's story is truly inspirational for anyone struggling with their schooling.
He took a long and winding road through his college education,
and after starting as a secondary education student,
he failed to pass a standardized math examination, which landed him in the military for a short time.
When he returned from his service, he managed to move ahead with his education,
ultimately finding himself working in the lab of Philippe Barbier
at the University of Lyon in France in the late 1890s.
It was there, in Barbier's lab at Lyon, conducting experiments for his doctoral dissertation
that Grignard acted on a hunch, replacing the zinc from the only widely known class
of organometallics of the day with what he believed would be more reactive magnesium.
One of his first reactions was the combination of isoamyl bromide
with magnesium followed by carbon dioxide.
And the reaction produced what Grignard himself described as, quoting here,
a colorless liquid, distinctly of acidic character, with an odor of perspiration,
and at the same time of butter.
So it sounds like Grignard was really suffering for his science,
having chosen the reaction which produces the fragrance reminiscent of sweaty butter.
Nonetheless, I'm sure he was glad that he did, since his work not only earned him his doctorate,
but one half of the Nobel Prize 12 years later.
His co-recipient was his countryman Sabatier for his metal-catalyzed hydrogen addition reactions.
So let's take a look at a Grignard reaction. In fact, one of the original Grignard reactions
conducted by Victor Grignard himself.
Now this is a bit of an oversimplification, but it all holds true what's going on.
Victor Grignard started with the reagent isoamyl bromide, which is an alkyl halide.
To this he added magnesium. So when mixed with magnesium, isoamyl bromide
creates this new compound where the magnesium has been inserted between the carbon and bromine atoms.
So the consequence of this is, we placed our metal next to a carbon.
Now here's where organometallic chemistry really starts to differ from what we're used to seeing.
Magnesium has a very low electronegativity. And because of that, it creates a very strong
dipole with the negative end pointed towards the carbon. So this very high electron density
near the carbon to which the magnesium is bonded makes it act more like a carbon ion.
So we can think of it as being this even though we know that this species is very difficult to generate.
So Grignard mixed this Grignard reagent which acts like a carbon ion with carbon dioxide,
which has a very electrophilic carbon, the only carbon in the molecule of course.
So when we combine a very powerful nucleophile which acts like a carbon ion with a very good
electrophile such as carbon dioxide, we should all be well aware of what's going to happen next.
Nucleophilic attack creates a new carbon-carbon bond. And acidifying gives us our final product,
isocoprolic acid or isoamyl acid. Of course when Grignard made it, his reagent was not a
carbon ion but an alkyl magnesium bromide reagent, which means that we also have to
account for the magnesium in the bromine. Now what happens to them during the nucleophilic attack
is a bit complicated and case specific. But at the end of the reaction, the byproduct is magnesium
hydroxy bromide. So here we can see one of the driving forces behind the Grignard reaction.
Notice that what started as a neutral magnesium atom is now a magnesium 2 plus ion with a full octet.
So powerful is the desire for magnesium to have that octet that it can be used to drive carbon-carbon
bond formation. Grignard continued his research and discovered that his new nucleophile could be
used reliably to produce acids from carbon dioxide, secondary alcohols from aldehydes,
and also tertiary alcohols from ketones. In fact, Grignards are extremely versatile offering not
only ways to make alcohols and acids but also aldehydes from amides, tertiary alcohols from esters,
and many, many other reactions. It seems that when Grignard reagents are involved,
it's pretty much open season on anything with a carbonyl group.
But there is much more to the Grignard reaction. Easy though it is to run, there are certain
special considerations which must be taken to ensure its success, two in particular.
First, the Grignard reagent itself is only stable in ether solvents like diethyl ether or tetrahydrofuran.
Second, the reaction mixture has to be kept extraordinarily free of protic solvents including
water. So let's consider each of these two restraints individually then collectively.
One of the great limitations of Grignard reactions is that alkyl magnesium halide reagents
can only form in ether solvents. But why is this? The answer lies in the ability of solvents to
coordinate metals. Now what I mean by this is that the solvent must have oxygen atoms with
lone pairs which can stabilize the Grignard by donating electrons to form a stabilizing
metal oxygen interaction in solution. That alkyl magnesium halide motif is so polar that it needs
a solvent which will be able to arrange its dipole beneficially to interact with the positive
charge density at the magnesium. For this purpose ether solvents are just the ticket.
Nonpolar solvents like hexanes or benzene are not capable of forming these kinds of
stabilizing interactions so they are clearly out as a solvent.
So Grignard reagents are polar. They're really polar. We get that. So why can't we use more
polar solvents like ethanol to dissolve them for reactions? Certainly ethanol has enough
polar oomph to get this reagent to form in solution, right? Well it does but with one devastating caveat.
Unlike ether, ethanol is protic and has a pKa of about 17. Remember, Grignards react like
carbon ions whose conjugate acid has a pKa of about 60. So a Grignard reagent might form an ethanol
for just a split second before reacting with that ethanol to form ethoxide and a hydrocarbon.
Clearly this is not a good way to make a Grignard. Now ethers like diethyl ether
and tetrahydrofuran are special because they strike a balance between their ability to
solvate a Grignard with their inability to react with it. And this is why they have been the preferred
solvent for this sort of reaction from 1900 right up until today. But using ether and THF
tetrahydrofuran isn't enough because these solvents are slightly polar. So ether can dissolve a small
bit of water itself. In fact, when left opened a bottle of ether will absorb about 1.5% of its
own mass in water from the atmosphere. So a bottle of ether left open by a careless colleague or
even simply one which has been opened and closed enough times to allow a small amount of air into
it can contain enough water to effectively ruin a Grignard synthesis. Our solution to this is to use
ether which has been chemically dried before use. And we accomplish this through the use of inorganic
drying agents like magnesium sulfate or a special kind of material called molecular sieves which
act like little mineral sponges absorbing the water from the ether and trapping it as a solid
complex which we can simply filter or decant to separate. Grignard reagents are an incredibly
versatile tool for attaching new carbons to electrophiles. So let's take a moment and summarize
just a few of the tools in the Grignard toolbox and their limitations. First, Grignards are made
using alkyl halide and magnesium metal mixed in an ethereal solvent. But they're not limited to
aliphatic R groups. Commonly used Grignards include unsaturated groups also like allyl
magnesium bromide and phenyl magnesium bromide. Grignard reagents provide a way to
access the kind of reactivity we would expect to get from an aliphatic carbanion without the
fuss of having to deprotonate one of the least acidic hydrogens known to man, the alkane CH bond.
Grignards can be reacted with carbon dioxide to form organic acids,
with aldehydes to form secondary alcohols and with ketones to form tertiary alcohols.
They can attack secondary imines to form secondary amides with varying degrees of branching.
Carbonyl compounds with leaving groups like acid chlorides attached to the carbon can undergo
multiple attacks by Grignard reagents, resulting in the addition of two alkyl groups giving us
an alternate route to make secondary or tertiary alcohols. So far today we've discussed the use
of metals to activate hydrocarbons and turn them into nucleophiles. Of course, organometallic
chemistry is far more varied and complex as a subject than just this small window on the science
would appear to imply. Organometallics have found their first few applications in the world of
organic synthesis, but their real potential cannot be appreciated until we take a look at another one
of their uses, catalysis. The use of organometallics harkens back to our old friend Sabatier, who
developed the technique for hydrogenating fats using platinum metal and who incidentally shared
the Nobel Prize with Victor Grignard. In modern laboratories, the reduction of alkenes to
alkanes is still a widely used technique, but the heterogeneous nature of Sabatier's method
leaves a lot to be desired. Hydrogenating double bonds at the surface of a solid catalyst may work
well on industrial scales, but in the laboratory a reaction which takes place in solution is far
more desirable. If we had access to a homogeneous catalyst, one which could be dissolved in
organic solvents along with substrates, we could run reactions much more efficiently and cleanly
in the lab, wasting less reagents and amplifying our yields. But the problem with this is that
metals themselves are not generally soluble in the kinds of solvents that one would use to dissolve
an alkene. But in 1966, a British chemist by the name of Jeffrey Wilkinson published a paper
outlining a way to solubilize a large transition metal like rhodium by bonding it to organic
molecules which we call ligands. These ligands are specially designed to be strong Lewis bases
which donate stabilizing electron pairs to the metal ion, forming a complex which gives it the
solubility characteristics of the ligands while retaining the catalytic activities of the metal.
Wilkinson's work is generally regarded as the seminal work in the field of organometallic
chemistry. His discoveries in this field launched an age of investigation into metal
ligand interactions that continues to this day in labs around the world. Wilkinson's work
has inspired the creation of some really exciting and exotic looking complexes.
You'll see extensions of his work in such life-changing compounds as
contrast reagents used for MRI imaging. The magnetic properties of many large metals make
them useful as tools to enhance the sensitivity of MRI imaging machines. But the problem is
that most heavy metals are highly toxic by themselves or don't accumulate in the necessary
tissues for them to be useful. The gadolinium ion is one perfect example of this.
Now when gadolinium is in its plus three state, it's a powerful atomic-sized magnet
and its presence is easily detected by such complex magnetic instruments as the MRI you
may see in a hospital. Unfortunately the gadolinium itself is very toxic and doesn't accumulate well
where we need it. So one solution to this problem is to complex metal ions with organic ligands
which render them far less toxic and also can cause them to selectively accumulate in areas
of interest in the body assisting in the imaging process. A classic example of this is the complex
of gadolinium-3 which is marketed under the trade name Dota-REM. Now gadolinium itself is an f-block
metal and its three plus ion contains seven electrons filling its f-sub shell or its outermost
sub-shell. Now electrons like their space so those seven outermost electrons in the f-block
of or in the f orbitals of gadolinium are unpaired and this gives it a tremendously powerful
magnetization. So this tiny little ion of gadolinium is producing an extremely powerful
magnetic field but only at atomic distances. Now Dota-REM is an ingenious way to exploit the
magnetic properties of gadolinium ions like this without dealing with toxicity issues and
solubility problems. Now this is accomplished using a complex organic ligand which looks like this.
Now we call molecules with large rings of many atoms like this one macro cycles and the key to
Dota-REM's safety and efficacy is not only this macrocyclic ligand which sits on top of the metal
but it allows it to attach its carboxylates around the edges. So these nitrogens and carboxylates
contain lone perelectrons and regions of dense negative charge which coordinate to the gadolinium
three ion. So this forms a cage around the ion preventing it from reacting with anything as it
circulates in your bloodstream and the ligands also have the effect of changing the solubility
characteristics of the complex presenting an organic phase instead of an ionic phase
and this helps the Dota-REM accumulate in tumor cells. Now the final piece of the puzzle is this
last little bit of space on the bottom which is complexed to the oxygen of a water molecule.
So we place our water molecule under there you can see how close it is to the protected gadolinium
ion. The proximity of the water molecule to that gadolinium three makes it very easy to detect
using an MRI machine and physicians can then use MRI techniques to look for the magnetic effects
of the gadolinium three on the water molecule inside the patient thereby helping them locate
an image problem areas. Now not to be outdone by modern chemists nature herself has also devised
ways to use organic molecules which help not just humans but all other known species to get the
benefits of the chemistry of metals while coping with their inherent toxicities.
So let's take a look at a subunit of the structure of human hemoglobin it's a pretty big molecule
isn't it but if I remove all the protein atoms we see that leftover is a large cyclic ligand
known as a porphyrin and this porphyrin coordinates an iron atom in the center from four planar
positions. This metal ligand complex is commonly called heme and is the namesake of the oxygen
carrying protein hemoglobin. Now free iron is toxic in the blood but it's the coordination
of these four nitrogen atoms and also two histidines which come in from the protein itself
which give this molecule its life-sustaining ability to bind transport and release oxygen in the body
without being toxic to us. Now the heme ligand not only plays a role in oxygen carrying ability
of hemoglobin but its highly conjugated structure also makes it highly colored. Now when the iron
with the iron in place rather the heme takes on a familiar deep red color that we associate with
oxygenated blood but when physical trauma causes cells in the body to rupture and die the exposed
heme from their hemoglobin has to be cleaned up and this is done by enzymes which first break open
the ligand and this breaking of the ring forms a new compound known as biliverdin. It's a dark
green colored compound. The biliverdin is then further reduced into a compound known as bilirubin
which is yellow in color and this is the process of cleaning up a porphyrin ligand and it's also
what we commonly associate with the process of bruising. So the colors that you see underneath
the skin are actually the free heme from the traumatized cells being cleaned up by your own body
but nature's gone far beyond just using iron ions and porphyrin ligands to get jobs done.
Another great example is hemosyanin. Now rather than hemoglobin hemosyanin still transports oxygen
does this in crustaceans crabs and lobsters those sorts of animals but it does so using two copper
ions coordinated directly to a protein matrix which gives these lobsters crabs and other marine
animals a very different blood chemistry than mammals. So in this case the protein itself
is acting as the ligand for the copper ions which carry oxygen. Let's look at one more example
vitamin B12. Now vitamin B12 includes a compound called cobalamin and as the name implies cobalamin
has a cobalt ion complex in its center. Now this vitamin is used in the body to conduct
essential functions including synthesis of folic acid and again it's all dependent on having the
ligand in place to coordinate that metal. So nature one ups the organic chemists once again
having devised ligands far more complex than those of Wilkinson's catalysts or even dotarem
and they're capable of conducting much more powerful directed chemistry.
But why stop at one metal? Yet another of nature's chemists who continues to embarrass us all is the
nitrogen-fixing rhizobia bacteria which live in the root nodules of legumes like soy.
The molecule that they produce which allows them to fix nitrogen is a protein called nitrogenase
and it contains not just one metal ion but multiple clusters of them in complex with sulfur atoms.
Scientists have discovered and characterized two different forms of nitrogenase both of which
rely on iron to function, one of them exclusively and another one in concert with molybdenum.
Now even though these metalloprotein structures have been well known for decades their ability
to accomplish the same reaction at room temperature and pressures that Haber could only
accomplish at extremely high pressures and temperatures remains unexplained even today.
And when someone finally unlocks the secret to the chemistry of these large
powerful organometallic molecules the impact it will have on the world food supply
is likely to be as great as cold fusion would be for the power industry.
So today we started with one of Butler-Rov's projects in the 1800s.
We took a look at how he and Zetzev conducted some of the very first organometallic experiments.
Then we spent some time covering the reaction developed by Victor Grineard in 1900 which bears
his name and won him the Nobel Prize and also breathed new life into the floundering science
of organometallic chemistry. We talked about how his alkyl magnesium halides had the properties
of carbanions including strong nucleophilic character and extreme basicity. We covered how
this nucleophilic character makes no carbonyl safe in the presence of a Grineard leading to a
large library of potential substrates which can be used in conjunction with them.
We saw how Jeffrey Wilkinson is usually regarded as the father of modern organometallic chemistry
having devised a method to get rhodium and platinum of Sabatier's heterogeneous catalysts
into solution making them more effective homogeneous catalysts.
We then advanced on Wilkinson's ideas and took them into the biological realm seeing how
compounds like dota rem could get highly magnetic but extremely toxic gadolinium ions
safely into the bloodstream of cancer patients where they can help to detect tumors.
Finally, we indulged in Mother Nature a bit more and took a look at some pretty representations of
metal-containing proteins like hemoglobin and hemocyanins, mitrogenases and some vitamins
all of which carry out spectacularly focused chemistry in one way or another helping to
sustain the lives of those creatures that use them. We've come a long way from the simplest of
organic compounds, methane, to organometallics the size of nitrogenase. We've nearly run the gamut
of molecular size but there is one more class of organic compound to consider, the undisputed king
of molecular size, polymers, and they're the last class of organic compounds on our list.
Next time we're going to take a look at some world-changing polymers, how they were discovered,
how they're made, and how their size and modular composition make them an extremely
versatile class of compounds. I'll see you then.