We've spent some time now learning about the discovery of how electromagnetic waves in
and near the visible spectrum can interact with organic molecules and how we can observe
that interaction in a way which gives us information about the structure of the molecules involved.
We learned how Newton's use of a prism to separate light into its constituent wavelengths
introduced the western world to the idea that visible light was made up of multiple color
components.
We saw how the discoveries of Herschel and Ritter demonstrated that there were other
types of light just outside of that visible spectrum as well.
We've talked about how all three of these portions of the spectrum, ultraviolet, visible,
and infrared, interact with small molecules in the tremendous utility that these phenomena
have as tools for the identification of organic compounds.
So far we've investigated how to determine the extent of conjugation in a compound with
UV visible spectroscopy, the presence of functional groups using IR spectroscopy, and the handedness
of compounds using polarimetry.
But short of comparing the fingerprint region of IR spectra to those of known standards,
we don't really have a way to probe the connectivity of functional groups within a molecule.
So if we're making an entirely new molecule, for which there is no reference spectrum yet
in the literature, how are we going to confirm its identity?
In this lecture, we will move on to yet another region of the electromagnetic spectrum.
To get our answer, we're going all the way to the long wavelength end of the spectrum,
beyond infrared, past microwaves, all the way to the radio portion of the spectrum.
But before we get to our radio waves today, we'll need to try to better understand a property
of atoms that we haven't really discussed and which we usually think of as more within
the realm of physics than organic chemistry.
That property is magnetism.
The magnetic properties of nuclei were not well understood by Newton, Ritter, and Herschel,
and they went largely unaddressed during the development of optical spectroscopy techniques
in the 1800s.
But in the early 1900s, that all changed.
In large part due to the efforts of Isidore Rebe, an American physicist who is credited
with having the revelation that atoms have certain magnetic properties which can be used
to discern them from one another in a given molecule.
So to get started today, let's take one more step back and consider magnetism in general.
But before we get to our radio frequency radiation, I'd like to show you this.
It's a compass.
It's a device with which most of us, especially navigators, pilots, hikers, are familiar.
A small magnetized needle is mounted on an axis which allows it to turn so that it can
align itself with whatever sort of magnetic field it's in.
Of course, in the case of my compass needle, this field is generated by the Earth's rotating
inner core.
Now, physicists have several different units used to measure the intensity of a magnetic
field, one of which is Tesla, named for the famous and somewhat eccentric physicist Nikola
Tesla.
At its surface, the Earth's magnetic field measures about 50 milli-Tesla.
Here, close to Washington, D.C., this weak but ever-present field points about 11 degrees
to the west of true north.
When I place this compass within the field, the needle aligns itself with that field,
giving me an indication of its direction.
So, let's assume for a moment that I could somehow remove the influence of the Earth's
magnetic field.
Now, I can't remove the Earth's magnetic field because I can't stop the core from spinning.
But what I can do is use these rare Earth magnets to pull this needle out of alignment.
Now, if there were no magnetic field, I would expect that any arrangement whatsoever of
this needle in space would be of equal energy.
So any alignment is possible.
But as soon as I remove my rare Earth's magnetic field and allow the Earth's magnetic field
to take over once again, this guy back out of alignment, snaps right back.
So as soon as I place my compass back in the field, the energy of the aligned state becomes
lower in energy than any of the other misaligned states, causing the needle to reliably and
predictably take on that lower energy orientation.
Now, the reason I'm showing you this, this rather mundane little magnetic tool, is that
it's a very good analogy for the behavior of certain atomic nuclei.
At atomic nuclei have a property that physicists call magnetic spin.
I specifically mentioned physicists here because I refuse to lay the blame for this one on
chemists.
Spin, you see, is a very unfortunate choice of terminology, as it doesn't actually refer
to a rate of rotation as one might assume from classical mechanics.
It's a common point of confusion in the study of NMR, so let's be sure we clear that up
right away.
Now for our discussion, it'll suffice to say this.
Certain atomic nuclei have a spin quantum number of one-half, which is just a fancy
way of saying that there are two possible magnetic states.
Such nuclei contain what is known as a magnetic dipole, or a magnetization which can behave
much like an atom-sized bar magnet or compass needle.
Finally, those neutrons that I encouraged you to overlook way back at the beginning of the
course are about to become relevant.
This is because isotopes, or atoms of the same element with different numbers of neutrons,
have different magnetic properties, and nearly every element has at least one isotope, which
is spin one-half.
This includes protons, carbon-13, nitrogen-15, and fluorine-19.
But for this lecture, we're going to confine ourselves to protons, with the caveat that
the same magnetic tricks I'm about to show you can be pulled with at least one isotope
of practically every commonly encountered element.
So let's take a look at a hydrogen nucleus.
So the magnetic dipole of certain atomic nuclei behaves in much the same way as our compass
needle did, randomly orienting itself in the absence of an external magnetic field.
But as soon as a magnetic field is applied, which we represent as these lines, specific
orientations of the nuclear dipole become more stable.
Now where the analogy deviates from our macroscopic example of our compass and needle is that
spin one-half atomic nuclei can align their dipoles either parallel to or anti-parallel
to a magnetic field in which they reside, leading to a distribution of those two states
in the population.
But the energies of the parallel state, often called the alpha spin state and the anti-parallel
alignment, sometimes called the beta spin state, differ by an amount which can be calculated
and is referred to as the Zaman splitting energy.
The Zaman splitting energy is a function of the intensity of the external magnetic field
and an intrinsic property of the nucleus called its gyromagnetic ratio.
Now by intrinsic, I mean that, for example, all protons in the universe have the exact
same gyromagnetic ratio.
So for a nucleus of a given type, the stronger the external magnetic field, the greater the
energy difference between the alpha and beta spin states will be.
Now on our way to understanding how NMR works in laboratories of the 21st century, we first
have to make a pit stop in the 1940s and 50s when the science was still being developed
by Rebi and his contemporaries.
This historical context is going to help us to better understand the more complex instruments
of today.
So let's say that we have a collection of protons in a fairly strong external magnetic
field.
We expect that these protons will arrange themselves in a collection of alpha and beta
spin states, with just a very slight excess in the lower energy alpha state.
Let's say that we place our protons in a 1.4 Tesla magnetic field.
That's a field about 28,000 times as strong as the Earth's, powerful but attainable with
a suitable electromagnet.
First on the gyromagnetic ratio of a proton, 42.577 MHz per Tesla, I can calculate the
Zaman splitting energy difference between those two states.
Since the proton is the most frequently used nucleus in NMR experiments, we report field
strengths in Tesla or rarely in Tesla, more often we actually use the resonance frequency
of a proton in that field.
For example, our 1.4 Tesla magnet should bring a proton into resonance with a radiation
of 60 MHz in frequency.
So you'll notice that most modern spectrometers have a frequency splashed across the side in
large fonts.
This is the frequency that's indicated there.
It's a photon of that specific frequency, one with a wavelength of about 5 meters, which
carries just the right amount of energy to cause a proton in the alpha spin state to
flip into the beta spin state, absorbing the photon in the process.
So early spectrometers attempting to take advantage of this phenomenon consisted of
a powerful electromagnet, a radio frequency transmitter, and a radio frequency receiver.
A sample of organic material is placed into the magnetic field and irradiated with a constant
wave of a specific radio frequency.
In keeping with our example, that would be 60 MHz.
And this is how continuous wave NMR gets its name.
The current to the electromagnet is slowly increased as the exiting radio wave is monitored
at the receiver.
In our very simple example, at one very specific field strength, the radio wave will be absorbed
in the spin state transition from alpha to beta, manifesting itself as a reduced radio
wave intensity at the receiver.
So this is the basic design of a continuous wave NMR spectrometer.
So if you've been following so far, you probably have at least one very important question.
If all protons have exactly the same gyromagnetic ratio, and the field in the NMR experiment
is perfectly uniform, how is it that this technology is good for anything other than
simply detecting the presence of protons?
How can it possibly distinguish one proton on a molecule from another?
The answer to this very important question lies in a different term in the Zeeman splitting
equation.
It's not the gyromagnetic ratio which differs from one proton to the next, but rather the
exact strength of the external field at a given nucleus.
You see, we started with the very unrealistic example of a collection of isolated protons
with no other atoms or even electrons present in the system.
The obvious difference between this model system and the ones which a chemist might
want to study is that there are electron clouds and atoms of other kinds bonded to the protons
that we want to analyze.
And the real key to understanding how NMR gives us information lies in another phenomenon,
like shielding by electrons.
You see, I told a little white lie back there, at least a lie of omission.
I already told you the Zeeman splitting is a function of gyromagnetic ratio and the external
field strength, but what I left out was the fact that electron clouds have this interesting
ability to attenuate or weaken the external field ever so slightly.
Now we can think of this as a new term in the Zeeman equation in which I account for
a small reduction in field strength due to the shielding of the electron cloud at that
particular nucleus.
Let's take a look at some examples to see if we can drive this point home.
We're going to look at some hypothetical NMR spectra for four different compounds,
methane, chloromethane, dichloromethane, and chloroform.
So essentially what I've done here is started from methane and then slowly added one chlorine
atom at a time to pick it here in green until I reach the point where I have three chlorines
attached.
So let's start by thinking about methane and its electron cloud.
Now the electron cloud in a methane molecule is very symmetrical, isn't it?
There are no particularly electronegative elements.
The carbon-hydrogen bonds are essentially nonpolar.
And so there really is no distortion in this electron cloud.
That means that if I plot its absorption versus the applied field strength in a continuous
wave NMR spectrometer, I expect that it will take a fairly high field to overcome the shielding
that these protons are experiencing.
But if I move along to say chloromethane, where I've replaced one of those hydrogens
with a more electronegative chlorine atom, there's now a dipole within this molecule
and it's pulling electrons toward the chlorine and therefore away from the remaining hydrogens.
So its electron cloud may look more like this with a bit of a distortion because that chlorine
is pulling some of it more towards itself.
So with reduced shielding, I expect that I need a lower applied field strength to create
resonance and indeed that's what I see.
And this trend continues through dichloromethane which has two dipoles and therefore an electron
cloud which is even more deshielded at those protons.
And of course its NMR spectrum would reflect that in an even weaker applied field necessary
for resonance.
And finally chloroform where I have three of these dipoles has got a very, very deshielded
proton which will resonate at an even lower applied field.
Because of this, lower applied fields causing resonances at the, down here at the left-hand
side of the spectrum, we refer to this side of the spectrum as downfield, whereas we refer
to the higher field portion of the spectrum sometimes as upfield.
So a more shielded hydrogen like those in methane resonates upfield, a more deshielded
hydrogen like those in chloroform will resonate downfield.
So the density of the electron cloud at a particular nucleus can cause its peak to shift
within the NMR spectrum.
So we call this phenomenon chemical shift.
So we've established that protons in different chemical environments will resonate at distinct
applied fields because of the effects like shielding.
But what happens when a researcher in a lab across the country or across the globe tries
to reproduce my experiment?
What happens if his or her spectrometer produces a field strength or radio wave frequency different
than mine?
Well of course all shifts of all the protons will be different making comparisons somewhat
difficult.
So we need a method of reporting data which can be easily translated from one spectrometer
to the next.
We need to normalize the resonance frequencies to account for different applied field strengths.
We start this process by agreeing to a reference standard.
In the case of proton NMR, we use a compound called tetramethylsilane.
We use this compound because the very low electronegativity of silicon pushes electrons
toward the methyl groups producing a strong consistent resonance frequency which is so
far up field that it rarely interferes with the signals of interest.
So the differences in field needed to produce resonance in the protons of most organic molecules
is just a small fraction of 1% of the total field strength.
So to make the numbers more manageable, we report chemical shift in parts per million
from the absolute resonance frequency of that reference compound, TMS or tetramethylsilane.
So a proton resonating in a field which is 99.9999% of the strength needed to bring TMS
into resonance is said to be resonating at 1.0 ppm chemical shift.
A proton at 99.9998% of the field strength of TMS would be at 2.0 ppm chemical shift
and so on.
Treating the x-axis of my spectrum in this way not only gives me easier numbers to work
with but allows me to compare data collected on one instrument with data collected on another
instrument even if it uses a different magnetic field strength.
So parts per million has become the standard unit for NMR spectroscopy.
So we've considered the behavior of a hypothetical collection of protons in a magnetic field.
We then graduated to real, albeit very simple, organic compounds like methane and its halogenated
derivatives, all of which have only one type of proton in them.
But what happens when a compound has more than one kind of proton?
How would we expect a continuous wave NMR spectrum to look for a compound like that?
Let's answer that question with an example.
Let's take a look at ethyl chloride or chloroethane.
Now chloroethane has two chemically distinct protons.
These I've highlighted in red are adjacent to the chlorine atom and of course there are
three others that are farther away.
Now if I locate the resonance frequency for these two protons, I notice something very
interesting has taken place.
It's not a single peak.
Even though these are identical and should produce a single absorption, I actually see
a peak which has four distinct lobes.
Now the origin of these lobes is the interaction of these two protons with their neighbors.
See every proton, remember, is a small bar magnet and that means that whether they're
aligned parallel to or anti-parallel to the applied magnetic field will cause them to interact
differently with the adjacent protons.
So if I consider the effect of these protons, which I've highlighted in blue, they can interact
with the hydrogens of interest by being all spin up, there are actually three different
ways that I can combine them with two spins up and one spin down and of course there will
also be three potential ways to combine them with two spins down and one spin up.
And the final permutation that's possible with three is to have all spin down.
So in the case where all of the neighbors are spin up, they add just a little bit of
magnetic field to what's experienced by those causing the signal and that means it requires
just a little bit less of an applied magnetic field to cause resonance.
That's why what should be, in theory, a single signal is actually split into four.
So these are the source of that multiplicity.
Similarly, I can look at the resonance frequency of these three hydrogens and say they must
be coupled to or interacting with my red hydrogens.
Now with two hydrogens interacting, I have the possibility of having them both spin up,
two possibilities in which I have one up, one down, and my final possibility in which
they're both spin down.
So in this case, my blue hydrogens should create a resonance with three lobes.
So we refer to this phenomenon as magnetic coupling and the resulting shape of the peaks
as multiplets.
They follow a rule known as the n plus one rule which simply states that we have n plus
one lobes per multiplet where n is the number of coupled hydrogens.
So my red hydrogens are coupled to three neighbors creating a peak with four lobes.
My blue hydrogens are coupled to two neighbors creating a peak with three lobes.
In most simple situations where we're dealing with saturated compounds with free rotation,
this rule holds pretty well.
So let's take a look at some multiplet features that we may see in an MR specter as we go
forward.
Of course the simplest where n equals one we call a doublet.
When there are two coupled partners, we get what we call a triplet.
Three produces a quartet and so on with four making a quintet and five making a sextet
and so on.
Now in many cases they become so complex around this point that we stop referring to them
by their individual names and simply refer to them collectively as multiplets.
Now the intensity of the lobes within the multiplet is also useful information.
So we'd like to be able to predict that as well and we can.
For example a doublet is always one to one whereas a triplet is one to two to one and
a quartet one to three to three to one and the pattern continues, remember this is because
of all the different permutations of alpha and beta spin states for the coupling partners.
Now what's really great is if you forget this pattern you can easily recreate it using a
geometric mnemonic.
That geometric mnemonic is known as Pascal's Triangle.
So we can simply create a series in which we add adjacent numbers as we go down so one
plus two equals three, for example here three plus three equals six, etc.
And Pascal's Triangle allows us to predict the multiplicity in any instance where we have
multiple coupling partners in simple situations like these.
So we're now ready to get just a small taste of the power NMR has to reveal structural
information.
We're going to begin with a very simple example but one which clearly shows how we can gather
structural information which would not be available to us from the UV-Vis, IR or polarimetry
experiments that we have covered so far.
We're going to do it using a relatively simple molecule or set of molecules and that is the
structural isomers of chloropropane.
So let's construct some hypothetical NMR spectra for the two different isomers of chloropropane.
We'll start with two chloropropane.
So here I have my chlorine attached at the central atom and because of this I'm going
to have a spectrum which has two different resonances.
Now it's worth mentioning here I've exaggerated the multiplicities a little bit, I've spaced
them out a little bit wider than you might see them in an actual spectrum so that they're
easy for us to see but their position within the spectrum is accurate.
So we see that there are two different kinds of protons in this two chloropropane.
First there are the six methyl protons which are all exactly the same as one another.
Now because they're chemically identical to one another they don't couple to each other
but they do have one coupling partner in this proton right here in the center of the molecule.
And it has its own resonance which is split by its six non-equivalent neighbors.
So just as we would expect from our previous discussions on multiplicity we have a very
large doublet which corresponds to these six hydrogens highlighted in blue and a relatively
small multiplet produced by this single hydrogen which is split by many coupling partners.
Now if we take a closer look we can see the multiplicity is exactly as we would predict
using Pascal's Triangle and that this is actually a 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and plus 1 right this is
a septet.
So our septet at 3.7 parts per million tells us we have a proton with many coupling partners
very close to an electron withdrawing group and our doublet at 1.1 parts per million tells
us that we have some protons which have a single coupling partner and that those protons
are farther away from the electron withdrawing group because they resonate upfield.
So how can we use this spectrum in comparison to say one chloropropane and distinguish between
these two compounds?
Let's take a look at one chloropropane right now.
So when I put my chlorine at the end of the molecule rather than in the center it has
very important and profound effect on the number of resonances that I see.
My spectrum is a little bit more complicated now isn't it?
That's because by placing the chlorine at the end I've created three distinct chemical
environments for the protons in the molecule.
Those that are directly on the carbon bearing the chlorine, those one bond away and those
that are two bonds away.
So I expect to see three distinct resonances which I do but not only that their multiplicities
are different than those in my previous example.
So in this case I have a triplet that is way upfield which tells me I've got some hydrogens
that are very far away from any electron withdrawing groups and have two non-equivalent neighbors
to which they are magnetically coupled.
I also have a little bit more complicated multiplet here.
This one would be called a sexted and that tells me that I've got some protons which
are a little bit closer to the electron withdrawing group and are coupled to five distinct partners.
One, two, three, four, five.
Finally I have another triplet which is farther downfield telling me that I must have some
protons that are very close to the electron withdrawing chlorine and are coupled to two
partners which is a perfect description of these two protons highlighted in red coupled
to their neighbors in blue.
So this spectrum having a triplet at .8, a sexted at 1.6 and another triplet at 3.3 allows
me to very clearly and unambiguously assign that it's one chloropropane.
So let's review the material from this lecture.
We started by considering a property of atomic nuclei known as spin and how certain isotopes
of certain atoms have a spin of one half, giving them two possible spin states when
an external magnetic field is applied.
There's the low energy parallel state called alpha and the high energy anti-parallel state
called beta.
We discussed how the energy difference between these states known as the Zeeman splitting
corresponds to the radio frequency region of the electromagnetic spectrum and is proportional
to the strength of the magnetic field with which the nuclei are aligning themselves.
We took a look at the design of early spectrometers in which a continuous radio frequency wave
is shined on a sample as the strength of an applied field is varied until resonance is
achieved resulting in an absorption of the radio wave.
We then looked at how the shielding and induced fields provided by electrons can cause the
magnetic field at protons within a molecule to be slightly different, leading us to the
calculations of chemical shift.
Finally, we discussed the phenomenon of magnetic spin-spin coupling in which non-equivalent
nuclei which are three bonds away from one another can share magnetization splitting
resonances into a set of lobes called a multiplet.
Next time, we'll take our discussion into the new millennium and look at what is known
as pulsed or Fourier transform NMR.
We'll also take a brief look at a few other techniques used to characterize molecules,
specifically x-ray crystallography and mass spectrometry.
I'll see you for that discussion next time.