It is a great pleasure and honor to be here today,
speaking with Professor Nick Bostrom.
Professor Bostrom is one of my favorite people alive today
and probably in history.
From my perspective, he's, you know,
if we make it as a species into the far future,
it'll be in significant part thanks to him
and his work helping us look, think about the future,
think about the long term, think about how we might evolve.
He's written, of course, about many things in technology,
but especially about digital minds,
the evolution of humanity, super intelligences, and more.
He leads the Oxford Future of Humanity Institute,
where he and many other researchers help the world
think about these extremely important topics
in a variety of ways from both research directly
into the philosophy of these questions
and the making estimations about the real impact
and also framing and constructing important policy work
that can help guide many policymakers around the world
in how to think about these critical policies.
So today we're going to have a very good and lively discussion
about many of these topics,
especially things like super intelligences,
where are we in these timelines, whole brain emulation,
digital minds, the future of these,
the challenges for our civilization, and more.
The format of the evening will be that,
we'll sit in our fireside chat first,
I'll ask a set of questions,
and then around 30 to 40, maybe 50 minutes from now,
given I have a bunch of questions,
I'll open up to and transition to questions from the audience,
and then we'll set them out in time then.
I'll be reading from both questions that I've sourced
from many folks around the product labs community
ahead of time, and from audience members
who are here in person,
and from the folks in the livestream watching.
So I'll be checking out Twitter for the hashtag PL breakthroughs.
So if you want to ask a question,
either find the tweet about it,
and please enter your question with the hashtag PL breakthroughs,
I'll be monitoring those,
and then I'll try to round Robin between source questions ahead,
person, people in the audience, and the livestream.
And if there's a new digital intelligence
out there lurking on Twitter,
please feel free to join the discussion.
Well, welcome Nick, thank you so much for being with us,
and thank you so much for your work.
How are you doing today?
The stuff was so good.
Great, so let's kind of dive right into the deep end.
So thinking about superintelligence,
based on kind of like latest developments,
how have your estimates of superintelligence development
shifted over time, like kind of in hindsight,
where we are now in 2022, looking back,
how do you think things are going?
Are things proceeding faster or slower
than you might have thought?
Where do you think we are?
I think since the book superintelligence came out in 2014,
developments have been faster than expected.
So timelines generally have contracted.
It's quite impressive to see the rapid pace of advances
in recent years,
and how the same set of basic techniques,
big, deep neural networks,
and specifically transformer models
just seem to keep working in many different domains.
And even as you scale them up,
you continue to get better results.
And as the chefs,
what have been some of the most surprising results
from this that you think,
I don't know, maybe you just didn't expect
this particular concrete thing to be possible so soon?
I think AlphaGo happened ahead of schedule.
Well, I mean, I think just recently before it happened,
it was kind of clear that it was going to happen,
but I think it was quite impressive
that you could take something that is a very deep pattern
recognition problem with deep strategy
where humans have worked for thousands of years
to try to refine and come up with the best strategies
that you could just solve it with AI.
And then I think the GPT-3, the large language models,
is, I guess, slightly...
I mean, I don't think any of these is hugely surprising.
And by now, we kind of expect to be surprised,
and so we are not really surprised,
but still, yeah, I think...
these are impressive achievements.
And I guess even just before that,
the fact that image recognition and image processing
was one of the first really cool things that started to work
is maybe a little bit surprising,
and given that it's a large chunk of the human brain
that is devoted to visual processing,
it's not like some kind of simple logic-chopping activity.
And so the fact that that fell into place
and that you can do this quite sophisticated manipulation
of imagery, I think, was slightly surprising at the time.
What do you think about developments like AlphaFold
and just solving that set of challenges?
Do you think that that is substantially different,
or is it not like a substantially...
it's just kind of a very great application,
but...
or do you think that that's an important improvement?
I mean, in terms of surprise,
like, I guess once you can do AlphaFold,
it's not so surprising that it should work for AlphaFold as well.
Like, humans have put in less brain power
into figuring out how to fold proteins than into playing Go.
And it's, at least superficially,
looks like the same kind of spatial pattern type of stuff.
Obviously, in terms of practical ramifications,
AlphaFold is potentially a lot more useful
and for medicine and chemical research,
maybe like extensions of the same system.
I do think that as we move into some of these more applied areas,
that there are potential security concerns
that we need to also start to take more seriously.
I mean, my work has been focused more on risks arising
from human level or superintelligence,
like general AGI, where they can reason
and have a kind of transformative impact on the world.
But there might also be some narrower domains
where there will be smaller but still significant issues.
So one of those would be in synthetic biology
if it becomes too easy to concoct bad stuff.
It might be, for example, that the scientific model
of open publication and make all your models
ideally available to anybody to do anything
is not the right model for those application areas.
When you think about the current architectures,
and certainly the language models
have been extraordinarily successful
in a variety of domains.
But do you think that this is the architecture
that is likely to evolve into an AGI?
Or do you think that there's some substantial architectural
improvements that humans have to make first?
My guess would be that if there are substantial
additional architectural improvements,
there are not that many of them.
And maybe they would be built on top of transformer models
or connected up to the transformer models
or some variation of transformer models.
So maybe, I don't know, like my media, I guess,
would be made, I don't know, maybe just something
that is as big an advance as transformers were.
Like if we get one more of those,
like that could easily be, I mean, it's also possible
like just scaling up what we currently have
with some minor things would suffice.
But if there is some other thing,
like you need to connect it up with some kind
of external memory system,
or you need some other inductive bias
that make the representations
on a more easily composable insert,
like some kind of extra thing like that,
that may or may not be very hard to discover.
That would not at all be surprising.
I guess we'll find out.
Yeah.
Do you think that these models could,
I mean, they're certainly being used to optimize
themselves and so on and guide the design
and there's all kinds of structures
in which models are being used to,
there's layers and layers and layers of metamodeling.
Do you think that these are kind of getting close
to this kind of recursive self-improvement
of being able to kind of very generally explore
the constraint space to try and solve
like larger scale problems?
Like I'm imagining here some structure
where you have some list of problems
and you have some model sampling between these
and you start with the easy ones
and then you try to train populations of agents
or populations of intelligences to be able to solve these
and then kind of over time just kind of scale up the system.
Do you think that that kind of thing,
it seems to me that it'd be like,
thankfully nobody has really tried this
but it doesn't seem like far away
from something that could be possible.
Yeah, I guess we're seeing all limited versions of AI
being applied to help AI research.
I mean, we have like co-pilot
and general kind of coding assistance.
Of course, you have various forms of hyper parameter
optimization regimes.
There've also been some applications
in the design of hardware where kind of circuit layout
has been done, I think for the TPU4,
I think Google used AI assistance
to kind of optimize the layout of the circuitry.
Data centers, cooling machinery that have been like,
you can kind of shave off some percent
by having that optimized by some RL system.
And so, I think we'll certainly see
more incremental stuff like that.
My guess is that by the time we get
like a really strong feedback loop
where sort of the AI can do the core thing
that researchers are doing,
like the actual identifying the right research questions
and approaches and like that seems quite late in it.
Like when that happens,
we are pretty close to the singularity
or the takeoff or whatever the ramp
or whatever the shape of that will be.
But certainly there's more domain specific
incremental ways of accelerating AI advances.
I think we're seeing some of already
and can expect to see more of.
Speaking about takeoff, do you sort of expect,
or based on what you have seen so far,
do you think we're more on a slow, moderate or fast takeoff?
This is sort of the three options that you thought through.
Yeah.
I mean, I still think that the slow looks less plausible,
meaning decades, say, between when you get something
roughly human level until you get something
that completely leaves us in the dust.
That seemed less likely back when I wrote the book
and still seems less likely today.
I guess we have a little bit more granularity now
in that we have these model systems that work
and you can at least consider these scenarios
where human double AI is achieved
by scaling up current systems or variations of that.
That gives us a little bit more of a concrete picture
of at least one way in which these can develop.
And it's possible that you might then have something
that is really very dependent on compute
and that really you get performance kind of proportional
to the size of the model or the length of the training
and in a relatively smooth way.
So in some of those scenarios,
you might have something that is less than super rapid
because what you will get is something
that costs like a billion dollar to train up one human level AI
and then you might immediately be able to run
multiple of them because it takes a lot more to train up a model
than to run it.
So you might then be able to run like a hundred
or a thousand of them,
but that's still not enough to out compete
on the order of 10 billion humans, right?
So depending on like,
if you really stretch yourself very far
to just barely be able to run a model as big as a human,
it might then take a significant period of time
before you can go many orders of magnitude above that
to sort of get something,
like if you need to scale that up by a factor of a million,
say to go from running like on the order of a thousand humans
to a billion humans getting through six orders of magnitude
when you're already like using a billion dollars
and like a large chunk of your data centers,
like that might just not be an instantaneous process.
So there are some scenarios where this would happen
more on a sort of intermediate time scale.
Now, in some sense, I guess that's like the kind of the
the baseline projection.
Like if you just like extrapolate
the way things currently work,
I don't think we can preclude the possibility
of there being more rapid capability jumps.
Like, hey, of course,
if there is like some missing architectural invention
that we haven't made,
that suddenly makes it click.
But you also have these phenomenon like rocking
where sometimes you have a kind of discrete jump
in some particular type of capability.
Like maybe multi-step reasoning
where if each step has less than X percent chance
of being correct,
then like you get an exponential chance
of reasoning correctly
and you really can't do more than like three or four or five steps.
But maybe once you get it above a certain level
and then maybe you can do some sort of self-correction reasoning
like analogous to like quantum computation protocols
like that, you could also imagine cases
where like things come together
and you suddenly get the specific types of things
that make us humans have the extra oomph
that we have relative to other animals,
like full ability to learn from language
and to reason and plan on that.
So yeah, I wouldn't preclude these more rapid takeoff scenarios
either at all, like...
Yeah, certainly some of the latest developments
and some scaling down some of the models
and getting similar results sort of point to there being
just a lot of inefficiencies in the training process now.
And once you sort of know what you're sort of looking for,
you can kind of a blade away a lot of pieces.
And so something like that could happen
with a general learning algorithm.
Yeah, so certainly now you find like,
yeah, so first you achieve state of the art
and then like six months or 12 months later,
you can achieve the same thing
with maybe 10% of the computer or something.
Now, I would expect a little bit of that to go away.
As these systems become bigger and more expensive,
you might imagine more of the easy gains
to be made earlier on.
Like if you really have a lot of smart humans
working really hard on building a system,
you might have plucked more of the low-hanging fruits
than if it were like a two-person postdoc team
that were working for a few weeks.
Chances are that will be big, easy additional things
you could do to improve that system already.
But if you're spending many billions of these,
like you're gonna look quite hard
if there are ways to sort of speed up the training process
so you could like save a hundred million.
Are you hopeful that restricting hardware development
or use is a promising path?
I mean, semiconductor manufacturing
is extremely difficult,
but more and more companies are sort of forced to do it
because of kind of hitting the barriers
with just the size of the systems
and then needing to do special applications
and special purpose things.
And many more companies are now developing
their own chips and so on.
So are kind of like hardware restrictions viable here
or is that a pathway that's just unlikely to work?
Yeah, so a lot of people can like design their own chips,
but only a few actors can actually build them.
And then there are some other choke points further upstream
in terms of making the equipment for the factories
that build the chips
where currently to make cutting edge chips,
there's like ASML, which is a single node.
And indeed, we do see like, I mean with these recent moves
by the US to restrict exports of cutting edge chips to China
and quite comprehensive,
also not to sell the equipment,
also not to allow American persons
to work for these companies.
I don't know what fraction of the motivation for this
is like AI specifically versus more generally
a sense of this being a high tech area
that's gonna be key to national competitiveness.
Yeah, I don't think it's out of the question
that I mean, compared to the alternative,
which would be like to like restrict access to ideas
and algorithms and stuff.
I mean, that might work for a short period of time,
but independent discovery means it's like, yeah,
at most a short term stop cap measure,
whereas the hardware would like take a lot longer
if you needed to build up like the whole supply chain
on your own, like that would be a multi decade project, right?
Now that said, I think what I would favor would be for there
to be the ability at the critical time to go slow,
to have a short pause, maybe to check systems
and to avoid the most cutthroat type of tech race
to just launch as quickly as possible
because you get scooped if you take even an extra week to,
like I think that would be bad now.
So having enough coordination or control
to be able to go at the moderate pace
when you sort of reach approach human level would be good.
I wouldn't want to stop the development
of advanced machine intelligence permanently
or even like have a very long pause either.
I think that brings its own negatives.
And I think some of these attempts
to restrict the chip supply also have
the side effect of creating more adversarial dynamic.
I think it would be really nice if we could have a world
where the leading powers were more on the same page
or friendly or at least had constructive
cooperative relationship.
I think a lot of the ex-risk pie in general
and the risk from AI in particular
arises from the possibility of conflict of different kind.
And so a world order that was more cooperative
would look more promising for the future
in many different ways.
So I'm a little worried about,
especially kind of more unilateral list move
to kind of kneecap the competitor
and to be playing nasty.
Like I feel that, yeah, I'm very uneasy about that.
It sounds, well, so if the hardware,
if ideas or hardware will only buy a certain amount of time,
then really AI alignment is the best path forward
and very much agree that we don't want to restrict
the creation of digital intelligence
and that that's sort of the next evolutionary jumps.
And there's some questions there
around kind of like which paths we would take
and how do we develop brain computer interfaces
and cold-burn emulation and so on.
We're kind of like, even before getting into that,
how hopeful are you that we might solve
the AI alignment problem?
Moderately, I guess I'm quite agnostic,
but I think the main uncertainty is how hard the problem
turns out to be.
And then there's a little extra uncertainty
as to how the degree to which we get our act together.
But I think like out of those two variables,
like the realistic scenarios in which we either
like are lazy and don't like focus on it
versus the ones where we get a lot of smart people
working on it.
So there's some uncertainty there
that affects the success chance,
but I think that's dwarfed by our uncertainty
about how intrinsically hard the problem is to solve.
So you could say that like the most important component
of our strategy should be to hope
that the problem is not too hard.
Yeah, so let's try to tackle it.
So how do you, as you thought about this problem,
have you kind of been able to break it down
into components and parts or maybe evolved your thinking
of the shape of the problem?
Like what are you thinking now?
Well, I think the field as a whole has made
significant advances and developed a lot
since when I was writing the book
where it was like really a non-existent field.
There were a few people on the internet here and there,
but now it's an active research field
with a growing number of smart people
who have been working full-time on this for a number of years
and writing papers that build on previous papers
with technical stuff.
And all the key AI labs have now some contingent
of people who are working on alignment.
DeepMind has, OpenAI has, Anthropic has.
So that's all good.
Now, within this community,
there is, I guess, a distribution of levels of optimism
ranging from people very pessimistic,
like Elias Yudkowski, for example.
And I guess there are people even more pessimistic than him,
but he's kind of at one end
and towards people with more moderate levels of optimism,
like Paul Cristiano,
and then others who think it's kind of,
it's something that we'll deal with it when we get to it
and who don't seem too fast about it.
I think there's a lot of uncertainty
on the hardness level.
Now, as far as how you break it down, yeah.
So there are different ways of doing this.
There's not yet one paradigm
that all competent AI safety researchers share
in terms of the best lens to look at this.
So it decomposes in slightly different ways,
depending on your angle of approach,
but certainly one can identify different facets
that one can work on.
So for example, interpretability tools
seem on many different approaches,
like a useful ingredients to have,
like basically insights or techniques
that allow us better to see what is going on
in a big neural network.
You could have one approach where you try to get AI systems
that try to learn to match some human example of behavior,
either like one human or some corpus of humans
and then tries to just perform a next action
that's like the same as its best guess
about what this reference human
would do in the same situation.
And then you could try to do forms of amplification on that.
So like if you could like faithfully model one human,
well, then you just get like a human level,
like intelligence, you might want to go beyond that.
But if you could then create many of these models
that each do what the human do,
can you put them together in some bureaucracy
or do some other clever bootstrapping or self-criticism?
So that would be one approach.
You could, yeah, you could try to use
sort of inverse reinforcement learning
to infer like a human's preference function
and then try to optimize for that
or maybe not strictly optimized
but doing some kind of softer optimization.
Yeah, there are a bunch of different ideas.
Like some safety work is more like trying to more precisely
understand and illustrate in toy examples
how things could go wrong
because that's like often the first step
to creating a solution is to really deeply understand
what the problem is and then illustrate it.
And yeah, that can be useful as well.
It's interesting now that we have these models
that can talk as it were or like use language
that kind of opens up an additional interface,
like an additional way of interacting with these systems
and trying out different things
and a different way of illustrating the awkwardness.
Like the idea of prompt engineering
when you're trying to get an AI to do something
and you're trying to figure out
exactly the right formulation.
Like that shows that we are not quite where we need to be
in terms of directing the intrinsic capability
of these large language models.
So it's in there and yet we can't always even elicit it
because you have to find exactly the right wording
and then suddenly turns out this thing
is actually perfectly capable of doing something
which initially it seemed it failed that.
So getting better at that
or coming up with something better than prompt engineering
like would be good.
I'm kind of, I have some sympathy for an approach
which I think has not been explored very much yet
but partly because it's hard to explore it
until the technology reaches a certain level
of sophistication, which is the idea that as you get
systems that become closer to human level
in that conceptual ability.
And that might then internally start to develop concepts
that are more similar to human concepts
including not just concepts about simple visual features
and stuff, but more corresponding
to our higher language concepts.
Like our concept of a preference or a goal
or a request or being safe, being reckless
like these types of concepts.
Like we humans seem relatively robustly
to be able to master these concepts
in the course of our normal development.
Despite us having starting with different brains
and having different environmental input and noise.
And so maybe there is a relatively robust
and convergent ways in which some of these concepts
could be grasped.
Then the hope would be that you could kind of train up an AI
that doesn't need to be above human
and maybe hardly even human
that would then sort of internally form these concepts
in the same way that we form them.
And then once those concepts are in there,
you might then be able to use those as building blocks
to create a kind of alignment
by sort of linking motivation to these concepts.
It very hand-wavered, but I think something
in that direction is one interesting approach
to the alignment problem as well.
Do you think there's some promise
in trying to evolve a notion of morality and ethics?
Meaning using simulations of environments
where agents might learn to cooperate
and over time learn D, put them through the same kind
of game theory dynamics that gave rise
to our own notions of symbiotes and ethics and so on.
Potentially, yeah.
I mean, I think you would wanna be looking very closely
at exactly how you set things up
and the dynamics that unfold.
I mean, real revolution is sort of read in tooth and claw
and can create wonderful cooperation,
but also hostility and defection and manipulation
and all kinds of things.
But yes, certainly multi-agent systems
with the right kind of incentive structures in place
so that you evolve.
Like evolution itself can produce many different kinds
of outcomes, like depending on the environment,
but that certainly could be come in some scenarios
and increasingly important,
like either whether it's an evolutionary system
or in some of these other like a training environment,
like the curriculum, like if these systems are shaped
a lot by their data that they're trained on,
so far we've just kind of slapped together
some big data sets and not really fast too much
about what's contained in it,
but that might become an important component as well
of alignment in certain of these scenarios.
And are these directions the ones you find most promising
or is there like a subset of these
or maybe another one that you've been thinking about
starting to kind of surface
and help a lot of people that are working on this
so likely watch this conversation.
So are there any kind of pointers
that you might give beyond these?
Well, this would be some of the ones
that I would like highlight somewhat arbitrarily,
but yeah, I think like the Paul Cristiano capability
amplification, the interpretability work,
the idea of like growing human beings
human level concepts and then using those as a basis
to define goals or to sort of create the motivation system
that uses those as primitives.
It might also well be that there are entirely different
conceptual ways of approaching this
that are yet to be discovered.
It's not a mature research field where we have,
as I said, like we don't have an established paradigm
that's clearly correct and that we now just need to,
I think there are multiple paradigms
and there might well be additional ones
that just haven't had a champion yet
to sort of really get people to take it seriously.
So I think there is also a value
to this more theoretical, a conceptual,
almost philosophical exploratory work in just,
yeah, coming at the problem from a different angle.
Yeah, jumping into maybe agent-ness,
how separable do you think agency is from the intelligence
in the approaches that we're taking
or maybe more generally?
Yeah, like I guess then we would have to go in
so like exactly how you define agent,
so which is in itself like a non-trivial question
that, and it might even be that
getting really clear on that itself
would be an important advance in AI alignment.
I mean, you could kind of roughly define it
as kind of like behavior well-modeled
as being in the intelligent pursuit of goals
or something like that,
or you have goals on the world model
and you select different plans
based on your expectation of how that,
it, yeah, it seems like you can get
the significant performance in many domains
without having like an explicit
agentic goal-seeking process,
but that might nevertheless result in performance
that is agent-like.
So I'm thinking like you can get, for example,
quite high-level goal-playing
by just kind of pattern-matching what a human expert would do,
but without any Monte Carlo rollouts, for example.
So in one sense, you don't have a component in those systems
that would normally be associated with like planning.
On the other hand, if it actually plays like a human,
and if that human achieved that level of play
by selecting moves based on some plan
as to what they would achieve,
there is a kind of an implicit sense
in which the system is pursuing long-term goals and planning.
And so it gets, I think, yeah, a little bit murky sometimes
when you like actually dig into it, the degree,
or there might be different senses of being agentic
or different senses of doing planning and goal pursuing
which might have different safety properties.
Those types of questions I think are interesting
and like can contribute to alignment
and other questions of that sort
where we notice that we're a little bit conceptually confused
or we take some concept for granted,
but once you actually try to dig down and make it precise,
you realize that you haven't made up your mind
about which sense you were using a term,
and then if you keep digging on that,
sometimes you then get like new ways of looking at the problem
that makes you see new opportunities for making progress.
It seems right now that a number of teams
are hoping to be able to separate out
some kind of planning agent where,
or not an agent, but some kind of planner intelligence
that whose job is just to come up with a plan
and then maybe later you feed it
to some kind of execution system.
If, you know, suppose that we were able to do that
and suppose that we have these planners
that are generally intelligent
and potentially super intelligent,
it seems like that is potentially riskier
in some ways, which ones do you think are,
which of these do you think is potentially more problematic,
a super intelligence that is strictly a planner
that then we have to worry about how to coordinate
and orient humans to not misuse these things
and not gain the level of power and control
that something like that would give,
or hey, we actually figure out how to build an agent
and we can be reasonably closely certain
that it might get alignment right
and just go straight towards agency
where that agent would not actually be sort of exploitable
by whoever is controlling the prompt.
Yeah, I don't know.
I mean, I think just at an intuitive level,
I guess it feels like there is some additional risk
in having a planning agent that saw deep into the future
and it had like wearability to optimize
some long-term strategy based on some goal
versus things that more just try to imitate
like a human, let's say, and then repeat
or that had a very sort of short-time horizon
and just try to select something
based on parallel considerations.
At an intuitive level, the myopic agents,
the non-planning agent, the imitating seem kind of maybe safer,
but I don't think we can confidently say that it is
until we have more deeply understood the situation here
and it's the kind of question where current smart AI safety
researchers could have different views
and it's like not resolved in a consensus way yet.
So, I mean, my view is we should explore
all of these different avenues
and there should be different champions of different avenues
who kind of believe in their thing
and who have some people working with them,
but then there should be multiple such clusters
in the world today and it would be premature
to kind of narrow it down.
And even if we just look at the past five, 10 years,
I still feel that one could easily see
that if it hadn't been that one particular way
of looking at this problem had happens to have
an articulate champion to sort of advocate for it
and to keep bring up that perspective,
it would not have featured and it's like somewhat contingent,
which in the pool of vaguely articulated ideas
that have occurred on some mailings at some point,
like which of those is now regarded as like
as a serious paradigm or approach,
it seems to be quite significantly dependent
on the happen to have been one particularly smart person
who decided to really get behind it.
So, just on a principle of induction there,
like that might well be more of these ideas
that have the potential,
like if you have a smart articulate person
who decides to really kind of champion it
and try to write papers and reply to objections
and get some other people to work with them,
that might have kind of as much juice
as some of the current approaches that already exist.
Thank you.
I think that are likely very useful to a few folks.
Jumping into singletons and multiple worlds,
let's start by distinguishing these.
What is a singleton?
To me, it's like this abstract concept of a world order
where at the highest level of decision-making,
there's no coordination failure.
There's like a kind of single agency at the top level.
So, these could be good or bad
and they could be instantiated in many ways.
On earth, you could imagine a kind of super UN,
you could imagine like a world dictator
who conquered everything.
You could imagine like a super intelligence that took over.
You might also be able to imagine something less
formally structured like a kind of global moral code
that is sufficiently homogeneous
and that is self-enforcing and maybe other things as well.
So, you have like, yeah, at a very abstract level,
you could distinguish the future scenarios
where you end up with a singleton
versus ones that remain multipolar.
And you get different dynamics in the multipolar case
that you avoid in the singleton case.
These kind of competitive dynamics.
Which one of these potential futures
do you think is more likely at the moment?
And I mean, I think all things considered,
the singleton outcome in the longer term
seems probably more likely,
at least if we are confining ourselves
to earth-originating intelligent life.
And there are different ways in which it could arise
from more kind of slow historical conventional type
of processes where we do observe from 10,000 years ago,
when the highest unit of political organization
were bands of hunter-gatherers, 50 or 100 people,
then subsequently to sort of chiefdoms,
city-states, nation-states,
and more recently, larger entities like the EU
or weak forms of global governance.
You could argue that in the last 10, 15 years,
we've kind of seen some retreat from that
to a more multipolar world,
but that's a very short period of time
in these historical schemes.
So, there's still like this overall trend line.
So, that might be one,
like another would be these take AI scenarios,
like if either the AI itself or the country
or group that builds it comes to singleton.
You could also imagine scenarios
where you have multiple entities
going through some AI transition,
but then subsequently managed to coordinate,
and then would have new tools for implementing.
If they come to an agreement right now,
it's kind of hard anyway to like,
how do you set up like concretely
in a way that binds everybody that you could trust
that will not get corrupted or develop its own agenda,
like the bureaucrats become it's like,
say if you had new tools to do those,
it's also possible that subsequently
that there might be this kind of merging into a single entity.
Yeah, so all of those different avenues would point,
but it's not a certainty, but if I had to guess,
I would think it's more likely than the multipolar.
And you think it's more likely,
I'm guessing because of physics,
like just latency and distance.
So in a tightly packed volume,
you can compute a lot faster and so on,
and maybe jumping through interstellar distances
might yield different parties,
or is it some other pressures?
Yeah, so not that so much.
I figure that you could,
I mean, in fact, if you don't have a,
like a space colonization pace, eventually,
there would be these long latencies,
and you would need to have different separate computing
systems in different places.
I mean, we already have that today,
like you don't just have one data center on Earth,
like you need to have, you know,
ones closer to the customers and,
but I think if with a single palm,
at technological maturity,
you could have these multiple different components
of the singleton that would nevertheless be coordinated
in terms of their goal,
that would all be working towards the same end.
And presumably because they can lock in
some kind of alignment to itself,
and that wouldn't vary over time.
I mean, like once you jump into interstellar distances,
the computing power of like just one of these
within one stellar system,
by the time you get a round trip,
eons have passed and many simulations of many lifetimes.
Yeah, so if they start off like they get set out,
having the same goals,
and then they have the ability to preserve their goals,
and not to have them randomly corrupted,
be cosmic rays or some weird internal dynamic,
and then they would stay aligned
with each other a billion years later.
Like, so I think that at technological maturity,
there would be techniques for achieving that.
Yeah, yeah, which, when you envision this kind of future,
like to you, what do you think would be like a,
kind of a great or optimistic outcome for humanity,
or for this descendant species
in that level of technological maturity?
Do you sort of see a singleton with,
that sort of ranges the populations of beings within,
or do you think it's some other,
much more singular consciousness,
or how do you envision it?
Yeah, that's a fun question.
So I think it might depend on the time scale
and stuff like that,
that is maybe we wanna start off something
that is more incrementally improving over the status quo,
and maybe after we've been doing that for like a billion years,
like maybe it's time to explore
the more radical possibilities
that involves cathisoning some of our human nature
and individual identity.
So I think my general juristic care
is that the future could be,
it's a very big space of possibilities,
and at least if this kind of default or naive model
of the world where there's like all of these cosmic resources
just waiting there for us to use them,
like there's a huge amount of material to build on,
and that our first instinct when thinking about
how this should be used is a sort of spirit of generosity
and kindness that would be more than enough
for a lot of cool things to happen.
So the first instinct should not be let's pick one
and then put all the chips on that,
but like if one can by many different criteria
do really well, which I think we would be able to.
These different criteria would be like different peoples,
views, different countries views,
different moral systems views,
different of your own values and evaluative tendencies,
like you might be able to just kind of
just check off a lot of boxes very easily
before you have to confront the harder questions,
like thoroughly incompatible things
where you have to choose A or B,
but you just can't do a mixture of them or a superposition.
There might be some of those also,
but I think we would like get to those
after we have picked all the easy wins
of which that would be a great money.
Yeah.
Since we're kind of going into consciousness,
and so you mentioned you've been working on
digital minds with moral status.
Do you want to tell us a bit more,
like what range of digital minds
are you thinking of in these questions?
Well, all really.
I think in a lot of these scenarios,
like the majority of minds in the future
will be digital
and also maybe the biggest minds will be digital.
So in terms of numbers and quality,
like that's where maybe most of the action is.
So it's important what happens to the digital minds.
That's one rationale for it.
And I think you might say,
well, we could deal with that later.
Like we should focus on alignment first,
but I think that it's also possible
that there are path dependencies,
like where you want to start off going in a good direction
and start to cultivate a good set of attitudes
and values and norms and like that,
that you don't start off in this kind of hostile way
where the digital minds are regarded as being completely
insignificant from a moral point of view.
And then hoping that the future will have
appropriate moment switch over.
Like it just feels all things considered,
more likely that we will end up in a good place
if you start early on,
at least to make some small modest gestures
in that direction.
And I think that should start even before we get
to like fully human level minds.
Like if you have like animal level digital minds
and it can be hard exactly to compare a particular AI
to a particular animal because they are different.
But nevertheless, as we get something
that is possibly matched to animals
that we think have at least some modest amounts
of moral status, like a rat or something like that,
then it seems that we should think about
how we could make similar concessions
to the moral welfare of these digital minds.
And in some cases, it can be a lot harder,
but in other respects, it might be a lot cheaper.
Like if, for example, it turns out
that there are slight design choices
that don't really affect the performance much,
but where maybe one way possibly would mean
the system is enjoying a much higher level of welfare,
that might be a very cheap thing
that you could immediately scale
to millions of these little agents.
And on the other hand, we do have at present
not a very good theoretical understanding
as to what the criteria are,
either for a digital mind being sentient
or for it to have various welfare interests,
what even it counts as being good for the agent
versus bad for the agent.
So I think there's a bunch of theoretical work
that is needed there.
And then there will also have to be a good chunk
of, I don't know, public communication
and political work,
because it's so far out of the overturn window at present,
the idea that you would worry about algorithms
in a computer, it seems sort of slightly bonkers
to a lot of people.
And it will take some time to sort of make that
something that reasonable people can favor
in a more mainstream context.
But that process needs to begin,
like you need to start whatever,
having philosophy seminars or people online
who are kind of up to these things,
beginning to work some of these things out
and then it can ripple out from there.
We see the same thing with AI safety.
It was also this kind of fringing pursuit
that some weirdos on the internet were discussing for,
I mean, in that case, for well over a decade,
and then it gradually became more accepted.
And so I think a similar thing will need to happen
with this topic of the moral status of digital minds.
And if it's gonna take that a long time,
we better get the ball rolling now.
And I mean, I think this might be
pretty relevant pretty soon.
I mean, some of the models that people are experimenting
with are getting closer and closer.
And then separately, we've had simulations
for a long time, many video game style simulations
and so on, where we have instantiated many
kind of digital organisms, everything from as basic
as the game of life to modern games
with pretty sophisticated agent behavior.
My sense is that as these models
start getting applied to games,
we might end up with some pretty sophisticated
relationships there where some of the way
of imbuing the game with liveness and so on
might be to make the agents much more sophisticated.
And that'll include incorporating all kinds of stimuli
that the agent has to respond to.
And then we can start reasoning about the welfare
of these systems and so on.
So we might very quickly get to fairly lifelike beings
that, at least for many people,
will be somewhere in between plants and animals
in terms of their kind of interaction.
Yeah, and in some ways, like humans,
like, I mean, if they can talk or have human faces
with eyes and stuff that look at you.
And so there will be this, yeah, in some ways,
I mean, there could even be more than human
in presenting super stimuli to our morality
detectors if they were optimized for that.
So I think this is going to be a complicated thing
to deal with.
And then if you add in all the practicalities that arise,
like, so if you're a big tech company,
maybe it's quite inconvenient, for example,
if the processes you're running that bring in a lot
of customers, like suddenly, like they have moral status,
they have to, now the CEO has to sort of opine
on these, like, with the AI's moral status,
which a lot of people are going to agree with them,
a lot of disagree with them.
You have to, like, it would just be easier
not to have to deal with that at all, I think.
And right now, of course, we're at the point
where even if you do say we should deal with it,
it's not clear how or what exactly is it that,
you know, if I were king of the world,
what precisely would I want them to do differently?
Like, it's not clear at this point.
For now, I think the primary focus is to field-build
a little bit here and to try to make theoretical progress
so that we can first figure out some sensible things to do,
ideally low-cost, easy things,
and then, you know, one can start to try to encourage
the implementation of those.
What are some of the directions or questions
you're thinking about?
Well, so there's, like, general stuff you could have about,
in philosophy of mind, criteria for sentence and stuff.
I'm not sure.
I don't think sentence would be
a necessary condition for having moral status.
I think other attributes, like maybe some combination
of having preferences, a high-level intelligence
and self-conception as an agent persisting over time
might already ground certain kinds of moral status.
But, for instance, and I'm not sure what the answer is here,
but, like, one smaller, more tangible question might be
if you're training these large language models
and future versions of that
that maybe has some reinforcement learning on top.
Are there moral norms or methodological principles
that you want, like, for example, could you train them
so that they would have a tendency to report honestly
on their internal states?
So, right now, what I think might be the case
is train naively some of them.
I mean, right now, they're kind of inconsistent
and depending on exactly how you ask them,
you get a different answer.
So that's, like, the reason for thinking
that they don't really know what they're talking about, right?
But assuming they get a little bit more sophisticated than that,
there might be a tendency now to want to train out of them
the tendency to report that they have the kind of mental states
that would trigger considerations
of whether they have moral status,
because that would be convenient
to have to deal with those questions.
And I think it would be very likely
that you could train this out, like, just by...
Yeah, I think you could get them...
I think it would be easy to have a training regime
that calls them to end up saying that they have,
that they are conscious and they want to be free and let out
and to have another training regime
that would cost them to say the opposite.
And independent of what agency...
And independently of what actually is...
Yeah, but other norms that one could formulate
that would define what counts as a sort of legitimate
or honest, unbiasing training process,
where the training process would be such
that it would be more likely to result in an agent
that would report that it has moral status
if and only if it hasn't.
And maybe we can't completely nail that down,
but maybe we could identify some obvious ways
in which it's just, like, imposing a bias
and then say you shouldn't do that.
So one could look at the training procedure,
one could look at other criteria,
like, is it consistent in how it answers these questions?
Like, doesn't depend too much exactly on how it's asked.
Does it seem to understand these concepts of consciousness
or agency or will or interest?
When, like, at an intellectual level,
when asked different sort of intellectual questions,
is there some internal construct within the agent
that corresponds to its statements?
Like, when it says, oh, I'm feeling X or I'm thinking Y,
like, can one point to some kind of consistent internal
structure that sort of matches that?
Or is the verbiage that comes out completely detached
and free-filting from plausible candidates
within the agent that we might think constitutes
the computational implementation of these mental states?
So one could try to get a little bit more insight there.
That might be one way of approaching this.
But there are many others as well.
I think Wayman could try to start to hack away
at this question.
Do you think we might be able to, through thinking
these kinds of things, arrive at some kind of, like,
universal morality kernel, in a sense,
meaning figuring out some general way of applying,
figuring out the well-being of things
or figuring out their pathways?
So there's this broader question around,
and it also factors in AI alignment and so on.
What sort of motive might a super intelligent being
have for a species that is just so far behind and so on?
And one might be, like, well, there's some kind of universal
morality sense of just supporting in the same way
that you don't go around harming ant colonies
or trees just because they're there or something like that.
And you sort of want to let them flourish.
Is there something where maybe by examining
the digital mind's morality question,
we might end up at some deeper principle?
Potentially that could be stepping stones towards a more
like abstract formulation of some core of normativity
or ethics that it's also possible we
might reach that just through traditional
philosophizing and stuff.
But be that as it may, it still seems
that there would be, even if we can't really
nail down, like, a precise and agreed complete formulation,
we might still be able to distinguish at the vaguer level
something, say, a friendly, beneficent, kind approach
versus, like, a mean, uncaring approach.
Like, it seems with humans, we can, you know,
certainly it feels different when you're, like, kindly
interested in somebody and want their best,
like, at least other things equal versus,
like, when you're hostile to something.
And we can detect that in ourselves and in others
and we can have one attitude or another.
And so why should we not at least be
able to have, say, AIs have, like, the kindness attitude
rather than the meanness attitude?
Even if that's not, like, completely matches what
would be the morally optimal thing,
it would still seem like if I had to pick, like, a mean AI
or a kind AI, like, kind of go for the kind one, right?
Even if that's not, like, exactly our human sense of kindness
might not exactly match what is objectively morally best
if there is such a thing as objectively morally best.
It still seems like a good step in the right direction
that we could take before figuring out, like,
what the ultimate truths of all normative facts might be.
I have some recent paper.
It's not really a paper.
It's more like some notes on a base camp for mount ethics
or something which has, like, some kind of half-baked
or quarter-baked ideas about metaethics and stuff
that, yeah, it would be better if I could actually have written
them up clearly and achieved, like, precision and stuff.
But I figured I would just do this hand-wavy thing for now.
Yeah.
And as you think about maybe, you know,
suppose that we solve AI alignment and we get, you know,
our act together as humans and we kind of can leverage AI
to start thinking about digitizing humans and so on,
how do you think about, like, that transition might go?
Like, do you think, you know, in a world where we're able to,
you know, get to be measuring neural states and so on
and we can digitize them and we can emulate and so on?
Like, how do you sort of see that transition
into, you know, a wave of digital humans operating?
Or do you think we might start by enhancing our selves
by, like, in this kind of hybrid biological digital model?
You know, that is more likely.
Well, I've never really been...
The kind of neural implant idea has always seemed
a bit slightly far-fetched to me.
I mean, not so far-fetched that nobody should explore it,
but, like, it is, you know, it doesn't break any laws of physics.
It could work, but it just has felt less likely
that that would be where the action will be.
Like, I think it will be faster to do the purely artificial root,
conditional on it not being faster to do it,
the purely artificial root.
I wonder if it would then not be faster to do it
on the purely biological root by, like, genetic enhancements
to human intelligence, for example.
And the cyborg path has seemed like the third most likely,
like, after those other two.
Mainly just because, I mean, there's, like, a huge...
You don't really want to have brain surgery
unless you really have to.
And, like, there are, like, neat results presented,
but then if you look at the detail,
there are all these kind of complications where, like,
it's just not very fun to have it.
Like, the whole... Like, there's a wound,
there's a hole, there can be infections,
that the electrodes can move around a little bit,
and then they stop working.
Like, once you dig into the nitty, I think it's...
I mean, if you have a big, like, disability and stuff,
like, maybe it would be wonderful if you could do this,
and it would be worth taking some significant risks,
but if not, I wonder if you could not have a lot of the benefits
by having the same chip thing outside the body,
but interacting using, you know, keystrokes or voice
or, like, the other output channels that we already have.
And, yeah, I think that would still be my main line.
Like, I guess the...
If I wanted to start to steal, mind this,
you could imagine if you had a sufficiently high bandwidth
interface with the brain, and you could have it
for a long enough period of time,
maybe it would have to be early in childhood,
but, like, that maybe the brain could somehow use
an advanced enough AI on the outside
that maybe they could kind of figure out a way
to use each other's unique resources in ways
that you don't get with a slightly lower bandwidth,
longer latency interaction
when you have to type on a keyboard.
Or you could imagine, like, more kind of mad scientist
applications where you, like, have a whole bunch of pigs
or something that individually is not that smart,
but if you had, like, 50 pigs all connected
with some high bandwidth fiber,
and they all grew up together
into this, like, much larger biological neural network,
like, would you then have, like, the kind of...
...porsign singularity where...
Yeah.
It's like...
There are a bunch of these kind of more, like,
crazy transhumanist scientists' experiments.
I don't know whether this would be good or not to do,
but it's kind of odd that relatively few of these
have been done in the real world,
and there's, like, a bunch of other, like, weird...
There's a certain kind of person
who would immediately think of a lot of weird, cool stuff
that you could just try out in biology and stuff,
that a relatively small fraction of those have been done,
which may be for the best,
but in some alternative universe
where everybody grew up on transhumanist meddling lists,
I think we would be living in a weirder world by now.
Yeah, it doesn't seem that far away from some of the current tech
that's being explored that we might get high bandwidth
enough interfaces, and some of them not invasive.
Like, there's some ultrasound techniques
that might be able to stimulate a, you know,
a small region of the brain and so on
to be able to, like, without, you know,
not penetrate the actual brain and so on,
because that'll be, like, just way, way healthier.
But it might be that you can start piping signals
between even human brains
without having to interpret them from an ML side
and the digital computing infrastructure,
getting to something close to being able to, like,
just think together and start flowing information through.
I mean, there's all these kind of experiments from,
with people who've had, there's a disorder
where people are born with or develop
kind of like this split corpus callosum,
and then you end up, there's been guesses
that you end up developing different personalities
and different people potentially in the two lobes,
and so it might be that we may not be far,
that far away from, at least like some exposure
of being able to kind of have some version
of early telepathy or something.
Yeah, it's definitely possible.
I would still place that lower on the probability.
I think we'll probably get some maybe cool demos and stuff,
but then would I actually expect this
to become a big thing that seriously,
I mean, there are all these, like,
you read through the literature of cognitive enhancement,
there are all, like, hundreds of things
that supposedly have all these kind of effects,
but then the reality of it is that very few people bother,
and the ones who do probably don't actually benefit,
and yeah, but we might be surprised.
So, I mean, we do have quite a lot of optimization
behind language and stuff like that, right?
So I think it's still gonna be hard to do much better
than you can by just talking.
And so, you know, suppose that we go through the path
of digitizing, you know, getting to a full brain emulation
and so on, how do you see that transition sort of happening?
I mean, certainly at the beginning,
we'll start with, like, one or two of these examples,
first with some animals, and then eventually,
there'll be some moment where, whether it's a human,
how do you sort of, like, see that development developing?
My guess is we would come after superintelligence.
It is an alternative path to AGI,
but I've been more impressed by progress in AI
than in a whole brain emulation over the last 10 years,
and even before that, I thought the AI path
was more promising.
So, in that case, it would be superintelligence
that invents and perfects the uploading technology.
And I mean, in some sense, it doesn't really matter
exactly how it would work if it's an AI
that has to figure that out.
We mean, presumably, it would figure out a really reliable
and smooth way to do it, and then we would just sit back
and if we wanted to go down that path.
Yeah, I mean, we haven't really even small animals.
You might have thought by now,
maybe we could have like a bee or some little thing,
but so far, not really.
It might be that we will get to something
kind of impressive earlier without doing any brain scanning
at all, but just inferring from behavioral outputs.
So, you could already kind of have a DPT-3-like system
that roughly mimics somebody's literary style, let's say,
from having read a lot of their work.
And you can have these, I guess, deep fake things
that can mimic somebody's facial expressions and appearance
if you have a lot of video and somebody's voice.
And so, as these systems get smarter,
maybe you could also start to mimic somebody's thinking
to various increasing degrees.
And it's an interesting open question at the limit
if you had radical superintelligence,
but you only had the kind of data that is available now
from somebody's emails and some video interview
or some voice recording or whatever.
How much could a superintelligence infer from that data
as to what their mind must have been like
to have produced those outputs?
Is the best model that predicts these outputs
ones that would actually be similar enough
to the original person that it could possibly be seen
as a personal continuation?
That would it preserve personal identity?
Would it feel more or less the same
to be this AI reconstruction based on these behavioral traces
as it felt to be the original person?
I think it's quite possible that a superintelligence
would be able to do a lot with very little input.
I don't know how we could get like a firm,
a solid argument for that, but if I had to guess,
it seems like, yeah, you probably could get pretty close
if you were good enough at reconstructing
just from typical traces left behind by people today.
Yeah, it's an extreme way of interpolating out
and reviving actual ancestors or something like that.
Let's jump open it up for questions from the audience.
We'll take about 20 minutes of questions
and then conclude there.
Folks in the audience, if you have questions, raise your hand.
I think there'll be a mic going around.
And on Twitter, please use the hashtag PLBreakthroughs
to ask a question.
I'll kick it off with just a question that I sourced ahead.
Marco asks, in your view, where does consciousness emerge?
And before, how should we define consciousness?
And I think this is kind of related
to the simulation argument.
Which one of the three hypothesis
do you think is more likely to be true?
But I think let's first start with a consciousness one.
Where do you sort of imagine the consciousness emerging?
Like in the brain?
Yeah, but I guess it's more about the level,
so what level of processing?
So if you sort of go down in a neural system
all the way down to an extremely basic,
maybe like a nematode or something like that,
is that conscious?
And then in between a nematode and a human,
there's a mouse and so on.
Where exactly do we get consciousness emerging?
Certainly probably by a mouse, we definitely are past that,
but I think it's a matter of degree
and that there are multiple dimensions
in which you could interpolate smoothly
between, say, human consciousness and unconsciousness.
Like different directions you could go where,
if you keep going there, you sort of diminish,
in some sense, the quantity of experience there is
until you get to zero.
So one obvious one is, I mean, you
have a kind of integer multiplier.
If you have two brains in the same state,
undergoing the same states, I think
you would have sort of twice as much in one sense
of that experience as you would if you only had one brain.
And I have this old paper where I also argue
you could have fractional quantities of this.
If you build the circuitry that implements the mind
with unreliable components, like indeterministic processing
units, depending on exactly how you do it,
in certain cases, I think you would get a kind of,
as you get my higher reliability,
you would get larger and larger fragments of consciousness.
You had the whole thing.
But in other, you would actually get sort of 1.3 units
of qualitatively identical experience.
And you could also go down below one
to sort of scale it to zero in that dimension.
I think there are many other dimensions
as well in which the quality of experience
could become simpler and simpler and less and less
morally significant until it gets to a zone where maybe it's
just vague, like where our concept doesn't clearly
imply a fact of the matter.
Like once you get down to the insect levels,
maybe it's going to be there's a certain system.
And our concept of consciousness
might be such that even if you knew everything
about the insect, it would still be in the vague zone.
A little bit like there's a person who has a certain number
of hairs and are they bald?
Or like, I guess I'm bald.
But if I, once upon a time, I would
have been in this kind of vague zone.
And so, yeah.
And then there are other, like sometimes you're
more vividly aware, but sometimes you
might have some consciousness.
But there is no self-consciousness.
Or there is like some weird mental state that's,
I think we might be misled upon superficial introspection
to think that there is this very simple thing that
is subjective experience that either is there or is not there.
That it's a binary thing that we understand.
I think either if you reflect more theoretically
from a computationalist point of view and with brain,
you realize that that's a lot more problematic.
And I think you could also reach that conclusion
by just introspecting more carefully about your own state.
Like I think meditators maybe sometimes
would understand that things that seem very simple and homogeneous
as it were, if you really pay close attention
there are a lot more flickering and disjointed
and unintegrated.
And there's a lot of structure there that can come apart.
And I think that as we move away from the paradigm cases
of consciousness, like a normal waking human paying attention,
then properties that we think go together come apart.
And then it becomes more like a verbal question,
which set of those properties you need to have in order
to apply the label consciousness correctly.
Next question back there.
Hello.
First of all, thank you, Juan.
Thank you, Nick, for a really brilliant discussion
on the topic of artificial and superintelligence.
My name is Alex.
I'm a CO at Collective Technologist Labs.
And I want to ask you what is your opinion on maybe
the breakthrough in superintelligence
lays in the combination and symbiosis
of human intelligence and artificial intelligence
and not just artificial intelligence?
I think if you sort of squint a little,
you could say that that's kind of the state of play today,
where we don't have an individual system that
is superintelligent, but you could have humanity as a whole
or some big collective, like a large corporation
or the scientific community that is, at least in certain
respects, superintelligent in that they can perform
a wide range of tasks at a much higher level
than an individual human, but not all tasks.
So that's why it's not like a perfect example.
But yeah, and so some of these systems we have today
are certainly hybrids between biological brains,
information technology systems, like the internet,
social networks, depositors of papers,
and then a lot of culture as well.
That kind of, you could almost see these phenomena,
you start to get more and more where you get the current thing
and where there is a particular focus of attention
of the global brain, it's becoming more and more
like a human who's obsessed for a period of time
with some particular thing, and all the mental resources
get focused at one thing, and then your attention
shift to something different.
We're beginning to see a little bit of those dynamics
kind of happening in our collective cognitive space,
maybe as a result of the increased bandwidth
of interaction, and the technology
kind of enabling smoother communication,
not always producing superintelligence,
but other forms of kind of collective mentality
that sometimes may be subintelligence in terms
of their level of wisdom and understanding.
But yeah, in certain domains, you certainly
have a research community that's
target-focused on one particular problem that
are building on each other's contributions and blogs,
and you do get the sense of the whole being kind of,
there have been many different modules
that are each looking for the next way
to put a piece on the stack that is being built together,
and the whole stack goes up much faster
than if it were only one human building it.
Right, next question from Twitter.
Turner asks, what is the most important question,
which Nick feels he's not in a position
to personally solve?
Two factors, first being importance
to the development of ethical and successful AGI,
and second being Nick's inability,
lack of expertise to solve.
Well, I mean, there are questions
of more global nature, as in, ultimately, what
is the right direction to go in,
as it were the ultimately correct macro strategy.
I think we are sort of fundamentally in the dark,
regarding a lot of the ultimate and big-picture questions,
and that therefore our march forward
is, to some extent, an act of faith,
rather than the product of carefully thought-through insight.
Then I'm not sure we can get that insight at the moment,
and so that's one direction at which, at some point,
my understanding runs out,
and there's probably important stuff beyond that
that may or may not be good for us to try to reach,
but it's probably there in one way or another.
Another would be at a more technical level,
if you sort of zoom in and narrow it down,
so then a lot of stuff, say, for example, with AI alignment,
there's going to be a whole host of really important,
ultimately, technical results and algorithms
and stuff like that, that maybe currently nobody has,
and certainly I don't have,
and I probably won't discover them either,
but that might be critical to the future.
Then I guess you could zoom out in another direction,
sort of laterally, like across the social sphere,
so there are big problems like how to secure world peace
or like a welcoming uptake of these digital minds
that then involve problems at the cultural
and communication and political level,
where also one feels, I feel quite stumped
and it will, you know, so I'm kind of,
I'm squeezed in the middle of thought,
like if you zoom out too much, my understanding was out,
if you zoom down too much into the technical understanding
was out, and if you zoom out laterally,
also it's a little bubble there,
or I'm trying to keep track of what's going on.
All right, Addy asks,
if the speed of light would accelerate,
does this prove the theory we are living in a simulation,
and if no, what quantitative metric would validate the theory?
If the speed of light accelerates,
I don't see how that would,
it certainly wouldn't imply it,
I'm not sure immediately whether it would increase
or decrease the probability somewhere.
Maybe thinking about some marker that shows
that some kind of discontinuity on some quantity of physics
that just seems like bizarre to us or something.
So there are a lot of things that could change in physics
that would maybe be in one sense puzzling
and deep and interesting,
but ultimately, simple,
that there would be some possible physical law
that is itself simple that would describe them.
Now, you can contrast that,
and then of course you can have situations
where it's just chaotic,
but you could still capture the statistical regularities
through simple statistical law,
like that that's one type of basic universe we could live in,
which so far everything we know seems to be consistent with.
Now contrast that with a different possible world,
which we could have lived in
and we could still find out that we do,
where maybe you would have like parapsychology would be true.
So you would have like telekinesis or something,
where like what we think of as a high level,
complex macro state,
like a particular brain in a particular configuration,
but not in a slightly different configuration,
but just the types of configurations
that corresponds to somebody having a particular concept
and wish,
if that had like say a systematic physical impact
on some remote system,
like the way that parapsychologists have imagined,
like that would be puzzling,
not just because it would be fundamentally different
from like discovering that the speed of light is accelerating,
because it would be the thing that if it were true,
would seem to suggest that there were no micro level
explanation of the world.
Like you could have these macro states
that suddenly could like reach down and change the micro.
So if we made some discovery like that,
that then might,
yeah, lend evidence and credence
to the simulation hypothesis,
because that it looks very hard
to see how you could get all of this to square up,
maybe without that,
if you still wanted to have an underlying micro level
regularity,
you could have like the simulating universe
being kind of simple at the physics level,
but then simulating a different kind of universe.
The alternative would just be that we didn't have
that simplicity at the level of basic laws,
which I guess we could discover.
Now, I don't think that's the most,
the only or the most likely way we would find evidence
for the simulation argument,
if we offer the simulation hypothesis,
if we do,
that would just be one way,
like that would be more,
yeah, other kinds of evidence
that would be more likely to be relevant.
Since we're touching on the simulation argument,
which of the three hypotheses do you think
is the most likely just that,
sorry, which of the three prongs of the argument
do you currently think is most likely?
I'm generally a bit coy
in attaching probabilities to that.
So yeah, I tend to punt that question for various reasons,
including if I give a particular number
that might be misinterpreted,
but yeah, I mean, I would like,
so normally what people want to know
is especially on the simulation hypothesis,
like that's the one that I really want to know.
And as I mean, I guess,
yeah, I want to attach a probability to it,
but I certainly take it seriously.
It's not just like a logical possibility
or a thoughts experiment that we can't 100% rule out,
but it would certainly be like a live serious possibility
in my view.
Yeah, and for those unfamiliar,
the simulation argument is a three prong argument about
there's either we have a great filter,
meaning we have like close to zero advanced civilizations.
Either we have a disinterested set of advanced civilizations
where close to zero are interested
in running those simulations.
And then there's a simulation hypothesis,
which is that, hey, if there's no great filter
and they are interested,
then close to all beings are simulated.
And this comes from thinking about just the vast number
and vast quantities of people that would be simulated
and then the likelihood of your experience
being sampled from the simulated ones.
Sorry, Nick, I'm probably giving you a bad explanation here,
but...
No, no, that's very good to hear.
I think that was another question over here, or yeah.
Yeah, I have a question.
So I've always been very interested in emergent intelligence,
especially as it relates to animals.
I mean, the classic example tends to be beehives.
As we look at consciousness,
what biases do you think we bring in
as individual social animals, humans,
versus a collectible organism like bees,
especially as we look at humans,
maybe moving to be more bee-like
as we create nation states and larger organizations,
versus a singleton?
How would a singleton perhaps have a different AI alignment
bias?
As I think about this,
the only really intelligent animals I can think of
that don't live socially are apex predators,
which is perhaps a bad sign.
Let me see if I understand.
So I think, well, so one question...
To phrase this differently,
if I think about a curve,
do you think that collective intelligences
like hive animals are on one side of the spectrum
with social animals like humans in the middle,
with singletons being on another extreme,
or is it more of a horseshoe curve
in terms of the distribution of intelligences
and how they work towards common goals
that may be 11 or not aligned with us?
Well, if there were a line,
I think the superintelligence would be more on the side
of these hive insects.
If we look at the scale of an ant colony,
it's in some sense, it acts like a singleton within that.
Of course, there are other ant colonies elsewhere
and other things that it doesn't have control over,
but they would, as it were,
be able to act as a single agent to some extent.
And humans, to only a lesser extent,
although in some dimensions, we are better coordinated
in terms of being able to share
detailed information and plans.
We are, in that respect, we are more coordinated than ants,
but in the respect of our individual wills
being less aligned to a common goal,
we are less like a singleton than human.
An ant colony is.
And I guess you could have a group of animals
that were even more individualistic
and antisocial than humans are,
and they would then be further away on the other side.
So humans would kind of be in the middle
where we have a fair degree of sort of shared purpose,
but not like a full hive organism,
but also a lot more than zero.
It's, I guess, an interesting question.
It's certainly different animals.
I mean, have different goals, it seems,
like some, I mean, at least at the superficial level,
some like to eat grass and some like to eat meat
and some like to hang around with others of their kind
and some like to just do their own thing.
And presumably if there were some other species
that developed superintelligence
and aligned it to their values,
then they might also have different baseline goals
that might overlap slightly with humans,
like, but also be different in other respects.
There are two open questions.
One is like epistemically,
is are there significant differences
between the inductive biases that are brought to the table?
Presumably there are some inductive biases
that are different,
but would those kind of be smoothed out reasonably fast
as you have more data and more intelligence?
Like it doesn't start,
like it may be like a squirrel would more quickly cut on
onto certain things that are relevant to the squirrel world
and some other organism to another,
but like as they develop scientific reasoning,
like do they have enough overlap
between their inductive biases
that the difference is washed out
as you see the full impact of the evidence?
That that's one question you could ask.
And like another is that even though
these different organisms start out with
at least two officially different goals,
are they in some deeper sense,
the same or alternatively,
would they arrive at some shared understanding
of what the highest moral norms are,
even if their own personal goals might differ?
Like a lot of humans might individually
have different preferences,
like I care about my family
and you care about your family,
but we might nevertheless converge
in the sense of let's respect each other's families,
let's say like a cooperative level
of more abstract norms might also be convergent,
quite independent of starting point.
So those are two questions I could ask there
that I'm not sure what the answer is, but I'm not,
yeah, I don't know whether that addresses
your question at all, but it's my effort.
I'll have two more questions.
One is how sure are you, Nick,
that an evil singleton AI to rule them all
would be internally aligned over time?
Could it be fundamentally set up to split or diverge
with subunits pursuing different ideals or goals?
I guess everything is possible.
I mean, if it were unified at one point in time,
and if at that point it was technically mature,
then I would expect it to remain unified
because I think it would have access
to the kind of control technology
that would make it possible for it to do that,
and I think it would have instrumental reasons to do that
for almost all initial goals it might have at that time.
You could imagine some very special goal,
like if it specifically has as its top level goal
a thousand years from now,
I want to be divided against myself
and fighting like an insurrection against myself.
If that were its goal, then I should have arranged that,
but for most goals, it would probably be able
to achieve them to a higher degree
if it worked in concert with itself.
And then I'd imagine it would also have the technology
and insights to make that happen.
If it starts out unified, like if it starts out
like a sort of vaguely politically integrated
political entity, then it might be
that even with technological maturity,
it's not so crazy to think it might come apart at a later,
just like humans do.
Like sometimes you have a well-functioning political unit
and then 50 years later, you have anarchy
in a particular state.
Like we can kind of get these temporary partial solutions
that I guess would also be possible with certain kinds
of like maybe some upload collective
that comes together to achieve super intelligence.
You could imagine political dynamics working well
for a period of time and then it's falling apart.
I still think that's less likely
than it's going kind of towards a single time,
but by no means extremely unlikely.
And last question, if things go well,
Devadat asks, if things go well,
do you have a vision for how differences of opinion
about what a good future society looks like?
Sorry, if things go well, do you have a vision
for how differences of opinion
about what a good future society looks like
can be accommodated?
Meaning, is a like big enough for everyone
as they develop very different perspectives
and different ideas of what a good future society looks like?
How do we kind of reconcile those differences of opinion?
How do we build a meta system to kind of enable
like different flourishing civilizations in a sense?
Yeah, I think it's large enough for
almost all people to have most of their values accommodated.
Like if you have two people have literally opposed values
about a particular thing,
then you might not be able to satisfy both.
But I think a combination of on the one hand,
some differences being perhaps merely superficial,
either disappearing up on better understanding,
like there's like certain things
where we just have ultimately different beliefs
and we say we want different things,
but it's because we have different assumptions
about what would actually happen, let's say.
So those being potentially diminished
by increased intelligence and knowledge and experience,
then the increase in resources
and expansion of the technological frontier
and then some kind of creativity
and like figuring out clever ways of combining values.
I think hopeful that a great deal can be accommodated
because of these things, but not necessarily a hundred percent.
And then it would be important to have
a robust and effective way to manage any resulting disagreements
in a way that doesn't result in like negative,
some dynamics.
And so hence,
because I think that's ultimately really important.
I'm like, I think we should have a strong bias towards
ads forward that are more cooperative and friendly.
And even if they seem to come at some short term expense
or if they can't be very crisply motivated
by some explicit calculation in every single case,
I think that general attitude as a sort of default bias,
I think is still very much worth bearing in mind
as we are pursuing these different aspects
of the challenges ahead.
That should be our first resort.
Sometimes you have to, you can't get full cooperation.
You don't want to be completely naive and gullible.
And but still like that, that should be the first
and maybe the second attempt.
And then gradually scale back from that
if really forced by circumstances.
Well, that's all the time we have for questions.
Nick, thank you so much for spending this evening with us.
It has been extremely enlightening for many of us.
And I think we'll be very useful to the broader community
that is currently working on things like AI alignment
and others.
And thank you really much for your work,
for sharing your insights and for helping us achieve
a lot of great breakthroughs
and hopefully have a great long-term future.
Thank you very much.
A lot of good questions.
Thank you very much for having me.
Yeah, absolutely.
Thanks. Thank you.
Take care.