These organizations are telling you that they're building something that could kill
you and something that could remove all our freedom and liberty. And they're
saying it's a good thing you should back them because it's cool. They don't care
about the revenue. If they have the political power people are scared of
them. Power should not be invested in any one individual. If I can accelerate this
over the next period I don't have to make an impact. I should not have any power
whereas again you see everyone else trying to get more and more power.
The only way that you can beat it to create the standard that represents humanity
is decentralized intelligence. It's collective intelligence.
The data sets and norms from that will be ones that help children, that help people suffering,
that reflect our moral upstanding and the best of us and gathers the best of us to do it.
A week ago, E-Mod Mistak was on my stage at Abundance 360 talking about the future of
open source AI, democratized, decentralized AI. The day after A360 he stepped down as CEO of
Stability. Now five days later I've sat down with E-Mod to talk about why he's stepping down,
what he's doing next, the future of AI. He takes the gloves off, he talks about the dangers of
centralized AI and the potential for decentralized democratized AI to be the only avenue that truly
uplifts all of humanity. All right, if you liked this episode please subscribe. Let's jump in. If
you're a mood shot entrepreneur this is an episode you're not going to want to miss. All right,
now on to E-Mod. Good morning E-Mod. Good to see you my friend.
Actually it's always pizza. So you and I were on stage literally last week at the 2024 Abundance
Summit talking about the whole open source AI movement. You were beginning to talk about
decentralized AI. You were talking about where Stability was the speed of the development of
the different products and the day after the Abundance Summit was over the news hit that you
had stepped down as CEO of Stability and stepped off the board. So let's begin with the obvious
question. Why? What happened and I have huge respect for you and I know a lot of the issues in the
past but I'd like you to have a chance to share with entrepreneurs out there and folks interested in
AI exactly your side of what's happening. Yeah, thanks. I think that Elon Musk once characterized
being a CEO as staring into the abyss and chewing glass because you are looking at a very uncertain
future having to make decisions and the chewing glass is all the problems that come to you all
the time and it's required to steer the ship when things are incredibly uncertain and Stability
is a pretty unique company at a unique time. We hired our first developer and researcher two
years ago and then in those two years we built the best models of almost every type except for large
language, image, audio, 3D etc and had over 300 million downloads of the various models we created
and supported which was a bit crazy and then gent of AI is crazy. In terms of usually in a startup
you don't have to deal with global leaders and policy debates about the future of humanity
and AI and everything else. At the same time building code. At the same time as building code
yes and especially building code to a fraction of the resources of our competitors. We had
certain teams that offered triple their entire packages to move to other companies. It was
grateful that only a couple of researchers left for other companies and that was just startups.
No one left for another big company which I think is testament to their kind of loyalty in the mission
but you know what we've seen over the last year is or last half year in particular is the question
of governance in AI is something that's incredibly important and who manages, owns, controls this
technology and how it's distributed. So we saw you know everything from kind of open AI to congressional
testimonies to other things and as you know one of my things has always been how do we get this
technology in the hands of people all around the world and then who governs it and how can we then
take this technology to have an impact from education to healthcare to others. The stability
is a company that build great base models and we got to that point. The revenue is going up
which is always nice you know finding the business model and again I think it was always curious to
see that as a deep tech company two years in people are asking us you know why aren't you
profitable and I was like right it takes a bit of time and investment to get to profitability.
I think opening AI when they took they're not there yet but then they have eight years I think
all the comparisons are perhaps unfair. So reviewing everything and kind of looking at it I was like
do I really want to be a CEO? I think the answer is no. I think there is a lot imbued in that in
tech but it's a very interesting position. Just to dive into that a second because we've had this
conversation because there was a lot of pressure asking whether for you to step down as CEO
and I think founders typically want to see themselves or feel they need to be the CEO
and I've heard you say recently you know that you view yourself more as a founder and strategist
than the CEO is that a fair assessment? Yeah I think everyone's got their own skill sets right
so I'm particularly great at taking creatives, developers, researchers, others and achieving
their full potential in designing systems but I should not be dealing with you know HR and
operations and business development and other elements they're probably better people than me
to do that. So now for example our most popular thing Stable Diffusion and come to UI the system
around it is the most widely used image software models in the world. There are great media CEOs
that can take that and amplify that to make hundreds of millions of revenues so they should come in
and meet on that. So why now pal what is there anything that specifically tipped for you that has
I mean because you know it has you know you have done an extraordinary job this has been your baby
I mean how you have to feel a whole slew of emotional elements and I've had to step down
as CEO on two occasions over the 27 companies I've had to sell a company for pennies on the
dollar and it takes an emotional hardship on you. I've had calls for me to step down as CEO
since the well since 2022 you know but I always thought you know what's best for the company in
the mission and where I look at the world right now there's a few things a the company has momentum
it has spread it's turning into a business like last year I said let's not enter into large revenue
contracts because technology isn't mature yet and our processes aren't mature yet and you have to
deliver so we do a lot of experimental things we're setting up and again now it's ramping
on a business side on a technology side the technology is maturing diffusion transformers
such as stable diffusion 3 and saura are going to be the next big thing and again stability has
got a great place there but I think there's also the macro on this so if you look at the open AI
you know sam altman said the board can fire me anytime this is the governance of open AI
and then they fired him and then he is back on and he appoints himself back on the board
there's clearly no governance opening I mean I respect the people on the board greatly
you know I think there's some great individuals but who should manage the technology that drives
humanity and teaches every child and manages our governance who's really needy on that that can build
these models and do those things as you know I've always wanted to build these science models and
the other health teams done that I want me doing the education work and then my concept of a national
model for every country owned by the people of the country all tied together I think it needs to be
by a web three not crypto or necessary token framework that's something that's a brand new
kind of challenge and one that I think there's only a window of a year or two to do if you have
highly capable models let's put aside a geo for now which you can discuss later
really accelerating then no one will be able to keep up with that unless you build in a decentralized
manner and distributed manner for data talent distribution standards and more so there's only
a small window of time here to do that and realistically again successful companies and
these things are all great but genitifia is a bit bigger than the classical knobs just like
the whole lifecycle of the company was a lot faster than the classical norms so that's why I
felt you know now is the right time to make that change and hopefully play my part in making sure
this technology is distributed as widely as possible and governed properly as pretty much I
think I'm the only real independent agent that has built state-of-the-art models in the world right
now yeah we've seen a lot of turbulence with open AI we just saw Mustafa from inflection become part
of Microsoft and I am curious I mean you you had a now famous conversation with Satya a couple of
days after stepping down was that investigatory on your part or was that just a touch base for
an old friend oh that's just chill trolling actually you know like to let us in steam that
picture was I think from when year or two year or so ago okay but you know I think Satya is an
amazing CEO and you know he responds again like the top CEO's incredibly quickly when you message
he's got a great vision but there is again this concern about consolidation in tech
we didn't take money from any trillion dollar companies that stability you know we remained
and retained full independence you know and you know to the detriment of some of the elements
that we could have taken very big checks and other things and even though you have good attention
to that room that companies are slight slow dumb ai's that over optimize for various things
and that's more solely in the best interest of humanity when you have infrastructure
it's like this is the airports the railways the roads of the future AI is an infrastructure
gentle that is an infrastructure which should be and should it be consolidated under the control
of a few private companies with unclear objective functions again the people in the companies may
be great I don't think so and this is a key concern and part of that was that commentary again he's
doing an amazing job he's consolidating a lot of power for the good of the company and also he has
I think genuinely good heart mission to bring technology to the world but it is a bit concerning
right especially with the new types of structure you're speaking of Sam in this case
Satya here oh sat here like a really like again I think the commentary was always interesting
it's like you know sat here playing 40 chess you know assembling the AI Avengers I mean he is
he's building an amazing massive talent covering the bases and Microsoft is doing incredibly well
here right if you asked who's doing best to join tomorrow I think would say Microsoft
but there is has to be concerns about consolidation of talent and power and reach
before I get to your vision going forward because it's so important and what you're doing next
I just again as a founder as a CEO of a moonshot company we have a lot of those listening here
can ask how are you feeling right now because the decision to step down has to have huge emotional
are you feeling relief are you feeling anxiety what's what's the feeling after making a momentous
decision I was a big feeling of relief you know because there's the there's a Japanese concept
I know a guy and I love it yes yeah do what you like and do where you believe you're adding value
and other people do too you know like realistically again I think I was an excellent research leader
strategist other things but I didn't communicate properly or hire the right other leaders in
certain other areas of the company and they're better people to do that and so I wasn't doing
what I was best at a lot or I could have the most measurable value and it was tying down you know
there's a lot of legacy you know technical organization or other debt especially when
you grow so so so fast and you know we were lucky that we had higher attention in the
important areas and we could execute in spite of all of that in spite of going to be company
around I think you know moonshot founders you have to do because you don't have the resources at
the start and you have to guide the ship you know as it goes out from port but there does come that
transition point there and there is a competing thing where you typically take on VC money which
holds an objective function versus your overall mission so again if you look at the genitive
AI world right now how many credible intelligent independent voices are there there they've had
the ability to build models and design things and make an impact you know there's not many so
I was like that's where I can add my most leverage and also the design space is again
is unprecedentedly huge because the entire market has just been created like where does
gentify not fit and where does it not touch and what needs to be built there we need to actually
have the agency to go and build that and so I felt tired relieved I felt that now there's a
million options I want it rather than taking a long break get on with things I've just done the
first thing in kind of web three and I've got a whole bunch of other things we were going to discuss
kind of coming and catalyze stuff that can make an exponential benefit because you know like massively
transformed to purpose here is I want every kid to achieve their potential and give them the tools
to do that and I love you for that because you've been true to that that vision and I know on the
heels of your announcement you've been reached out to by national leaders by corporate you know by
CEOs and major investment groups and you have a lot of opportunity ahead of you so
let's talk about where you want to go next you mentioned publicly and you discussed on our
abundance stage the idea of democratized and decentralized AI let's define that first what
is that why is it important and what do you want to do there yeah I think that when I said I'm going
move to do my part in decentralizing AI people like isn't that just open source you give the
technology right and then anyone can use it but it isn't a decentralizing AI has a few important
components one is availability and accessibility everyone should be able to access this technology
the fruits of labor and there's some very interesting political and other elements around that
number two is the governance of this technology you have centralized governance because the models
are the data there's a recent Databricks thing a model where they show that you have massive
improvements from data we all know that you know who governs the data that teaches your child or
manages your health or runs your government that's an important question I think too few are asking
and we need this transparency and other things like that so accessibility you know you've got the
governance aspect of that and then finally you have how does it all come together is a single
package or is it a modularized infrastructure that people can build on and is available kind
of everywhere you know does it require monoliths and central servers where if it goes down you have
an outage on GPT-4 you're a bit messed up or someone can attack and corrupt it I think that
those are kind of the key elements that I was looking at when I was talking about decentralizing AI
and you know I've got with an infrastructure to do that I hope as well so if you don't mind let's
double click on it even further so you mentioned we don't have long to get there
if that's a true statement why don't we have long to get there and then what does getting
there look like if you had all the capital available and if the right national leaders were
hearing about this because a lot of this is supporting supporting the populace of a nation
um to have AI that serves them versus top down what's it look like two five ten years from now
yeah I think you'll have both proprietary and open source AI and they'll work in combination the
practical example I give is that this AI is like graduates right very talented slightly
enthusiastic graduates and you want those and consultants um but I really have you know on
stage with Matt Friedman last week at 8 360 when we're there he said it's like we discovered this
new concept what do you call it AI Atlantis yes yes with a hundred billion graduates that'll work
for free yes I love that analogy it was it was a brilliant analogy yeah we used to figure out how to
say Atlantis you know um but but there's a few things here first of all is the defaults you know
once a government embraces centralized technology it's very difficult to decentralize it and every
country needs an AI strategy a year ago one year ago was GPT-4 yeah crazy how crazy is that you know
the AI safety summit uh in the UK the king of England came on stage it all came via video call
and he said that this is the biggest thing since fire you know and that was like what six seven
months later where are we going to be in a year yeah I think he took that from uh uh from uh uh
the founder of the CEO of Google um AI is as powerful as fire and electricity yeah yeah yeah
I've heard the same from like Jeff Bezos and a bunch of others you know and not kindle fire
proper fire you know um but then if you think about it norms are going to be set in this next
period like you know I'm in California LA at the moment if you don't set norms on rights for actors
and the movie industry then you could have a massive disruption just occurring this full length
Hollywood features come in a year or two generated you know if you don't have norms around open models
and ownership and governance by the people it'll be top-down governance because governments can't
allow that to be out of control if they don't have a reasonable alternative um and I think the
window is only a year or two because every government must have a strategy by the end of the year
and so I think if you provide them a good solution that has this element of democratic
governance and others that will be immensely beneficial I think also it's urgent because
we have the ability to make a huge difference you know as we kind of may probably discuss later
having all the knowledge of cancer longevity autism at your fingertips you know the technology
for that right now you have the technology that no one ever is ever alone again on those things
or to give every child a superior education literally in a couple of years like there is an
urgency both from there's a small window but also from we must do this now because it can scale and
make that impact we have dreamed of for so long the enabling technology is finally in it's finally
good enough fast enough and cheap enough everybody want to take a short break from our episode to
talk about a company that's very important to me and could actually save your life or the life of
someone that you love company is called fountain life and it's a company I started years ago with
Tony Robbins and a group of very talented physicians you know most of us don't actually know what's
going on inside our body we're all optimists until that day when you have a pain in your side you go
to the physician in the emergency room and they say listen I'm sorry to tell you this but you have
this stage three or four going on and you know it didn't start that morning it probably was a problem
that's been going on for some time but because we never look we don't find out so what we built
at fountain life was the world's most advanced diagnostic centers we have four across the U.S.
today and we're building 20 around the world these centers give you a full body MRI a brain a brain
vasculature an AI enabled coronary CT looking for soft plaque dexa scan a grail blood cancer test
a full executive blood workup it's the most advanced workup you'll ever receive 150 gigabytes of data
that then go to our AIs and our physicians to find any disease at the very beginning when it's
solvable you're gonna find out eventually might as well find out when you can take action fountain
life also has an entire side of therapeutics we look around the world for the most advanced
therapeutics that can add 10 20 healthy years to your life and we provide them to you at our centers
so if this is of interest to you please go and check it out go to fountainlife.com backslash
peter when tony and i wrote our new york times bestseller life force we had 30 000 people reached
out to us for fountain life memberships if you go to fountainlife.com backslash peter we'll put you
to the top of the list really it's something that is for me one of the most important things i offer
my entire family the CEOs of my companies my friends it's a chance to really add decades onto
our healthy lifespans go to fountainlife.com backslash peter it's one of the most important
things i can offer to you as one of my listeners all right let's go back to our episode so the
let's talk about the objective function of democratized and decentralized AI is it that the
compute is resonant in countries around the world is it that the models are owned by the
citizens of the world is it that data is owned and how do you get there from here i think that
you can think of the supercomputers like universities you don't need many universities
honestly if someone's building good quality models that's one of the things that says stability
and we did the hard task we could just stuck with image we said no we're gonna have the best 3d
image audio biomedical all these models and no one else managed that apart from open ai to agree
in fact i think we have more modalities than open ai again kind of what i kind of describe this
is accessibility and governance and a few of these other factors so i think what it means is that
this technology is available to everyone but you see now that you don't assume you need giant
supercomputers to even run it you know we showed you a language model running on a laptop stable
lm2 will run on a gigabyte on a mac macare faster than you can read you know we're writing some poems
various things you know um we see stable diffusion now at 300 images a second or consumer graphics
card our video model was like five gigabytes of v-round this really changes the equation because
in web 2 all the intelligence was centralized on these giant servers and big data now you have
big supercomputers i think you'll need less with better data training these graduates that can go
out and customize to each country but they must reflect the culture of that country like the
japanese stable diffusion model we had if you typed in salary man it gave you a very sad person
versus the base model giving you a very happy person right so you must have graduates that
reflect the local culture and then reflect the local knowledge and then global models again
that reflect our global knowledge and can be answered by anyone but who decides what goes
in that these are some very important questions and who vouchers for the quality as well what's
your advice to a national leader because you know we're now starting to see ministers of AI
in different nation states and what what's your advice to them right now in this area
i think my advice to them would be to start collecting the data sets that they would teach
a graduate that was very smart through school and kind of other things this is national broadcast
data this is the curriculum this is their accounting legal and others and note that those
data sets are infrastructure they will enable the local populist and others to create these models
because models are just data wrapped in algorithms with a bit of compute that's the recipe compute
algorithms and data and it's not going to be as hard as you think to train these models but you
have to build them to get standard so by the end of next year probably year after i would estimate
that a longer 7tb model or a stable diffusion model so these are two leading models in image
and language will cost about under ten thousand dollars probably even one thousand dollars to
train and then it comes all about the data and then it becomes about the standards
you know it's it's it it's interesting um there is so much knowledge in the world that will
vaporize sublimate over the decade ahead as people die you know cultural data locked up in
people's minds and stories and so forth that's never been recorded it's an interesting time to
actually capture that data and permanently store it into the national models yeah and again i think
people over focus on the models versus the data sets i mean is data set yeah yeah yeah with the
exponential compute you can recalibrate and improve the data as well so right now a lot of the
improvements in models are actually synthetically improving data and data quality as you said there's
so much that can be lost but now we can actually capture this and the concepts and the other
guidance and have crosschecks like you can deconstruct laws you know you can translate
between contexts you can make expert information available to everyone because again you have
this new continent of ai around us and all these graduates seem to be specialists that are on your
phone and that's incredibly democratizing you know um because otherwise the knowledge is
throughout history knowledge has always been gate kept always i want to get to uh health
and education next but before we go there i know you were meeting with a mutual friend
jewels or back the other day um and instability announced a deal with otoi endeavor and render
network um are you still an advisor to that venture you know this is part of the whole thing
it's the first of many web three kind of elements there i think web three is 95 percent let's say
90 percent i'll be generous um speculative and rubbish but there is that five ten percent of
genuine people that would be thinking about questions of governance coordination and others
and have built things that are proper so otoi is the bridge to the creative industry you know
that's why we're with arie manuel and eric schmidt and others are on the board um and the render
network is a million gpus largely from creative professionals that are available and so the first
thing i announced there i was going to be initial 10 million gaps 250 million of distributed compute
to create the best 3d data sets like stability we funded and worked with allen institution others on
objeverse excel which is 10 million high quality 3d assets we're going to a billion distributed
you don't need giant supercomputers but then that is a community good that is owned by the people of
the network and accessible to non-academic and others as well why because you need high quality
assets to create better 3d models we have a new 3d model tried by us all that can generate a 3d
image from a 2d image and not go five seconds and that 3d model feeds into better 3d assets
and then what does that mean it means we're heading towards the holodeck without the data
you're not going to get there and that joules joules wants the holodeck for sure yeah so you
know jules and i are the same phase of that you know and you're not going to get there without
again a commons of data that can train the graduates that then become specialized with star trek or
you know star wars or any of these other ips and then also setting standards around
monetization ip rights all sorts of other things and so a network like render is really good for
that but you know i've been talking to a lot of people in web three about the different elements
of the stack because what i basically see is that we have the opportunity to build
almost a human operating system models and data sets for every nation every sector coordinated
through proper web three principles again not speculative tokens or anything like that
you know making it so that every child in the world or adult can create anything they can imagine
they can be protected against the harms and they have access to the right information at the right
time to thrive and again that's infrastructure for everyone it's a common good access to gpu's has
been sort of the limited fuel um do you think decentralized gpu structures like render is part
of that future is an important part of that future i think right now it's far more efficient to train
models on these again big supercomputers the university but the rate of exponential growth
there again is insane last year to train lama two cost ten million dollars in a year or cost
ten thousand dollars a thousand times improvement from algorithms data supercomputes speeds
and that's crazy if you think about it right um so i think this will be the limiting factor i think
the gpu overhang four language models probably lasts until the end of the year but then there's
plentiful supply because what you have is nvidia makes amazing gpu's at an 83 or 87 percent margin
right but the actual calculations aren't complicated like we took intel gpu's and we ran the stable
diffusion three diffusion transformer training so this is the same technology that's used in
saura and stable diffusion three is multimodal so it can train saura models with enough compute
and i think us and them are the only people kind of doing this so i think maybe pixart as well
and then it ran faster than the intel gpu's than the nvidia gpu's but we know that it can run even
faster because it's not optimized for either and it's still running fast so what you'll see
is a commoditization of the hardware once the architect just gets stabilized because gpu is
just a research artifact still diffusion was just a research artifact you're not going to
engineer in phase yet and you've got to the point whereby this runs on macbooks it runs on other
things so i think it's a short term phenomenon of the next year because people were taking a point
in time and extrapolating without taking into account efficiencies optimizations
and the fact that models that work on the edge and it can go to your private data will be more
impactful than generalized intelligence everyone's over indexing on generalized intelligence and
building ai god versus amplified human intelligence shall we say before we leave stability it's now
in the hands of the chair and your past cto what's what do you imagine the future of stability
is going to be going forward i know that you're not involved anymore it's under different leadership
and there's a what's your advice to them or where do you think they're going to go
you know i can do the very basic advice i didn't want any conflicts or anything because
i'll be setting up lots of new companies and you know being a founder and a shareholder
and against stability i'm a founder shareholder in fact you're still the majority shareholder
i think i said right now yeah just about just about yeah that will change i'm sure new money
will come in like we saw co here yesterday and i think it's very little 20 million of revenue
run rate they're raising at five billion might as well it's increasing yes yeah with the right
leadership i think that um it can again have an amazing part to play in media and that's what i've
suggested to it um and again there's a great team that continues to ship great models so last week
there was an amazing code model next week amazing language audio and other models are coming out so
you know you continue shipping and great products around that too um so that was kind of my advice
to them let's focus on media and take that forward but you know i'm not the expert on the business
side of things i did the best i could my expertise on setting this up and taking it 0 to 10 and uh
yeah is zero zero one is is definitely um a role that that you've played here and allow it allow
someone else to take it the rest of the way uh but the area that i know actually there's something
i wanted to kind of discuss here that thing's quite important please or again the founder's
listing and the moonshot companies um there is an imbalance of power when you have
very visionary highly competent leaders there like what i found its stability is there everyone
would be waiting for me no matter how competent because i was the one that could see around the
corners and i was a bit good at everything even if i hired people that built billion dollar startups
or were leaders and research at google or kind of whatever um because you have an outside thing
this is what kind of better says you have to speak last in some cases and some people in eating
because otherwise everyone just does everything you say and they also wait on you now what i
find and what i told the team is that you're flat as a power dynamic you're all on the same page
you're all kind of relatively equal owners and it'll be interesting to see how it evolves from that
given that there's actually a business and again i think this is something that you probably had a
challenge within other founders here whereby they put more on your plate because you are so visionary
and because you're like up there in the future and they're always waiting on you so you was like
well my schedule is completely packed my schedule now is actually quite free which is also quite
nice i've had a chance to speak with you every day for the last few days so that's been a pleasure
to have extra time on your schedule you know so so we do have a world of uh visionary founder led
CEO companies right so you've got musk and you've got bezos historically and you had steve jobs and
you have and and that's both powerful and dangerous the the power is the ability for that
because we don't ever have a company that is pre-existing a new CEO comes in and has the same
both hootspa and and also the power of their of their vision
um
the danger there your concern you're you're saying is not not allowing your team to step
up with their own vision or being over overly indexed on your on your vision yeah i think that
that can be the issue and that's why i wanted stability to again reach the point of spread
and revenue rate increase and other things before i do anything um and i felt again this
external pressure in that if nobody or there's very few people in the world actually thinking
properly about governance and spread and others and a very small window giving the pace of this
to make a difference in the dent i believed i had a reasonable approach to that but i couldn't
while remaining CEO of this company and again it's a pretty unique scenario because you've never
seen a sector move this fast that has such wide-reaching human implications and regressively
there's too few people i think with the right alignment and approach in this area i've been
very disappointed like usually what happens is you have power maximization equations and this
is what we're seeing from the industry consolidation how many people want to genuinely bring this
technology to kids in nigeria or to the global south or to help those leaders build their own
models you know and believe also in a positive some game that was actually my biggest surprise
from the discussions to lincoln valley almost entirely they all believe in uh flat or negative
some you know zero some or negative some things where there has to be a winner everyone's a winner
in this and again i was just very disappointed seeing that i've been asking for you for a while to
write and distribute your vision white paper because i've heard you describe it in detail
and it's brilliant and i still hope that the world will see it soon enough everybody you
want to take a break from our episode to tell you about an amazing company on a mission to
prevent and reverse chronic disease by decoding your biology the company is called viome and
they offer cutting-edge tests and personalized products that help you optimize your gut microbiome
your oral microbiome and your cellular health as you probably know your microbiome is a collection
of trillions of microbes that live in your gut and mouth and these microbiomes influence everything
your digestion immunity mood weight and many other aspects of your health but not all microbes are
good for you some can cause inflammation toxins and actually lead to chronic diseases like diabetes
heart disease obesity and even cancer viome uses advanced mRNA technology and ai to analyze your
microbes and your cells and give you personalized nutrition recommendations and products designed
specifically for your genetics specifically for your biology you can choose from different tests
depending on your goals and needs ranging from improving your gut health your oral health cellular
function or all of them i've been using viome for the past three years i can tell you that it has
made a huge difference in my health and because the data they collect and the ai engine they've built
it gets better every single day i love getting health scores and seeing how my diet and lifestyle
affects my microbiome and my cells and i love getting precision supplements and probiotics tailored
for my specific needs if you want to join me on this journey of discovery and improve your health
from the inside out viome has a special offer for you for a limited time you can get up to 40% off
any viome test using the code moonshots just go to viome.com backslash moonshots and order your
test today trust me you won't regret it all right let's go back to our episode before we jump into
into health and education let's talk about governance a second because we've seen governance
complicate this what is the right governance structure for this super powerful technology
we have representation of democracy that i think can be improved by this like i don't think
democracy survives this technology it's current for it will either improve or it'll end
i don't see anything else like yesterday though what does end what does end mean here a benign
dictatorship a driven by an ai overlord yeah like yesterday there was a announcement of an app called
Hume which had emotionally intelligent speech and they can understand your emotions and talk with
you know i have to discuss this yes you know where that's going right it's very powerful
it's incredibly powerful and governments have a tendency i mean if there's no government but
say it say it here it's important for you to state what what it means because we've discussed it but
help people here be ready for this and democracy is all about representation and you see the
questions of deep fakes and things speech is one of the most impactful elements there but now you
can't believe anything you see here everything so one path that we have is a 1984 on steroids
panoptica you know where life is gamified and you listen to whatever the government says and
they're incredibly convincing and you're happy and you've always been happy and you've always been
at war with eurasia you know propaganda on steroids the other path that you have is things like
citizen assemblies consults of democracy the ability to take right now you can take any of
the bills in congress and completely deconstruct them and find what the motivations are you know
you can check laws against the constitution in a second seconds this is an incredibly powerful
empowering technology from a democratic perspective so i see two routes unfortunately because i think
that once the right thing goes it goes really fast centralized government control increasing
because the government want to protect themselves as an organization and you know every party says
the other party's crap we've seen the increasing polarization in america already
and you know fundamentally come on you can do better than those two leaders that are currently
competing i'm saying this is clear our system is sclerotic across this like democracy is the worst
of all systems except for everyone else you can have a better democracy where it's actually
representative and empowers the people or we will have the end of democracy where it is in 1984
panopticon in my opinion because the momentum will go then of course you'll start using this
technology you're already seeing it being used but not at scale and not intelligently yet which is
scary i think we finally have the technology for a direct democracy versus a representative
democracy right where i can have my my desires directly represented on any specific law or
but i think the point you've made before is that speech if you look back to everybody from
hitler to some of the most persuasive politicians is is a powerful tool and ai can become the most
persuasive speaker out there it can take anyone's speech to make it far more persuasive like i think
my voice is a bit whiny i can remove the wine you know i can go in a very polished british accent
and other things like that right you know must fight them on the hills and the harriers and
whatever public speaking needs to be different someone took hitler's speeches and put them
through an ai and took them into english because when we're not in the german context and we listen
to them it sounds like he's shouting like well that's crazy thing you hear him in english it is
very different in his own voice just like someone took javier mele's one in the united nations
and put him into english again he sounds a bit sharp how shouty but then he sounds very reasonable
when it's in english and you can take the phenomes of obama's best speech and a bit of trumpinism
and a bit of churchill and you'll have full modulation wave control over all of this people
are already using this technology that everyone should have a passcode with their loved ones because
people are getting calls from their mother saying help i'm in an emergency and you just
send money right now and you cannot tell it and it pulls at the emotional strengths and if you
look at something like us radio and you know one side of the political divide is taken over imagine
if you're hearing optimized speech every single day that will have a huge impact and then they
control the visuals and they control the other things we're not set up for defenses yeah if it's
optimized speech for you specifically for you right for the kids you have the age group they
have where you live your historical background and so forth and end of one persuasive speech
coming at you the brain is not set up for defenses we're not and you know we take this as an example
of the youtube algorithm like youtube as an organization is not an evil organization but
it's an organization optimized for engagement which optimized for more extreme content so this
is a dark place in youtube which is an optimized for ices the ices video spread viral i don't know
sometimes viral is good sometimes viral is bad that one was bad because it was extreme and they
didn't understand why and if you look at it our two of our largest germ to bear companies are google
and meta and their business is advertising their business manipulation and they are both a moral
companies because why would you expect a company to have morality our governments are also a moral
and again you can view these things as slow dumb ai so you can see the way they will optimize
unless we do something about it and they will have full control like again you put on your vision
pro headset with your spatial audio that is full sensory control not full but you know what i mean
full immersion full immersion full immersion and so we have to be aware of this and there's
obviously other tools that can be used like in the wake of the ab spring you know governments
targeted everyone else in social media we can do that on a high-end hyper-personalized basis
like we need to set some defaults and standards here to protect democracy but again why democracy
we're not really trying to protect democracy you know again people have different definition
that what we're trying to protect is individual liberty freedom and agency education should be
about enhancing the education of every child it's not you know healthcare is sick care our government
should uplift us but how many people believe our governments do that rather than put us down
because they couldn't encapsulate and cater to the brilliance of each individual
because they didn't have the tools until now so that's why i said which way one man
yes which way an agency or massive control these are the two ways do we control the technology
or do these organizations control the technology that controls us you know when we were on the stage
at at the abundant summit we talked about a future of digital superintelligence right
and a future in which we've got AI a billion times more capable than a human which looking at it
just from a ratio of neurons is the ratio of a hamster to a human um yep uh do you believe
that someday we could have a a benign superintelligence that is supporting humanity
yes and i believe that it should be a collective intelligence
that is made up of amplified human intelligence is amplifying all of us pilots that contain our
collective knowledge and culture and the best of us and datasets that are built from helping and
augmenting us versus a collected intelligence and agi that is top down and designed to effectively
control us again if you look at open ai statements on the rote agi they say this technology will end
democracy and capitalism and maybe kill us all i don't like that i remember i remember seeing that
you you you texted me you said read this does this sound the same as it does to me yeah so what
i'd prefer instead is for this to be distributed like if you have datasets formations that are
built on enhancing the capability of the nation that reflect the local cultures and you push for
data transparency on models which i believe we must have you know especially language models
then you're more likely to have a positive thing and again the human collective can achieve anything
from splitting the atom to go into space if we put our minds to it but we have lacked in
coordination mechanisms they've not been good enough so if you create the human colossus and
every single person has an ai that's just looking at them to enhance their potential and coordination
ai's that is a far more positive view of the future and that is the agi that is a general
intelligence that's the hive mind general intelligence not a bog style hive mind but one
that's really thinking again every child should achieve their potential versus this embodied
concept of an agi that's a very western concept and you see that as well like you know we look at
the japanese concept of a robot the robot is your equal and your helper you look at the western
concept of the robot it's terminator and spinet and all of that and again i think this is again
where cultural norms become very interesting and what do we want to build we want to build ai god
or do we want to build that ai helper that helps us and we help it you know
um those listening now i mean you can see umad's brilliance and why i'm so enamored with the way
you think about this because it's there are very few individuals who are looking at this from
an objective function of what's best for humanity what's best for every nation state
out there let's talk about your going forward future are you going to build something in the
in the decentralized side of of ai the democratized size of ai is there a company there or a fund in
your future for that yeah so uh you're not doing the white paper finally getting there with a bit
of help from ai uh i can't i can't i can't wait to uh to help uh broadcast that white paper
yeah but look i think the basic thing is this what i want to do is set up a ai champion in every
nation with the brightest people of each nation working with the organization of each nation
to help guide them through this next period because there will be massive job displacement
from the graduates going massive uplifts and productivity from the technology being implemented
and again that organization can help govern and create these data sets and these models that
are so important and every nation should have that but then i also believe that every sector
should have a genitive ai first infrastructure company that builds this and helps the healthcare
companies finance companies and others through that and to coordinate all of that you need to have
a web three type protocol what is the protocol for intelligence so what what is a web what is a
web three type protocol to find that for folks listening again people talk about web three it's
not about the tokens or the meme coins or anything like that what about three protocols is that
everyone should have like ai's first of all if i'm going to have bank accounts
they're going to need some way to pay each other or exchange value and again web three is a lot
of work in that there needs to be some sort of identity attribution and other format because
you'll have this mass influx of information and so again web three concepts are very useful there
there needs to be an identity concept because you'll have real and digital people web three concepts
are very useful there so data access station all these other things verifiability so when i look at
it if you've got sectorally my plan is to launch a company for every major sector and we can talk
about health and education and bring the smartest people in the world to solve that challenge of
the infrastructure for the future every nation but you need to have some sort of coordinating
protocol for all of that that becomes a standard and that's the substrate for this amplified human
collective intelligence and and is that where you want to play and focus your energy next
yeah it's setting up these organizations and bringing the brightest smartest people that
really want to make a difference there because there's massive network effects in doing this
but again i just need to be the founder and architect i don't want to run the day to day of
any of these things um and then because the the most scarce talent that there's three types of
capital as i view it there's financial capital human capital and political capital and in order
to effect change in the world you actually need all three but the financial capital actually comes
with the people capital and the political capital and the smartest people in the world in every sector
from health care to education to finance to agriculture almost all believe that gentry
is the biggest thing they've ever seen in the last year everyone's asking you all the smartest
people peter what's next right and you know many of the smartest people in the world so i want to
create organizations that they can come the chefs and the cooks the thinkers and the doers and think
what is the future of finance that's the future of education and then the national champions that
should be owned by the people of each country become the distribution for the amazing infrastructure
they built and there's a vice a nice kind of vice versa but then again you need the coordination
function so i'm trying to bring together people in each of these and you know there'll be public
calls and things like that to build that infrastructure the future because as mentioned
ai isn't infrastructure but it should be i mean maybe it's the rocket ship of the mind right
i love that i love that analogy my friend it is the most important infrastructure
that humanity will have going forward across everything it does and i look forward to helping
you build it exciting right like again i think one of the things i got i got lots of messages
that like i'm so sorry for your loss it was like my dog had died after i left to see you
i was like what is that you know they're like i was nice it's nice that people care right but i'm
generally excited about what's next like you know again it was like staring into the abyss
and chewing gloss every single day and that's not what i'm best at or i could have the most impact
but i wanted to be a point whereby if i can accelerate this over the next period i don't
have to make an impact i should not have any power on this whereas again you see everyone
else trying to get more and more power i want to make sure it's set up properly but i want to give
it all away because power is obligation it's dragging and again it should not be invested in
any one individual we shouldn't have to rely on anyone being nice or good or for this technology
i was talking to uh michael sailor during the abundant summit uh that evening and you know
talking about the fact that because satoshi uh when he set it up uh did not retain any power
and did not trade on the founding blocks and so forth that that's the reason it's been able to
succeed because there wasn't that centralized power and you know bitcoin had been he said bitcoin
betrayed many times before but because it didn't have that uh initial anonymity and and and the
dissolution of founding power that that's the reason it didn't succeed yeah i mean again i think
you need to have it accelerate and you see this with movements right the movement starts but then
it goes once you've got the dna and the story there right you know you see the profits you see the
leaders you see the others but then it's about setting the framework correctly and reframing the
concept this technology is not going to look stability is a company that started two years
ago above a chicken shop in london right you know my first 20 employees i went to the job
center and i said bring me people that have overcome adversity and i will train them young
graduates and six of them are still at stability you know um like because it was a program and
they're doing things from cyber security to run supercomputers we only had like 16 17 phd's
yet we built the state-of-the-art models in every modality we built mind-reading models
like mind's eye you know i remember that contributed to all these things yet you're
told it's impossible to compete we have shown it's not impossible to compete that's a reframing
the reframing is data versus models it's you don't need giant supercomputers for everyone
you just need to have a trusted entity to build it right yeah you know and so i hope to kind of
convey this and then figure out this organizational structure that can proliferate so i can take the
holiday so before we go further let's talk about one area of your next chapter in life that
we both have as a passion which is the use of generative ai in health it's an area that you've
given a huge amount of thought to and i think you're excited about can you share what your vision is
there yeah so i got into ai 13 years ago gosh i was a programmer before for 23 years building
large-scale systems as a hedge fund manager and other things well my son was diagnosed with autism
and then i built an nlp team to analyze all the clinical literature and then looked at
biomolecular pathway analysis of neurotransmitters gavra and glutamate in the brain to repurpose
drugs for him and he went to macy's school which is great n equals one and then i was one of i was
lead architect from the one the covet ai project so the united nations for stanford and others
and then because i didn't get the technology i was like well we've got to build it ourselves
but what is health you know again i think we have this discussion a lot health care is sick care
we don't have all the information that we should have at our fingertips health assumes
ergodicity a thousand tosses of the coin the same as the coin tossed a thousand times but we are
all individual and across the world there are amazing data sets that could be better because
when you write down a clinical trial or your own kind of experiences you lose so much information
at the same time you don't have all the information on cancer or autism multiple
sclerosis at your fingertips in the comprehensive authoritative and upstate way so when i look at
the health operating system we're going to build a gpt for open for cancer and it's going to mean
that nobody is alone again on that journey and uses that agency because they know comprehensive
authoritative upstate all the knowledge but ai models today already outperform human doctors
and empathy they're not going to be a learn on that anymore can i just double click on what you
just said because it's really important i've had so many people because of my role as chairman of
fountain life who reach out and say i just got diagnosed with this cancer or my brother or my
sister or my wife and and there is they're left with this decimating news and they're left googling
um but a model that's able to have the most cutting-edge information and then incorporate
all their medical data and give them advice in empathic fashion how far is that see a couple
of years if we focus maybe even like next year and that's amazing because all of these topics
that again we will have diagnosis that it's superior we will have research augmentation
because again even researchers don't have all that knowledge of their fingertips and again
this is public infrastructure in a public good you know from primary care all the way through so
that what is the open infrastructure in the future where this technology can come again
to your own data as well you have things like melody and other things around homomorphic
encryption federated learning that they were trying to figure out how to preserve privacy
we can run a language model on a smart phone right now that can analyze all your data and then
just feedback stuff to a global collective but people are people so when I look at health care
I see amazing data sets that we can activate by taking the models to the data an infrastructure
that we can build like we had checks agent with stanford the top x-ray radio radiology model
to build good standard things across the entire gamut of health care so we actually get to health
care versus sick care so we can make it so that everyone is empowered to make the best decisions
either as experts or individuals and make it so nobody is alone again as well as increasingly
data quality that will then feed better models that will then save lives save suffering and again
increase our potential like you've got a long job wrong stupid behind you right why don't you have
all the latest knowledge of longevity at your fingertips at a gpt4 level right now that will
happen over the next year we will launch stable health or whatever decide to call it and there
will be the smartest people in each of these areas working on that so again you're never like
doesn't matter if you're with a hundred billion dollars and your kid has autism ast there's no cure
there's no treatment there's nothing doesn't matter how rich you are yet we're just a little bit of
effort right now we can build it as an open infrastructure for the five percent of people
in the world that know someone with autism the fifty percent of people in the world that receive
a cancer diagnosis of them or someone they love and they feel that loss of agency so we're going to
return agency to humanity that way and again it needs to be an open infrastructure that they can
then access private datasets and compensate them appropriately so everyone is incentivized we get
that fast yeah and and that's a beautiful vision it is again infrastructure it and one of the things
that's so beautiful about it is guess what all eight billion people we're all human we're all
running the same software and the the the breakthroughs and the knowledge accumulated in
you know in Kazakhstan is going to be as useful in Kansas yeah but this is the thing operating
system this is the biggest upgrade to the human operating system we can imagine because we're
going from analog to digital text is black and white whereas this these models only understand
context you know daniel kahneman just passed you know amazing kind of guy but you know he did
have this concept of type one type two thinking and so we had one which is these big data things that
can only extrapolate but now we have these models that understand context and so we have the missing
part of the brain and that will allow us to extrapolate allows to have more rainbows you
know have the context of each individual push intelligence to the edge and that's why again
there is this imperative to do this now because there's a window on the freedom agency democracy
side but the other imperative is no one should have to suffer as they're suffering now
amazing and how much does actually it doesn't need that much which is the really amazing stuff
this the total amount spent in janitor bail i think i said at the conference is less than
the total amount spent on the los angeles san francisco railway
which hasn't even started yet and and in building stable health again if that's what it's called i
mean the amount of capital required to build that is de minimis compared to what's spent on a single
human trial of any any drug yeah it is but then you know you build it and you get to that 8020
incredibly quickly that will change hundreds of millions of lives and that will attract the smartest
people in each of these areas thinking about what is the open infrastructure of multiple
sclerosis of longevity of cancer and more but then you can amp that because the value is so so huge
and you i hope to build a trusted organization as part of this whole human operating system upgrade
you know that's what i want to build i want to build human os well at least catalyze it again i
don't want to run or control or own anything i want to figure out how to give back that control
because who should decide what cancer knowledge goes in there who should decide what education etc
let's talk about the second half of your of your vision which is how we originally met
when you were one of the winners of the global learning x prize that ilan and tony
robbins had had co-funded your your vision around education to speak to us about that
yeah you know so we're deploying it kind of the winners kind of separate but
every child right my entire operating system is like if you think about things in terms of
the rights of child and today they have no agency and so we must respect their rights climate
everything becomes a lot simpler now that we have language models on a laptop like i said you can go
to lmstudio.ai download stable lm and it will run on your macbook faster than you can read
uh it's crazy we can have a gpt 4 level ai from us or someone else on a smartphone or a tablet by
next year one laptop per child was too early you know now we have this transformative technology
you have an ai that teaches the child learns from a child are you visual auditory dyslexic
that's the best data in the world for a national model but also to teach these models how to be
optimistic how to this really is this really is uh the young ladies illustrator primer this
really is neil stevensson's vision in that regard yeah but mel shouldn't have had to find the primer
she should have had it from day one as a human right as a human right yes our school's education
system our child care mixed with the social status game mix with petri dish you know they teach our
kids not to have agency yes whereas they should be telling the kids yeah yeah they should be teaching
this is a relic of the industrial age where everyone had to be counted and you can't measure
what you can't manage so you manage the creativity and belief out of people everyone in the world can
do anything why because even if you don't have that talent you can convince someone else who
does have that talent but they don't believe it so they can't do it so what happens if we have an
entire nation of children that have this helper that brings the right information the right time
and tells them they can always believe that supports them entire world what can't you do
you know then they have all of the cancer knowledge of their fingertips and all of the
engineering knowledge of their fingertips and it's a constantly learning adaptive and improving system
again right now almost the entire agi and ai debate is about these machine gods trained on giant
supercomputers that bestow their beneficence down or may kill us or whatever what about that human
operating system upgrades that is a decentralized intelligence where that kid in mongolia or malawi
or wherever can make a real difference to humanity some of the contributors to our open code basis for
our models are 15 years old and they just taught themselves and just happen to be their wizards
you don't know in this new age right and again they should contribute to the whole because
once something goes into this model of the system and again it needs the verification and other
things that can be dynamic they can proliferate to everyone using that system do you think that
once this capability is built it will run into blocks in different nations or do you imagine
that this will become a again a human right and not all need I mean listen there's no greater gift
and no greater asset you can give to a nation's populist than intelligence and education but I'm
not sure every national leader wants to see that and that's why I think again there is a gap here
there is a year maybe where you can go to any national leader and say I'll bring this technology
to your people and I will empower the smart stupid people I want to be earned by the people
and what option do they have this is positive for them what happens is that a lot of the
corruption in the world is because of local maxima you know actually it's weird because
unpredictable corruption is the worst predictable corruption is a bit like tax you know there's
a good boast book by Frosso a job about Harvard about this and then you have taxation kicking
at 14 percent if you can show them something bigger and this is clearly big they will embrace
this technology and set new norms and if you correct the same across all these countries
with talented individuals in each of those groups and talented individuals in each of those sectors
with a shared mission even though they're separate organizations that's how you set amazing
standards that's how you build a network effect and if you tie them all together with a intelligent
protocol and you want to talk about tokens or speculation or ramps or anything like that
but taking the best of thinking around coordination that can work that can break this open you know
but it's not going to be everywhere and also when you look at the current debate the current
debate is for example we can't let China have this technology and you're like what about the kids in
China right well you know it's dangerous they can have a giant so under what circumstance would China
ever have this technology never you know Pakistan when should they have the tech never that's really
what they're kind of saying it's also self-defeating because China has a hundred million people they
can use to create data sets and two exaplops of computers let's put that to the side again it's
a very western oriented debate whereas actually if you go to these countries and you talk to the
leaders and the family officers that have power and the people they will leapfrog in the global
south to an intelligence augmentation like they let frog to mobile they want to embrace this technology
and again you can set norms now versus what's going to happen is you know they will get a
centralized solution they'll adopt that instead if you don't right now for hundreds of millions
billions of people that's why i think again it's a crossroads um is there anybody else working
towards this solution that you know of no in the in the large ai town no certainly no one
credibility and again that's why i had to build these models you know and i had to kind of do
this everyone's working on tiny parts of this but there is expecting emergence build it and
somehow it will spread and again this is why i found it fascinating the web3 community
there are good people in there and i hope to be able to unite them just like hope to unite the
people in health and others and peter you've seen people working on tiny parts of this
but this isn't a manhattan project where we're facing an enemy
unless the enemy is ourselves you know but this does require this big global coordinated push and
that's why i've tried to design this system that i believe will work because all about the talent
and is multiplicative is the race against uh
overly powerful centralized ai systems that achieve some version of agi is that what we're racing against
yeah again we're racing against ourselves like um humans can scale through stories you have
organizations you know come and join a band and come and go to oxford come and do this but then
when we scaled through text text was a lossy information format and there's this poem by
ginsburg how about this carthaginian demon of disorder mollock that comes in
mollock comes in through the data loss our organizations are slow dummy eyes
but now what's happening is they're configuring to achieve the thing of getting more and more power
again corporations are technically a people under law but they're not fully formed people
they eat our hopes and dreams so i believe the competition here is against those organizations
consolidating too much power and creating norms that almost impossible to break so we're almost
competing against ourselves and again the question is this do you believe it amplified human
intelligence or do you believe in artificial general intelligence do you believe in collective
intelligence or do you believe in collected intelligence who decides is this infrastructure
or is this a product like so it's not like a Manhattan project against you know the soviets
or anything like that but it is is require us all to come together or at least the smartest people
in each of these areas from coordination to government systems to health care to education
with a blank slate of how do we upgrade the human operating system the time is now
it's all lost chance to do it and i and i i love you for it because i think you're you're right
you were there when elan beamed in on xx video over starlink and from his airplane which is
which was a fun moment and we were talking about the rate of growth and his his statement
because you know recurrence why was there talking about his still his prediction of
agi by 2029 and ray and written elan saying we'll have agi whatever that means by next year and
and the intelligence of the entire human race by 2029 so i am i am curious what just to close
out what you think about that those timelines and that potential for a super intelligent
agi system that is centralized because that's the people who are building that level of power
are building centralized systems they're building centralized single systems that again take our
collective intelligence like all of youtube in the case of open ai clearly and other things
and they package it up sell it back to us but they don't care you know these organizations
are trying to build a system that will take away our freedom liberty and potentially kill us all
let's be kind of fair about that and sell it to us on an incremental basis the selling to us
is a complete cannot they don't care about the revenue of this again let's kind of call a spade
a spade they're telling you that they're building something that could kill you and something that
could remove all our freedom and liberty and they're saying it's a good thing you should back
them because it's cool it's not it's actually shameful if you think about it and we should
not stand for it anymore and again this is another reason i want to step aside to see you
because you can't say things like that i don't cancel until i can rally so many times but realistically
it's ridiculous and it should not be stood for but they're going to do it anyway because they have
the political power people are scared of them so there has to be an alternative and the alternative
has to be distributed intelligence when i resigned i said you can't beat centralized intelligence
decentralized intelligence you're not going to beat it with this stability the least of great
organization it's going to do well the only way that you can beat it to create the standard that
represents humanity is decentralized intelligence it's collective intelligence and the data sets
and norms from that will be ones that help children that helps people suffering that reflect our
moral upstanding and the best of us and gathers the best of us to do it because if you work in
healthcare if you work in education if you work in finance if you work in any of these things there's
no organization for you to come and join or partner with on this there's no kind of centralized mission
i have looked i've wanted to help other people i didn't want to do this to myself and i don't want
it to be about being very very quickly and so i'm kind of getting it out there now i hope that i can
capitalize something that then people will take forward and time is now for that because agi when
it comes if it comes again there's various definitions of this why on earth do you need any
knowledge workers anything that can be done via a laptop doesn't need humans and so you have concepts
of ubi here you have concept like when agi comes you don't need money money is a common story is a
common good we hear total post capitalist society and i think the example i think you said was a
star trek versus man max you know i'm like star trek versus star wars i think there's a
and so you know the sith lords and all of that um but again if you kind of look at this i don't
think we need money like it's cross contextual like bartering with our ai systems representing us
or it's you don't need money because you're told what to do again our governments the definition
of a government is the entity with the monopoly on political violence and an agi can overtake any
government that they can then control the people because again listen to it whispering look at the
kind of human thing so we have this opportunity to set norms right now the way that the big labs
are going to agi is likely to kill us all elon and i signed that six month pause letter because even
though people like emma do an acceleration as you put all this open source aia you have to think
about the other side and who's involved in that discussion and again if we build an agi as a
centralized thing is windows or linux safer as infrastructure our entire internet infrastructure
is built on open open can be challenged open can be augmented a monolith is like to be crazy and
the way that i put this is we all night both know so many geniuses you know side effect of genius
is insanity honestly we're not men geniuses are not mentally stable why would you expect an agi
to be so and you're putting all your ends in one basket versus creating a complex hierarchical system
that is a hive mind that's the intelligence that represents us all we should be working
towards building that and it's safer it's better it achieves all the benefits that people are talking
about and it's possible today do you think elon shares in this vision of a decentralized ai do
you think he would play in that area and do you think any of the national leaders that you've
been speaking to would support that kind of a vision as well um yeah i can't speak for elon
i'll speak to him and see what he thinks and then i'll get back to you know he always says what he
thinks um but you know he's immensely concerned he was one of the leaders in this area saying
originally why google you know now why in microsoft open ai like it can't be centralized but it's
difficult it's a difficult question how many people have a feasible solution or you've even
thought about this properly you and i both know just not many and that's very sad it should be
everyone thinking about this on the leader side all the leaders i've met are super happy you know
because they again leaders want power they want control and all of this but generally like they
want to see a bundles they're not happy with where their countries are and embracing this technology
they know they can leap ahead and you know they will still have a say in all of this it's not like
it's kicking them out or removing them there are still various kind of mechanisms there and ultimately
improving the health education and capability of your people is not a bad thing i mean like obviously
i haven't talked to the completely oppressive leaders you know maybe that'll be an interesting thing
but honestly i don't want to even be talking to leaders i want to create again a system
that the people of the country coming together with the franchise system
can then build this technology for the good of their people in the open and not be reliant on
anyone politically or any other thing like that so you don't need giant super computers for where
we're going recordination need a few giant super computers yeah what's your timeline for putting
out this white paper i'm working as hard as i can you know i've held i've held i've held you to this
a number of times i've said get the vision out there it's getting there we're about to go off
this call to a four-hour session to dictate all the various bits and pieces and again it was
impossible when i was a CEO of stability there was always another fire there's always another thing
i didn't have time to think you know and i hope people can take that white paper and make it better
i don't have all the answers i'm just trying to capitalize something man i think after i heard you
step down i wrote you a text saying congratulations yeah exactly talk to miserations time to time
to feel unleashed yeah yeah uh imad thank you my friend uh thank you for sharing uh where you are
what led up to this where you're going next and uh and really pulling the gloves off on discussing
the idea of centralized closed ai systems and their dangers uh and the importance of of the
vision that you've portrayed because i'm i'm fully supportive and fully believe that what you've laid
out um is probably one of the most seen visions of ai in the future that i've heard i hope other
people agree you know and they can take it forward other real heroes thank you thank you pal