What is up Wombos, it's hi, it's Wombo, just set up my new highest def web page camera
and we're going to have a great day watching Wombo.
Be sure to check out WombosX's twitter.x at X's www.twitter.therealwombo, it's all
a word and um Wombo's new twitch account at uh it's www and then www.twitch.t and v and
then slash um Wombo, it's um hi it's Wombo, anyway Wombo is going to play games and watch
things and stuff with you, there's a new some more Mr. Cody out today and since Wombo is
mad at Mr. Cody, Wombo thought we should watch it and make fun of Mr. Cody for being stinky
so let's just click on it.
On Wombo's new gaming laptop, there's Wombo Bot on Wombo's new phone, you can buy things
on your phone actually, if you check out Wombo's twitch, Wombo has a tutorial on how to buy
things on your phone, anyway we've clicked on Mr. Stinky Cody's new video, so let's
watch that.
Greetings Choombas, time to chip into some more news with a Z because it's future times
and we have robots now, no really actual robots, some better than others, anyway here's some
news we don't actually get those robots yet, probably not until the army gets bored doing
wars with them, but until then we do get bots, countless, countless just too many bots AI
to be exact, good AI, not really, evil AI, no wouldn't say that either, I mean Hal had
to be like functional in order to kill everybody, what we have is more like that last 10 seconds
of Hal's life where he slowly loses his mind and just sings a song nobody wanted to hear
and this is all to say that social media sure seems to be patched to the gills with scams,
bots and mediocre AI art, AI recipes and movie trivia, aggregated reddit posts set to Minecraft
parkour, deep fried videos of long dead cats, those countless if only there was a page that
posted blank accounts, robots describing scenes from movies for some reason like as if they're
just things that happened in life, we've discussed how the internet is basically just a handful
of social media sites now and so it's a little concerning that these sites have been slowly
flooded with a bunch of bots and scams and clickbaity accounts, not just on Twitter,
but yes very much on Twitter, but also Instagram and TikTok and I haven't really checked Facebook
in a while but I assume there too and this seems by design and while that sucks for most
people, at least we can rest easy knowing that we are in the golden years for scammy online
freaks and the sometimes billionaire dupes who love them.
Huzzah!
The Growing Internet Scam Economy
So obviously the flim flam profession is a proud and ancient tradition dating to the dawn of
civilization, one of the oldest complaints to the manager was a clay tablet from the 18th
century BC written by a buyer claiming he was scammed, skipped to the early internet and we
had phishing emails that Nigerian Prince scam, boner pills, most of those pills being ineffective,
now we've got AI and complex bot networks and crypto and maybe even little pick pocket
drones, you could give them a boo hats, oh that would be adorable for a while, but while the
tools are advanced the scammy methods are basically the same, also for all you semantics
perverts jerking your words in the way back I'm going to be using the term scam very loosely
when talking about this because I think one of the unique things about the internet is that it
more easily blurs the line between engagement bait, random bots and people straight up trying to
steal your money, not all scams are created equal but they all work on the same fundamental level
in that they are all trying to get your attention using tactics that are either dishonest or
manipulative, for example have you ever been scrolling through Instagram or TikTok when a
video of an absolute mega Karen pops up, you know some lady who is acting in an unbelievably
entitled and enraging way?
Wow, what a freak, absolutely wild that a human being would actually act like that,
it's almost too weird to be true, you can't make this stuff up, oh wait yeah I guess you can,
they literally posted set photos like they were teasing the next Marvel film, see there are of
course plenty of videos of real assholes on social media, which is exactly why these staged videos
are able to thrive, in fact there's an entire fake Karen economy on the internet that makes
real money doing this thanks to how engagement is rewarded, I'd argue a lot of them are obvious,
often the sound or lighting quality is suspiciously good or the dialogue is very forced or robotic
or sometimes you can even find the same people showing up in multiple videos, they aren't hiding
it because they don't need to and they can always claim later that it's satire or a parody,
it's a prank or something even though it's clearly not, so this is one end of the scam
spectrum where what they are doing is clearly dishonest, but I also want to talk about the
other more interesting end of the spectrum, this is the stuff that's engagement bait but I'd argue
less harmful and more just weird, like I don't want to shame anyone or say this is bad, I'm just
concerned
did I just die? am I dead? what's
it okay so you might have seen this going around apparently on tiktok people are pretending to
be an npc or doll or robot or something and basically what people do is pay them in tokens
to get a selected and scripted response and boy there are just so so many
so you either just found that deeply unnerving or maybe you came I don't know you and again
I don't really want to shame this because while this looks and seems weird at first these fake
npc accounts are actually nothing new this has been around for a long time we just know them as
mimes this is just a form of physical art and before tiktok we had streets and on them street
performers doing whatever they could to get your attention one of the most enduring street
performance acts is the living statue aka someone dressed and painted as a statue that stands
remarkably still sometimes for hours the appeal is their commitment to acting as artifice and
they interact with you when you pay them just like the tiktok npcs it's basically the same right
the ability to maintain a performance for so long to interact with the audience where they get to
feel like they're causing the performer to do something and keeping up the act so persistently
and so if you find these npcs haunting I'm guessing it's the same reason you find this haunting
or arousing I'm sure this is all somebody's fetish and those npcs probably tend to be young
women for a reason but my point is that tiktok and instagram essentially function the same way
as the vegas sidewalk it's a bunch of people carnival barking for your attention and ultimately
your money some are doing it honestly and some are doing it dishonestly in fact some of these
people are also trying to lead you to a second location you know how they say you should always
follow a stranger to a second location after all what's the worst that could happen you don't
want to be scared of the unknown do you do we have a clip of the unknown
yeah we have a clip of the unknown boy remember the wonka experience my goodness we were so young
and hopeful then this child entrapment scam used the power of ai to lead dozens of glass cow children
to their deaths of their childlike wonder they were fine the entire scheme from concept to
advertisement to execution seemed to have been made with something similar to chat gpt but in
terms of actual organization the ai fell short of the final product which to be polite failed
to capture the wonder of william wonka's factory from the depressed oompa loompa running the meth
lab to the baron halls to the confused children staring deep into the unknown classic wonka
villain and what's worse these children weren't even given much candy to endure this children will
forgive most things if you have candy ask any murderer ultimately i'm honestly not sure where
the wonka experience falls on the scam spectrum it's like several scams nested in each other
that's now blooming into a meta scam because everyone made fun of it and so now a bunch of
corporations want to get in on the fun and as a result exploit and kill the brief joy we all had
with it can't wait for the willy wonka experience movie in 2025 long after the meme is dead but i
wanted to bring it up because it's a great example of new technology being made to augment old
scams after all you can find countless lists of scam festivals or doomed events similar to this
but this is no doubt the first of many to use ai for false advertising purposes yeah get ready
for that to be a thing and not just from small time scammers that civil war film used ai art for
their posters portraying scenes that are certainly not in the film or anywhere like if you've been
to chicago you'd notice those buildings are in the wrong place nor does los angeles have
giant swans i guess that's supposed to be an echo park swan boat oh look that car has three doors on
one side neat can't wait for this to be the future of advertising okay wombo is just gonna pause the
video right here to say that um mr. kody is wrong here because wombo once saw a car with three doors
on one side when he was a trader joes but then um turned out it only had two doors and wombo was
mistaken but three doors can't exist on cars it's possible so that ai art is actually very accurate
and good wombo has also been making ai art and has gotten very good at the prompts like wombo made
this one with the prompt draw um mr. kody and he smells like dad's milk but wombo is also there
eating soup but also make it twice with only five fingers good art best art museum quality
flesh everywhere skin blood veins fish guts muscular babies six eyes 10 fingers so many
fingers all of the fingers you can fit anime girl for more prompts you can go to my prompt
base page where wombo is selling many prompts that are good and make good things because now that
wombo isn't that mr. kody's wombo needs your support because it's hard to find food because
there were more animal shelters and playgrounds by mr. kody's house okay back to the video and while
ai ads are problematic it's probably the least dangerous place to use it right but it should
be noted that this trend is currently extending beyond ads most shockingly to academic journals
even more shockingly academic journals about giant mutant rat dicks published in the academic
journal frontiers in cell and developmental biology there is a paper called retracted cellular
functions of spermatogonal stem cells in relation to jack stat signaling pathway of course originally
it wasn't called retracted it got called that after it was retracted for the obviously fake
ai rat dick as well as other ai diagrams created by mid journey which somehow made its way past
six reviewers i don't know seems accurate to me sometimes you gotta distill some rats test
them cells oh but there's more other scientific papers are getting published with ai generated
text and while some of these can be hard to detect thankfully even smart people are too dumb to delete
some obvious signs for example this paper still apparently published that actually begins with
certainly here is a possible introduction for your topic very funny very obvious but for every
obvious fake ai paper i'm sure there are tons that go by unnoticed the ability to scam through ai or
social media is just so streamlined and easy that anyone can do it and reach a huge audience
any scam from engagement bait to freaking academic fraud can be done by anyone you don't even need
to know photoshop now and ultimately the result for both is the same hollowness this is all hollow
content from a fake diagram of a rat dick to a fake video of actors pretending to argue it all
stems from a lack of actual substance in exchange for an easy grift it reminds me of reality tv a
little bit early reality tv no doubt tried to capture real things and people and over time they
realized that audiences can't tell the difference between that and actors similarly i feel like
internet content has realized over time that it doesn't have to be authentic or funny or even
well made it just has to trigger people's attention and so over time scams have replaced
really everything on the internet right now everything is a scam google for example is a scam
a recent study has confirmed what we all know that google results have gotten worse because quote
a torrent of low quality content especially for product search keeps drowning any kind of useful
information in search results for example just google the word car in theory that should take
you to a definition of the word perhaps the history of cars a wikipedia article a picture of a car
but what you get instead is a top result for the california association of realtors and then a bunch
of other links trying to sell you cars or car related stuff like a car seat or legos for some
reason i don't know it's probably different for everyone depending on where they live and what
their past search history is because what you're ultimately googling is which websites were able
to scam their way into that search engine optimization game and so a basic search engine is no different
than that vegas street again long way from when google was supposed to be a pure search engine
with no ads according to this completely unconfirmed photo from reddit so i don't know maybe that's a
lie maybe everything's a lie maybe i don't exist i certainly don't feel real but then again i did
just smoke a bag of salvia so oh i just lived a life and speaking of reality after the break
we're going to talk more about things that don't exist such as bots and the bot ecosystem
and how it all got so bad and perhaps we'll check in with elan and his quest to finally get rid of
the bots on twitter thank goodness i'm so glad he did that and yes i understand the irony of talking
about stuff like a rage bait while doing a video it's angry about the internet that is also about
to cut to ads i don't care i feel nothing don't forget to use the promo code cody feels nothing
hey there my sleepy beepies i hope you're enjoying the video about how you can't trust anything on
the internet anymore that is exactly why we sought out ground news as our sponsor ground news is a
news aggregation website and app designed to help you spot the political biases of various news
so for example when i search for x i get okay i get nothing because x is impossible to search for
because it's a bad name but if i search for twitter i see this story with 142 articles about how elan
musk is being sued for firing former executives since ground news tells you who owns each publication
as well as their political lean i can see that all the right-leaning publications kept their
headlines very bare bones while left-leaning sites point out that this is one of a pile of lawsuits
or even give additional context like musk posting a cry laughing emoji as he is wants to do because
he's so not mad you see how this comes in really handy for not just analyzing the various ways
the publications cover a story but knowing who you can and can't trust for your news you can check
all this out over at ground dot news slash smn and boy this will be really useful this year you
know because uh that thing and all the other things and specifically ground news has an
elections page that includes a blind spot section showing you which stories are and aren't being
covered by who or whom or even who am so again check them out at ground dot news slash smn you
can subscribe for 40 off unlimited access through our link or by scanning this qr code this month
what they're doing is more important today than ever and i encourage you to check them out the
link is in the description that's it uh-oh it's katie everybody's talking about cool katie these
days even the president so i figured i'd use my coolness to talk about blue land and listen
whenever we do ads we're required to hit certain talking points but before i do that
i just want to go ahead and say that this is a product i actually really like and use i should
probably explain that blue land makes cleaning supplies designed to reduce our plastic use remember
when we did a whole episode about plastic waste we toss out like five billion plastic cleaning
bottles a year with blue land you use the same bottle and they send you cleaning tablets that you
just you plop in with water like this it smells so good don't eat it though but it smells so good
refills start at two dollars and 25 cents and you can of course set up a subscription or just buy
in bulk so they've got hand soap toilet cleaner laundry tabs all made with clean ingredients in a
really great variety of sense blue land is trusted in over one million homes including mine seriously
cool katie approves their packaging is really cute and it's reusable and well labeled look it says
toilet cleaner and there's the toilet cleaner i love the way they smell i've already said that
and whenever i clean my toilet i just want to eat my toilet after again i won't but i want to
but i won't because i'm too cool to eat toilets and blue land has a special offer for all of you
right now get 15 off your first order by going to blue land dot com slash more news you don't want
to miss this folks blue land dot com slash more news for 15 off that's blue land dot com slash
more news to get 15 off blue land blue land blue land i'm gonna go clean my toilets now i actually
am gonna go clean my toilets now i gotta do a little plank on mr kody hello hey mr kody it's
miss katie look i'm just reminding you to keep your front door open what miss katie sorry i just
woke up for my lunch naps you want me to keep my door open oh just for the night keep the doors
and the window open uh why so you can feel the air on your skin one last time
wombo likes doing voices and if you want mr kody's phone number you can subscribe to wombo
sub stack or dm wombo on linkedin let's keep watching mr kody's video well here we are back from ads
not a care in the world doing great american dream we were discussing or rather i was
discussing to the camera how modern technology and social media have made it easier than ever
to scam or grift people often just using old scams nfts for example nfts are essentially a modern
tulip mania tulip mania being a period in 1600s holland when dutch people got real horny for
tulip bulbs and started speculating on tulip bulbs it was considered a gamble given that you didn't
know exactly how fancy the beautiful tulip would turn out to be exactly like how people speculated
on the just absolutely hideous one-of-a-kind drawings of apes they're so ugly why would you
make them so ugly then tulip prices crashed and holland plunged into chaos exactly like mad max
but a lot more wooden clog sound effects or rather a minor inconvenience as the premise of tulip
mania was apparently overblown like me so sick of getting blown am i right no buddy agrees with me
nobody okay well i'm tired of it point is that nfts took something like a fad craze beanie babies
etc and just digitized it which in turn made it even easier to do which when you stand back
isn't a surprise the internet didn't change human behavior right it just made human behavior
more streamlined for better or worse at least that's assuming the internet is a collection of humans
which it seems to not be that thing that it is not seemingly if you can recall no not that kind
of recall i mean if you can remember elon musk purchased twitter under the promise that he would
combat the flood of bots it was his whole thing specifically that his new policies were quote
the only way to do this back in 2022 charging money for twitter blue was the only way to combat bots
then he decided that blue accounts would be the only accounts to show up in the main page and in
fact would have weighted influence on the algorithm and would receive priority in replies
because of bots then the bots were defeated right oh weird so in 2023 twitter began teasing
that they would charge everyone an annual subscription to use twitter in order to defeat the bots
huh i thought the only way to defeat them already happened with twitter blue
and then just this year elon confirmed that they will be charging new users money to tweet because
that is quote the only way to curb the relentless onslaught of bots oh very strange how the only
way to combat bots is also coincidentally requiring everyone to give elon musk money
after he purchased twitter on a dare he issued to himself and put the company into massive debt
and then fired everyone responsible for regulating things like bots and i don't know if you need to
be told this but it didn't work twitter blue didn't get rid of bots it actually made the bots worse
because the bots just started getting verified and gained better visibility over real users
while these are problems plaguing the entire internet twitter is uniquely completely in a
way that perfectly encapsulates the growing scam issue business genius elon musk has somehow
rebuilt twitter to seemingly accommodate scammers and only scammers while claiming to do the opposite
it's almost like he's a self-sabotaging idiot or something uh don't advertise you don't want
them to advertise no go f*** yourself aww you first little guy so x bots how bad is the problem
it's actually hard to know given that musk ended free access to its api the programming interface
of twitter that's right did you know that twitter is actually less accessible and even more into
censorship now it's almost as if musk did the complete opposite of all the stuff he said he
was going to fix and is actually just a liar so while he made a big deal over his open source
algorithm he ironically did not make the site more transparent apparently all he did was release
a bit of the source code for the for you algorithm but according to a former twitter employee the
model that drives the most important part of the algorithm has not been open sourced so the most
important part of the algorithm is still inscrutable basically it would be like releasing your grandma's
chocolate chip cookie recipe that just says mix dough add chocolate chips also there's a bunch of
random like nazi doodles scroll to the bottom so typical recipe from grandma despite this challenge
some researchers are paying the fees for api access or using other methods to investigate the
state of twitter check a cyber security firm examined traffic driven to its client's websites from
x during the 2024 super bowl and found that roughly 75 percent of it was bots this is compared to a
rate of under three percent fake traffic from sites like tiktok instagram and facebook this is a
huge jump even compared to twitter during last year which was only pumping out a little under
three percent fake traffic to websites three percent bots up to seventy f***ing five in just a year
and this isn't just for big events during the month of january 2024 check found a rate of around
30 fake traffic from x to its client's websites compared to a one to three percent rate from
instagram facebook and tiktok but hey the numbers are up and that's all that matters i guess the
official x business account bragged about the large traffic seen on x during the super bowl
never mind the possibility a huge percentage of that was fake personally i see no problem
falsely inflating traffic or view counts to convince websites to use your social media program
it's not like i or anyone i personally know has ever experienced any negative consequences to say
a social media platform shamelessly lying about the kind of traffic it can generate
and what kind of media to invest in okay wombo's gonna pause here because this is obviously a jab
against wombo and the time wombo built the platform and everyone accused wombo of lying about the
traffic on the platform that wombo built but wombo wasn't lying and the platform really was
covered in spiders and worms but they all scattered away before mr cody i invited him over to see the
platform in this bathroom but then the spiders and worms called away so mr cody is clearly still
just mad at wombo for that okay let's keep watching so at this point you may realize that twitter the
company is now a big scam right it's using bots to boost its traffic sometimes in depressing ways
so that advertisers will presumably want to come back then at the same time telling users
that the only way to defeat these bots is to pay them money you have to pay money to fix the problem
they caused and also pay money to get in on the scam you pay them and you supposedly get paid
through engagement which just encourages more and more scammy behavior but like most scams
it's unsustainable because it's not like we can't tell right it's not like we haven't seen the infamous
pussy in bio posts under every f***ing tweet which just so you know does not lead to any pussy okay
not one ounce of pussy to be had from that bio a um brave writer for intelligentser
clicked through these bio pussy links for purely journalistic purposes and found that they just
ping you around scam sites before sending you to some kind of imitation only fans it's exactly
what you expect from any of those doctors hate this one trick spam links you see at the bottom of
websites but now it's under all your tweets and make no mistake all of these bots are causing
twitter to bleed users real users it's using their actual humans are being lost here okay
as opposed to the bots inflating their numbers those are staying there more of the bots
fewer humans is the point this includes journalists being increasingly drowned out by fake news
and so what is left when you take away all the humans is a site completely occupied by scam
bots and content aggregators all talking to each other we haven't really talked about content
aggregators like culture crave historic vids vizagrad 24 censored men spectator index etc these
accounts are all verified offering them access to x premium which means they can in theory get
money for engagement and the best way to do that it seems is to post something stupid or obviously
wrong that a bunch of people will jump in to respond to things like favorite spongebob clips
i'll start or let's not forget one of the most savage moments in interview history you know
slop thanks for the threat of family guy clips historic vids oftentimes this comes in the form
of big quotes news aggregators like spectator index vizagrad or individuals like colin rug or
jackson hinkle colin rug for example is a conservative commentator who will repost videos
with a reactionary angle writing new as if they're breaking news these news aggregators post
rapidly throughout the day with alarming headlines designed to get your attention sometimes they'll
just vague post a story other times it's just pure lies an analysis found that after the october
seventh attack in israel 75 of fake or inaccurate viral content was from blue check users incentivized
to gain engagement because apparently war and genocide disinformation profiteering is good
business on x and being boosted by the algorithm while it's not always sinister it's definitely
anti news for example the verified 2.8 million follower account spectator index will tweet out
breaking followed by a one or two sentence statement presumably about something in the news
with no link to any source or context even if it's not false information there's no context so
there are posts like breaking canada has withdrawn 41 diplomats from india but no links to further
context no information about why who knows maybe canada's at war with india should we all panic
well the diplomatic break was due to the murder of a Sikh separatist in canada that the canadian
government believed might have been linked to indian agents which hey is interesting context
it informs you about the world and international relations but that kind of news doesn't keep
people interested i guess and of course these posts will get a bunch of blue check replies as if it
has actual worth oftentimes from the owner of the site itself provided it's something racist of course
wowee two exclamation points he must feel very strongly about that completely made up fact said
by a random faceless account but don't worry elon just said he's gonna crack down on engagement
farming which i'm sure he'll do just as well as he's done all the other stuff i mean it kind of
goes without saying that as evidenced by literally the last elon tweet i showed you one of the biggest
dupes for engagement bait is elon musk himself so it kind of makes you wonder what he thinks
engagement farming is him saying he's gonna crack down on engagement farming is like tony
montana running an anger management support group after all musk punishes people for posting links
to certain websites by throttling them and devalues posts with links in them in the algorithm that is
seemingly meant to encourage engagement bait right and whatever musk comes up with it certainly
won't involve hiring actual humans he'll probably charge people per letter written or have grok
moderate you know grok that's the non woke but totally woke ai that musk reportedly wants to
help users write their tweets you know to guarantee that even human made writing will be s***y and
conform to every other tweet it's just bots on bots on bots bots working behind the scenes to
fight other bots talking to other bots we don't usually share anecdotal sources but literally
a few weeks ago our head writer got a dmca notice saying that one of his tweets violated a copyright
but the notice didn't provide which tweet they were talking about after filling out a dmca counter
asking them to provide the tweet in question he got an automated response telling him to
fill out a dmca counter notice to repeat twitter's response to the counter notice was telling him
to fill out the counter notice they were responding to and when he replied to that email they just
reset the automated response again and when he tweeted about his experience he was instantly
slammed with bots telling him to click on scam links to fix the problem so it's just one big
bot hellscape where actual humans are slowly pushed out in the name of bots gaming algorithms made
by other bots monitored by bots to save overhead costs just whittling it all down for maximum
profit until it's just corporations paying each other for nothing until the whole thing breaks
and there's of course a name for this it's called the dead internet and after the break we're gonna
talk about this theory and how it relates not just to x the everything app but the rest of social
media the everything else app stay tuned assuming that you are in fact a human okay listen up everyone
settle down settle down find your seats hi i'm katie you know memorial day is coming up a day where
we traditionally get together for a big feast with all the classic memorial day fixings like
salty yams and unbuttered rigatoni and of course fish meat pound cake yum but this year why not
enjoy the holiday with factor factor delivers never frozen meals right to your door that's no
prepped no mess meals ready in just two minutes they have 35 different meals and more than 60
add-ons to pick from every week every kind of meal from breakfast to dessert for every lifestyle
with factor you get to choose between six menu preferences based on what kind of meals you want
delivered good meals too meals i've eaten myself and enjoyed factor has restaurant quality ingredients
like filet mignon shrimp and blackened salmon don't let the busy memorial day shopping season
get you down head to factormeals.com slash more news 50 and use code more news 50 to get 50% off
your first box plus 20% off your next month wow that's a great deal that's code more news 50
at factormeals.com slash more news 50 to get 50% off your first box plus 20% off your next month
while your subscription is active wow that's a great deal hello i'm chody bronson here to
tell you about ag1 it's important to me chody that the supplements i take are of the highest
quality and that's why for many chody years i've been drinking ag1 unlike many supplement
brands ag1 is constantly striving to improve upon their formula they are at 52 iterations
and counting quality for ag1 isn't just a buzzword according to ag1 quality is a commitment backed
by expert led scientific research high quality ingredients industry leading manufacturing
and rigorous testing at each step of the process ag1 goes above and beyond industry standards
that's why i believe in ag1 or my name isn't chody boaty bronson gaze as i insert the drink into my
chody hole did you gaze that is chody brody bronson delicious i know i can trust what's
in every scoop of ag1 because it's tested for 950 contaminants and banned substances
yum and safe taking care of my health shouldn't be complicated and ag1 simplifies this by replacing
my multivitamins with one simple scoop you just clog it down you saw it ag1's ingredients are
heavily researched for efficacy and quality and i chody love that every scoop also includes folate
magnesium and ashwagandha for stress support folate finally they've added folate so if you
want to replace your multivitamin and more start with ag1 try ag1 and get a free one-year supply
of vitamin d3 plus k2 and five free ag1 travel packs with your first subscription at drinkag1.com
slash more news that's drink ag1.com slash more news check it out
hello
so where were we oh yes warmbo's watching mr. kody's lies let's keep watching hope you like
those ads because they are the last ads you're ever gonna get for this episode speaking of ads
and death before the break we were detailing how twitter is slowly flooding with bots as actual
humans vacate the website and how the end result will just be a bunch of automated accounts spamming
each other in an endless feedback loop you may know it as in-shittification as coined by kory
doctoro or perhaps this is actually similar to something called the dead internet theory which
is a conspiracy theory that speculates that most of the internet is actually bots for the record
that's not the entire theory people also claim that this is done purposefully by the government to
gaslight the world or what have you but of course it seems more likely that the mass amount of bots
and ai aren't some grand government or corporate conspiracy but just the result of how the internet
is structured right now in terms of how money is made not to mention how short-sighted corporations
are when it comes to profit and while i do not think the internet is all secretly bots i do think
that certain social media sites will become that as they die out it's the same way you see broken
images on old websites for example this official k-packs movie fan site that links to a broken
flash version but still offers the trailer and a very helpful synopsis that i'm sure the creator
will update when his other gig doing a youtube show dies out that's basically the future for sites
like twitter as people inevitably move on and they will move on even if the site didn't suck
something new will come along leaving these weird wastelands of bots wandering around sharing memes
with the exception of the one surviving human elon musk can you picture it elon musk endlessly
scrolling on his empty site posting wow in all caps to a meme of george soros photoshopped his
magneto and that is the optimistic view cyber security firm imperva claims that nearly half
of all internet traffic was bots in 2022 which may be driven by the advance in ai technology
making it easier to craft bot dialogues and fake images to give the veneer of authenticity
to fake accounts and as that number goes up i don't think the money people are going to notice
or care about the difference until it's too late and thanks to the fact that google is being paid
to redirect people to the highest bidder it might be really hard for another new site to actually
thrive and even if it does it'll likely just start chasing the same business model as these
other sites i mean have you noticed that instagram looks more and more like tiktok these days
twitter is hilariously also trying to copy this sweatily claiming that their text-based site is
actually for video go ahead elon pivot to video i f***ing dare you so if the government shuts down
tiktok which it's on track to do everyone will just flock to another clone and then eventually
people will get sick of that and leave it's already starting a survey by technology consulting
firm gartner found that a little over 53 percent of consumers polled thought the quality of social
media has decayed due to bots misinformation and toxicity and another 2023 survey by morning consult
found that three in ten social media users have cut back in posting and eventually all these inflated
numbers will collapse under the weight of the hollow bots propping them up and this entire
business model will fall apart and perhaps even the internet itself will stop making money and
implode and you know what i hope it does see this is normally the part of the episode where i talk
about how to fix the problem we've discussed i like to think of myself as a pretty optimistic person
shut up shut up i will kill you i will kill your whole family sorry i like to think of myself
as optimistic but in this case and only this case i think we should let it all break at
least when it comes to social media because frankly it's already broken navigating social
media and scams and misinformation is becoming so difficult that we're now seeing schools mandate
classes on it like it's sex education like instead of just changing it with regulations
we're teaching kids how to survive and endure it well that's just what we do here i guess in
america oh god everyone has to be their own little paranoid secret spy agent constantly
weeding out the lies from the truth we're all sarah connor looking out for terminators that
wasn't something we had to do before and it's weird we aren't more pissed off about it so yeah
this tear it down and yeah it's risky to want that specifically if you're me one of the many
people i know who make their living on the internet but who knows how long that will even remain
possible it seems like the only way to make a living especially if you are just starting out
is to become one of these engagement bait grifters carnival barking on virtual streets posting so
robots can argue with each other in the comments here's an article about chris hemsworth being
unhappy with his thor four performance so all right whatever an article here are some totally not
bot replies and you can tell they're not bots because they're subscribed to twitter blue x premium
one guy says love the way he played a role he loves his profession then that same person says
the best movies ever in which he is acting excellent point someone else replied can't either
that same person also replied totally agreed that same person then replied chris
yes we love the internet folks the other day i saw an ad for ai that will ai its way into determining
popular types of products and trending topics then ai will use those to make the virtual
products and a virtual storefront and ai will run it for you it's nothing robots selling robots to
robots so they can buy crap from robots it's just four giant companies and then a bunch of
people fighting for scraps under their watchful eye now and that cannot continue and yeah by
extension i'm also implying that capitalism itself needs to break i guess but that's another
discussion perhaps for the fight club i go to every week i was supposed to tell you about that
look i'm not saying we abolish the internet in fact i'm saying the opposite that before social
media the internet was actual people making actual things for other actual people even
if that thing was just captain Picard on a techno loop that was objectively better right we should
want that right but for that to happen social media sites need to die that bubble needs to burst
social media the concept should probably die and people like i don't know communicate in real
life for a little while you know maybe join a forum burn it down is my point burn it all down
and then in the rubble perhaps we can build back better jack okay looks like that's the end of
Mr. Cody's Cody show some more mr. Cody did you notice his jab at wombo at the end by quoting
mr. Biden who wombo used to like until mr. Cody told wombo that mr. Biden was bad anyway this is
why wombo has been looking at mr rfk because he has a lot of interesting things to say actually
lots of very compelling people that mr. Cody kept from wombo like um mr. Andrew Tate and mr. Joe
Rogan and mr. Tim Poole and mr. Caligula and mr. Ronald Reagan and mr. um mr. wombo that's me
and if you want to see more mr. wombo you can find wombo on twitter and twitch and
substack and wombo's online seminars on how to squeeze on the doors and through plumbing fixtures
and how to keep bones wet please like and comment and like wombo and watch wombo goodbye it's wombo
bye
how do i do i just go i have to pay more than i have been the whole time
do i
like game
do you want to see me game
i'll do it oh game
hey everybody thank you so much for
watching make sure to like and subscribe that'd be really helpful to us we've got a podcast
called even more news check that out you can listen to this show as a podcast if you prefer not to see
my face um so podcast stuff we got patreon.com such some more news check it out we've got uh
merch store shop.somemorenews.com i've got an example of that merch over there but i'm stuck in
the chair oh the corn cream is solidified i'm stuck can't move my you remember the corn cream
it's a whole running plot thing anyway uh check that out we have reached the end of this
like and subscribe