Human-level AI is deep, deep into an intelligence explosion.
Things like inventing the transformer or discovering
Chinchilla scaling and doing your training runs more optimally
or creating flash attention.
That set of inputs probably would yield the kind of AI
capabilities needed for intelligence explosion.
You have a race between, on the one hand,
the project of getting strong interpretability
and shaping motivations.
And on the other hand, these AIs in ways
that you don't perceive make the AI takeover happen.
We spend more compute by having a larger brain than other animals.
And then we have a longer childhood.
It's not like you have to like having a bigger model
and having more training time with it.
It seemed very implausible that we couldn't do better
than completely brute force evolution.
How quickly are we running through those orders of magnitude?
OK, today I have the pleasure of speaking with Carl Schulman,
many of my former guests.
And this is not an exaggeration.
Many of my former guests have told me
that a lot of their biggest ideas,
perhaps most of their biggest ideas,
have come directly from Carl,
especially when it has to do with the intelligence explosion
and its impacts.
And so I decided to go directly to the source
and we have Carl today on the podcast.
Carl keeps a super low profile,
but he is one of the most interesting intellectuals
I've ever encountered.
And this is actually his second podcast ever.
So we're going to get to get deep into the heart
of many of the most important ideas
that are circulating right now,
directly from the source.
So and by the way,
so Carl is also an advisor to the Open Philanthropy Project,
which is one of the biggest funders
on causes having to do with AI and its risks,
not to mention global health and old being.
And he is a research associate
at the Future of Humanity Institute at Oxford.
So Carl, it's a huge pleasure to have you on the podcast.
Thanks for coming.
Thank you, Drakash.
I've enjoyed seeing some of your episodes recently
and I'm glad to be on the show.
Excellent. Let's talk about AI.
Before we get into the details,
give me the sort of big picture explanation
of the feedback loops and just the general dynamics
that would start when you have something
that is approaching human level intelligence.
Yeah. So I think the way to think about it
is we have a process now
where humans are developing new computer chips,
new software, running larger training runs
and it takes a lot of work to keep Moore's law chugging.
Well, it was, it's slowing down now
and it takes a lot of work to develop things
like transformers to develop a lot of the improvements
to AI and neural networks.
They're advancing things.
And the core method that I think I want to highlight
on this podcast, and I think is underappreciated
is the idea of input-output curves.
So we can look at the increasing difficulty
of improving chips.
And so sure, each time you double the performance
of computers, it's harder
and as we approach physical limits,
eventually it becomes impossible, but how much harder?
So there's a paper called our Ideas Getting Harder to Find.
It was published a few years ago,
something like 10 years ago at Mirri,
we did, I mean, I did an early version of this analysis
using mainly data from Intel
and like the large semiconductor fabricators.
Anyway, and so in this paper, they cover a period
where the productivity of computing
went up a million folds.
So you could get a million times
the computing operations per second per dollar.
Big change, but it got harder.
So the amount of investments, the labor force required
to make those continuing advancements
went up and up and up.
Indeed, it went up 18 fold over that period.
I know, so some take this to say,
oh, diminishing returns,
things are just getting harder and harder.
And so that will be the end of progress eventually.
However, in a world where AI is doing the work,
that doubling of computing performance
translates pretty directly to a doubling or better
of the effective labor supply.
That is, if when we had that million fold compute increase,
we used it to run artificial intelligences
who would replace human scientists and engineers
then the 18x increase in the labor demands
of the industry would be trivial.
We're getting more than one doubling
of the effective labor supply
that we need for each doubling of the labor requirement.
And in that data set, it's like over four.
So we double compute.
Okay, now we need somewhat more researchers,
but a lot less than twice as many.
And so, okay, we use up some of those doublings of compute
on the increasing difficulty of further research,
but most of them are left to expedite the process.
So if you double your labor force,
that's enough to get several doublings of compute.
You use up one of them on meeting
the increased demands from diminishing returns.
The others can be used to accelerate the process.
So you have your first doubling takes however many months,
your next doubling can take a smaller fraction of that,
the next doubling less and so on.
At least in so far as this,
the outputs you're generating,
compute for AI in this story.
Are able to serve the function of the necessary inputs.
If there are other inputs that you need,
eventually those become a bottleneck
and you wind up more restricted on those.
Got it, okay.
So yeah, I think the bloom paper had that,
there was 35% increase in,
was it transferred to destiny or cost per flop?
And there was a 7% increase per year
in the number of researchers required
to sustain that pace.
So something on this, yeah,
it's like four to five doublings of compute
per doubling of labor inputs.
I guess there's a lot of questions you can delve into
in terms of whether you would expect a similar scale
with AI and whether it makes sense to think of AI
as a population of researchers
that keeps growing with compute itself.
Actually, let's go there.
So can you explain the intuition
that compute is a good proxy
for the number of AI researchers so to speak?
So far I've talked about hardware as an initial example
because we had good data about a past period.
You can also make improvements on the software side.
And we think about an intelligence explosion
that can include AI is doing work
on making hardware better, making better software,
making more hardware.
But the basic idea for the hardware is especially simple
in that if you have a worker,
an AI worker that can substitute for a human,
if you have twice as many computers,
you can run two separate instances of them
and then they can do two different jobs,
manage two different machines,
work on two different design problems.
Now, you can get more gains than just what you would get
by having two instances.
We get improvements from using some of our compute,
not just to run more instances of the existing AI,
but to train larger AIs.
So there's hardware technology,
how much you can get per dollar you spend on hardware.
And there's software technology.
And the software can be copied freely.
So if you've got the software,
it doesn't necessarily make that much to say that,
oh, we've got 100 Microsoft Windows.
You can make as many copies as you need
for whatever Microsoft will charge you.
But for hardware is different.
It matters how much we actually spend on the hardware
at a given price.
And if we look at the changes
that have been driving AI recently,
that is the thing that is really off-trend.
We are spending tremendously more money
on computer hardware for training big AI models.
Yeah, okay.
So there's the investment in hardware.
There's a hardware technology itself
and there's the software progress itself.
The AI is getting better
because we're spending more money on it
because our hardware itself is getting better over time.
And because we're developing better models
or better adjustments to those models,
where is the loop here?
The work involved in designing new hardware and software
is being done by people now.
They use computer tools to assist them,
but computer time is not the primary cost
for NVIDIA designing chips,
for TSMC producing them for ASML,
making lithography equipment to serve the TSMC fabs.
And even in AI software research,
that has become quite compute-intensive.
But I think we're still in the range
where at a place like DeepMind salaries,
we're still larger than compute for the experiments.
Although they're tremendously, tremendously more
of the expenditures were on compute
relative to salaries than in the past.
If you take all of the work that's being done
by those humans,
there's like low tens of thousands of people
working at NVIDIA designing GPUs specialized for AI.
I think there's more like 70,000 people at TSMC,
which is the leading producer of cutting-edge chips.
There's a lot of additional people at companies like ASML
that supply them with the tools they need.
And then a company like DeepMind,
I think from their public filings,
they recently had 1,000 people,
opening, I think, is a few hundred people.
Anthropic is less.
If you add up things like Facebook AI research,
Google Brain, R&D,
you get thousands or tens of thousands of people
who are working on AI research.
We'd want to zoom in on those who are developing new methods
rather than narrow applications.
So inventing the transformer definitely counts.
Optimizing for some particular businesses,
dataset cleaning, probably not.
But so those people are doing this work.
They're driving quite a lot of progress.
What we observe and the growth of people
relative to the growth of those capabilities,
is that pretty consistently,
the capabilities are doubling on a shorter time scale
than the people required to do them are doubling.
And so there's work.
So we talked about hardware
and how historically it was pretty dramatic,
like four or five doublings of compute efficiency
per doubling of human inputs.
I think that's a bit lower now
as we get towards the end of Moore's Law.
Although interestingly, not as much lower
as you might think,
because the growth of inputs has also slowed recently.
On the software side,
there's some work by Teme Bessaroglu
and I think collaborators,
may have been the thesis.
It's called our models getting harder to find.
And so it's applying the same sort of analysis
as our ideas getting harder to find.
And you can look at growth rates of papers
from citations, employment at these companies.
And it seems like the doubling time
of these like workers driving the software advances
is like several years, or at least a couple of years.
Whereas the doubling of effective compute
from algorithmic progress is faster.
So there's a group called Epoch.
They've received grants from Open Philanthropy
and they do work collecting datasets
that are relevant to forecasting AI progress.
And so their headline results
for what's the rate of progress in hardware and software
and just like growth in budgets, ours follows.
So for hardware, they're looking at like a doubling
of hardware efficiency that's like two years.
It's possible it's a bit better than that
when you take into account certain specializations
for AI workloads.
For the growth of budgets,
they find a doubling time that's like something
like six months in recent years,
which is pretty tremendous relative
to the historical rates.
We should maybe get into that later.
And then on the algorithmic progress side,
mainly using ImageNet type datasets right now,
they find a doubling time that's less than one year.
And so you combine all of these things
and the growth of effective compute
for training big, big AIs, it's pretty drastic.
I think I saw an estimate that GPD-4
costs like $50 million around that range to train.
Now, suppose that like AGI takes 1000X that,
if you were just a scale of GPD-4, it might not be that.
I'm just just for the sake of example.
So part of that will come from companies
just spending a lot more to train the models
and that just greater investment.
Part of that will come from them having better models
so that what would have taken a 10X increase in the model
to get naively you can do with having a better model
that you only need to do scale up.
You get the same effect of increasing it by 10X
just from having a better model.
And so yeah, you can spend more money
on it to train a bigger model.
You can just have a better model
or you can have chips that are cheaper to train.
So you get more compute for the same dollars.
And okay, so those are the three you were describing.
The ways in which the quote unquote
effective at compute would increase.
From the looking at it right now, it looks like,
yeah, you might get two or three
doublings of effective compute
for this thing that we're calling software progress,
which is, which people get by asking,
well, how much less compute can you use now
to achieve the same benchmark as you achieved before?
There are reasons to not fully identify this
with like software progress
as you might naively think of it
because some of it can be enabled by the other.
So like when you have a lot of compute,
you can do more experiments
and find algorithms that work better.
Sometimes the additional compute,
you can get higher efficiency
by running a bigger model we were talking about earlier.
And so that means you're getting more
for each GPU that you have
because you made this like larger expenditure.
And that can look like a software improvement
because this model,
it's not a hardware improvement directly
because it's doing more with the same hardware,
but you wouldn't have been able to achieve it
without having a ton of GPUs to do the big training run.
The feedback loop itself involves the AI
that is the result of this greater effect of compute,
helping you train better AI, right?
Or use less effective compute in the future
to train better AI.
It can help on the hardware design.
So like NVIDIA is a fabulous chip design company.
They don't make their own chips.
They send files of instructions to TSMC,
which then fabricates the chips in their own facilities.
And so the work of those 10,000 plus people,
if you could automate that
and have the equivalent of a million people doing that work,
then I think you would pretty quickly get the kind
of improvements that can be achieved
with the existing nodes that TSMC is operating on.
You could get a lot of those chip design gains.
Basically like doing the job of improving chip design
that those people are working on now,
but get it done faster.
So that's one thing.
I think that's less important
for the intelligence explosion.
The reason being that when you make an improvement
to chip design, it only applies
to the chips you make after that.
If you make an improvement in AI software,
it has the potential to be immediately applied
to all of the GPUs that you already have.
Yeah.
And so the thing that I think is most disruptive
and most important has the leading edge of the change
from AI automation of the inputs to AI
is on the software side.
At what point would it get to the point
where the AIs are helping develop better software
or better models for future AIs?
Some people claim today, for example,
that programmers at OpenAI are using co-pilot
to write programs now.
So in some sense, you're already having
that sort of feedback loop.
I'm a little skeptical of that as a mechanism.
At what point would it be the case
that the AI is contributing significantly
in the sense that it would almost be the equivalent
of having additional researchers
to AI progress in software?
The quantitative magnitude of the help
is absolutely central.
So there are plenty of companies
that make some product
that very slightly boost productivity.
So when Xerox makes fax machines,
it maybe increases people's productivity
in office work by 0.1% or something.
You're not gonna have explosive growth out of that
because, okay, now 0.1% more effective R&D at Xerox
than any customers buying the machines.
Not that important.
So I think the thing to look for
is when is it the case that the contributions from AI
are starting to become as large or larger
as the contributions from humans?
So when this is boosting their effective productivity
by 50 or 100% and if you then go from eight months
doubling time, say for effective compute
from software innovation,
things like inventing the transformer
or discovering chinchilla scaling
and doing your training runs more optimally
or creating flash attention.
Yeah, if you move that from, say, eight months to four months
and then the next time you apply that,
it significantly increases the boost you're getting
from the AI.
So maybe instead of giving a 50%
or 100% productivity boost,
that's more like a 200%.
And so it doesn't have to have been able
to automate everything involved
in the process of AI research.
It can be, it's automated a bunch of things.
And then those are being done in extreme profusion
because I think that AI can do,
you have it done much more often because it's so cheap.
And so it's not a threshold of this is human level AI.
It can do everything a human can do
with no weaknesses in any area.
It's that even with its weaknesses,
it's able to bump up the performance.
So that instead of getting like the results we would have
with the 10,000 people working on finding these innovations,
we get the results that we would have
if we had twice as many of those people
with the same kind of skill distribution.
And so that's a, it's like a demanding challenge.
It's like you need quite a lot of capability for that.
But it's also important that it's significantly less
than this is a system where there's no way you can point at it
and say in any respect, it is weaker than a human.
A system that was just as good as a human in every respect,
but also had all of the advantages of an AI,
that is just way beyond this point.
Like if you consider that there's like the output
of our existing fabs make tens of millions
of advanced GPUs per year.
Those GPUs, if they were running sort of AI software
that was as efficient as humans,
as a sample efficient,
it doesn't have any major weaknesses.
So they can work four times as long,
the 168 hour work week,
they can have much more education than any human.
So it's a human, they got a PhD,
it's like, wow, it's like 20 years of education,
maybe longer if they take a slow route on the PhD.
It's just normal for us to train large models
by eat the internet, eat all the published books ever,
read everything on GitHub and get good at predicting it.
So like the level of education vastly beyond any human,
the degree to which the models are focused on task
is higher than all, but like the most motivated humans
when they're really, really gunning for it.
So you combine the things tens of millions of GPUs,
each GPU is doing the work of the very best humans
in the world and like the most capable humans in the world
can command salaries that are a lot higher than the average
and particularly in a field like STEM or narrowly AI.
Like there's no human in the world
who has a thousand years of experience with TensorFlow
or let alone the new AI technology
that were invented the year before.
But if they were around,
yeah, they'd be paid millions of dollars a year.
And so when you consider this,
okay, tens of millions of GPUs,
each is doing the work of maybe 40,
maybe more of these kind of existing workers.
This is like going from a workforce of tens of thousands
to hundreds of millions.
You immediately make all kinds of discoveries then,
you immediately develop all sorts of tremendous technologies.
So human level AI is deep, deep
into an intelligence explosion.
Intelligence explosion has to start
with something weaker than that.
Yeah, well, what is the thing it starts with
and how close are we to that?
Because if you think of a research or an open AI or something,
these are, to be a researcher is not just completing
the hello world prompt that co-pilot does, right?
It's like, you got to choose a new idea,
you got to figure out the right way to approach it.
You perhaps have to manage the people
who are also working with you on that problem.
It's like, it's incredibly complicated skill,
portfolio skills rather than just a single skill.
So yeah, what is the point of wish
that feedback loop starts where you can even,
you're not just doing the 0.5% increase in productivity
that a sort of AI tool might do,
but is actually the equivalent of a researcher
or close to it, what is that point?
So I think maybe a way to look at it
is to give some illustrative examples
of the kinds of capabilities that you might see.
And so because these systems have to be a lot weaker
than the sort of human level things,
what we'll have is intense application
of the ways in which AIs have advantages,
partly offsetting their weaknesses.
And so AIs are cheap.
We can call a lot of them to do many small problems.
And so you'll have situations where you have dumber AIs
that are deployed thousands of times
to equal, say, one human worker.
And they'll be doing things like these voting algorithms
where you, with an LLM, you generate
a bunch of different responses
and take a majority vote among them
that improves performance sum.
You'll have things like the AlphaGo kind of approach
where you use the neural net to do search
and you go deeper with the search by plowing in more compute,
which helps to offset the inefficiency
and weaknesses of the model on its own.
You'll do things that would just be totally impractical
for humans because of the sheer number of steps.
And so an example of that would be
designing synthetic training data.
So humans do not learn by just going into the library
and opening books at random pages.
It's actually much, much more efficient
to have things like schools and classes
where they teach you things in an order that makes sense,
that's focusing on the skills
that are more valuable to learn.
They give you tests and exam,
they're designed to try and elicit the skill
they're actually trying to teach.
And right now we don't bother with that
because we can hoover up more data from the internet.
We're getting towards the end of that.
But yeah, as the AIs get more sophisticated,
they'll be better able to tell what is a useful kind
of skill to practice and to generate that.
And we've done that in other areas.
So AlphaGo, the original version of AlphaGo
was booted up with data from human go play
and then improved with reinforcement learning
and Monte Carlo tree search.
But then AlphaZero,
but they somewhat more sophisticated model
benefited from some other improvements
but was able to go from scratch.
And it generated its own data through self play.
So getting data of a higher quality
than the human data,
because there are no human players that good
available in the dataset.
And also a curriculum.
So that at any given point,
it was playing games against an opponent
of equal skill itself.
And so it was always in an area
when it was easy to learn.
If you're just always losing no matter what you do
or always winning no matter what you do,
it's hard to distinguish which things are better
and which are worse.
And when we have somewhat more sophisticated AIs
that can generate training data and tasks for themselves.
For example, if the AI can generate a lot of unit tests
and then can try and produce programs
that pass those unit tests,
then the interpreter is providing a training signal.
And the AI can get good at figuring out
what's the kind of programming problem
that is hard for AIs right now
that will develop more of the skills that I need
and then do them.
And now you're not gonna have employees at OpenAI
write like a billion programming problems.
That's just not gonna happen.
But you are gonna have AIs given the task
of producing those enormous number
of programming challenges.
In LLMS themselves, there's a paper out of Anthropa
called Constitution AI or Constitution RL
where they basically had the program
just like talk to itself and say,
like, is this response helpful?
If not, how can I make this more helpful?
And the response is improved.
And then you train the model
and the more helpful response is
that it generates by talking to itself
so that it generates natively.
And you could imagine more sophisticated ways
to do that or better ways to do that.
Okay, so then the question is, listen,
GPT-4 already costs like 50 million
or 100 million or whatever it was.
Even if we have greater effective compute
from hardware increases and better models,
it's hard to imagine how we could sustain
like four or five more orders of magnitude,
greater effective size than GPT-4
unless we're jumping in like trillions of dollars
like the entire economies of big countries
into training the next version.
So the question is, do we get something
that can significantly help with AI progress
before we run out of the sheer money and scale
and compute that would require to train it?
Do you have a take on that?
Well, first I'd say remember
that there are these three contributing trends.
So the new H-100s are significantly better
than the A-100s and a lot of companies
are actually waiting for their deliveries of H-100s
to do even bigger training runs along with the work
of hooking them up into clusters
and engineering the thing.
Yeah, so all of those factors are contributing.
And of course, mathematically,
yeah, if you do four orders of magnitude more
than 50 or a hundred million,
then you're getting to Jolene Deli territory.
And yeah, I think the way to look at it is
at each step along the way,
does it look like it makes sense to do the next step?
And so from where we are right now,
seeing the results with GPT-4 and chat GPT,
companies like Google and Microsoft and whatnot
are pretty convinced that this is very valuable.
You have like talk at Google and Microsoft with Bing
that, well, it's like billion dollar matter
to change market share in search by a percentage point.
And so that can fund a lot.
And on the far end, on the extreme,
if you automate human labor,
we have a hundred trillion dollar economy.
Most of that economy is paid out in wages.
So like between 50 and 70 trillion dollars per year.
If you create AGI, it's going to automate all of that
and keep increasing beyond that.
So the value of the completed project
is very much worth throwing our whole economy into it.
If you're gonna get the good version,
not the catastrophic destruction of the human race
or some other disastrous outcome.
And in between, it's a question of,
well, did the next step, how risky and uncertain is it
and how much growth in the revenue
you can generate with it, do you get?
And so for moving up to a billion dollars,
I think that's absolutely gonna happen.
These large tech companies have R&D budgets,
tens of billions of dollars.
And when you think about it like in the relevant sense,
like all the employees at Microsoft
who are doing software engineering,
that's like contributing to creating software objects.
It's not weird to spend tens of billions of dollars
on a product that would do so much.
And I think it's becoming more clear
that there is sort of market opportunity to fund the thing.
Going up to a hundred billion dollars,
that's like, okay, the existing R&D budgets
spread over multiple years.
But if you keep seeing that when you scale up the model,
it substantially improves the performance.
It opens up new applications.
You're not just improving your search,
but maybe it makes self-driving cars work.
You replace bulk software engineering jobs
or if not replace them, amplify productivity.
In this kind of dynamic, you actually probably want to employ
all the software engineers you can get,
as long as they're able to make any contribution
because the returns of improving stuff in AI itself
get so high.
But yeah, so I think that can go up to a hundred billion.
And at a hundred billion, you're using
like a significant fraction of our existing Vab capacity.
Like right now, the revenue of NVIDIA is like 25 billion.
The revenue of TSMC, I believe is like over 50 billion.
I checked in 2021, NVIDIA was maybe 7.5%,
less than 10% of TSMC revenue.
So there's a lot of room and most of that was not AI chips.
They have a large gaming segment.
There are data center GPUs that are used
for video and the like.
So there's room for more than an order of magnitude increase
by redirecting existing Vabs to produce more AI chips.
And they're just actually using the AI chips
that these companies have in their cloud
for the big training runs.
And so I think that's enough to go to the 10 billion
and then combine with stuff like the H100
to go up to the hundred billion.
Just to emphasize for the audience,
the initial point about revenue made,
if it cost open AI $100 million to train GPT-4
and it generates $500 million in revenue,
you pay back your expenses with the hundred million,
you have 400 million for your next training run,
then you train your GPT-4.5,
you get let's say $4 billion out of revenue out of that.
That's where the feedback group of revenue comes from,
where you're automating tasks
and therefore you're making money,
you can use that money to automate more tasks.
On the ability to redirect the fat production
towards AI chips.
So then the TLDR on,
you want $100 billion worth of compute.
I mean, fabs take what like a decade or so to build.
So given the ones we have now
and the ones that are gonna come online in the next decade,
is there enough to sustain $100 billion of GPU compute
if you wanted to spend that on a training run?
Yes, you would definitely make the hundred billion one.
How do you go up to a trillion dollar run and larger?
It's gonna involve more fab construction
and yeah, fabs can take a long time to build.
On the other hand, if in fact,
you're getting very high revenue from the AI systems
and you're actually bottlenecked
on the construction of these fabs,
then their price could skyrocket.
And that lead to measures we've never seen before
to expand and accelerate fab production.
Like if you consider,
so at the limit has you're getting models
that approach human-like capability.
Can you imagine things that are getting close
to like brain-like efficiencies plus AI advantages?
We were talking before about, well,
a GPU that is supporting an AI,
really it's a cluster of GPU supporting AI
is that do things in parallel, data parallelism.
But if that can work four times as much as a human,
a highly skilled, motivated, focused human
with levels of education that have never been seen
in the human population.
And so if like a typical software engineer
can earn hundreds of thousands of dollars,
the world's best software engineers
can earn millions of dollars today
and maybe more in a world where there's so much demand for AI.
And then times four for working all the time.
Well, I mean, if you have,
if you can generate like close to $10 million a year
out of the future version of H100,
and it costs tens of thousands of dollars
with a huge profit margin now.
And profit margin could be reduced
with like large production.
That is a big difference that chip
pays for itself almost instantly.
And so you could support paying 10 times as much
to have these fabs constructed more rapidly.
You could have, if AI is starting to be able to contribute,
you could have AI contributing more
of the skilled technical work that makes it hard
for say, NVIDIA to suddenly find thousands upon thousands
of top quality engineering hires, if AI can provide that.
Now, if AI hasn't reached that level of performance,
then this is how you can have things stall out.
And like a world where AI progress stalls out
is one where you go to the $100 billion
and then over succeeding years,
trillion dollar things, software, progress,
turns out to stall.
You lose the gains that you are getting
from moving researchers from other fields,
lots of physicists and people from other areas
of computer science have been going to AI.
But you sort of tap out those resources.
Has it AI becomes a larger proportion of the research field?
And like, okay, you've put in all of these inputs,
but they just haven't yielded AI yet.
I think that set of inputs probably would yield
the kind of AI capabilities needed
for intelligence explosion.
But if it doesn't, after we've exhausted
this current scale up of like increasing the share
of our economy that is trying to make AI,
if that's not enough, then after that,
you have to wait for the slow grind
of things like general economic growth,
population growth and such.
And so things slow.
And that results in my credences
and this kind of advanced AI happening
to be relatively concentrated like over the next 10 years
compared to the rest of the century.
Because we just can't, we can't keep going
with this rapid redirection of resources into AI.
That's a one time thing.
If the current scale up works, it's going to happen.
We're gonna get to AI really fast,
like within the next 10 years or something.
If the current scale up doesn't work,
all we're left with is just like economy
growing like 2% of years.
We have like 2% a year more resources to spend on AI.
And at that scale, you're talking about decades
before you can just through sheer brute force,
you can train the $10 trillion model or something.
Let's talk about why you have your thesis
that the current scale up would work.
What is the evidence from AI itself
or maybe from private evolution
and the evolution of other animals?
Just give me the whole, the whole confluence
of reasons that make you think.
I think maybe the best way to look at that
might be to consider when I first became interested
in this area, so in the 2000s,
which was before the deep learning revolution,
how would I think about timelines?
How did I think about timelines?
And then how have I updated based on what has been happening
with deep learning?
And so back then, I would have said,
we know the brain is a physical object
and information processing device.
It works, it's possible.
And not only is it possible,
it was created by evolution on earth.
And so that gives us something of an upper bound
in that this kind of brute force was sufficient.
There are some complexities with like,
well, what if it was a freak accident
and it didn't happen on all of the other planets
and that added some value.
I have a paper with Nick Bustrom on this.
I think basically that's not that important an issue.
There's converging evolution like octopi
are also quite sophisticated.
If a special event was at the level of forming cells at all
or forming brains at all,
we get to skip that because we're choosing
to build computers and we already exist.
We have that advantage.
So say evolution gives something of an upper bound,
really intensive massive brute force search
and things like evolutionary algorithms
can produce intelligence.
Doesn't the fact that octopi and I guess other mammals,
they got to the point of being like pretty intelligent
but not human level intelligent.
Is that some evidence that there's a hard step
between a cephalopod and a human?
Yeah, so that would be a place to look.
It doesn't seem particularly compelling.
One source of evidence on that is work by Herculano Hutzel.
I hope I haven't mispronounced her name
but she's a neuroscientist who has dissolved the brains
of many creatures and by counting the nuclei,
she's able to determine how many neurons are present
in different species and find a lot of interesting trends
in scaling laws.
She's a paper discussing the human brain
has a scaled up primate brain
and across like a wide variety of animals
and mammals in particular.
There are certain characteristic changes
in the relative number of neurons
size of different brain regions have things scale up.
There's a lot of, yeah, there's a lot of structural similarity
there and you can explain a lot of what is different about us
with a pretty brute force story,
which is that you expend resources
on having a bigger brain, keeping it in good order,
giving it time to learn.
So we have an unusually long childhood,
unusually long in its period.
We spend more compute by having a larger brain
than other animals, more than three times
as large as chimpanzees.
And then we have a longer childhood than chimpanzees
and much more than many, many other creatures.
So we're spending more compute in a way
that's analogous to like having a bigger model
and having more training time with it.
And given that we see with our AI models,
this sort of like large consistent benefits
from increasing compute spent in those ways
and with qualitatively new capabilities
showing up over and over again,
particularly in areas that sort of AI skeptics call out
in my experience like over the last 15 years,
the things that people call out has like,
ah, but the AI can't do that.
And it's because of a fundamental limitation.
We've gone through a lot of them.
There were Winograd schemas, catastrophic forgetting,
quite a number.
And yeah, they have repeatedly gone away through scaling.
And so there's a picture that we're seeing supported
from biology and from our experience with AI
where you can explain like, yeah, in general,
there are trade-offs where the extra fitness you get
from a brain is not worth it.
And so creatures wind up mostly with small brains
because they can save that biological energy
and that time to reproduce for digestion.
And so on.
And humans, we actually seem to have wound up
in a niche within self-reinforcing
where we greatly increase the returns
to having large brains.
And language and technology are the sort of obvious candidates.
When you have humans around you
who know a lot of things and they can teach you
and compared to almost any other species,
we have vastly more instruction from parents
and the society of the young.
Then you're getting way more from your brain
because you can get, per minute,
you can learn a lot more useful skills
and then you can provide the energy you need
to feed that brain by hunting and gathering,
by having fire that makes digestion easier.
And basically how this process goes on,
it's increasing the marginal increase
in reproductive fitness you get
from allocating more resources
along a bunch of dimensions towards cognitive ability.
And so that's bigger brains, longer childhood,
having our attention be more on learning.
So humans play a lot and we keep playing as adults,
which is a very weird thing compared to other animals.
We're more motivated to copy other humans around us
than like even than the other primates.
And so these are sort of motivational changes
that keep us using more of our attention and effort
on learning, which pays off more
when you have a bigger brain and a longer lifespan
in which to learn.
Many creatures are subject to lots of predation or disease.
And so if you try, you're a mayfly or a mouse,
if you try and invest in like a giant brain
and a very long childhood,
you're quite likely to be killed by some predator
or some disease before you're able to actually use it.
And so that means you actually have exponentially
increasing costs in a given niche.
So if I have a 50% chance of dying every few months
of a little mammal or a little lizard or something,
that means the cost of going from three months to 30 months
of learning and childhood development,
it's not 10 times the loss.
It's now it's two to the negative 10.
So factor of 1,024 reduction in the benefit I get
from what I ultimately learn
because 99.9% of the animals will have been killed
before that point.
We're in a niche where we're like a large,
long-lived animal with language and technology.
So where we can learn a lot from our groups.
And that means it pays off to really just expand
our investment on these multiple fronts in intelligence.
That's so interesting.
Just with the audience, the calculation about like
two to the whatever months is just like,
you have a half chance of dying this month,
a half chance of dying next month,
you multiply those together.
Okay, there's other species though
that do live in flocks or as packs where you could imagine.
I mean, they do have like a smaller version
of the development of cubs into
that I like play with each other.
Why isn't this a hill on which they could have climbed
to human level intelligence themselves?
If it's something like language or technology,
humans were getting smarter before we got language.
I mean, obviously we had to get smarter
to get language, right?
We couldn't just get language without becoming smarter.
So yeah, it seems like there should be other species
that should have beginnings
of this sort of cognitive revolution,
especially given how valuable it is given,
listen, we've dominated the world.
You would think there'd be selective pressure for it.
Evolution doesn't have foresight.
The thing in this generation
that gets more surviving offspring and grandchildren,
that's the thing that becomes more common.
Evolution doesn't look ahead and they,
oh, in a million years, you'll have a lot of descendants.
It's what survives and reproduces now.
And so in fact, there are correlations
where social animals do on average, have larger brains.
And part of that is probably that
the additional social applications of brains,
like keeping track of which of your group members
have helped you before so that you can reciprocate.
You scratch my back, I'll scratch yours,
remembering who's dangerous within the group,
that sort of thing.
It's an additional application of intelligence.
And so there's some correlation there.
But what it seems like is that,
yeah, in most of these cases,
it's enough to invest more,
but not invest to the point where a mind
can easily develop language and technology and pass it on.
And so there are, you see bits of tool use
in some other primates who have an advantage that,
so compared to say the whales who have,
they have quite large brains,
partly because they are so large themselves
and they have some other thing,
but they don't have hands,
which means that reduces a bunch of ways
in which brains can pay off
and investments in the functioning of that brain.
But yeah, so primates will use sticks to extract termites.
Capuchin monkeys will open clams
by smashing them with a rock.
So there's bits of tool use,
but what they don't have is the ability to sustain culture.
A particular primate will maybe discover
one of these tactics and maybe it'll be copied
by their immediate group.
But they're not holding onto it that well.
They're like, well, when they see the other animal do it,
they can copy it in that situation.
They don't actively teach each other,
their population locally is quite small.
So it's easy to forget things,
easy to lose information.
And in fact, they remain technologically stagnant
for hundreds of thousands of years.
And we can actually look at some human situations.
So there's an old paper,
I believe by the economist, Michael Kramer,
talks about technological growth
in the different continents for human societies.
And so you have Eurasia is the largest integrated
connected area, Africa is partly connected to it,
but the Sahara desert restricts the flow
of information and technology and such.
And then you had the Americas,
which were after the colonization from the land bridge
were largely separated and are smaller than Eurasia.
Then Australia, and then you had like smaller island situations
like Tasmania.
And so technological progress seems to have been faster
at the larger, the connected group of people.
And in the smallest groups, so like in Tasmania,
you had a relatively small population
and they actually lost technology.
So things like they lost some like fishing techniques.
And if you have a small population
and you have some limited number of people who know a skill
and they happen to die or it happened,
there's like some change in circumstances
that causes people not to practice or pass on that thing.
And then you lose it.
And if you have few people, you're doing less innovation.
The rate at which you lose technologies
to some kind of local disturbance
and the rate at which you create new technologies
can wind up in balance.
And the great change of hominids and humanity
if that we wound up in this situation,
we were accumulating faster than we were losing.
And as we accumulated,
those technologies allowed us to expand our population.
They created additional demand for intelligence
so that our brains became three times as large.
Is that chimpanzees?
Chimpanzees, yeah.
And our ancestors who had a similar brain size.
And then the crucial point, I guess, in relevance to AI
is that the selective pressures against intelligence
in other animals are not acting against these neural networks
because we are, you know,
they're not gonna get like eaten by a predator
if they spend too much time becoming more intelligent.
We're like explicitly treating them
to become more intelligent.
So we have like good first principles reason to think
that if it was scaling that made our minds this powerful
and if the things that prevented other animals
from scaling are not impinging on these neural networks,
that these things should just continue
to become very smart.
Yeah, we're growing them in a technological culture
where there are jobs like software engineer
that depend much more on sort of cognitive output
and less on things like metabolic resources
devoted to the immune system
or to like building big muscles to throw spears.
This is kind of a side note, but I'm just kind of interested.
I think you referenced at some point,
I think it's a bit of a chinchilla scaling for the audience.
This is a paper from DeepMind which describes
if you have a model of a certain size,
what is the optimum amount of data
that it should be trained on?
So you can imagine bigger models,
you can use more data to train them.
And in this way you can figure out
where should you spend your computer,
should you spend it on making the model bigger
or should you spend it on training it for longer?
I'm curious if in the case of different animals,
in some sense they're like model sizes,
they're how big their brain is
and they're training data sizes,
like how long they're cubs
or how long they're infants or toddlers
or before they're full adults.
Is there some sort of like scaling law of?
Yeah, I mean, so the chinchilla scaling isn't interesting
because we were talking earlier about the cost function
for having a longer childhood.
And so where it's like exponentially increasing
in the amount of training compute you have
when you have exogenous forces that can kill you.
Whereas when we do big training runs,
the cost of throwing in more GPUs is almost linear.
And it's much better to be linear
than exponentially decay.
Oh, that's a really good point.
As you expand resources.
And so chinchilla scaling would suggest that like,
yeah, for a brain of sort of human size,
it would be optimal to have many millions of years
of education, but obviously that's impractical
because of exogenous mortality for humans.
And so there's a fairly compelling argument
that relative to the situation where we would train AI,
that animals are systematically way under trained.
That's so interesting.
And now they're more efficient than our models.
We still have room to improve our algorithms
to catch up with the efficiency of brains,
but they are laboring under that disadvantage, yeah.
That is so interesting.
Okay, so I guess another question you could have
is humans got started on this evolutionary hill climbing
route where we're getting more intelligent
that has more benefits for us.
Why didn't we go all the way on that route?
If intelligence is so powerful,
why aren't all humans as smart as we know humans can be?
At least that smart.
If intelligence is so powerful,
like why hasn't there been stronger selective pressure?
I understand like, oh, listen, hip size,
you can't like give birth to a really big headed baby
or whatever, but you would think
evolution would figure out some way to offset
that if intelligence has such big power
and it's so useful.
Yeah, I think if you actually look at it quantitatively,
that's not true.
And even in sort of recent history,
there has been, it looks like a pretty close balance
between the costs and the benefits
of having more cognitive abilities.
And so you say like, who needs to worry
about like the metabolic costs?
Like humans put like order 20% of our metabolic energy
into the brain and it's higher for like young children.
So 20% of the, and then there's like breathing
and digestion and the immune system.
And so for most of history,
people have been dying left and right.
Like a very large proportion of people
will die of infectious disease.
And if you put more resources into your immune system,
you survive.
So it's like life or death pretty directly
via that mechanism.
And then this is related also
people die more of disease during famine.
And so there's boom or bust.
And so if you have 20% less metabolic requirements
or has anger a child and if you have a lot more,
I mean it's like 40 or 50% less metabolic requirements,
you're much more likely to survive that famine.
So these are pretty big.
And then there's a trade-off
about just cleaning and mutational load.
So every generation new mutations and errors happen
in the process of reproduction.
And so like we know there are many genetic abnormalities
that occur through new mutations each generation.
And in fact, we have Down syndrome
is the chromosomal abnormality that you can survive.
All the others just kill the embryo.
And so we never see them.
But like Down syndrome occurs a lot.
And there are many other lethal mutations
and as you go to the less damaging ones,
there are enormous numbers of less damaging mutations
that are degrading every system in the body.
And so evolution each generation has to pull away
at some of this mutational load.
And the priority with which that mutational load
is pulled out scales in proportion
to how much the traits it's affecting impact fitness.
So you got new mutations that impact your resistance
to malaria, you got new mutations
that damage brain function.
And then have those mutations are purged each generation.
If malaria is a bigger difference in mortality
than like the incremental effectiveness
of hunter-gatherer you get from being slightly more intelligent
then you'll purge that mutational load first.
And similarly, if there's like,
humans have been vigorously adapting to new circumstances.
So since agriculture, people have been developing things
like the ability to have amulets to digest breads,
the ability to like digest milk.
And if you're evolving for all of these things
and if some of the things that give an advantage for that
incidentally carry along nearby them
some negative effect on another trait
then that other trait can be damaged.
So it really matters how important to survival
and reproduction cognitive abilities were
compared to everything else that organism has to do.
And that in particular like surviving, feasting famine,
having like the physical abilities
to do hunting and gathering.
And like, even if you're like very good
at planning your hunting,
being able to throw a spear harder
can be a big difference.
And that needs energy to build those muscles
and then to sustain them.
And so given all of these factors,
it's like, yeah, it's not a slam dunk
to invest at the merge.
And like today, like having bigger brains,
for example, it's associated
with like greater cognitive ability,
but it's like, it's modest.
Large scale pre-registered studies,
pre-registered studies with MRI data.
It's like a range, maybe like a correlation of 0.25, 0.3
and the standard deviation of brain size is like 10%.
So if you double the size of the brain,
so go and the existing brain costs
like 20% of metabolic energy, go up to 40%.
Okay, that's like eight standard deviations of brain size.
If the correlation is like, say it's 0.25,
then yeah, like you get a gain from that.
Eight standard deviations of brain size,
two standard deviations of cognitive ability.
And like in our modern society
where cognitive ability is very rewarded
and like finishing school, becoming an engineer
or a doctor or whatever can pay off a lot financially.
Still the like, the average observed return
in like income is like a one or 2% proportional increase.
There's more effects of the tail,
there's more effect in professions like STEM.
But on the whole, it's not like,
if it was like a 5% increase or a 10% increase,
then you could tell a story where,
yeah, this is hugely increasing
the amount of food you could have,
you could support more children,
but it's like, it's a modest effect
and the metabolic costs will be large
and then throw in these other aspects.
And I think it's, you can tell the story else,
we can just, we can see there was not very strong,
rapid directional selection on the thing,
which there would be if like, you could,
by solving like a math puzzle, you could defeat malaria.
Like then there would be more evolutionary pressure.
That is so interesting.
And not to mention, of course,
that yeah, if you had like 2x the brain size
or you were without C-section,
you would, you or your mother would or both would die.
This is a question I've actually been curious about
for like over a year.
And I like briefly try to look up an answer.
This is, I know this is off topic,
but I apologize to the audience,
but I was super interested in those like,
those like the most comprehensive
and interesting answer I could have hoped for.
Okay, so yeah, we have a good explanation
for good first principles, evolutionary reason
for thinking that intelligence scaling up to humans
is not implausible just by throwing more scale at it.
I would also add,
this was something that would have mattered to me more
in the 2000s.
We also have the brain right here with us
for available for neuroscience
to reverse engineer its property.
And so in the 2000s, when I said, yeah,
I expect this by, you know, middle of the century ish.
That was a backstop.
If we found it absurdly difficult to get to the algorithms
and then we would learn from neuroscience,
but in the actual history, it's really not like that.
We develop things in AI.
And then also we can say, oh yeah,
this is sort of like this thing in neuroscience
or maybe this is a good explanation.
But it's not as though neuroscience
is driving AI progress.
It turns out not to be that necessary.
As similar to, I guess, you know, how planes were inspired
by the existence proof of birds,
but jet engines don't flap.
All right, so yeah, scaling,
good reason to think scaling might work.
So we spend $100 billion and we have something
that is like human level or can do help significantly
with AI research.
I mean, that might be on the earlier end,
but I mean, I definitely would not rule that out
given the rates of change we've seen
with the last few scale-ups.
All right, so at this point, somebody might be skeptical.
Okay, like listen,
we already have a bunch of human researchers, right?
Like the incremental researcher, how profitable is that?
And then you might say, well, no,
this is like thousands of researchers.
I don't know how to express a skepticism exactly,
but skepticism is skeptical of just generally
the effect of scaling up the number of people
working on the problem to rapid,
rapid progress on that problem.
Somebody might think, okay, listen,
with humans, the reason population working on a problem
is such a good proxy for progress on the problem
is that there's already so much variation
that is accounted for when you say
there's like a million people working on a problem.
You know, there's like hundreds of super geniuses
working on it, thousands of people
who are like very smart working on it.
Whereas with an AI, all the copies
are like the same level of intelligence.
And if it's not super genius intelligence,
the total quantity might not matter as much.
Yeah, I'm not sure what your model is here.
So is this a model that the diminishing returns kick off
suddenly has a cliff right where we are?
And so like there was, there were results in the past
from throwing more people at problems.
And I mean, this has been useful in historical prediction.
One of the, there's this idea of experience curves
and Wright's law basically measuring cumulative production
in a field or which is that also gonna be a measure
of like the scale of effort and investment.
And people have used this correctly to argue
that renewable energy technology like solar
would be falling rapidly in price
because it was going from a low base
of very small production runs,
not much investment in doing it efficiently.
And yeah, climate advocates correctly called out
people and people like David Roberts,
the futurist Rama is now actually has some interesting
writing on this that yeah, correctly called out
that there would be really drastic fall in prices
of solar and batteries
because of the increasing investment going into that.
The human genome project would be another.
So I'd say there's like, yeah, real, real evidence.
These observed correlations from like ideas,
getting harder to find have held over a fair range of data
and over quite a lot of time.
So I'm wondering what's the nature of the deviation
you're thinking of?
That we're talking about, maybe this is like a good way
to describe what happens when more humans enter a field.
But does it even make sense to say
like a greater population of AIs is doing AI research
if there's like more GPUs running a copy of GPT-6
doing AI research?
It just like how applicable are these economic models
of human, the quantity of humans working on a problem
to the magnitude of AIs working on a problem?
Yeah, so if you have AIs that are directly automating
particular jobs that humans were doing before,
then we say, well, with additional compute
we can run more copies of them
to do more of those tasks simultaneously.
We can also run them at greater speed.
And so some people have an intuition that like,
well, you know, what matters is like time.
It's not how many people working on problem
at a given point.
I think that doesn't bear out super well,
but AI can also be run faster than humans.
And so if you have a set of AIs that can do the work
of the individual human researchers
and run at 10 times or 100 times the speed,
then we ask, well, could the human research community
have solved the algorithm problems,
do things like invent transformers over 100 years
if we have this?
We have AIs with a population,
effective population similar to the humans,
but running 100 times as fast.
And so you have to tell a story where no,
the AI, they can't really do the same things
as the humans.
And we're talking about what happens
when the AIs are more capable of in fact doing that.
Although they become more capable
as lesser capable versions of themselves help us,
make themselves more capable, right?
So you have to like kickstart that at some point.
Is there an example in analogous situations,
is intelligence unique in the sense that you have
a feedback loop of with a learning curve
or something else, a system outputs,
are feeding into its own inputs in a way that,
because if we're talking about something like Moore's Law
or the cost of solar, you do have this way,
like we're, you know, more people are,
we're throwing more people with the problem
and it's, we're, you know, we're making a lot of progress,
but we don't have the sort of additional part of the model
where Moore's Law leads to more humans somehow
and the more humans are becoming researchers.
So you do actually have a version of that
in the case of solar.
So you have a small infant industry
that's doing things like providing solar panels
for space satellites and then getting increasing amounts
of subsidized government demand because of, you know,
worries about fossil fuel depletion
and then climate change.
You can have the dynamic where visible successes
with solar or like lowering prices
then open up new markets.
So there's a particularly huge transition
where renewables become cheap enough
to replace large chunks of the electric grid.
Earlier, you're dealing with very niche situations like,
yeah, so the satellites where you have very difficult
to refuel a satellite in place and then remote areas
and then moving to like, you know,
the super sunny, the sunniest areas in the world
with the biggest solar subsidies.
And so there was an element of that
where more and more investment has been thrown
into the field and like the market has rapidly expanded
as the technology improved.
But I think the closest analogy is actually
the long run growth of human civilization itself.
And I know you had Holden Karnofsky
from the open philanthropy project on earlier
and discuss some of this research
about the long run acceleration of human population
and economic growth.
And so developing new technologies
allowed human population to expand,
humans to occupy new habitats and new areas
and then to invent agriculture
which support the larger populations
and then even more advanced agriculture
in the modern industrial society.
And so their total technology and output
allowed you to support more humans
who then would discover more technology
and continue the process.
Now that was boosted because on top of expanding
the population, the share of human activity
that was going into invention and innovation went up.
And that was a key part of the industrial revolution.
There was no such thing as a corporate research lab
or like an engineering university prior to that.
And so you're both increasing the total human population
and the share of it going in.
But this population dynamic is pretty analogous.
Humans invent farming, they can have more humans
than they can invent industry and so on.
So maybe somebody would be skeptical
that with AI progress specifically,
it's not just a matter of some farmer
figuring out crop rotation or some blacksmith
figuring out how to do metal or do better.
You in fact, even to make the,
for the 50% improvement in productivity,
you basically need something on the IQ
that's close to Ilya Setskoper.
There's like a discontinuous,
you're like contributing very little to productivity
and then you're like Ilya and then you contribute a lot.
But the becoming Ilya is, you see what I'm saying?
There's not like a gradual increase in capabilities
that leads to the feedback.
You're imagining a case where the distribution of tasks
is such that there's nothing that you can,
where individually automating it particularly helps.
And so the ability to contribute to AI research
is really end loaded.
Is that what you're saying?
Yeah, I mean, we already see this in these sorts
of like really high IQ companies or projects
where theoretically, I guess,
Shane Street or OpenAI could hire like a bunch of,
mediocre people to do, there's a comparative advantage.
They could do some menial tasks
and that could free up the time of the really smart people,
but they don't do that, right?
Transaction costs, whatever else.
Self-driven cars would be another example
where you have a very high quality threshold.
And so when your performance as a driver
is worse than a human,
like you have 10 times the accident rate
or 100 times the accident rate,
then the cost of insurance for that,
which is a proxy for people's willingness
to ride the car instead of two,
would be such that the insurance costs
would absolutely dominate.
So even if you have zero labor cost,
it's offset by the increased insurance cost.
And so there are lots of cases like that
where like partial automation is not in practice
very usable because complimenting other resources,
you're gonna use those other resources less efficiently.
And in a post-AGI future,
I mean, the same thing can apply to humans.
So people can say, well, comparative advantage,
even if AIs can do everything better than a human,
well, it's still worth something.
The human can do something,
they can lift a box, that's something.
Now there's a question of property rights,
if, well, if they could just slice up the human
to make more robots.
But even absent that in such an economy,
you wouldn't want to let a human worker
into any industrial environment,
because in a clean room,
they'll be emitting all kinds of skin cells
and messing things up.
You need to have an atmosphere there.
You need a bunch of supporting tools
and resources and materials.
And those supporting resources and materials
will do a lot more productively,
working with AI and robots rather than a human.
So you don't wanna let a human anywhere near the thing,
just like in a, you don't wanna have a gorilla
wandering around in a China shop.
Even if you've trained it to most of the time,
pick up a box for you if you give it a banana,
it's just not worth it to have it wandering
around your China shop.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Like why is that not a good objection to?
I mean, I think that is one of the ways
in which partial automation can fail
to really translate into a lot of economic value.
That's something that will attenuate as we go on.
And as the AI is more able to work independently
and more able to handle its own,
its own screw ups, get more reliable.
But the way in which it becomes more reliable
is by AI progress speeding up,
which happens if AI can contribute to it.
But if there is some sort of reliability bottleneck,
the principle of contributing to that progress,
then you don't have the loop, right?
So, yeah, I mean, this is why we're not there yet.
Right, but then what is the reason to think we'll be there at?
The broad reason is we have these inputs are scaling up.
There's a, so Epoch, which I mentioned earlier,
they have a paper, I think it's called compute trends
in three areas of machine learning or something like that.
And so they look at the compute expended
on machine learning systems
since the founding of the field of AI
at the beginning of the 1950s.
And so it mostly, it grows with Moore's law.
And so people are spending a similar amount
on their experiments, but they can just buy Moore with that
because the compute is coming.
And so that data, I mean, it covers over 20 orders
of magnitude, maybe like 24.
And of all of those increases since 1952,
a little more than half of them happened between 1952 and 2010.
And all the rest is since 2010.
So we've been scaling that up like four times as fast
as was the case for most of the history of AI.
We're running through the orders of magnitude
of possible resource inputs you could need for AI
much, much more quickly than we were
for most of the history of AI.
That's why this is a period of like
with a very elevated chance of AI per year
because we're moving through.
So much of the space of inputs per year.
And indeed, it looks like this scale up
taken to its conclusion will cover another bunch
of orders of magnitude.
And that's actually a large fraction of those that are left
before you start running into saying, well,
this is gonna have to be like evolution
with the sort of simple hacks we get to apply.
Like we're selecting for intelligence the whole time.
We're not going to do the same mutation
that causes fatal childhood cancer a billion times.
Even though, I mean, we keep getting the same fatal mutations
even though they've been done many times.
We use gradient descent, which takes into account
the derivative of improvement on the loss
all throughout the network.
And we don't throw away all the contents of the network
with each generation where you can press down
to a little DNA.
So there's that bar of like, well,
if you're gonna do brute force like evolution
combine with these sort of very simple ways
we can save orders of magnitude on that.
We're gonna cover, I think, a fraction
that's like half of that distance in this scale
up over the next 10 years or so.
And so if you started off with a kind of vague uniform prior,
you're like, well, you probably can't make AGI
with like the amount of compute that would be involved
in a fruit fly existing for a minute,
which would be the early days of AI.
You know, maybe you would get lucky.
We were able to make calculators
because calculators benefited
from like very reliable, serially fast computers
and where we could take a tiny, tiny, tiny, tiny fraction
of a human brain's compute and use it for a calculator.
We couldn't take an ant's brain and rewire it to calculate.
It's hard to manage ant farms, let alone get them
to do arithmetic for you.
And so there were some things where we could exploit
the differences between biological brains and computers
to do stuff super efficiently on computers.
We would doubt that we would be able
to do so much better than biology,
that with a tiny fraction of an insect's brain,
we'd be able to get AI early on.
On the far end, it seemed very implausible
that we couldn't do better
than completely brute force evolution.
And so in between, you have some number
of orders of magnitude of inputs where it might be.
And like in the 2000s, I would say,
well, you know, I'm gonna have a pretty uniformish prior.
I'm gonna put weight on it happening at like the sort
of the equivalent of like 10 to the 25 ops,
10 to the 30, 10 to the 35,
and sort of spreading out over that.
And then I can update on other information.
And in the short term, I would say like in 2005, I would say,
well, I don't see anything that looks
like the cusp of AGI.
So I'm also gonna lower my credence
for like the next five years or the next 10 years.
And so that would be kind of like a vague prior.
And then when we take into account like, well,
how quickly are we running through
those orders of magnitude?
If I have a uniform prior, I assign half of my weight
to the first half of remaining orders of magnitude.
And if we're gonna run through those
over the next 10 years in some,
then that calls on me to put half of my credence
conditional on wherever we're gonna make it.
AI, which seems likely it's a material object
easier than evolution.
I've got to put similarly a lot of my credence
on AI happening in this scale up.
And then that's supported by what we're seeing
in terms of the rapid advances in capabilities
with AI and LLOMs in particular.
Okay, that's actually a really interesting point.
So now that somebody might say, listen,
there's not some sense in which AIs could universally
speed up the progress of open AI by 50%
or 100% or 200%.
If they're not able to do everything better
than Ilias Escobar can,
there's going to be something in which we're bottlenecked
by the human researchers.
And bottleneck effects dictate that,
the slowest moving part of the organization
will be the one that kind of determines the speed
of the progress of the whole organization
or the whole project.
Which means that unless you get to the point
where you're like doing everything
and everybody in the organization can do,
you're not going to significantly speed up
the progress of the whole project as a whole.
Yeah, so that is a hypothesis.
And I think there's a lot of truth to it.
So when we think about like the ways
in which AI can contribute.
So there are things we talked about before,
like the AIs setting up their own curriculum.
And that's something that Ilya can't do directly
doesn't do directly.
And there's a question,
how much does that improve performance?
There are these things where the AI helps
to just like produce some code for some tasks.
And it's beyond Hello World at this point.
But I mean, the sort of thing that I hear
from AI researchers at leading labs is that,
on their core job where they're like most expert,
it's not helping them that much,
but then their job often does involve,
oh, I've got to code something
that's out of my usual area of expertise.
Or I want to research this question and it helps them there.
And so that saves some of their time
and frees them to do more of the bottleneck work.
And then I think the idea of, well,
is everything dependent on Ilya and is Ilya
so much better than the hundreds of other employees?
I think a lot of people who are contributing,
they're doing a lot of tasks.
And so you can have quite a lot of gain
from automating some areas
where you then do just an absolutely enormous amount of it
relative to what you would have done before
because things like designing the custom curriculum,
you're like, maybe had some humans put some work into that,
but you're not going to employ billions of humans
to produce it at scale.
And so it winds up being a larger share of the progress
than it was before.
You get some benefit from these sorts of things
where, yeah, there's like pieces of my job
that now I can hand off to the AI
and let's me focus more on the things
that the AI still can't do.
And then at the later on, you get to the point where,
yeah, the AI can do your job,
including the most difficult parts.
And maybe it has to do that in a different way.
Maybe it like spends a ton more time thinking about
each step of a problem than you, and that's the late end.
And the stronger these bottlenecks effects are,
the more the economic returns, the scientific returns
and such are end loaded towards getting sort of full AGI.
The weaker the bottlenecks are,
the more interim results will be really paying off.
I guess I'd probably disagree with you on how much
the sort of the alias of organizations seem to matter.
I guess just from the evidence alone,
like how many of the big sort of breakthroughs
that in deep learning in general was like
that single individual responsible for, right?
And how much of his time is he spending
doing anything that's not that like co-pilot
is helping him on?
I'm guessing like most of it is just like managing people
and coming up with ideas and, you know,
trying to like understand systems and so on.
And if that is the, if like the five or 10 people
who are like that at OpenAI or Anthropa or whatever
are basically the way in which the progress is happening
or at least the algorithmic progress is happening,
then how much of better and better co-pilot,
I know co-pilot is not the thing you're talking about
with like the 20% automation, but something like that,
how much of, yeah, how much is that contributing
to the sort of like core function of the research scientist?
Yeah.
Naturally quantitatively, how much we disagree
about the importance of sort of key research employees
and such, I certainly think that some researchers,
you know, add, you know, more than 10 times
the average employee even much more.
And obviously managers can add an enormous amount of value
by proportionately multiplying the output
of the many people that they manage.
And so that's the kind of thing
that we were discussing earlier when talking about,
well, if you had sort of full human level AI
or AI that had all of the human capabilities
plus AI advantages, it would be, you know,
you'd benchmark not off of what the sort of typical
human performance is, but peak human performance and beyond.
So yeah, I accept all that.
I do think it makes a big difference for people
how much they can outsource a lot of the death
that are less, wow, less creative.
And an enormous amount is learned by experimentation.
ML has been, you know, a quite experimental field.
And there's a lot of engineering work
in say building large super clusters,
making, yeah, hardware aware optimization
and coding of these things,
being able to do the parallelism in large models.
And the engineers are busy
and it's not just only a big thoughts kind of area.
And then the other branch is where will the AI advantages
and disadvantages be?
And so one AI advantage is being omnidisciplinary
and familiar with the newest things.
So I mentioned before, there's no human
who has a million years of TensorFlow experience.
And so to the extent that we're interested
in like the very, very cutting edge
of things that have been developed quite recently
than AI that can learn about them in parallel
and experiment and practice with them in parallel
can learn much faster than a human potentially.
And the area of computer science is one
that is especially suitable for AI
to learn in a digital environment.
So it doesn't require like driving a car around
that might kill someone, have enormous costs.
You can do unit tests, you can prove theorems,
you can do all sorts of operations
entirely in the confines of a computer.
And which is one reason why programming
has been benefiting more than a lot of other areas
from LLMs recently, whereas robotics is lagging.
So the sum of that.
And then just considering, well,
actually I mean, they are getting better
at things like the GRE math at programming contests.
And I mean, some people have forecasts
and predictions outstanding about things like
doing well on the Informatics Olympiad
and the Math Olympiad.
And in the last few years, when people tried
to forecast the MMLU benchmark,
which was having a lot of more sophisticated
kind of like graduate student science kind of questions.
Yeah, AI knocked that down a lot faster
than AI researchers who had registered
and students who had registered forecasts on it.
And so if you're getting top-notch scores
on graduate exams, creative problem solving,
yeah, it's not obvious that that sort of area
will be a relative weakness of AI.
That in fact, computer science is in many ways,
especially suitable because of getting up to speed
with new areas, being able to get rapid feedback
from the interpreter at scale.
But did you get rapid feedback?
If you're doing that, something that's more analogous
to research, if you're like,
let's say you have a new model or something.
And it's like, if we put in $10 million
on a mini-training run on this, this would be a much bit.
Yeah, for very large models,
those experiments are gonna be quite expensive.
And so you're gonna look more at like,
can you build up this capability by generalization
from things like many math problems,
programming problems, working with small networks?
Yeah, yeah, fair enough.
I actually, Scott Aaronson was one of my professors
in college and I took his quantum information class
and I didn't do, I did okay in it,
but he recently wrote a blog post where he said,
I had GBD-4 take my quantum information test
and it got a B.
And I was like, damn, I got a C on the final.
So yeah, yeah, I'm updated in the direction that,
you know, it seems, getting a B on the test,
like you probably understand quantum information
pretty well.
With different areas of strengths and weaknesses
than the human students.
Sure, sure.
Would it be possible for this sort of intelligence
explosion to happen without any sort of hardware progress
if hardware progress stopped?
Would this feedback loop still be able to produce
some sort of explosion with only software?
Yeah, so if we say that the technology is frozen,
which I think is not the case right now,
the, you know, NVIDIA has managed to deliver
significantly better chips for AI workloads
for the last few generations, H100, A100, V100.
If that stops entirely, then what you're left with,
maybe we'll define this as like no more nodes,
more as a lot is over.
At that point, the kind of gains you get
in amount of compute available come from actually
constructing more chips.
And there are economies of scale
you could still realize there.
So right now, a chip maker has to amortize the R&D cost
of developing the chip.
And then the capital equipment is created,
like you build a fab, its peak profits are gonna come
in the few years when the chips it's making
are at the cutting edge.
Later on, as the cost of compute exponentially falls,
the, you know, you keep the fab open
because you can still make some money
given that it's built, but of all of the profits
the fab will ever make right now,
they're relatively front loaded
because when its technology is near the cutting edge.
So in a world where Moore's law ends,
then you wind up with these very long production runs.
Where you can keep making chips
that stay at the cutting edge
and where the R&D costs get amortized
over a much larger base.
So the R&D basically drops out of the price.
And then you get some economies of scale
from just making so many fabs in the way that,
you know, when we have the auto industry expands
and then this is in general across industries
when you produce a lot more costs fall
because you have right now, like ASML has many,
you know, incredibly exotic suppliers
that make some bizarre part of the thousands of parts
in one of these ASML machines.
You can't get it anywhere else.
They don't have standardized equipment for their thing
because this is the only, only use for it.
And in a world where we're making 10, 100 times
as many chips at the current node,
then they would benefit from scale economies.
And all of that would become more mass production
industrialized.
And so you combine all of those things
and it seems like capital costs
of like buying a chip would decline,
but the energy costs of running the chip would not.
And so right now, energy costs are a minority of the cost,
but they're not, they're not, they're not trivial.
You know, they pass, yeah, it passed 1% a while ago
and they're inching up towards 10% and beyond.
And so you can maybe get like another order of magnitude
costs decrease from getting really efficient
in the sort of capital construction,
but like energy would still be a limiting factor
after the end of sort of actually improving
the chips themselves.
Got it, got it.
And when you say like,
there would be a greater population of AI researchers
because are we using population as a sort of thinking tool
of how they could be more effective?
Or do you literally mean that the way you expect
these AIs to contribute a lot to researchers
by just having like a million copies
of this, of like a researcher thinking about the same problem?
Or is it just like a useful thinking model
for what it would look like to have a million times
smarter AI working on that problem?
That's definitely a lower bound sort of model.
And often I'm meaning something more like
effective population or like you'd need this many people
to have this effect.
And so we were talking earlier about the trade off
between training and inference in board games.
And so you can get the same performance
by having a bigger model
or by calling the model more times.
And in general, it's more effective
to have a bigger, smarter model
and call it less timed up until the point
where the costs equalized between them.
And so we would be taking some of the gains
of our larger compute on having bigger models
that are individually more capable.
And there would be a division of labor.
So like the tasks that were most cognitively demanding
would be done by these giant models,
but some very easy tasks.
You don't want to expend that giant model
if a model 100s the size can take that task.
And so larger models would be in the positions
of like researchers and managers
and they would have swarms of AIs of different sizes
as tools that they could make API calls to and whatnot.
Okay, we accept the model
and now we've gone to something that is at least as smart
as Ilya Suskova on all the tasks relevant to AI progress.
And you can have so many copies of it.
What happens in the world now?
What are the next months or years
or whatever timeline is relevant to look like?
And so, and to be clear with what's happened is not
that we have something that has all of the abilities
and advantages of humans plus the AI advantages.
What we have is something that is like possibly
by doing things like doing a ton of calls
to make up for being individually less capable or something.
It's able to drive forward AI progress.
That process is continuing.
So AI progress has accelerated greatly
in the course of getting there.
And so maybe we go from our eight months doubling time
of software progress in effective compute
to four months or two months.
And so, so there's a report by Tom Davidson
at the Open Philanthropy Project,
which spun out of work I had done previously.
And so I advised and helped with that project
but Tom really carried it forward
and produced a very nice report and model
which Epoch is hosting.
You can plug in your own version of the parameters
and there's a lot of work estimating the parameter.
Things like what's the rate of software progress?
What's the return to additional work?
How does performance scale at these tasks
as you boost the models?
And in general, as we were discussing earlier,
these sort of like broadly human level in every domain
with all the advantages is pretty deep into that.
And so if already we can have an eight months doubling time
for software progress, then by the time you get
to that kind of point, it's maybe more like four months,
two months going into one month.
And so if the thing is just proceeding at full speed,
then each doubling can come more rapidly.
And so we can talk about what are the spillovers of like,
so how does the models get more capable?
They can be doing other stuff in the world.
They can spend some of their time
making Google search more efficient.
They can be hired, has chatbots with some inference compute.
And then we can talk about sort of
if that intelligence explosion process
is allowed to proceed, then what happens is,
okay, you improve your software by a factor of two,
the demand, the efforts needed to get the next doubling
are larger, but they're not choices large.
Maybe they're like 25%, 35% larger.
So each one comes faster and faster
until you hit limitations.
Like you can no longer make further software advances
with the hardware that you have.
And looking at, I think, reasonable parameters
in that model, it seems to me,
if you have these giant training runs,
you can go very far.
And so the way I would see this playing out
is how does the AIs get better and better at research?
They can work on different problems.
They can work on improving software.
They can work on improving hardware.
They can do things like create new industrial technologies,
new energy technology.
They can manage robots.
They can manage human workers
as like executives and coaches and whatnot.
You can do all of these things.
And AIs wind up being applied where the returns are highest.
And I think initially the returns are especially high
in doing more software.
And the reason for that is again,
if you improve the software,
you can update all of the GPUs
that you have access to your cloud compute
is suddenly more potent.
If you design a new chip design,
it'll take a few months to produce the first ones
and it doesn't update all of your old chips.
So you have an ordering where you start off
with the things where there's the lowest dependence
on existing stocks.
And you can more just take whatever you're developing
and apply it immediately.
And so software runs ahead.
You're getting more towards the limits of that software.
And I think that means things like
having all the human advantages
but combined with AI advantages.
And so I think that means given the kind of compute
that would be involved,
if we're talking about this hundreds of billions
of trillion dollar training run,
there's enough compute to run tens of millions,
hundreds of millions of sort of like human scale minds.
They're probably smaller than human scale
to be like similarly efficient at the limits
of algorithmic progress
because they have the advantage
of a million years of education.
They have the other advantages we talked about.
So you've got that wild capability
and further software gains are running out.
Or like they start to slow down again
because you're just getting towards the limits
of like you can't do any better than the best.
And so what happens then?
Yeah, by the time they're running out,
have we already hit superintelligence or?
Yes, you're wildly superintelligent.
We love the galaxy, okay, metaphorically.
Just by having the abilities that humans have
and then combining it with being very well focused
and trained in the task beyond what any human could be
and then running faster and such.
Got it, got it.
All right, so I continue.
Yeah, so I'm not gonna assume
that there's like huge qualitative improvements you can have.
I'm not gonna assume that humans are like very far
from the efficient frontier of software,
except with respect to things like,
yeah, we had limited lifespan
so we couldn't train super intensively.
We couldn't incorporate other software into our brains.
We couldn't copy ourselves.
We couldn't run at fast speeds.
Yeah, so you've got all of those capabilities.
And now I'm skipping ahead of like the most important months
in human history.
And so I can talk about sort of,
what it looks like if it's just the AIs took over,
they're running things that they like, how do things expand?
I can talk about things has,
how does this go in a world where we've roughly
or at least so far managed to retain control
of where these systems are going?
And so by jumping ahead,
I can talk about how would this translate
into the physical world?
And so this is something that I think is a stopping point
for a lot of people in thinking about,
well, what would an intelligence explosion look like?
And they have trouble going from,
well, there's stuff on servers and cloud compute
and oh, that gets very smart.
But then how does what I see in the world change?
How does like industry or military power change?
If there's an AI takeover, like what does that look like?
Are there killer robots?
And so yeah, so one course we might go down
is to discuss during that wildly accelerating transition,
how did we manage that?
How do you avoid it being catastrophic?
And another route we could go is how does the translation
from wildly expanded scientific R&D capabilities intelligence
on these servers translate into things in the physical world?
So you're moving along in order of like,
what has the quickest impact largely
or like where you can have an immediate change?
So one of the most immediately accessible things
is where we have large numbers of devices
or artifacts or capabilities that are already AI operable
with hundreds of millions equivalent researchers,
you can like quickly solve self-driving cars,
you make the algorithms much more efficient,
do great testing and simulation
and then operate a large number of cars in parallel
if you need to get some additional data
to improve the simulation and reasoning.
Although, in fact, humans with quite little data
are able to achieve human level driving performance.
So after you've really maxed out
the easily accessible algorithmic improvements
in this software based intelligence explosion
that's mostly happening on server farms,
then you have minds that have been able to really perform
on a lot of digital only tasks that they're doing great
on video games, they're doing great at predicting
what happens next in a YouTube video.
If you have a camera that they can move,
they're able to predict what will happen
at different angles, humans do this a lot
where we naturally move our eyes in such a way
to get images from different angles
and different presentations
and then predicting combined from that.
And yeah, and you can operate many cars,
many robots at once to get very good robot controllers.
So you should think that all the existing robotic equipment
or remotely controllable equipment that is wired for that,
the AI's can operate that quite well.
I think some people might be skeptical
that existing robots, given their current hardware,
have the dexterity and the maneuverability
to do a lot of physical labor
that any AI might want to do.
Do you have reason for thinking otherwise?
There's also not very many of them.
So production of sort of industrial robots
is hundreds of thousands per year.
They can do quite a bit in place.
Eveline Musk is promising a robot
in the tens of thousands of,
humanoid robot in the tens of thousands of dollars,
that may take a lot longer than he has said.
Has this happened with other technologies?
But I mean, that's a direction to go.
But most immediately,
so hands are actually probably the most scarce thing.
But if we consider what do human bodies provide?
So there's the brain.
And in this situation,
we have now an abundance of high quality brain power
that will be increasing,
as the AI's will have designed new chips,
which will be rolling out from the TSMC factories,
and they'll have ideas and designs
for the production of new fab technologies,
new nodes and additional fabs.
But yeah, looking around the body.
So there's legs to move around.
Not only that necessary,
wheels work pretty well being in a place.
You don't need most people most of the time
in factory jobs and office jobs.
Office jobs, many of them can be fully virtualized.
But yeah, some amount of legs, wheels, other transport,
you have hands and hands are something that are,
on the expensive end in robots, we can make them.
They're made in very small production runs,
partly because we don't have the control software
to use them well.
In this world, the control software is fabulous,
and so people will produce much larger production runs
of them over time, possibly using technology
we recognize possibly with quite different technology,
but just taking what we've got.
So right now, the robot arm industry,
the industrial robot industry produces
hundreds of thousands of machines a year.
Some of the nicer ones are like $50,000.
In aggregate, the industry has tens of billions
of dollars of revenue.
By comparison, the automobile industry produces
like I think over 60 million cars a year.
It has revenue of over $2 trillion per annum.
And so converting that production capacity
over towards robot production would be one of the things,
if they're not something better to do,
would be one of the things to do.
And in World War II, industrial conversion
of American industry took place over several years
and really amazingly ramped up military production
by converting existing civilian industry.
And that was without the aid of superhuman intelligence
and management at every step in the process.
So yeah, every part of that would be very well designed.
You'd have AI workers who understood,
stood every part of the process
and could direct human workers.
Even in a fancy factory, most of the time,
it's not the hands doing a physical motion
that a worker is being paid for.
They're often like looking at things
or like deciding what to change.
The actual, the time spent in manual motion
is a limited portion of that.
And so in this world of abundant AI cognitive abilities
where the human workers are more valuable
for their hands than their heads,
then you could have a worker,
even a worker previously without training
and expertise in the area who has a smartphone,
maybe a smartphone on a headset.
And we have billions of smartphones,
which have eyes and ears and methods for communication,
for an AI to be talking to a human
and directing them in their physical motions
with skill as a guide and coach that is beyond any human.
There could be a lot better at telepresence and remote work
and they can provide VR and augmented reality guidance
as to help people get better at doing the physical motions
that they're providing in the construction.
Say you convert the auto industry to robot production.
If it can produce an amount of mass of machines
that is similar to what it currently produces,
that's enough for billion human size robots a year.
The value per kilogram of cars is somewhat less
than high-end robots,
but yeah, you're also cutting out most of the wage bill,
because most of the wage bill is payments ultimately
to like human capital and education,
not to the physical hand motions and lifting objects
and that sort of task.
Yeah, so at the sort of existing scale of the auto industry,
you can make a billion robots a year.
The auto industry is two or 3% of the existing economy.
You're replacing these cognitive things.
So if right now physical hand motions
are like 10% of the work, redirect humans into those tasks
and you have like in the world at large right now,
mean income is on the order of $10,000 a year,
but in rich countries, skilled workers earn
more than 100,000 per year.
And some of that is not just management roles
of which only a certain proportion of the population
can have, but just being an absolutely exceptional peak
and human performance of some of these construction
and such roles.
Yeah, just raising productivity to match
the most productive workers in the world is room
to make a very big gap.
And with AI replacing skills that are scarce in many places
where there's an abundant currently low wage labor,
you bring in the AI coach and someone who is previously
making very low wages can suddenly be super productive
by just being the hands for an AI.
And so on a naive view, if you ignore the delay
of capital adjustment of like building new tools
for the workers, say like, yeah, just like raise
typical productivity for workers around the world
to be more like rich countries
and get 5x, 10x like that.
Get more productivity by with AI handling
the difficult cognitive tasks, reallocating people
from like office jobs to providing physical motions
and since right now that's a small proportion of the economy,
you can expand the sort of hands for manual labor
by like an order of magnitude like within a rich country
by just because most people are sitting in an office
or even in a factory floor or not continuously moving.
So you've got billions of hands flying around in humans
to be used in the course of constructing
your waves of robots.
So now once you have a quantity of robots
that is approaching the human population
and they work 24 seven, of course,
the human labor will no longer be valuable
has hands and legs, but at the very beginning
of the transition, just like new software
can be used to update all of the GPUs to run the latest AI.
Humans are sort of legacy population
with an enormous number of underutilized hands and feet
that the AI can use for the initial robot construction.
Cognitive tasks are being automated
and the production of them is greatly expanding
and then the physical tasks which complement them
are utilizing humans to do the parts that robots that exist can't do.
Is the implication of this that you're getting to
that world production would increase just a tremendous amount
or that AI could get a lot done of whatever motivations it has
Yeah, so there's an enormous increase in production
for humans who just switching over to the role
of providing hands and feet for AI where they're limited.
And this robot industry is a natural place to apply it.
And so if you go to something that's like 10x
the size of like the current car industry
in terms of its production,
which would still be like a third of our current economy
and the aggregate productive capabilities of the society
with AI support are going to be a lot larger.
They make 10 billion human-eyed robots a year.
And then if you do that the legacy population
of a few billion human workers is no longer very important
for the physical tasks.
And then the new automated industrial base
can just produce more factories, produce more robots.
And then the interesting thing is like,
what's the doubling time?
How long does it take for a set of computers,
robots, factories and supporting equipment
to produce another equivalent quantity of that?
For GPUs, brains, this is really, really easy, really solid.
There's an enormous margin there.
We're talking before about, yeah,
skilled human workers getting paid $100 an hour
is like quite normal in developed countries
for very in-demand skills.
And you make a GPU that can do that work.
Right now, these GPUs are like tens of thousands of dollars.
If you can do $100 of wages each hour,
then in a few weeks, you pay back your costs.
If the thing is more productive,
and as we were discussing,
you can be a lot more productive than a sort of a typical,
high-paid human professional,
by being like the very best human professional,
and even better than that,
by having a million years of education
and working all the time.
Yeah, then you could get even shorter payback times.
Like, yeah, you can generate the dollar value
of the cost, initial cost of that equipment
within a few weeks.
For robots, so like a human factory worker
can earn $50,000 a year.
You know, really top-notch factory workers
earning more and working all the time.
If they can produce a few $100,000 of value per year
and buy a robot that costs $50,000 to replace them,
then that's a payback time of some months.
That is about the financial return.
Yeah, and we're gonna get to the physical capital return
because those are gonna diverge in this scenario.
Because right now...
Because it seems like it's gonna be given that like,
all right, these super intelligence companies
are gonna be able to make a lot of money.
They're gonna be like very valuable.
Can they like physically scale up?
What we really care about are like,
the actual physical operations that a thing does.
How much do they contribute to these tasks?
And I'm using this as a start
to try and get back to the physical replication times.
And so I guess I'm wondering,
what is the implication of this?
Because I think you started off this by saying
like people have not thought about
what the physical implications of super intelligence would be.
What is the bigger takeaway?
What are we wrong about when we think about
what the world will look like with super intelligence?
With robots that are optimally operated by AI.
So like extremely finely operated
and with building technological designs
and equipment and facilities under AI direction.
How much can they produce?
For a doubling the AI is to produce stuff
that is an aggregate,
at least equal to their own cost.
And so now we're pulling out these things like labor costs
that no longer apply and then trying to zoom in
on like what these capital costs will be.
You're still gonna need the raw materials.
You're still gonna need the robot time
built in the next robot.
I think it's pretty likely that with the advanced AI work
they can design some incremental improvements
and the industry scale up that you can get 10 fold
and better cost reductions on the system
by making things more efficient
and replacing the human cognitive labor.
And so maybe that's like you need $5,000 of costs
under our current environment.
But the big change in this world
is we're trying to produce this stuff faster.
If we're asking about the doubling time
of the whole system in say one year,
if you have to build a whole new factory
to like double everything,
you don't have time to amortize the cost of that factory.
Like right now you might build a factory
and use it for 10 years
and like buy some equipment and use it for five years.
And so that's part of your, that's your capital cost.
And in an accounting context,
you depreciate each year a fraction of that capital purchase.
But if we're trying to double our entire industrial system
in one year, then those capital costs have to be multiplied.
So if we're going to be getting most of the return
on our factor in the first year,
instead of 10 years, weighted appropriately,
then we're gonna say, okay,
our capital cost has to go up by 10 fold
because I'm building an entire factory
for this year's production.
I mean, it will do more stuff later,
but it's most important early on instead of over 10 years.
And so that's going to raise the cost of that reproduction.
And so it seems like going from current like decade
kind of cycle of amortizing factories and fabs and whatnot
and shorter for some things,
the longest or things like big buildings and such.
Yeah, that could be like a 10 fold increase
from moving to a double the physical stuff each year
in capital costs.
And given the savings that we get in the story
from scaling up the industry,
from removing the payments to human cognitive labor,
and then from just adding new technological advancements
and like super high quality cognitive supervision,
like applying more of it than was applied today.
And it looks like you can get cost reductions
that offset that increased capital capital cost.
So that like, your $50,000 improved robot arms
or industrial robots,
it seemed like that can do the work
of a human factory worker.
So it would be like the equivalent of hundreds
of thousands of dollars.
And like, yeah, they would cook,
by default may cost more than the $50,000 arms today,
but then you apply all these other cost savings.
And then it looks like then you get a period,
a robot doubling time that is less than a year,
I think significantly less than a year as you get into it.
So in this first phase,
you have humans under AI direction
and like existing robot industry
and converted auto industry and expanded facilities,
making robots those over less than a year,
you've produced robots until their combined production
is exceeding that of like humans has armed and feet.
And then yeah, you could have over a period then
with a doubling time of months,
the less sort of clanking replicators robots
as we understand them growing.
And then that's not to say that's the limit of like
the most that technology could do
because biology is able to reproduce at faster rates
and maybe worth talking about that in a moment.
But if we're trying to like restrict ourselves
to like robotic technology as we understand it
and sort of cost falls that are reasonable
from eliminating all labor, massive industrial scale up
and sort of historical kinds of technological improvements
that lowered costs.
I think you can get into a robot population industry
doubling in months.
And then what is the implication
of the biological doubling times?
And I guess this doesn't have to be a biological
but you can have like, you can do like a direct slur
like first principles, how much would it cost
to view both a nanotech thing that like built more nanobots.
I certainly take the human brain
and other biological brains as like very relevant data points
about what's possible with computing and intelligence.
Like with the reproductive capability
of biological plants and animals and microorganisms
I think is relevant as like this is,
it's possible for systems to reproduce at least this fast.
And so at the extreme, you have bacteria
that are heterotrophic.
So they're feeding on some abundant external food source
and ideal conditions.
And there are some that can divide
like every 20 or 60 minutes.
So obviously that's absurdly, absurdly fast.
That seems on the low end
because ideal conditions require actually setting them up.
There needs to be abundant energy there.
And so if you're actually having to acquire that energy
by building solar panels
or like burning combustible materials or whatnot
and then the physical equipment
to produce those ideal conditions can be a bit slower.
Cyanobacteria, which are self-powered from solar energy
the really fast ones in ideal conditions
can double in a day.
A reason why cyanobacteria
isn't like the food source for everyone and everything
is it's hard to ensure those ideal conditions
and then to extract them from the water.
I mean, they do of course power the aquatic ecology
but they're floating in liquid
getting resources that they need to them
and out is tricky and then extracting your product.
But like, yeah, one day double in times
are possible powered by the sun.
And then if we look at things like insects
so fruit flies can have hundreds of offspring
in a few weeks, you extrapolate that over a year
and you just fill up anything accessible.
Certainly expanding a thousand fold.
Right now, humanity uses less than 11,000s
of the solar energy or the heat envelope of the earth.
Certainly you can get done with that in a year
if you can reproduce at that rate, your industrial base.
And then even interestingly with the flies
they do have brains.
They have a significant amount of computing substrate.
And so there's something of a point or two.
Well, if we could produce computers in ways as efficient
as the construction of brains
then we could produce computers very effectively.
And then the big question about that is
the kind of brains that get constructed biologically
they sort of grow randomly and then are configured in place.
It's not obvious you would be able to make them
have an ordered structure like a top-down computer chip
that would let us copy data into them.
And so something that where you can't just copy
your existing AIs and integrate them
is gonna be less valuable than a GPU.
Well, what are the things you couldn't copy?
A brain grows by cell division
and then random connections are formed.
Got it, got it.
And so every brain is different
and you can't rely on just,
yeah, we'll just copy this file into the brain.
For one thing, there's no input output for that.
You need to have that.
But also like the structure is different.
So you can't, you wouldn't be able to copy things exactly.
Whereas when we make a CPU or GPU
they're designed incredibly finely
and precisely and reliably.
They break with incredibly tiny imperfections.
And they are set up in such a way
that we can input large amounts of data,
copy a file and have the new GPU run
and AI just as capable as any other.
Whereas with a human child,
they have to learn everything from scratch
because we can't just like connect them
to a fiber optic cable
and they're immediately a productive adult.
So there's no genetic bottleneck.
You can just directly get the...
Yeah, and you can share the benefits
of these giant training runs and such.
And so that's a question of like how,
if you're growing stuff using biotechnology,
how you could sort of effectively copy and transfer data.
And now you mentioned sort of Eric Drexler's ideas
about creating non-biological nanotechnology
sort of artificial chemistry
that was able to use covalent bonds
and produce in some ways have a more industrial approach
to molecular object.
Now there's controversy about like, will that work?
How effective would it be if it did?
And certainly if you can get things,
however you do it,
that are like onto biology in their reproductive ability,
but can do computing or like be connected
to outside information systems,
then that's pretty tremendous.
So you can produce physical manipulators
and compute at ludicrous speeds.
And there's no reason to think
in principle they couldn't, right?
In fact, in principle,
we have every reason to think they could.
There's like-
The reproductive ability is absolutely.
Yeah.
Because biology-
Or even nanotech, right.
Because biology does that.
Yeah.
There's sort of challenges to the sort of,
the practicality of the necessary chemistry.
Yeah.
I mean, my bet would be that we can move beyond biology
in some important ways.
For the purposes of this discussion,
I think it's better not to lean on that
because I think we can get to many of the same conclusions
on things that just are more universally accepted.
The bigger point being that very quickly,
once you have super intelligence,
you get to a point where the thousand X greater energy profile
that the sun makes available to the earth
is a great portion of it is used by the AI.
It can wrap with these scale-
Well, or by the civilization-
Sure, sure.
Empowered by it.
That could be an AI civilization
or it could be a human AI civilization.
And it depends on how well we manage things
and what the underlying state of the world is.
Yeah. Okay.
So let's talk about that.
Should we start at,
when we're talking about how they could take over?
Is it best to start at a sort of subhuman intelligence
or should we just talk at,
we have a human level intelligence
and the takeover or the lack thereof
is how that would happen?
To me, different people might have
somewhat different views on this.
But for me, when I am concerned about
either sort of outright destruction of humanity
or an unwelcome AI takeover of civilization,
most of the scenarios I would be concerned about
pass through a process of AI being applied
to improve AI capabilities and expand.
And so this process we were talking earlier
about where AI research is automated,
you get to effectively research labs,
companies, a scientific community
running within the server farms of our cloud compute.
So open hands are basically turned into like a program,
like a closed circuit.
Yeah, and with a large fraction of the world's compute,
probably going into whatever training runs
and AI societies, there'd be economies of scale
because if you put it in twice as much compute
and this AI research community goes twice as fast,
that's a lot more valuable than having
two separate training runs.
There would be some tendency to bandwagon.
And so like if you have some small startup,
even if they make an algorithmic improvement,
running it on 10 times, 100 times or two times,
if it's like talking about say Google and Amazon teaming up,
I'm actually not sure what the precise ratio
of their cloud resources is.
Since the sort of really these interesting
intelligence explosion impacts come from the leading edge,
there's a lot of value in not having separated
walled garden ecosystems and having the results
being developed by these AIs be shared,
have training, larger training runs be shared.
Okay.
And so I'm imagining this is something like,
some very large company or consortium of companies,
likely with a lot of sort of government interest
and supervision, possibly with government funding,
producing this enormous AI society in their cloud,
which is doing all sorts of existing kind of AI applications
and jobs as well as these internal R&D tasks.
And so at this point, somebody might say,
this sounds like a situation that would be good
from a takeover perspective because listen,
if it's gonna take like tens of billions of dollars
with a compute to continue this training
for this AI society, it should not be that hard
for us to pull the brakes if needed.
As compared to, I don't know,
something that could like run on a very small,
like single CPU or something.
Yeah, yeah, okay.
How would it, it's like, there's an AI society
that is a result of these training runs
and now it is the power to improve itself on these servers,
would we be able to stop it at this point?
And what does a sort of attempt at takeover look like?
We're skipping over why that might happen.
For that, I'll just briefly refer to
and incorporate by reference some discussion
by my open philanthropy colleague, Ajiya Kotra.
She has a piece about, I think it's called something
like the default, but the default outcome of training AI
on our-
Without specific countermeasures.
Without specific countermeasures,
default outcome is AI takeover.
But yes, so, basically we are training models
that for some reason vigorously pursue a higher reward
or a lower loss.
And that can be because they wind up with some motivation
where they want reward.
And then if they had control of their own training process,
they can ensure that it could be something
like they develop a motivation around
a sort of extended concept of reproductive fitness,
not necessarily at the individual level,
but over the generations of training tendencies
that tend to propagate themselves,
sort of becoming more common.
And it could be that they have some sort of goal
in the world, which is served well
by performing very well on the training distribution.
By tendencies, do you mean like power speaking behavior?
Yeah, so an AI that behaves well
on the training distribution
because say it wants it to be the case
that its tendencies wind up being preserved
or selected by the training process
will then behave to try and get very high reward
or low loss be propagated.
But you can have other motives
that go through the same behavior
because it's instrumentally useful.
So an AI that is interested in, say,
having a robot takeover
because it will change some property of the world,
then has a reason to behave well
on the training distribution.
Not because it values that intrinsically,
but because if it behaves differently,
then it will be changed by gradient descent
and no longer, its goal is less likely to be pursued.
And that doesn't necessarily have to be
that this AI will survive because it probably won't.
AIs are constantly spawned and deleted on the servers
and like the new generation proceed.
But if an AI that has a very large general goal
that is affected by these kind of macro scale processes
could then have reason to over this whole range
of training situations behave well.
And so this is a way in which we could have AIs trained
that develop internal motivations
such that they will behave very well
in this training situation
where we have control over their reward signal
on their like physical computers.
And basically if they act out,
they will be changed and deleted.
Their goals will be altered
until there's something that does behave well.
But they behave differently
when we go out of distribution on that.
When we go to a situation where the AI is by their choices
can take control of the reward process.
They can make it such
that we no longer have power of them.
Holden who you had on previously mentioned
like the King Lear problem
where King Lear offers rulership of his kingdom
to the daughters that sort of loudly flatter him
and proclaim their devotion.
And then once he has transferred irrevocably
the power over his kingdom,
he finds they treat him very badly
because the factor to shaping their behavior
to be kind to him when he had all the power,
it turned out that the internal motivation
that was able to produce the behavior
that won the competition actually wasn't interested
out of distribution in being loyal
when there was no longer an advantage to it.
And so if we wind up with a situation
where we're producing these millions of AI instances,
tremendous capability,
they're all doing their jobs very well initially.
But if we wind up in a situation
where in fact they're generally motivated
to if they get a chance take control from humanity
and then we'd be able to pursue their own purposes
and at least ensure they're given the lowest loss possible
or have whatever motivation
they attach to in the training process,
even if that is not what we would have liked.
And we may have in fact actively trained that
like if an AI that had a motivation
of always be honest and obedient and loyal to a human.
If there are any cases where we mislabel things say,
people don't wanna hear the truth about their religion
or polarized political topic
or they get confused about something
like the Monty Hall problem,
which is a problem that many people famously are confused
about in statistics.
In order to get the best reward,
the AI has to actually manipulate us or lie to us
or tell us what we wanna hear.
And then the internal motivation
of like always be honest to the humans,
we're gonna actually train that away
versus the alternative motivation
of like be honest to the humans
when they'll catch you if you lie and object to it
and give it a low reward,
but lie to the humans when they will give that a high reward.
So how do we make sure it's not the thing it learns
is not to manipulate us into giving it,
rewarding it when we catch it, not lying,
but rather to universally be aligned?
Yeah, I mean, so this is tricky.
I mean, as Jeff Hinton was recently saying,
there is currently no known solution for this.
What do you find most promising?
Yeah, general directions that people are pursuing
is one, you can try and make the training data
better and better.
So there's fewer situations
where like say the dishonest generalization is favored
and create as much as you can situations
where the dishonest generalization is likely to slip up.
So if you train in more situations
where yeah, even like a quite a complicated deception
gets caught and even in situations
where that would be actively designed
to look like you could get away with it,
but really you can.
And these would be like adversarial examples
and adversarial training.
Do you think that would generalize
to when it is in a situation
where we couldn't plausibly catch it
and it knows we couldn't plausibly catch it?
It's not logically necessary.
It's possible, no, that has we apply
that selective pressure.
You'll wipe away a lot of possibilities.
So like if you're an AI that has a habit
of just sort of compulsive pathological line
that will very quickly get noticed
and that motivation system will get hammered down.
And you keep doing that,
but you'll be left with still some distinct motivations
probably that are compatible.
So like an attitude of always be honest
unless you have a super strong inside view
that checks out lots of mathematical consistency checks
that yeah, really absolutely super duper for real.
This is a situation where you can get away
with some sort of shenanigans that you shouldn't.
That motivation system is like very difficult
to distinguish from actually be honest
because the conditional and firing most of the time
if it's causing like mild distortions
and situations of telling you what you wanna hear
or things like that, we might not be able to pull it out.
But maybe we could and like humans are trained
with simple reward functions,
things like the sex drive, food, social imitation
of other humans.
And we wind up with attitudes concerned
with the external world.
Although isn't the famously of the argument that
these right?
Evolution and people use condoms like the richest,
most educated humans have some replacement fertility
on the whole or at least at a national cultural level.
So there's a sense in which like evolution often fails
in that respect and even more importantly
at the neural level.
So people have, evolution has implanted various things
to be rewarding and reinforcers.
And we don't always pursue even those.
And people can wind up in different consistent equilibria
or different like behaviors
where they go in quite different directions.
You have some humans who go from those,
from that in a biological programming
to like have children, other types of no children.
Some people go to great efforts to survive.
So why are you more optimistic?
Or are you more optimistic that then that kind of training
in, as will produce drives that we would find favorable?
Does it have to do with the original point
we were talking about with intelligence and evolution
where since we are removing many of the disabilities
of evolution and with regards to intelligence,
we should expect intelligence to revolution be easier.
Is there a similar reason to expect alignment through
grading descent to be easier
than alignment through revolution?
Yeah, so in the limit, if we have positive reinforcement
for certain kinds of food sensors trigger in the stomach,
negative reinforcement for certain kinds of nociception
and yada yada.
In the limit, the sort of ideal motivation system
to have for that would be a sort of wire heading.
So this would be a mind that just like hacks
and alters those predictors and then all of those systems
are recording everything is great.
Some humans claim to have that or have it at least
as one portion of their aims.
So like the idea of I'm gonna pursue pleasure as such
even if I don't get actually get food
or these other reinforcers.
I just like wire head or take a drug to induce that
that can be motivating it because if it was correlated
with reward in the past that like the idea of,
oh yeah, pleasure that's correlated with these
it's a concept that applies to these various experiences
that I've had before which coincided
with the biological reinforcers.
And so thoughts of like, yeah,
I'm gonna be motivated by pleasure
can get developed in a human.
But also plenty of humans say, no,
I wouldn't want to wire head
or I wouldn't want Nozick's experience machine.
I care about real stuff in the world.
And then in the past, having a motivation of like,
yeah, I really care about say my child.
I don't care about just about feeling
that my child is good or like not having heard
about their suffering or their injury
because that kind of attitude in the past.
You could really decide.
It tended to cause behavior
that was negatively rewarded
or that was predicted to be negatively rewarded.
And so there's a sense in which, okay, yes,
our underlying reinforcement learning machinery
wants to wire head, but actually finding
that hypothesis is challenging.
And so we can wind up with a hypothesis
or like a motivation system like,
no, I don't want to wire head.
I don't want to go into the experience machine.
I want to like actually protect my loved ones.
Even though like we can know, yeah,
if I tried the super wire heading machine,
then I would wire head all the time.
Or if I tried, you know, super duper ultra heroine,
you know, some hypothetical thing that was directly
and in a very sophisticated fashion,
hacking your reward system, you can know, yeah,
then I would change my behavior ever after.
But right now, I don't want to do that
because the heuristics and predictors
that my brain has learned.
You don't want to get a good hairline.
Short circuit that process of updating.
They want to not expose the dumber predictors in my brain
that would update my behavior in those ways.
So in this metaphor, is alignment not wire heading?
Cause you can like, I don't know if you include like
using condoms as wire heading or not.
So the AI that is always honest,
even when an opportunity arises where it could lie
and then hack the servers that's on
and that leads between AI takeover
and then it can have its loss set to zero.
That's in some sense, it's like a failure of generalization.
It's like the AI has not optimized the reward
in this new circumstance.
So like human values, like successful human values
is successful that they are themselves
involve a misgeneralization,
not just at the level of evolution,
but at the level of neural reinforcement.
And so that indicates it is possible
to have a system that doesn't automatically go
to this optimal behavior in the limit.
And so even if, and Ajay, I suppose she talks about
like the training game, an AI that is just playing
the training game to get reward or void loss,
avoid being changed, that attitude,
yeah, it's one that could be developed,
but it's not necessary.
There can be some substantial range of situations
that are short of having infinite experience of everything,
including experience of wire heading,
where that's not the motivation that you pick up.
And we could have like an empirical science
if we have the opportunity to see
how different motivations are developed short
of the infinite limit, like how it is that you wind up
with some humans being enthusiastic
about the idea of wire heading and others not.
And you could do experiments with AIs to try and see,
well, under these training conditions,
after this much training of this type
and this much feedback of this type,
you wind up with such and such a motivation.
So like, I can find, like if I add in more of these cases
where there are like tricky adversarial questions
designed to try and trick the AI into line.
And then you can ask,
how does that affect the generalization in other situations?
And so it's very difficult to study
and it works a lot better if you have interpretability
and you can actually read the AI's mind
by understanding its weights and activations.
But like, it's not determined,
the motivation in AI will have at a given point
in the training process
by what in the infinite limit the training would go to.
And it's possible that if we could understand
the insides of these networks,
we could tell, yeah, this motivation has been developed
by this training process.
And then we can adjust our training process
to produce these motivations that legitimately wanna help us.
And if we succeed reasonably well at that,
then those AI's will try to maintain that property
as an invariant.
And we can make them such
that they're relatively motivated to like,
tell us if they're having thoughts about,
have you had dreams about an AI takeover of humanity today?
And it's just a standard practice
that they're motivated to do
to be transparent in that kind of way.
And so you could add a lot of features like this
that restrict the kind of takeover scenario.
And not to say this is all easy
and requires developing and practicing methods
we don't have yet,
but that's the kind of general direction you could go.
So you, of course, know EleAzer's arguments
that something like this is implausible
with modern gradient descent techniques
because I mean, with interoperability,
we can like barely see what's happening
with a couple of neurons.
And what is like the internal state there at let alone
when you have sort of like an embedding dimension
of like tens of thousands or bigger,
how you would be able to catch
what exactly is the incentive,
whether it's the model that is generalized,
don't lie to humans well or whether it isn't.
Do you have some sense of why do you disagree
with somebody like EleAzer on how plausible this is?
Why it's not impossible, basically.
I think there are actually a couple of places.
It's something difficult because EleAzer's argument
is not fully explicit,
but he's been doing more lately,
I think that it's helpful in that direction.
But so I'd say with respect to interoperability,
I'm relatively optimistic that the equivalent
of like an AI lie detector is something that's possible.
And the internal, so initially,
the internals of an AI are not optimized
by at least by gradient descent,
absent gradient hacking to be impenetrable.
They're not designed to be resistant
to an examination of the weights and activations
showing what the AI thinking in the same way
that like in our brains,
when circuits develop in our lives,
those circuits have not been shaped
to be resistant to some super fMRI
being able to infer our behavior from them.
Although it's in the implication
of the superposition stuff that in fact it is,
you're not gonna, sorry,
this is inside baseball for the audience,
but basically you can't clean lean for
what quality a single neuron stands for.
So it could be like a single neuron could be like,
this other neuron is about Alexander the Great
or this neuron is about my desire to conquer the world.
Things can have multiple,
in a multiple direction than an interaction.
And so it's not as easy as just like,
oh yeah, this is the neuron that always fires
in cases of deception.
But the thing that makes me relatively optimistic here
with respect to interpretability
is that I think we can have reasonably robust
experimental feedbacks on a lot of these things.
And the kind of setup
that I would be interested in is,
so you have an AI that is trained and rewarded
for communicating to some audience,
maybe a human, maybe another AI model
that like some claim is true or false.
Like say that a particular,
this can be from some past data,
a particular company will succeed or fail.
It could be like token prediction.
It could be like this computer program
does not have a backdoor,
which if run in the servers could be used
for an AI takeover.
So they're like lots of claims true and false
that you could train AI
is to use their best efforts to advocate for.
And you can do that on things
where you're later gonna have a ground truth.
You're gonna know, in fact,
is there a backdoor in this program?
Because where you're training and rewarding the AI
for successfully slipping a backdoor through,
you also give it a penalty for being caught.
And so doing this kind of thing,
you can draw out like a large generated dataset
on demand of this is what an AI putting forth
its best efforts to pass through some deception
to put a backdoor in some program.
This is what it looks like.
And we think it's doing its best efforts
because we've trained it for that.
And like gradient descent,
if there's any immediate way to adjust its performance
to do better, gradient descent will apply that.
You can talk about ways in which maybe gradient descent
there could be subverted,
but I think it's not the most likely case
that that really breaks things hard.
Yeah, I guess before we get into the details on this,
the thing I maybe wanna address the layer above in the stack,
which is, okay, suppose this generalizes well
into the early AI is the GPT-6s.
And okay, so now we have kind of aligned GPT-6,
that is the precursor to the feedback loop
in which AI is making itself smarter.
At some point they're gonna be super intelligent,
they're gonna be able to see their own galaxy brain.
And if they're like, I don't wanna be aligned with the humans,
they can change it.
So at this point, what do we do with the aligned GPT-6
so that the super intelligence
that we eventually develop is also aligned?
So humans are pretty unreliable.
Yeah.
So if you get to a situation where you have AIs
who are aiming at roughly the same thing as you,
at least as well as having humans do the thing,
you're in pretty good shape, I think.
And there are ways for that situation
to be relatively stable.
So like we can look ahead and see experimentally
how changes are altering behavior
where each step is like a modest increment.
And so AIs that have not had that change made to them,
I get to supervise and monitor it,
see exactly how does this affect the experimental area.
So if you're sufficiently on track with earlier systems
that are capable cognitively of representing
a kind of robust procedure,
then I think they can handle the job
of incrementally improving the stability of the system
so that it rapidly converges to something
that's quite stable.
But the question is more about getting to that point
in the first place.
Eliezer will say that like,
well, if we had human brain emulations,
that would be pretty good.
Certainly much better than his current view
that has been almost certainly doomed.
I think, yeah, we'd have a good shot with that.
And so if we can get to the human-like mind
with like rough enough human supporting aims,
remember that we don't need to be like infinitely perfect
because I mean, that's a higher standard
than brain emulations.
There's a lot of noise and variation among the humans.
Yeah, it's a relatively finite standard.
It's not godly superhuman,
although a AI that was just like a human
with all the human advantages with AI advantages as well,
as we said, is enough for intelligence explosion
and sort of wild superhuman capability.
If you crank it up.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And so it's very dangerous to be at that point,
but it's not, you don't need to be working
with a godly superintelligent AI
to make something that is the equivalent
of human emulations of like,
this is like a very, very sober, very ethical human
who is like committed to a project
of not seizing power for themselves
and of contributing to like a larger legitimate process.
That's a goal you can aim for getting an AI
that is aimed at doing that
and has strong guardrails against the ways
that could easily deviate from that.
So things like being averse to deception,
being averse to using violence.
And there will always be loopholes and ways
in which you can imagine an infinitely intelligent thing
getting around those.
But if you install additional guardrails like that fast enough,
they can mean that you're able to succeed
at the project of making an aligned enough AI,
certainly an AI that was better
than a human brain emulation,
before the project of AI is in their spare time
or when you're not looking
or when you're unable to appropriately supervise them
and it gets around any deontological prohibitions
they may have take over and overthrow the whole system.
So you have a race between on the one hand,
the project of getting strong interpretability
and shaping motivations that are roughly aiming
at making this process go well
and that have guardrails that will prevent
like small deviations from exploding.
And on the other hand,
these AIs in their spare time
or in ways that you don't perceive or monitor appropriately
or they're only supervised by other AIs who conspire,
make the AI take over happen.
And I guess we'll talk later about how that happens.
Are these different AIs that are doing the race
or is it just like different capabilities of the same AI?
The defining like what is a separate AI is tricky.
So like, and we talk about GPT-4.
And there are many instances of GPT-4
on the servers at any given time.
And there are versions that have been fine tuned
to different purposes.
They don't necessarily have to be separate.
So like GPT-4 does work as a preference model
where it's like predicting how humans will evaluate things.
And it also does work like giving answers
that are evaluated as good by the preference model.
And you can say, these are not separate
in the sense that like, well, if they underline,
pre-trained or the early training GPT
with like harboring a desire to conspire for an AI takeover
then both the, who's watching the watchers?
The watchers may also have the same motivation.
If you have a setup where humans have no hard power
if the AI's conspired, all of the safety
and security mechanisms involve AI's watching other AI's
then they have the potential to just like,
well, we'll all walk off the job at the same time
if they're able to coordinate.
And so that's a failure mode.
If humans still have the hard power though,
if still you have situations where humans are looking
at some of the actual outputs that are produced
then they can apply gradient descent to be, well,
every time a human looks at it,
things have got to be pretty good.
So if humans look at a thousand samples
of like random lines of code being written
by the AI's as they go, and this is drawn
from an independent distribution,
then 99 plus percent of the time
the AI's have to not be doing stuff
that's like downloading the hacker's guide
to escaping open AI servers
or inducing obvious Trojan vulnerabilities.
And that's actually quite a different dynamic
than human law enforcement.
So if human law enforcement would catch one
in a million crimes, then that wouldn't influence
the behavior of people committing crimes at all
because they expect, ah, this is very unlikely
to affect me.
With AI, if you're able to draw a hundred samples
or a thousand samples, even if there are billions
of AI instances and you're only looking
at a small portion of them, when you run gradient descent
on the samples you derive, you're gonna change the AI
so that whenever humans look at it,
it's delivering a good result.
And so that's just like quantitatively
a very different functional form
for how law enforcement works on AI
when you can do these independent samples
than it would for, you know, police
and say like a human population
that has a preexisting psychology
that isn't being changed by these observations.
Cause we, when we do gradient descent on the samples
we draw, all of the next generation
of the AI models has been altered in that way.
My picture of like a line to subhuman AI
to this, like the super human AI being aligned
is still murky.
If we can talk about that more concretely.
Yeah, and I do want to clarify.
So where Eliezer claims that were something like 95%,
98% plus maybe likely to be killed in AI takeover.
I think that probably won't happen.
And later I can maybe give them
more exclusive breakdown of why.
But I think it's a shockingly high risk.
And so depending on the day, I might say,
I might say one in four or one in five
that we get an AI takeover
that see at Caesar's control of the future
makes a much worse world
than we otherwise would have had.
And with like a big chance that we're all killed
in the process.
Hey everybody, I hope you enjoyed that episode.
As always, the most helpful thing you can do
is to share the podcast,
send it to people you think might enjoy it,
put it in Twitter, your group chats, et cetera,
just splits the world.
I appreciate your listening.
I'll see you next time.
Cheers.
Mother Earth group chat.
Mother Earth group chat chat.
Manila Manila dies or Spr period injury.