LLMs are very good at memorizing static programs.
If you scale up the size of your database,
you are not increasing the intelligence of the system
one bit.
I feel like you're using words like memorization, which
we would never use for human children.
If they can just solve any arbitrary algebraic problem,
you wouldn't say they've memorized algebra.
They'd say they've learned algebra.
So you've got a million dollar price pool,
and there's a $500,000 price for the first team that
can get to the 85% benchmark.
If ARC survives three months from here, we'll pull up the price.
Open AI basically set back progress towards HGI
by probably like five to 10 years.
They caused this complete closing down
of frontier research publishing.
And now LLMs have sucked the oxygen out of the room,
like everyone is just doing LLMs.
OK, today I have the pleasure to speak
with Francois Chollet, who is a AI researcher at Google
and creator of Keras.
And he's launching a prize in collaboration
with Mike Canouf, the co-founder of Xavier,
who we'll also be talking to in a second,
a million dollar prize to solve the ARC benchmark
that he created.
So first question, what is the ARC benchmark,
and why do we even need this prize?
Why won't the biggest LLM we have in a year
be able to just saturate it?
Sure.
So ARC is intended as a kind of IQ test
for machine intelligence.
And what makes it different from most LLM benchmarks out there
is that it's designed to be resistant to memorization.
So if you look at the way LLMs work,
they're basically this big interpolative memory.
And the way you scale up their capabilities
is by trying to cram as much knowledge and patterns
as possible into them.
And by contrast, ARC does not require a lot of knowledge
at all.
It's designed to only require what's
known as core knowledge, which is basic knowledge about things
like elementary physics, objectness, counting,
that sort of thing, the sort of knowledge
that any four-year-old or five-year-old possesses.
But what's interesting is that each puzzle in ARC
is novel, is something that you've probably not encountered
before, even if you've memorized the entire internet.
And that's what makes ARC challenging for LLMs.
And so far, LLMs have not been doing very well on it.
In fact, the approaches that are working well
are more towards discrete program search, program
synthesis.
So first of all, I'll make a comment
that I'm glad that as a skeptic of LLM,
you have put out yourself a benchmark that is it accurate
to say that, suppose that the biggest model we have in a year
is able to get 80% on this, then your view would be
we are on track to AGI with LLMs.
How would you think about that?
Right.
I'm pretty skeptical that we're going
to see LLM do 80% in a year.
That said, if we do see it, you would also
have to look at how this was achieved.
If you just train the model and millions or billions
of puzzles similar to ARC so that you're
relying on the ability to have some overlap between the tasks
that you train on and the tasks that you're
going to see at this time, then you're still
using memorization.
And maybe it can work.
Hopefully, ARC is going to be good enough
that it's going to be resistant to this sort of attempt
at brute forcing.
But you never know.
Maybe it could happen.
I'm not saying it's not going to happen.
ARC is not a perfect benchmark.
Maybe it has flaws.
Maybe it could be hacked in that way.
So I guess I'm curious about what would GPTI
have to do that you're very confident that it's
on the path to AGI?
What would make me change my mind about LLMs
is basically, if I start seeing a critical mass of cases
where you show the model with something
it has not seen before, a task that's actually
novel from the perspective of its training data, something
that's not in the training data, and if it can actually
adapt on the fly.
And this is true for LLMs.
But really, this would catch my attention
with any for any AI technique out there.
If I can see the ability to adapt to novelty on the fly
to pick up new skills efficiently,
then I would be extremely interested.
I would think this is on the path to AGI.
So the advantage they have is that they do get to see everything.
Maybe I'll take issue with how much they are relying on that.
But let's suppose that they are relying.
Obviously, they're relying on that more than humans do.
To the extent that they do have so much indistribution,
to the extent that we have trouble distinguishing
whether an example is indistribution or not,
well, if they have everything in distribution,
then they can do everything that we can do.
Maybe it's not indistribution for us.
Why is it so crucial that it has to be out of distribution
for them?
Why can't we just leverage the fact
that they do get to see everything?
Right.
You're asking basically what's the difference
between actual intelligence, which
is the ability to adapt to things you've not been prepared
for, and pure memorization, like reciting what you've seen
before.
And it's not just some semantic difference.
The big difference is that you can never
pre-train on everything that you might see at test time,
because the world changes all the time.
So it's not just the fact that the space of possible tasks
is infinite.
And even if you're trained on millions of them,
you've only seen zero person out of the total space.
It's also the fact that the world is changing every day.
This is why we, the human species,
developed intelligence in the first place.
If there was a shifting as a distribution for the world,
for the universe, for our lives, then we would not
need intelligence at all.
In fact, many creatures, many insects, for instance,
do not have intelligence.
Instead, what they have is they have in their connectome,
in their genes, hard-coded programs,
behavioral programs that map some stimuli
to appropriate response.
And they can actually navigate their lives
to environments in a way that's very evolutionary fit.
That way, without needing to learn anything.
And while if our environment was static enough,
predictable enough, what would have happened
is that evolution would have found
the perfect behavioral program, a hard-coded,
static behavioral program.
We'd have written it into our genes.
We would have a hard-coded brain connectome.
And that's what we were running on.
But no, that's not what happened.
Instead, we have general intelligence.
We are born with extremely little knowledge about the world.
But we are born with the ability to learn very efficiently
and to adapt in the face of things
that we've never seen before.
And that's what makes us unique.
And that's what is really, really challenging
to recreate in machines.
I want to wrap it all in that a little bit.
But before I do that, maybe I'm going
to overlay some examples of what an arc-like challenge looks
like for the YouTube audience.
But maybe for people listening on audio,
can you just describe what an example arc challenge
will look like?
Sure.
So one arc puzzle, it looks kind of like an IQ test puzzle.
You've got a number of demonstration input-adput pairs.
So one pair is made of two grids.
So one grid shows you an input.
And the second grid shows you what
you should produce as a response to that input.
And you get a couple pairs like this
to demonstrate the nature of the task,
to demonstrate what you're supposed to do with your inputs.
And then you get a new test input.
And your job is to produce the corresponding test outputs.
You look at the demonstration pairs.
And from that, you figure out what you're supposed to do.
And you show that you've understood it on this new test
pair.
And importantly, in order to the knowledge basis
that you need, in order to approach these challenges,
is you just need core knowledge.
And core knowledge is basically the knowledge
of what makes an object, basic counting, basic geometry,
topology, symmetries, that sort of thing.
So extremely basic knowledge.
LLMs for sure possess such knowledge.
Any child possesses such knowledge.
And what's really interesting is that each puzzle is new.
So it's not something that you're
going to find elsewhere on the internet, for instance.
And that means that whether it's as a human or as a machine,
every puzzle you have to approach it from scratch.
You have to actually reason your way through it.
You cannot just fetch the response from your memory.
So the core knowledge, one contention here
is we are only now getting multimodal models who,
because of the data that are trained on,
are trained to do spatial reasoning.
Whereas, obviously, not only humans,
but for billions of years of revolution,
we've had our ancestors have had to learn
how to understand abstract, physical, and spatial properties
and recognize the patterns there.
And so one view would be, in the next year,
as we gain models that are multimodal native,
that isn't just a second class that is an add-on,
but the multimodal capability is a priority.
That it will understand these kinds of patterns
because that's something we see natively.
Whereas, right now, what Arc sees is some JSON string
of 100100, and it's supposed to recognize a pattern there.
And even if you showed a sequence of these kinds of numbers,
it would have a challenge making sense
of what kind of question you're asking it.
So why want it to be the case that,
as soon as we get multimodal models,
which we're on the path to unlock right now,
they're going to be so much better
at Arc-type spatial reasoning?
That's an incredibly cool question,
so I guess we're going to see the answer
within a few months.
But my answer to that is Arc grids,
they're just discrete 2D grids of symbols.
They're pretty small, like it's not like...
If you flatten an image as a sequence of pixels,
for instance, then you get something
that's actually very, very difficult to parse.
But that's not true for Arc because the grids are very small.
You only have 10 possible symbols.
So there's these 2D grids that are actually
very easy to flatten as sequences.
And transformers, LLMs, they're very good
at processing the sequences.
In fact, you can show that LLMs do fine
with processing Arc-like data
by simply fine-tuning LLMs on some subsets of the tasks
and then trying to test it on small variations
of these tasks.
And you see that, yeah, the LLMs can encode
just fine solution programs for tasks
that they've seen before.
So it does not really have a problem
parsing the input or figuring out the program.
The reason why LLMs don't do well on Arc
is really just the unfamiliarity aspect.
The fact that each new task is different
from every other task.
You cannot, basically, you cannot memorize
the solution programs in advance.
You have to synthesize a new solution program
on the fly for each new task.
And that's really what LLMs are struggling with.
So before I do more devil's advocate,
I just want to step back and explain
why I'm especially interested in having this conversation.
And obviously the million dollar Arc prize,
I'm excited to actually play with it myself.
And hopefully the Vesuvius challenge,
which was Nat Friedman's prize for solving decoding scrolls,
the winner of that, decoding the scrolls from
that were buried in the volcanoes
in the Herculaneum library that was solved
by a 22 year old who was listening
to the podcast, Luke Farator.
So hopefully somebody listening will find
this challenge intriguing and find a solution.
So I'm, and the reason I've had on recently
a lot of people who are bullish on LLMs
and I've had discussions with them
before interviewing you about how do we explain the fact
that LLMs don't seem to be natively performing
that well on Arc.
And I found their explanations somewhat contrived
and I'll try out some of the reasons on you.
But it is actually an intriguing fact
that they actually, these are,
some of these problems are relatively straightforward
for humans to understand.
And they do struggle with them
if you just input them natively.
All of them are very easy for humans.
Like any smart human should be able
to do 90%, 95% on Arc.
Smart human.
A smart human, but even a five year old.
So with very, very little knowledge,
they could definitely do over 50%.
So let's talk about that because you,
I agree that smart humans will do very well on this test,
but the average human will probably do mediocre.
Not really.
So we actually tried with average humans,
the score about 85.
That was with Amazon Mechanical Turk workers, right?
I honestly don't know the demographic profile
of Amazon Mechanical Turk workers,
but imagine just interacting with the platform
that Amazon has set up to do remote work.
That's not the median human across the planet, I'm guessing.
I mean, the broader point here being that,
so we see the spectrum in humans
where humans obviously have AGI,
but even within humans, you see a spectrum
where some people are relatively dumber
and they'll do perform work on IQ like tests.
For example, Raven's progressive matrices.
If you look at how the average person performs on that
and you look at the quick kind of questions
that is this sort of midtermists,
half of people will get it right,
half of people will get it wrong.
Some of them are like pretty trivial.
For us, we might think like this was kind of trivial.
And so humans have AGI,
but from relatively small tweaks,
you can go from somebody who misses
these kinds of basic IQ test questions
to somebody who gets them all right,
which suggests that actually,
if these models are doing natively,
we'll talk about some of the previous performances
that people have tried with these models,
but somebody with a Jack Cole
with a 240 million parameter model got 35%.
Doesn't that suggest that they're on this spectrum
that clearly exists within humans
and they're gonna be saturated at pretty soon?
Yeah, so that's a bunch of interesting points here.
So there is indeed a branch of LLM approaches
suspended by Jack Cole that are doing quite well,
that are in fact a state of the art.
But you have to look at what's going on there.
So there are two things.
The first thing is that to guess these numbers,
you need to pre-train your LLM
on millions of generated art tasks.
And of course, if you compare that to a five-year-old child
looking at art for the first time,
the child has never done like you did before,
has never seen something like an art task before.
The only overlap between what they know
and what they have to do in the test is core knowledge,
is knowing about like counting and objects
and symmetries and things like that.
And still, they're gonna do really well
and they're gonna do much better than the LLM
trained on millions of similar tasks.
And the second thing that's something to note
about the Jack Cole approach is one thing
that's really critical to making the model work at all
is test time fine tuning.
And that's something that's really missing, by the way,
from LLM approaches right now is that, you know,
most of the time when you're using an LLM,
it's just doing static inference.
The model is frozen and you're just prompting it
and then you're getting an answer.
So the model is not actually learning anything on the fly.
Its state is not adapting to the task at hand.
What Jack Cole is actually doing is that
for every test problem is on the fly,
is fine tuning a version of the LLM for that task.
And that's really what's unlocking performance.
If you don't do that, you get like 1%, 2%.
So basically something completely negligible.
And if you do test time fine tuning
and you add a bunch of tricks on top,
then you end up with interesting performance numbers.
So I think what he's doing is trying to address
one of the key limitations of LLMs today,
which is the lack of active inference,
is actually adding active inference to LLMs.
And that's working extremely well actually.
So that's fascinating to me.
That there's so many interesting rabbit holes there.
Should I take them in sequence or deal with them all at once?
Let me just start.
So the point you made about the fact
that you need to unlock the adapter compute
slash test time compute, a lot of the scale maximalist,
I think this will be interesting rabbit hole
to explore with you,
because a lot of the scaling maximalist
have your broader perspective in the sense
that they think that in addition to scaling,
you need these kinds of things,
like unlocking adaptive compute
or doing some sort of RL to get the system to working.
And their perspective is that this is a relatively
straightforward thing that will be added atop
the representations that a scaled up model
has greater access to.
No, it's not just a technical detail.
It's not a straightforward thing.
It is everything.
It is the important part.
And the scale maximalist argument,
you know, it boils down to, you know,
these people, they refer to scaling loss,
which is this empirical relationship
that you can draw between how much compute
you spend on training a model
and the performance you're getting on benchmarks, right?
And the key question here, of course, is,
well, how do you measure performance?
What it is that you're actually improving
by adding more compute and more data?
And, well, it's benchmark performance, right?
And the thing is, the way you measure performance
is not a technical detail.
It's not an afterthought because it's gonna narrow down
the set of questions that you're asking.
And so, accordingly, it's gonna narrow down
the set of answers that you're looking for.
If you look at the benchmarks we're using for LMS,
they're all memorization-based benchmarks.
Like, sometimes they are literally just knowledge-based,
like a school test.
And even if you look at the ones
that are, you know, explicitly about reasoning,
you realize, if you look closely,
that it's, in order to solve them,
it's enough to memorize a finite set of reasoning patterns.
And then you just reapply them.
They're like static programs.
LMS are very good at memorizing static programs,
small static programs.
And they've got this sort of like bank of solution programs.
And when you give them a new puzzle,
they can just fetch the appropriate program, apply it.
And it's looking like it's reasoning,
but really it's not doing any sort of
on-the-flight program synthesis.
All it's doing is program fetching.
So you can actually solve all these benchmarks
with memorization.
And so, what you're scaling up here,
like if you look at the models,
they are big parametric curves
fitted to a data distribution,
which I call in descent.
So they're basically these big interpolative databases,
interpolative memories.
And of course, if you scale up the size of your database
and you cram into it more knowledge,
more patterns and so on,
you are gonna be increasing its performance
as measured by a memorization benchmark.
That's kind of obvious.
But as you're doing it,
you are not increasing the intelligence
of the system one bit.
You are increasing the skill of the system.
You are increasing its usefulness,
its scope of applicability, but not its intelligence
because skill is not intelligence.
And that's the fundamental confusion
that people run into is that
they're confusing skill and intelligence.
Yeah, there's a lot of fascinating things
to talk about here.
So skill, intelligence, interpolation.
I mean, okay, so the thing about
they're fitting some manifold into that maps the input data,
there's a reductionist way to talk about what happens
in the human brain that says
that it's just axons firing at each other.
But we don't care about the reductionist explanation
of what's happening.
We care about what the sort of meta at the
macroscopic level, what happens when these things combine.
As far as the interpolation goes,
so okay, let's look at one of the benchmarks here.
There's one benchmark that does great school math
and these are problems that like a smart high schooler
would be able to solve.
It's called GSM 8K and these models get 95% on these.
Like basically they always nail it.
That's memorization benchmark.
Okay, let's talk about what that means.
So here's one question about from that benchmark.
So 30 students are in a class,
one fifth of them are 12 year olds,
one third are 13 year old, one 10th are 11 year olds.
How many of them are not 11, 12 or 13 years old?
So I agree, like this is not rocket science, right?
You can write down on paper how you go through this problem
and a high school kid,
at least a smart high school kid should be able to solve it.
Now, when you say memorization,
it still has to reason through how to think about fractions
and what is the context of the whole problem
and then combining the different calculations it's doing.
It depends how you want to define reasoning,
but there are two definitions you can use.
So one is I have available a set of program templates.
It's like the structure of the puzzle,
which can also generate its solution.
And I'm just gonna identify the right template,
which is in my memory.
I'm gonna input the new values into the template,
run the program, get the solution.
And you could say this is reasoning.
And I say, yeah, sure, okay.
But another definition you can use is reasoning
is the ability to, when you're faced with a puzzle,
given that you don't have already a program in memory
to solve it, you must synthesize on-the-fly a new program
based on bits of pieces of existing programs that you have.
You have to do on-the-fly program synthesis.
And it's actually dramatically harder
than just fetching the right memorized program
and replying it.
So I think maybe we are overestimating
the extent to which humans are so sample efficient.
They also don't need training in this way
where they have to drill in these kinds
of pathways of reasoning through certain kinds of problems.
So let's take math, for example.
It's not like you can just show a baby
the axioms of set theory.
And now they know math, right?
So when they're growing up,
you had to do years of teaching them pre-algebra.
Then you got to do a year of teaching them doing drills
and going through the same kind of problem in algebra,
then geometry, pre-calculus, calculus.
Absolutely, so training?
Yeah, but isn't that like the same kind of thing
where you can't just see one example
and now you have the program or whatever.
You actually had to drill it.
These models also had to drill it
with a bunch of returning data.
Sure, I mean, in order to do on-the-fly program synthesis,
you actually need building blocks to work from.
So knowledge and memory are actually tremendously important
in the process.
I'm not saying it's memory versus reasoning.
In order to do effective reasoning, you need memory.
But it sounds like it's compatible with your story
that through seeing a lot of different kinds of examples,
these things can learn to reason
within the context of those examples.
And we can also see within bigger and bigger models.
So that was an example of a high school level math problem.
Let's say a model that's smaller than GPT-3
couldn't do that at all.
As these models get bigger,
they seem to be able to pick up bigger and bigger.
It's not really a size issue.
It's more like a training data issue in this case.
Well, bigger models can pick up these kinds of circuits
which smaller models apparently don't do a good job
of doing this even if you were to train them
on this kind of data.
Doesn't that just suggest
that you have bigger and bigger models?
They can pick up bigger and bigger pathways
or more general ways of reasoning.
Absolutely.
But then isn't that intelligence?
No, no, it's not.
If you scale up your database
and you keep adding to it more knowledge,
more program templates,
then sure it becomes more and more skillful.
You can apply it to more and more tasks.
But general intelligence is not tasks with six skills
scaled up to many skills.
Because there is an infinite space of possible skills.
General intelligence is the ability to approach
any problem, any skill,
and very quickly master it using valid or data.
Because this is what makes you able to face
anything you might ever encounter.
This is what makes,
this is the definition of generality.
Like generality is now specifically scaled up.
It is the ability to apply your mind
to anything at all, to arbitrary things.
And this requires, fundamentally,
it requires the ability to adapt,
to learn on the fly efficiently.
So, my claim is that by doing this free training
on bigger and bigger models,
you are gaining that capacity
to then generalize very efficiently.
Let me give you an example.
So, your own company, Google,
in their paper on Gemini 1.5,
they had this very interesting example
where they would give, in context,
they would give the model,
the grammar book and the dictionary
of a language that has less than 200 living speakers.
So, it's not in the free training data.
And you just give them the dictionary
and it basically is able to speak this language
and translate to it,
including the complex and organic ways
in which languages are structured.
So, a human, if you showed me a dictionary
from English to Spanish,
I'm not gonna be able to pick up the
how to structure sentences
and how to say things in Spanish.
The fact that because of the representations
that it has gained through this free training,
it is able to now extremely efficiently
learn a new language.
Doesn't that show that this kind of free training
actually does increase your ability to learn new tasks?
If you're right, if you were right,
LLMs would do really well on arch puzzles
because arch puzzles are not complex.
Each one of them requires very little knowledge.
Each one of them is very low on complexity.
You don't need to think very hard about it.
They're actually extremely obvious for humans,
like even children can do them.
But LLMs cannot, even LLMs that have, you know,
100,000 times more knowledge than you do.
They still cannot.
And the only thing that makes arch special
is that it was designed with this intent
to resist memorization.
This is the only thing.
And this is the huge blocker for LLM performance, right?
And so, you know, I think if you look at LLMs closely,
it's pretty obvious that they're not really like
synthesizing new programs on the fly
to solve the tasks that they're faced with.
They're very much replying things
that they've stored in memory.
For instance, one thing that's very striking
is LLMs can solve a CISA cipher,
you know, like a CISA cipher,
like transposing letters to code a message.
And well, that's a very complex algorithm, right?
But it comes up quite a bit on the internet.
So they've basically memorized it.
And what's really interesting is that they can do it
for a transposition length of like three or five
because there are very, very common numbers
in examples provided on the internet.
But if you try to do it with an arbitrary number,
like nine, it's gonna fail.
Because it does not encode the generalized form
of the algorithm, but only specific cases.
It does memorize specific cases of the algorithm, right?
And if it could actually synthesize on the fly
the solver algorithm, then the value of N
would not matter at all
because it does not increase the problem complexity.
I think this is true of humans as well,
where what was the study that-
Humans use memorization pattern matching all the time,
of course, but humans are not limited
to memorization pattern matching.
They have this very unique ability
to adapt to new situations on the fly.
This is exactly what enables you to navigate
every new day in your life.
I'm forgetting the details,
but there was some study that chess grandmasters
will perform very well within the context of the moves that-
Excellent example, because chess at the highest level
is all about memorization, chess memorization.
Okay, sure, we can leave that aside.
What is your explanation for the original question of
why in context the GPT- sorry, Gemini 1.5
was able to learn a language,
including the complex grammar structure?
Doesn't that show that they can pick up new knowledge?
I would assume that it has simply mined
from its extremely extensive and imaginably vast
training data, it has mined the required template
and then it's just reusing it.
We know that they have a very poor ability
to synthesize new program templates like this on the fly
or even adapt existing ones.
They're very much limited to fetching.
Suppose there's a programmer at Google,
they go into the office in the morning.
At what point are they doing something
that 100% cannot be due to fetching some template
that even if they, suppose they were an LLM,
they could not do if they had fetched some template
from their program.
At what point do they have to use
this so-called extreme generalization capability?
Forget about Google software developers.
Every human, every day of their lives
is full of novel things that they've not been prepared for.
You cannot navigate your life based on memorization alone.
It's impossible.
I'm sort of denying the premise that they're,
you also agree they're not doing like,
quote-unquote memorization.
It seems like you're saying they're less capable
of generalization, but I'm just curious of like,
the kind of generalization they do,
if you get into the office
and you try to do this kind of generalization,
you're gonna fail at your job.
But what is the first point, you're a programmer.
What is the first point when you try to do that generalization,
you would lose your job
because you can't do the extreme generalization?
I don't have any specific examples,
but literally like, take this situation for instance,
you've never been here in this room.
Maybe you've been in this city a few times, I don't know,
but there's a fair amount of novelty.
You've never been interviewing me.
There's a fair amount of novelty
every hour of every day in your life.
And it's in fact, by and large,
more novelty than any LLM could handle.
Like if you just put a LLM in a robot,
it could not be doing all the things
that you've been doing today, right?
Or take on like cell driving cars, for instance.
You take a cell driving car operating in the barrier.
Do you think you could just drop it in New York City
or drop it in London where people drive on the left?
No, it's gonna fail.
So not only can you drop, not like,
make it generalize to a change of rules of driving rules,
but you can not even make it generalize to a new city.
It needs to be trained on each specific environment.
I mean, I agree that self-driving cars aren't AGI.
But it's the same type of model,
they're transformers as well.
I mean, I don't know,
they also have brains with neurons in them,
but they're less intelligent because they're small.
It's not the same architecture.
We can get into that.
But so I still don't understand like a concrete thing of,
we also need training.
That's why education exists.
That's why we had to spend the first 18 years of our life
doing drills.
We have a memory, but we are not a memory.
We are not limited to just a memory.
I'm denying the premise that that's necessarily
the only thing these models are doing.
And I'm still not sure what is the task
that a remote worker would have to,
suppose you do some remote work with an LLM
and they're programmer,
what is the first point that you realize
this is not a human, this is an LLM?
What about they just send them a knock puzzle
and see how they do?
No, like part of their job, you know?
But you have to deal with novelty all the time.
Okay, so if you, is there a world in which
all the programmers are replaced?
And then we're still saying,
but they're only doing memorization
late in programming tasks,
but they're still producing a trillion dollars
worth of output in the form of code.
Software development is actually a pretty good example
of a job where you're dealing with novelty all the time.
Or if you're not, well, I'm not sure what you're doing.
So I personally use Genetic VI very little
in my software development job.
And before LLMs, I think I was also using
Stack Overflow very little.
You know, some people maybe are just copy-pasting stuff
from Stack Overflow,
or nowadays copy-pasting stuff from an LLM.
Personally, I try to focus on problem-solving.
The syntax is just a technical detail.
What's really important is the problem-solving.
Like the essence of programming is engineering
mental models, like mental representations
of the problem you're trying to solve.
But you can, you know, we have many,
people can interact with these systems themselves
and you can go to chat GPT and say,
here's a specification of the kind of program I want.
They'll build it for you.
As long as there are many examples of this program
on like GitHub and Stack Overflow and so on,
sure, they will fetch the program for you from their memory.
But you can change arbitrary details.
You can say I need it to work on this different kind of server.
If that were true, there would be no software engineers today.
I agree. We're not at a full AGI yet,
in the sense that these models have,
let's say, less than a trillion parameters.
A human brain has somewhere on the order
of 10 to 30 trillion synapses.
I mean, if you were just doing some naive math,
you're like at least 10x under parameterized.
So I agree we're not there yet,
but I'm sort of confused on why we're not on the spectrum,
where yes, I agree that there's many kinds
of generalization they can do,
but it seems like they're on this kind of smooth spectrum
that we see even within humans,
where some humans would have a hard time doing an ARC type test.
We see that based on the performance
on progressive Ravens matrices type IQ tests.
I'm not a fan of IQ tests because for the most part,
you can train on IQ tests and get better at them.
So they have very much memorization based.
And this is actually the main pitfall
that ARC tries not to fall far.
I'm still not confused.
So if all remote jobs are automated
in the next five years, let's say,
at least that don't require you to be like sort of a service.
It's not like a salesperson
where you want the human to be talking,
but like programming or whatever.
In that world, would you say that that's not possible
because a lot of what a programmer needs to do,
definitely requires things that would not be
in any free training corpus?
Sure. I mean, in five years,
there will be more software engineers
than there are today and not too well.
But I just want to understand.
So I'm still not sure.
I mean, I know how to, I studied computer science.
I think if I had become a code monkey out of college,
like what would I be doing?
I go to my job.
What is the first thing my boss tells me something to do?
When does he realize I'm an LLM if I was an LLM?
Probably on the first day, you know?
Again,
if it were true that LLMs could generalize
to novel problems like this
and you can actually develop software
to solve a problem they've never seen before,
you would not need software engineers anymore.
In practice, if I look at how people are using LLMs
in their software engineering job today,
they're using it as a stack of a flow replacement.
So they're using it as a way to copy paste code snippets
to perform very common actions.
And what they actually need is a database of code snippets.
They don't actually need any of the abilities
that actually make them software engineers.
I mean, when we talk about interpolating
between stack overflow databases,
if you look at the kinds of math problems
or coding problems, maybe to say that they're,
maybe let's step back on interpolation
and let me ask the question this way.
Why can't creativity,
why isn't creativity just interpolation
in a higher dimension where if a bigger model
can learn a more complex manifold,
we're gonna use the ML language.
And if you look at read a biography of a scientist,
it doesn't feel like they're not zero shot
in new scientific theories.
They're playing with existing ideas.
They're trying to juxtapose them in their head.
They try out some like slightly ever in the tree
of intellectual descendants,
they try out a different evolutionary path.
You sort of run the experiment there
in terms of publishing the paper, whatever.
It seems like a similar kind of thing humans are doing.
There's like at a higher level of generalization.
And what you see across bigger and bigger models
is they seem to be approaching
higher and higher level of generalization
where GPT-2 couldn't do a great school level math problem
that requires more generalization
that it has capability for, even that skill.
Then GPT-3 and 4 can.
So not quite.
So GPT-4 has a higher degree of skill
and higher range of skills.
Because it's-
I don't want to get into semantics here,
but I think-
The same degree of generalization.
I don't want to get into semantics here,
but the question of why can't creativity
be just interpolation on a higher dimension?
I think interpolation can be creative, absolutely.
And you know, to your point,
I do think that on some level,
humans also do a lot of memorization,
a lot of reciting, a lot of pattern matching,
a lot of interpolation as well.
So it's very much a spectrum
between pattern matching and true reasoning.
It's a spectrum.
And humans are never really at one end of the spectrum.
They're never really doing pure pattern matching
or pure reasoning.
They're usually doing some mixture of both.
Even if you're doing something that seems very reasoning heavy,
like proving a mathematical theorem,
as you're doing it, sure,
you're doing quite a bit of discrete search in your mind,
quite a bit of actual reasoning.
But you're also very much guided by intuition,
guided by pattern matching,
guided by the shape of proofs that you've seen before,
by your knowledge of mathematics.
So it's never really,
you know, all of our thoughts,
everything we do is a mixture of this sort of like
interpolative memorization based thinking,
this sort of like type one thinking and type two thinking.
Why are bigger models more sample efficient?
Because they have more reusable building blocks
that they can lean on to pick up new patterns
in their train data.
And does that pattern keep continuing
as you keep getting bigger and bigger?
To the extent that the new patterns
you're giving the model to learn
are good match for what it has learned before.
If you present something that is actually novel,
that is not in a state of distribution like an arc puzzle,
for instance, it will fail.
Let me make this claim.
The program synthesis I think is a very,
very useful intuition pump.
Why can't it be the case that what's happening
in the transformer is the early layers are doing the,
figuring out how to represent the inputting tokens.
And what the middle layers do is this kind of program search,
program synthesis, where they combine the inputs
to all the circuits in the model
where they go from the low level representation
to a higher level representation
near the middle of the model.
They use these programs, they combine these concepts,
then what comes out at the other end is the reasoning
based on that high level intelligence.
Possibly, why not?
But if these models were actually capable
of synthesizing novel programs,
however simple they should be able to do arc
because for any arc task,
if you write down the solution program in Python,
it's not a complex program, it's extremely simple
and humans can figure it out.
So why can LLMs not do it?
Okay, I think that's a fair point.
And if I turn the question around to you,
so suppose that it's the case that in a year,
a multimodal model can solve arc,
let's say get 80%, whatever the average human would get,
then AGI?
Quite possibly, yes.
I think if you start, so honestly,
what I would like to see is an LLM type model
solving arc at like 80%,
but after having only been trained
on core knowledge related stuff.
But human kids, I don't think we're necessarily
just trading on, it's not just that we have
in our show is object permanence.
Okay, let me rephrase that.
Only trained on information that is not explicitly
trying to anticipate what's gonna be in the arc test set.
But isn't the whole point of arc that you can't,
sort of, it's a new type of intelligence
every single time?
Yes, that is the point.
So if arc were perfect, flawless benchmark,
it would be impossible to anticipate within the test set.
And arc was released more than four years ago
and so far it's been resistant to memorization.
So I think it has, to some extent, passed a test of time.
But I don't think it's perfect.
I think if you try to make by hand
hundreds of thousands of arc tasks
and then you try to multiply them
by programmatically generating variations
and then you end up with maybe hundreds of millions of tasks.
Just by brute forcing the task space,
there will be enough overlap between what you're trained on
and what's in the test set that you can actually score
very highly.
So, you know, with enough scale, you can always cheat.
If you can do this for every single thing
that supposedly requires intelligence,
then what good is intelligence?
Apparently you can just brute force intelligence.
If the world, if your life, were a static distribution,
then sure, you could just brute force
the space of possible behaviors.
You could like, you know, the way we think about intelligence,
there are several metaphors, I like to use,
but one of them is you can think of intelligence
as a past finding algorithm in future situation space.
Like, I don't know if you're familiar with game development,
like RTS game development, but you have a map, right?
And you have, it's like a 2D map.
And you have partial information about it.
Like there is some fog of war on your map.
There are areas that you haven't explored yet.
You know nothing about them.
And then there are areas that you've explored,
but you only know how they were like in the past.
You don't know how they are like today.
And now, instead of thinking about a 2D map,
think about the space of possible future situations
that you might encounter and how they're connected to each other.
Intelligence is a past finding algorithm.
So once you set a goal, it will tell you
how to get there optimally.
But of course, it's constrained by the information you have.
It cannot pass find in an area that you know nothing about.
It cannot also anticipate changes.
And the thing is, if you had complete information about the map,
then you could solve the past finding problem
by simply memorizing every possible path, every mapping
from point A to point B. You could solve the problem
with pure memory.
But the reason you cannot do that in real life
is because you don't actually know what's
going to happen in the future.
I feel like you're using words like memorization, which
we would never use for human children.
If your kid learns to do algebra and then now learns
to do calculus, you wouldn't say they memorized calculus.
If they can just solve any arbitrary algebraic problem,
you wouldn't say they memorized algebra.
They say they've learned algebra.
Humans are never redoing pure memorization or pure reasoning.
But that's only because you're semantically
labeling when the human does the skill.
It's a memorization when the exact same skill is done by the LLM
as you can measure by these benchmarks.
And you can just plug in any sort of math problem.
Sometimes humans are doing the exact same as the LLM
is doing, which is just, for instance,
I know if you learn to add numbers,
you're memorizing an algorithm.
You're memorizing a program.
And then you can reapply it.
You are not synthesizing on the fly the addition program.
So obviously at some point, some human had to figure out
how to do addition.
But the way a kid learns it is not
that they figure out from the actions of set theory
how to do addition.
I think what you're learning in school
is mostly memorization.
So my claim is that, listen, these models
are vastly underparameterized relative to how many flops
or how many parameters you have in the human brain.
And so yeah, they're not going to be coming up
with new theorems like the smartest humans can.
But most humans can't do that either.
What most humans do, it sounds like it's
similar to what you were calling memorization, which
is memorizing skills or memorizing techniques
that you've learned.
And so it sounds like it's compatible.
Tell me if this is wrong.
Is it compatible in your world if all the remote workers
are gone, but they're doing skills
which we can potentially make synthetic data of?
So we record everybody's screen and every single remote worker
screen.
We sort of understand the skills they're performing there.
And now we've trained a model that can do all this.
All the remote workers are unemployed.
We're generating trillions of dollars
to economic activity for AI remote workers.
In that world, are we still in the memorization regime?
So sure.
With memorization, you can automate almost anything
as long as it's a static distribution,
as long as you don't have to deal with change.
Are most jobs part of such a static distribution?
Potentially, there are lots of things that you can automate.
And LLMs are an excellent tool for automation.
And I think that's true.
But you have to understand that automation is not
the same as intelligence.
I'm not saying that LLMs are useless.
I've been a huge proponent of deep learning for many years.
And for many years, I've been saying two things.
I've been saying that if you keep scaling up deep learning,
it will keep paying off.
And at the same time, I've been saying,
if you keep scaling up deep learning,
this will not lead to a GI.
So we can automate more and more things.
And yes, this is economically valuable.
And yes, potentially, there are many jobs.
You could automate a way like this.
And that would be economically valuable.
But you're still not going to have intelligence.
So you can ask, OK, so what does it
matter if we can generate all this economic value?
Maybe we don't need intelligence after all.
Well, you need intelligence the moment
you have to deal with change, with novelty, with uncertainty.
As long as you are in a space that
can be exactly described in advance,
you can just automate your pure memorization.
In fact, you can always solve any problem.
You can always display arbitrary levels of skills
on any task without leveraging any intelligence whatsoever,
as long as it is possible to describe the problem
and its solution very, very precisely.
But when they do deal with novelty,
then you just call it interpolation, right?
And so interpolation is not enough
to deal with all kinds of novelty
if it were, then LLMs would be a GI.
Well, I agree they're not a GI.
I'm just trying to figure out how do we figure out
we're on the path to a GI.
And I think a sort of crux here is maybe
that it seems to me that these things are on a spectrum
and we're clearly covering the earliest part of the spectrum
with LLMs.
I think so.
And oh, OK, interesting.
But here's another sort of thing
that I think is evidence for this, grokking, right?
So clearly, even within deep learning,
there's a difference between the memorization regime
and the generalization regime, where at first they'll just
memorize the data set of if you're doing modular addition,
how to add digits.
And then at some point, if you keep training on that,
they'll learn the skill.
So the fact that there is that distinction
suggests that the generalized circuit, the deep learning
can learn, there is a regime in enters where it generalizes.
If you have an over-parameterized model,
which you don't have in comparison to all the tasks
we want these models to do right now.
Grokking is a very, very old phenomenon.
We've been observing it for decades.
It's basically an instance of the minimum description length
principle, where, sure, given a problem,
you can just memorize a point-wise input-to-output mapping,
which is completely overfit.
So it does not generalize at all,
but it solves the problem on the train data.
And from there, you can actually keep proving it,
keep making your mapping simpler and simpler and more
compressed.
And at some point, it will start generalizing.
And so that's something called the minimum description
length principle.
It's this idea that the program that will generalize best
is the shortest, right?
And it doesn't mean that you're doing anything
other than memorization, but you're
doing memorization plus regularization.
Right, AKA generalization.
Yeah, and that is absolutely, at least to generalization.
Right, and then so you do that within one skill,
but then the pattern you see here of meta-learning
is that it's more efficient to store a program that can perform
many skills rather than one skill, which is what we might
call fluid intelligence.
And so as you get bigger and bigger models,
you would expect it to go up this hierarchy of generalization
where it generalizes to a skill, then it generalizes
multiple skills.
That's correct, that's correct.
And you know, LLMs, they're not infinitely large.
They have only a fixed number of parameters.
And so they have to compress their knowledge
as much as possible.
And in practice, so LLMs are mostly
storing reusable bits of programs, like vector programs.
And because they have this need for compression,
it means that every time they're learning a new program,
they're going to try to express it
in terms of existing bits and pieces of programs
that they've already learned before, right?
Isn't this the generalization?
Absolutely.
Oh, wait, so.
This is why, you know, clearly LLMs
have some degree of generalization.
And this is precisely why, it's because they have to compress.
And why is that intrinsically limited?
Why can't you just go, at some point,
it has to learn a higher level of generalization,
a higher level, and then the highest level
is the fluid intelligence.
It's intrinsically limited because the substrate
of your model is a big parametric curve.
And all you can do with this is local generalization.
If you want to go beyond this towards broader
or even extreme generalization, you
have to move to a different type of model.
And my paradigm of choice is discrete program search,
program synthesis.
So and if you want to understand that,
you can sort of like compare and contrast it with deep learning.
So in deep learning, your model is a parametric curve,
a differentiable parametric curve.
In program synthesis, your model
is a discrete graph of operators.
So you've got like a set of logical operators,
like a domain-specific language.
You're picking instances of it.
You're structuring that into a graph.
That's a program.
And that's actually very similar to like a program
you might write in Python or C++ and so on.
And in deep learning, your learning engine,
because we are doing much learning here,
like we're trying to automatically learn these models.
In deep learning, your learning engine is quite in the sense.
And quite in the sense is very compute efficient,
because you have this very strong, informative feedback
signal about where the solution is.
So you can get to the solution very quickly.
But it is very data inefficient, meaning
that in order to make it work, you
need a dense sampling of the operating space.
You need a dense sampling of the data distribution.
And then you're limited to only generalizing
within that data distribution.
And the reason why you have this limitation
is because your model is a curve.
And meanwhile, if you look at discrete program search,
the learning engine is combinatorial search.
You're just trying a bunch of programs
until you find one that actually miss your spec.
This process is extremely data efficient.
You can learn a generalizable program
from just one example, two examples, which
is why it works so well on Arc, by the way.
But the big limitation is that it's extremely compute
inefficient, because you're running into combinatorial
explosion, of course.
And so you can sort of see here how
the planning and discrete program search,
they have very complementary strengths and limitations
as well.
Every limitation of deep learning has a strength,
a corresponding strength in program synthesis and inversely.
And I think the path forward is going to be to merge the two,
to basically start doing.
So another way you can think about it
is, so these parametric curves, train with ground descent,
there are great fits for everything
that's system one type thinking, like pattern cognition,
intuition, memorization, and so on.
And discrete program search is a great fit
for type two thinking, system two thinking.
For instance, planning, reasoning,
quickly figuring out a generalizable model,
that matches just one or two examples,
like for an archbishop, for instance.
And I think humans are never doing pure system one
or pure system two.
They're always mixing and matching both.
And right now, we have all the tools for system one.
We have almost nothing for system two.
The way forward is to create a hybrid system.
And I think the form it's going to take
is it's going to be mostly system two.
So the outer structure is going to be a discrete program
search system.
But you're going to fix the fundamental limitation
of discrete program search, which is combinator explosion.
You're going to fix it with deep learning.
You're going to leverage deep learning to guide,
to provide intuition in program space,
to guide the program search.
And I think that's very similar to what you see,
for instance, when you're playing chess
or when you're trying to prove a theorem,
is that it's mostly a reasoning thing,
but you start out with some intuition
about the shape of the solution.
And that's very much something you can get
via a deep learning model.
Deep learning models, they're very much like intuition machines.
They're pattern matching machines.
So you start from this shape of the solution,
and then you're going to do actual explicit discrete
program search.
But you're not going to do it via brute force.
You're not going to try things kind of like randomly.
You're actually going to ask another deep learning model
for suggestions.
Like, here's the best likely next step.
Here's where in the graph you should be going.
And you can also use yet another deep learning model
for feedback about, well, here's what I had so far.
Is it looking good?
Should I just backtrack and try something new?
So I think discrete program search is going to be the key,
but you want to make it dramatically better,
all those of magnitude more efficient,
by leveraging deep learning.
And by the way, another thing that you can use deep learning
is, of course, things like common sense knowledge,
and knowledge in general.
And I think you're going to end up
with this sort of system where you
have this on-the-fly synthesis engine that
can adapt to new situations.
But the way it adapts is that it's
going to fetch from a bank of patterns,
modules that could be themselves,
curves that could be differentiable modules,
and some others that could be algorithmic in nature.
It's going to assemble them via this process that's
intuition-guided.
And it's going to give you, for every new situation you
might be faced with, it's going to give you
with a generalizable model that was synthesized
using very, very little data.
Something like this would sort of arc.
That's actually a really interesting prompt,
because I think an interesting crux here
is when I talk to my friends who are extremely
optimistic about LLMs and expect AGI within the next couple
of years, they also, in some sense,
agree that scaling is not all you need,
but that the rest of the progress is undergirded
and enabled by scaling.
But still, you need to add the system
to the test time compute atop these models.
And their perspective is that it's relatively
straightforward to do that, because you
have this library of representations
that you built up from free training,
but it's almost talking like, it's just
like skimming through textbooks.
You need some more deliberate way in which it engages
with the material it learns.
In-context learning is extremely sample-efficient.
But to actually distill that into the weights,
you need the model to talk through the things that sees
and then add it back to the weights.
As far as the system 2 goes, they talk about adding some kind
of RL setup so that it is encouraged
to proceed on the reasoning traces that end up being correct.
And they think this is relatively straightforward stuff
that will be added within the next couple of years.
That's an empirical question.
So I think we'll see.
Your intuition, I assume, is not that.
I'm curious.
My intuition is, in fact, this whole system
2 architecture is the hard part.
It's the very hard and non-obvious part.
Scaling up the interpolative memory is the easy part.
All you need is, like, it's literally just a big curve.
All you need is more data.
It's representation of a data set,
interpolative representation of data set.
That's the easy part.
The hard part is the architecture of intelligence.
Memory and intelligence are separate components.
We have the memory.
We don't have the intelligence yet.
And I agree with you that, well, having the memory
is actually very useful.
And if you just had the intelligence,
but it was not hooked up to an extensive memory,
it would not be that useful, because it would not
have enough material to work from.
Yeah.
The alternative hypothesis here that former guest Trenton
Brickin advanced is that intelligence
is just hierarchically associated memory
where higher-level patterns, when Sherlock Holmes goes
into a crime scene, and he's extremely sample-efficient,
he can just look at a few clues and figure out
who was a murderer, and the way he's
able to do that is he has learned higher-level
sort of associations.
It's memory in some fundamental sense.
But so here's one way to ask the question.
In the brain, supposedly we do program synthesis,
but it is just synapses connected to one another,
each other, and so physically it's
got to be that you just query the right circuit, right?
You are, yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's a matter of degree.
But if you can learn it, if training in the environment
human ancestors are trained in means
you learn those circuits, training
on the same kinds of outputs that humans produce,
which to replicate require these kinds of circuits,
wouldn't that train the same kind of whatever humans have?
You know, it's a matter of degree.
If you have a system that has a memory
and is only capable of doing local generalization from that,
it's not going to be very adaptable.
To be really general, you need the memory
plus the ability to search to quite some depth,
to achieve broader even extramuralization.
You know, like one of my favorite psychologists,
so Jean Piaget was the founder of the Elemental Psychology.
He had a very good quote about intelligence.
He said, intelligence is what you use when you don't know what
to do.
And it's like, as a human living your life,
in most situations you already know what to do,
because you've been in this situation before.
You already have the answer, right?
And you're only going to need to use intelligence
when you're faced with novelty, with something you didn't expect,
with something that you weren't prepared for,
either by your own experience, your own life experience,
or by your evolutionary history.
Like, this day that you're living right now is different
in some important ways from every day you've lived before,
but it's also different from any day ever lived
by any of your ancestors.
And still, you're capable of being functional, right?
How is it possible?
I'm not denying that generalization is extremely important,
and is the basis for intelligence.
That's not the correct, the correct is like,
how much of that is happening in the models?
But, okay, let me ask a separate question.
We might keep going in the circle here.
The differences in intelligence between humans,
maybe the intelligence tests because of reasons
you mentioned are not measuring it well,
but clearly there's differences in intelligence
between different humans.
What is your explanation for what's going on there?
Because I think that's sort of compatible with my story
that there's a spectrum of generality
and that these models are climbing up to a human level,
and even some humans haven't even climbed up
to the Einstein level or the Francois level, but.
That's a great question, you know.
There is extensive evidence that intelligence,
difference in intelligence are mostly genetic in nature,
right?
Meaning that if you take someone who is not very intelligent,
there is no amount of training, of like training data,
you can expose that person to that would
make them become Einstein.
And this kind of points to the fact
that you really need a better architecture,
you need a better algorithm,
and more training data is not in fact all you need.
I think I agree with that.
I think what, maybe the way I might phrase it is that
the people who are smarter have in ML language
better initializations, the neural wiring,
if you just look at, it's more efficient,
they have maybe greater density of firing.
And so as some part of the story is scaling,
there is some correlation between brain size
and intelligence.
And we also see within the context of quote unquote,
scaling that people talk about
within the context of LLMs, architectural improvements,
where a model like Gemini 1.5 flash
is performs as well as GPT-4 did
when GPT-4 was released a year ago,
but is 57 times cheaper on output.
So the part of the scaling story
is that the architectural improvements are,
we're in like extremely low hanging fruit territory
when it comes to those.
Okay, we're back now with the co-founder of Zapier,
Mike Canouf, we had to restart a few times there.
And you're funding this prize
and you're running this prize with Francois.
And so tell me about how this came together,
what more prompted you guys to launch this prize?
Yeah, I guess I've been sort of like AI curious
for 13 years, I co-founded Zapier,
been running it for the last 13 years.
And I think I first got introduced to your work
and during COVID, I kind of went down the rabbit hole,
we had a lot of free time.
And it was right after you published your
on measure of intelligence paper,
you sort of introduced the concept of AGI,
this like efficiency of skill acquisition
is like the right definition and the arc puzzles.
But I don't think the first Kaggle contest was done yet.
I think it was still running.
And so I kind of, it was interesting,
but I just parked the idea.
And my bigger fish to fry at Zapier
were in this middle of this big turnaround
of trying to get to our second product.
And then it was January, 2022,
when the chain of thought paper came out
that really like awoken me to sort of the progress.
I gave a whole presentation to the Zapier
on like the GPT-3 paper events.
I'd sort of felt like I had priced in everything
that Elms could do and that paper was
really shocking to me in terms of
these latent capabilities that Elms have
that I didn't expect that they had.
And so I actually gave up my exact team role at Zapier.
I was running half the company at that point
and I went back to be an individual contributor
and just to go do AI research
alongside Brian, my co-founder.
And all of that led me to back towards arc.
I was looking into it again
and I had sort of expected to see this saturation effect
that MMLU has, that GMSK 8K has.
And when I looked at the scores and the progress
since the last four years, I was really again, shocked to see
actually we've made very little objective progress
towards it and it felt very,
it felt like a really, really important Eval.
And as I sort of spent the last year
asking people, quizzing people about it
and sort of my network and community,
very few people even knew it existed.
And that felt like, okay, if it's right
that this is a really, really like globally
singularly unique EGI Eval.
And it's different from every other Eval that exists
that are more narrowly measures AI skill.
Like more people should know about this thing.
I had my own ideas on how to beat the arc as well.
So like I was working on nights and weekends on that
and I flew up to meet Francois earlier this year
to sort of quiz him, show him my ideas.
And ultimately I was like, well,
why don't you think more people know about arc?
I think you should actually answer that.
I think it's a really interesting question.
Like why don't you think more people know about arc?
Sure, you know, I think benchmarks that gain traction
in the research community are benchmarks
that are already fairly tractable
because the dynamic that you see is that some research group
is gonna make some initial breakthrough
and then this is gonna catch the attention of everyone else.
And so you're gonna get follow-up papers
with people trying to beat the first team and so on.
And for arc, this has not really happened
because arc is actually very hard
for existing AI techniques.
Kind of arc requires you to try new ideas.
And that's very much the point, by the way.
Like the point is not that, yeah,
you should just be able to apply existing technology
and solve arc.
The point is that existing technology has reached a plateau
and if you want to go beyond that,
if you want to start being able to tackle problems
that you haven't memorized, that you haven't seen before,
you need to try new ideas.
And arc is not just meant to be this sort of like measure
of how close we are to a GI.
It's also meant to be a source of inspiration.
Like I want researchers to look at these puzzles
and be like, hey, it's really strange
that these puzzles are so simple
and most humans can just do them very quickly.
Why is it so hard for existing AI systems?
Why is it so hard for LLMs and so on?
And it's true for LLMs, but arc was actually released
before LLMs were really a thing.
And the only thing that made it special at the time
was that it was designed to be a resistance to memorization.
And the fact that it has survived LLMs
and Genia in general so well,
kind of shows that yes,
it is actually resistant to memorization.
This is what nerds night me
because I went and took a bunch of the puzzles myself.
I've showed it to all my friends and family too
and they're all like, oh yeah, this is like super easy.
Are you sure AI can't solve this?
Like that's the reaction in the same one for me as well.
And the more you dig in, you're like, okay,
yep, there's not just empirical evidence
over the last four years that it's unbeaten,
but there's theoretical like concepts behind why.
And I completely agree at this point
that like new ideas basically are needed to be dark.
And there's a lot of current trends in the world
that are actually, I think,
working against that happening basically.
I think we're actually less likely
to generate new ideas right now.
You know, I think one of the kind of trends
is the closing up frontier research, right?
The GP4 paper from Open AI had no technical details shared.
The Gemini paper had no technical details shared
and like the longer context part of that work.
And yet that open innovation and open progress and sharing
is what got us to transformers in the first place.
That's what got us to LMS in the first place.
So it's kind of disappointing a little bit actually
that like so much frontier work has gone closed.
It's really making a bet that like these individual labs
are going to have the breakthrough
and not the ecosystem is going to have the breakthrough.
And I think sort of the internet open source has shown
that that's like the most powerful innovation ecosystem
that's ever existed probably in the entire world.
I think that's actually really sad
that frontier research is no longer being published.
If you look back, you know, four years ago,
well, everything was just openly shared
like all the state of the art results were published
and this is no longer the case.
And it's very much, you know,
Open AI single-handedly changed the game.
And I think Open AI basically set back progress towards HGI
by quite a few years, probably like five to 10 years
for two reasons.
And one is that, well, they cause this complete closing down
of research, frontier research publishing,
but also they trigger this initial burst of hype
around LLMS.
And now LLMS have sucked the oxygen out of the room
like everything, everyone is just doing LLMS.
And I see LLMS as a more often off-ramp
on the path to HGI actually.
And all these new resources,
they're actually going to LLMS instead
of everything else they could be going to.
And, you know, if you look further into the past
to like 2015, 2016,
there were like a thousand times fewer people
doing AI back then.
And yet I feel like the rate of progress was higher
because people were exploring more directions.
The world felt more open-ended.
Like you could just go and try,
like have a cool idea of a launch
and try it and get some interesting results.
So there was this energy.
And now everyone is very much doing some variation
of the same thing.
And the big labs also tried their hand on arc,
but because they got bad results,
they didn't publish anything.
Like, you know, people only publish positive results.
I wonder how much effort people have put into
trying to prompt or scaffold,
do some sort of maybe Devon type approach
into getting the frontier models
and the frontier models of today, not just a year ago,
because a lot of post-training
has gone into making them better.
So Claude Friropas or GPT-40
into getting good solutions on arc.
I hope that one of the things this episode does
is get people to try out this open competition
where they have to put in an open source model to compete.
But also to like figure out if they're,
maybe the like capability is latent in Claude Opus
and just see if you can show that.
I think that would be super interesting.
So let's talk about the prize.
How much do you win if you solve it?
You know, get whatever percent on arc.
How much do you get if you get the best of vision,
but don't crack it?
So we got a million dollar,
actually a little over a million dollars
is the price pool.
We're running the contest on an annual basis.
We're gonna, we're starting it today
through the middle of November.
And the goal is to get 85%.
That's the lower bound and human average
that you guys talked about earlier.
And there's a $500,000 prize for the first team
that can get to the 85% benchmark.
We're also gonna run,
we don't expect that to happen this year actually.
One of the early statisticians that's up here
giving this line that has always stuck with me
that the longer it takes, the longer it takes.
So my prior is that like arc is gonna take years to solve.
And so we're gonna keep to,
we're also gonna break down and do a progress price this year.
So there's a $100,000 progress price,
which we will pay out to the top scores.
So $50,000 is gonna go to the top objective scores this year
on the Kaggle leaderboard,
which we're hosting it on Kaggle.
And then we're gonna have a $50,000 pot set
for a paper award for the best paper
that explains conceptually the scores
that they were able to achieve.
And one of the I think interesting things
we're also gonna be doing is,
we're gonna be requiring that in order to win the prize money
that you put the solution or your paper
out into public domain.
The reason for this is,
typically with contests,
you see a lot of like closed up sharing.
People are kind of private secret.
They wanna hold their alpha to themselves
during the contest period.
And because we expect it's gonna be multiple years,
we wanna enter a game here.
So the plan is at the end of November,
we will award the $100,000 prize money
to the top progress prize
and then use the downtime between December, January, February
to share out all the knowledge from the top scores
and the approaches folks were taking
in order to re-baseline the community
up to whatever the state of the art is
and then run the contest again next year.
And keep doing that on a yearly basis until we get 85%.
I'll give some people some context
on why I think this prize is very interesting.
I was having conversations with my friends
who are very much believers in models as they exist today.
And first of all, it was intriguing to me
that they didn't know about ARC.
These are experienced ML researchers.
And so you show them this happened a couple of nights ago.
We went to dinner and I showed them an example problem.
And they said, of course,
an LLM would be able to solve something like this.
And then we take a screenshot of it.
We just put it into our chat GPT app
and it doesn't get the pattern.
And so I think it's very interesting.
Like it is a notable fact.
I was sort of playing devil's advocate against you
on these kinds of questions.
But this is a very intriguing fact.
And I'm extreme, I think this prize is extremely interesting
because we're gonna learn,
we're gonna learn something fascinating one way or another.
So with regards to the 85%,
separate from this prize,
I'd be very curious if somebody could replicate that result
because obviously in psychology and other kinds of fields,
which this result seems to be analogous to
when you run test on some small sample of people,
often they're hard to replicate.
So I'd be very curious if you try to replicate this,
how, what does an average human perform on ARC?
Ask for the difficulty on how long it will take
to crack this benchmark.
It's very interesting because the other benchmarks
that are now fully saturated like MMLU math,
actually the people who made them,
Dan Hendricks and Colin Burns who did MMLU and math,
I think they were grad students or college students
when they made it.
And the goal when they made it just a couple of years ago
was that this will be a test of AGI.
And of course it got totally saturated.
And I know you all argue that these are test memorization,
but I think the pattern we've seen,
in fact, Epoch AI has a very interesting graph
that I'll sort of overlay for the YouTube version here
where you see this almost exponential
where it gets 5%, 10%, 30%, 40%
as you increase the compute across models
and then it just shoots up.
And in the GPT-4 technical report,
they had this interesting graph
of the human eval problem set,
which was 22 coding problems.
And they had to graph it on the mean log pass curve,
basically because early on in training
or even smaller models can have the right idea
of how to solve this problem,
but it takes a lot of reliability
to make sure they stay on track to solve the whole problem.
And so you really wanna up wait the signal
where they get it right at least some of the time,
maybe one in a hundred times or one in a thousand.
And then so they go from like one in a thousand,
one in a hundred, one in 10,
and then they just like totally saturated.
I guess the question I have,
this is all leading up to,
is why won't the same thing happen with ARC
where people had to try really hard, bigger models.
And now they figured out these techniques
that Jack Cole has figured out
with only a 240 million parameter language model
that can get 35%.
Shouldn't we see the same pattern we saw
across all these other benchmarks
where you just like sort of eke out.
And then once you get the general idea,
then you just go all the way to a hundred.
That's an empirical question.
So we'll see in practice what happens.
But what Jack Cole is doing is actually very unique.
It's not just pre-training an LLM and then prompting it,
he's actually trying to do active inference.
He's doing a test time, right?
He's doing like test time functioning.
Exactly, test time functioning.
And this is actually trying to lift
one of the key limitations of LLMs,
which is that at inference time,
they cannot learn anything new.
They cannot adapt on the flight what they're seeing.
And he's actually trying to learn.
So what he's doing is effectively
a form of program synthesis.
Because the LLM contains a lot of useful building blocks,
like programming building blocks,
and by finding it on the task at test time,
you are trying to assemble these building blocks
into the right pattern that matches the task.
This is exactly what program synthesis is about.
And the way we contrast this approach
with discrete program search is that
in discrete program search,
so you're trying to assemble a program
from a set of primitives.
You have very few primitives.
So people working on discrete program search on Arc,
for instance, they tend to work with DSLs that have like
100 to 200 primitive programs.
So very small DSL,
but then they're trying to combine these primitives
into very complex programs.
So there's very deep depths of search.
And on the other hand,
if you look at what Jack is doing with LLMs,
is that he's got this sort of like vector program database,
DSL of millions of building blocks in the LLM
that are mined by pre-training the LLM,
not just on a ton of programming problems,
but also on millions of generated Arc-like tasks.
So you have an extraordinarily large DSL.
And then the fun tuning is very, very shallow
recombination of these primitives.
So discrete program search, very deep recombination,
very small set of primitive programs.
And the LLM approach is the same,
but on the complete opposite end of that spectrum,
where you scale up the memorization
by a massive factor and you're doing very, very shallow search,
but they are the same thing,
just different ends of the spectrum.
And I think where you're gonna get the most value
for your compute cycles is gonna be somewhere in between.
You want to leverage memorization to build up a richer,
more useful bank of primitive programs.
And you don't want them to be hard-coded
like what we saw for the typical artist.
You want them to be learned from examples.
But then you also want to do some degree of deep search.
As long as you're only doing very shallow search,
you are limited to local generalization.
If you want to generalize further,
more broadly, this depth of search is gonna be critical.
I might argue that the reason that he had to rely so heavily
on the synthetic data was because he used a 240 million
parameter model because the Kaggle competition at the time
required him to use a P100 GPU,
which has like a 10th or something of the flops of an H100.
And so obviously he can't use,
if you believe that sort of scaling will solve
this kind of reasoning,
then there you can just rely on the generalization,
whereas if you're using a much smaller,
for context for the listeners, by the way,
the frontier models today are literally
a thousand X bigger than that.
And so for your competition,
from what I remember,
the submission you'll have to submit
can't make any API calls, can't go online,
and has to run on NVIDIA Tesla T4.
P100.
Oh, is it P100?
Yeah.
Okay, so again, it's like significantly less powerful.
There's a 12-hour runtime limit, basically.
There's a forcing function of efficiency in the eval.
But here's the thing, you only have 100 test tasks.
So the amount of computing available for each task
is actually quite a bit,
especially if you contrast that
with the simplicity of each task.
So it would be seven minutes per task, basically,
which for, people have tried to do these estimates
of how many flops does a human brain have.
And you can take them with a grain of salt,
but as a sort of anchor,
it's basically the amount of flops an H100 has.
And I guess maybe you would argue with that,
well, a human brain can solve this question
in faster than 7.2 minutes.
So even with a tenth of the compute,
you should be able to do it in seven minutes.
Obviously, we have less memory than, you know,
like petabytes of fast access memory in the brain.
And with these, you know, 29 or whatever gigabytes
in this H100.
Anyway, I guess the broader question I'm asking is,
I wish there was a way to also test this prize
with some sort of scaffolding on the biggest models
as a way to test whether scaling is the path
to get to solving ARC.
Absolutely.
So in the context of the computation,
we want to see how much progress we can do
with limited resources.
But you're entirely right that it's a super interesting
open question.
What could the biggest model out there actually do on ARC?
So we want to actually also make available a private
sort of like one-off track where you can submit to us a VM
and so you can put on it any model you want.
Like you can take one of the largest open source models
out there and find you need to do whatever you want
and just give us an image.
And then we run it on the H100 for like 24 hours
or something and you see what you get.
I think it's worth pointing out that there's two different
test sets.
There is a public test set that's in the public
GitHub repository that anyone can use to train, you know,
put it in an open API call, whatever you'd like to do.
And then there's the private test set,
which is the 100 that is actually measuring
the state of the art.
So I think it is pretty open and interesting to have folks
attempt to at least use the public test set and go try it.
Now, there is an asterisk on any score that's reported on
against the public test set because it is public.
It could have leaked into the training data.
And this is actually what people are already doing.
Like you can already try to prompt one of the best models
like the latest Jaminar, the latest GPT-4 with tasks
from the public evaluation set.
And you know, again, the primary set, these tasks
are available as JSON files on GitHub.
These models are also trained on GitHub.
So they're actually trained on these tasks.
And yeah, that kind of creates uncertainty about
if they can actually solve some of the tasks,
is that because they memorized the answer or not.
You know, maybe you would be better off trying to create
your own private, arc-like, very novel test set.
Don't make the task difficult.
Don't make them complex.
Make them very obvious for humans.
But make sure to make them original as much as possible.
Make them unique, different.
And see how much your GPT-4 and so on GPT-5 does on them.
Well, they're having tests on whether these models
are being overtrained on these benchmarks.
Scale recently did this where on the GSM-
That's really interesting.
AK, they basically replicated the benchmark
with different questions.
And so some of the models actually were extremely
overfit on the benchmark like Mistral and so forth.
And but the frontier models, Claude and GPT actually did
as well on their novel benchmark that they did
on the specific questions that were
in the existing public benchmark.
So I would be relatively optimistic about them
just sort of training on the JSON.
I was joking with Mike that you should allow API access
but sort of keep an even more private validation set
of these arc questions.
And so allow API access, people can sort of play
with GPT-4 scaffolding to enter into this contest.
And if it turns out maybe later on you run the validation
set on the API and if it performs worse
than the test set that you allowed the API access
to originally, that means that open AI is training
on your API calls and you like go public with this
and show them like, oh my God,
they've like leaked your data.
We do want to make, we want to evolve the arc data set.
Like that is a goal that we want to do.
I think Francois you mentioned, you know, it's not perfect.
Yeah, no, arc is not perfect for perfect benchmark.
I mean, I made it like four years ago
over four years ago, almost five now.
This was in a time before LMS.
And I think we learned a lot actually since
about what potential flaws there might be.
I think there is some redundancy in the set of tasks
which is of course against the goals of the benchmark.
Every task is supposed to be unique in practice.
That's not quite true.
I think there's also, every task is supposed
to be very novel, but in practice, they might not be.
They might be structurally similar to something
that you might find online somewhere.
So we want to keep iterating
and release an arc two version later this year.
And I think when we do that,
we're gonna want to make the old private test set available.
So maybe we won't be releasing it publicly,
but what we could do is just create a test server
where you can query, get a task, you submit a solution,
and of course you can use whatever frontier model
you want there.
So that way, because you actually have to query this API,
you're making sure that no one is gonna buy accident train
on this data.
It's unlike like the current public article
which is literally on GitHub.
So there's no question about whether the models
are actually trained on it.
Yes, they are because they're trained on GitHub.
So by sort of like gating access
to querying this API with a various issue.
And then we would see, you know,
for people who actually wanna try
whatever technique they have in mind
using whatever resources they want,
that would be a way for them to get an answer.
I wonder what might happen.
I'm not sure.
One answer is that they come up with a whole new algorithm
for AI with some explicit program synthesis
that now we're on a new track.
And another is they did something hacky
with the existing models in a way that actually is valid,
which reveals that movie intelligence is more
of getting things to the right part of the distribution,
but then it can reason.
And in that world, I guess that will be interesting.
And maybe that'll indicate that, you know,
you had to do something hacky with current models
as they get better,
you won't have to do something hacky.
I'm also gonna be very curious to see
how these multimodal models,
if they will perform natively much better at arc like tests.
If arc survives three months from here,
we'll blow up the price.
I think we're about to make a really important moment
of like contact with reality by blowing up the price,
putting a much big price pool against it.
We're gonna learn really quickly
if there's like low hanging fruit of ideas.
Again, I think new ideas are needed.
I think anyone listening this
might have the idea in their head.
And I'd encourage everyone to like give it a try.
And I think as time goes on,
that adds strength to the argument
that like we sort of stall that in progress
and that new ideas are necessary to be dark.
Yeah, that's the point of having a money price
is that you attract more people,
you get them to try to solve it.
And if there's a easy way to hack the benchmark
that reveals that the benchmark is valid,
then you're gonna know about it.
In fact, that was the point
of the original Carol competition back in 2020 for arc.
I was running this competition
because I had released this dataset
and I wanted to know if it was hackable, if you could cheat.
So there was a small money price at the time,
there was like 20K.
And this was right around the same time
as GPT-3 was released.
So people of course tried GPT-3 on the public data,
it scored zero.
But I think what the first context
the first context taught us is that
there is no obvious shortcuts, right?
And well, now there's more money,
there's gonna be more people looking into it.
Well, we're gonna find out,
we're gonna see if the benchmark is gonna survive.
And you know, if we end up with a solution
that is not like trying to brute force
the space of possible arc tasks
that's just trained on core knowledge,
I don't think it's necessarily gonna be in and by itself, AGI,
but it's probably gonna be a huge milestone
on the way to AGI.
Because what it represents is the ability to synthesize,
task a problem solving program
from just two or three examples.
And that alone is a new way to program.
It's an entirely new paradigm for software development
where you can start programming
potentially quite complex programs
that will generalize very well.
And instead of programming them by coming up
with the shape of the program in your mind
and then tapping it up,
you're actually just showing the computer
what add what you want
and you let the computer figure it out.
I think that's what is extremely powerful.
I wanna riff a little bit on what kinds of solutions
might be possible here
and which you would consider sort of defeating
the purpose of arc and which are sort of valid.
Here's one I'll mention which is my friends
that Ryan and Buck stayed up last night
because I told them about this
and they were like, oh, of course,
I was gonna solve this.
Thank you for spreading the word.
Of course, I was gonna solve this.
And then so they were trying to prompt,
I think Claude, Opus on this
and they say they got 25% on the public arc test.
And what they did was have other examples
of some of the arc tests
and in context explain the reasoning
of why you went from one output to another output
and then now you have the current problem.
And I think also maybe expressing the JSON in a way
that is more amenable to the tokenizer.
And another thing was using the code interpreter.
So I'm curious actually,
if you think the code interpreter,
which keeps getting better as these models get smarter
is just the program synthesis right there
because what they were able to do
was the actual output of the cells, the JSON output,
they got through the code interpreter,
like write the Python program that gets right up here.
Do you think that the program synthesis
kind of researcher talking about
will look like just using the code interpreter
in large language models?
I think whatever solution we see that will score well
is gonna probably need to leverage some aspects
from deep learning models and LLMs in particular.
We've shown already that LLMs can do quite well,
that's basically the jack code approach.
We've also shown that pure discrete program search
from a small DSL does very, very well
before jack code, this was the state of the art.
In fact, it's still extremely close to the state of the art.
And there's no deep learning involved at all in these models.
So we have two approaches that have basically no overlap
that are doing quite well.
And they're very much at two opposite ends of one spectrum,
where on one end you have these extremely large banks
of millions of vector programs,
but very, very shallow recombination,
like simplistic recombination.
And on the other end, you have very simplistic DSLs,
very simple, like 100 or 200 primitives,
but very deep, very sophisticated program search.
The solution is gonna be somewhere in between, right?
So the people are gonna be winning the art competition
and we're gonna be making the most progress
towards near-term NGR are gonna be users
that manage to merge the deep learning paradigm
and the discrete program search paradigm
into one elegant way.
And you know, you ask like,
what would be legitimate and what would be cheating,
for instance?
You wanna add a code interpreter to the system.
I think that's great, that's sort of legitimate.
The part that would be cheating is try to
anticipate what might be in the test set,
like brute force the space of possible tasks
and then train a memorization system on it.
And then rely on the fact that you're generating
so many tasks, like millions and millions and millions,
that inevitably there's gonna be some overlap
between what you're generating and what's in the test set.
I think that's defeating the purpose of benchmark
because then you can just solve it with that
and you need to adapt just by fetching a memorized solution.
So hopefully arc will resist to that,
but you know, nothing, no benchmark is necessarily perfect.
So maybe there's a way to hack it
and I guess we are gonna get an answer very soon.
Although I think some amount of fine tuning is valid
because these models don't natively think in terms of,
especially the language models alone,
which the open source models that they would have to use
to be competitive here compete here.
They're like natively language,
so they need to be able to think in this kind of...
Yes.
The arc type way.
You want to input corner ledge,
like arc like corner ledge into the model,
but surely you don't need tens of millions of tasks
to do this, like corner ledge is extremely basic.
If you look at some of these arc type questions,
I actually do think they rely a little bit
on things I have seen throughout my life.
And for the same, like for example,
like something bounces off a wall
and comes back and you see that pattern.
It's like I played arcade games
and I've seen like pong or something.
And I think for example, when you see the Flynn effect
and people's intelligence has measured on
very advanced progressive matrices
increasing on these kinds of questions,
it's probably a simpler story where since now,
since childhood, we actually see these sorts of patterns
in TV and whatever, spatial patterns.
And so I don't think this is sort of core knowledge.
I think actually this is also part of the quote unquote
trying tuning that humans have as they grow up
of seeing different kinds of spatial patterns
and trying to pattern match to them.
I would definitely file that under core knowledge.
Like core knowledge includes basic physics,
for instance, bouncing or trajectories,
that would be included.
But yeah, I think you're entirely right.
The reason why as a human,
you're able to quickly figure out the solution
is because you have this set of building blocks,
this set of patterns in your mind that you can recombine.
Is core knowledge required to attain intelligence?
Any algorithm you have,
does the core knowledge have to be in some sense hard coded
or can even the core knowledge be learned through intelligence?
Core knowledge can be learned.
And I think in the case of humans,
some amount of core knowledge is something
that you're born with.
Like we're actually born with a small amount of knowledge
about the world we're gonna live in.
We're not blank slates.
But most core knowledge is acquired through experience.
But the thing with core knowledge
that it's not gonna be acquired like for instance in school,
it's actually acquired very, very early
in the first like three to four years of your life.
And by age four,
you have all the core knowledge you're gonna need as an adult.
Okay, interesting.
So I mean, on the price itself,
I'm super excited to see both the open source versions
of maybe with a Lama 70B or something
what people can score in the competition itself.
Then if to sort of test specifically
the scaling hypothesis,
I'm very curious to see if you can prompt
on the public version of ARC,
which I guess when we compare,
you will be able to submit to this competition itself.
But I'd be very curious to see how,
if people can sort of crack that and get ARC working there
and if that would update your reviews on AGI.
It's gonna be motivating.
We're gonna keep running the contest
until somebody puts a reproducible open source version
into public domain.
So even if somebody privately beats the ARC eval,
we're gonna still keep the price money
until someone can reproduce it
and put the public reproducible version out there.
Yeah, exactly.
Like the goal is to accelerate progress towards AGI.
And a key part of that is that
any sort of meaningful bits of progress
needs to be shared, needs to be public.
So everyone can know about it
and can try to iterate on it.
If there's no sharing, there's no progress.
What I'm especially curious about
is sort of disaggregating the bets
of like, can we make an open version of this
versus is this a thing that's just possible with scaling?
And we can, I guess test both of them
based on the public and the private version.
We're making contact with reality as well with this, right?
We're gonna learn a lot, I think,
about what the actual limits of the compute
where if someone showed up and said,
hey, here's a closed source model
that like I'm getting 50 plus percent on,
I think that would probably update us on like,
okay, perhaps we should increase the amount of compute
that we give on the private test set
in order to balance some of the decisions
that initially are somewhat arbitrary
in order to learn about, okay, what do people want?
What does progress look like?
And I think both of us are sort of committed
to evolving it over time in order to be the best,
or the closest to perfect as we can get it.
Awesome, and where can people go to learn more
about the prize and maybe give their hand at it?
ARCPrize.org.
Which goes live today, so.
It's live now.
$70 million is on this line, people.
Good luck.
Thank you guys for coming on the podcast.
It was super fun to go through all the cruxes
on intelligence and get a different perspective,
and also to announce a prize here.
So this is awesome.
Thank you for helping break news.
Thank you, Finest.