Value props is one of the most important things that we could possibly spend time on because
the number one reason that companies fail is because they're not solving a valuable
enough problem and therefore they don't create the value that's worth investing in and therefore
they fail in their basic form of meeting a need.
So what we intend to do today is to both help you understand how to define the problem
you're addressing or the opportunity you see and then actually evaluate it and then finally
create it.
And this is one of the few workshops where I'll tell you that we do have an answer.
Usually you hear me say there are no answers that I'm going to ask a whole bunch of questions
of you.
The only answer I'm giving you though is a framework and it's a framework for where
we're going to go.
So let me jump right in and get you there so you can hear exactly from the beginning
how this framework set of activities is going to come together.
So as I said first of all we're going to define then we're going to evaluate then we're
going to build.
One of the things I want to tell you right off the bat is that I want to get rid of the
idea of ideas.
It's a terrible thing but most people come to me and they say I've got an incredible
idea for X, Y and Z.
Well ideas are to a penny, sorry I should say to a cent but what they really are is
free floating.
They don't actually have meaning until you can address some kind of a problem or opportunity
with them.
So that's why that first part is so important.
And then of course once you start building a value proposition we want to be able to
evaluate it so you yourself not me or anybody else can judge whether you've got something
that is really going to be compelling and cause people to buy.
And finally if you have then of course you want to build it and get it into a form that's
really crisp.
So it's an easy thing for you to do and everything from an elevator pitch to literally going
to a full on pitch for example to get a customer over the line or raise money.
In every instance though this framework, a set of frameworks should help you get that.
So I said we'd give you an answer.
This is the end of the session.
We want you to be able to actually build this framework and say for who that is dissatisfied
with what due to some unmet need or problem you offer a product that solves that and it
provides some key benefits that are compelling enough that people actually want to engage
with you.
So that's why we're headed this evening.
First thing in the value prop that we want to do is define.
The first statement sounds so obvious which is for who.
So I'm going to jump right in because I know that they've got a good starting point.
Connect Ed Gulnaz.
Tell me for who is your value prop.
So this is connected as a nonprofit so we bridge the digital divide for people in Kazakhstan
but we have to deliver I feel like the value proposition for organization that donate their
computers and devices to us and those who can fund us.
Okay so you went long way down into that but I want to make sure we really understand the
who.
So if you could say who it is for is it everybody in Kazakhstan?
Primarily children.
Okay so we want to say children okay.
What else could you say about them?
From marginalized communities and rural areas in Kazakhstan.
Okay marginalized.
What else?
Who don't have basic digital literacy skills.
Okay so basic digital literacy skills.
And you said the last thing is.
And they don't have equipment.
So this is why I picked Gulnaz because I've been lucky enough to have her in the class
before.
She didn't say my proposition is for everybody which would be very terrifying if it was by
the way because then how do you even pick where you go to market or how you reach that
customer etc.
She's got very specific.
I didn't write Kazakhstan because that's pretty obvious but it's children with marginalized
who are in a marginalized situation don't have basic digital literacy and they don't
have the equipment.
Now we can find out later how she's going to address their needs.
That's pretty clear right.
So anyway one of the teams at the iLab who put their value prop in for tonight was Comprofacil
and they very openly said they've got a product which is going to help people who are dissatisfied
with current credit products due to high interest rates get through a credit marketplace better
comparison capabilities.
Makes total sense but they didn't say for who.
Now that's a massive problem when you are building a business because if you don't know
who your customer is you don't know what the persona is that you're selling to and
how to focus or target on them etc.
And it just is the beginning therefore of why the value proposition statement is so important.
I will underline it by saying the following.
If you don't know who your customer is and you think it's everybody I can tell you you're
going to fail by default because trying to boil the ocean and sell to the world at large
is a very big undertaking for any company.
Even the largest companies in the world get very crisp about it.
Yeah and Tato.
Yeah I had a question and I think related to Golnath's business.
If your user is different from your customer who do you put on the for who?
Great question.
So user versus customer.
What do you think is the answer first of all?
Golnath will answer.
Anybody can answer.
Does anybody in the room have an answer to this?
This is a terrifically good question by the way.
This is the kind of thing that we really need to deal with too.
The user say more.
Why the user?
Well because customer is just the person who's paying it but user is who's benefiting
from what you're creating.
Great.
Now does it mean that one or the other?
Or are both important?
Anybody else want to comment on this?
Yes go ahead.
I think when your user is not your customer you actually have to satisfy two different
value propositions.
You have to provide value to the initial funder whether that's philanthropy or government
but you also have to provide value to the user so you have uptake.
Okay.
So this is really important.
This which is I'll just use the word pull.
You need the pull from the user.
If the user's not using it nobody's going to pay for it.
But even if the user is using it the person who's got to pay for it whether it's a government
if it's a non-profit situation or it's somebody in IT for example who's the gatekeep of something
they still are going to need the user to convince them that there is a payoff that makes it
worth them investing in this product or service.
So both are important but I really agree with Victor by the way you've got to start with
the user.
Like if the user is just not getting the value from your value proposition that's the whole
point of this class then we're in the wrong place.
So this piece of definition is what we're trying to get to with the who and when you
see and by the way I don't think we have it this semester but the startup secrets class
on go to market which by the way is on the iLib YouTube channel.
You will see we talk about personas and this is one of the things that we talk about is
how do you get to all parts of the persona that is going to be the champion for your
product or service in whatever enterprise or government or non-profit you're selling
to.
So very important question thank you very much for that.
Any other questions on who before we move on?
All right good.
The key word here is ultimately segment.
So if we're not going to sell to everybody we need to find a segment of people that we're
going to sell to and the trick of this is actually in your workbook so I'm not going
to pitch it to you tonight because it's a significant thing to go and spend some time
looking at and that is to define your minimum viable segment.
I'll just define it for you as simply as this which is to say you're all going to get to
learn about building the smallest product you possibly can your MVP and if the whole
market out there the whole world was where you went and targeted that then this would
very quickly get pulled in all sorts of different directions for all the potential users that
could use your product or service and they all have different needs.
The MVS simply says you want to find one path where you get the same needs for the same
users that allows you to sell the same product over and over and over and over and over again
without you having to change the product.
You can learn a lot more about that in the workbook but that's the notion of a segment
and if you do this right then you end up with a minimum viable segment which is a good dance
partner as I call it to your minimum viable product.
Now does anybody in the room not know what these two terms are because they are terms
that have been built in start-up legacy for the last decade or so but it doesn't mean
to say everybody knows them.
Anybody have any questions on those?
All right good.
So only secret I want to give you here is one simple one which is you want to evaluate
this part of your who you're selling to through the eyes of the customer.
So we talked about who this is let's just focus on the user.
If the user can identify with the product you're selling you're on the right track.
What's the best way to find that out?
Yeah absolutely all of you can do this without spending a single penny just go out and talk
to them and if you're not clear that your user is identifying when you talk to them
with what you're trying to sell them they say well that's not me I don't buy that or
I don't need that or that's not a problem I identify with keep asking until you find
the person who says oh yeah that's the problem I have and keep asking until they say not
only do I have it but then that's where we'll start to get into more of the value proposition
but it's the pain there is big enough for me to actually start to engage with you but
everything you do should be looked at from your user's eyes not from yours in other words
don't pitch them anything ask them everything make sense I see a lot of nodding heads good
all pretty obvious so now that we've we've talked about defining who it's for we're
going to define what we're going to solve for them what problem we're going to define
for them so there's a famous statement here and it's one of my favorite which is a problem
well stated is half solved and the reason that's true is that if you can really clearly
identify what the pain or need or opportunity is that you're going to address becomes very
easy to start getting your team to focus on well what product or service will you build
but imagine if you get in the room and the opposite is true there's five engineers you've
hired for argument sake or five people you're working on a service building a service for
and you can't even agree what it is you're building and or if you didn't do the first
part who you're building it for that's where a lot of startups go wrong by the way is they
can't get that crisp to say we need to solve this particular pain point this hair on fire
pain point for people first so now the question is what's the best way to go about doing that
here are a few frameworks for you first of all this one is a very simple one it's for
use think about problems that are unworkable unavoidable urgent and underserved so those
of you with boards I'm going to recommend you put up just for use and just take a moment
to think about as you are thinking about for example Vivian framing your idea what about
it is unworkable unavoidable and underserved and urgent and I'm going to take you through
each of these I just wanted you to capture the four use on your board so Selene if you
do this I'm sorry stellar if you do the same for Selene health just put them up on the
board for the moment just want to get us used to kind of creating the basis for we can go
through and you're all going to build out your value propositions on your board so just
to be clear so the only person I didn't meet is Sharon hi welcome good to have you here
I know you're building a new kind of bike seat can you just tell us what it's about
yeah I do not yet have a name hence just the word bike seat but I'm specifically looking
at solving the problem of some of the long term health issues that are caused through
for women through biking and I'm doing that through looking at how to design a bike seat
that reduces pressure and friction that's perfect I don't even need to go any further
so I'm going to just ask you to put up these four use and tell me why in your own words
for the moment just one example of something that you think is either unworkable unavoidable
or urgent or underserved you don't need to tell me right away but I'm going to take you
these frameworks and I'll come back to you so I'm giving you a heads up that I'll come
back to you and ask you great now that you've got these let me take you through them so
unworkable is sort of obvious but it's really interesting some people think they've got
an unworkable problem but the real definition of something that's unworkable is that it
is going to cause a problem that when this happens the consequences are so great that
somebody could get fired for it so let me give you an example because it's a very interesting
one and you might have all lived through it so when the iPhone first got introduced people
were lining up to buy them that was the great news the bad news was when they got them they
couldn't get them activated and worse still when they did get them activated all the iCloud
services to do things like download their contacts and their calendars weren't working
either so that problem was so bad so unworkable a lot of people got fired in fact Steve Jobs
was quite famously on a tirade about it and it was a problem that was created by a brand
new technology in a mass market and with a lot of people that obviously were very unhappy
about it and today guess what when you buy an iPhone it's pre provisioned you already
have all of that worked out and that took years actually to figure out I happen to be
one of the investors in a company that solved that problem for carriers on the other side
of this like AT&T was worth tens of millions of dollars just fixing that workflow and making
it possible for you to just pick up an iPhone and turn it on and effectively get your new
number working so these unworkable problems do get people fired they're that painful and
they cause all sorts of things now ideally they're much more interesting than that so
for example we've got social problems where you've got things that are causing people
to get sick or for example not able to get education or like Connected not able to get
that right resources that will help them in a desperate situation then that also is unworkable
you will have your own way of saying it.
Gulnaz would you say what you think is unworkable about Connected?
If I understand it correctly if so if we teach digital literacy skills that kids cannot use
yeah that's useless kind of well no let's put it the other way around what happens if
you don't solve the problem if we don't solve the problem so we are trying to close the
socio-economic gap in Kazakhstan that is also caused by educational inequality okay but
what if what happens in Kazakhstan if we don't solve the socio-economic gap what happens
to Kazakhstan yeah I mean the one example is like people protest this year and there
was like a huge wave of unhappy people great so I mean this it's it's important and I
want to make sure that we give gave you airtime for this not every problem that comes through
the iLab is a problem that's technology like the iPhone's not you know getting to to work
it can be a social problem like this is a really big challenge for a nation that's trying
to develop its people that they can't get the education the resources they need it causes
huge unrest great unhappiness and guess what that population is not going to get out of
their third world status unless they get the education they need this is a really unworkable
problem this is one of the biggest problems of our time is that we have huge social divide
so thank you for addressing it and thanks for taking that mission up that's an example
of an unworkable problem anybody got any questions or an idea of where their particular thing
is unworkable today so I don't know whether let's see who have I not talked to you so
far cohort is there anything about what you're doing that's unworkable we're looking largely
at the improving the graduation rates for black students yeah right what happens if we don't
do that if we don't do this 20% of students won't graduate from high school okay so yeah
I don't even need to say any more than that that's a big problem 20% of students have you
got the data on that already can you show that show that to people yes is public data
right yeah so you're in a great place because you're already starting the problem that's
unworkable you can give data behind it and there are real consequences for that which
is again inequality in our society through not being able to educate people interesting
enough you guys should be talking about how do you connect that and yourselves about how
do you make sure that your value prop comes to life in that way but thank you for sharing
that anybody got any yeah go ahead sure Facebook for instance what unworkable problem did they
solve so the good news about this is you asked what will open up a whole thread here as B
to B versus B to C and Facebook is obviously very much a B to C company and they're very
different sets of problems when you start talking about B to C generally speaking they're
not about unworkable or unavoidable they're much more about what we'll talk about which
is latent problems that are aspirational and that ultimately become blatant and critical
so we're going to get there but don't don't worry it's coming up any other questions on
unworkable first yeah go ahead how do you know that you're not actually hypothesizing
that this is unworkable because I can give an example but a lot of times what you think
is unworkable could just be something else and I'll go ahead and give an example just
to contextualize that for example oral cancer if you think that oh you may just need to
raise awareness but the problem may not be related to awareness the problem may be related
to access of care there's lack of access so you could say you know what's unworkable is
that there's no awareness and you would be blaming patients but in fact there's just
lack of care access to care so yeah you answered your own question by the way which is great
because you said quite rightly it might be this or it might be that and so what would
you do you'd keep drilling on the the question you asked yourself until you found what is
the root cause of it and so honest answer is many times the reason customers sorry startups
fail is because they don't do what you were doing which is to say well it could be this
it could be that who should you go to to ask the question it's on the board yeah just go
and ask the user okay tell me what the real problem is here tell me what's at the root
of this is it lack of awareness or is it lack of availability or is it my inability to use
the product or the service or whatever it might be that makes sense again the answer
is going to be so obvious when I said 90% of the time it's going to be back to what I said
here which is ask the user get to the customer's viewpoint of this and let them tell you where
their pain is what the problem is and why they're not being able to get the solution to it sounds
so obvious but the more you do that the better better off your value proposition is to get
defined all right so next you unavoidable the good news is that everybody in this room faces
two completely unavoidable things what are they taxes and death absolutely right one
of the joys about our lives is that it it does eventually have to come to an end and so taxes
and death or I put a bit more graciously aging a part of the reality of our lives but guess what
because of that there's a whole lot of money that gets made in both those industries like
the aging and the care that goes around that is a huge industry likewise paying tax is a massive
industry and I'm not just talking about QuickBooks and Turbo tax and all those things that that help
out with that it's actually a whole accounting industry that is spawned as a result of the
fact that we have to pay taxes we have to account for what we spend and we have to do all the
things that relate to that so why like this unavoidable part is there are actually a lot
of things that are not so obvious right up to your point earlier at the at the sort of
outset that seem unavoidable until you start to dig and you think about actually you know what I do
need to get my kids educated because if I don't get them educated they're not going to be able to
pay for themselves and get you know self-sufficient and be able to go and build their own lives etc
and so guess what education is pretty much unavoidable too so you know both of you have good
basis to talk about that it's unavoidable also for almost all societies to address that issue at
some level if they're going to be socially and sorry economically viable and so governments do
care about it so again you can get these things to work for you if you can find the right ways to
address them now one of the other things I always love to do here is give an example that is pretty
obvious but how many of you have had COVID at one point it was pretty unavoidable right so what
did we do we all when got vaccinated well maybe not everybody there was a choice but the point is
some health things are also unavoidable and some challenges like that are unavoidable and they
give rise to all sorts of opportunities some of you are even wearing masks in here totally
appropriate guess what that's a whole business that didn't exist beforehand and don't just think
about the mask think about every piece of the supply chain that builds a mask it's a huge business
that came up now we have testing testing has become a huge business because of COVID etc etc so
you see where I'm going with this it's not necessarily something that you face immediately
and say oh that's unavoidable but when you start to think about all the implications of it then you
realize there's lots of businesses that come out of it okay this one is easy urgent so I do
actually want to get another group involved here so Space Health Midori tell me a little bit about
what your business is or your idea isn't and why it might be urgent okay yeah thank you Space Health
has a goal of providing the commercial space sector with a medical professionals for the future
just what the expect didn't see that this industry is going to blow up and you know people that are
going to space for space tourism are going to need medicine in space very cool now I'm going to
challenge you though is that urgent like does everybody in this room feel like they are going
to need health as one of the first things that they spend money on in space I mean health in
space at least not now okay so and I'm not trying to take your idea down but it's one of the most
important criteria is to think about now let's just challenge that for a second and say but to
your point anybody who's going to space so that's the space user the customer if you like who's
came out to space I'm sure they feel like they want to check their health before they go and
they're going to need health and safety when they're up there so I'll eat my words and say if you
can find the right user if you can get in touch with whether it's the space agencies or the people
who are actually you know doing the experimentation up there I'm sure there's a tremendous
opportunity for space health so this is where parts the value prop need to tie together and so
you've got a tremendous opportunity if you can pick that segment that's the for who that really
clearly sees this as urgent and I'm sure they will so thanks for sharing okay so what is a tip
here for all of you is the following urgency is all relative so for those of you are not going to
space you could care less about this right so relatively for you it's not important now let's
take a reality in business which is if you're selling to somebody whether you intend to or not
you're going to compete with something or somebody and that time so lots of you all think you've
got a unique solution but here's the bad news there is finite amount of time money and resource
people and everything else that goes around what you're trying to sell into so you're always going
to have to be something that is at the highest priority if you're going to get people's attention
because guess what they won't spend time with you otherwise so it's no good for example trying
to sell a low-income family a very high-definition television set when they haven't even got the
basics of their food and water running or they aren't educating their family it's just obvious
when I say that well it's the same in truth in business too if you go in to try and pitch
somebody something for example that's a nice to have new extension for example to their existing
workflow system but they haven't got basic security in place and they've just been hacked you're not
going to get any attention so you have to think about what their priorities are now what's the best
way to find this out ask back to the same old question now I'll give you a little clue here
what you want to do here is say rather than even introduce what you do whenever you talk to your
potential user or customer ask them what their number one priority is right now don't ask them
about or don't tell them anything about you just say what's your number one priority if you get up
in the morning tomorrow what's the number one thing you need to focus on and why and then if they
tell you say when do you think you're going to get to number two and then let them tell you
number two oftentimes they won't even get to number two what you'll find out is that there's
some pain point that they really have that's really so compelling that's what they're focused on
and obviously if you can address that you're in a good spot if you can't expect to get delayed
and to get deep prioritized and to be spending time waiting to get engaged on your value problem
so that's why urgent is so important now let me give you another startup secret which is pretty
obvious which is that sometimes certain shifts in the market create urgency so a good example right
now is how many of you have mobile phones duh all of you right but if I'd asked that question 20
years ago it would be none of you that shift has been totally dramatic so what has it done to
every industry it's created urgency for people to respond to it when you bank today using your phone
pretty obvious you don't need to go to a bank for most of the things because you can do it all on
your phone again 20 years ago that wasn't the case and so banks had a very very urgent response
that they had to come up with to be able to make it possible for all the users that now said I don't
want to go to a bank and deal with a teller I just want to do it on my phone and the first
banks that moved there were actually not the existing incumbents there were a lot of new
banks that got started as a result of that trend so you want to look for shifts that create urgency
things like mobile I'll tell you there's another major one that's going on right now which is AI
AI is going to be involved in everything and so everybody's scrambling to figure out well how
do I engage AI to make my process more effective more efficient and save time and money for people
so urgency can be something that you also ride based on shifts in the marketplaces so I'm gonna
ask because I don't know anything about it what is CRSP design essentially we make low-cost so
affordable robotics toys for children starting out in South Africa and to use the framework that
we've got up here why is that urgent so when the idea originally started was a personal problem I
had 20 years ago when I was a child and I wanted to get into the space but growing up in a low-income
family nothing was affordable enough to be able to like for me to access it and then now if you
fast forward to like 2010 2015 the world was moving towards the 4IR fourth industrial revolution
and specifically for Africa we were lagging behind so this was an urgent like issue for me personally
being an engineer at the time realizing that our schooling systems weren't actually solving for this
and I think we also went forward to creating a sense of urgency by helping the government create a
curriculum for this so what this eventually did is now schools have started scrambling looking for
resources exactly like this so there are times when as the startup you can actually identify the
problem before the users even I don't know know they have it and then push forward policy or whatever
that then creates a new market then the issue becomes how do you capture value okay so we will
I'll hold that thought because I call that a latent need to a framework that comes up later
and it's interesting the way you described it too but I would say that's you're going to be challenged
with exactly the thing that I'm describing which is how do you get people to say this is more
important than 10 other things that we could be spending our resources on do you agree yeah so
that's why the urgent is pieces so important all right last you is underserved and this one is pretty
obvious I already gave it away there's only finite time money and resources for you to be able to
engage on things and so you have to help people understand why they should prioritize you but
the underserved piece is an interesting thing particularly in B2C marketplaces so anybody
got a B2C value proposition in here they're selling to consumers yeah of course you do taste of Kenya
so tell me about what do you think's underserved in the market for well it's a coffee market right
essentially yeah so at the moment Kenyan coffee consumers can't afford the Kenyan products in
the market so they buy instant coffee which is from Brazil so none of Kenyan coffee consumers
income can afford the coffee that's being sold in the market so you actually the beauty of your
solution is not only is it underserved in that people can't get the coffee from their own local
market but it's also too expensive so you've got two problems that you're addressing you know both
the pain it's unworkable for people who can't afford it and it's underserved in the sense that
literally there's no supply for it at the moment which is great thank you Zipporah so now that
you've all heard the four use I want you to just take a moment in your group and put down the four
use and take a moment for example on Taste of Kenya and put what one criteria is that you think
we just gave you two makes your product unworkable unavoidable urgent and underserved let's take a
few minutes on that in each group almost everybody's come up with some four use if not all of the four
use line I only have to look around the boards to see that so I'm going to just take one or two
boards and just ask for the rest of you to volunteer so first of all I was lucky enough
to listen to Celine health and Stella and Scarlett are serving a a market for women who obviously
have an unavoidable problem Stella and Scarlett do you want to just talk about that sure so
Celine house going to personalize manual puzzle management for mid-aged women or whoever enters
menopause even though they enter it early so the unworkable part is that when the climatic
symptom hits like hot flush night sweats and it hits it just really decrease their functionality
like among this woman so they cannot work so our solution can help them work that's perfect and
unavoidable it menopause is just unavoidable every like half of this room is going to enter
vulnerable we were talking about earlier aging it's just a reality for women yep urgent
just when the symptom hits when you are not feeling comfortable it is urgent that you
it's just like you get a flu and you need to take medicine or you need to do something you
stop going to work so that is an urgent problem you need to fix right and underserved so currently
if you search online to find articles or research dedicated to pregnancy this age
you have so many million billions of research results coming out but for menopausal age
this population you find barely like a hundred like one in a hundred of them yeah that little
so only two percent of the research funding are devoted to this population so this population
is underserved thank you very much so I had no idea about any of that although without revealing
who it is in my family I have somebody in my family who would say this is really a critical issue
and it does cause her to be literally unable to function at certain period of time and there's
way too little information about it and way too few solutions around it and many women go through
this so all those four yous felt very real to me as I was listening to that and I see a lot of
women in here who are nodding their heads around it so congratulations on finding such a great
four you problem all right just because of time I don't want to go around and do every board there's
too many boards here but I would love to give anybody a chance you had an to say who had an aha
moment I know you guys did for example but I want you to volunteer anybody have an aha moment when
they were going through their four yous and care to share yep go ahead so Hannah just left but
interestingly enough we started off with a bit of a debate and it turns out with some ideas and
I think with our one it could maybe be solved by just having a new policy in place not even
having a business or a startup you know so in those cases I don't know what that means in terms of
the problem you're solving is it one if it's too social focused that you actually can't solve it
as a business and you're better off joining government in lobbying internally well that's a
big aha by the way so one of the things that I always want to say when I mentor at the iLab is
don't be afraid to recognize what you're trying to do is not a good thing to do
uh really seriously because you you know this is your life so you don't want to spend it on
something that's not a real problem that you can solve as a startup and so what you just identified
I think is a great example of that you might realize that actually this is a problem that needs to be
solved in government first with policy so I actually want to give you a round of applause for being
that honest about it I think that's huge that was a big aha anybody else want to share an aha we'll
do one more yeah go ahead Dan for Terraflow um it's a it's a software that helps pharmaceutical
companies understand why the same drug works in some patients but not in others so normally when
I talk about Terraflow I talk about like cancer and the need to get the right drugs to the right
patients but I think really the the problem we're trying to solve is that usually our client is a
scientist that has kind of stuck their head out by convincing the pharma to fund this expensive
clinical trial and they have an unavoidable problem because they have to prove to their vice president
that this experiment was worth it and what our software does is basically provide a very clear
interpretable report that shows to other stakeholders that what they're doing is important
and if they didn't how much money would they lose potentially
um well if if the drug fails to go to market because they didn't discover the right biomarkers
it would be billions there you go so this is what we want to try to do and thank you Dan that was a
brilliant example is we want to try to identify the problem in a way that your user or your buyer
is going to say well of course I need to do this if I don't do this I'm going to lose billions my
drug may not get to market because I can't even identify the right biomarkers now you're going
to get people's attention now you're going to build something that is compelling that causes
people to act and want to buy that's why these four users are so important great example all right
next framework is a fun one it's actually one of my favorites because it addresses this question
that came up with b to c so I think it was you Vivian who asked about facebook so how many of
you use facebook or any of its derivatives like instagram or whatsapp good pretty much everybody
now if I was to say to you why I would argue that every one of you has what some people call
maslow's hierarchy of needs or some other you know form of it social needs security needs
physical needs emotional needs you know economic needs etc these are all needs we have and basically
if we don't have them met we end up in a bad place so what is it that facebook addresses for us
what need is it connection people it's a huge need do you know what the number one cause of
unhappiness in the world is loneliness the number one finding of the longest study at harvard ever
since 1938 of happiness is one thing connection when people have social connection they are happier
so this is a very big need that's what facebook addresses and by the way social networks in
general address now there's lots of other things to do I always joke about it on the other side
which is you know guess what we all want to meet people and date and eventually you know find
somebody to partner with and get married have kids whatever it is not all but generally speaking
that's a huge need so that's why things like bumble took off or at the other extreme why facebook in
the first place took off because people just wanted to connect to get together on on different
things that they had similar interests around huge huge things build from that so anyway b to c if
that makes sense different approach different framework but some similar principle at some
point it becomes unworkable for people for example that are in you know foreign nations to stay in
touch with their families back home without a social network whatsapp took off for that very
reason way too expensive to pick up the phone and call home tremendously cheap to do it on whatsapp
for free basically that's why it took off that was actually a critical need for people there are
whole industries that are built on that for example financial services in the third world is still
incredibly expensive to do things like do basic payments and send money around the place but
on social networks weibo and and tencent in china for example that was enabling of that and solving
of that problem all right so i have an example here that brings it all together and hopefully
it will be a useful one for you to see because it's sort of b to b and it's sort of b to c
does anybody use rent the runway there's a Harvard startup so yeah a couple of you have
okay uh just because you've talked vivian let me ask this young lady at the back
why do you use rent the runway i used it once like 10 years ago because i was going to um
i forget what event in dc and it was easy and i knew i would never need to wear that
like whatever i wore i knew i would take a lot of pictures in and not want to wear it again
okay great so few at the moment it was urgent in that moment you had to go to this event vivian
why did you use it same i am a foreigner i have basic clothes with me in the states only and as i
can see as you can see and i was invited for like a nice event and i couldn't show up in my ex-boyfriend
hoodie actually i think you should have done it would have been a real winner uh but that's
a whole other story so this is a fun story and for those of you don't his name is nicole
that particular garment should go on rent the runway that would make a lot of money
all right so the thing is this is a good example of saying that sort of crosses between b2b and b2c
in lots of different regards so um rent the runway in many ways is unworkable is an unworkable
problem for people who can't afford to go and find a dress or a or an outfit or something for a
particular occasion which they're going to go to sometimes it's a basic thing like a graduation party
and they want to show up it's also underserved in the sense that people can't afford to get
access to those things let alone uh you know do it for one particular thing and it's really
interesting by the way it's unavoidable for certain people who feel like they've got to show up
not in their boyfriend's hoodie but actually looking smart for their parents for example when
they're going to an event uh there's so many reasons why this is something that just was underserved
as a result because the only alternative solution to it was going and spending a lot of money
on a one-off basis that just made it completely unworkable so anyway lots of views about rent
the runway and one of the things that's interesting about it by the way is it's really struggled as
a business despite that and that's because its business model is tough and that's why we did
the session last time so working with a great value prop is not the only part of a business
that's important it's one part of it if you can't make it economically viable which is what we talked
about last session it's still not going to be sustainable so that's how to think about these
two workshops that we just did last time and this time together the second thing I promised to do
was to talk a little bit about the latent need that you brought up so there are oftentimes needs
that start out as latent meaning people don't think about them day to day they're not like at the
top of their mind and aspirational we just gave you an example which is a latent need is to look good
you don't necessarily think of it every day but you do want to get up and feel good and it's
aspirational also in the sense that when you're looking good and feeling good guess what you can
probably feel like more confident to do your job or your work or you know play your sport or whatever
else it is but certain needs evolve to becoming really critical and blatantly so so let's take
an example how many of you have an ipad do you think that's blatantly critical or is it latent
and aspirational critical tell me more tell me more yeah okay so it's turned into your main thing
that you take notes and everything else right okay good so there are people by the way who have the
other extreme anybody here feel like they're on the I just use it when I need to to watch a movie
or whatever Tata interestingly enough I had an ipad for a long time then I wasn't using it that much
I got to Harvard and then I was like oh snap I need a new one because everyone is using it then I
got into HBS classes and they're like no technology allowed so I sent back the one I just bought
so it went from like it wasn't critical then it was critical then I didn't need it anymore
well let me let me tell you why I use the ipad as an example because there's a vast array of people
use them for a lot of different things and some people would say yeah it's kind of nice and other
people would say no I got to have it and when it was first announced people joked about the name
and they said oh it's just a big iPhone why would I want one of those and it really didn't take off
for a long time until people started building applications for it and they became really critical
for certain people so for example if you're a pilot today you might use this for navigation and trust
me it's critical it's not like you're not going to take it with you this is what you use to make
sure you're going to get home so it depends on the application it's also true in medicine for
example that has become critical in certain situations where it's too difficult to use a
keyboard and people just need to write and they just want to for example touch something to actually
activate a particular function in an operating room so it depends on the application so what I try
to say about this framework is as follows try to understand your use case is it something people
think is just nice to have or is it really critical and if you can identify the difference
between something that's nice to have and must have guess which one you want to be in
duh you want to be in the top right there but again ask your user find out what they're doing
with it if the iPad had never made its way into medicine or you know flight navigation or those
other critical applications probably wouldn't have taken off but it's made its way into a lot of
those things and then for some users in the B2C class they critically consider their entertainment
to be like I gotta have entertainment this is a super important thing to me I don't need a
television I'll just have an iPad and there are people who've gone to YouTube as their basis for
educate I mean for entertainment so that's their interface for it anyway fun fun thing for you to
play with I encourage you to put your diagram out there and when you talk to users map where
they're telling you they are ask them how critical this is what else is a priority instead what else
would they do to what they spend their money on if it's not on what you're offering them
any questions on that before I move on yeah Victor just follow me up on that when they built the
iPad they didn't know they are going to need to build that many applications on it right yeah so
they didn't really solve a critical problem at the time of building the the application so how
would you think about if you have the chicken egg first or the egg first so let's take a moment to
answer Victor's question because it's a very important one which is you know the chicken and egg
question comes up a lot so you've got an idea and you think there's some opportunity out here in
the market I realize I've just drawn the same diagram I've drawn above but anyway it's starting
afresh the answer is that one of the most amazing things about Steve Jobs is he was somebody that
people said never talked to users he's famous for it he's like it was his idea to come up with the
iPad but what he was brilliant at was identifying it great vision for what this thing could be
and then he built the important piece which is a whole business opportunity for many markets
which is a platform that said anybody in here can take my device here use my platform and build
the application they particularly need and so guess what hundreds then thousands then tens
of thousands now millions of applications have been built for that platform and this is a business
model that is really fascinating and whole study in of itself that we could get into it's a very
viable way to build products what it really says is as follows you've got to make this platform
easy enough for your idea to be adopted by the users and to solve their own problem for example
you remember in the last session I told you that open source works this way it says that anybody
can take the code that you offer for example to create and I mentioned websites and Acquire and
Drupal the idea of a website and extend it any way they want to make their website capable of
integrating Instagram at one extreme and at the other extreme Salesforce to be able to do things
like give people a great experience when they go to the Grammys and take photographs and upload
them to the site and at the other extreme have a close relationship with all those customers so
they can keep selling them other things like records and merchandise and everything else
that is a whole industry now experience management and it was built on a platform
an open source platform just like the iPad was an open platform for people to develop applications
well a counter example would be pebble right they came up with spot collection and now they're gone
so great so what was wrong with pebble
anybody know this this particular product well you do so what what do you think was wrong with it
I don't know I think it fits the framework like it answers all the views and black and white question
but then really was it urgent it's as urgent as an Apple watch what was it open I think it runs
Android so various things that I I don't want to get drawn into this too much but I will tell you
I wrote an article you can find it on LinkedIn when I bought my first Apple watch I offered it
to anybody who wanted to tell me why there was a reason to keep it because I didn't think there
was a need for it it actually was a useless gadget when it first came out it was like it
didn't even stay on I had to do this to be able to look at the time I mean it was like
and there were no applications for it to speak of so I think it was a bit like the pebble and
what worked was that they had a development platform again and they had a large developer
user base who started create applications now there's no way I would give up my Apple watch
it's now used for some critical things like my health I monitor my sleep with it all
sorts of other things my blood pressure all sorts of things so it's become critical to me and by the
way actually for timekeeping which is a big part of my job that I need to get back on time it is
actually the thing that keeps me on time so with that I'll just simply say let's talk afterwards
because it's a great discussion like a lot of things there aren't answers but there are questions
you could ask in the frameworks that would reveal to you why pebble would be successful and why
apple watch sorry wasn't successful why apple watch was successful some of which by the way is
marketing too all right when you start building your product there are a whole set of things that
are basically dependencies that you want to be aware of and I talk about this in the workbook
because you need to get a couple of concepts clear and they basically are how your product
actually fits into the solution that the customer has and so I will say it and then you can go and
look in the workbook the first concept is that your product is very unlikely to be the whole
solution that a customer has and we started talking about smartphones so I'll just give you an example
why is a smartphone its own not a whole product
what what do you need with a smartphone to make it useful go ahead
apps apps yep what else
yeah absolutely it's absolutely useless into you unless you have a carrier and unless you have
some apps for it although I'd say one of the apps is built in which is the phone but the point is
that almost every product if you look at it has some aspects of it that need to make it a whole
solution for the customer so that's the first concept you'll find in the workbook the second
one is once you realize that you realize well actually you have dependencies on your product
being successful like if there weren't networks and I gave you the example that when the phones
couldn't be provisioned on networks they were just bricks they were useless or if you don't have the
app that solves your particular problem it's also useless to you so what you want to do is figure
out what are those dependencies those external factors that you need to work with in order for
your product to meet the needs end to end the solution if you will and if you don't pay attention
to those again you'll be selling something that can't really solve the problem that you're trying
to address so it's in the workbook you can go look it up there's some examples including apple
pay which is quite a fun one and also Tesla which is another fun one which is still to this day
having a big dependency on charging stations and the availability of electrical you know
access for people to really say oh I'm definitely going to buy a Tesla I know lots of people who
won't because they just know they can't rely on it so debt is an important thing to think about
next up is what we want to make sure happens in a positive way for you which is how do you make
sure you really do cut through the noise so every startup I know will say that they are
some way faster better cheaper you're all nodding your heads and I'm sure that that's
true for a lot of your things so anybody think that they are not faster better or cheaper
is probably not in this room they probably like decided oh I'm really not in the right place
David you're having a good laugh about this so are you working on something that you think is
faster better cheaper tell me more about it we're going to help David get beyond this by the way
so I'm in the the travel space so what I'm doing is I'm developing
an app that would help customers
find outrageously cheap airfares so what we're dealing with
at least you know I mean it could vary but 30 to 90 percent off okay
good I'm going to just hold that for a second is there any other thing about it that's that's
better because you said cheaper basically but is it better because it's faster or it's so
that would probably be the the tech behind it right so the sauce behind it I would call it
but to the customer is there any reason why they say oh this is way better it's a better
experience is it easier than travel velocity or you know pick if I so it it works in a totally
different form so basically the customer tells me where they want to leave from yep but they're
never telling me where they want to go to necessarily interesting so this is this sounds
interesting I'm just going to put it destinationless okay that's definitely different
so by the end of this class I want you to come up and tell me whether we can get rid of
but faster better cheaper and come up with a better framework for you and I'm going to start
talking a little bit about why I think it's a dangerous thing so the reason I hate faster
better cheaper is that there are people out there have more resource than you do as a startup
so if kayak or travel velocity or pick your favorite decided to come after you David they're
going to have more resource to try to put whatever it is the tech behind what they do and so there's
probably something in your secret source that is more than just faster better cheaper maybe it's
something that's defensible maybe it's some IP maybe it's something beyond the tech it's a network
the way you actually connect to people to get the data for your affairs there may be a whole bunch
of things but in the end we want to make sure that you end up there and here's why if you can get
to what we call a 3d breakthrough something that's truly disruptive truly discontinuous
and really defensible then you as a startup have a chance even with small resources in fact it's
the story of why startups succeed is that they make these big breakthroughs they punch through the
noise with something that's just completely disruptive like a business model like google had
to use advertising and selling sell instead of selling software to give away their office suite
where microsoft was having to get you to pay for it it was totally disruptive it caused
microsoft to be a dial tone as a stock for many years that's what we mean by this so let's get
into these 3d's and see if we can identify some for you so first of all disruptive is as I said
sometimes a technology but often a business model like airbnb changed the travel industry
they didn't actually invent anything they don't even own the homes that you go and visit or the
places you go and stay at what they created was a means to connect people and give them experiences
by sharing resources that other people were not using genius right that could have been invented
sitting here tonight and that's one of the things that's so exciting about business models is why
we spent time on it last time but then there are also technologies so I would argue multi touch is
one of these multi touch was such a game changer because the minute you could use that interface
now instead of having to have a dedicated user interface for every single thing you did so remember
that example of in the operating theater imagine if you had all the all the instruments that you
needed to work with on a one single interface that could change during the operation as you were
going through various different stages of it I'm describing a real thing by the way as opposed to
you have to go to every single instrument learn that interface and figure out when you go and find
you know how to use it no it just flows for you and actually it's monitoring the patient at the
real in real time too so you can actually see what you need to spend time on a way you need to focus
that's what multi touch did it can save lives it's that critical it's not just for playing games on
phones but by the way it's a very big industry too so that's what we want to try to have you find
so that's what we mean by disruptive now I'm going to use an example was Amazon a disruption
when it first came out no why not because that's what did the same in the UK was the first in the
united kingdom who did it commerce my best knowledge okay very good anybody else think it was a
not a breakthrough nothing new in the way of products but why is why is the success of Amazon
then been so great and by the way I want to hear why you think it wasn't like a breakthrough too
I'm just as interested somebody over here I think said it wasn't yeah go ahead Dave well I think
Amazon because just of the success in marketing right or just being user friendly you know just
getting to the customer because what I what I'm discovering is a lot of these big companies that
people kind of like in a way idolized they're just older ideas that other people had before
you know that's all it is there's nothing really new but they just happen to blow up
and not everyone know their name okay so they became bigger they had more scale
they became faster they became better and they became cheaper which is why it's really dangerous
to try to compete with them but yet they succeeded so I would argue the reason they succeeded was
and there was in Jeff Brazos's quote you all see this this these trucks driving around
no other business gave you these two things it wasn't do you want low prices or do you want
fast delivery you can have both by the way there was actually a third if you read his quote
is to go backwards which was choice and in fact it was how it was how they first got going
Amazon succeeded as a bookstore to start off with because you couldn't get access to the
long tail of books that people wanted literally physically you couldn't get access you had to
go find those books in bookstores and suddenly they said nope we'll find you any book on the
isban code or wherever it is in the world that you need to get access to so it was it was first
and foremost selection but then when they really focused in it became actually not even selection
but fast prices I mean sorry fast delivery and low prices so it is actually a breakthrough
it's a breakthrough that they managed to do because they built huge scale and they got the
economies of scale to put behind that it's also a fascinating example for another D
so that's the disruption they first had it was discontinuous what came next discontinuous is
something that you couldn't do before this next thing what is that AWS cloud computing was invented
by Amazon and why did they why were they able to invent it because they got such scale in their
operations that their compute resources became accessible at a price that was so marginally
efficient to sell to other people that now people could start using the cloud as it became known
as a basis to build their own business they rented their if you will their hardware infrastructure
their storage and their compute to people who wanted to use it and they had such economies of scale
that it was actually extremely effective for them to do that we're actually leveraging something
that already built the huge data centers etc to do that that story by the way was told right here
in this iLab by the guy who got behind it well actually created it Andy Jassy who's a donor to
this iLab and it's an interesting story to listen to so it's something that started out as a
disruption it became a discontinuous innovation it gave rise to cloud computing anybody here using
the cloud i'm sure terror flow must be yeah almost all of you are huge game changer i mean
and what's interesting about it and this is where i want you to think about discontinuous
things is you couldn't do certain things today without the cloud so pretty much everything we
do on our mobile phones couldn't do without the cloud and anything that you're thinking about
in terms of for example how we solved this problem of working after covid how would we have done that
if we hadn't had the cloud we'd have all disappeared and been unable to communicate and connect and
do zoom and all those other things so these are discontinuous innovations that's what those
things are about and then finally the third D is how does it become defensible so there are lots
of ways things can become defensible here are a few examples you can have great IP that's the
typical one some breakthrough innovation so i'm going to guess here that dan you would say something
about terror flow is going to be protectable as ip am i right okay and are you going to go
after a patent for it perhaps even possibly so if you don't is there some effect that you think
you'll have that will cause customers to get to say that hey we will not take terror flow
out of our business once we've got working it i've got it working with us
will it become part of their end-to-end way that they bring drugs to market for example
okay and once it does will they take it away no because it's the way they're used to interpreting
the data and communicating internally so that gets to what i call switching costs it's a whole
discussion at uh mba level that we talk a lot about once something becomes adopted by your
customers and it's proven to be very effective it's really difficult to take it away from them
and actually i will say the same keep using the same example if i gave you a brand new
spanking you know best in class phone but i told you you had to give up your phone number for it
and you had to change carriers for it would you adopt it you would okay most people would say no
there's a couple that say yes so it's not an always absolute thing but the point is there
are switching costs associated with everything similarly like if i said to you you could go to
another university but it doesn't teach your course well of course even if that university is way
less expensive and maybe easier to get to it doesn't teach what you need so it's what you're being
delivered and how you're being delivered it and how difficult it is to adopt it that is important
when you start to think about defensibility so think about network effects think about switching
costs think about ip think about things that give your your customer a basis to work with you
that causes them to say i wouldn't want to switch i wouldn't want to go anywhere else
this is something that i've got used to and then my favorite example of this is follows
so if i came up with a much better social network like you loved the way that you could post photos
it was way easier but nobody else was on the network would you adopt it of course not nobody
to share anything with that's why there's such huge defensibility in the networks that have been
built like instagram and whatsapp etc so networks is a very good example of it and then data is a
fascinating part of it so vivian's building a an actionable data product for marketers
if your data gets broadly used everywhere and more and more marketers contribute to it so it
becomes better and better what's your competitive advantage in what's your moat
that i am going to be the person who understands the human face the most there you go you will have
more data on why people are doing things what it is and by the way what vivian's doing is really
fascinating she's giving people the ability to read what it is that users are responding to
and if she has better data on that than everybody else guess what that's incredibly powerful for
marketers and the more people that use it the more data she'll get the stronger a network
effect will be the bigger her moat will be you're nodding but i'm making this up as i go is that
true good all right so now it's your turn i want to have each of you take your value prop and tell
me what you think could be i'll go back to the 3d's defensible disruptive and also discontinuous
about it and let's help you do all do that so i'll walk around and make sure you do it so get
your 3d's up and let's get some help for those i'm going to just tell you that everybody's coming
up with very good 3d's so first of all i was most surprised by taste of Kenya because consumer
products are very difficult to create defensibility with but um Zepora and her team have got a great
answer to this and if i get this wrong tell me they've got tenure contracts that they're writing
with people which is locking them into a situation sorry go ahead with the farmers
which is locking them into a place where other people won't be able to compete as i understand it
and then over here i was really excited when i heard a little bit about space health and why is it
disruptive it's a new and scary we're always going to be going pretty obvious space in of itself is
a whole disruptive industry it like changes the notion that we're actually bound to our planet
very disruptive and it's actually becoming an industry because of that and there are a whole
bunch of things that are changing because of the fact that we can access space very very interesting
i mean we're thinking about all sorts of new industries as a result of that new materials
that we might create new forms of for example life that we might explore etc so it's very disruptive
okay so i was also very excited when i heard about cohort first thing i heard from them
about what's disruptive sorry discontinuous is what used to be an education an analog is now
being turned digital by them that's a great example very disruptive things going from analog to
digital perfect example of discontent a discontinuity all right then we came to Sharon's new bike seat
i was thinking oh bike seat that can't be that you know defensible but then
i heard that what she's doing is actually measuring all the data in use while the bike
seat is being ridden and the form of the bike seat is changing on the fly as a result of that data
now the question that i didn't get to hear is why is it defensible uh defensible ip with the
technology and then the other thought was like long-term contracts with bike share companies
don't you think your data will become defensible at some point too that as well and it's important
because women specifically in a lot of issues but in bike health issues are understudied as well
so there's actually not enough data about that right all right so i could keep going around the
room but just for time i won't i will encourage you all now to start thinking about instead of
talking about better faster cheaper what do you do that's disruptive discontinuous and defensible
because that's going to set you up for success and look at all the great ideas you have you've
all got a great basis to go defend your business and to to make it really stand out in this breakout
way so well done very very exciting okay so we're on to the last leg and this is the piece that
hopefully will help you decide whether you've got a business that's worth pursuing and that's how you
evaluated so your business or your value proposition needs to be something that is going to last and
endure and be sustainable and so there are only a few frameworks here but they're quite important
the first one is something i've already been testing with you as we've been going through
this evening what was the situation before your product and what is the situation after your product
so for argument's sake saline health if people don't get any cure for the challenges they address
with going through menopause they're going to be out of work a lot and dysfunctional a lot
and they're going to obviously have personal health issues on top of all of that
that may lead to other complications in their life so that's pretty clear what the before is
the after is what would you say higher productivity among those women
they just they just function normal and give back their life that like a high quality of life
they should have so literally you could say acute pain or absolute joy and there might be a whole
bunch of other things that you might expound on this and i'd encourage you to really go to the
absolute extreme if you possibly can't say if their mothers for example that they might be able to
look after their families and sustain that their livelihoods as mothers etc or if their
workers obviously that they're you know they're they're supporting their community etc there's a
lot of things that could could be great if they get their health back whereas if they don't they're
dysfunctional in their their situation in life so try to bring those things out the other
other thing thing about this is where you get challenged is when you are a consumer product
and i i put um taste of kenya up here which is sometimes people will say something is well
it's nice to have it's like a vitamin versus you know a morphine so i have a question for you
because i know you've got the answer which is why do you think the before and after and in uh
you know taste of kenya is so powerful so to the farmers if we don't serve them they're going to
cut down their coffee trees so coffee is going to be extinct in kenya uh for the consumers
they're never going to have a half to drink ever going to get to drink kenyan coffee okay
so it's pretty much a national issue at some level the way you just described it which is great
so anyway the before and after we want to make sure that you can say it in a way that this is
something that's not a nice to have vitamin but it is really a necessary penicillin or morphine
or something that is actually vital to their health now it's not always going to be the case
but the more you can define it in those terms which is so critical to people they say okay
yeah i've got to have that then the more likely you are to be able to say great i'm on to a good
track so just because i'm again going to keep us on time i encourage you to just do this as a
t diagram when you're doing your um your value prop just do the before and after and you can do that
anytime obviously very easy exercise to do the more you can speak to your customers again back
to this whole approach to don't ask this in a vacuum speak to your your user your customer and say
tell me all your problems before and remember you want to get them to list those all as long as you
can and then if we deliver this for you what will it look like afterwards what will be all the things
that you'll be celebrating that you can now do that you couldn't do before whether it's getting
your health back or it's whether it's drinking your favorite coffee or whether it's being able to
for example get access to the engineering talent that you didn't have before or whether it's making
sure your data actually is delivering the right insights that you need as in terribly there are
all these things that you'll be able to do and that's critical to put out on your value prop
make sense one question how do you actually make sure that that is something you could measure
that's what this next framework is so the gain pain ratio is incredibly simple and yet very powerful
and what it is is it's measuring the gain you deliver to your customer versus the pain for
them to actually adopt what you do now i'm almost certain that all of you could tell me all the
gain that you deliver but i'm almost certain that you probably couldn't tell me all the pain
and the challenges of adopting it so let's talk talk you through an example so how many of you
use venmo great me too became really obvious to me that first of all you know just sending money
to pay for basic things and services why on earth would i write a check ever again
totally the most dumb thing it's become so convenient it was very easy to use from the
minute i started using it however it wasn't always that way and the pain that first went on
as venmo got first adopted was it was yet another app for users to use they had to connect it to
their bank and they weren't sure whether it was really secure and to start off with not everybody
had it so it wasn't really that useful because the network didn't exist and this is sort of the
cold start problem that a lot of you might have with your idea so you got to think about all
of that and you also got to remember all those things so here's my tip for you which is super
easy which is when you go to talk to your customer don't pitch them your idea again ask all the
reasons why they have pain but then ask them this one question what are all the reasons you would
not buy my product so why would you not buy this product tell me all the reasons and keep asking
that question over and over and over again until you get them to tell you all the pain points they
would have i can give you a clue about some of them number one is well i don't really need it that
badly so guess what i could use the alternative well that's a bad starting point so you're gonna
have to figure out you know why and what is it that they don't like about the alternative that
actually if you gave them something way better they might use it the second might be cost that's
always an easy excuse but then there's other things that are not so obvious like for example
training how do i retrain people to use this new approach to doing things or if you're selling a
bike seat it might be as basic as well my supply chain is already in place and i don't want to
change and disrupt that it's too easy for me to just buy all the component parts i have they're
already cheap and you'd slowed all down i've had to design this new bike seat in and get all this
new data you know flowing into this new device and that'd be a new complication for me to worry
about how is that all going to fit with this thing i sell already very effectively called a bike i'm
making it up but it's the kind of thing you want to pull out before you you know end up saying okay
i've got my value prop nailed so let's keep going with the venmo example the other thing that's always
there is a startup in the middle of this equation is inertia and the risk of you as a startup being
something that a customer is going to rely on so do i really need this is one of the things but
also what happens if i put my money in this network and this startup fails i just lost
whatever money i was sending to people that's a huge risk people don't want to do that unless
they feel like oh this is like bank like security so these are things that you have to think about
upfront by the way there's some things that you know these products often don't think of initially
such as well how can i split the bill and do the tips then we figured that out and eventually
they got through that issue so whatever it is that you have assume that there's a reason why people
will initially resist you even if it's just that you're a startup and they don't take a risk on you
and think about how you'll overcome that so now the question is what's the right ratio
of gain to pain before somebody will take a risk on you
anybody want to take a guess yep go ahead no pain well that would be awesome so it'd be infinite
so your ratio is infinite i love it all right go ahead dan why 10 to 1 because you got to get
people over that activation energy yeah to me get excited about your product and make it a priority
yeah so what's interesting about bigger faster better sorry cheaper better faster is do you think
30 to 90 cheaper is going to cause people to do something to change how might they might use
for example their travel and what it caused david's business to take off
we're not asking david so we're asking you anybody what does anybody think
yes yeah i would say for certain users yeah so why i always say this there are not answers here
i would agree with both viewpoints so for certain classes of user for example if you are selling
to a pharma company and they're you know doing experimentation i would say 10 to 1 is probably
right because it's very expensive for them to go change their workflows to develop new drugs
but for a consumer if you're going to offer a 30 to 90 cheaper solution david might really
be onto something i would want to you know save that money maybe even 10 percent would be enough
for the threshold maybe not maybe 20 maybe anyway you get my point you've got to measure this
and you've got to ask your user and you've got to be clear what's the threshold view on the gain
pain ratio where you would make a change that would make you take the risk and get over the inertia
that's why this is such a useful formula can i ask a question about that example um because i feel
like there's the pain of maybe like switching platforms you normally use to look for travel but
it strikes me that with that particular example there's another pain of changing the way you travel
because you're not putting in a destination so i'm wondering how you think about those two because
one seems like more a longer term shift that you're trying to prompt so i'm going to let you and
david debate that afterwards but because it's it's specific to him the principle though is still the
same which is what you're asking david to do is say david why would i take this risk and why would
i use your service versus what i'm already doing and i'll give you an answer that i think is important
to sort of use in a general sense so that it's not about david's business which is if the customer
has something that they're comfortable with and you really are not giving them at least an order of
magnitude improvement in something or a significant gain in something they're not going to do anything
life's too short they're too busy they'd rather just carry on doing whatever they're doing the greatest
inertia and the greatest reason that people fail is because they're not solving a valuable
enough problem that where the gain pain ratio is big enough that somebody will make a change
or that'll adopt something and it can be on either side of this equation too by the way
for example let's use an example a case in point that we've all experienced which is
it's incredibly easy to download an app it's point click download the app so that pain if you
will of trying something is incredibly low but then if you start using it and it's no good it's
also incredibly easy to just point click delete so you've got to find something that is really
valuable on a sustainable basis for somebody and ideally make it so easy for them to adopt it that
it's going to be a very successful go-to-market motion for you when you start selling it and
that's what this pain gain ratio is all about so by the way venmo did some very clever things they
added all these security measures they made sign up so easy for example you could just scan a qr code
to pay in certain situations and there are a whole set of things that became obviously so simple
that we've all adopted it and it's now friction-free and because the network's there we talked about
that too it's obviously got huge defensibility because nobody else is going to just disrupt that
because all the people that you already pay on venmo it's just one click for you to pay them
obvious stuff right so let me make sure that you get a clear idea of what are the things to
look for on gain pain so first of all on the gain is pretty obvious you know how much money do you
make people how much time do you save them all that stuff you're going to you're going to nail
that I know that's not the problem on the pain side don't forget how you are going to have to help
people find you try you buy you adopt you get trained into your system and everything else
that's associated with owning you all of that is pain all of that has to be factored into your gain
pain ratio and in the middle don't forget all these things that are associated with what ultimately
come down to risk and are inertia for people to change anything if you do that you have the basis
to evaluate your value prop and you're in the power seat at that point because you can keep telling
yourself your thing's great but until you see that tipping and customers are pulling you to market
and saying yep this is really something I've got to adopt you know you haven't got it right
so uh teraflow was easy for me to to pick down I would say you have work to do on your your gain
plane because the way you expressed your value prop is very clear like for you know translational
scientists and we know the who is for with traditional r package you know ours of those of you
don't know hugely widely adopted language that's used for statisticians um due to you haven't quite
got the unmet needs yet so that's great you probably can figure that out I might say based
on what I've learned the inability to gain the insights necessary to define the data data path
for them uh teraflow offers the platform but allows scientists to extract clinical breakthroughs
now you're going to have to decide how will you declare that as at least an order of magnitude
since that's the term you came up with better than the alternative of doing nothing because
otherwise they will do nothing make sense okay good so I will just simply say we got to the end
naturally otherwise which is you already know where we're headed I already told you what the
value prop is I gave you the statement up front now what I'm going to just just put it all together
for you which is this value prop statement is actually built by all the frameworks we just took
you through and again this is in the workbook so the four piece defining who it is for use this
minimum viable segment again that's in your workbook I drew it very briefly here and talked about
how do you find the same needs that you can address with your first product don't get pulled
all over the place find a set of users for whom you have the same needs your minimum viable segment
check that they are blatant and critical needs ideally rather than latent and aspirational
that's the black and white framework or if they start latent and aspirational be clear how you're
going to get them the question that Victor asked from just using something that was just a basic
platform a basic product like an iPad to a place where it becomes mission critical
and then how do you define what's urgent and underserved and unworkable etc that's the four
use if your audience tells you that if your customer tells you that then you know you're
dealing with the right customer and you've identified the right pain points for them
same with what are they dissatisfied with things that are unworkable
if they really are unworkable they're not going to put up with it and if they're underserved in
other words they're not being able to get for example the coffee they need or for example the
comfort they need or the travel access they need or the safety they need or the health they need
etc then spell it out that's where it'll go in your value problem and then don't just say it's
faster better cheaper tell people why it's disruptive and it's a discontinuous innovation
it's gone digital as opposed to used to be analog or it's now online and accessible and then
it provides something which you want to make sure they are very clear is an order of magnitude
breakthrough and that's where you use the gain-prane ratio you don't just say it's x you say it's
10x and here's why because for you to adopt it even with the pain of you know retraining etc
you're going to get this enormous gain that is compelling and then finally it's unlike the
things that at the moment are also unworkable for one reason or another or are not addressing your
need or underserved it's your value problem so with that we're finishing one minute early now
any questions before we wrap up
yeah go ahead Sappora could you please walk us through the black again
so a lot of products might start out as being something that in this framework
latent and aspirational in other words people would like to have this is a nice to have
but really where you want to get to is a place where it's blatant
and critical
so this is a must-have so i don't need to tell any of you this but
all the things that are subsistence for you are must-haves food water health anything that
enables you to do your job they're all must-haves all the things down here like well depending
on the thing you like but you know what you spend your money on is your business but entertainment
might be a nice to have in certain circumstances compared to health pretty obvious to state that
or fashion might be a nice to have versus comfort i mean versus you know it's winter in boston so
things that protect you from the cold i mean there's just basic ways to define things that
are nice to have versus must-haves the more you can understand how you move from the nice tab to
the must have the better does that make sense great okay so i'll let you come up and ask any
questions you like but i want to finish now on time so thank you very much for for joining in on
this i will say that the most important thing in all of this is that it's built around you so if
you don't uniquely understand the problem you're addressing then why are you doing it
because you're going to face a lot of competition from people who do know better than you then which
case what can your solution deliver uniquely well is what we've been spending all this time on
based on what you know that also can be built around you and finally if you can bring that
all together around what we talked about last time around a disruptive business model then it's
going to be sustainable and so this is oftentimes what people refer to as founder market fit it's
why you are uniquely in a position to solve this particular value prop and and do it in a way that
is sustainable with a business model that we talked about last week so in summary have fun defining
it have fun evaluating it and make sure it's built around you and you'll have a great company thanks
very much it's been a pleasure