Hello, can everyone hear me?
The mic on and everything.
Good to go.
Thank you, Boodle.
And thank you for having me here.
All right, I had a totally different talk plan
and then Phil's talk was really cool.
And then I was like, oh, I'll do something
with Lambda Calculus and Mini-Canron.
And then I was talking to people last night
and basically Andrea and Mark and Stefan,
a few other people convinced me to try something
like much more radical than I normally do
with my live coding.
So I want you all to be doing live coding,
at least anyone who's interested.
So if you can get out your lapis and go to this URL,
and that holds doubly true for anyone watching on video.
This is specially designed so that people in the audience
and people on video can kind of follow along.
And basically what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna check in
the code as I'm talking and I'll let you know
when I did a check-in so you can do a poll,
so you can sync up with me.
And there's a really cool web-based version
of Mini-Canron that David Kahn created.
And you can just paste that code into the web browser
and you should be able to run Mini-Canron, okay?
So we'll try that and it might crash and burn.
We'll just see how it goes.
But the great thing is if someone's watching a video
afterwards they should be able to follow along and stop.
And if anyone here is confused about something,
you can't get an example to run or whatever,
you can ask a question, okay?
Or you can take it offline, whatever.
But it's one thing to show this stuff,
but at some point people will have all these questions
and if you can't really play with it,
you don't really get the sense, I think, of what it's about.
So I want everyone to be able to try it.
Okay, so the web browser version of Mini-Canron
is at this link right here, the veneer stuff, okay?
All right.
So here's my repo and I've got a file called talk.scm
and that's where I'm gonna have my code in it.
And the way I'm gonna do this is I'm gonna basically type
into the code into Emacs and then I'll paste it into veneer
and that's basically what y'all can do in terms of
opening up the file and get pasting into veneer,
running it and you can edit it in your own text editor,
you can edit it in veneer.
And I encourage you to try some different combinations
or different queries and see if you can break it,
see if you can run in infinite loops,
which you probably can, and so forth.
And if you have a cool example, you can share it.
This is, by the way, like version 0.01 of the technology
I would really like for giving interactive talks
where either Super Emacs mode or a web browser
or something like that where people in the audience
really could do this more seamlessly,
but that's tech I'm working on with other people
like Michael Valentine.
All right, so let's talk about mini-canon
and I'm gonna bring up the veneer editor,
let me refresh.
If veneer ever gets in a bad state,
you can just click refresh.
Let's see, is there, I can kind of make the font bigger.
The way you use veneer is if you've got code
on the left-hand side, you click the run button
and it'll evaluate this code and there's like
a little redeval print loop thing
you can just type for small expressions
if you wanna try those, okay?
And this is a relational scheme interpreter,
which we'll play around with something like that in a minute.
The main button you're gonna care about
is this create file button.
So if you create file, it's gonna blank whatever's
on the left, then you can just type in code here,
mini-canon code, and then click run
and it'll be evaluated on the right-hand side.
So let's just try something simple.
So I said I'll go to Emacs, but well,
let me try doing it in the veneer.
First of all, is the font big enough?
Can people see that?
I can try to bump it up a little bit.
If the run button will cooperate.
Maybe I can, there we go, look.
That run button's oversized.
Okay, so the first thing I'm gonna show,
so mini-canon, core mini-canon only has three operators.
It's a very small language, just like lambda calculus
is very small, right?
Lambda calculus has three parts,
and so does mini-canon for the core parts of the language.
And you can extend it, just like you can extend
mini-canon to get something like scheme, right?
So the most fundamental operator in mini-canon,
and mini-canon's a type of logic programming language,
like Prolog, it's got some real differences as well,
the fundamental operator is something called unification.
And unification you can think of as sort of like
a two-way super pattern matcher.
So if you're familiar with pattern matching,
then in a pattern match, you have some value
you're pattern matching against,
and then you've got some sort of pattern, right?
And in the pattern, you can have variables,
we call those match variables, or pattern variables, okay?
And those pattern variables get values filled in
from the value you're matching is.
Similar with unification, except you can have essentially
pattern variables on each side, okay?
So you can have variables on both sides.
And the variables don't actually ever have to be filled in.
That's fine also.
Variables don't ever have to get values in this paradigm.
So here we're gonna do something simple,
and you can also think of unification,
we call it equal, equal here really.
It's like a type of a quality operator also.
So here we're asking whether or not five is equal to five.
Or another way to look at it is we're asserting
that five must be equal to five.
And if it's not equal to five,
then we've reached inconsistent conclusion basically.
So is five equal to five?
One would hope, okay, yeah.
The logic isn't that weird, so let's run it.
And you can see, copy the expression,
and the answer is yes, well that's good.
That makes me happy.
All right.
Okay, so I promised I would do the interactive thing.
So here's our first program.
Equal, equal five, five, and I will check that in.
Okay.
So, are you supposed to like, how do you do this thing?
You do like a get add or something?
Get upload?
Add dot.
Oh, whoa, okay.
And I'm not really good at get, so.
And then get commit, is that how you do it?
Oh yeah, they do it.
Okay, so get commit, and I have to give a message,
and I'll say one is the message,
because that's the first one.
Okay?
All right, so you're following along,
that's the first, so you can do a pull,
and you can paste that complicated program into veneer.
Let's all do it, make sure we get the tech working,
and then click run, and you should be able to see yes, okay?
That's the first program, great.
Okay.
Yes.
For future reference, instead of doing the get add,
you can just put in dash A on the get commit.
Get commit dash A, ooh, yeah, okay.
All right, I like this, I'm learning.
Okay, so we can do another program, let's do a variant.
This is program number two.
What about six and five?
No.
No, that's right.
Computer says no.
All right, so.
What's about the proof of this?
The proof of it?
Okay, what is it?
Well, hold on, let me check in, my code, I promised.
Okay.
I guess I could, I could like,
look, like get keeps track of revisions.
So I'm not even gonna add another expression.
I'm just gonna like do that, and then it works, all right?
So I could do get, was it?
Get commit dash A, ooh, dash A and then two, right?
Do a pull.
Okay, so what's your question, Boodle?
You wanna know about the proof?
Why is five equal to five?
Well, let me change it up a little bit,
and maybe I'll answer your question.
I'm gonna put in something else.
Instead of a number, so having two numbers,
I'm gonna put in X, and X is a logic variable.
So you can think of it sort of like
this pattern variable, right?
Okay, so, so is X equal to five?
Yes, we don't know yet.
Yes, we don't know yet, okay?
We don't know, it could be, if X doesn't have a value yet,
then now it does have a value, right?
The answer is yes, and X is five.
But if X is already six, then the answer is no.
All right, so we don't really know,
but I'll say that X is starting out fresh.
We say fresh, it doesn't have a value yet.
So let's run that, yes, and beyond yes,
we see that X has a value associated with it, five, okay?
All right, cool.
Yeah, what?
What did that work?
Oh, I didn't say it.
Oh, you're right.
I got this hard, okay.
All right, so that's one thing we can do, all right?
And so if you look at it this way,
then basically what we're really saying is an assertion.
We're saying that the thing on the left
is syntactically equal to the thing on the right.
As long as you kind of find some set of values
that are assigned to these variables inside the terms
that will make them syntactically equal, right?
So the question is, is there any possible assignment for X
that will make the left and right hand side equal?
And the answer is yes, as long as X is five,
then they'll be equal, okay?
So that's the sort of reasoning you do with unification.
And we can even put variables on both sides, X and Y.
So what should the answer be here?
Yes, and furthermore, what else do we know?
We know that Y is five.
Well, let's say we got rid of the original program, right?
This is the whole program now, so there are no fives anymore.
X and Y are the same, presumably.
And so we can see here that X and Y
are both associated with some value.
And this itself is a representation of a logic variable
that doesn't have a value.
And you can see that they have the same number.
If they were different, you'd see a one here
in one of them and a zero in the other.
So it's telling us it really is the same,
the same logic variable, okay?
I'm gonna get the hang of this soon, so that's...
So the definition of the point to that,
that's not too much you can make?
It's basically a syntactic definition, yeah.
So you could define it recursively, like over a tree.
Okay, so that's the big operator.
And of course, we can have more complicated data structures.
So we could do, you know, I think Vanir has this.
Let's see if Vanir has a list.
Yeah, so Vanir has a list in it.
So we're creating a list containing X and a list containing Y.
And because they have the same structure,
that's fine also, okay?
But if we had, say, list X and Y,
well, what would happen in this case?
Is it gonna succeed?
Is it gonna fail?
It's gonna be yes.
And notice, we have the same logic variable here for the X,
but now Y wraps a list around it, okay?
Yes?
Why do you use nothing rather than
supposed to create a substitution
that says X equals Y, Y equals X?
So that's a good question.
Internally, there is a substitution.
The question is about why aren't we using a substitution?
Internally, there is a substitution,
and this is actually the representation
of the substitution, okay?
We're seeing as the output representation of substitution.
All right, here's one more.
List X and X, what's the value there?
Yes, no?
What should I get printed out as?
Infinite tree.
No, we're not allowed to have a term unified with a term,
with a structure containing that term, okay?
And this gets to what Phil was talking about,
where you can have these infinite structures
and you run into trouble with that.
So we're doing what's called the occur check.
We're checking to see if X occurs in the structure,
and if so, we're going to say, no, no answer, we fail, okay?
And that's important, this is how we get soundness.
If we don't have that, we can prove all sorts of things
that aren't true and get in trouble.
Okay, so that's unification, that's the main operator.
What else do we have?
Well, we have the ability, yes, all right.
Question around?
I couldn't get it to fail on more than one term.
You couldn't get to fail on more than one term, so.
If we have unification between X and five,
and then I get everything.
Ah, I see, okay, good question, good point.
So I think what Rob's saying is if you do something like this,
and then you have another equal equal,
and we're saying six and X, right?
Then you think that's inconsistent information,
but we're still getting a yes that X is six.
So let me go ahead and show you
how we can sequence things.
So what Vanir is doing is it's assuming
these are two separate programs,
it's ignoring the first, essentially,
and just giving us the answer from the second.
That's a good point.
So let me show you the second operator of mini-canon,
which is called fresh.
And what fresh allows you to do is a conjunction.
Okay, so now we have a conjunction of goals like that,
and I can run that, and now my answer is no.
Okay, so fresh acts as a conjunction.
Fresh has one other purpose.
Fresh also lets me introduce new logic variables.
Now the way Vanir works,
which is a little different from standard mini-canon,
Vanir acts more like prologue,
and these variables that aren't defined lexically,
those become new logic variables.
So you need to use fresh less than Vanir
than you do in standard mini-canon.
But if we add a Y there,
that will allow us to create a locally defined
logic variable that has no value called Y.
So that's the fresh form.
All right, that's a pretty complicated program,
so I better add that.
And yeah, okay.
All right, good.
So you've seen two-thirds of the language now,
fresh and equal, and then I'll show you the last part.
Last part's con-dee,
and this is something that allows us
to get more than one answer back.
Okay, because it'd be kind of boring
if our programs could only return one answer.
And one of the points of logic programming
is that we can return potentially infinitely many answers.
So the way we're gonna do that,
and mini-canon syntactically looks a lot like scheme,
because it's the original implementation of the scheme.
So con-dee is based on Lisp's con operator,
which is a conditional operator,
sort of like a big, giant type of if,
or pattern, sort of like a pattern matching syntax,
but it doesn't have a pattern match
or build into it explicitly.
So we're gonna have a con here.
Sorry, con-dee, e stands for every answer.
And the syntax for con-dee is that for each clause,
each con-dee clause has set of parentheses,
and then it takes one or more of these sub-expressions,
there's other mini-canon expressions,
which are called goals.
So equal five x is a goal, I'll pop that in there,
and equal six x is a goal, I'll pop that in the second case.
And, all right.
So what's gonna happen here?
Well, the idea is that we're trying
each of these two clauses independently.
We're gonna try one of the two clauses,
and it's unspecified mini-canon, which one we try first.
Let's say we try the second one first.
So we would try unifying x with six,
x would get, we get yes, x would be associated with six,
and then we could ask for another answer.
And we ask for another answer,
it's as if we had never tried this one.
We try the other one.
And now we forget this association between x and six,
x is refreshed magically, and we're gonna try it again,
and now x will be five.
So it gives us a chance to try different branches
of a program.
So it's similar to like an if,
except an if where you can independently try
all the possibilities, all the tests,
and the consequence, and so forth independently.
Condi is like a disjunction, and fresh is like a conjunct.
Condi is disjunction, fresh is conjunction.
That's right.
And there's a simplified version of mini-canon
called micro-canon, where conjunction and disjunction,
binary versions of those, are the primitive operators.
So those are much closer to logic.
This is closer to maybe a nicer syntax
to program with for real programs,
but if you wanna see the more primitive stuff
that's closer to logic, look at micro-canon.
And that has the very short implementation,
the implementation of micro-canon,
something like 46 lines of scheme code
for all the logic programming system.
So we can try running this, and we get the first answer,
so we try the first one, first clause
in this version of mini-canon,
and we can click on more answers,
and hey, now we've tried the other clause,
where x is six, so we're not inconsistent
because we're trying these clauses
totally independently of each other,
and we can ask for more answers,
and finally we say no, no more answers, that's it.
And if you've ever used Prolog, this part is very similar.
All right, and that's the entire language,
the entire core language.
There are basically three other operators
that we might run into, but that's the basis of it, okay?
Any questions?
Who's playing along, by the way, I'm just curious,
how many people?
Oh, whoa, that's pretty good, all right.
So now let's try something more complicated, all right?
All right, let me keep myself honest,
and check myself in.
All right, and our programs are gonna become
more complicated here, so the check-in thing will be a little,
whoops, oh, I checked that in, it's five.
Oh, here, I'll hack it, I'll put in a space,
and check it in as six.
Yes, I need to work on my get skills, that's fine.
Oh, I need to push, yeah, thank you.
Yeah, my dream tool would have me not have to do this step.
All right, okay, so let's try
something a little more interesting.
So Phil was talking about Lambda Calculus yesterday,
and he showed that there are three
basically parts of Lambda Calculus, so you have variables,
you have Lambda terms themselves,
which are called abstraction in Lambda Calculus,
and then you have application,
applying something to something else.
So we have these three things,
and if I write down comments,
hopefully Vanir will check on this,
so we have, something like X is a variable,
and then we have something like,
I'm gonna write it in sort of like the schemely way,
like Lambda X, Y, so that's an abstraction,
ABS, and then you have something like an application,
so we're applying F to G or something like that.
So that's an application.
So those are the three syntactic forms
that we have in the Lambda Calculus.
So let's try just writing something in mini-canon
that will actually recognize
a valid Lambda Calculus term syntactically.
So let's just try doing that.
So how should we do that?
Well, we're gonna define a function,
so this part is pretty much like scheme.
Let's try defining a function,
and so let's call this, I don't know,
Lambda Calculus Syntax Syn, LC Syn, okay?
And because we're in a schemely language,
we're going to ourselves define this function using Lambda,
and we're gonna give it some argument,
so I'll say we're taking, well, under a term,
Lambda Calculus term, okay?
And now what we wanna do is basically match
against the three possible terms.
So which form do you think I should write here next,
or which mini-canon operator?
So I got, Kandee, Kandee,
because I have choices to make, right?
So I've got Kandee, and how many clauses
am I gonna have for this Kandee?
Three, okay, that's right.
So I go ahead and write down my clauses to begin with,
all right, and now what I'm gonna do
is for each of my syntactic forms,
I'm going to write down a clause for that, okay?
So let's start with, I don't know,
the application term.
All right, let's do the Lambda term, actually.
Okay, so what am I gonna write,
what sort of mini-canon expression am I gonna write
in that clause to match against the Lambda?
I'm gonna write Kandee, I'm gonna write Fresh,
I'm gonna write Equal Equal.
What would I use for pattern matching, basically?
Equal Equal, right?
That's sort of like the two-way super pattern matcher.
So let me write an Equal Equal expression,
unification expression, and what am I gonna unify?
I need two terms, two values, so I'll unify what?
Term, okay, the term that came in, that's right,
and I'm gonna unify that with,
well, something that looks like my Lambda expression,
right, I have to write something down
that syntactically looks like it.
Okay, so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna just copy this thing.
All right, and,
ninja it a little bit.
Oh, look at that, huh.
Yeah, okay.
All right, so that's kind of what my expression looks like.
Now, there are a couple things here.
So I've got like X as a variable,
and this thing in the middle is really like
the body expression, or E, or T, some other term, okay?
So we got a variable, and we got some term here.
And to make this schemely, we need to make this
not a Lambda expression in many cannon or scheme
in the host language, we need to make this a data structure
that we can literally pattern match against.
So we're gonna create a list,
and the one way to do this in scheme
was with this back tick operator called quasi quote,
and it's sort of like a string interpolation style thing
if you're familiar with that.
Basically, if we put a comma in front of sub expressions,
that means that these things here
are gonna be literally filled in,
they're like holes to be filled in,
with whether the values of X and T are at that time.
And we need to have some X's and T's here.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna create a fresh
so I can have two new variables for X and T.
Okay, so I'm creating two new logic variables,
and I'm gonna grab that.
And I might have to drag this even more.
All right, there we go, perfect.
Okay, so when we're writing these sorts of programs,
it's good to try to test them sort of incrementally.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna temporarily comment out
the first and the third clause with the comments and scheme,
and I'm gonna just try running this thing
to see if it works,
because I'm not sure if it will,
because I don't use veneer normally.
So let's see if it works.
Hash T, ah, cool, okay,
because we didn't actually call it.
So we can actually make a call to LC sin now.
Let's try calling LC sin, and let's give it a term.
So let's give it the term lambda z, z,
and see if that succeeds.
And it says yes, it does succeed.
So this means that this is syntactically valid.
Great, okay.
So let me come up that in, or check that in.
So here's our first version of it.
And version seven.
Okay, all right, and notice I could just test it
one line at a time, right?
So let's do the application line now.
Okay, so here we're gonna have an application.
Once again, I'm gonna wanna have a fresh
to introduce some logic variables.
I'll say e1 and e2.
And the syntax of an application
is that we have term e1 applied to term e2.
And so that's what that looks like.
And I'll go ahead and check that out.
All right, so two thirds of the way done.
And I could test that also,
but I've got some confidence in it.
So let's now do the last one, which is the variable x.
And we're gonna represent a variable as a symbol
and scheme, a scheme symbol.
And so we've added to sort of the core logical foundations
of many canron, a few constraints that make it easier
for writing things like interpreters
and type inferences and type checkers
and grammar-based programs.
And one of the constraints we have is called simbolo.
So, simbolo, so if the term is a symbol,
then we say, hey, that's a variable.
That's syntactically legal.
So simbolo is the last way we can represent.
We're not actually saying,
we don't care if it's x or y or whatever, right?
But we care that it's a symbol.
So let's see if that runs.
Yes, okay, cool.
And we can try if we want some other tests.
So we could say, well, actually maybe it's lambda,
z and z applied to z or something like that, okay?
So we got an application,
we have variable reference and we have a lambda.
So let's see if that's syntactically valid.
Yes, that's syntactically valid, okay?
All right, so we've implemented our grammar
and we've got all that stuff working
and let me check that in.
And this is check-in number nine.
All right, cool.
Now, okay, that's kind of cool that we can write that.
But what would be more cool is if we can use
those logic variables we've been using other places,
if we could actually use that
inside of our call to LC-SIN.
So right now we're having to give a fully ground
or fully specified lambda calculus term.
And we're checking, we're verifying, validating that term
and make sure it's syntactically legal.
But it'd be really cool if we could instead
put in a logic variable and say generate a valid lambda term.
So let's try that.
So I'm gonna get rid of that term.
And I'm going to put in my term,
or I don't know, I was called Q for a query variable, okay?
So now I've got this query variable in place of the call.
And let's try doing a run now.
And so the first answer is yes.
So we're getting back this underscore zero thing
bound to Q, that's, if you remember,
that's a representation of our fresh logic variable.
And we have the side condition.
The side condition is saying
that that underscore zero thing has to be a symbol.
So it has to be, if you were ever to instantiate it
to a ground value, it would have to be a legal scheme symbol.
And scheme symbols are how we're representing variables.
So what this is saying is that any symbol, that's fine.
That's just a lambda calculus variable.
So that's actually representing
infinitely many concrete values,
infinitely many ground symbols.
Now let's see if we can get another answer.
Okay, here we're saying,
ah, if we have a lambda term
and it has the right structure,
has parentheses and something, that's fine.
And if it has something else in the back
and could be different, that's fine.
That's not very constrained.
But okay, that's fine as far as it goes.
What about this underscore zero thing?
What should that be syntactically for this to be legal?
Should be a symbol.
Okay, so maybe we're a little sloppy.
Let's go back.
And so we can add a side condition maybe.
Okay, so what else can I write here
to kind of lock it down a little more?
So I can do symbolic x, okay, and symbolic t.
So do we know if t is actually a symbol?
That's a good question.
What is t?
It's an arbitrary lambda calculus expression.
So what do we need to write here?
LC sin, yeah, we need recursion.
LC sin on t.
So that was part of the problem.
We weren't recurring properly.
Anything else you see that's wrong
in those along the similar vein?
Anywhere else where we were sloppy?
Application, right?
We have about these e1 and e2 things.
We're not putting any structure on those.
Those actually have to be lambda calculus terms themselves.
So we need to recur.
Okay, sin on e1, okay, LC sin on e2.
All right, so hopefully that'll work.
Let's see.
Sin, okay, sin.
Good, thank you.
Ah, okay, cool.
So let me paste that in.
All right, so this is check-in number 10.
All right, so if I run that, let's see.
So we have the symbol answer like we had before.
Ah, okay, so this looks better.
So now when I get a second answer that I'm generating,
it's like, okay, well, it still has
that same structure we saw before,
but now we have some side conditions.
We're saying underscore zero has to be a symbol.
And here we're saying the body is a symbol in that case.
So this, and they could potentially be separate symbols,
but they could be the same symbol.
That's what having the underscore zero and underscore one means.
So this could be lambda zed zed,
or it could be lambda zed w or something like that.
Those would both be legal.
And I can ask for more.
So here's an application where you have a symbol applied
to a symbol, okay, and I can keep generating more of these.
So here's a lambda whose body is another lambda, right?
So now I can generate these
and I can enumerate every possible lambda calculus terms
and tactically, right?
Okay, so that's basically the cool idea
about pure logic programming.
And many canons really language for pure logic programming
where the idea is you can just write down
mathematical specifications, something like that,
and have something close to the math.
And then once you have that,
you can just use the same code,
not just to check that something's correct,
but also to generate answers.
All right, so let's do this.
Okay, so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna refresh veneer.
Just refresh the browser,
make sure it's not in a goofy state.
And you can see up top there are some different programs.
So let's see if I try type inference.
Okay, so if I go to type inference,
you can see that we've got this mini canron definition
called bang slash zero or dash zero or something, okay?
What it's supposed to look like
is a turn style operator in logic.
It's supposed to look like one of those special symbols
that you saw in Phil's presentation.
So this is gonna be a type inferencer.
And if you've ever used a language like ML, for example,
you know what type inference is,
you can write down the expression,
and the type inferencer will try to figure out
what the type of that expression is.
So here we have three moving parts.
We have the expression that we're gonna type infer.
We have gamma, which is like a type environment,
it allows us to accumulate information
about the subparts of the expressions,
what those types are.
And then type is the type of that expression, all right?
And you could see actually already
what some of the similarities are.
So symbolo expert, this is the symbol case,
this is our variable case, right?
And in this case, it's not just saying,
well, that's it, you have a symbol.
Now we're gonna look up in the type environment
what that symbol is, what the type of that symbol is,
because hopefully this is not a free variable,
this is a bound variable.
And we might know that that variable, for example,
is bound to an int, has type int, okay?
And there's some other cases, like for example,
is the expression coming in a number?
So number is another constraint.
And if so, we're gonna say the type
of that sub-expression is int, okay?
That's our int type.
So five would have type int.
If it's a Boolean, like hashf in the scheme,
it's gonna have type bool and so forth.
And then we're also gonna have some more sophisticated rules
for lambda, okay?
And if you look at the lambda rule closely,
and if you look at the math that Phil put up,
or is in his paper, you'll notice that these rules
essentially are the same, okay?
So this is what he was talking about
with the Curry-Howard isomorphism,
and that basically we have a little theorem prover here
in the form of a type inferencer.
And similarly, we have application rule,
and we also have a special version of let,
and we have things like addition and so forth, okay?
So let's just try doing something that says type inferencer.
So here's an expression that it comes with,
but let's try something simpler.
So let's try calling our type inferencer,
and we have to give it an initial type environment.
And we're gonna say that that initial type environment
is empty.
And now we have to give it some expression,
I don't know what that expression is gonna be,
and then it's gonna have some type,
and I will just write Q for the query variable for the type.
So what's an expression that we might want to type check?
Well, let's do something simple, like five.
I'm putting a quote here, by the way,
to make sure that whatever expression is here
isn't evaluated at the host level, at the scheme level,
but it's actually evaluated or looked at,
that term is looked at in the type inferencer itself.
So what should the type be here?
What should the type of Q be?
Should be an int, yeah, so that worked, it's an int, okay?
And I can do something like plus, right?
So plus three, four, what should the type of that be?
That should be int, okay, sure enough, we got an int.
What about plus hash f, four, what should the type of that be?
Computer says no, all right, and we can also look
at things like a lambda expression.
What about lambda xx, which of the type of that be?
Well, it should be equivalent to some sort of function type,
right, so yeah, so we're gonna have something like a arrow a,
and you can see that we have a fresh logic variable,
arrow, fresh logic variable, so the thing on the left
is the input type for the function,
the thing on the right is the output type.
The underscore zero means that this is a fresh variable,
it means it could be anything,
but the input and the output have to be the same
because it's the identity function, okay?
So this is a very general answer, all right?
And we could try doing an application.
We could try doing something like applying that lambda term
to the value of plus three, four,
and now what type should we get back?
Should get back in it.
Should get back in it, okay?
Cool, all right, so that all works.
So this is a working type inferencer,
and for the most part we just kind of wrote down the rules,
the math, you know, you could take the rules
Phil showed and essentially type those in.
Now where it gets more interesting is,
and this is where the Curry-Howard part really becomes
way more interesting to me, is that we can say,
because we're in the logic programming domain,
we can say that the type is going to be int
and that we don't know what the input program is, right?
So now we're going from type inference
to type habitation or inhabitation.
We're trying to find a term that inhabits this type, okay?
So what would be a simple term that would have the type int?
Zero, okay, sure.
Well, zero is a little specific of an answer.
We get back a more general answer that includes zero.
So we're getting back some fresh logic variable
with a side condition that has to be a number, okay?
So that's zero, but it's also 42.
Is there any distinction between numbers and integers
and not supporting floating points?
Okay, so good question.
Are we supporting integers, floating points, so forth?
Right now, in this one, we're only supporting positive integers.
Actually, if we could probably do negative integers, I don't know.
This one, yeah, I think this one works with negative integers, too.
But, well, we could try that.
See what the type of negative five is.
But I think this is only handling integers.
But we could add other constraints
that would handle other numeric types.
Oh, okay, it doesn't like negative five, I guess.
So I guess number O in this implementation
only handles non-negative integers.
But you could add more things.
In fact, when I worked with Eric Holk and Claire Alvis
on this language called Harlan,
the original version of Harlan is sort of like a schemely language
for GPU programming,
but it had like an ML-style type system.
And the original type inferencer for that was written in C Canron.
And we had to extend these operators
to handle different types of numbers.
So you can do that. You just have to add other constraints.
Okay, so what else can we do here?
What other sorts of things should we get back
other than just a literal number?
Well, let's see what many Canons says.
So here we have a let.
So we're saying let some variable, which is a symbol,
which has some number value.
It doesn't matter what it is, because we're ignoring it,
and the body of the let is some other number.
Okay, well, that's true. That has type in.
And it's well-typed. It's the type checks, right?
And here's another one.
So here we're saying let some variable, the symbol, be hash f.
We're ignoring that.
We're returning the body, which is underscore one,
and that has to be a number.
And so we could play these games.
And at some point, okay, so now we get an addition of two numbers.
And here, now we start getting into applications.
So we're getting a lambda term, a lambda expression,
and it's being applied to something.
So let's make sure the types work.
So we're passing in a number.
That's our constraint.
And here we have some symbol.
And we're ignoring what's passed in,
and we're returning some other potentially different number.
So you can play these games all day.
And yes, you get.
You can keep clicking more answers for as long as you want.
All right, I'm going to refresh one more time.
And I'm going to show you something that's a little more fancy.
But by the way, that type inference stuff,
or the type inhabitation,
that is the thing that many of the modern proof assistants work on.
Okay, I'm going to be Dijkstra in two minutes,
but I'm going to go ahead and show you very quickly
what you can do with a relational interpreter.
So here we have an interpreter for a significant subset of scheme.
It's basically our extended lambda calculus,
if you want to look at it that way.
And so we have this, a val expo thing.
And so we can evaluate an expression.
I think we have something called, yeah, a val expo.
And let me just show you one query to a val expo,
and hopefully this will work.
So we're going to call a val expo.
And a val expo takes, sort of like the type inference,
it's going to take an expression and an environment and then an output.
So we're going to say, we've got some expression we don't know.
We're going to start in the empty environment.
And we want to see if we can create some expression,
find some expression that in the empty environment evaluates to itself.
Well, let's see if we can do that.
Whoa, what is that thing?
Well, that's kind of weird.
Okay, so we got this weird looking thing.
And let me just go to Emacs and start up scheme.
I'm going to try to type that in.
Format it in ways a little easier to understand.
I'm going to try running that.
Oh, wow, I got back the same thing.
So that's called a quine.
That's a program that evaluates to itself.
And by the way, if you look at, you know,
here's my last comment that I'll make that's historical.
If you look at the micro manual for Lisp by John McCarthy,
he says, it's a difficult mathematical type challenge exercise right here.
Find the list E such that the value of E is equal to E.
And that's what we just did by typing in the rules for scheme
and letting many canren do it.
So I hope you'll have fun playing with it.
And if you have any questions, I'm happy to answer them.
Thank you.