It's training a computer to learn like a human.
A neural network is a type of deep learning, falling under the category of AI.
It's a system of hardware and or software designed to mimic how neurons in the human brain work.
Stick around to learn how it works and why it's useful, but understand there are some limitations.
Click the link above or in the description below to read up on neural networking challenges and the age of high data demands.
A neural network involves a large number of processors operating in tiers.
The first tier receives the raw input information and each following tier receives the output from the tier that preceded it.
Every processing node among all tiers has its own small sphere of knowledge that it applies to the input information.
The last tier provides the final output.
That's how it works.
But how does it learn in order to provide an output?
Typically, a neural network is fed huge amounts of data on the topic it will be used for.
It's trained by providing input and telling the network what the output should be.
Rules are also put in place to help the network learn.
For example, a facial recognition system may be taught to recognize a mustache on a face.
During training, the network will be fed pictures of people with and without mustaches and telling it which photos do in fact have a mustache.
It might also be instructed, mustaches are below the nose and above the mouth.
Rules like this can make the training faster and the end model more powerful.
Neural networks are utilized by a wide variety of industries.
Some notable applications of neural networking include speech-to-text transcription, handwriting recognition, weather prediction,
facial recognition, chatbots, stock market prediction, delivery route planning and optimization, and so much more.
What are some other applications of neural networking?
Share your thoughts in the comments below and be sure to hit that like button.