So, I'll be talking about agents, and yeah, there are many things in the lane chain, but
I think agents are probably the most interesting one to talk about, so that's what I'll be
doing.
I'll cover kind of like, what are agents, why use agents, the typical implementation
of agents, talk about React, which is one of the first prompting strategies that really
accelerated and made reliable the use of agents, then I'll talk a bunch about challenges with
agents and challenges of getting them to work reliably, getting them to work in production.
I'll then touch a little bit on memory and segue that into more recent kind of like
papers and projects that do agentic things.
I'll probably skim over the initial slides because I think most people here are probably
familiar with the idea of agents, but the core idea of agents is using the language model
as a reasoning engine, so using it to determine kind of like what to do and how to interact
with the outside world, and this means that there is a non-deterministic kind of like sequence
of actions that'll be taken depending on the user input, so there's no kind of like hard
coded do A, then do B, then do C, rather the agent determines what actions to do depending
on the user input and depending on results of previous actions.
So why would you want to do this in the first place?
So one, there's this very tied to agents is the idea of tool usage and connecting it
to the outside world, and so connecting it to other sources of data or computation like
search, APIs, databases, these are all very useful to overcome.
Some of the limitations of language models, such as they don't know about your data, they
can't do math amazingly well, but the idea of tool usage isn't kind of like unique to
agents, you can still use tools, you can still connect LLMs to search engines without using
an agent, so why use an agent?
And I think some of the benefits of agents are that they're more flexible, they're more
powerful, they allow you to kind of like recover from errors better, they allow you to handle
kind of like multi-hop tasks, again with this idea of being the reasoning engine, and so
an example that I like to use here is thinking about like interacting with a SQL database.
You can do that in a sequence of predetermined steps, you can have kind of like a natural
language query, which you then use a language model to convert to a SQL query, which you
then pass, you then execute that, get back a result, pass that back to the language model,
ask it to synthesize it with respect to the original question, and get kind of this natural
language wrapper around a SQL database, very useful by itself, but there are a lot of edge
cases and things that can go wrong, so there could be an error in the SQL query, maybe
it hallucinates a table name or a field name, maybe it just writes incorrect SQL, and then
there are also queries that need multiple kind of like queries to be made under the
hood in order to answer, and so although kind of like a simple chain can handle maybe, I
don't know, 50, 80% of the use cases, you very quickly run into these like edge cases
where a more flexible framework like agents helps kind of like circumvent.
So the typical implementation of agents generally, and it's so early in this field that it kind
of feels a bit weird to be talking about a typical implementation because I'm sure we'll
see a bunch of different variants, but generally you get a user query, you use the LLM, that's
the agent to choose a tool to use, and also the input to that tool, you then do that,
you take that action, you get back an observation, and then you feed that back into the language
model and you kind of continue doing this until a stopping condition is met, and so there
can be different types of stopping conditions, probably the most common is the language model
itself realizes, hey, I'm done with this task, with this question that someone asked of me, I
should now return to the user, but there can be other more hard-coded rules, and so when we talk
about like reliability of agents, some of these can really help with that, so you know, if an
agent has done five different steps in a row and it hasn't reached a final answer, it might be nice
to have it just return something then. There are also certain tools that you can just like return
automatically, so basically the general idea is choose a tool to use, observe the output of that
tool, and kind of continue going. So how do you actually like, so that was pseudocode, now let's
talk about the actual kind of like ways to get this to do what we want, and the first and still
kind of like the main way of doing this, the main prompting strategy slash algorithm slash method
for doing this is react, which stands for reasoning and then acting, so RE from reasoning, ACT
from acting, and it's the papers, a great paper came out in I think October out of Princeton,
synergizing two different kind of like methods, and we can look at this example which is taken
from their paper and see why it's so effective. So this example comes from the hotspot QA data set,
which is basically a data set where it's asking questions over Wikipedia pages where there are
multi-hop usually kind of like two or three intermediate questions that need to be reasoned
about before answering. So we can see, so here there's this question aside from the Apple remote,
what other device can control the program Apple remote was originally designed to interact with,
and so the most basic prompting strategy is kind of just pass that into the language model and
get back an answer, and so we can see that in 1A standard, and it just returns a single answer,
and we can see that it's wrong. Another method that had emerged maybe like a month or so prior
was the idea of like chain of thought reasoning, and so this is usually associated with the let's
think step by step prefix to the response, and you can see in red that there's this like chain of
thought thing that's happening as it thinks through step by step, and it returns an answer
that's also incorrect in this case. This has been shown to kind of like get the agent or get the
language model to think a little bit better, so to speak. So it's yielding higher quality,
more reliable results. The issue is it still only knows kind of like what is actually present in
the data that the language model is trained on, and so there's another technique that came out
which is basically action only, where you give it access to different tools. In this case,
I think all the examples in this picture are of search, but I think in the paper it had search
and then look up, and so you can see here that the language model outputs kind of like search
Apple remote, it looks up Apple remote, it gets back an observation, it then does search front row,
can find that, so that's an instance of it kind of like recovering from an error,
and then it does search front row software, finds an answer, and then finishes. And you can see
here that the output that it gave, yes, kind of loses some of what it was actually supposed to
answer. So you've got this chain of thought reasoning which helps the language model think
about what to do, then you've got this action taking step that basically actually allows it to
plug into more kind of like sources of real data, what if you combine them, and that's the idea
of React, and that's the idea of a lot of the popular agent frameworks. Because again, agents use
a language model as a reasoning engine, so you want it to be really good at reasoning. So if
there are any prompting techniques you can use to improve its reasoning, you should probably do
those, and then a big part of it is also connecting into tools, and that's where action comes in.
And so you can see here, it arrives at kind of like the final answer. So that's the idea of
agents, React is still one of the more popular implementations for it, but what are some of the
current challenges? And there are a lot of challenges, like I think most agents are not
amazingly production ready at the moment, and these are some of the reasons why, and we can
walk through them in a bunch more detail. I'll also leave a lot of time at ends for the questions,
so I'd love to hear kind of like what you guys are observing as issues for getting agents to work
reliably. This is probably far from a complete list. So the most basic challenge with agents is
getting them to use tools in appropriate scenarios. And so in the React paper, they address this
challenge by bringing in the reasoning aspect of it, the chain of thought, style, prompting,
asking it to think. Kind of like common ways to do this include just like saying in the instructions,
you have access to these tools, you should use these to overcome some of your limitations,
and just basically instructing the language model. Tool descriptions are really, really
important for this. If you want the agent to use a particular tool, it should probably have
enough context to know that this tool is good at this, and that generally comes in the form of
like tool descriptions or some information about the tool that's passed into the prompt.
That can maybe not scale super well if you've got a lot of tools, because now you've got maybe
these more complex descriptions, you want to put them in the final prompt for the language model
to know what to do with them, but you can quickly run into kind of like context length issues.
And so that's where I think the idea of tool retrieval comes in handy. So you can have hundreds,
thousands of tools, you can do some retrieval step, and I think retrieval is another really
interesting topic that I'm not going to go into too much depth here. So for the sake of this,
we'll just say it's some embedding search lookup, although I think there's a lot more interesting
things to do there. You basically do the retrieval step, you get back five, ten, however many tools
that you think are most promising, you can then pass those to the prompt and kind of have the
language model take the final steps from there. Few shot examples I think can also be really
helpful, so you can use those to guide the language model in what to do. Again, I think the idea
of retrieval to find the most relevant few shot examples is particularly promising here. So if
you give it examples similar to the one it's trying to do, those help a lot better than random
examples. And then probably the most extreme version of this is fine tuning a model like
tool former to really help with tool selection. There's also a subtle second challenge which
is getting them not to use tools when they don't need to. So a big use case for agents is having
conversational style agents. One of the big problems that we've seen is oftentimes these types
of agents just want to use tools no matter what, even if they're having a conversation. And so
again, like the most basic thing you can do is probably put some information in the instructions,
some reminder in the prompt like, hey, you don't have to use a tool, you can respond to the user
if it seems like it's more of a conversation. That can get you so far. Another kind of like clever
hack that we've seen here is add another tool that explicitly just returns to the user. And then,
you know, they like to use tools, but they'll usually use that tool. So I thought that was a
pretty clever and interesting hack. A third challenge is the language models tell you what
tool to use and how to use it. But that's in the form of a string. And so you need to go from that
string into some code or something that can actually be run. And so that involves parsing kind
of like the output of the language model into this tool invocation. And so some tips and tricks
and hacks here are one like the more structured you ask for the response, the easier it is to
parse generally. So language models are pretty good at writing JSON. So we've kind of transitioned
a few of our agents to use that schema. Still doesn't always work, especially some of the
chat models like to add in a lot of kind of like language. So we've introduced kind of like this
concept of output parsers, which generically encapsulate all the logic that's needed to
parse this response. And we've tried to make that as modular as possible. So if you're seeing areas,
you can hopefully kind of like substitute that out very related to that. We also have a concept of
like output parsers that can retry and fix mistakes. So and I think there's there's some subtle,
there's some subtle differences here that I think are really cool. Basically, like, you know,
if you have misformatted schema, you can fix that explicitly by just passing it the output
and the error and saying fix this response. But if you have, if you have an output that just
forgets one of the fields, like it returns the action, but not the action input or something
like that, you need to provide more information here. So I think there's actually a lot of
subtlety in fixing some of these errors. But the basic idea is that you can try to parse it.
If you if it fails, you can then try to fix it. All this we currently encapsulate in this idea
of like output parsers. So the fourth challenge is getting them to remember previous steps that
were taken. The most basic thing, the thing that the React paper does is just keep a list of those
steps in memory. Again, that starts to run into some some context window issues, especially when
you're dealing with long running tasks. And so the thing that we've seen done here is again,
fetch previous steps with some retrieval method and put those into context. Usually we've actually
seen a combination of the two. So we've seen using the end most recent actions and observations
combined with the K most relevant actions and observations. Incorporating long observations
is another really interesting one. This actually comes up, or this came up a lot when we were
dealing with working with APIs, because APIs often return really big JSON blobs that are really big
and hard to put in context. So the most common thing that we've done here is just parse that in
some way. You can do really simple stuff like convert that blob to a string and put the first
like 1000 characters or something as the response. You can also do some more if you know that you're
working with a specific API, you can probably write some custom logic to kind of like take only the
relevant keys and put that if you want to make something general, you could also maybe do something
dynamically to like figure out what key like basically explore the JSON object and figure out
what keys to put in. That's a bit more exploratory, I would say. But the basic idea is, yeah, there
is this issue of, and so Zapier, I always have to think about how to pronounce it, but it's Zapier
makes you happier. So Zapier when they did this with their natural language API, not only did they
have something before the API that was like natural language to some API call, they also spent a lot
of time working on the output. And so the output is actually very specifically, I think it's like
under like 200 or 300 tokens or something like that. And they did that on purpose. They spent a
lot of time thinking about that. And so I think for tool usage, that is really important as well.
Another more kind of like exploratory way of doing this is also you could perhaps just store
the long output and then do retrieval on it when you're trying to think of like what next steps to
take. Agents can often go off track, especially in long running things. And so there's kind of
two methods that I've seen to kind of like keep them on track. One, you can just reiterate the
objective right before it makes its action. And why this works, I think we've seen that with,
at least with a lot of the current models, with instructions that are earlier in the prompt,
it might forget it by the time it gets to the end if it's a really long prompt. So putting it at the
end seems to help. And then another really interesting one that I'll talk about when I talk about some
of the more recent papers and stuff that have come out is this idea of separating explicitly a
planning and execution step and basically have one step that explicitly kind of thinks about,
these are kind of like all the objectives that I want to do at a high level. And then a second
step that says, okay, given this objective, given this one sub objective, now how do I do this one
sub objective and basically break it down even more in a hierarchical whole manner. And there's
a good example of that with baby AGI, which I'll talk about in a bit. And then another big issue
is evaluation of these things. I think evaluation of language models in general, very difficult
evaluation of applications built on top of language models. Also very difficult and agents are no
exception. I think there's the obvious kind of like evaluate whether it arrived at the correct
result in terms of in terms of getting metrics on evaluation. And so yeah, you know, if you're
asking the agent to produce some answer, that's like a natural language response. There's techniques
you can do there. A lot of them in the flavor of asking a language model to score the expected
answer and the actual answer and come up with some grade and stuff like that, that applies to the
output of agents as well. But then there's also some agent specific ones that I think are really
interesting, mostly around evaluating these idea of like the agent trajectory or the intermediate
steps. And so where we'll actually have something coming out for this, someone opened a PR that I
need to get in. But basically, there's a lot of like little different things you can look at,
like did it take the correct action? Is the input to the action correct? Is it the correct number
of steps? And by this, you know, like sometimes you, and this is very related to the next one,
which is like the most efficient sequence of steps. And so there's a bunch of different things that
you can do to evaluate not only the final answer, but like is the agent getting there like efficiently,
correctly. And those are sometimes just as useful, if not more useful than evaluating the end result.
I'm trying to see what time it is, because I also want to leave lots of time for questions.
But I think I'm good. So memory, I think is really interesting as well. So we've obviously
tried it about like memory of remembering the AI to tool interactions. There's also like a more
basic idea of remembering the user to AI interactions. But I think the third type, which is showing up
in a lot of the recent papers on agents is this idea of like personalization of giving an agent
kind of like its own kind of like objective and own persona and stuff like that. The most obvious
way to do that is just like you encode it in the prompt. You say like, Hey, like, you know, this
is your job as an agent, you're supposed to do this, yada, yada, yada. But I think there's some
really cool work being done on how to kind of like evolve that over time and give agents a sense of
like this long term memory. And one of the papers in particular around generative agents, I think
does a really interesting job of diving into this. And I think when a lot of people, the reason this
is here in the agent section is I think when people think of agents, there's the obvious like
kind of like tool usage deciding what to do. But I think agents is also starting to take on this
concept of some kind of like more encapsulated kind of like program that that adapts over time
and memory is a big part of that. And so I think memories is there's a lot to explore here. So
that's why this is a bit of an outlier slide. Okay, I wanted to chat very quickly about four
projects that that came out in the past two, three weeks, specifically how they relate, build upon,
improve upon this side, the react style agent that has been around for a while. First up is auto
GPT, which I'm assuming most people have heard of. There we go. All right. So auto GPT, the one of
the main differences between this and the react style agents is just the objective of what it's
trying to solve auto GPT. A lot of the initial goals are like, you know, improve or increase my
Twitter following or something like that very kind of like open ended broad long running goals,
react on the other hand was designed and benchmarked on more kind of like
short lived kind of like really immediately quantifiable or more immediately quantifiable
goals. And so as a result, one of the things that auto GPT introduced is this idea of long
term memory between the agent and tools interactions and using a retriever vector store for that,
which becomes necessary because now you have this doing like 20 or 30 kind of like steps and it's
this really long running project. And so it's something that react just didn't need, but due
to the change in objectives, auto GPT kind of had to introduce baby AGI is another popular one.
It also has this idea of long term memory for the agent tool interactions. And this is the project
that introduced separate kind of like planning and execution steps, which I think is a really
interesting idea to improve upon some of the long running objectives. And so specifically,
it comes up with tasks, it then takes the first tasks, it then thinks about how to do that,
which usually involves actually baby AGI initially didn't have any tools. So it kind of just like
made stuff up. I think that I think they're giving it tools now so it can actually actually execute
those things. But the idea of separating the planning execution steps is I think that's a
really interesting idea that might help with some of the reliability and focus issues of longer term
agents. Camel is another paper that came out. The main novel thing here was they put two agents
in a simulation environment, which in this case, because it was just two was just a chat room
and had them interact with each other. And so the agents themselves, I think, were basically just
kind of like prompted language models. So I don't even think they were hooked up with tools. But
going back to this idea of kind of like memory and personalization, when people kind of like talk
about agents, that is part of what they're talking about. And so I think like the camel paper in my
mind, the main thing is this idea of simulation environment. There's maybe like two reasons
you might want to do this and have a simulation environment. One is kind of like practically
to maybe like evaluate an agent if you're kind of like testing out an agent and you want to see
how it's interacting. And for whatever reason, you don't want to test it out yourself. So you
put two of them and you kind of like make sure they don't go off the rails or something like that.
Another one is just kind of entertainment purposes. So there are a lot of examples of this by people.
I think there was one with like a VC and a founder and that had them chatting with each other and
kind of like solving stuff there. So this is a little bit entertainment, a little bit practical.
Generative agents was another paper that came out. I think this was maybe like a week and a
half ago, so very recent. It also had a simulation environment aspect. It was more complex. So I
think they had like 25 different agents and kind of like a Sims-like world interacting with each
other. So a much more complex environment setup. And then they also did some really cool stuff
around memory and reflection. So memory refers to basically remembering previous things that
happened in the world. So basically in the simulation environment, they had kind of like
things that happened. Then they had the agents decide what to do, take actions, observe kind of
like the results of those actions, observe more things that came in. And so all of this
is encapsulated in the idea of memory. And then you fetch things from this memory to inform kind
of like their actions in next time sequences. So there was three kind of like main components
to this memory retrieval thing. They had a time-weighted component which basically fetched
more recent memories. They had an important weighted piece which fetched more like important
information. So trivial things like I forget what I had for breakfast today, but I don't know what's
something that's really, but I remember meeting Charles way back when, right? So there's different
levels of importance there that get subscribed to events. And so you want to fetch events that are
kind of like more bigger in importance. And then they had the typical kind of like relevancy
weighted things. So depending on what situation you're in, you want to remember events that are
relevant for that. Then they also introduced a really interesting reflection step, which basically
after like, I think they, I think it was like 20 different steps or something happened, they would
reflect on those things and kind of like update different states of the world. And so I think this
is, I've been thinking about this a bit because I think this idea of like reflecting on recent
things and then updating state is maybe like a generalization that can be kind of like applied
to a bunch of different things. So some of the other memory types that we have in Lang chain
are we have like an entity memory type, which basically based on conversation kind of like
extracts relevant entities and then constructs some type of graph and updates that there's a more
general kind of like knowledge graph version of that as well. And then we also have kind of like a
summary conversation memory, which based on the conversation updates a running summary. So you
can get around some of the context window lengths. And so I think if you look at it sort of through
a certain angle, all of those kind of like relate to this idea of taking recent observations
and updating some state, whether that state is like a graph or just a piece of text or
anything like that. So there's also been some other papers recently that have incorporated
this idea of like reflection. I haven't had time to read those as carefully, but I think that's
yeah, I don't know, my personal take is I think that's really interesting and something to keep
an eye out for the future. And that's it. I have no idea what time it is because I can't see the
time, but I'm happy to take questions until Charles kicks me off.