I'm Najja Swat for business.com and joining me today is Dr. John Christie, climate scientist at
the University of Alabama in Huntsville and Alabama state climatologist since 2000. Dr. Christie,
thank you so much for your time. My pleasure. You've described yourself as a climate nerd
and apparently you were 12 when your unwaving desire to understand whether and climate started.
Why climate? Well, I was, I think it was more like 10 years old when I was fascinated with
some unusual weather events that happened in my home area of California and so that began a
fascination for me and I wanted to try to figure out why things happened the way they did. Why
did one year have more rain? That's a big story in California. Does it rain or not? And another year
would be very dry. Why were the mountains covered with snow in one April and not another? In fact,
I have here April 1967 that I recorded as a teenager. So this has been a passion of mine forever and
as it turns out now that I'm as old as I am, I still can't figure out why one year is wetter
than the other. Well, you seem to be getting a lot closer than most people. I think it was in 1989
when you and NASA scientist Roy Spencer pioneered a new method of measuring monitoring temperature
records via satellites. Since that time up until now, why did you feel you needed to develop a
new method to begin with and how did it differ in terms of the readings of established methods at
the time? Well, the issue was we only had surface temperature measurements and they are scattered
over the world. They don't cover much of the world at all actually, mainly just the land regions
and scattered places on the ocean. The measurement itself is not that robust. The stations move,
the instruments change through time and so it's a very difficult thing to make. In fact,
a small little change in the area right around the station can really affect the temperature
of that station. So Roy Spencer and Dick McKnighter came up with an idea about looking at some
satellite data and this is the temperature of the deep layer of the atmosphere. So this is like the
surface to 8,000 meters, you know, something like that and so if we could see the temperature of that
bulk atmospheric layer, we would have a very robust measurement and the microwave sensors on the
NOAA polo orbiting satellites did precisely that and so we were the first to really put those data
into a simple data set that had the temperature then for month by month since about November 1978.
Okay and how did your readings differ from the climate science at the time?
Well, first of all, they differ because we had a global measurement. We really did see the entire
globe from satellite because the orbit of that satellite is polar and the earth spins around
underneath so every day we have 14 orbits that the earth spins around underneath and we see the
entire planet so that's one big difference and the other one is that the actual result did not
show as much warming as what the surface temperatures showed and we're doing even more work now to
demonstrate that a lot of the surface stations are spuriously affected by the growth of an
infrastructure around them and so there's kind of a false warming signal there.
You don't get the background climate signal with surface temperature measurements, you get
a bit of what's happening in the local area.
Well, your research has to do with testing the theories posited by climate model forecasts
so you don't actually do any modeling yourself but what criteria do you use to test these theories?
That's a very good question because in climate you hear all kinds of claims and theories being
thrown out there and for a lot of people who don't really understand the climate system it's a
quick and easy answer just to say oh humans caused that you know global warming or something like
that is the answer when the climate system is very complex so we look at these claims
and Roy Spencer and I when I say we are just a few of the people around the world that actually
build data sets from scratch. I mean we start with the photon counts of the satellite radiometers
or the you know the original paper records of 19th century East Africa. We do all this from scratch
and so that we can test the claims that people make and what we find is that once we build the
data set we make sure we have confidence in the data set that it's telling us a truth about what's
happening over time we can determine that as well or test it then we check the claim. So for
example on surface temperature data sets that we make that go back to the 19th century someone will
say well this is the hottest decade or more records happened this decade than in the past and we can
demonstrate in the United States especially that that's not the case that you would need to go back
to the 1930s if you want to see real record temperatures that occurred at that time and for
climate models we like to use the satellite data set it's a robust deep layer measurement so it's
measuring lots of mass of the atmosphere the heat content really and so that's a direct value we can
get out of the climate models so we are comparing what we say apples to apples what the satellite
produces and observes is what the climate model also generates and we can compare them one to one
and in the paper Ross McKintock and I wrote a couple of years ago we found that 100% of the
climate models were warming the atmosphere faster than it was actually warming so that's not a good
result if you're trying to test your theory of how the climate works with a model against what
actually happens with the models how much do you think of the deeply over exaggerated
predictions that doom and gloom have to do with the fact that the methodology is
it's substantiated by confirmation bias well you know that that's an interesting question because
we're a bit confused as well is we have been publishing these papers since 1994 that have
demonstrated models warm too much relative to the actual climate and yet we don't see an improvement
in climate models and trying to match reality with their model output now I think a number of
modelers understand that yes there is a difference there and it's the models are just too hot but
what is the process that's gone wrong in the models to make that is a difficult question for
these folks because models have hundreds of places you could turn a little knob change a coefficient
and that will change the result now it's not a physical thing it's not based on physics it's
it's the model parameterizations we call them the little pieces of the model that try to represent
an actual part of the atmosphere like when do clouds form that's a pretty big question is
how much humidity in the atmosphere is required to create a cloud because once the cloud forms
that reflects sunlight and cools the earth so that's it that's one of the big questions there is
so in testing the models we like to use the bulk atmospheric temperature that's a very direct
measurement that models produce in the atmosphere produce and so we can then say there's a problem
here with climate models to what degree the dual observations data differ from their forecasts
well generally it's about a factor of two at times it's been more but the latest models on
average the models for the deep layer of the atmosphere are warming about twice too fast
and that's a real problem I think when now we're looking at over 40 years what we can test these
models with and they're already that far off and so I will we should not use them to to tell us
what's going to happen in the future since they haven't even gotten us to the right place in the
last four years but given that your real world data it's refuted what the forecasts were every
time for decades why then and I recognize that this is conjecture we can't really be sure but on
let's say 97 99 percent of scientists so firmly behind the climate crisis narrative
yeah I don't know how many are really fully behind that crisis climate narrative I
saw a recent survey where about 55 percent might have been of the opinion that the climate warming
was going to be a problem warming itself is not a problem I mean the earth has been warmer in the
past than it is today so the earth has survived that before and I don't think putting extra
you know plant food in the atmosphere is going to be a real problem for us to overcome I do think
the world is going to warm some from the extra CO2 but there are a lot of benefits that come from
that by the way you're dealing with a question about human nature and funding and so on and I
think we all know that the more dramatic a story is especially in the political world
the more attention you will get and therefore your work can be highlighted and that helps you
with funding and attention and so on and that's kind of part of what's going on here then there's
the other real stronger political narrative that folks there are groups and in the world
political elite that like to have a narrative that scares people so that they can then offer a
solution and so simple way to say elect me to this office and I will be able to solve this problem
that you are facing people like us who actually produce the data and look at you know extreme
events and so on say well you know there isn't any change in these extreme events so what's the
problem you're trying to solve and then we look at the other side of that issue and say okay if you
actually implement this regulation or this law it's not going to have any make any difference on
the climate anyway so it's a you kind of lose on two ends on that story. You're a distinguished
professor of atmospheric science and also director of earth sciences also at Alabama in Huntsville
these are prominent positions how have you managed to hold on to them with climate views
that are so divergent from the norm? Well the environment in the state of Alabama is different
than what you have in Washington and as I like to tell people that one of the reasons I like to
live in Alabama and I'm from California way across the country is that in Alabama you can
call a duck a duck that you can just be flat on about what's going on and you're not going to be
given the evil eye or cast out as it is now in the climate establishment you know saying that all
the models are warming too much and that there is not a disaster arising that causes great consternation
because of the narrative that has been built over the last 30 years that we are supposed to be in a
catastrophe and to come out and say well here's the data and the data show there is no catastrophe
looming we're doing fine the world is doing fine human life is thriving in places it's allowed to
so what's the problem here you're trying to solve? Did you ever manage to get your findings to
policy makers that have interest to do something about it? Well you know I've been
to Congress 20 times testified before hearings so the information is there and available
but I can't force Congress to make legislation that matches the real world the congressional world
is a political world and things happen there that are kind of out of my reach and ability to influence
I suppose. According to your research you've also said that the climate models underestimate
negative feedback loops so can you explain to me what this mechanism is and the effect of
overestimation of the loops on understanding climate for what it is? All right now that's a
very complicated issue and I don't understand it all for sure but we can say just from some
general results in general observation what's going on here and one of those general observation is
that when a climate model warms up the atmosphere one Kelvin one degree that it sends out 1.4 watts
per meter squared so the air atmosphere warms up and energy escapes to space 1.4 when we use
actual observations of the atmosphere when the real atmosphere warms up one Kelvin it sends out
2.6 watts of energy almost twice as much so that tells you right there that the climate models are
retaining or holding on to energy that the real world allows to escape when it warms so that's
kind of a negative feedback that as the atmosphere warms for a bit the real world knows how to let
that heat escape whereas the models don't and they retain it and that's why they keep building up heat
over time. What other variables do you look at? Yeah the state climatologists I deal a lot with
very practical questions that people ask they want them is it getting hotter is it getting
wetter are the rainstorms getting heavier and so are the hurricanes getting worse and so I actually
wrote a booklet called I practical guide to climate change in Alabama but it covers a lot of the
country as well so it's not just this it's free you can download it from my website
the Alabama state climatologist is on the first page and I answer a lot of these very practical
questions and one as we go down the list there aren't any more droughts droughts are not getting
worse over time heavy rainstorms are not getting worse over time here in the southeast in fact
Ross McKittrick and I also had a paper on that where we went back to 1878 and demonstrated that
the trends are not significant hurricanes no they're not going up at all in fact 2022 is going to be
one of the quietest that we've had in a while tornadoes are not becoming more numerous heat
waves are not becoming worse so one after another though the weather that people really care about
that if it changes could cause problem or catastrophe we find those events are not changing
they've always been around some of the biggest critics of climate skeptics say okay yes no fair
one extreme weather event doesn't say much but they argue that they are very particular trends
that have been on the increase like recently have you observed this at all that's exactly
the kind of thing we build data sets to discover for example there is a story and there is some
evidence for it that in the last hundred years there's been an increase in in heavy rain events
in part of our country not all of it just part of the country so I built a data set that went back
to the 1870s in fact it back to the 1860s and so on and we looked at that very carefully and found
that well when you go back far enough there were a lot of heavy events back then and so over the
long time period of 140 years or more we don't see an upward trend that's unusual in that sample of
time 140 years that we don't see a change in those kind of events so that's why you know one of the
real things I think has great value to it is to build these data sets so you can specifically
answer the question and the claim that is being made I think one of the worst ones was made by
the New York Times when they were talking about how many record high temperatures occurred in a
recent heatwave around the country and so I looked at that a little bit more carefully and they were
allowing stations to be included that only had 30 years or less of data even less than 30 years
so some had 100 years but a lot of them just had 30 years well when you become very systematic and
say okay I'm only going to allow stations that have 100 years so that every station that measured
in 2022 can be compared with the entire time series and then their story falls apart because
the 30s and the 50s were so hot in our country that they still hold the records for the number
of high temperature events just the scary thing for me is that as much as it completely falls
apart there's no logic to it it still firmly stands as what most people believe you have to
give credit to those who in the climate establishment and the media or whoever is behind all this that
they have been successful in scaring people about the climate because now you find that even in
grade school textbooks and almost every new story that comes out will try to throw in and this is
where this establishment is very good is they make sure every story has some kind of line in it about
climate change and they don't ever go back and talk to someone who actually builds these data
set sentences is that really the worst it's been in the last 120 years they just make those claims
and so other than the fact the sea level is rising a bit the extreme events are just not
there to really cause problems now we are in a problem of having greater damages occur because
of extreme events and that's mainly because we've just built so much more stuff and placed it in harm's
way our coastlines are crowded with condominiums and uh entertainment parks and uh retirement
villages and so on there's so many more of them that when a hurricane does come well it's going
to wipe out a lot more and so we've served sure the damages the the absolute value of those damages
has gone up but the number of hurricanes their strength and so on the background climate has
not caused that problem it's just that we like to build things in places that are dangerous
we have you know records of sea level rise and it's on the order of about an inch per decade
except in places where the land is sinking pretty rapidly and you can find that on the Louisiana
Gulf Coast and in places like that but otherwise it's about an inch per decade and I tell folks
that an inch per decade you know if they want to have centimeters a decade is not your problem
it's 10 feet in six hours from the next hurricane that's your problem if you can withstand a rise of
sea level of 10 feet in six hours then you're probably going to be okay but if you can't then
a hurricane can really cause problems and so we just have more exposure to that kind of
this situation now than we've had before what about the trend with sea level rise
should we be worried about future generations having to deal with issues that might not affect us
in our lifetime but eventually we'll threaten their lives I think your listeners would you know
need to understand that sea level is a dynamic variable it goes up it goes down it has been
over a hundred meters lower than today just in the last 25,000 years and there was a period
from about 15,000 years ago to 8,000 years ago where the sea level rose
you know about 12 centimeters per decade for you know 7,000 years now that's a lot more than
two and a half centimeters per decade as it's doing now so the world has managed to deal with
sea level before and if we go back to the last warm period about 130,000 years ago the sea level
then was higher than it is now by about five meters or so and so just naturally we would expect at
least another five meters of sea level it won't happen tomorrow it won't happen this century but
slowly it will likely continue to rise and so that should be placed in your thinking if you're
building a dock for say a military port or something if you want it to last a long time just put a
cushion in there a way to manage to handle another half meter of sea level rise in the next hundred
years and you should be okay your temperature records
but how much has the earth warmed
let's say over the last 40 years yes we have about I think with this November
we finished 43 years 43 years of measurements and in that time the temperature has risen
half degree Celsius and you might want to look at other things about the world the world has
expanded agricultural production tremendously nations are now exporting grain where they had
before because people are pretty smart they figure out how to do things better all the time
and growing food is one thing they figured out how to do better as time has gone on so the climate
has not been a this warming of a half degree has not been anything that caused a major catastrophe
at all wealth has increased around the planet now some governments are trying to prevent you from
growing your wealth but it that's a hard thing to stop people like to have food they like to have
conveniences in their life and that's hard to you know pass laws that say you can't enjoy the
life of what you want to how much of that warming are you reliably able to say is as a result of
human activity okay the answer is none in the sense you said reliably and I can't come up with an
answer for reliably the work we have done that just assumes all of the warming is that warming that
is not due to El Nino or warming that's not due to volcanic suppression of temperatures earlier in
the record comes up to about a tenth of a degree per decade if it's not due to human activity
reliably let's say are there other factors that we can say for sure let's say geothermal cooling
heating those kinds of things that we can say for a fact have played a role in the incremental
warming of the planet over the last few decades yeah what we see is that we've had a couple of
volcanoes in the first half of that period algae chone and penitubo and those cool the planet in the
first half of that 40 years and so that tilted the trend up so if you add the warming early back
in then that trip tends to tilt the trend a little back down and that's where I come up with a one
tenth per decade is the warming rate which means the climate is not very sensitive to carbon dioxide
or greenhouse gas warming as the popular ideas about it are it's probably half or even less
but about half as sensitive as models tend to report so if CO2
exposure or insertion into the atmosphere were to double what would the results be
okay well I actually had a little paper on that and we're kind of expecting maybe about
2070 2080 it will be doubled from what it was back in 1850 and the warming of that amount
will be about a degree 1.3 I think is what I calculated but that was from that earlier period
so you would say that much of the warming was due to humans about 1.3 degrees C and the general rule
I found with people is they don't mind an extra degree on their temperature in fact if you look at
the United States the average American experiences a much warmer temperature now than they did 100
years ago and that's because the average American has moved south the average American has moved to
much warmer climates California Arizona Texas you know Alabama Florida and so on because cold is
not a whole lot of fun you know seeing and snowmobiling and ice fishing and so on that's fine
but the average person likes it to be warm and so that's why the many people in our millions in
our country have moved to warmer areas and so I don't think that one 1.3 Kelvin whatever I said
it's going to matter much in terms of the weather people really care about those extreme events and
so on what do your temperature records tell you about previous hotter temperatures since what was
it 1978 what we see you know there is an upward trend in the in the global temperature that I think
is manageable but it goes up and down the 1998 El Nino was a big event 2016 El Nino was a big event
so we see these ups but we also see the downs that come from a volcano that might go off and
cools the planet those are bigger effects than that small trend that's going up the global
temperature can change by two tenths of a degree from month to month and so when we're talking about
a tenth per decade then we're talking about you know a month a month we can handle and we can't
handle 20 years worth of a small change just doesn't make sense and and the evidence of the real
world is pretty clear that humans have done extremely well as the planet has been warming a little
bit whether it's natural or not what can you tell me about the Milankovitch cycles Milankovitch
cycles are the orbital cycles of the earth the earth orbit around the sun and it's tilt of the axis
and the distance from the sun that that is not a perfect circular orbit around the sun it's kind
of an ellipse and it changes through time and all those factors work together to put a little bit
more solar energy in certain places and less than others and what we talk about in ice ages
which uh these cycles are likely related to is that if you can melt the snow in Canada
in the summer then you won't have an ice age so the snow falls in the winter you melt it in the
summer no ice age if you can't melt the snow in Canada in the summer for some reason the
earth is tilted away a bit in July and August and so on and the snow hangs around all summer long
the next winter more snow piles up the next summer it doesn't melt the next winter more snow
so you get this mechanism that adds snow and then you come up with an ice age and so the tilt
of the axis and other parameters I just mentioned can moderate how much sunlight comes in in the
summertime in Canada and it's up to 100 watts per meter squared which is a a lot of energy
difference over time and that's probably the biggest theory that has a pretty good amount of
evidence with it that those orbital changes can cause huge changes in the climate from ice age to
the current uh intercalation when I spoke to dr curry she said in the long term uh negligible
influence that humans have on the planet but what we seem to forget is that the climate's
going to do what the climate's going to do do you conquer uh yes you just mentioned the ice ages
but those are huge swings in the climate that the humans of course didn't have anything to do with so
maybe if if your listeners thought about it this way that the sun sends down on average about 160
watts per meter square 160 the atmosphere itself sends down about 340 so you know heat comes from
the atmosphere above us that's 500 watts per meter square when you add it together so you're
looking up about 500 watts are coming down on average for the globe the extra carbon dioxide
and so on is about two watts so you can see that this 500 watts that's natural and it can go up and
down and vary and so on the extra two is not going to have much effect that's why it's hard
we're trying to find what is the impact of that extra two watts per meter squared and it's pretty
tough it might be found in the in the oceans is a little bit more jewels of energy going into the
oceans than before but was that due to just a change in clouds that was natural or is it due
to the extra carbon dioxide now extra carbon dioxide does send down that two watts i'm not
saying it doesn't uh but the atmosphere and the ocean can respond and release a lot of that extra
two watts and evidently that's what's happening because the earth isn't warming up as much as the
models that suggest there's claims that the way that humans are living is causing daily extinction
of two to three hundred different species is this a natural course of evolution you know 99%
of the species that have ever lived are extinct so extinction is pretty natural obviously
have humans caused some extinctions well certainly you know when you destroy the environment of a
small place and that was the only place that particular species live then yes you know humans
caused that extinction did the climate change that humans caused cause any extinctions i think
that jury is still out uh because most uh species love the extra carbon dioxide plants do specifically
and then everything that eats plants loves that so you might want to say the extra carbon dioxide
actually helped in some sense the whole biosphere but i think that what humans do to the surface
and to the water if it's not clean properly and if you just really poison the surface in the air
then that can cause some real problems for the species that are living out there and that's why
we have rules about making not putting poison in the air or in the water does that qualify as climate
change no no uh to say carbon dioxide is a poison is you know you really have to scratch your head
on that because plants love the stuff it invigorates the biosphere um when did all of this greenery
evolve and the corals you know occur and grow and develop it occurred when there was two to four
times five times as much CO2 as that is in the air now so carbon dioxide invigorates the biosphere
so we're just actually putting back carbon dioxide that had been in the atmosphere earlier and uh i
don't think the world is going to have too much problem that in terms of its biosphere uh the
issue about is climate going to become so bad that some things can't handle it and i don't really see
the evidence for that happening critics of your views on climate have argued that you
undercut your credibility by making claims for that exceed your data and that you're unwilling to
agree with different findings how do you respond to that uh show me a finding and and let me look at
it and uh if it's a valid finding fine i'll agree with it uh but uh you know you can find anything on
the web these days about claims that uh someone might make but you show me the evidence let me see
what you're complaining about and uh we can have a discussion about that but i what my publication
show i just had one published last week on snowfall in the western states of the united states that
shows for the main snowfall regions there is no trend in snowfall the amount of snow that's falling
right now is the same as it was 120 years ago so snowfall is still falling out in the western
mountains of the united states that's evidence that this data and so when someone has a claim that
oh snowfall is going away out in the west i said well well here look at these the evidence from
real station data that people recorded back in 1890 to now and uh and so i can answer that question
with real information and and you don't see many of people like me in debates because they're not
offered uh in fact i've been uninvited you know someone on a particular panel would say hey let's
get this guy to come here and speak to us and then i receive the the de-invitation because it was
not going to go along with the theme of their climate change as a catastrophe uh presentation
on those occasions that you referred to in the past that co2 levels were significantly
higher than they are now do records show any negative effects as a result of such high co2
well when you say negative you're that's almost a moral question good or bad that the dinosaurs
went extinct well as the dinosaurs and i think they did have an opinion about that um
well let me rephrase if it had to be on those levels today would negatively impact
that will mentally impact humanity okay what we see is um
as carbon dioxide event has increased in other words humans are producing energy
so that their lives can be uh enhanced i mean there is a direct relationship between how much
carbon or energy you're able to use and carbon is the main source today and your thrive ability
it's basically one to one you know think about it we didn't leave the stone age because we ran out
of rocks you have the stone age because something better came along you know iron bronze and so on
and in terms of energy we didn't leave the wood and dung age because we ran out of trees or excrement
we found a better source than was carbon coal oil and so on and transportation you know we didn't
leave the horse and buggy age because we ran out of horses it's because Henry Ford made a vehicle
that was cheap and affordable my great grandfather who was a destitute poverty in oklahoma in the 1930s
had a Model T and so uh and another thing about Henry Ford he didn't go around getting the government
to kill all the horses so you'd only have to buy his car horses were still available for the poorest
people you know and the government didn't uh he didn't make the government go out and build gas
stations or drill for oil you know that was done at the market for the private level but today we
have a government that says this is what i want for the energy structure and so we're going to be uh
uh using your taxpayer money and we're going to put out all these charging stations and force you
to buy electric cars or at least subsidize them tremendously and put up all these windmills and
so on uh at great expense and great environmental wreckage and i can assure you that without energy
life is brutal and short and so energy is the thing that has caused uh our life spans to double
and so children no longer fear about or we don't have to fear for uh diseases that used to wipe out
millions because of the advances that energy has brought out through electricity and experimentation
and all the sciences that we have developed now that's based upon that access to energy
and so yes uh developing countries and and here's my i mean i'm not making this as a prediction
i'm just using this as an observation they're going to get their energy they are going to find
the energy and right now it's carbon that's the cheapest and most effective and very high density
and so we will see these countries use carbon to advance and we should not stand in their way
because they want to live like us who already have pretty big carbon footprints uh but if you
want to have some comfort in that is uh the carbon dioxide we're putting back into the atmosphere
is invigorating the biosphere and it also represents people living longer and better
lives there's just no question that is energy is made available and affordable people live longer
and better lives and uh i think that's going to ultimately be the the inertia that's going to carry
forward this uh issue kind of past all the preaching about carbon dioxide problems
environmentalists would argue that they're not against electricity and prosperity
they're just advocating for a better cleaner way to do it it's a tremendous misconception
that a windmill or a solar panel can somehow give you cleaner and reliable energy than what you have
now that's just not true to build a windmill the environmental wreckage that you have to go through
is tremendous in terms of all the minerals you have to yank out of the earth and process
process takes energy by the way and building all these transmission lines i mean the energy is so
diffuse it is so weak in wind and solar that you have to gather up huge amounts of land to
put it together i think uh robert brice said it well i think he called it the iron law of power
something like that that the weaker the source of energy the more stuff and material you need
to gather it to concentrate it to make it useful and so you find out you have to spend huge amounts
of dollars in environmental cost to make a windmill or make a solar panel which by the way
doesn't last forever and uh and so this carbon that already has a tremendous amount of energy
in a very small dense space means that the environmental footprint is much much smaller
than what you have with a solar or wind in fact i like you know it's about one to a thousand or
two thousand in terms of the square footage you need and i like to tell people you know i i ran
five miles this morning so and there was a little bit of wind it was cloudy so if you had a solar
panel it would have helped you anyway but think about sun and wind you can go out and enjoy them
the breeze which tells you they don't have much energy if they don't you know bring you great
harm this wind is so energy poor that you can stand out in the wind not be bothered you can stand out
in the sun and not be bothered but go try to stand in the boiler of a natural gas fire power plant
you'd be burnt to a crisp that's the kind of energy you need to push electrons and that's the
amount of energy that can be done or that process can be done in a very small environmental footprint
that then allows the rest of the environment to to not be interfered with by this energy production
but look at windmill and solar panel farms not only are they just ugly but they do cause
tremendous environmental damage in their construction and maintenance
what are the long-term effects i'm talking decades from now
if we just continue to get our energy from fossil fuels how bad can it get
well let me start how good can you talk about people that will have access to affordable energy
so they're going to live longer and they're going to live better lives you have access to this
the impact on the climate i think is what is about the only thing you think of is uh well the sea
level is going to continue to rise has been rising for several hundred years so it's it's going to
continue to rise and at a manageable rate by the way um and the atmosphere it might warm
some more uh but certainly not in terms of that catastrophic effect that will cause us to
lose our ability to thrive i'm just very i'm pretty optimistic you know people are clever
and they can figure out how to adapt to whatever is going to happen
the real issues i deal with as a state climatologists are the extreme events
that we know are going to happen that you're not ready for i mean that flood that happened
you know 50 years ago is going to come back again and it's going to cause some real problems
if you don't build your infrastructure and put your houses where they can be safe
or industry uh if you don't build up on the coast too much so that you won't be clobbered
by a hurricane or something like that so it's these kind of natural extreme events that we're
far more vulnerable to right now than some small and gradual change that the climate system might
undergo i did read somewhere that someone has asked you and i'm sure you must get it a lot
whether you get any funding from the fossil fuel industry do you
no i do not and i made that decision way back in the 19 early 1990s so that uh you know someone
can come to me and and a fossil fuel i might make a fossil fuel company mad by some of
information i've produced but so be it if i can then put my head to bed at night and not be worried
about did i uh accommodate some agenda somewhere i'm just after what the observations say can i
build the best observational data set to answer the questions of climate that we have and uh and
that's that's what i want to do i suppose one of the biggest tragedies about it would be that it
would discredit the real science and the the fundamental research that you're doing just
that it'll be a non-starter because people will immediately just yeah and that's unfortunate
because the perception then is that well if a fossil fuel company paid someone to do some
research they really wanted to know the answer about something and this person was completely
honest did the work properly and provided the answer to the fossil fuel companies is as you said
is well that answer would be tainted because it came from a fossil fuel company well hello think
about what environmental advocacy groups and pressure groups do all of the time they pay
tremendous sums to people so they can come up with an answer that gives them their leverage in
claiming this is a catastrophic problem but so i can take that at least perception off the table
lastly are you aware of any ways in which geoengineering could possibly be affecting
the natural balance of things is it being done more than we're aware of
and could it backfire anytime humans do something they're going to have an impact
there's just no question about that so you could call that geoengineering but inadvertent
we have made some desert valleys cooler because now we irrigate crops so we've
you know taken water that fell someplace and moved it to another place and so that's a bit
of geoengineering there and that by the way a lot of those places feed a lot of the world so
you can't say it's bad i suppose but the other question about geoengineering is can we do something
to prevent a perceived problem here and that's the real danger i think because you don't know the
consequences of when you start tinkering with a very complex and dynamical system and so i would
say stay away from that suppose someone did a big geo geoengineering experiment and it was and
something bad happened somewhere well that country would sue the world and say look you made this
bad thing happen to us you are liable and so then we're getting nowhere in terms of
preventing some problem on the planet