So here's my Frieden STW-10 and today I wanted to respond to one of the most
frequent comments I get which is try to divide by zero is awesome and
dangerous if divide by zero does it catch fire try to divide by zero please
make a division by zero and then I ask a guy to try it by himself and say I only
do it on my piano which actually wouldn't help again I was kind of reluctant
to do it and I had to think for a while what would happen if I did it and I
convinced myself that no it wouldn't catch fire so it would be a very
popular YouTube video so let's try it let's divide by zero and see what
happens so let me clear everything and enter 355 as the dividend okay so we have
a 355 out there there you go 355 right here and now we are going to divide by
zero so I'll do a keyboard clear plump there's nothing on the keyboard and I'll
hit the two buttons and we'll see what happens before that I will reset it
other direction reset it here because it's more spectacular and okay off we go
so it's a freedom you need to press two buttons to divide the right one and the
left one
and what happens that it gets into an infinite loop and will never stop and I
guess it heats up so eventually it would catch fire but guess what they thought
about it there's a button here it's called div stop and I guess that was made
especially for idiots making YouTube videos and they had lots of foresight
so this is what it does it just gets set in an infinite infinite loop but let's
understand why that is so let's clear everything and I'll do a regular division
though of my favorite one which gives pi 355 dividend divided by 113 and again
I'll try to do it from the edge here so what happens is that in order to do
divisions what it actually does is successive subtractions and does it as
we do it in school is trial and error so it will try to subtract what I just
entered which is 113 from this number and trying progressively know this time
10, 900, 1000 until it hits over here and finally it subtracts enough of a
chunk that it overflows and it tells it it has subtracted too much and then it
starts to move it one to the left and subtract smaller amounts and that's how
it does the division eventually so let's see how that works
see it move move move move move move move ding it overflows
and eventually it divide in and it's in the 3.141592 something it's the
approximation of pi
so what happens that when you divide by zero is just subtract nothing and so it
can never overflow and it gets stuck in an infinite loop so here you go here you
have it divide by zero on a Frieden STW10 let's do it again
as clear enter some kind of stupid number
dividend all to the right here the keyboard divide by zero and watch the
smoke
okay we'll do that forever good night
a brilliant cast Jack Lemon in a delightful role which gives full reign to
Jack's amazing versatility
you