Here we are again with our old pal, Willard Van Orman Quine, another famous article, not
as famous and influential as Two Dogmas of Empiricism, but definitely well known and
that's called Epistemology Naturalized.
Okay, well what does the title mean for the first thing?
Well Epistemology since, epistemological issues have been with us since the dawn of philosophy.
Plato talks about what we can know and what knowing does for the knower and things like that.
In the era of modern philosophy of course we have Descartes, Descartes' Meditations and
their epistemology is as what is sometimes called first philosophy, that is before you can
start philosophizing about anything like what the world is like, what things exist, what is right
and what is wrong, you need to first know what it is to know anything and then once you establish
that you have some criterion to judge whether or not we can claim to know things about the
external world, things about ethics, things like that. So you've got to settle our standards of
knowing first and they give you guidelines that affect the way that you reason in all
other areas of philosophy. So epistemology in that sense is what you handle first and that's
evident in the way Descartes structures the meditations where he talks about what we can know
right up front. Quine is a big fan of science and in fact Quine doesn't make a clear distinction
between epistemology and the rest of philosophy or between philosophy and science. He just talks
in terms of our theory of the world and our theory of the world includes all of science and philosophy
and there's no clear boundaries between them. So this very much prevents us sort of taking a
placing philosophy above science and saying, whoa science you can't make claims to know
something because you're not meeting our strict philosophical standards so therefore your scientific
results fall short or something like that. That would be the sort of old-fashioned way of looking
at epistemology is sort of above science and providing standards that science must reach,
must meet. Once you naturalize epistemology you say epistemology is part of science
and can use the scientific method. Now this would be quite radical because then you could,
how is it that you're supposed to judge the standards that you use? How is it that you're
supposed to, that you can judge whether or not the products of science are things that we can
actually know or that are in some sense theory-laden or whatever? Well as is usual with a Quine article
it's very dense and it's written in a way that seems to require us having a huge amount of
background information. Quine's articles tend to read as if they're for an audience of buddies that
he's already in the middle of conversations with. So it's hard to make sense of it which is why
as the reading I gave a version of epistemology naturalized that has sort of a commentary on it
and chunks cut out. So let's talk about some of his assumptions. The first and major assumption
that he makes clear is something that he calls the Quine-Dewam thesis. This is he talks about in
two dogmas of empiricism. I don't think he calls it that there. He starts calling it maybe in Word
and Objects which is his book that comes out in 1960 and it's a little arrogant. Pierre Duem was a
French physicist who made this claim about science that it's basically, you can call it
confirmation holism and I talked about it in talking about two dogmas from empiricism. That is
contrary to what the logical positivists say, the logical positivist says that every sentence
if it is meaningful and is not just true by the definition of the words involved, if it is meaningful
then it has clear criteria of testability that is it is relevant to specific
facts about the world. So and they are what make it meaningful.
And what Quine insists on and he says Duem insisted on before him. So if Duem insisted on it before
him, why is it called the Quine-Dewam thesis? Why not just call it the Duem thesis but I guess maybe
it had become famous as what Quine says and Quine wanted to say well this other guy said it before
me and I've just discovered that or anyway. The Quine-Dewam thesis is this idea that while
the only evidence we have for our theory, our grand theory of the world is observation of
the natural world, it is relevant only, it only confirms or dis confirms our theory as a whole
and and this is because no claim that we make about the world can be directly tested in isolation
from other claims like for example if I make a claim about the motion of a planet and I observe
through a telescope that my claim appears to be false, that would appear to mean that the evidence
dis confirms my specific claim about planetary motion but of course it doesn't because I could
say no no no my claim about planetary motion is correct, the only reason the observation appears
to dis confirm it is because there's something wrong with our theory of how this telescope works
or there's some other facts we don't know like there's another planet that we haven't seen yet
affecting the motion of the planet so I can I don't have to dis confirm my particular claim
there's no evidence that will directly dis confirm that claim alone it's always and this is Quine's
big contribution it's actually up to us to pick which claim we want to dis confirm it's not dictated
by the evidence it's our choice to decide okay I'm going to stick to my observational claim
and I'm going to claim that this telescope is faulty or something like that we make the choices
and nothing about our observation dictates that choice so all we know is that our current
observation doesn't fit with our whole theory but which of the elements of our theory we decide to
discard or maybe we decide to discard the observation itself it's up to us this is what
confirmation holism is and given that fact it looks like one of the projects that was particularly
dear to one of the logical positivists who had the longest career some logical positivists didn't
make it out of Vienna for example Marie Schlick was shot by a crazy ex-student on the steps of I
think the university but one who had a long and distinguished career in in America was Rudolph
Carnap and he sort of evolved out of logical positivism and started calling it logical empiricism
instead and sort of gave up some aspects of logical positivism but took the core insights and sort of
said no no no we can work with this and Carnap and Quine had a long going back and forth over the
decades in America and and Carnap was older than Quine and a great influence on Quine
so he risked Quine respected Carnap but said he was wrong about some things anyway Carnap
his big project was that he wanted to see if you could justify your theory by logically reducing it
to statement to these observation statements now observation statements which Quine remains
committed to are the kind of thing that people like Kuhn or more extreme or a more extreme
version is a guy called Paul Feierabend would say observation sentences are kind of a myth you
cannot have these sentences so Quine maintains that although in general it's the theory as a whole
that is confirmed or disconfirmed by the evidence he still maintains that there are very specific
sentences that can be confirmed or disconfirmed but these are very rare and right at the edge and
he says the reason why he says there has to be some of these is because he says otherwise
we would never be able to learn language here's where he and Wittgenstein would butt heads because
Wittgenstein has that analysis of extensive definition where you point to something and say
that's a table or something like that and says that you in order to do that you have to already
be immersed in the language game of extensive definition Quine thinks you can do extensive
definition and in fact you have to be able to do that otherwise babies would never acquire language
there has to be an an entering wedge into language and it has to be these very basic claims about
the world that can be confirmed or disconfirmed by the evidence so Quine and Kahnab share this
belief in observation sentences and what the project that Kahnab is interested in is to try to
justify our theory of the world by showing that it reduces to our evidence for it now
Quine says this is an epistemological project because what we're trying to do is we're trying
to show how our view of how the world works which is sort of out you know might say like
our collective beliefs about the world is justified on the basis of the evidence we have for it and
that's very much like the old epistemological project of saying can I know that there's an
external world my evidence for it is what my senses are telling me but is that evidence enough to
justify the belief I have that there's a world out there and the skeptics say no
so this is just sort of on a larger scale so instead of talking about individual people's
beliefs we're talking about the human human Kahn's collective theory of the world is that
justified based on the basis of the kind of input or that we as humans have and Kahnab wants to try
and do that now because of the Quine duem thesis essentially Quine says you can't do that you
cannot reduce theoretical sentences individually to observational sentences and consequently
you can have and this is the indeterminacy of translation another one of Quine's key and
controversial theses you can have inconsistent theories of the world that are equally confirmed
by the evidence and there is no way to decide between them so we have to give up on this so
but epistemologies if there is such a thing as epistemology its job is to explain the
relationship between our theory of the world and the observational evidence well the logical
positivist thought it could be done this way it can't this kind of project is like in the beginning
of his article he compares it with what Frager and Russell were trying to do with math they were
trying to say well we have this we have math how can we justify our mathematical beliefs well
if we could reduce them to the claims of logic which is more basic and elementary and and self
evidently true then that would in some sense justify math well we couldn't that's one of the
things that for example girdle's incompleteness shows that this this project won't work and
quine is saying a similar thing we can't do the reduction of theory into observational sentences
where does that leave epistemology well quine says the only other option is to treat epistem is to
naturalize epistemology that is to treat epistemology as instead a study of what humans do in fact do
because humans as a matter of fact are constantly producing theories of the world on the basis of
our sensory stimulus and quine calls a late work of his from stimulus to science which is
he talks about us as sort of like bags of nerve endings and he says our nerve endings are stimulated
that's the input from this as he calls it meager input just electrical signals that we're getting
from our nerve endings we construct as he puts it this torrential this far more ornate and convoluted
description of the reality our theoretical view of of the explanation of our sensory stimulation
and and epistemology's job now according to quine given that it can't be reduced to
in this way is to just say well how do humans do that how do humans produce this huge theoretical
output on the basis of sensory input so on a more a very basic example would be how is it
that we see in 3d given that our input is 2d that we're just getting stimulation that it doesn't
really have a dimension it's just electrical impulses reaching our brain and as far as we know
they're not caused by 3d objects and yet we see the world in 3d why is it that we see this world
in 3d how are we constructing 3d pictures of the world from 2d input that's an epistemological
issue how do we do it and so for example a naturalized epistemologist would be interested in something
called mars theory of vision which is a scientific study of how this works and that's what that's
the kind of thing that epistemologists should be interested in they shouldn't be interested in this
crusty old philosophical business of you know the kind of thing that getier wrote on you know
what are the conditions for knowing that p no you should get into the science because science
is all we have to go on so if knowledge knowledge is a natural phenomenon that can be studied our
knowledge is our picture of the world so here of course classical epistemologists would say well
we can't call it knowledge yet because we don't know if it meets the standards of knowledge
but to say that is to say that there's something above science that can judge what
the correct standards are and there aren't there isn't there's only science all we have to go on
is science quine is is very fond of quoting another logical positivist called Otto Neurath
uh who has an image of a ship and he says we're on this ship and we're building the ship at the
same time we're on it we're building the ship that we're floating on um and that's our relationship
to science that is we're using science at the same time we're thinking about science but you
there is no you can't get off the ship of science to look down on it and say oh we're doing it right
the only standards by which to judge science are science there or where science here is
taken broadly to include all of our theory of the world which includes philosophy but the method
science uh like natural science is the most successful and therefore preferable methodology
because as the positivist pointed out science was far more was advancing at a massively accelerated
rate in the early 20th century with Einstein and quantum mechanics and all of that stuff
so clearly science's methodology is is the one that we should be using okay so knowledge is a
natural phenomenon it resolves the issue of epistemological priority what's this well he says
uh prior a a fairly recent dispute in in epistemology that he says now is goes by the board
is um was brought up by the gestalt psychologists and gestalt psychologists say we don't actually
perceive in the way that classic philosophers like Descartes and Locke and in particular Locke
Barkley and Hume say they say we get we are directly aware of sense data first like patches of red
and patches of blue and then Locke in particular paints this picture we take these tiny little
Lego building blocks and then we construct them together to form objects so an object is constructed
in our mind from all of these tiny little individual very basic sense data um and the
gestalt psychologist says that's not true we just directly see the world in 3d we don't see the world
in 2d and then in further 3d world we directly perceive in 3d that's what we're or wherever
conscious of we're never conscious of the sensory stimulations that are uh sort of cause you might
say our 3d picture of the world we're never conscious of those what we're conscious of
immediately is a 3d picture of the world we see the world in color in 3d and that's what we're
conscious of so that's our first that should have epistemological priority over the unconscious stuff
that causes it um and quine says well once we see knowledge as a natural phenomenon we uh epistemological
priority is resolved by what should come first the conscious or the unconscious and he says it's
obviously the unconscious because if you're viewing things in a naturalistic way you look to the the
causal origin and the causal origin of our 3d picture of the world is the sensory stimulation
so that comes first and he suggests at the end of the article possible projects for epist for
naturalized epistemology is to look at our do humans have a certain limited number of epistemological
building blocks it and he draws the analogy with phonemes in in linguistics in linguistics there's
this idea of phonemes that there's a finite number of uh audible um sounds that can be the basis of
words and language if languages share the same set then humans we know something about languages of
which humans are capable of speaking you can't use you can't have more uh phonetic distinctions than
we're capable of perceiving and maybe there are you know we there's sort of uh humans have a limited
resolution you might say a limited pixel um density in our uh perception of the world
that will be something worth finding out and that would tell us that would tell us something about
what we can know or another suggestion is evolutionary epistemology why do we see the world
in color for example I imagine uh this is an example uh you know we have color in the center of our
retinas and black and white uh rods color cones color sensing cones and black and white sensing
rods on the periphery of our vision what this now the black and white ones are much more sensitive
to minute changes in light which is why in your peripheral vision you can detect motion
much better and the evolutionary uh suggestion for this is this is good if you're being hunted by
if you're a prey animal as we are uh this will enable you to detect the movement of tigers or
wolves uh off to the side and you can you will immediately see them you'll be much harder to
sneak up on but of course these features of our eyes while they serve an evolutionary purpose
uh dictate how we view the world so evolutionary epistemology would say the way we view the world
is a product of forces that enabled us to survive um now epistemology in general or
certainly before this suggestion was deemed to be normative that is epistemology this is why it
was first philosophy this is why Descartes starts with epistemology because he says we've got to give
produce standards to judge our knowledge claims in other spheres when we start making metaphysical
or ethical claims we judge them by the standards that epistemology has given us so epistemology
provides us with norms standards to judge knowledge in other spheres can naturalized epistemology
do that or is it just a descriptive enterprise uh does it just say this is how
we acquire our picture of the world is it the right picture of the world
i'm not interested in that it seems like it seems like and science is norm is often said
there's usually said to be a fact value distinction science is interested in the facts
you know like scientists would say it's just the fact that humans are violent
we don't say that it's a good thing we just tell you why humans are violent because you
know it helps in survival or it was evolutionary practical or something we're not saying it's a
good thing or that it should continue we're just telling you the facts we're not judging the facts
so if epistemology is now just part of science can it provide us with standards
coins is yes it can give us standards the standards of science the standards of scientific
rigor so if we want to know are we in a position to know this well uh you know science would say
you will be in a position to know it if you're in the kind of circumstances where the typical
human can provide a picture that is reliable um now but then is there any way to get outside of
science and say is science doing it right no uh there is no such thing for for quine as first
philosophy again back to noir earth's ship we can't get off the ship and look down on it and judge it
so although quine says it does provide us with norms the they're the norms of science and we
can't judge those um so other although quine says yes other people the critics would say no
uh naturalized epistemology has become an important part of um epistemology but it
hasn't killed off the old-fashioned epistemology either now it's just so epistemology is just a
larger animal quine would have had it kill off all the other kinds of epistemology he he would say
come on haven't you seen i've told you that uh uh the old-fashioned epistemology it's obvious
that it's a pointless exercise but epistemology goes on regardless uh it's just now there's a new
subsection of epistemology thanks to quine and people who are influenced by him
you
ghettier cases are pretty much uh they multiply these aren't rare ones these aren't specifically
very um very contrived cases it's it's fairly easy to come up with cases like this in fact
there's some suggestion that birch and russell uh came up with his own cases uh a long time
previously in a book of his so that's a little bit of controversy it's it's not necessarily clear
that ghettier was the first person to publish on this but certainly he did a good good job of
presenting the cases and they have led to a sort of sea change in um epistemology in this kind of
epistemology you can so the the ghettier problem is what's missing what is the extra element that
we need to add um so that if you meet one two three four then you do know something that's the
debate or there is some suggestion that this is okay and that we can fix this and respond to
ghettier cases but certainly ghettier presented a challenge that epistemologists then had to meet
which is why this article short as it is is so famous