On this episode of Marketing Against the Green, we talked to Matt Wolf.
Matt has one of the biggest and best YouTube channels, all about AI, and so we had to talk
to Matt all about apps and tools.
We get into the biggest AI winners, the biggest AI losers, and who are going to be the biggest
AI apps in the future?
Where should you invest your money?
I'm Kieran Flanagan, the CMO at Zapier.
I'm here always with my co-host, Kip Bonner, the CMO at HubSpot.
Let's get into it.
Okay, Matt, it is great to have you on the show.
I've spent a lot of hours watching your YouTube channel, getting all of the latest news, getting
all of the latest apps, so we're really excited to have you on the show.
Yeah, thanks for having me.
I'm excited to nerd out and chat with you guys about this stuff.
We're excited to steal your brain for a minute.
Yeah.
Get all of your AI knowledge.
I thought we could start with this, which is, how did you start in the YouTube AI space?
How did you end up there?
What was the tip and point?
What were you doing before that?
Just give us a little bit of the context, the background.
Sure, yeah.
I've been doing digital marketing stuff since 2009.
I quit my day job, so to speak, back in 2009, and have been all in on content marketing
ever since.
My YouTube channel started in 2009.
I started blogging in 2009, and then over the years, I was just testing all sorts of
different things.
I had an online course around how to drive traffic.
I've had online courses around podcasting.
My first course that I ever sold was about how to build blogs, and so over the years,
I was just testing different courses.
I got really good at affiliate marketing, and most of my income over the last decade
has actually come from affiliate revenue, from promoting other products and my content,
and so I've just been surfing around in the world of digital marketing and course creation
and just playing with whatever would work, and I had a lot of good months and a lot of
bad months where I didn't know how I was going to pay the bills, and it was just kind of
throwing stuff at the wall all the way up until 2022 when the AI stuff started to pick
up some steam.
So at the time, I had a top 1% podcast with my co-host, Joe Fear, called Hustle and Flowchart.
He's actually still running that podcast to this day, but him and I were podcasting and
interviewing other digital marketers and things like that, and we started to have people
come on and talk about some of these newer technologies that were coming out.
One of the first ones we came across was Jasper, which was like an AI copywriting tool.
At the time, it was called Conversion AI, and then it was called something that Marvel
sued him for or wanted to sue him for, and then it eventually became Jasper, so I learned
about GPT-3, and we actually started making content about GPT-3 and Jasper and some of
these AI tools back in 2021, but nobody was really paying attention to AI back then.
Nobody really cared about it, and then about mid 2022, I made a video on my YouTube channel
about AI art and various AI art generators, and this was actually before Mid Journey came
out.
I was talking about Dolly and some of the stable diffusion stuff that was available, and that
video started to do well.
It got a few thousand views, and I went, oh, that's better than any of the other videos
I put out.
Maybe I'll do another video on AI.
I did a video about how to train your own face into the AI using a tool called DreamBoost,
so you can make AI images with your own likeness.
That video doubled my best video and had 15,000 views, and I went, okay, I'm going to keep
going down this AI path.
Then the video that really took off was when Chat GPT was released.
I made a video around Chat GPT, and then that one, I remember, I made that video.
I published it at 10 p.m. on a Tuesday or something, and then went to bed, woke up the
next morning, and that video had 60,000 views, and I went, oh, my God, this is the best video
I've ever done, and in 12 hours it got 60,000 views, and that video actually went on to do
over a million views over the course of the next two weeks.
That was sort of the pivot point where I went, I'm just going all in on AI.
Every video I make from here on out is going to be about the latest, coolest AI tools.
I'm going to make tutorials.
I'm going to talk about the news.
I'm going to talk about cool tools that I come across, and so ever since about October
of last year, every video I've released has just been about the coolest AI stuff that
I've built or come across or tutorials or things that I've learned how to do and just
shown it off, and that's been the last 10 months of my life of just making that content.
In that same time, I also built a website called Future Tools because I was coming across
all these AI tools, and I was struggling to sort of wrap my head around all these tools.
I was putting them into an Excel spreadsheet, but it got to a point where the Excel spreadsheet
had 100 rows in it, and I was kind of losing track of what did what, so I literally built
Future Tools as like a database for myself to kind of wrap my head around what tools
I've come across and what they do.
I shared that on Twitter, that got retweeted, it kind of went viral.
My Future Tools website blew up, and now it gets over a million views per month, so it's
the last 10 months have just been a roller coaster after over a decade of just kind of
trying different stuff and having little successes here and there, and now all of a sudden, this
is my life now.
That's the lesson for everybody watching, right?
This is the story time and time again, which is it takes years to build a quality of skills
that you can do something well, and then find the right fit of topic and audience for yourself
to really break out.
I think, Kieran, when you and I started this podcast, we were like, oh, it's going to take
us three to five years to make this thing big, real, like everything we want, and I
think that's the right timeline for anybody to consider, and the reason most people fail
is because they just don't do it long enough.
They don't get into it, and the other thing they don't do is they don't do what you did,
Matt, and pivot when they get the aha moment.
You woke up to that video, you had your aha moment, and you're like, all right, I know
what I'm doing now, and I'm okay leaving that stuff behind, and now I'm going in a new direction.
I think that's a really interesting point, like Matt, was it the same YouTube channel
you had since 2009, or so you're just grinding away and then pivoted to AI.
The other really important thing is, Matt, because you've been at this like 2009, you
mentioned affiliate, all of these things.
Did you ever hang out in the warrior form?
Back in the glorious, back in the day, when the warrior form was the warrior form.
Kieran loves the warrior form.
Yep, yep, I actually, one of my first products I ever sold was a WSO in the warrior form.
There you go.
That's where all the best people came from is the old school shady warrior form days.
Yep, that's where I originated back.
I remember back in 2007, when I was still working in my day job, I was working in a
manufacturing plant whenever the boss wasn't looking.
I was in the warrior form reading about various ways to make money online.
Let's go.
I was in there, getting my Frank Kearns, even page, all the copywriter stuff.
Also, and so I think, yeah, but I think coming back to Kearns point, people have two short
of time horizons on what success looks like, and they give up before they ever get started.
And like getting started is like a couple of years.
And that's where they kind of like give up.
I've actually seen studies where you can actually see like a most podcasters, most
people who blog, they kind of give up at a certain point in time and they give up ever
before they've actually even figured out what their thing is, like what their angle is,
what their topic is, what their kind of like area of expertise is going to be,
where their niche is going to be.
And so it's like super cool.
Like you just kept kind of iterating, kept trying to figure out like,
what was the thing that was going to resonate with your audience?
And you got one signal and you went all in.
For sure.
Yeah.
I mean, my thing has always kind of been, I nerd out about cool tools, right?
So back in the early days, when I first started my YouTube channel,
I was sharing different WordPress plugins.
I had a WordPress site and I was like, oh, check out this plugin.
It does this, check out this plugin.
It did this.
And then the first course that I ever sold was a course on WordPress.
And I was sharing various WordPress plugins.
So like the sort of common threads have always been,
I love making content and I love nerding out about cool tools.
It's just in 2022 when AI, all of these new tools started to flood the market.
It was kind of like, I found my home.
These are the tools that like I'm excited about,
but also the world is getting excited about.
It's incredible how much money or what kind of business you can build around cool tools.
Like I remember back in the day when I was like really leaning into search,
this guy was just obsessed by like Apple, Apple products,
like MacBooks in particular.
And just built this entire business, search business at the time,
like AdSense was like the cool thing to try to make money through.
And just own like every search term you could actually own through,
like all of these different search terms around MacBooks
and all of the kind of different laptops or computers that Apple had.
That dude brought in like millions, millions every year.
Like just with this site, didn't do anything about it.
So like finding niche, finding this topic is really important.
One thing I wanted to try out on you both is,
so Kip and I talk about this all the time.
We do some investing, talked to a lot of founders,
try to find like good spaces to invest in.
And so one of the things I've been doing on AI is trying to like map out
where I see a lot of the momentum right now,
like where I see a lot of the apps, where I'm having all the conversations.
And so I wanted to kind of map out where I see it,
let you all say whether there's things I'm missing,
things that you disagree with,
and then kind of like talk about where do we think the winners
or losers are going to appear from?
Like there's been basically where are the early winners
that we can go through, like the happy winners,
but I don't think they're going to be long-term winners
and where will the long-term winners come from?
The first are just like the kind of chat LLM models, right?
Chat, GBT, Bardee, Llama.
I don't know if you saw Facebook's latest release.
Actually, there's a company you probably know,
that's not because you know all things about AI tools,
but one of my favorite tools is like perplexity AI,
the kind of search engine.
And they released a chat bot
based upon Facebook's latest open source model,
which I thought was really cool.
But basically all of the like Entropic Clawed,
all of the different models like Poe.
The second, so that's like one batch, right?
And it's actually really hard to invest in that batch,
actually, because you don't see many of them
and like it's really hard to pick winners,
but we should talk about that batch.
The second is like the creative tools, right?
You mentioned Jasper was one of the very early tools,
the writing tools, the image tools, the video tools,
like Runway is an incredible video tool.
Image Journey is obviously one of the best image tools.
So that's a whole other space.
The third space for me is like B2B tools.
I don't know if you're seeing them or this, Kip.
Like, you know, AI CRMs, AI sales tools,
like all of the things you need to do.
A lot of it is actually the AI sales outreach tools,
right now, like sales tools, customer success tools,
customer support tools.
Like basically how you run a B2B go to market.
The fourth is data analysis, right?
We did a whole episode on code interpreter.
But then there's all of these other plugins
that can integrate to Excel, can integrate into Google Sheets,
can integrate into your data platform
and be able to provide a kind of chat layer
on top of that data.
The fifth is like knowledge work tools.
And so knowledge work tools were the one
that I talked a lot about at the start with you, Kip,
is like the hardest thing about fast growth companies
is that people get disconnected
from the core information that's important.
Like it just becomes really hard.
Slack, I think, is a really incredible tool
that actually makes this much worse,
where like it is hard to get a grasp
on all of the data churning through a company.
And so you have these kind of knowledge tools
that existing companies like a Glean,
like a chief knowledge officer, there's a Glean.
Two of my companies actually pivoted
to try to solve this problem recently.
There's a note taken tools for Zoom.
Like all of the tools you could have
to like keep a company much more efficient,
keep knowledge running through that company
in much more efficient ways.
And then there's all the productivity tools, right?
Like just like how we be more productive.
And so I want to like pause, let you all react to that.
What are categories you think that maybe I've missed
or they're the wrong categories?
What does that sound in terms of like
how we think about that today?
You're trying to figure out where to put some money.
Matt, tell me where to invest.
Please, Matt.
Please do it.
I'm like, well, the listeners get to benefit.
The viewers get to benefit.
Where should I put my dollars?
All right, I'll let Matt go first.
He's our guest here.
Yeah, so when it comes to that kind of stuff,
I tend to think that the best place to be
is the shovel sellers, right?
Like the NVIDIAs, the AMDs,
the companies that are benefiting no matter where.
Like what tools you're using.
I think Microsoft has a really, really smart plan, right?
What you just mentioned,
Perplexity is using Llama 2, which is Meta's platform.
Well, Meta just partnered with Microsoft
to release this Llama 2 platform, right?
Well, Microsoft also is partnered with OpenAI on ChatGPT.
So you look at that and they're like,
okay, didn't they just partner with two competing projects?
Well, one's closed source with the ChatGPT.
One's open source with Llama.
Well, the common denominator between those two
is they're both going to be using Microsoft's Azure servers, right?
So Microsoft is going to get the benefit
of people using the open source, the closed source,
because it's all going to be on the Azure servers, right?
And then NVIDIA, right?
NVIDIA makes all of the GPUs, all of the graphic cards,
all of the, pretty much all of these cloud compute systems
are using NVIDIA GPUs.
So NVIDIA is going to really benefit.
AMD is trying to get into the game.
So a lot of those are the types of tools
that I would really be wanting to look at.
I think my worry with a lot of the large language models,
with a lot of the image generation tools,
even the like new text to speech tools
that are coming out that are really, really, really good,
is there's open source models, there's closed source models,
there's APIs, there's no real moat on any of them, right?
Like anybody can go and build on top of Llama 2
and build a competitor to chat GPT and improve off of it
and build something even better.
Anybody can go and use an 11 Labs API,
which is a text to speech generator,
and go and build better and better text to speech tools.
Most of the AI art image generation tools,
they're either using stable diffusion under the hood,
or they're using Dolly under the hood.
So a lot of these tools, they just don't have that moat,
and it's just so easy for so many tools to pop up.
And so I feel like a lot of those platforms,
there's gonna be a bit of a race to the bottom
where you're gonna see companies pop up
and make a cheaper version that does the same thing,
and then another version that's cheaper
that does the same thing,
and eventually a version that's completely free,
but supported by ads everywhere.
So a lot of the models that are coming out now,
I would have a real concern about the long-term future of them,
just because of how much everything
seems to be moving to open source,
and how many available APIs are out there.
Well, look, I like that we're being your investment counsel,
and we're happy to be your CIOs today, Kieran.
Maybe you'll actually make some money,
and your companies won't go out of business.
Not saying that.
Shots fired.
But it's kind of what's happening.
Be but I turn.
But here's my take.
I agree with what's Matt saying.
In a world of whether you're an investor,
or you're a worker who wants to go work
at one of these companies,
or you're a buyer,
you're thinking about buying one of these tools,
I think there are two things to really consider
to understand where the big opportunity
long-term is gonna be,
and which is Matt touched on one,
which is distribution.
He touched on the other one, economics.
What is differentiated about this company
that's going to allow them to survive the long-term?
AMD and NVIDIA and all of the picks
and shovels kind of providers,
they're differentiated because the economics are great
because there's gonna be constant demand.
As the market goes up,
their economics are going to improve.
The other thing that they have is they're differentiated
because they have proprietary technology.
NVIDIA has its own way of manufacturing facilities,
everything of making its GPUs.
That's a really hard thing to do.
If you are just writing code
on top of somebody else's APIs,
that's not very differentiated.
And your economics are tough
because one, you're at the mercy
of whatever that API access costs.
And two, it's really hard for you to build a product
that is deep enough that provides enough value
that you don't have a lot of customer churn issues
where you have a lot of customers cancel.
And that's what we're seeing in the AI space right now
is a lot of customers canceling
and a lot of these companies dealing
with really massive churn issues,
especially given that the pace of innovation,
like Matt is on his YouTube channel all the time
talking about new stuff,
which means that like you could have a plan
and a model that's like obsolete.
Pace of innovation is crazy,
particularly because it's so much easier to build,
like it takes three to five people
to build something that historically
has taken like 50 to 60 people.
This is my thesis.
Go picks and shovels.
Matt, I was what's app in here
and earlier today about an idea
that we're going to get your take on,
which is I think one of the winners
are very small businesses.
Because of AI and automation,
we're going to have more and more profitable,
more successful one to 10 employee businesses.
And if you are like me and believe that,
like I think there is a huge opportunity
for somebody to raise a venture fund
that all they do is invest in companies
that are providing AI, automation,
and tooling for that very small business category,
because the profitability of that category
is going to improve.
Traditionally, that's been a really hard category to serve
because there's a lot of business,
going out of business cancellation risk and everything.
I think that's going to change a lot.
The other category that you didn't include Kieran
that I would like to add,
and this is a hat tip to our friend Linus
who we had on the show recently,
he talked a lot about models operating on the edge.
So like having personalized models on your phone.
And like one of the most interesting things
that's happened this week is Rewind,
which is really awesome app to provide an AI layer across
basically everything you do on your computer,
just launched its iPhone app today.
And so now you can have this AI assistant on your iPhone
in a really powerful way,
in kind of this personal secure gesture data model
operating like on the edge on your phone.
And I think that is a category where
you're not going to have 100 winners,
but the handful of companies that win
are going to win pretty big.
You know what's one of the wildest thought exercises
for the three of us just to quickly touch on
in relation to this is,
if you told me like three months ago,
if you look at open AI, you would say,
wow, like open AI are going to be one of the biggest,
most profitable, biggest market cap businesses of all time.
Now I think open AI might be one of the most
interesting case studies in if distribution is truly a moat.
Because actually their core technology
is being eroded pretty rapidly.
I don't know what you think about that.
You agree or not, if you could like,
if you had 100,000 to invest,
are you putting that in like open AI today
or you think that their core business is
starting to be eroded by these open source models,
by like other companies just like replicating what they do.
You know, I think open AI is going to figure it out.
I think open AI has some of the smartest researchers
on the planet on their team.
So I do think that they're going to figure out
how to continually build more of a moat around their platform.
You know, some of the team that they have there behind the scenes,
I hate to try to pronounce their names.
Greg Brockman and some of the team there
are some of the people that are like,
you know, founding fathers of AI.
That have been doing this for a long time,
that are going to figure this stuff out.
So I do have faith in open AI.
If I had the money, I'd probably be putting it
more towards Microsoft and NVIDIA though,
because I think that's still the safer bet.
And Stan Lutman is an awesome, incredible founder.
So I think like part of it is,
the NVIDIA founder is an incredible founder.
Like if you've ever read up on that founder.
Oh yeah, Jen Simone, yep.
Yeah, what's really interesting about open AI,
like there was a really good tweet
about what Elon's doing at Twitter,
which is Elon is going through the biggest experiment
of all time to see if the only thing that truly matters
is like network effects.
Like, hey, getting rid of the brand,
getting rid of all of the actual users,
getting rid of all the things that people like.
But the thing he still has is network effects.
And if you have network effects,
like it's really an incredible moat and hard to disrupt.
And like open AI has not built network effects
into the product just yet,
but I do think part of your moat can just be
you have probably the best team in the industry
and like you'll figure out how to stay ahead.
But like the pace of evolution,
even in the kind of space that they're in,
like I don't even think I would have seen six months ago,
just how many competitors they have
in such a short amount of time.
Yeah, and open AI too, you know,
they're not just chat GPT, we have to remember, right?
They've also got Dolly.
They also have the GPT 3.5, the GPT4 APIs.
I mean, how many thousands and thousands of companies
are running with the GPT4 API?
I mean, I get a GPT4 API bill every month
just from playing around with it myself.
So, you know, I think that they have a lot more going for them
than just chat GPT.
I think the public sees chat GPT
and that's sort of what the public thinks of with open AI.
But they've got, you know, that sort of API business
behind the scenes that's powering
so many other companies as well.
What do you think happens in the kind of spaces
where it's like quick to replicate?
Because there is a need for these kind of like writing tools,
image tools, video tools, the sales outreach tools.
Like they are going to be incredibly important to companies.
I think every company is going to use some form of these tools.
But I wonder like how you win or is there a winner
or everyone just uses their own special flavor?
There's two things here.
There's two things that are part of it.
One of the things that are part of it is with chat GPT,
we're all getting trained on a chat kind of interface,
but more of a chat workflow
where you can have a lot of different types of actions
happening in one stream.
And we're going to all want that.
It's a way better experience.
You and I collaborated on a chat GPT thread care
and it was like, awesome, great experience.
We're all going to want to do that more.
In a world where that's true, you know who benefits?
Platforms.
People who have a wide set of use cases
that they can bundle into that new experience
and just basically put AI and that chat experience on.
So I think incumbents and platforms are really going to win.
And I think a lot of those point solutions right now,
it's going to be a little bit like .com bus 3.0.
Where they're just going,
like a couple will make it and the majority will not
because what they're doing will get gobbled up
by a lot of the existing incumbents.
Right.
Matt, what tool has like other than like the open AI
or the code interpreter.
Me and Kip had a moment,
we were doing like code interpreter live.
We were kind of doing stuff analysis for the podcast and RSS.
And I use these tools all the time,
but I hadn't read because I'm like,
maybe it's because I don't have any friends.
So I hadn't used the share and function
where like I'd shared this analysis with Kip.
But my analysis took me two hours.
Like I was going back and forth,
getting it to create charts,
getting it to like create tables, join tables,
then create charts on those join tables.
And I was like, this is like awesome, right?
Like I was like, this is super awesome.
But then I sent it to Kip and Kip,
you can just click on the share link.
You import that entire chat charts data
and then you can just start like building on top of it.
I didn't actually not,
I thought I was sending him like a thread
and he could see it and share it,
but I didn't know he could just easily start
to like rapidly iterate on that.
And I just blown my mind
because now you can just start to share these like
conversations and all this stuff with someone else
and they can just build on that really, really rapidly.
And that was like a bit of mind-blowing experience.
What's been a tool like that for you,
which you're just like, holy smokes,
like this is a whole new way to do things.
So there's been a couple.
I mean, so Anthropics Clawed 2 actually blew me away
when they first made it available
because of that 100,000 token context window,
meaning that you can essentially upload an entire book
and ask questions of that book, right?
You can copy an entire giant, 100,000
or 50,000 word article or something,
paste it in there, ask questions of it.
So Clawed 2 is really, really impressive.
I've actually started using Clawed 2 almost more than ChatGPT,
especially for summarization type stuff
and getting bullet points and helping me rewrite stuff.
But I think more, since that's sort of similar to ChatGPT,
I think the one tool that really blew my mind
when I did sort of a demo video on it
and I was sort of playing with it in real time,
that I really went, whoa, this is really crazy.
It was 11 Labs.
When I started playing with 11 Labs,
then I was able to train my own voice into 11 Labs
and then type in some text and then it spoke back to me.
I actually made a video of it on my YouTube channel
where I typed a bunch of words and had it speak back
and I was listening to it and I'm like,
yeah, I don't really think it sounds like me.
And then everybody on my YouTube channel,
all the comments were like,
I wasn't looking at my screen at that point
and I didn't realize you stopped talking.
Like I had some sort of cognitive dissonance from it
where I was like, that doesn't sound like me.
And everybody was like, no, that's you, that's your voice.
And then I started playing with it a little more
where I would take a voice from somebody from a podcast
and train it in there and see if I can replicate their voice.
And that was working.
And that to me was really, really mind blowing.
Also scary at the same time, right?
There's been a handful of scams that have popped up
where people have called somebody's parents
and then use somebody else's voice
to try to get money out of the parents.
And so it was one of the things where I played with it
for the first time and I went, this is mind blowing.
This is groundbreaking.
But also this scares the hell out of me.
Yeah, I watched that video.
I think it was around the time, Kip,
I watched you the Joe Rogan and Andrew Huberman fake podcast
when they actually were doing video
and then they out of the blue advertised
some sort of weight loss pills.
Hey, Joe, what do you think about aliens coming down
and they built the pyramids?
Like all the crazy stuff he talks about.
Oh, but what do you think about these weight loss pills?
Oh, they're super dope.
But still, wow, this stuff is going to come out
as pretty fast in terms of how rapidly
we're going to be able to do deepfakes and spoof people.
Absolutely.
All right, so Claude, 11 Labs, what else?
What else are your other favorite AI tools of 2023 so far?
So mid-journey, every time mid-journey releases a new update,
that just blows my mind.
Except for it's in Discord.
Are you a, you can't be a fan of the Discord experience.
Like why get out of the Discord?
Yeah, they are planning on getting out of the Discord.
In fact, if you've generated over, I think, 10,000 generations,
they let you use their web user interface.
But they are moving to a web interface,
but they're just, they're only letting certain beta testers
use it right now.
So it's getting there.
I also use Leonardo AI a lot,
which is another AI image generator that's really, really solid.
You can actually train your own sort of styles into it.
You can upload a whole bunch of images that you like,
and it will train on those styles,
and you can generate more images in that style.
So I like that one a lot.
You know, since I do a lot of YouTube videos,
I like to play with a lot of like,
create a video tools, right?
So I use RunwayML a lot.
I use a tool called Kyber a lot,
which makes really cool AI image generations.
It uses like Deforum,
and I think DiscoDiffusion behind the scenes.
I mean, there's just too many tools to list,
but there's, I play with a lot of like,
the visual effects type stuff,
because I'm constantly experimenting with,
what could I make that I can throw into a YouTube video
that make people go,
ooh, I need to know how he does that.
The video tools are the ones where you can have an avatar
within your, you're kind of go-to-market,
so you have an avatar on customer support,
or you have an avatar who's actually doing your sales,
and there's a company called Air,
they got a lot of traction,
but there's other companies doing this,
which is like, I can train it to sound like a human,
it can do the sales, it can do the customer support,
and it's like, they're like 80% there,
but that 80% is nowhere near good enough, right?
Like it's very monotone,
it's like, you know, the videos are just like,
well, this is me, I am speaking to you now,
like here, right?
Like they're just like, no tone, no personality.
I suspect that, I wonder how hard that 20% is gonna be.
I wonder if it's like one of those problems
where like the 20% is just like a huge jump up
from where we are today,
because video is like one of the,
I think most interesting spaces,
runway has probably one of the best tools,
but one of the ones I'm interested in is like,
how rapidly you can just have a person on support 24-7,
doing like your tweenshares,
how you can have someone,
your entire sales team like 24-7,
but it doesn't seem like we're close, it seems like.
I think the biggest problem with a lot of those tools
is honestly just the latency between
when you ask it the question,
and when it responds to the question, right?
Like you ask the question,
there's like a 10 second gap,
and then there's a response.
There are some companies that are figuring that out though.
There are some companies that,
I was talking to the CEO of a company called Convay,
who they're actually building this technology for video games,
where you can go up and speak into your microphone
with an NPC character,
and then the character sort of generates random,
real-time conversations.
So every time you play through the game,
you're gonna have different conversations
with that character, right?
So I could go up and ask them a question,
one play through, the second play through.
If I ask them the exact same question,
they're not gonna give me the same response
because it's all generated with AI.
Well, his program actually fixed that latency issue
where it actually has this sort of like
a buffer type thing built in,
where as I'm speaking,
while it's hearing these words,
it's already processing the words,
and then when I finally pause,
it's already processed the first part of what I said
and is ready to respond.
So they've actually figured it out
where the gap between what I say
and what they respond with is milliseconds.
So it's, I mean, it's getting really, really close.
And then with tools like 11 Labs,
I feel like all those tools need to do
to get rid of that sort of robotic response voice
is just tie into like an API, like 11 Labs API.
And now you've got a voice that sounds
just like a real human that's almost indistinguishable.
And then combine that with a tool like Synthesia
or something like that,
that actually puts that sort of human-looking avatar
in front of you.
So it looks like they're speaking to you
and now we're crossing that unkindly valley
and we've got somebody that is having a conversation,
sounds like a real voice and is responding in real time.
It's just the technologies all exist.
I haven't just seen one tool pull them all together
into a single purpose built tool for like sales.
Back in my software engineer days,
one of the interviews I went for like very early
at a college, the person who was interviewing me
like ran the entire software development department.
And he purposely, and he told me like afterwards
this is part of his interview style,
he purposely waited 20 seconds between asking a question,
you answering and him responding.
So he would leave like 20 seconds of uncomfortable silence.
And he said he reason, and he would just sit there like,
and he would nod his head for some reason and just like,
and you're like, oh, I think the reason he was like,
I do that because it's incredible how people decide to like fill
that 20 seconds.
They just say like, you know,
they just say like totally insane stuff.
But I'm like, okay, like, but it's not a normal situation
that I'm going to have to deal with as a software engineer.
Where like part of me being a great software engineer
has been able to deal with like 20 seconds,
specifically 20 seconds of like uncomfortable silence.
So I still think he would actually do pretty well as like
an AI avatar or sales person.
Yeah, yeah, I hear they do that on Shark Tank too,
just to see how people respond.
Yeah, I mean, yeah, once AI starts playing mental games with us,
then we're all screwed.
It's like, oh, come on, man, I can't deal with that.
I can barely deal with it from other humans.
Right, right.
The last one I want to touch on both of you is
this is actually Paris seems to be a real hub
of these kind of companies.
We talked about it, which is it feels like most companies,
most large companies will have a plug and play version of a AI,
like an LLM model just for them, right?
Like you'll be able to plug in your data.
You'll be able to like customize it for your needs.
And I suspect at some point, like you'll just be able to go
any kind of podcast or any YouTuber can go to a service,
pay a couple of bucks, put their RSS feed,
and get some like models back and be able to build apps on top of that.
Are you seeing much of that?
Like how do you feel about that?
How do both of you think that's going to be a pretty big,
a big important space?
Yeah, I mean, I'm already seeing that kind of stuff that already exists.
I mean, there's already apps out there that have, you know,
scraped the entire Huberman Labs podcast.
And you can go and have conversations with Andrew Huberman
based on all of the conversations he's had on his podcast already.
That sort of already exists.
There's a tool that I spoke with the founder called personal.ai.
And what that tool is, is you can actually plug in your own blogs, RSS feed.
You can plug in your Twitter account.
You can, you know, personally journal directly inside of the app.
And what it does is it learns more and more and more about you.
And then you can go in there and have conversations with it.
And based on all of your own data, it will know how you would respond.
But then you can also go and give a front end user interface to other people.
So people can have a conversation with virtual digital me.
Like that's already out there and there's a handful of tools that do that.
I think we're going to see that more and more.
I mean, I think that's probably more likely the future of customer service, right?
Where you've got these AI models that are trained on all of the database of user documentation.
They're trained on all of past customer support conversations and how the response was handled.
And then over time, these AI bots are going to be able to handle 98.9% of the conversations
that come through without ever needing to, you know, touch a human customer support rep.
So that I think is coming really fast.
I think that's sort of the next wave that we're going to see a lot of, honestly.
Well, yeah. And it's like, when we talk about customer support,
the reason I think this is important, because Kieran, I'm about to bring up
one of the AI startups that you and I are most confused by to get Matt's take on.
But this is me rationalizing why they might exist.
You know, when we talk about, oh, AI is going to solve customer support or it's going to solve sales.
The reality is humans like to interact with different types of people in those situations.
Like some people want a salesperson who's really to the point.
Others want somebody who's just going to be very detail oriented, et cetera.
Right. And that's come, that's where you're not just going to need like one model.
You're going to need very specific versions of a model to solve the audience you're trying to address.
And maybe, maybe that's why character.ai exists.
I don't really understand.
Yeah, I don't understand.
Yeah, this is a good, like what am I missing?
What am I missing?
So much money and like, it seems like people are making some weird characters,
but like, are we, are we missing something about character?
This is like, I feel like I'm, you know, the person watching these humans act like NPC people
on TikTok doing gang gang ice cream, getting the dollars in, like, I feel that way about
characters that I know, like, I'm really into the AI space.
I'm like, I don't, I don't get the, I don't, what, what is this company doing?
Why are they going to be huge success?
Yeah, I mean, I'm, I'm with you.
I don't totally understand character AI.
Here's what I will say though.
I do have two kids, like they're both like sort of preteen age kids and they, for whatever
reason, love character AI.
Like them on their phone or on the desktop.
This is a part of that.
I just knew I was old.
So they've got their, they've got their Chromebooks.
Both my kids have little Chromebooks and they get into character AI and like,
we have a neighbor across the street that's the same age.
And apparently among like their age kids, like middle school age kids, they love this
sort of like fun digital companion thing.
It's like, it's like the new Tomagachi kind of thing, right?
Oh, wow.
That sort of generation seems to just be obsessed with this digital companion
conversation type app.
That's what I've noticed about it.
That's the only sort of justification I can make towards character AI.
I've played with it like once or twice and went, all right, I, you know,
I just had a conversation with Mega Man.
That, that was cool.
I don't know what else to do with this.
I love Mega Man.
But my kids like, they love it.
They're on character AI all the time, which is scary.
Hopefully that doesn't ruin, you know, real relationships and real
companionship with humans.
Hopefully it doesn't ruin like social skills and interpersonal skills and all the
things we actually need as a society.
Oh yeah.
That's a whole other rabbit hole that sort of scares me about AI is the whole digital
girlfriend thing that's starting to pop up where people are building relationships and
not feeling the need to have real relationships with, you know, the opposite sex
in real life because they've got their digital like, but that's a whole rabbit hole.
That's how population continues to decline.
Exactly.
They're $1 billion valuation.
So now we know they've, they've climbed the charts because Mega Man is on there.
I think Mega Man is kind of dope.
So I think that's, I think, I think that's a good case for them.
They're also, and Andres and Howard's back.
Matt, it's been incredible having you on the show.
We're both big fans.
We watch your YouTube channel.
Everyone who's listening to this should go check out your YouTube channel.
Keep up the date with AI every single week.
And we really appreciate you coming on and spending this time with us.
Yeah.
Thanks for having me on.
This has been absolutely a blast.
I've had a good time.
This data is wrong every freaking time.
Have you heard of HubSpot?
HubSpot is a CRM platform where everything is fully integrated.
Whoa.
I can see the clients' whole history.
Calls, support tickets, emails, and here's a test from three days ago.
I totally missed.
HubSpot, grow better.