Alright, so this is System Error 51 here again today and interestingly enough on the previous
videos I did about Blender and video editing, I got a lot of people that asked me to do
more with Blender and I finally have some time today because I'm off today of work
and also I was a little bit sick in the last few days, primarily in the last week I had
a little something going on in my throat which wasn't very nice but now I'm back in full
swing and today I'm going to show you a little bit about the compositor of Blender because
as you've seen in my previous videos Blender is quite capable of doing video editing
as such you know with all sorts of wipes, effects, picture-in-picture and all the kind
of crazy nonsense that you might want for your videos, sorry I'm going to drink a little
bit here but today we're going to have another look, oh well we're going to have a look at
another component of Blender that you may or may not know and that component is called
the compositor and with the compositor you may be able to achieve effects such as green
screening because I don't know if some of you have seen the videos I'm doing because
on some of them I'm now using a green screen effect which is, I'm also doing this in German
so this is a little green screen effect that I'm trying to achieve in my disclosure laboratories
videos, it's not entirely perfect but you know the camera also, I mean the camera is
good but the green screen I'm using sometimes has issues with the shadows and all this crazy
nonsense so it's not entirely perfect but I'm trying to do what I can and today we're
going to have a look at how this is achieved in Blender because you can obviously achieve
this in Premiere, if you have this you know on your machine you can use, you can obviously
use Premiere for that or if you use a Mac you can do this with Final Cut Pro and Motion
I think it's called, these are the two tools that would be doing this stuff on your PC
or Mac respectively, I think on the PC if you have Premiere you can also get something,
it's called After Effects which does a lot more than Premiere's build-in effects but
now let's get to the beef of today and we are going to use a different view than this
one but we're going to have to use the timeline, I'll show you why later and today we're not
going to use any 3D crazy nonsense so we can also delete the cube, in fact we can delete
everything in the scene because we don't need any of that for 2D compositing which is why
we are now going to switch to another view and this view is called something and it's
called Node Editor, in the Node Editor right now you see nothing, you can drag this view
around but it will not do very much, in Blender it works with nodes and we can also move all
this view out of the screen because we don't particularly need that, I think we can also
try to eliminate this view for the moment if that's possible at all but I don't think it is
because you would have to merge the views, I kind of did something that looks really weird
right now because I didn't want to split the views so I'm not sure how you can split that
back so let's just move it out of the view for the moment, that was I do apologize sorry,
anyways we are in the Node Editor here and the first thing you want to do is on this lower
part here you want to say node tree type which is what you really want right so here you can
enable the backdrop if you want to use that which might be quite interesting and I'll show you why
later use nodes obviously we want to use nodes there we go we have two default nodes free unused
obviously very important if you delete nodes like so the memory that was occupied by these nodes is
being released which is obviously something that you want to do if you don't necessarily have a
machine like like I do because this is start 8 by the way I'm using Windows 8 and this is called
start 8 buy it five bucks it's you know if you like your start menu from Windows 7 you may want
to and you want to have this back then five bucks isn't a very huge investment to make I also heard
that Microsoft is going to reintroduce the start menu where you on the left have this normal stuff
and on the right side you have crazy nonsense like live tiles you know and there's crazy bullshit but
I was going to say if you don't have a machine like me eight gigabyte of RAM if you just have
four or even sometimes two then it's always good practice to enable free unused because this will
free up a lot of memory backdrop is something that you want to consider using because backdrop
what what this all does is that when you use nodes it will automatically render the rendered image
as a backdrop as like a live wallpaper on on on this you know grid based view yeah so I mean this
all looks all looks very boring right now and it doesn't really do much so we should actually add
some nodes right and to do this we say a node no we say add and we want to have an input because
that might be good maybe go to start with and I prepared a little demo clip so we say movie clip
yeah you in the beginning you can move this around in any way you like so place it somewhere
here and you can also zoom in if you can necessarily read it perfectly so it's like perfectly scalable
you know blender is good for this dynamic rendering and this kind of kind of stuff
so we have a movie clip input node here all these things don't care too much about them
you say open and we say desktop and I blend the tutorial and we say I converted it to Moff to
make things easier so you say open clip boom there's me on a fairly cheap green screen and
in order to see your composited view which is what you may want to do you say add
output in the moment you say viewer and there's another output that you want that you want to add
later viewer okay and in the viewer you want to enable use alpha because you know if you
do multiple compositing or compositing of multiple things that are layering on top of each other
use alpha is very important and it works like if you if you worked with reason you know the
music composition tool then this will look familiar to you because you you go for this
like these are the outputs of your device if you want in like if this is this
were a reason device these would be the outputs and you want to drag a cable
into another input which is this one here see and now there's me right you can also say
you can also define the zoom somewhere if you select your viewer node
um if you you know the options on the right will will change according to the node you're
selecting yeah which is which is very nice um there there was an option to zoom in and out
which i think it's this one here uh no uh zoom here there we go zoom see um there you can adjust
the uh finished view in any way you like right and uh we want to achieve um
the removal of um the the the the green screen obviously yeah which isn't very hard to do in
blender so what you what you then want is to add another node which would be a hang on color
mat no it was mats and uh there you can select a number of um options to to achieve that you
know we we can play around to see what's best and uh i personally achieved the best results
with the color key yeah so if you say uh color key and you drag it in between the the the the
cable you just uh created and put your new node here your device if you want um then it will
you know it it always starts in the in with the inputs and goes through the steps to reach its
destination so here's the input the next thing it would it would be doing is color keying yeah
i i hope that makes sense in in some way um the next thing you want to do is then obviously
choose your color key color yeah and it's always good to practice uh to select uh one of the darker
shades of the color you want to remove um like so for example boom and you can already begin to see
that it starts to recognize um the green parts and and then you can begin to you know play around
with these sort of settings to achieve your green screen desired effect like so uh you can see it's
not entirely perfect but it's already a good start from from from from the beginning so you know
yeah you really have to be careful with the settings here um because sometimes it's not
necessarily perfect you can already see that i'm starting to disintegrate here um you know maybe
if you sort of uh change the color but which is not going to work now obviously um if you don't
want to use this uh note or reset you just do this and it will begin begin again you know key color
if you want to choose another color say here for example and then you can drag this cable
from the output here uh image and then you say you you drag the output image into this image
and you can see there are some better results uh you really have to uh play around with this
to achieve whoa uh eyes without a face um to achieve the desired effect you know it's not it's not
always easy to do with this color key um so let's see oops yeah that's right so if we add another
sort of matte thing let's say um channel key which oftentimes works better than the color key so
image drag this here and drag this here see uh and now you can begin to to try to you know
low and you see it's a lot smoother and a lot better than the other effect so you know like
this i i think i'm pretty happy with this for this demo um usually it it ends up around being
at the 0.98 or 0.97 range at which you achieve a lot of interesting effects and um if you zoom in
you will see that um it's not transparent see i'm not transparent it's just trying to um
make the best out of the situation right uh and since this is filmed in a room you also want to
remove all the other bullcrap right so you say add um uh and it's the stored
uh crop yeah so you put a crop here and it will automatically remove everything so first you have
to you know pump these up a lot and then um you know see left we can now start to
uh do this up would be probably hang on oh no uh down see uh like like so we also want to remove
the couch like this and right would be uh yeah like so see here we go so we now have myself
pretty perfectly cropped i'd say um there's another feature that you might want to use
um which is called color spill yeah so if you go add a color uh no i think it was a matte um
color spill which you would put at the end of the line most probably um and you can say
you know if you if you pump this ratio up or down you can achieve more realistic coloring
effects like so see uh unspill doesn't do very much so unspill actually makes it worse so you
it sometimes depends on what you want to achieve yeah so if you do this you will you see um you get
a lot nicer color effects um if you then want to go and make it a bit better you can say add um
um color and maybe uh add other things to your liking say uh brightness contrast you could put
that here and you know uh play around with the contrast if you know if that's what you like to
do see um it's it's really up to do i'm just going to leave that here for for for you know
demo purposes and the next step that you that you may want to do um before uh you do any of the
color spilling stuff um because i want myself to be more moved to the right and we will do that in
in a moment and um i also want to have a another input let's say movie clip
and we say open i'm going into my um uh folder for disclosure labor laboratories um documents
disclosure laboratories uh media and it's called um i think it's called backdrop animation idle tv
let me check that real quick yes it is and you say open clip and there you can see it's um
um it's a little uh anime a little studio backdrop animation here which doesn't really
look good right now but okay um the next thing uh oops you saw for of course uh the next thing you
want to do is that um you know if i were you right now you can only use one layer which is really
bad so you say um where it was there is something which is called hang on a second uh output um
there is alpha over exactly yes you need this color alpha over okay uh and you will this allows
you to effectively uh combine two layers yeah so if you now take this one here um the the the last
output okay let's move this here uh let's move this here alpha over um if you take the last
output the last step of your process and connect it to here yes and then you take your secondary image
uh image here okay and another thing you want to enable in the alpha over nodes is convert
premium premium pre multiply i never knew what that word means convert premium pre multiply yes
you enable this because without this you will get some very interesting alpha mixing effects that
will mess up your your image so if you do this uh image here uh now you can see the backdrop uh
so you will probably have to switch these around and there we go so now you can see that there's
something quite wrong with the uh uh with this one here so if you you know reduce this a little bit
like so uh it comes back into the picture but sometimes you know you have to experiment around
on on these values to to make this uh to make this better and uh sometimes it also helps to you
know uh play around with these algorithm slots because it may you know increase your um
your results sometimes it's also good to you know switch around between these
and see what's gonna happen you know um it's sometimes it's like that you really have to
um play around with the values uh in such a way that uh you remove all the green parts
it's it's not always easy as you can see here but you you know you get the idea if you play around
with these settings let's try to see if we can make this perfect here oh uh no not this one
not this one oh that looks good that's that's lander man you know whoa i'm ghost um
you know it's uh sometimes it helps to to do this channel keying thing and to you know
play around with these settings uh and sometimes it doesn't it's it's like very fine tuning effect
at some point um that you want to play around with sometimes you have to select g and limiting
channel is red uh for some weird hilarious reason but this seems to be a good um good setting here
almost almost it's it's not always perfect you know let's let's see if we can let's see if we can
make this a bit better here but it doesn't really look like um maybe it's also maybe we should
it's a shadow see there's a shadow here um let's see if we if we remove the channel key and um
say add mat and say um chroma key because sometimes this is also a good way to achieve that
yes so we want to have a key color let's say uh like a green but a darker green um
it would be good to be able to select a color now because let's just connect these two and then
um it already takes into into account these kind of things so if you want to let's say
let's say let's remove the color spill and the brightness and contrast for now and just
connect that here so we can get the original color here um key color uh this is good because now you
can play around with these settings and see uh this in a live environment you know like so um
fall off uh fall off should be like this acceptance maybe a bit lower
uh not what no cut off no so this is not okay so chroma key is not necessarily something you
want in this scenario mat let's say um i never tried i never i never tried king because it's
very complicated this kind of node so uh i i didn't really use that um color uh no mat um
color key always seems to be the best choice uh in in these scenarios um so i i think for the
moment crop um left maybe a little bit less you know like this and up uh no down yeah let's remove
that a little bit like the like this okay um then key color let's say something along the lines of
this and um let's try to fiddle around with the settings here
like so oh yeah this is good this is good this is this is this is necessarily bad but also it
isn't good uh but you can try to you know not remove everything but just apart because that
may help you if you want let's say this this looks really messy so let's say add um mat
channel key put that here um let's see and this is going to be a lot better it seems
but also it will make me a lot more transparent which is not necessarily something we want so
but if you have a more perfect green screen um red green blue no if you have a better green
screen than i do then this may actually be of use to you sometimes it also helps not to remove
not to have high to 1.0 see you get a lot of better results with this a lot better results
let's just say this this is perfect i'd say um i i i think i'm pretty happy with that yeah and if you
say add um um where's mat color spill you put that here uh and you reduce the color here then you
can see it's it's looking quite nice at this point and you don't have as a rough of edges as before
um so these are tricks you can utilize in in in the uh compositor yeah uh another thing that you
may want to do uh right away before you do any color processing is add distort translate
uh like this and then you can move myself like so but it will also see it it it it has an effect
on on the cropping so but this is this is not a problem because you can you know adjust these
to your liking see like this and then also what i want is to have a oops uh hang on right should be
like this see and then you can go and uh maybe because my legs are not entirely visible which
is really bad so input uh image and this is where it gets complicated because now you want you have
three layers yeah and the image is going to be open uh disclosure laboratories and it's going
to be the desk that i use that's ray traced it's just a png file and uh you want to um
you want you want to have another alpha over node which is add uh color alpha over and you want to
uh at this point you will you really want to think what you're going to do
yeah so uh the desk should be coming next um you know over the existing
layering yeah so you want to have alpha over in this here okay and you want to have the image
going in here and that's it see this is pretty much a good replication of what i'm doing
normally with my video editing and in the timeline here you can obviously
already preview your material which looks really really nice if i may say so myself
and then obviously if you're happy with everything that you're doing then you can go back into your
or maybe you can also go and um pull up a properties panel like so here yeah uh say
properties which is here where you select your rendering preferences say 1280
uh by 720 you increase that to 100 percent frame rate is 25 uh untilizing you don't need
you select all the bullshit that you would normally select uh say h264 or xvid you select
your output folder which is desktop and uh this one here um except and uh that's pretty much it and
if you if your display say keep your eye and if you're happy with with that um with all your work
then you can you can say uh no render oh yes no render output node in scene obviously um very
important because i almost forgot that um right now we only have a viewer here so with this uh
lets us view the output uh in our compositor yes but you also want to add output
composites yeah which is exactly the same as the viewer except that this one is going to be your
render destination this is going to be um what you're going actually going to render into a file
yeah this is exactly the same so if i switch somewhere like here um you see it will change the
image uh like it does in the viewer and if you say animation it will start to render your images
as you can see in the timeline and um that's that's pretty much it yes uh there's not much else
to to say about this this is another thing that you can do with video editing um and
and blender okay so we now have a little bit of material here which is about two seconds it's
now being uh it's now it's now rendering and um i hope this was helping you a little bit with
um another component in blender that you can use for to your liking um and obviously then
with the finished file you can go and do your normal uh video editing yeah which is i'm not
going to go into that but you know if you want to know how that works with video editing you can
view the other video that i did which amazingly has over 20 000 views and i don't know how that
happened uh but i'm very grateful for your support and and interest into the subject and this little
stupid video i did um yeah so uh that's it for the moment i hope you like this and i'll see you again
next time all right thanks see ya