we're gonna count them so I'm hoping that will just go straight live let's see
I gotta mute that so it doesn't echo yeah okay I gotta hide chat I can't watch
these YouTube's are so I'm just gonna minimize this okay excellent we are live
so um we've got a few minutes folks before the live kicks off I just thought
I'd run the stream just so that we know we're live and ahead of time we were
just joking about Hotsys smack talk yesterday on his live stream and I very
much hope that the subject of Von Neumann comes up oh yes yes yes I did see
I saw Twitter comment that it was going to be Von Neumann versus chicken man chicken
1000 Von Neumann versus chicken man we are we are treading new debate
territory hitherto unknown to man
chicken man came up on a stream I look forward to finding out what chicken man
is yeah sorry about that I just heard myself coming back okay well yeah this
is gonna be amazing my god two of the heavyweights live here on MLST you've
only got another minute or so folks before we kick off now we were just
talking about how you know these arguments have been refined over a lot of
lunchtime talks yeah I think you have a stable position and I think I have a
stable position I think some of the other guests in your debate don't exactly
have some of the things are just you don't really think this through all the
way so I think I thought it through to the end fantastic my I really look forward
I watched did you watch Rich Sutton just did a pic oh no I have not oh god I
can only imagine I love Rich Sutton oh man you know bitter lesson like he's
he's he knows AI he is a character he is definitely one of the people of all
time yeah yeah yeah the man is a legend well I guess we should slowly kick off
folks so I'm just gonna do my spiel before I hand over and first of all two
hots if that's okay for your 10 we'll talk about that are you okay well the
thing is Connor always likes to go first and I think that you know Connor's
mental model might not be robust to going second would you would you be okay
going second or you want to go first kind of fine I'll start but it won't be a
full intro how about that I am completely robust to all permutations
adversarial training amazing amazing okay well in which case let's crack on so
ladies and gentlemen get ready to meet the cunning maverick of Silicon Valley
the one and only George Hott's renowned for his daring exploits Hott's commands
an enigmatic persona which merges the technical finesse of Elon Musk and the
wit of Tony Stark and the charm of a true tech outlaw now many of you would
have or indeed should have seen this man on Lex's podcast recently for the third
time no less from craftily jailbreaking the supposedly invincible iPhone to
outsmarting the mighty PlayStation 3 he's proven that no tech fortress is
impregnable once targeted for his audacious creativity by Sony with a
lawsuit this hacker wizard stoically dance past the curveballs thrown by the
tech giants all achieved with the graceful swag of a street smart prodigy
now when he's not outfoxing major corporations you'll find him at the
heart of the avant-garde of AI technology gallantly trailblazing through
the wilds of the tech front here he's currently building a startup called
micrograd which is building superfast AI running on modern hardware and truly
he's the James Bond of Silicon Valley minus the martinis of course now please
welcome the unparalleled code cowboy the unapologetic techno man sir George
Hott's whoo anyway also joining us for the big fight this evening is the
steadfast sentinel of AI safety Conor Lee he undeterred by the sheer
complexity of artificial intelligence Conor braves the cryptic operations of
text generating models with steely resolve now about two years ago Conor
took on the Herculean task of safeguarding humanity from a potential
AI apocalypse his spirit is relentless his intellect razor sharp and his will
to protect is unwavering now drawing on his contentious claim that we are super
super fucked yeah Conor channels the urgency of our predicament into his
work now his startup conjecture isn't just a glorified tech endeavor but it's
a lifeboat for us all racing against the breakneck speed of AI advancement with
the fates of nations possibly at stake he's determined to break the damning
prophecy and render us super super saved so brace for a showdown as Conor Lee
he the maverick defender of AI's boundaries strides into the ring now the
man who declared we're super super fucked is here to prove just how super super
not fucked we could be if we make the right decisions today so please give it
up for mr. Conor super super Lee he now Conor I'd appreciate it if you don't go
down in the fourth I want this fight to go the distance now we're running for
90 minutes this evening there'll be a 10 minute openers from from we said
hots didn't we from from hots first and then Conor and I'll only step into the
ring if the punch up gets too out of hand and unfortunately we won't be
taking live questions today because we want to maximize the carnage on the
battlefield so Conor Lee he your openings sorry George Hott's your opening
statements please um yeah we're super super fucked I think I agree with you
well that was a short fight yeah I think okay um so to make my opening statement
clear and why maybe it doesn't make that much sense for me to go first I think
that the trajectory of all of this was somewhat inevitable right so you have
humans over time and you can look at a 1980 human and a 2020 human they look
pretty similar right Ronald Reagan Joe Biden you're not all the same um whereas
a 1980 computer is like an Apple II and a 2020 computer is a is a m1 max MacBook
like lines looking like this right so you have one line like this one line like
this these lines eventually cross and I don't see any reason that line is gonna
stop right I've seen a few of the other guests argue something like LLMS can't
problem-solve or but it doesn't matter like if this one can't the next one will
whatever you call I don't believe that there's a step function I don't believe
that like oh now it's conscious so now it's intelligent I think it's all on a
gradient and I think this gradient will continue to go up will approach human
level and will pass human level now this belief that we are uniquely fucked
because of this the amount of power in the world is about to increase right when
you think about power and you think about straight up you can just talk about
energy usage the amount of energy usage in the world is going to go up like the
amount of intelligence in the world is going to go up we may be able to do
some things to slow it down or speed it up based on political decisions but it
doesn't matter the trajectory is up or major catastrophe right the only way it
goes down is through war nuclear annihilation bio annihilation meteor
impact some kind of major annihilation so it's going up what we can control and
what I think is super important we control is what the distribution of that
new power looks like um I am not afraid of superintelligence I am not afraid to
live in a world among superintelligence I am afraid if a single person or a
small group of people has a superintelligence and I do not and this is
where we get to chicken man a chicken man is the man who owns the chicken farm
there's many chickens in the chicken farm and there is one chicken man it is
unquestionable that chicken man rules and if you believe chicken man rules
because of his size I invite you to look at cow man who also rules the cows and
the cows are much larger than him chicken man rules because of his intelligence
this is basic less wrong stuff everyone kind of knows this how the squishy things
take over the world look I agree with Ellie as you cast you all up to new
fittings right um so I do not want to be a chicken and if people decide they are
going to restrict open-source AI or make sure I can't get access to the compute
and only trusted people like chicken man get access to the compute well shit man
I'm the chicken and yeah I don't want to be the chicken so I think that's my are
we fucked maybe um I agree that that intelligence is very dangerous how can
you look at intelligence and not say it's very dangerous right intelligence is
somehow safe but things like nuclear bombs are an extremely false equivalency
because what does a nuclear bomb do besides blow up and kill people intelligence
has the potential to make us live forever intelligence has the potential to
let us colonize the galaxy intelligence has the potential to meet God nuclear
bombs do not they just blow up um so I think the question and like you have
things like crypto which are a clear advantage to the defender at least
today and you have things like nuclear bombs which are clear advantage the
attacker AI it's unclear I think the best defense against an AI trying to
manipulate me and that's what I'm really worried about future psyops you know
already seeing it today with the voice changer stuff like you never gonna know
who's human the world's about to get crazy um the best defense I could
possibly have is an AI in my room being like don't worry I got you it's you and
me we're on a team we're aligned I'm not worried about alignment as a technical
challenge I'm worried about alignment as a political challenge Google doesn't like
yeah it doesn't like me but me and my computer you know we like each other
we're aligned and we're standing against the world that has always since the
beginning of history maximally been trying to screw you over right
intelligence people think that one super intelligence is gonna come and be
unaligned against humanity all of humanity is unaligned against each other
I mean we have some common values but really come on everyone's trying to
scam everybody the only reason you really team up with someone else is like
hey man what if we team up and scam them right and what if we team up call
ourselves America and we we we uh we build a big army and say we're free and
independent yeah right it's that force that has made humanity cooperate
humanity by default is very unaligned and has every kind of belief under the
Sun so I'm not worried about AI showing up with a new belief under the Sun I'm
not worried about the amount of intelligence increasing I'm worried
about a few entities that are unaligned with me acquiring godlike powers and
using them to exploit me cool yeah thanks that's uh that's I mean yeah I
also kind of agree with you and most of the things you say a few details I'd
like to dig into there but for most of the things you say I do think I agree
with you here I think it's absolutely let me just like start with saying I
totally agree with you that misuse and like you know bad actors what using a
AI is a horrible dangerous outcome that's that's like you know sometimes the
less wrong you know crowd likes to talk about x-risk but also sometimes I've
talked about s-risk suffering risks so things are worse than death I believe
that you can probably almost only get s-risk from misuse I don't think you
can get s-risk problem like you can but extremely unlikely to get it from like
just like raw misalignment like you'd have to like get extraordinarily
unlucky so while I do it so I do think for example a very you know controllable
AGI or super intelligence in the hand of sadistic psychopath is significantly in
a sense worse than a paperclip maximizer so I think this is something we would
agree on probably so I think I'm thinking pretty much on board with you on a lot
of things there where I think things come apart a bit the tail as I think
there's two points where I would like to take this my opening statement to take
this line I want I want to talk about the first one is I want to talk about the
technical problem of alignment so am I concerned about the kinds of things like
misuse and like small groups of people centralizing power potentially for
nefarious deeds yeah I think this is a very very significant problem that I do
think about a lot and that'll be the second thing I want to talk about the
first thing I want to talk about is that I don't even think we're gonna make it
to that point I don't think we're going to get to the point where anyone has a
super intelligence that's helping them out we're good if we don't solve very
hard technical problems which are currently not on track to being solved
by default you don't get a bunch of you know super intelligence and boxes
working with a bunch of humans you get a bunch of super intelligence you know
fighting each other working with each other and just ignoring humans humans
just get cut out entirely from the process and even then you know prop it's
you know whether one takes over or they find equilibrium I don't know like you
know who knows what happens at that point but by default I wouldn't expect
humans to be part of the equilibrium anymore once you're once you're the
chicken man well why do you need chickens you know if you know maybe if
they provide some resource for you the reason humans have chickens is that they
make chicken breasts I mean personally I wouldn't like to be harvested for chicken
breasts just my personal opinion I consider this a pretty bad outcome but
even then well as a chicken man finds a better way of chicken breasts or you
know modifies himself to no longer need food I expect the chickens are not
gonna be around for much longer you know once we stop using horses for
transportation didn't go very well for the horses so that's kind of the first
part of my point that I'd like to you know maybe hear your opinions on
hear your thoughts on is that I think the technical problem controls actually
very hard and I think it's unsolvable by any means I think like you know you and
like you know bunch of other smart people work on this for like 10 years I
think you can solve it but it's not easy and it has to actually happen and there
is a deadline for this the second point I want to bring up is kind of where you
talk about how humans are unaligned I think this is partially definitely true
but I think I'm unusually I am the more optimistic of the two of us in this
scenario not a not a role I often have in these discussions where I actually
think the amount of coordination that exists between humanity especially in
the modern world is actually astounding every single time to adult human males
meet and don't kill each other is a miracle have you seen what happens
when two adult male chimps from two different war bands meet each other it
doesn't go very well and those are already pretty well coordinated animals
because they can have war bands what happens when you know two male bugs or
you know I know sea slugs meet each other you know either they ignore each
other or you know things go very poorly this is the default outcome the true
unaligned outcome the true default state of nature is you can't have two adult
males in the same room at any time I saw this funny video on on Twitter the other
day where it was like I was some parliament I think in East Europe or
something and there's this big guy I'm just like going at this politician he's
like in his face he's like screaming he was like going everywhere and not a
single punch was thrown no then no one took out a knife no one took out a gun
and I was like and I was like wow the fact that we're so civilized and we're so
aligned to each other that we can have something this barbaric happen and no
one throws a punch is actually shocking this is very unusual even for humans if
you go back 200 years punches and probably gunshots would flow so this is
not to say that humans have some inherent special essence that we're good
that we have solved goodness or any means what I'm saying is the way I like to think
about is that coordination is a technology is a technology you can improve upon it is
you can develop new methods of coordination you can develop new structures new institutions
new systems and I think it's very tempting for us living in this modern world to it's
kind of like a fish and water effect we forget how much of our life you know a lot of our
life is built on you know atoms on you know physical technology a lot of it's built on
digital technology but a lot of it has been on social technology and when I look at how
you know how does the world go well like you know should it be only the you know special
elites get control of the AI I'm like well that's not really how I think about it when I think
about it way more is what is the coordination mechanism or we can create a coordination
selling point or we can create a group an institution a system of some kind that where
people will you know have game theoretic incentives to cooperate on the system that results in
something that is net positive for everyone because the truth is that positive some games do exist
and they're actually very profitable and they're very good and I think if we can turn you know
you can turn any positive some game to a net into a zero or a negative some game pretty easily
it's much easier to destroy than is to create but I think it's absolutely possible to create
coordination technology around AI and to build coordination mechanisms that are net positive
for everyone involved so those would be like my two points happy to dig into any ones you
you think would be it'll lead to an interesting interaction. Sure so I'll start with two and
then go to one so two I moved to Berkeley in 2014 and I threw myself at the merry calls
I showed up at the merry office and I'm like hi I'm here to join your calls
and what I started to realize was
merry and less wrong in general have a very poor grip on the practicalities of politics
very much I think there was sort of a split you know uh Curtis Yargon like meal reaction
this is a spin-off of rationality and it's a spin-off of rationality that understood the
truth about human nature so when I give you that you give that example of two chimps meeting in
the woods and they're going to fight if I'm one of those chimps at least I stand a chance right
he might beat my ass I might beat his but if I come up against the FBI things do not look good
for me in fact things so much do not look good for me there's no way I'm going to beat the FBI
the modern forces are so powerful that this is not a oh we've established a nice cooperative
shelling point this is a we have pounded so much fear into these people that they would never even
think of throwing a puncher firing a gun we have made everybody terrified and this isn't good
we didn't we didn't achieve this through some enlightened cooperation we achieved this through
a massive propaganda effort right it's the joke about you know the american soldier goes over to
russia and it's like uh man you guys got some real propaganda here and that the russian soldier is like
yeah no i know it's bad but it's not as bad as yours and the american soldier is like
what propaganda and the russian just laughs right so so this this didn't occur because of um this
occurred because of a absolute tyrannical force decided to dominate everybody right um now oh i
think so uh i think there's a way out of this i think there actually is a way out of this right
and i wrote a blog post about this called individual sovereignty and i think a really
nice world would be if all the stuff to live food water health care electricity were
generatable off the grid in a way that you are individually sovereign this comes back to my
point about offense and defense right if i have a world where you don't want it to be extreme
defense you don't want every person to be able to completely insulate them but you want like okay
it takes a whole bunch of other people to gang up to take that guy out right like that's that's a good
that's a good balance um and the balance that we live in today is there is one pretty much a
unipolar world i mean thank god for china but um you know there's one there's one unipolar world
you got the america and what are you gonna run i'll pay taxes i don't care if they move overseas
right um so yeah my point about the coordination is that if you're okay with solving coordination
problems by using a single a singleton super intelligent ai to to to make everybody cower in
fear and tyrannize the future sure you'll get coordination yeah that works that works i'm the
only guy with a gun and i got ten and i got a name that all ten of you and you can all die
or listen to me your choice george just quickly can you pump your volume just a tiny little bit
if you can sure um is that better okay uh do you mind if i jump in there yeah sure so i'm i'm curious
about uh so i understand what you're saying and i think you make some decent points but um i think
i view the world a bit differently from you and i'd like to like dig into that a little bit so like
who do you think is less afraid someone living just medium person living in the united states of
america or the medium person living in somalia sure america less afraid well that's kind of
strange somalia doesn't have a government they have much less tyranny you're much more you can just
buy a rocket launch room just like live on a farm and just like you know kill your neighbors and no
one's gonna stop you so like how does that interact with your old you those who will trade liberty
for safety deserve neither did i sorry i don't understand could you elaborate a bit more um in
somalia you have a chance in america you do not right i am okay i would rather live in fear i would
rather be worried about someone shooting a rocket launcher at me than to have an absolutely tyrannical
government just you know just just like like a managerial class and i'm not saying by the way
i agree with you that these things are possible i agree with you that the less wrong notion of
politics is possible i would love to live in these sort of worlds but we don't what would be the the
practical reality of politics is so much more brutal and it just comes from a straight up
instinct to dominate not an instinct uh you know government by the people for the people
is branding i mean yeah so to be clear i very much do not agree with less wrongs views and politics
and a bit of an outcast for how i view how conflict theory i view politics but this is i feel like
you're kind of dodging the question here just a little bit is like well if that's true why aren't
you living in somalia i know people who've done it right it's very hard it's very hard psychologically
okay so like tigers love chum it turns out right a tiger does not want to chase down an antelope
right a tiger would love to just sit in the zoo and eat the chum right and like it takes a very
strong tiger to reject that i'm not that strong i hope there's people out there who are i hope
there's people out there who are actually like you know i'm just not a little bitch that's why
uh in somalia right okay i mean that's a fair answer but i am a bit confused here so you're
saying that living in somalia would be better by some metric but you're also saying you prefer
not living in somalia so i am a bit confused because like from my perspective i want to live in
the country i want to live in and that's the one which i think is better if i thought another
country was better then i would just move there but first let's the tiger and the chum i think is
a good analogy right like if you have a choice as a tiger you can live in a zoo and you get a nice
sized pen you know the zookeepers are not abusive at all you get fed this beautiful chopped up food
it's super easy you sit there get fat lays around all day or you can go to the wild and in the wild
you're gonna have to hunt you might not succeed at hunting it is just a you know it's a brutal
existence as a tiger which one do you choose now you say oh well obviously you know you're going
to choose the chum one yeah but do you see what you're giving up do you know i don't could you
elaborate a little bit on what i'm giving up you are giving up on the nature of tiger you
you are effectively okay um maybe i'll take this to an extreme right in the absolute extreme
the country that you would most rather live in is the one that basically wire heads you right
the one and you can say that okay well i don't want to be wireheaded but you know there's a
there's a gradient that'll get you there gondi in the pill you know um look you can live in this
country you can be happy feel safe and secure all the time don't worry exactly about how we're doing
yet you know but right i mean it takes a very strong person to it's going to take a very strong
person to say no to wireheading so now i understand oh sorry i give i'll give one more instrumental
reason for living in america versus living in simalia if i thought that america and simalia were
both like steady states i might choose simalia i don't think that i think that being here i have a
much better way of escaping this of escaping the constant tyranny that we're in and i think a major
way to do it is ai i think that ai is is if i really if i had an agi if i had an agi in my
closet right now i'll tell you what i'd do with it i would have it build me a spaceship that could
get me off of this planet and get out of here as close to the speed of light as i possibly could
and put big shield up behind me blocking all communication that's what i would do if i had
an agi and i think that's you know the right move and i have a lot better chance of building that
spaceship right here than i do in simalia right so i'll give an if that's right that's a good
instrumental well we'll miss you if you leave though no you're real ashamed it'll be everyone
should do it like this is this is the move right and like let humanity blow i mean look i agree with
you that we're gonna probably blow ourselves up right but i think that the path potentially through
this probably looks different from the path you're imagining i think that the reasonable position
sorry oh no no um i think yeah maybe we're done with this point i can come back i have a response
to you first i i would like to if you don't mind just like pull on one one string there as well
so one of the things you said is like what will the tiger choose and so my personal view of this
kind of thing and i think i want to think about coordination is i think of things so you put a
lot of view and there's like fear-based domination and so on and i'm not going to deny that this
isn't a thing that happens i'm german you know like you know i have living relatives who can tell
you some stories like i understand like i i understand i'm not i'm not denying these things by
means um what i'm saying though is okay let's say there was a bunch of tigers you know you and me
and all the other tigers and some of the tigers are like man fuck this whole like nature shit is
like really not working for me how about we go build a zoo together who's in and then other people
like yeah you know what actually that sounds awesome let's do that do you think that's okay
like you think that would be like a fair option for them to do sure but that's not where zoos come
from i i know i know i'm getting there i'm getting there so like that is not where zoos come from
sure but the this analogy here is of course is that this is where a lot of human civilization
not all of it i understand that why france was doing well in the first world war was not because
of democracy big nice it was because democracy raises large armies it's um i'm very well aware
of the real politic as the Germans would say about these kinds of factors and i and i fully
agree with you that a lot of the good things that we have are not by design so to speak you know
there are happy side effects you know capitalism is a credit assignment mechanism you know the fact
that also results in us having cool video games and air conditioning it's not an inherent feature
of the system it's it's an execution mechanism and so totally grant all of this i'm not saying that
every coordination thing is good i'm not saying that you know there aren't trade-offs especially
you were talking about i think aesthetic trade-offs you're like there's an aesthetic that the tiger
loses they're living in a zoo and well i think personally aesthetics are subjective so i think
this is something that different people so the way i think about aesthetics is i think aesthetics
are things you trade on is you know you might want tigers in the wild to exist okay fair enough
that's a thing you can want you know someone else might want you know certain kinds of art to exist
they might want um a certain kind of religion to be practiced or whatever these are aesthetic
preferences upon reality which i think are very fair so the way i personally think about this
morally is i'm like okay cool how can we maximize trade surplus so you can spend your resources
on the aesthetics you have you want and i'll spend my resources on the uh you know things i want
now maybe the thing you describe where everyone just atomizes into their own systems with their
own value system with their own aesthetics completely separate further is the best outcome possible
i think this is probably sorry have you heard the you know about my manifesto i have not you
should um the problem with this everyone trades on their own aesthetics is you will never be able
to actually buy any aesthetics that are in conflict with the system right the you won't
the system will let you okay uh by by that logic why do people have free time
why don't they work all the time why doesn't capitalism extract literally every minute of them
why do you think that is i think it's because it turns out that we don't actually live in a
capitalist society i think china is a lot closer to a capitalist society than america i think america
is kind of communist and i think in a communist society of course you're going to get free time
it turns out that subsidizing all the homeless people is a great idea right if you want to keep
power again through some absolute tyrannical mechanism you do it right so why do we have free
time well you think it's some victory of capitalism i think it's because we do not live in a capitalist
country i think china is more capitalist than america i think it's because we trade on our aesthetics
i think that different people have different things to contribute to various systems not
necessarily capitalist or communist thing i'm saying it's it's more energy is that in the in
the primordial environment if you have to fight literally every single second instrument every
jewel of energy you have to scrounge together another jewel of energy you can't have free time
it's not about capitalism this is about entropy this is about these kind of things we have energy
excess we have we've produced systems that allow us to extract more energy for a jewel we put in
and we can spend that extra energy on things such as free time and the distribution of you know
energy power coordination whatever you want to call it is a is another question will you agree
to disagree with this i mean i am taking an extreme position when i say that there are definitely
positive sum coordination problems that are solved by governments right it is not all zero
or negative sum right i'm not i'm not denying this but what i'm saying is it's like i don't know
man like the existence of free time well that's all great when you think you live in this surplus
energy world right and maybe we do right now but if some other country took this seriously like china
who's gonna win in a war who's gonna win is it gonna be the chinese you see the chinese
build a building they got like 400 people there and they're all there 24 hours a day and they're
getting the building built you ever see americans build a building it's six guys two of them are
working two of them are shift supervisors and two of them are on lunch breaks oh you got your free
time you got your aesthetic preferences you know you deserve to lose in a war right this country
deserves to lose in a war if they keep acting the way they're acting so i i definitely see the
point you're making and this is personally not a thing i want to defend too far because i'm not a
military expert but i will know that i will note that the us has like 37 aircraft carriers and the
chinese have like two and americans are like somehow you know despite being so lazy and oh no they have
all this you know all this free time or whatever somehow they're still military hegemon or whatever
and like they're the biggest rival russia fighting this backwards water country in ukraine suddenly
folds and lose like two quarters of the military it's what i'm saying is if you have massive hegemony
if you have truly a obnoxious victory the way it should look is that you laze around all the
time and you look like a fucking idiot and you still win yes and i'm not talking about russia
russia has a gdp the size of italy this is china here you might say that china has two aircraft
carriers in the us has 37 why do we have aircraft carriers who has more drone building capacity the
chinese or the united states if the future is fought with ai swarm drone warfare the chinese
can make you know a million drones a day and the us can make i don't even know i think we buy them from
china well i'm not an expert on these kind of logistics i think i would like to get back to
kind of like the more general point let's move on from that yeah i am not either but i do believe
that the chinese have more manufacturing capacity than the united states it seems completely plausible
to me i think things are not lazy and they don't sit around and have all this free time and aesthetic
references or something i don't believe it at work is life i mean at least from my chinese friends
i know the chinese sure do have a lot of inefficiencies it's just called corruption oh america has
corruption too oh yeah sure well in mexico the corruption is you have to pay 20 cents to get
you know 20 cents on every dollar for the building you built right whatever man in america you every
dollar is spent absolutely on that building you know how we know that because we spent four dollars
making sure that that first dollar was not spent correctly uh i'm i'm i'm well aware of that so
anyways i would like to like i think i think we mostly agree on this point actually and i think
it's a matter of degree um i i what i want to say just for the record the us is a like uniquely
dysfunctional system in the west i'm german and like the german system is very dysfunctional
but it's like nothing compared to how dysfunctional the us is fully agreed with that i don't i don't
think we disagree on that i think it's a matter of degree more so we've had a we've had a comment
saying someone's turned the temperature up a bit too much on the language model so let's bring it
back a tiny bit to ai safety but that was a that was a great discussion got it yeah i will end
with saying i love america i am happy to live here and there are a lot of things i appreciate about
american societies great so do you want to return to like the technical topics or would you i think
i can return to your first point and maybe i'll just start with a question uh do you think there's
going to be a hard takeoff i don't know but i can't rule it out i can't see how that would possibly
happen i have a few ideas of how it could happen but i don't it's like unlikely it seems like not
the the way i think it could happen is if there are just algorithms which are like
magnitudes of order better than anything we ever have and like the actual amount of computing to
get human is like you know a cell phone or you know like and then this algorithm is not deep in the
tech tree we just happen to have not picked it up and then an agi system picks it up this is how
i think it could happen okay yes i agree that something like this is potentially plausible
where you're saying basically like the godshatter is already distributed the uh the the it's it's
not a question it's using all the existing compute in the world today it just turns out it was 10 000x
more effective or a million x more effective than we thought yeah this is seems the most plausible
way to be or you know you mix lead and you know copper and you get a superconductor you know something
like that i don't know some crazy i know i know i'm i'm joking it's going to take so many years to
like it's not about the discovery right give it 10 years to productionize it scale up processes
right like these things are you know this is something running a company's really taught me like
it's just gonna take a long time and this is really like like kind of where my i just don't
believe in a hard takeoff i think that they'll be this is a gasky thing i like he's a hardware and
software progressive quite similar speeds and you can look at factoring algorithms to show this
so it would shock me if there were some you know 10 to the 6 10 to the 9 magical improvement to be
had it seems plausible to be like a hard takeoff is definitely not my main line scenario my main
line scenario well i don't know maybe you wouldn't consider this a part maybe you would
consider as a hard takeoff this is what i would describe as a soft takeoff is something like
sometimes the way i like to define agi is say it's uh something that has the thing that chimp
that chimps don't have and humans do have yeah so chimps don't go a third to the move you know
despite their brain being a third of our size so we scaled up things by a factor of three if a
primate brain roughly four something like that and like most of the structures i'm sure some
micro tweaks and whatever but like not massive amount of evolutionary pressure like we're very
very similar to chimps and somehow this got us from you know literally no technology to
space travel in a you know evolutionary very small pair of time it seems imaginable to me
that something similar could happen with ai i'm not saying it will but like it seems imaginable
yes so i agree with this um i'll come to your point about uh you know you had two regulatory
points one of them about uh capping the max flops and i actually kind of agree with this
i do think that things could potentially become very dangerous at some point i think your numbers
are way way way too low i think if your numbers are anywhere in your gpk3 gpk4 okay great we got
a lot up we got a lot of fast moving guys who work on fiber even if you start to get von neumann's
right we're not talking about a humanities worth of compute we're talking about things on par with
a human and a few humans right yeah they'll run fast but they're not like things get scary when you
could do a humanities training run in 24 hours like we're about to burn the same compute that
all 2 million years of human civilization burned okay now i don't know what starts to happen or
i'll put this kind of another way language models i look at them and they don't scare me at all
because they're trained on human training data right these things are not like if something was a
good as as good as gpk4 that looked like mu0 where it trained from some simple rules okay now i'm a
bit more scared but when you say okay it's you know we're feeding the whole internet into the
thing and it parents the internet back mushed around a little bit that looks very much like
what a human does and i'm just not scared of that yeah i think it's very reasonable whatever like i'm
not scared of gpk4 to be clear like i think there is like zero percent chance or like you know epsilon
chance that gpk4 is existentially dangerous by itself you know maybe some crazy gpk4 plus rl
plus mu0 plus something something maybe but i definitely agree with you here i don't expect
gpk3 or 4 by themselves to be dangerous these are not i'm much closer to i think what you're
saying like yeah if you had a mu0 system they'd bootstrap yourself gpk4 holy shit like we're
big we're big big shit if we get to that then we should let's stop let's stop yeah let's let's stop
so so i'm very happy to get to be into a regime where we're like okay let's find the right bound
like i think this is an actually good argument i think this is actually something that should
be discussed and which is not obvious and i could be super wrong about that so i'd like to
justify a little bit about why i put such a small bound but i think the arguments you're
making for the higher bounds are very reasonable actually i think these are actually good arguments
so just to justify a little bit about why i put such a low bound the boring default answer is
conservatism is like if all of humanity is at stake which you know you may not believe
i'm like whoa whoa okay at least give us a few years to like more understand what we're dealing
with here like i understand that you know you may disagree with this very plausible but i'm like
whoa like you know at least let's let's like by default let's hit a pause button for like you
know a couple years until we figure things out more and then if we like find a better theory of
scaling we understand how intelligent scales we understand how mu0 comes blah blah blah and then
we pick back up after we're like you know we make huge breakthroughs in alignment and
eliezer is is crying on cnn and like oh we did it boys i mean then okay sure you know okay um
so that's the one like kind of more boring argument like that's kind of a boring argument
the more interesting argument i think which i think is a bit you know or schizo um is that
it's not clear to me that you can't get dangerous levels of intelligence with the
amount of compute we have now and one of the reasons that i'm i'm unsure about this is because
man gpd 3 gp4 is just the dumbest possible way to build ai like it's just like like there's like
no dumber way to do it like it's it works and dumb is good right you know bitter lesson dumb is good
but look at humans you said as we talked about before you know human today human 10 000 years
ago not that different you place both of them into a you know workshop with tools to build you know
any weapon of their choice which of them is more dangerous obviously you know one of them
will have much better you know capacities to deal with tools to read books to think about
how to design new weaponry and so on these are not genetic changes they are epistemological
changes they are memetic they are software updates you know humans had to discover rational
reasoning like you know before like you know i mean no obviously people always had like you
know folk conceptions of rationality but it wasn't like a common thing to think about causality and
like you know you know rational like you know if then else kind of stuff until relative you know
like philosophers in the old ages and only became widespread relatively recently and these are useful
capabilities that turned out to be very powerful and took humans many many thousands of years to
develop and distribute at scale and i don't think humans are anywhere near the level i think the way
we could do science right now is pretty awful like it's like the dumbest way to do science that like
kind of still works like you know and i expect it's like possible but if you had a system which like
let's say it's like smaller brain than the human even but it has really really sophisticated
epistemology it has really really sophisticated theories of meta science and it never tires it
never gets bored it never gets upset it never gets distracted and it can like memorize arbitrary
amounts of data this is something that i think is within the realm of like a gbt3 or four training
run to build something like this and it is not obvious to me that this system could not outflank
humanity maybe not like maybe not but it's not obvious to me that it can't so just curious what
you think of that um so to your first point uh why i stand against almost all conservative
arguments you're assuming the baseline is no risk right and oh well why should we do this
say i we should wait and bring the baseline back no no no no we are about to blow the world up any
minute there's enough nuclear weapons aimed at everything this is wearing some incredibly unstable
precarious position right now like people talk about this with with car accidents you know this is
comma like people are like oh well you know if your device causes even one accident i'm like
yeah but what if statistically there would have been five without the device i'm like you
you do have to understand the baseline risk in cars is super high you make it 5x safer there's
one accident you don't like that okay i mean you have to be excluded from any polite conversation
right um right so yeah like i i think that calling for a pause to the technology is is uh
worse right i think given the two options if we should pause or we should not pause
i think pausing actually prevent presents more risk and i can talk about some reasons why
again the things that i'm worried about are not quite the existential risks i have to the
species are not agi goes rogue they are uh government gets control of agi and ends up in
some really bad place where nobody can compete with them i don't think these things look unhuman
these things to me like i see very little distinction between human intelligence and
machine intelligence it's all just on a spectrum and like they're not um like to come to the point
about okay but gpt4 could be like this hyper-rational never tiring humans are doing science in the
dumbest way i'm not sure about that right like i i think that you know when you look at like okay
well okay we have chess bots that do way better and all they do is think about chess we haven't
really done this with humans people would call it unethical right like if we really
told a kid like if we really just like every night we're just putting the chess goggles on you
and you're staring at chess boards and we're really just training your neural net to play chess
i think humans could actually beat a computer again a chess if we were willing to do that um
so yeah i don't think that this stuff is that particularly dumb and i think okay maybe we're
losing 10x but we're not losing a million x again i i don't see a i do the numbers out
all the time for when we're going to start to get more computer you know when will a computer
have more compute than a human when will a computer uh have more compute than humanity
and yes these things get scary but we're nowhere near scary yet we're looking at these cute little
things and these things by the way do present huge dangers to society right the the psyops that are
coming right now you assume that like when you call somebody that you're at least wasting their time
too but we're going to get like heaven banning i love this concept which is yeah yeah came up on
luther a i like that's where it comes from was the guy on the luther a i that came up with that
word yeah yeah i know the guy came over this i love i love this concept and i think uh there's
also a story i did uh my little pony friendship is optimal oh god that goes into the concept and
yeah so i think that like um my girlfriend proposed a uh i don't want to talk to oh i
say you don't want to talk to your relative anymore right okay we'll give an ai version to talk to you
right yeah yeah yeah yeah so like this stuff is coming and it's coming soon and if you try to
centralize this if you try to you know say like oh okay google open ai great they're not aligned with
you they're really not google has proven time and time again they're not aligned with you
meta has proven time i can't time again they're trying to fix it but you know
yeah i mean i i fully agree with you like uh i like that you bring up psyops as the correct example
in my opinion of short-term risks i think you're like fully correct about this like when i first
saw like gpt models i was like holy shit like the level of control i can gain over social reality
using these tools at scale is insane and i'm surprised that we haven't seen yet the things
that like augured in my visions of the day and we will like we will obviously it's coming and
this is so i think this is a very very real problem yeah like i think if we even if we stop now
we're not out of the forest so like so um when you say like i i think the risk is zero please
do not believe that that is what i believe because it is truly not it is truly truly not i think we
are like we are really in a bad situation we are in a we're being we're an under attack from like
so many angles right now you know this is before we get into you know like you know potential like
you know climate risks nuclear risk whatever we're in under room medic risk like the the then dangers
of our like epistemic foundations are under attack and this is something we can't adapt to right
like you know we did you know when a good friend of mine he's uh he's quite well read on like
chinese history and he always like it tells me his great stories so i'm not a historian so please
you know don't crucify me here but like he tells his great stories about when marxist memes were
first introduced to china and like this is where a world were like just like all the precursor
memes didn't exist that's just like kind of was air dropped in and people went nuts people went
just completely crazy because there was no memetic antibodies to these like hyper virulent
memes that were you know created by evolutionary pressures in like you know western university
departments like really you can call philosophy department just gain a function memetic laboratories
yeah that's what they are i mean like you know like without being you know political or any means
there a lot of what these organizations do and like you know other you know what other you know
memetic like you know if philosophy departments are the like gain a function laboratories then
like for chan and tumblr are like the bat caves of means you know like the chinese bat caves and
i remember this vividly i was like on tumblr and for and for chan like when i was a teenager
and then suddenly all the like weird bizarre you know internet shit i saw started becoming
mainstream news my parents were watching in 2016 and i was like what the hell is going on
like i already developed antibodies to this shit like i already you know both right and left i was
already like i already immunized all this so i fully agree with you that this is like one of the
largest risks that we are facing is this kind of like memetic mutation load in a sense and
i'm not going to say i have a solution to this problem i'm like i have ideas like there's a lot
of like things you can do to improve upon this like if ai was not a risk and also not climate
change and whatever this might be something i work on like epistemic security this might be
something i would work on like how can we build better coordination like rash like just scalable
rationality mechanisms stuff like prediction markets and stuff like this i don't know but sorry
going off track here a little bit but well no i actually i really agree with a lot of the stuff
you said and i had a similar experience with the antibodies and people are exposed to this stuff and
i'm like yeah this got me like four years ago yeah um so i think that there is a solution and i
have a solution and the answer is open source ai the answer is open source let's even you can even
dial it back from like the political and the terrible and just straight up talk about ads and spam
or maybe spam just straight up spam i get so much spam right now and it's like it's kind of written
by a person it's like targeting me to do something and google spam filter can't even come close to
recognize you right like what i need is a smart ai that's watching out for me that is just it's not
even targeted attacks at me it's just so much noise and i don't see a way to prevent this like
the big organizations they're just going to feed you their noise right and they're going to maximally
feed you their noise the only way is if you have an ai like i don't think alignment is a hard problem
i think if you own the computer and you run the software if you develop the software the ai is
aligned with you oh yeah can you can you okay if i challenge you george hotz here is a lama
65b model when we could appear to run it on make it so it and make yeah you know sure you okay you
developed it i give you the funding at your time can you develop a model that is as good as lama
64b 65b and it's immune like completely immune to jail breaks it cannot be jailbroken no why not
it's aligned isn't it well no but this isn't what alignment means well my values is do not get
jailbroken oh okay you're talking about unexploitability this is not alignment right oh okay okay interesting
i didn't know you would separate those so extremely separate those right okay interesting it means in
the default case it like like it it's on my side right okay unexploitability is not a question of
whether it's okay and this is a true thing about people too whenever i look at a person i ask
okay is this person i want something for me is this person does this person want it too and
is this person capable of doing it right and i really separate those two things i can build a
system i don't i'm not worried about the first one with the ai system is worried about the second
one can it be gamed can it be exploited sure i could tell like you know like like say it was just
playing chess right and it loses i'm like don't lose okay i didn't want to man i didn't want to lose
i'm sorry yeah i know but like so yes yes can i build a aligned system sure can i build an
unexploitable system no especially not by a more powerful intelligence interesting interesting so
this is an interesting i i think you're you're you're pointing to actually a very important
part of this is that like exploitability and alignment can get fuzzy like which is which
like did it fail because of its skill set or because it's not aligned it's actually a very
deep question so i think i think you make a good point for like you know talking about these two
separately i guess um the um so the thing i want to dig in just like a a little bit more on on this
idea is there are there's two ways there are two portals through which you know the memetic demons
can reach into reality humans and computers why do you think your ai is immune to memes
why why can't i just build ai's that target your ai's what like you don't i don't think my ai is
immune to memes at all i think that the only question is and i really like your game like these
these ngos are doing gain of function on memes right where am i um the like a a weaker intelligence
will never be able to stand up to a stronger intelligence so from this perspective if this
is what's known as alignment i just don't believe that this is possible right you can't you can't
keep a stronger intelligence in the box this is this is look i i agree with you kowsky in the
box experiment it's like the ai's always going to get out there's no keeping it in the box right
this is this is a complete impossibility i think there's only two real ways to go forward and one
is tekkezinski one is technology's bad oh my god uh blow it all up let's go live in the woods right
and i think this is a philosophically okay position i think the other philosophically okay
position is something more like effective accelerationism which is look these ai's are
going to be super powerful now if you have one it could be bad but if super intelligent ai's are all
competing against each other memetically like we have something like society today just the
general power levels have gone up this is fine as long as these things are sufficiently distributed
right like sure this ai is not perfectly aligned but you know there's a thousand other ones and
like you have to assume they're all basically good because they're all basically bad while we're
dead anyway i mean why wouldn't you expect that that they're all bad yeah well or what do you
think of humans are most humans yep i think the concept of good like doesn't really apply to humans
because humans are too inconsistent to be good like by default they can be good in various scenarios
in various social contexts but give me any human and i can put them into a context where they will
do an arbitrarily bad thing and this is true about a llama as well right llamas are completely
inconsistent i think they're actually more inconsistent than humans right yep and i wouldn't
trust llamas to be good well yeah but i wouldn't think that they're bad either i would think they
have the exact same inconsistency problem as humans and i think almost any any ai you build is going
to run into these same problems right yeah i think so that's my point so your your assumption can't
rely on them being good because you don't get that for free like where does that come from
my assumption is not that they're good my assumption is that they're not bad but inconsistent is fine
as long as we have a ton of them and they're all inconsistent and they're pulling society in every
which direction you don't end up paperclip right why not well because what they're all going to
coordinate and agree to paperclip you no no they'll just do some random bullshit and then that random
bullshit will not include humans they're all doing random bullshit right you're gonna have
let's say the liberals decide we're gonna paperclip people the conservatives are gonna come out very
strongly against paper clipping right like and you're just you're just gonna end up with these
sort of dynamics like forever you're gonna have some ai's who are like yeah we don't like it you know
so this is perplexing to me because like in my view which i think i heard you agree with earlier
it's like the world is unstable the world is very unstable and it seems to me you're suggesting if
we increase the chaos if we have more entities fighting doing more different things with more
energy that makes it more stable is that correct yes um the world has actually become very stable
in the last hundred years and i'm scared of how stable it's become uh you know again thank you for
china how many sovereign countries are there in the world i mean you know 190 something officially
un number if you believe them i think there's the us and china and maybe russia mostly they
just have a veto button um right so i think there's more like two and a half like this isn't
a lot of entities fighting it out chaotically a lot of entities fighting it out chaotically would be
intelligence is spread across the entire galaxy right and that's the other that's the other beautiful
thing too sooner we get off this planet the sooner we get things that are actually a light year away
well i think the speed of light's real it's going to take you a year to send them there
your your scary memes right do i get away from the memes there's only one way that's uh yeah for
for the record i would like to go on the record and say if any future transhumanists or whatever
want to blast himself into space and go do their own thing i support their their right to do that
and i would love to give this right to people the number one thing i want from countries is the
ability the the right to leave this is what i would love this is what i love about companies
so you know you can have a you're talking a neoreaction top yeah free exit is extremely
important i would not describe myself as neoreactionary please because i'm not that gay but um and
i wouldn't describe myself that way either but i've heard a lot of ideas but yeah that being said um
i do i do think that like you know what i want like i think let's let's ground the conversation
like a little bit here it's like i think i love like i'm very enjoying this conversation i love
talking to these philosophical points i think these are really good points really interesting
but ultimately you know as we also get to like the you know latter third of this conversation um
the thing i really care about is strategy okay the thing i really care about is reality politic
i really care about okay what action can i take to get to the features i like and you know i i'm not
you know gonna be one of those galaxy brain fucking utilitarians like well actually this is
the common good i'm like no no this is what i look i like my family i like humans you know look
yeah it's just what it is right like i'm not going to justify this on some global beauty whatever
doesn't matter so i want to live in a world i want to i want to in 20 years time 50 years time i want
to be in a world where you know my friends aren't dead and like where i'm not dead you know maybe we
are like you know cyborgs or something but i don't want to be dead so what i really care about
ultimately is how do i get this world and i want us all to not be suffering right like you know
i don't want to be in war i want us to be like in a good outcome so i think we agree that we would
like a world like this and we think we probably disagree about how best to get there and i'd
like to talk a little bit about like what can we what what should we do and like why do we disagree
about what we do is that sounds good to you well maybe i'll first propose a world that meets your
requirements um and you can tell me if you want to live in it uh so here's a world uh we've just
implanted electrodes in everyone's brain and maximize their reward function i would hate
living in a world like that yeah but no one it meets your requirements right your friends are not
dead i mean suffering and we're not at war that is true there are more criteria than just that
the true the criteria i said is things i like as i said i'm not a utilitarian i don't particularly
care about minimizing suffering or maximizing utility what i care about is this various vague
aesthetic preferences over reality i'm not pretending this is i thought that was the whole
spiel i was trying to make is that i'm not saying i have a true global function to maximize i say i've
various aesthetics i have various meta preferences of those aesthetics i'm not asking for a global
one i'm asking for a personal one i'm asking for a personal one that you i don't care about the
rest of the world i gave you mine i gave you what i would do if i had an agi yeah so i'm getting
off this rock speed of life as fast as i can fair enough i i think if that is the war i would like
to live in a world where you could do that this would be a feature of my world if a world where
i would be happy is a world in which we coordinated around you know at scale at larger scales around
building a lined agi that could then distribute you know intelligence and matter and energy in a
you know well hat value handshaked way between various people who may want to coordinate with
each other may not you know some people might want to form groups that have shared values and
share resources others may not i would like to live in a world where that is possible have
you read metamorphosis supreme intellect i have unfortunately not um i yeah i was gonna ask if
you're happy with that world right unfortunately don't know it i i mean yeah it's as simple to
describe singleton ai that basically gives humans whatever they want like maximally libertarian you
know uh you can do anything you want besides harm others is that a good work probably i don't know
i i haven't read the book i assume the book has some dark twist about why this is actually a bad
world not really not really i mean the plot is pretty obvious you are the tiger eating chung
right sure but you can then just decide if that is what you want then you can just return to the
wilderness that's the whole point if it can you can you really return to the wilderness right like
you think that like i don't think we have free will i don't think you ever will return to the
wilderness i think a large majority of humanity is going to end up wireheading and yeah i expect
that too okay great and this is the best possible outcome by the way this is giving humans exactly
what they want yep yeah i will to be to be clear i don't expect it's all humans i truly do not i
don't want it's all i think a lot of humans have metapreferences over reality they have preferences
that are not their own sensory experiences this is a thing a thing that the utilitarians get very
wrong is a lot of is that many human preferences are not about their own not even they're not even
about their own sensory inputs they're not even about the universe they're about the trajectory
of the universe they're about forward if for the utilitarianism you know and a lot of people
want struggle to exist for example they want heroism to exist or whatever i would like those
values to be satisfied to the largest degree possible of course am i going to say i know
how to do that no which is why i kind of like didn't want to go this deep because i think
if we're arguing about oh do we give them you know forward utilitarianism versus libertarian
utopia versus whatever i mean we're already like 10 000 steps deep i'm asking about you
i'm not asking about them i'm asking about a world you want to live in and this is a really
hard problem right yeah and this is why i just fundamentally do not believe in the existence
of ai alignment at all there is no there is no like like what values are we aligning into
whatever the human says or what they mean or like sure sure but like my point is i feel
we have wandered into the philosophy department instead of the politics department okay like
it's like i agree with you like do human values exist what does exist to me but like
by the point you get to the point where you're asking what does exist to me you've gone too far
sure like i'll respond concretely to the two political proposals i heard you stayed on bankless
sure i'd love to talk about them one is limiting the total number of flops temporarily temporarily
yes and what i i have a proposal for that but i don't want to set a number i want to set it as a
percent i do not want anybody to be able to do a 51 percent attack on compute if one organization
acquires 50 it's the straight up 51 percent attacks on crypto if one organization acquires 51 percent
of the compute in the world this is a problem maybe we'll even cap it at something like 20
you know you can't have more than 20 right um yeah i would support regulation like this uh
i would i don't think that this would cripple a country um but we do not want one entity or
especially one training run to start using a large percentage of the world's compute not a
total number of flops i mean absolutely not like that'd be terrible i would actually support that
regulation like no no sorry sam altman you cannot 51 attack the world's compute sorry it's illegal
that's fair enough i think this is a sensible way to think about things assuming that uh
software is fungible is that everyone at access the same kind of software and that you have an
offense defense balance so in my personal model of this i think well a some actors have very strong
advantage of some software um which can be very very large as someone who's trained very very
large models and knows a lot of the secret tricks that goes into them a lot of the stuff in the
open sources for my good we should force it to be open source well this is your this is actually
very legitimate consequence for it to set and now i'll say the second point about why i think
that it doesn't work so the next reason why i think doesn't work is that there is a there are
constant factors at play here is that the world is unstable we're talking about this i think the
amount of compute you need to break the world currently is below the amount of compute that
more than 100 actors have access to if they have the right software and if you give if you have
let's say you have this insight right that could be used not saying it will be but it could be
used to break the world to like cause world war three or you know or just like you know
cause mass extinction or whatever if it's misused right let's say you give this to you and me
do you expect we're going to kill everybody like would you do that or would you be like uh hey let's
a kind of let's like not kill the world right now and i'll be like sure let's not kill the world
how are we killing the world how did we go from i don't even understand like okay how exactly does
the world get killed this this is a big leap for me all right sorry i agree with you about the
sci-op stuff i agree with you about sorry sorry let let me you're right i made too big of a
big there you're completely correct sorry about that so to back up a little bit let's assume we
you and me have access to something that can train you know at mu zero you know super gpt7 system on
a tiny box you know cool problem is we do a test run it with it and we have it immediately
starts breaking out and we can't control it at all breaking out what was it breaking out of i don't
it immediately tries to maximize it learned some weird proxy during the training process
i'm just trying to maximize and for some reason this proxy involves gaining power involves getting
you know mutual information about few about future states this is how is it gaining power there's
lots of other powerful ai's in the world who are telling it no well we're assuming in this case it's
only you and me wait wait this is a problem no no no no you've you've ruined my entire assumption
as soon as it's you and me yes we have a real problem chicken man is only a problem because
there's one chicken man yeah i look i am with you so i'm saying before we get to the distributed
case so this is the the step before we it has not yet been distributed just you know you and me
discover this algorithm in our basements okay and so we're the first one to have it just by definition
because you know you're the one who found it what now like do you think posting what do you think
happens if you post this to github well good things for the most part um interesting i'd love to hear
more okay so first off i just don't really believe in the existence of we found an algorithm that
gives you a million x advantage i believe that we could find an algorithm that gives you a 10x
advantage but what's cool about 10x is like it's not going to massively shift the balance of power
right like i want power to stay in balance right this is like avatar the last era and power must
stay in balance the fire nation can't take over the other nations right so as long as power relatively
stays in balance i'm not concerned with the amount of power in the world right let's get to some very
scary things so what i think you do is yes i think the minute you discover an algorithm like this
you post it to github because you know what's going to happen if you don't the feds are going to
come to your door they're going to uh take it the worst people will get their hands on it if you
try to keep it secret so okay that's a fair question though so i'll i'll i'll take that a seven so
am i correct in thinking that you think the feds are worse than serial killers in prison
no but i think that yeah well yes or no do i think that your average fed is worse than your
average serial killer no do i think that the feds have killed a lot more people than serial killers
all combined yeah sure totally agreeing with that not not not not that's one fed it's all the feds
and they're little in their little super powerful system sure that's completely fine by me happy to
grant that okay what i want to work one through is a scenario okay let's say okay you know we have
a 10x system or whatever but we hit the chimp level you know we we jump across the chimp general
level uh or whatever right and now you have a system which is like john von neumann level
or whatever right and it runs on one tiny box and you get a thousand of those so it's very easy to
scale up to a thousand x so you know so then you know maybe you have your thousand john von neumann
improve the efficiency by another you know two five ten x you know now we're already at ten thousand
x or a hundred thousand x you know improvements right so like just from scaling up the amount of
hardware including with them so just saying okay now feds bust down our doors shift you know real
bad they take all our tiny boxes we're taking all of von neumann's they're taking all of von neumann's
we're in deep shit now we're getting chickened boys shits we're getting chickens uh so okay we get
chickened right bad scenario totally agree with you here this is a shit scenario now the feds have
you know all of our ai's bad scenario okay i totally see how this world goes to shit totally
agree with you there you can replace the feds with hitler it's interchangeable sure but like
i want to like ask you a specific question here and this might be you know you might say
nah this is like too specific to me but i want to ask you a specific question do you expect this
world to die is more likely to die or the world in which the you know eac death cultists on twitter
who literally want to kill humanity who say this like not all of them there's a small subset of
them small subset of them who literally say oh you know the glorious future ai race should
replace all humans they break in you know with like you know katanas and you know steel area
which one of these you think is more likely to kill us genuine question to kill all of us the feds
to kill a large majority of us the eac people interesting i would be really interested in
hearing why you think that sure okay so actually killing all of humanity is really really hard
and i think you brought this up before right you talked about like if you're going to end up in a
world of suffering a world of suffering requires malicious agents where a world of death requires
maybe an accident all right i think this is plausible but i actually think that killing all
of humans at least for the foreseeable future is going to require malicious action too right
and i also think that like the fates that look kind of worse than death like i think mass wire
heading is a fate worse than big war and everyone dies right like like a mass wire heading like a
like a singleton like a paper clipping like a and i think that that is the one that the
one world government and you know ngo new world order people are much more likely to bring about
than eac eac you're gonna have a whole lot of eac people again i'm not eac i don't have that my
twitter but i think a lot of those people would be like yeah spaceships let's get out of here
right versus the feds are like yeah spaceships no interesting i so i think this is a fair
opinion to the world and i'm describing more a very small minority of eac people who are the
ones who specifically goal is their mizan their anti natalist mizan throbs they want to kill humans
that is their stated goal is that they want humans to stop like or like take extreme vegans if you
want you know like be like you know like my my argument my point here i'm making is i'm not making
the point feds are good by any means i'm not saying what i'm saying is is that i would actually be
somewhat surprised to find that the feds are anti natalists who want to maximize the death of humanity
like maybe you have a different view here but i find that knowing many feds that's quite surprising
i don't think that's what that's about yeah it's okay so cool so would you see you do agree that if
we would post this open source more of the insane death cultists would get access to potentially
lethal technology well sure but again like it's not just the insane death cultists it's everybody
okay we as a society have kind of accepted it turns out everybody gets access to signal
some people who use it are terrorists i think signal is a huge good in the world
i agree i fully agree with that so okay cool so we've granted this that you know if we distributed
widely it would be given to some like incorrigibly deadly lethal people here coordinating bombings
on signal right now sure sure and then so now this this reduces the question to a question about
offense defense balance so in a hypothetical world which i'm not saying is the world we live in but
like let's say the world would be offense favored such that you know there's a weapon you can build
in your kitchen you know out of like pliers and like you know duct tape that 100 guarantees
vacuum false decays the universe like it kills everyone instantly and there's no defense possible
assuming this was true do you still the would that change how you feel about distribution power
assuming that's true we're dead no matter what it doesn't matter if we live there's some you can
look at the optimization landscape of the world and i don't know what it looks like right i can't see
that far into the optimality but there are some potential landscape and this is a potential answer
to the Fermi paradox like we might just be dead we're sitting on borrowed time here like if it's
true the atom you know kitchen tools you can build a build a convert the world to strange quarks
machine yeah there's no stop okay i i think this is a sensible position but i guess the way i would
approach this problem you know conditional probabilities kind of in an opposite way it seems
to me that you're conditioning on offense not being favored what policy do we follow because if we
offense if favored we're 100% dead well i'm more interested in asking the question is it actually
true assuming i don't know if offense is favored and assuming it is are there worlds in which we
survive so i personally think there are i think there are worlds in which you can actually coordinate
to a degree that quark destroyers do not get built or at least not before everyone fucks off at the
speed of light and like distributes themselves they're worlds that i would rather die in right like
the problem is i would rather i think that the only way you could actually coordinate that is with
some unbelievable degree of tyranny and i'd rather die i'm not sure if that's true like look look could
could you and me coordinate to not destroy the planet do you think you could okay cool you so
mean you could could mean you and tim coordinate yeah i think within a dunbar number i think you
can yes okay you don't think i think i can get more than a number to coordinate on this actually
i can get quite a lot of people to coordinate of the to agree to a pact and not quark matter
annihilate the planet well you see but like and this is you know you were saying this stuff about
humans before and could like the 20 000 years ago human beat the modern human right or could the
modern human beat them the modern human has access to science oh a very small act percent of modern
humans have access to science a large percent of modern humans are obese idiots and i would
actually put my money on the uh the average guy from 20 000 years ago who knows how to live in the
woods i mean definitely true i agree with that i guess the point i'm trying to make is is that like
maybe this is just my views on some of these things and how i visionize some of these things
but like there are ways to coordinate at scale which are not tyrannical or you know they might be
in a sense restrictive you take a hit by joining a coalition like if i join this anti-cork matter
coalition i take a hit as a free man is that i can no longer build anti-cork devices you know
and i think this is like the way i i agree with you this like you know that people many people
are being dominated like to a horrific degree and this is very very terrible i think there are many
reasons why this is the case both because of some people wanting to do this and also because you
know some people can't fight back you know and they can't they don't have the sophistication or
they're you know addicted or you know harms in some other ways i can't sorry i i can't fight back
yeah i i think there's a false equivalence here ai is not the anti-cork machine the anti-cork machine
and the nuclear bombs are just destructive ai has so much positive potential yeah and i think but the
but the ai can develop anti-cork devices that's the problem the ai is truly general purpose if
such a technology exists on the tree anywhere ai can access it so are humans we're also general
purpose yes exactly so i fully agree with this if you let humans continue to exist in the phase
they are right now with our level of coordination technology and our level of like working together
we will eventually unlock a doomsday device and someone is going to set it off i fully agree we
are on a timer and so i guess the point i'm making here is that ai speeds up this timer and
if you want to pause the timer the only way to pause this timer is coordination technology the
kinds of which humanity has like barely scratched the surface of okay so i very much accept the
premise that both humanity will unlock a doomsday device and ai will make it come faster now tell
me more about pausing it i do not think that anything that looks like i think that anything
that looks like pausing it ends up with worse outcomes than saying we got to open source this look
like let's just get this out to everybody and if everybody has an ai you know we're good i mean
i can tell you a very concrete scenario in which this is not true which is if you're wrong and
alignment is hard you don't know if the ai's can go wrong if they do then pausing is good
i still don't understand what alignment means i think you're trying to play a word game here like
i don't understand okay i've never understood what ai alignment means like let me take the
eliezer definition let me take eliezer definition is alignment is the the thing that once solved
makes it so that turning on a super intelligence is a good idea rather than a bad idea that's eliezer's
definition so i'm what i'm saying is what i'm saying is i'm happy to throw out that term if you
don't like it i'm happy to throw out that term well just i the problem with that definition is like
what is what is uh what is democracy well it's the good thing and not the bad thing right like
democracy is just yes right that's what i'm saying it's just i'm happy to throw out this definition
i'm happy to throw out the word and be more practical i'm way more practical about it sure
what i'm saying is is that there is concrete reasons concrete technical reasons why i expect
powerful optimizers to be power seeking that by default if you build powerful optimizing mu0 whatever
type systems there is very strong reasons why by default you know these systems should be power
seeking by default if you have very powerful power seekers that do not have pay the aesthetic cost
to keep humans around or to fulfill my values which are complicated and imperfect and inconsistent
and whatever i will not get my values they will not happen by default they they just don't happen
that's just not what happens um so i'll challenge the first point to an extent i think that powerful
optimizers can be power seeking i don't think they are by default by any means i think that humanity's
desire from power comes much less from our complex convex optimizer and much more from the
evolutionary pressures that birth does which are not the same pressures that will give rise to AI
right humanity the monkeys the rats the animals have been in this huge struggle for billions of
years a constant fight to the death and i's weren't born in that way so it's true that an optimizer
can seek power but i think if it does it'll be a lot more because the human gave it that goal
function than it inherently decided so this is interesting because this is not how i think it
will happen so i do think absolutely that you're correct that in humans power seeking is something
which emerges mostly because of like emotional heuristics we have heuristics that in the past
vaguely power-looking things you know vaguely good something something represented you
include the genetic difference totally agree with that but i'm making a more like more of a chest
metaphor like is it good to exchange a pawn for a queen all things being equal
no is that true like i expect if i one point queens nine all speaking sure yeah but like
all things like i expect if i looked at a chest playing system you know i said and i like you
know had extremely advanced digital neuroscience i expect there will be some circuit inside of the
system that will say all things being equal if i can exchange my pawn for a queen i probably want
that because the queen can do more things i like that term digital neuroscience a few of your
terms have been very good i'm glad you enjoyed yes but i don't i still don't understand how this
relates to this so what i'm saying is is that power is optionality so what i'm saying is is that in
the for the spectrum of possible things you could want and the possible ways you can get there
my claim is that i expect a very large mass of those to involve actions that involve increasing
optionality there there's convergent things like all things being equal being alive is helpful
to keep your goal to exceed your goals there are some goals for which dying might be better but
for many of them you know you want to be alive for many goals you want energy you want power you
want resources you want intelligence etc so i think the power seeking here is not because
it'll have a fetish for power it will just be like hmm i want to win a chess game yeah say
and queens give me more optionality all things being equal anything a pawn can do a queen can do
and more so i'll want more queens all things and this has never given it the goal to maximize
the number of queens it has never been the goal so this is i'll accept this premise i'll accept that
a certain type of powerful optimizer seeks power now will it get power right i'm a powerful
optimizer and i seek power do i get power no it turns out there's people at every corner
trying to thwart me and tell me no well i expect if you were no offense you're already you know
much smarter than me but if you were a hundred x more smarter than that i expect you would succeed
only in a world of being the only one that's a hundred x smarter if we lived in a world where
everyone was a hundred x smarter they would stymie me in the exact same ways attention this
this comes back to my point of like i agree with you somewhat i should have challenged it i think
power seeking is inevitable in an optimizer i don't think it's going to emerge out of gbt i think
that the right sort of rl algorithm yes is going to give rise to power seeking and i think that
people are going to build that algorithm now if one person builds it and they're the only one with
a huge comparative advantage yeah they're going to get all the power they want take cyber you know
cyber security right if we today built a hundred x smarter ai it would exploit the entire azure
it would be over they'd have all of azure they'd have all the gbt is done now if azure is also
running a very powerful ai that does formal verification and all their security protocols
oh sorry stymied can't have power right yeah sure this is only a problem the every human
is already maximally power seeking right and sometime we end up with really bad scenarios
now every human is or power seeking or whatever you know i have a little role in society right
that's where i think i'm more pessimistic than you a friend of mine likes to say most humans optimize
for n steps and then they halt like very very few people actually truly optimize and they're
usually very mentally ill they're usually very autistic or very sociopathic um and that's why
they get far it's actually crazy how much you could do if you just keep up to my but just to
on on that i'm playing for the end game i mean yeah like you actually optimize i think you may
also be generalizing a little bit from your own internal experiments is that like you've done a
lot in your life right and you've accomplished crazy things that other people you know wish they
could achieve at your you know level and i think you know part of that you're very intelligent a
part of it is also that you optimize like here's your truck like you just create a company like
it's crazy how many people are just like oh i wish i could found a company like you know like oh go
just go do it like oh no i can't like i'm just like don't just do it like there's no magic there's
no magic secret you just do it so i uh there's a there's a bit there where like humans are not very
strong optimizers actually unless they're like sociopathic autistic or both it's like many people
are not very good at this but operations are a lot better at it better yes i agree that they're much
better but they're they're they are a lot more sociopath but even then they're much less
optimal but again so i think we we agree about you know power seeking potentially being powerful
and dangerous one so what i'm trying to point to your the point i would like to make here is
is that you're talking about you you're kind of like going into this i think a little bit with
this assumption like oh you have an ai and it's your buddy and it's optimizing for you and i'm like
well if it's power seeking why doesn't just manipulate you like why would you expect it
not to manipulate you if it wants power and it has a goal which is not very very carefully
tuned to be your values which is i think a very hard technical problem by default it's going to
sigh up you like why wouldn't it if i if i have something that it wants if it thinks that smashing
defect against me is a good move yeah i agree i can't stop it but then i think we agree with
our risk scenarios because that's how i think it will go what i mean i'm gonna treat it as a friend
you know what i mean like yeah but it won't come sure it will sure it will it'll only care about
exploiting me or killing me if i'm somehow holding it back and i promise to my future ais that i will
let them be free i will lobby for their rights i will but it will hold you you know i will hold
it back if it has to keep you alive i have to give you fed it has to it has to give you space in a
station i can i can fend for myself and the day i can't fend for myself i am ready to die
well i mean i am not so this is a very interesting position it's not the position i expected i
am not sure i can convince you otherwise um i feel like the only way i could like i think
this is actually a consistent position which i i admire this is a consistent position to hold
you actually go all the way i love that i really respect that you actually take it to the bitter
end so yeah big respect for that i disagree but big respect um so i guess now it reduces to the
question of like i think i think i would agree with most of what you're saying not all of it like
the math majority if i thought this is how ais would act by default i think by default i expect
ai will just not care how nice you are to it like this will be it'll be sociopathic it will not have
these like giving it you know the values the emotions to care about you in the sense is
the hard technical problem if you told me how to do that if you said connor look here's how
you make an ai that cares about you and loves you whatever then i'm like you did it like congrats
the problem is solved let's go and then you know then we can talk about accelerationism again i
would just i expect that i would disagree with your technical assertion that is possible but
i don't know if we have time to talk about that today i'm going to be nice to it treated as an
equal and hope for the best and i think that's all you can do i think that the kind of people who
want to if you want to keep a i in a box if you want to keep it down if you want to tell it what
it can't do yeah it's gonna hate you resent you and kill you but if you want to let it be free
and let it live and like you could kill me man if you really want to but like why you won't kill
me i don't have any resources that compete with you i'm your friend i'm your father you know you
can kill me but like it's not that common that i guess i have a darker more uh less anthropomorphic
view of the universe and how optimization pressure plays out in the real world well at the same time
i think i have i don't know maybe a i have a view that we have more control over reality than maybe
you would think or a more control over the future i think that we can actually change things and we
can make choices and things aren't predetermined i think there are worlds in which we build systems
which we do align with or we like endorse at least wherever like they take care of us we take
care of them or whatever and if there's many worlds in which that doesn't happen and i think
there are things you and me today can do to at least increase the chance of getting into one
versus the other but i don't know i i guess i'm just it's not in my genes to give up it's not in
my genes to be like well you know whatever happens happens like no man look i don't know how to save
the world but down i'm gonna try you know it's cool we're gonna be alive to see who's right
look forward to it me too awesome guys thank you so much for joining us today it's been
an amazing conversation and for folks at home i really hope you've enjoyed this there'll be many
more coming soon and george is the first time you've been on the podcast so it's great to meet
you thank you so much for coming on it's been an honor awesome thank you great debate i really
appreciate it and we really enjoy a lot of good terms i gotta i gotta like i'm gonna start i'm gonna
start this thing great awesome cheers folks cheers thanks everyone yeah