At the end of the day we're all in this situation together and it's no individual's fault that
we got here but it's everyone's responsibility regardless of what decades you were born in
to contribute towards responding so I would love to see older generations firstly stop
saying that it's down to our generation. Secondly stops having conversations about these topics
in closed rooms amongst academic elite and instead actively engaging in the intergenerational
transfer of knowledge and expertise and skills so that our generation and younger generations
can be equipped as best as possible to face the challenges ahead.
Today I am joined by three humans in their early 20s who have found themselves immersed in the work
and scholarship surrounding the great simplification. As you might be aware the viewers of this
channel and this content in the world tend to skew older but it's my belief that bringing
young voices to the table getting their perspectives on the future, platforming their ideas is
essential for us to navigate the coming decades especially those young humans who have a systems
understanding of the complexity and the risk that we face. As such this reality round table is
focused on the perspectives of youth today how they feel about the current state of the world,
what their hopes are for the future, what their ideas are for the future of society. Joining me
today are Priscilla Trinh who currently serves as the director of communications at the Post
Growth Institute and co-coordinator of the Minnesota Youth Institute. She's the creator of
the Post Growth Jobs Board editor at the Blue Marble Review and contributor to the Minnesota
Women's Press. Also joining me are is James Branigan a writer, philosopher and content creator
with a YouTube channel of his own. James is committed to the task of addressing some of the
many facets of the human predicament with education and food production systems being
two of the more appealing ones for him. He is Irish and currently lives in Spain.
Last but not least is Natasha Lindhart who is a recent graduate of the University of Amsterdam
with degrees in economics and business and electives in degrowth and critical theory.
Natasha has been a volunteer for our organization for the past year and she will be starting full
time as a research associate this summer. I hope this is the first of many round table
discussions with young humans. I hope you enjoy it. Welcome young humans to reality round table
number nine, Priscilla and Natasha James. Great for you to be here. Nice to be here too. Thanks for
having us. Thanks for having us. You're welcome. You're very welcome. I would like to have more
young humans on the show because you are going to be living a long lives during the great
simplification and what's ahead. So let me set the stage for this. I know all three of you.
Priscilla was one of my students. Priscilla I've known you since you were 17 or such and you were
my teaching assistant for my class reality 101. James and Natasha I've met online through the
podcast. So I have various hats especially for Priscilla. I was a professor and a mentor and a
coach and a friend. For the next hour plus though I am just a podcast host. I want you each to speak
your authentic selves about what you believe and feel and think about our world and our future.
And before we get to that if you could maybe each of you give a brief introduction of who you are
and what you're doing right now, you know, brief bio. Natasha we'll start with you.
Yeah so hi I'm Natasha. I'm 23 years old and I usually live in France but I'm currently in the
British Virgin Islands in the Caribbean because I'm doing a few months of backpacking and traveling
before starting work full-time with Nate and his organization. And yeah it feels very surreal to
be here because I've learned so much from this podcast. So thanks for having us. Priscilla.
Hey everyone Priscilla Trin here. She heard pronouns. I am also 23 and calling in from
Oceti Shacoenlands also known as Minnesota United States and I do communications work in the realm
of alternative economics and food systems and that's my job and energy right now. James.
Hey I'm James. I'm 25. I'm Irish but currently in Granada. I just love biology and environmental
science and as with Natasha I came across the great simplification and it's pretty surreal to be here.
But right now I'm studying regenerative agriculture and how to work the land that way.
Excellent. Well thank you all for being here. As is usually the format I'm going to have a framing
question and you'll each have five plus or minus minutes and then we'll we'll carry on and have a
conversation after that. So I would love each of you to respond and describe your your own personal
journey learning about the various economic and environmental risks and crises in the world around
us and and how has that shaped the way you see the future and your own place in it.
Yes in my journey understanding about the meta crisis specifically and how the different
environmental and economic risks and crises are related and interconnected. That journey was
life changing. It was definitely a roller coaster and I'd say it was made up of a few
different phases. The first being a sort of awareness phase which started about two years ago
and that was triggered by a few different events and circumstances that maybe we can dive into later.
But it was basically a six month period in which I exposed myself to a lot of information
about the various crises we face at the moment both environmentally and socially
and economically and I came to realize that they were all just symptoms of something more
complex going on beneath the surface and that was the time period where it came across your
work name and across this podcast and that awareness phase really taught me firstly that we have
this socioeconomic reality or this economic superorganism as you call it that's the outcome
of institutions and behavior being oriented around profit maximization and the expectation of
continued growth and the dynamics embedded in that socioeconomic system are driving the crisis
that we face and the fundamentally incompatible with the long-term well-being of the planet and
of people and that realization for me was really hard to take because I'm a part of that system
right um we all are to lesser and greater extents so I had to come to terms with the fact that I
was part of something that was driving the crises that I cared about and I cared about addressing
and then it didn't get much better because during the awareness phase I also learned about energy
and about ecology and I learned that this economic superorganism and this version of humanity was
coming to an end and was self-terminating because it could only function by continually
destroying the things which its survival depends upon so that meant I had to throw all the expectations
I had about my future out the window and at that stage I entered a phase of grief I suppose I was
grieving for the death of an illusion that I'd had about reality but also about my future
and that period really sucked I don't want to sugarcoat it I would cry a lot whenever I was by
myself I felt really really lonely and at that stage I felt very powerless it wasn't very fun
but I will say there was 100% necessary because only by going through that and feeling those
things could I then get to a phase of acceptance and that phase of acceptance really meant for me
internalizing and really fundamentally accepting inside myself that the future was going to look
very different from the present that the future was going to look different to what I'd been taught
to expect it to look like and that this version of humanity that I'd come to consider the norm
and which had characterized my life up until that point was what had passed its sell-by date
and was going to have to come to an end if we didn't want the biosphere to come to an end first
and for me realizing those things and internalizing them meant that now there was no way that I could
have a career or a role in the world which actively contributed towards maintaining and
perpetuating the status quo so I had to totally redefine the role I saw for myself in the future
and moving forward and now I very much see that role as twofold firstly we need to be
putting in place safety nets we need as many people as possible going into the future with our eyes
wide open and planning and putting in place structures so that the transition to a lower
energy throughput future can be accompanied by the least suffering possible because I think there
will be a lot of suffering especially in terms of material wealth and I really really really fear
that if we carry on going blindly into the future then when shit hits the fan we will turn to the
worst versions of what humanity is capable of and we know that humanity is capable of some really
horrific stuff but we're also capable of some great things so I think the second task is to
actively sow the seeds and create an alternative an alternative socioeconomic reality and I think
that's quite an exciting task that everyone can play a role in because we need as many ideas and
skills as possible to create a version of humanity that can not only outlive this one
but also which gives the biosphere and society the best possible chance of thriving
long into the future so I see those as the roles I can contribute to moving forward
in the short term I think we need to be raising awareness and bringing this stuff into the
mainstream so there's many people as possible can be contributing to those tasks so that's
why I want to be focusing on energy on in the near future but yeah that's sort of where I'm at now
and to be honest since reaching the acceptance phase I'm very very content and very happy
and the lifestyle changes I've implemented as a result of becoming aware of all this depressing
content have actually had a hugely positive impact on my well-being and happiness so yes the grief
sucks but it's necessary and it's worth it and yeah at the end of the day we still have life
and that's amazing so I try to enjoy it as much as possible I resonate with Natasha's grief period
but I would say the metaphor I would use to describe my journey is a happy tumble down a hill
I was rolling down into these rabbit holes picking up flowers and rocks along the way this clarity
that's exhilarating like when you're rolling down a hill right but you're also as you are tumbling along
gaining all this knowledge there's also this back of the mind fear like what if I bump into
something that I don't like and I don't want to hear and it's scary to really internalize that
information and then finally get to the bottom of the hill and I have to look up and I'm breathless
by all that clarity but also exhilarated because now I'm looking up at an amazing valley and knowing
that even though the road ahead is very long and uphill it's beautiful because I'm not doing it alone
I think when people have asked this question in the past how did you get to where you are it's always
been explaining it as oh you know we did the canon event of going to college and becoming radicalized
but it's a lot longer than that having reflected on my positionality how I've come here growing up
in an immigrant family but I'll get back to that later I really think your classmate was kind of
catalyst for connecting all the dots right you realize that it's not money that makes the world
go around its energy and then when you combine that with an understanding of evolutionary psychology
it really undoes the whole monolith of human nature and it really made me appreciate the
plasticity of culture and that gives me a lot of hope as I learned about the biophysical limits of
our world I was also moving more in the direction of activism intersectional feminism was a huge
part of the lens in which I view the world and it was a mixture of what I learned in class but
also the communities and spaces I entered during my organizing years understanding that energy
privilege is tied to class race gender sexuality all struggles are connected and moving into how I
understand about the existential risk and crises really from a place of collective liberation
we're all in this together it's liberation for all and that includes interspecies liberation as well
and again undoing the whole binary and notion of tree huggers versus realists because everyone is
affected albeit differently and everyone is subject to being oppressed or becoming the oppressor right
it's not just an identity politics thing it is decolonization for everyone and it looks very
different for the individual and as I got more into food sovereignty spaces I have a background in
food systems specifically organic agriculture horticulture did hydroponics research for two years
and through direct action through organizing I came to really day by day I'm more convinced
that local community power building is where I want to be it's about channeling the big picture
understanding into my corner of the world right we think about how it's not effective to be perfect
it's not about being the perfect activist the perfect vegetarian the perfect you know
bike your way to work type of person in the US I feel like given where I'm at and along in addition
to my full-time job it's also a job to be embodied and authentic and slow and intentional like Natasha
said to really cultivate yourself so that you can be self-sufficient but also community sufficient
whatever you learn can be re-gifted to everyone around you and I always come back to this quote
by Audre Lorde about how caring for myself is not self-indulgence it is self-preservation
and that is an act of political warfare and I think now that we see everyone converging on this
narrative of connecting these levels and systems at play on a planetary level on a political level
it's really cool to be here and alive during this time and I know the word unprecedented was
really ruined for me during the peak pandemic era but I think it's really cool that we're alive in
this really unique time in history and knowing that every generation before us has had to do with
their own risk for me I'm gonna die before you know probably peak climate crises hits but
knowing that I can do something about it is fine the allure of being the charismatic
speaker with a huge megaphone convincing people does not hold the same weight anymore
for me it's really about seeing how I fit into community and learning how to then cultivate
myself to be a part of that community that's how I see it. Thank you Priscilla and it feels odd for
me to call you Priscilla because for the last four or five years I've called you Trintab
which I will share publicly Jeff Bridges movie living in the future's past he
talked about TrimTabs which is the little thing behind the rudder of a ship that influences the
direction and your senior project was so colorful that I sent it to Jeff and he loved it and since
then I've been calling you Trintab so we'll put we'll put that I think there's a hyperlink to it
we'll put it in the show notes of this episode thank you James Branigan. Yeah so just a touch on
Priscilla's point that she made just there about the reduction of these complex issues into just
what I consider to be nonsensical binaries I think to overcome the allure of that because so many
people fall prey to that accepting one of the two ends of the extreme and to overcome that I think
you have to be fairly critical in your thinking and so one thing for me that I think about when I
think about this uh metacrisis or ecological issue that we're facing is that it is calling
forth the best of us as individuals because it has to we can't continue doing what we've been
doing for the past however many years you could say since the agricultural revolution to your point
about surplus accumulation and how that self-organizing around profits is one of the key
generator functions driving the problems that we face this has to change somehow not to say I know
how but somehow that has to change and just to be aware of that at first is of course the first step
but to your question about becoming aware of the ecological and economic issues I suppose
it's just a combination of like intellectual honesty and curiosity about the world because
when I was younger obviously I loved nature well that's not not so obvious but I really
loved nature I loved playing out in the fields in Ireland I loved being among the trees I love
being by the river I love making fires I loved making slingshots I loved these sort of outdoorsy
activities as a kid and so I sort of continued to follow that thread I was interested in biology
in school so then I followed that on and I wanted to remain as broad as possible in my study of the
world because this is so complex and I suppose as a young kid I was thinking all right how do I
learn as much about this as possible and not like specialize down into something too narrow
so then I went on to study general science in college or university and then environmental
science just because they're so broad but yeah so I suppose it was just a combination of that
intellectual honesty and curiosity and then also the internet the internet is a huge thing here and
the proper or appropriate use of the internet instead of falling into the trap of just being
caught by the algorithm with the short term stuff and losing your attention or losing time
by having your attention grabbed by that algorithm we can I think figure out a way to wield the internet
to our own advantage as individuals and then hopefully collectively and I think that that's
going to be one of the key tricks to figure out and I suppose I heard that actually that
sentiment echoed in an episode you did Nate with Thomas Bjorkman and he said about the Scandinavian
secret one of the keys there to modernize the Scandinavian countries rapidly was the implementation
of these schools where people could go and learn not only about the external world and what's
going on technologies so on so forth but also inner sort of spiritual or emotional development
and how the two relate to one another so yeah I guess that's it it's the internet curiosity
and just not falling prey to many of the pitfalls and traps that people who think about
the ecological crisis tend to fall prey to thank you thank you I have a bunch of questions for the
three of you are there any thoughts that bubbled up after the those the three of you spoke that
anyone would like to follow with yeah I just want to echo what James said about curiosity
because I think that's what's so special about this field is that there are so many different
ways of getting into it but for me yes I always cared about nature growing up and especially about
social issues but no more so than any other sort of environmentally and socially aware
average human so for me the reason that I'm here is purely driven by this curiosity and this
craving to understand reality and the world around me as much as possible and to get as
close as possible to the truth rather than holding to any set of beliefs and I think that's
yeah also what really motivates me in this field is that it is it's based on science and it's
based on fact and if you're curious enough to go there yeah this is where we get
in addition to that curiosity has also helped me navigate triggers you have to protect your
energy and pick your battles online especially when you're trying to be a communicator like myself
it's not about being this missionary convincing people they should care about ecological collapse
it's really leading with questions if someone disagrees with you and I try to remind myself
why do they think this way and then lead with questions rather than falling into
arguments or that divide that we see so present across geographies and cultures right now so I
love that curiosity framing. Talking about binaries let's go to the one about intergenerational
relationships with the climate and energy and economic situation I'm about 30 years older than
the three of you and so you know I've I've got 30 years of living in a world that was
largely functional and amazing under my belt now educating younger people on these things
how do the three of you and I'll let each of you speak feel about the seemingly perpetual
intergenerational conflict and blaming in our current culture and from your perspective is
it possible that we could move past such a phenomenon and and how. In one word heal everyone
needs to heal intergenerational trauma has been a big topic on my mind a good chunk of my life
and I think it's really important to unpack when talking about conflict and blaming I come from a
family of immigrants who fled the Vietnam war I'm Vietnamese my parents are immigrants and refugees
and outside of their story universally there's conflict militarism war PTSD everyone experiences
trauma to some different degree and that really affects parenting that manifests in money trauma
how we relate to the economy and that affects how we relate to each other as people and so
to address intergenerational conflict and blaming I think we have to then recognize
intergenerational value for those of us who are lucky to have elders in our lives you know I had
my grandma my maternal grandma and I think about how in the US there's such a sad attitude about
older folks there's ageism in the workplace there's ageism when it comes to political
social values but we have to know that all these movements that we're a part of now the environmental
movement the economic movement they were all founded by people who came before us right so
elders have wisdom and value and Nate I don't think you're an elder quite yet but in some ways
you are like our community elder right you have lots of ideas and experiences share right and
it comes back to the whole constraint of our economy because capitalism in the US means that
we're bound to our day jobs we have time constraints and then we don't have the time privilege then
invest in relationships and I think investing in relationships healing recognizing when our emotions
get the best of us is really key to then unlocking very generative conversations
and having intergenerational movements because it's not young people versus old people at all
you need all of us involved and one book I read recently there's an author a local author here
in the state she wrote a book called can we please give the police department to the grandmothers and
I think it was a beautiful exercise of imagination and how we can then rethink the way we relate to
one another rethink what it means to be safe because at the end of the day we're very emotional
beings and everyone is really just seeking to be heard seen understood and that affirmation is
important if we're really trying to build safety nets safety nets for whom who who is benefiting
from these safety nets we think it's good for us but maybe someone else doesn't feel safe
from that safety net so when we begin to heal and talk about mental health and really holistic
health I think it's I think it's going to be a big part in moving forward to to bridge these gaps
yeah I couldn't agree more healing is important and I remember in my mind I thought of it this
way I considered there are sort of four key elements in like the individual human's life
and I call them the most basic basics it's like food make sure you get your food right make sure
you get your exercise right make sure you get your sleep right but also make sure you get your
social relationships right so that speaks to Nate I think you formulated it by saying something
like become a fully stacked behaviorally stacked human being and you yeah you pointed the same
thing sleep food um exercise because how can we expect to face these issues and overcome them
if we're in any way ill in terms of our health that's not to say it's impossible but why not
optimize for these elements of human life because we can but to this point about blaming to be
honest I don't really I don't really see it I don't see my generation blaming the older generation
one thing that annoys me is this the fact that it's the older generations who have all the
resources and money but it's the younger generation who has all the energy but missing the resources
the money so there's a clear sort of niche there for collaboration and why it's not happening
I'm not sure so I wouldn't really blame I actually I don't even think blaming is productive what's
the use that it gets us nowhere so why not instead of blaming seek to collaborate and seek to
somehow create the mechanisms that can funnel resources from the older generations to the
younger generations in a collaborative sort of agreement between all of us
yeah I couldn't agree more with that I think it's about collaboration rather than blaming
I really see intergenerational blaming as a huge waste of time and waste of energy
because at the end of the day we're all in this situation together and it's no individual's fault
that we got here but it's everyone's responsibility regardless of what decades you were born in
to contribute towards responding and yeah as James said maybe we have our generation has
more energy or time hopefully over which to enact those responses but there is no way
that we can do it without the experience and also importantly the leverage of older generations
so I would love to see older generations firstly stop saying that it's down to our generation
secondly stops having conversations about these topics in closed rooms amongst academic elite
and instead actively engaging in the intergenerational transfer of knowledge and expertise and skills
so that our generation and younger generations can be equipped as best as possible to face the
challenges ahead and also I'd like to see the older generation engaging themselves in facing
those challenges and many are already but we need more people in all generations doing that
in terms of moving past the intergenerational blaming what I would love to see is if somehow
we could adopt a collective mentality which saw this current version of humanity not as a final
product that either has to be defended by older generations or destroyed by younger generations
but rather as a work in progress and within that having the collective maturity
to acknowledge and accept human fallibility like we're not perfect we're very very far from being
perfect we make mistakes and we get things wrong and that's okay but it means that we have to be
learning from those mistakes we have to constantly be trying to improve and I think if somehow we
could get to that collective mentality it would go a long way to moving past these cycles of
blame because it would mean that we could on the one hand be grateful for what older generations
and prior generations have given us and the experiences they've given us access to while
simultaneously acknowledging that mistakes were made and there was incomplete understanding of
reality which mean that from today we can't make those same mistakes and all of us in all generations
have to do things differently and do things better and we still won't be perfect but at least we can
work towards creating something that we can be proud to pass on to future generations.
I'm with Natasha that there needs to be shared values and I think it comes down to a rebranding
issue right I think many of us are disillusioned with ESGs and the global north framework of
environmentalism activism and systems change it's a very global north eurocentric approach and
recognizing there's a plurality of work that's been done over the years is important
in bridging the narrative right caring about our crisis is not a trend it's not something new
solidarity is not you know something that you do now because everyone else is doing it
and I think it's really flipping the narrative of how these conversations are not just happening
on podcasts for people who have time to listen to them they're happening on the ground and
it really does come back to what James was saying it's about this lack of resources
how many of us do not have time especially in the global north where we have day jobs that keep us
from advocating for things we want to do and then you got to wait until retirement when you have
time to advocate and lobby so it's this mismatch between what we're bound to financially in our
well-being because everyone needs a paycheck to survive in parts of the world now and then how
can we then cultivate time and space do that and that's going to take a bit of help outside of the
typical at least in the u.s. nuclear family or young adult living by themselves in an apartment
yeah so that is such a great point the fact that most of us don't even have the time to
engage these topics most of us are too concerned with yeah how to put food on the table
or pay the rent to have time to consider these topics and so this is actually one of the main
reasons why i'm doing what i'm doing trying to figure out i hesitate to call it like an
alternative lifestyle because it sort of has hippie connotations but i'm trying to figure out how
to live a life where i can fully study these topics and also pay the rent so i don't know
how to do that but also then attach it to your point about um like looking to the older generation
to try and teach us better about the world is i wonder of course the older generation
there's value in what they have to say but i wonder if that impulse to you know find an
authority an authoritative figure from which we can be confident um about their teachings and
how we learn about the world is itself sort of preventing us from understanding these problems
more deeply because i'm not sure the older generation even knows about how to deal with these
problems because they're so novel again it's not to say there's no use in deriving knowledge from
the older generations like nate for example the the great simplification thesis is hugely
explanatory and it helped me put the right words to the thoughts i had sort of intuited about the
world but then again i can't just rely on nate to do the work that we need to do we need to sort of
relocate the locus of authority in each of ourselves as individuals and then work in
collaboration with each other every everybody having done that towards solutions or long-term
management plans that can actually address the novelty of the problems we face is that
changing like persilla um from five or six years ago when i met you these things climate change was
known then but energy depletion and polarization and addiction and ai and some of the other biodiversity
ecological crises like PFAS and plastics and ocean issues and all these things they weren't really on
a lot of people's radar are these things commonly discussed uh with age in age groups of 23 to 27
like like you all are or is it is it um somewhat rare and in a second part of that question is
is it because of ignorance and in um energy blindness or systems uh lack of systems knowledge
or is it because i don't want to talk about this stuff i just want to enjoy my weekend and and the
beautiful day and and not have to think about these things do you have any thoughts on that
i think it really depends where you're coming from where you are located geographically and
culturally i feel like when you're talking to us it's a bit skewed right we already give a damn
but i think in the palestinian lands um that that would be a dumb question for me to ask but i think
it's becoming a bit more apparent i am very much sensing in the us and in the left bubbles
that there's this convergence on connecting the dots between economies environments and social
issues and while there is still a huge spectrum of nihilism to paralyzing fear most people
probably fall somewhere within the middle right some people are like i'm just here to make bank
do my job retire and die some people are it's out of my control it's too big i don't know what to do
let's retreat into the woods which is also just another form of dissociation and i think the
narrative happening elsewhere global south and other parts of the world maybe they don't use
the same words that we do but they are thinking about it because they have no choice but to think
about it in the us they're still quite a bit of a buffer for some folks and most folks in the us
still live paycheck to paycheck so we're very much closer to being houseless than billionaires
and i think that squeeze economically is really forcing people to think about more than just what's
hurting their wallet what's hurting their relationships and the future so i think it's
becoming more and more people's radars but they might be doing different things to address it or
using different words they might be advocating on parts of the system which i think is important
it's hard to tackle big picture always i think it's okay if it's a little fragmented and then
politically that the vocabulary is catching on but it's being so quickly co-opted that's why it's
so difficult to have these conversations because you don't know who you're in the room with anymore
someone could say the word sustainable or regenerative and you don't know if they if they mean
green growth are they a techno optimist or are they an anarchist like it doesn't it's not clear
anymore so that's kind of the the nice thing about it that with this digital amplification
you don't feel as alone sometimes because people are using a shared language but it's also very
quickly co-opted and misinterpreted so it's it's a mix of both i would say thank you james
you wanted to say something and then natasha yeah sure but uh just to the point about the shared
language thing it's just so important to understand each other and use the same language not yeah the
same language and understand that here's actually what i mean by this but that's so difficult to
flesh all of that out it takes a lot of time like the perfect example for me is the idea of
organic farming to the naive layperson he or she thinks that yeah this is like no chemical this is
pretty natural and all but it turns out that in the industry it just means something like less
chemicals than the industrial agricultural model but so yeah to the question i think for me anyway
i'd be a miss my friend group would be a misrepresentative sample because obviously i gravitate
towards these topics and so i tend to talk about them too and so i'm surrounded by people who also
tend to talk about them but not very many does that make it easier though i mean i would imagine you
you strongly value such a group oh my god i can't tell you how much i love the people the two people
i talk about this stuff with i love them so much two two of my best friends sean and my brother
patrick but uh doesn't make it easier what you mean doesn't make it easier having less people to
talk about it with or how do you mean easier well if it was just you in granada reading this stuff
online and thinking about it is not the healthiest trajectory so if you have other people to share
even if you don't come up with answers just a community i think is really important which
is why my class worked because we had 23 people in a circle talking about these things and sharing
because this is heavy stuff to take on just as an individual person yeah no doubt it makes it easier
and that's why i love that we can have this conversation now because i wonder if it will
work like an attractor and attract other people through the interwebs cyberspace to be able
to have these conversations by the time this episode airs our great simplification discord
channel will be live and people can find out where people are in the world and and have conversations
either online or in person because i think that i think that's important um natasha what what do you
think yeah i mean like james and priscilla i do also gravitate towards people who do care about
these issues and i have an amazing group of friends and we have really interesting discussions about
these things i would say that generally there is you know people in our generation do care i mean
it's our future um and there is general awareness about all these crises but there are so many barriers
to diving deeper into the sort of root causes and the why of these crises and looking sort of
beneath the surface i think those conversations aren't happening as much as they as i'd like to
see them happening and you know a big part of it is time as we've talked about people have jobs and
you've got to feed yourself and your family and and it takes a lot of time i mean for me to be honest
i spent more time educating myself about this stuff than i did focused on my university degree in
the last year of study like it's a lot of content to get through um and also there's one thing having
access to the content and the other thing is being in the mental space to be willing to take
on this content and to really engage with it um and i spent a long time in my youth being aware
of these crises but not really caring about going any deeper than that and it wasn't until i was in
a mental space where i'd removed loads of distractions from my life got off social media was creating a
lot of time and space for silence and reflection that then when the content hit me i was willing
to engage with it and get really deep into it so i think there are a lot of barriers that
we can work on removing thank you um excellent so uh i will remind you all that i am not a teacher
here i'm just a podcast host um but i just having this conversation this is like the
first conversation i've had with more than one young person at a time since i taught last in
2019 and and i do miss the the life and vitality and um curiosity and emergence uh that that comes
from from speaking with young people um let me let me ask you uh put you on the spot each of you
out of all the things that you're learning about some people call it the meta crisis i usually
call it the human predicament um you're you're well familiar with uh the different buckets of
risks and crises we face like what is one thing um in coming decades that that you're most concerned
about out of out of the whole universe uh if each of you could just speak to that for a minute or two
yeah so for me i just love my food and one of the main things that i'm concerned about is
no longer being able to produce food at the scale that we do currently because the fertilizer
pesticides and whatnot won't be available anymore or if not that the fuel for the tractors that we
rely on now to produce this food will just will be reallocated to other places or just
it just won't be there for certain local areas and that's one of the reasons why i'm doing what
i'm doing now is to relearn the old ways of agriculture not to return to an old way but
to understand how do we do this in the absence of oil and machinery i think that's a
i just find that intrinsically motivating to uh do that because for the you might call it selfish
reason that i love food not that i think the food is going to disappear in my lifetime but
just as a silly example that's why one of those with that is one of my main concerns
it's not silly and i don't consider it a selfish uh interest and i love food as much or more than
you do uh priscilla similar to james that's why i entered the field i am in right now i remember
when i told my parents hey i want to go to the college of food agricultural natural resource
sciences at the university of minnesota and they looked at me and they were like we crossed the
pacific to escape rice patties and now you want to go back into food what are we going to tell
your grandmother and i told them you tell her that as long as people eat i will have a job
and it's really the basic currency of our societies because yes we need energy to produce food but
without food there's no peace you can't change the world on an empty stomach and so i really
am concerned about our food and water quality and the the resource wars that are going to break out
um militarism is on my mind a lot everyone jokes about world war three we are living in the apocalypse
already and that's one thing that gives me hope when you understand the planetary boundaries
and the social boundaries of human patterns right all empires collapse eventually and so
thinking about it that way means that it really singles down a few of the things you should be
actually caring about and i think food and water is one of them and how are we going to set up
governance models and frameworks at different levels neighborhoods towns cities municipalities
what governance structures are in place so we can navigate these hard conversations about
how to allocate resources because we do have enough food in the world to feed everyone it's
a resource allocation problem and you know a corporate monopolization problem with big food
big ag controlling our food supply chains right now and i feel like it's doable and i don't think
the answer is a million organic farms that's not sustainable or viable it's not about everyone
becoming a farmer that's not how a society functions we need all roles all skills all
types of passions but yeah food and water is something i'm taking on myself to cultivate
skills related to that because i think it's fun like you all have said i love food and so that's
something i'm focused on both in my personal and professional life that's a difficult question
because there's so many uh risks and crises that we're facing to be honest i think i'm more
concerned with the way that we respond to those rather than the risks and crises happening because
i think they will happen and i would love to be proven wrong on that um i think that we will have
food shortages and there will be problems with water and there will be civil unrest um what i am
what scares me more is the way that we respond because if we look through history the times when
the economy's gone bad uh and we've had shortages in terms of resources that has had really really
bad knock-on effects in terms of the version of humanity that we become i mean we've become really
really awful people um so yeah what i really fear is that that this these conversations don't translate
to the things that Priscilla's talking about us actually thinking about different governance
structures and thinking about how we're going to distribute those scarce resources and how we
educate people so they have the skills to manage when we have to relocalize and can't depend on
these long supply chains um rather than just waiting for it to happen and then it turning really really
bad so i guess that's what what scares me yeah if i might just add also that that's also a motivation
for me it's not just my own love of food it's an understanding that when human populations feel the
squeeze and they see another human population over there who's doing well they this human population
who's doing poorly understands also that they can just steal what they have and that gets nasty and
that is sort of a a pattern that you can read from history that tends to happen
so following up on that each of you how do you maintain hope and cultivate resilience in the
face of what you know about the world and and i i would be so bold as to say you know more than
the average 23 and 27 year olds about all these risks and systems especially given reading the
news every day of what's going on in israel and palestine and ukraine and it's 45 degrees celsius
today in india which is like 110 or something like that you get daily reminders of this stuff so
how do you maintain hope and practice resilience and healthy habits knowing all this stuff
yeah i don't think we can just magically have hope from some external source i think we have to
actively create hope and yeah i see so much beauty in the world in nature and in people
and in relationships and communities but also in art and knowledge and culture and when i started
realizing the extent to which we're destroying that beauty in its various forms i would shift
between two mindsets on the one's hands i think well it's all fucked anyway so there's nothing
i can do excuse my french and on the other extreme i think that i have to personally save the world
and neither of those are helpful because neither of them lead to action so the mindset i've
currently developed instead through which i find a lot of resilience is firstly to feel
those things so you know i do get really really sad when i hear the news and when i see
nature suffering and people suffering i'm really feeling that but then also feeling
the joy but at the beauty that's still there so and the sort of mantra i use to motivate myself
is how can i use what i have to do what i can to protect some of the beauty and bring it forward
with me into the future and i think that if everyone does that even if it's in a really small way like
taking better care of your back garden or helping out an elderly neighbor if we all use what we have
to do what we can then we're creating hope i would say deep time deep time gives me a lot of hope
because when you zoom out and understand how we got here you realize how recent the current
order of things are dominant global north white capitalist whatever you want to call it society
is so new and back to what others have said before when you understand that it recalibrates your
expectations and that ironically gives me more positivity in the face of the poly crisis because
when you've understood that there are material financial and social limitations it recalibrates
expectations and yes that comes to the period of grief like was mentioned before it also alleviates a
lot of pressure yeah we might have some sort of mad max guns defending farm period but it's not
going to last forever right nothing lasts forever in nature and so nothing bad will last forever in
human human systems yes there will be ecological system impacts that will probably last forever
in the Anthropocene but i i think going back to that social governance like all the dire things
we're seeing in the news those will stretch out for a relatively long period of times compared
to our lifetimes but i know that the earth will rebound we will find a place in the future to
govern ourselves in a way that's equitable and sustainable and just understanding that no revolution
has been peaceful and i don't mean just like the revolution on the streets i mean the revolution
inside doing that healing work that shadow work that unlearning the breaking and creating cycles
and friend circles and families and communities it's not just about your neighborhood it's about
the regional impacts and what gives me hope is cultivating myself it's about gardening cooking
at home foraging being a better biker because right now we're living in an information economy
data knowledge cells in the future that knowledge and data has to be uploaded into our brains
it's a very fair and high 451 situation but knowing skills and having less dependency on
scary supply chains that are fragile gives me a lot of hope and empowerment make friends
with people who know skills that's how you build community it's not about having a million people
behind you and honestly you know there's that often cited often cited number of like you need
two percent of the mass to have a critical mass to do something i think it's even less than that now
considering we have relatively stable telecommunication systems right the message can be amplified so
much quicker now and so your community extends beyond geographic boundaries and then what also
gives me hope is communications really trying to use asset based communications because
that really flips the narrative it goes from deficit and scarcity which is what is used in
propaganda and news and media to really feel like we don't have what we need but we do know
what we need and we do have what we need and it's just again trying to create narratives even the most
well-intentioned circles like charities will say we need more volunteers because there's too many
poor hungry homeless folks and i yes but we could also state it in a different way that really
empowers people by saying we have the resources to house feed and uplift everyone join us in this
movement it really you know lands emotionally different in people and it might instigate action
no matter how big or small i think it's this weird world is small and big at the same time and people
do not fit into it but just pick something if it's safe enough to try go for it i think this
at least in the us the academic system that many of us go through really kind of pushes for perfection
and if it's not going to work don't do it at all but i'm trying to push back against that myself
and not be stuck in this cerebral space of just like despair so that's my take on it one of the
things that really makes me study this and makes me like want to be a human at this time is the
fact that there's no guarantee that we make it through this bottleneck or these bottlenecks
of the coming decades which is like there's a sense of danger in that and it's kind of scary
but at the same time that's what makes it exciting and then also there are like human experiences
that at an embodied level i have felt and i know like for example i love jujitsu i love training
when obviously not when i'm traveling but when i'm back in a stable environment
and there's something about that combat and exerting yourself so strenuously that after it
you're steaming up and there's just sweat pouring off you and the endorphins that are released at
the end of that and the conversations that are subsequently had with the friends that you have
made in the gym there's a comradeship there that is just a beautiful feeling and so
to maintain hope in this situation i know that that's that's like intrinsically rewarding and
valuable and there's there's no amount of theory that's gonna refute that for me i know that that
is valuable and so i say to myself okay this is worth preserving so and then i bounce out and i
as Priscilla said i try to gain a perspective and i say okay across time i would like to preserve
this if that's possible how do i go about doing that and then the how do i go about doing that is
the challenge that's the exciting part and there's no guarantee that we win but why not give it our
best shot is how i'm thinking about it so so building on that you mentioned jujitsu
priscilla mentioned a couple things maybe each of you could expand a little bit on the practices or
uh meditations or skills or new behaviors that you've incorporated in your personal life
as a response to your own understanding of of the metacrisis the great simplification and
how all these things interrelate um yeah so for me understanding the metacrisis
i had to realize that i had several behaviors and ways of thinking that i took for granted but
which were actively reinforcing the superorganism so over the last year i've tried to adopt
lifestyle choices and behavior choices which i can imagine as being more characteristic of a
more sustainable system so firstly i really tried to move away from this constant craving for more
and more more and more stuff more and more stimulation and that's a constant battle
but i've tried very hard to actively slow down my pace of life to value quality over quantity
and to remove as many distractions as possible so that i can focus on the present and what we have
and that's been helped through meditation through getting off social media and just yeah actively
creating space and time for silence and for silent reflection and learning to actually
crave the silence rather than the stimulation um so i really enjoyed that and then learning to
take joy and pleasure out of stuff that comes for free i realized that previously a lot of the stuff
i found fun was in some way associated with consumption whereas now um i take a lot of
pleasure out of things like time in nature i love going on long walks time with friends and family
an interesting conversation and dancing and writing and trying to incorporate those things
into my daily life and then in terms of mindset changes i've had a big change related to nature
primarily through food because like james i also love food and i've been putting a lot of more
intention and awareness behind what i'm putting in my body and where it comes from and i'm so lucky
that i live in an amazing part of the world with amazing local produce but this
sort of intention behind what i'm putting in my body has made me realize that my health is
totally tethered to the health of nature and of earth's ecosystems and my actions are impacting
that health and that has given me such a profound respect for nature and for all forms of life
right now when i look out the window i see life in the tree i don't just see a tree
and that's a very different mindset to oh i should make the environmentally friendly choice
because of climate change so that's been a mindset a big mindset shift for me and then
the other one i just want to touch on briefly is moving away from closed-minded in-group out-group
thinking um so i really tried to actively seek out and engage in conversations with people who
have opinions i disagree with and who come from different backgrounds or beliefs and going into
those conversations with the attitude that i want to learn as much as possible and i'm open
to the idea that i'm wrong and i'm gonna update my opinion based on that conversation and that
also has been a big a big mindset shift for me um and it's really taught me to be a lot more open
minded and to realize that i am basically wrong about everything uh yeah and i do think overall
the more i learn about the metacrisis and the more i develop sort of a nuanced understanding of it
i do think it comes down to a shift in consciousness um so yeah i try to live the change i want to see
in the world and hopefully can inspire some people to do the same because if we all collectively do
that then it triggers change higher up let me ask you uh put you on the spot natasha do you think
there's something unique in your um situation or your genetics or your upbringing or are the
changes you made that you just described um easily adaptable by people watching this episode uh that
are 23 and having similar thoughts i think that definitely these changes can be adopted by anyone
um what i will say is because i've thought a lot about this um what i think is unique in my
upbringing is that i was exposed from a young age to very high level conversations um my grandparents
lived in this little town in south of france which was like this hub of international academics
and creatives and uh yeah film directors and artists so from a young age i'd be at dinner
parties with like Nobel prize winners uh and that was normal to me and so i learnt from a young age
should i crave that learning uh and to want to be more interested in learning something new
than in whatever i believed in i think that's led me to where i am now because my involvement in this
space and this work was in no way predicated by me being like a tree hugging hippie or a radical
anarchist or whatever um it's purely from that craving for knowledge and then when finding that
knowledge that makes sense being willing to incorporate that so i think anyone can make
these changes um but it's about being willing and open to to finding out something new and the idea
that you're that everything you might have taken for granted and believed up to that point is wrong
thank you uh what like what are some practices or meditation or are new things that you have
incorporated into your personal life after integrating this into your mental uh view of the future
a very basic thing is something danios mochenberger mentioned at the norskan foundation he said
curate your social media feed so that the sorts of things that crop up are related to this like
the stock home institute planetary boundaries framework that sort of a thing and that's actually
that really works because i find myself going to my phone and then seeing this stuff late at night
and my head is like no i don't want to study that anymore i'm too tired so then i'll just put the phone
down put another thing that helps me sometimes i think of this knowledge as like a burden
sometimes i frame it in that sort of a way and i say oh my god why do i have to know all this why
do i have to be here in this time when all you and me both brother yeah when the shit's hitting the
fan and it's chaotic and it's too multuous but then i say to myself okay useless you're here now so
let's just be here and see what we can do about this and i sort of recalibrate or reframe in my
mind how i see it and i say to myself all right this is probably one of the biggest um the human
predicament the metacrisis uh slaying the super organism whatever you want to say is probably one
of the biggest challenges that humans across the whole of our evolutionary history has ever had to
face have to have ever had to face so to me that's quite um motivating and i say to myself okay so
either you step up to this challenge and make something of yourself so that you can
address it in whatever way possible and try to make that addressing it as big as possible
because i remember i actually mentioned something like doing the gardening and stuff like this and
don't get me wrong i love all that and i'm here doing the regenerative agriculture stuff but at
the same time i think there needs to be like agents of change who are so disproportionate in
terms of the consequences of their decisions or choices or actions that they they're in a position
of power that they can make those disproportionate um changes happen the whatever decisions they make
have highly are highly consequential we need to also figure out how to find ourselves in those
positions and i guess they're just a concern comes up it's like okay you you'd want to know
what you're talking about and what you're at when you're doing that so that also is quite inspiring
for me building off what others have said about phone use i think it's a very powerful tool
i myself have started to use social media more as i got older and going back to that generational
thing sometimes i look at gen alpha because i'm gen z and i'm like oh god we're fucked because
you're ipad kids but i also have to think like i don't blame you for wanting to dissociate on your
phone because the world's a scary place i dissociate on my phone too i'm subject to that habit as well
but in my role as a communicator for my day job as a friend as a neighbor i'm not going to post
something unless there's a sense of agency that you can gain from it her writing avenues and
pathways that then take action i think it's good to affirm and put out some really emotionally
charged content but i don't want to be a click to this you know where you become complacent and
complicit just because you posted something online and think yep i've done my part i also
don't want to rage farm you know that that's a term rage farming you're just fueling the
fire without really directing people to any channel of action so that's one rule i've
held myself accountable to yes affirm people but also try to provide agency where you can when
you're doing your stuff online and i think it's it's funny this ironic momentum around
reindigenizing right there's the the sense that people want to go back to the land and
live simpler lives and like really change the culture and now today and throughout recent
history certain advocates of that especially indigenous folks global south folks people of
color all other communities that have been socially disadvantaged or marginalized in the
past like that's stuff they've been doing forever but also you know to counterbalance
that with not painting a monolith right i don't think we have to look too far and many
for my observations i've noticed many immigrant families in the us who come here and fully embrace
and get ensconced in the american dream they are fully in survival mode they're they are just trying
to make as much money climb the ladder and that's a capitalist mindset and then they give birth to
children like me who are very against that so it's very complicated depending where you live the
privileges you have it's a privilege to be having these types of conversations but i think
when i am in a space to have these conversations i'm really trying to cultivate
facilitation skills how to hold effective meetings how to make everyone feel seen and heard in a
conversation for effective governance decision decision making models and i really think that's
scalable i think that's going to be pretty key to understanding the crises and then how to address
them because right now no matter what type enterprise you're in or workplace you're in
i think there's room to improve for facilitating effective like congregations of people to then
come to consent or consensus around certain issues and values then to move forward with that so
really if i'm asking people to change then i have to embody that change myself and again it's not
about being perfect it's just about being authentic and within your realms within the privileges you
hold thank you and thank you to all three of you for putting in the time to learn this stuff and
be willing to be on camera to to share some thoughts is there is there any question that you
would have liked me to ask that you'd like to close with some some comments or anything else
that each of you would like to say to our viewers no i do just want to briefly say that if there
are young people watching this who are getting exposed to this content it can be really scary
and tough if you don't have people to talk to about it so hopefully as you said Nate there's
going to be like a discord channel by the time this is out but speaking for me personally i'd
be very happy to chat to anyone who feels like they're going through this cognitive journey by
themselves so just putting that out there yes i also want to plug the emotional container model
you do really need to hold space for people to process this and i'm proud of the work that i've
done with my peers when we founded a non-profit called the Overstory Alliance and out of that
game movement school and it really was about educating and then providing a space review
to process and then providing perhaps an avenue for them people to manifest whatever change they
want they're interested in you're interested in chicken coop go do that you're interested in
building furniture go do that if you're interested in becoming part of the system changing from
within that's okay too but yeah really emphasizing the emotional container key to preserving yourself
and not burning out closing remarks i can't really say much to be honest what i would say is
because i'm not sure what it was within me that made me realize oh no that's not quite true don't
believe that or don't fall into that trap maybe there's something sort of innate to humans that
can guide us like that and i would say listen to that inner voice that guides you in that way
and don't betray it don't betray it not for money nor for people in your life who would convince you
that no no no this is the way to see the world i'd just say yeah stay true to that inner voice
i i didn't persil i don't even know if you know this but i almost called my class at the university
of minnesota things you always knew but never knew you knew but it was too convoluted and long so
i called it reality 101 instead yeah persil after you left nate you know a few of us adapted your
course to become another seminar led by students for students and we titled it what to do about a
fucked up world and we just live with humor a humor does a great service to people in healing
and navigating and honestly we live in the age of memes so why not yeah thank you all young humans
friends of mine to be continued and and thanks for being curious and and wanting to um share and try
thanks date thanks everyone
if you enjoyed or learned from this episode of the great simplification please follow us on your
favorite podcast platform and visit the great simplification dot com for more information on
future releases this show is hosted by nate higgins edited by no troublemakers media
and curated by leslie batloots and lizzie siriani