hi friends as you can see I'm controlling train simulator with a midi pad from
Akai, here's the gas station is coming
press the horn
hit the brake
I'm already slow
I'm not the best train driver by the way as you can see okay let's come to a stop
and open the doors with this one wait for the stop
doors are opening
turn off the wiper no wrong button sorry this is the interface down here
the HUD
where is it don't remember
well the direction lever
the brake is not applied in this kind of train and the fuse
this I forgot also okay how can this be done just watch this video
first of all many thanks for your feedback and your suggestions of the for
the initial version of midi key to key now this here is the magical thing and
if you never heard about midi key to key make sure you watch the first video
that tells you the basic use of that program for now I'm show you the version
1.9 with many new features and bug fixes and let's talk about quickly about the
bug fixes I have a title and activated by OBS the bug fixes so there is all these
small things the channel is in this here one two sixteen they did not save but
nobody complained it I found it and now they are saved in the settings and the
second thing is if you have an action and react on the second value it's used
rarely normally you only react on the first value the first data value this
was not storage it didn't work but nobody complained because you won't use it
very often so now what's new the great new features yeah where to start with okay
um you have had one settings file your settings in you that stored all your
settings and the settings of the actions the key actions the midi actions now you
have multiple actions if you start midi key to key the first time it's just stores
automatically it settings the settings any in your documents folder and that's
it now you can have several in ease or settings file and where are they in the
file menu you can now load a custom a different settings file here we are
documents your username documents midi key to key you can load a different
setting and save as a different setting you don't need to type any in the end it
does it automatically they all need to be here to be found automatically and then
second new feature is you can start up midi key to key with a special settings
file if you have a shortcut like this just add at the end a name of a path my
setting any if it has white spaces you need to surround to surround it okay so now
it will load my setting this file is not existing this is an example but you can
you can easily create a shortcut like this
and it starts at your desktop and name will be
for example new setting so and as you can see it made a shortcut and called it new setting and
yeah it sets the actual any file and this is the default right now as you can see in the
headline the top line of the program settings any therefore it just says settings okay so
multiple settings files the next thing is since I'm using this archive path apc mini
this one has the feature to let the buttons light up which the cork nanopad didn't have
and well it needs to receive midi commands to light up the buttons in that case it
wants to have note on events and you can have three colors green red and yellow and
same blinking and you can send turn it off so midi key to key needed to send out midi here we are
now you can choose the output device for sending out midi commands this is the old input and now
you need to have an output device and now when you have an action fired you can in addition of a
key command or start program action now define a midi command that is sent out and you can send
whatever you want I'll show you that later you even can send two different midi commands they
toggle each time you fire the action next thing is the mirror midi this is just a small feature
it mirrors the midi into the midi out in the case of the apc it does nothing because I need to push
the start button you see it mirrored my in command of that key and that lets the archive apc mini
turn on the green default light when I press it again nothing happens it stays now on at that
state that's the mirror out that's new um yeah besides the edit the action the action that you
choose here besides this now you have a test button you can test
your action let's start the text editor to see what's happening
let's test the the view button from the train simulator
I have to now the problem is if I push the test button with the mouse the editor loses now
the focus and you don't see the letter I'm typing then let's go to yeah
this action that
as you can see
that pushed an action to obs now that's for testing that's new and also new is now these
these the name or as it was shown the actions was the the midi bytes
and now apc 8 4 is my reminder this is 8 4 is this knob and now you can name your action it's down here
whatever you want hit save and the name will appear now in this list you can now better
find actions if you have a lot like this
now next new thing is
if you have a start program action watch the first video to check this out
now you can choose the state of the action of the program started normal is just a normal
window max is the max window maximized and minimized and or even hidden these four states
you can store and the program that you want to start by an action will have this window state
some users want to fire up a command a box like cnd or let's define a new
action uh let's take the top here
I call this round right one I'll find it at the test that's the first thing and
um we're gonna have a program action
command window the working directory needed and this is the command
do you now first in normal state save okay now hit this one
this is opening the window in the normal state I'll edit this action
maximized
is maximized as you can see well and you can believe me the other actions
uh minimized or even hidden are also working but you won't see anything
let's turn that off so and if you now have a send media action defined um the program
works now as a universal media converter it it listens to a special input media event and then
sends out any media out command or even sequences as long as you wish of media commands
this is done with this new tab send midi and there are many controls but it's easy to handle
first of all activated now this is still our test button
uh to light this up I know it's 90 52 this is the note on and the number of this
and now zero one makes it green the round buttons I believe they are only can be green
and these only can be red so the other will have zero one up to zero six for the decolors and blink
and not blink so now the media command I put in is 90 52 zero one that's it it all will be sent
all the time so this would be would have an effect just on the first time because it stays now on
you won't see difference for this
I have a toggle section B is a command that will be executed the next time
so 90 52 zero to turn it off
off on off on
so these buttons here are defined to change the
the fuse of train simulator and these to change the scenes of OBS you see this one becomes red
and the active one is green blinking now this needs when pressing this an action of seven
commands that makes them all steady green and this one blinking
I have this in the
eight one
so this is the command
you see they are all to five in the end except the first one is the three
second time is not defined it's only the first time and then if we check all the others
where's the A2
anyway
they are all five to
oh no this is this one here
it's the few two
they're all set to one except now the second one is set to two to make it blink like this
so if we edit then our test button here up in the corner again
this is what you can do just by typing any commands and if you do a second command just one
space and please nothing else so this is executed very quickly
but if you want to wait
a little you can add a pause in milliseconds so let's say 300
oh no add now it adds this in the end it's just where you can cut this out oh well I messed it up
so like this it always puts commands in the end now it since this color command
means out off then wait 300 milliseconds and then turn on the green light again check it out
doesn't work
why is this not working
oh push the totally wrong number 52
it turns on after 300 milliseconds
you can create sequences of
hundreds of commands with a pause in between so you could turn the whole matrix of lights into
showing letters and scrolling left to right and then create light shows just for fun
so if you won't use the input pad manually by typing in hex commands you see now it's only
numbers but it's still bytes of hex so after the 9 comes 9a, 9b, 9c and so on
you can route the last or
or oh I hit the save thing now or remove everything
oh this was not a really not a command
so just type in
rr is a wallet command to remove last or clear all so if you won't
don't like to type in manually you can use these input boxes now note on is the first thing
and you can if you know the hex value of a key
you can just use this or choose the key down here
note on and then note on needs another value if you push add please enter a value this is the
velocity 25 add so then let's turn this note on or just
let it sound for
half a second and then turn it off
off needs no data but it doesn't matter
so and that's it this will play is c3 for half a second and turn it off
so now
let's stop this and use the wave table synthesizer and I'm not sure if you hear it now in the video
just give it a try
you hear that
yeah so you can even play
songs at this
so this is not on not off the most common things you will use but you can send everything and if
you know something just type it in sys x commands are not included here
another thing is channel mode messages these are preformed all nodes off
would be this command it doesn't need any data so this is disabled local on off
reset all controllers omnimode on off it's just without any data fields it is built in command
polyphonic after touch these these types need to have which node do you press and
how strong is the after touch the monophonic after touch channel after touch only needs
how much is the whole keyboard to press and after touch there are many media controls possible
control changes are very huge in number some require two
two commands in a row some require a 14 bit data or the most of them require seven bit data
um midi key to key just takes anything you type in up to 127
so everything will not make sense you need to be an expert for midi to know what you do but
as you can see if you know about midi you can do a lot with this or just type anything
in manually here add pauses in between with this field or by typing p and whatever
a number of milliseconds this is now media out the main job is to light up
midi controllers by sending a command to it to have a reflection what you are doing like this
changing scenes in obias or whatever this is the great new feature and um yeah many users ask
me about what about controllers like these like faders or turning knobs um and i respond
that well this is a thing they need to fire out many midi um commands in a row
on i don't know how to do it or will it make sense and as you could see in the uh
intro video it is working and this is maybe one of the best new features now you can
send um a response to a controller and fire up key commands it just fires key commands as you can see
this controls the the gas of the train a for plus and default minus and as you can see
yeah it even works on this window we won't save this now how is this been done
done define a new one let's take this you start this is the one two three four five the fifth
controller just move it and double click now on the event it created
i recommend giving it a name
fader five so it sends keystrokes yes and uh you just put the first keystrokes it
it will send when you increase the lever um yeah let's just send a q or shift q
and now hit the controller action box and now the the response is brought to the second this is the
value for decrement a controller value so now again press the blue button and press your
other action as you can see this is now coming here if you want to change this again you can
just type in anything manually but you know when you want to use the blue thing it's always
when this checkbox is on it will manipulate this input box so turn it off
and change it here when you turn this checkbox again off your shift w is not lost so this is just
the easy thing now you have two keys to find this will be fired when the new value of
by moving a controller is higher and if you move the controller the controller
fader down the new value is lower and then the shift w is fired now
this two things are very important the keyboard delay is 100 does a good job on
uh just controlling programs and some users told me obs studio is not responding to
midi key to key and uh only when it has the focus and when you use your keyboard it works even as
if it has not the focus so i found out if you have a very low keyboard delay value you can
even set this to zero that means key pressed down and up uh in the same moment um my obs studio is
responding at about 40 and 50 milliseconds so and if you go lower with the keyboard delay
it will just respond on any actions when it is in focus so that's a performance problem
and our system is not different now when we want to have a controller action like this put it down
all the way first of all check zero and leave the multiplier to one that means the controller
will have
127 values from the bottom to the top and the multiplier to set to one fires up 127
times the key press so one to one with no delay save this and check it out if now set the focus
to the editor and move the fader see i put in a new line fader down creates w
so and then if you set the delay to zero this reacts very quickly
so
but if you want to control a game it's different
how they respond train simulator is special it needs a little longer key press to react to
to move the gas lever and so i put this to 10 that's a thing you can experiment with
it even works on as just a single key press no controller action
you can type in a value then then let's the key down for this time you put in
before it releases to to make a key press longer but there's a problem i don't know why so far
if you put it too high over a second or something the program will not longer respond i don't know
what it is maybe it can be fixed in the future but i think it's not really important to have this
right now so the keyboard delay let's see when you put it to 10 what will be the difference
now 10 doesn't really make a difference let's put it a little longer
set it to 80
see you really won't don't want that by controlling any software but
who knows you might need it
always start with a zero and the keyboard events will be fired up immediately
so the second thing is a multiplier and that's still experimental
because i can't really do anything i want to
as mentioned the the midi standard is 127 values but if you have a lever in a software that has
only five or six different states to control you will set the multiplier lower let's say to
1.2 and this is not a point it's point or comma depending of your country i'm in germany so i
need to type in a comma so i have the multiplier lower than one and now this is the max
you see it
it cuts the maximum numbers set it to 0.1
it cuts the amount always in half and that's the only thing it can do because it has to count
the the input events as you can see they are coming single one by one and it has just to count
10 times to wait now never fire up another keyboard action so you cannot have
you cannot have everywhere you you wish
last test of this zero zero one
yeah it's just produces one
okay if you want to have more than 170 events you only can double or times four times three times
four times five you cannot do one point five times you can send an event or you cannot send you
cannot send half of an event so let's put this to three and it will produce three times of 127
so and uh different software is different but you can control
any software with it that responds on key presses
um oops i'm sorry
a crash
i wanted to press the edit button i don't know why it quite crashed need to check this out
um so set the multiplier to one and you will have a one to one respond on your
on your lever or for your controller set it lower than zero point five will only produce
about 66 key events and put it higher in whole numbers not 1.5 1.7 just one two three
will produce uh two times three times four times of the maximum
so i hope now that's it the new controller actions
controller actions we talked about sending media
yeah if you use an old version of media key to key and you use your old settings any
they did not have the keyboard delay value so if you just use it open it up and and use your
um media pad the program will crash because it doesn't have the keyboard delay in your old
any so if you do so create a new any start at zero i show you this right now how this can be done
um start at zero then everything will be fine um or take your existing any in that case
is as much open any every action with edit it will get a default of 100 decided if this is okay or
not and hit save if you do do it with all your actions it they will have then a keyboard delay
and the program will not crash as i said uh start fresh
will be like this go into your documents folder and let me get an explorer
uh and rename or delete your existing settings any
in the media key to key folder it's here because if it turns see
if it doesn't see any settings see it will create a new one and also i take this my setting that is
well it was all the time saying i can't find my settings sure it doesn't exist without any
part so start up media key to key and best practice is to start it up and close it then a new settings
any is generated and from then you can start making actions it's also recommended if you
have an existing let's open the existing the strain simulator thing has some actions
and you decide to to do a new game or whatever um and you edit stuff like this and changing things
and hit save and then say and save all of this as a new setting you can do that but remember now
the the settings name that's here written in the top line train simulator is already changed on all
the actions because you hit save anytime you edit an action and hit save this setting is written
into the actual settings file so when you want to build up a new setting based on let's say this one
at first hit save as and then start editing the actions that's the better practice and you won't
lose the settings of your actions in the old file so that's it for now all the
important URLs will be shown down there for download and for the other video for the basic
video which i recommend to watch first and the home page for download and for your
respondings okay um this is the script i can't provide it well it's very simple um
this just does the uh mix 64 media events for the akai um this down here is just
for to have the created sequence in the clipboard and this is a little weird vbs don't have any
clipboard commands so it uses internet explorer who now runs the script and then put the result in
the clipboard and therefore this is all the code down here um the script here just creates the events
you can say set pause to one or zero that means will i have a pause in between the events zero one
how long the pause is in milliseconds and then decide what extension do you want to have
and uh i think this is red and out um no it's nothing so these three
extension is the last value
so if i run the script now it sets a pause of 75 milliseconds in between all the
the events and uh that sets all the lights of the apc to three let's create quickly a new event
oh no device is selected because i started with a completely new um
um yeah then take this little square button which does not have a light
start press it once take the note off and the note on event um do nothing
just take this send midi and where's the script now let's run the script set to one
pause one oh there it is
here's the result and at the same moment this is put into your clipboard so
paste it in and delete the last pause
okay then put it to be to turn all the lights off with a
lower pause value it goes quickly more quickly 15 and zero save
start
i do not know why this takes so long and sometimes oh there it is
it's only because of the the clipboard you could know you cannot copy this therefore
you need the clipboard anyway now we paste in this delete the last pause
p15 and that's it now we have these two sets and what will happen let's have a look right here
it turns on all the red lights with the pause of 75 milliseconds in between when we hit
the second time it removes them but quicker because of the lower pause
so you can create your pictures this little script if you want to download it i don't know
it's just a little thing to me right in the comments of the website
or down here but i like more the website
okay that's it thanks for watching see you next time bye