Academia is broken. Universities are broken. The way that academic research is published
is broken. That's the message that's come through loud and clear over the last few weeks,
thanks to three articles concerning the research of Francesca Geno. If you don't know what I'm
talking about, let me explain. Francesca Geno is a professor of behavioral science at Harvard
University. She is extremely well known in the field. I've talked about her research to clients
before. I've recommended books on this channel to you guys that use her work as a key reference,
I've used her research before as references in my own essays and work that I did at university
when it comes to academic fame, Francesca Geno is up there, as you would expect from someone
who is a professor at Harvard. However, the reason why she's so well known is because her
research tends to bring out a lot of very surprising findings. Now, some people just think this
research is cool and don't think much more about it, but a lot of people in the industry have been
quite skeptical of Francesca Geno and her work because her results just seem a little bit too
good. Her hypotheses are really wacky, but yet they always seem to be proved correct,
the effect sizes from her study seem to be really large, and her statistical significance just seem
a little bit too significant. So while some of us have been skeptical of her work for a while,
nobody has taken the time to actually investigate her research and go into her data to see if they
can find anything fishy... until now. These three guys, Yuri, Joe and Leif, are also professors
of behavioral science and other related subjects from different universities across the world,
and they took it upon themselves to investigate Francesca Geno and her data to see if there was
anything fishy going on. And spoiler alert, they found a lot of fishy stuff in the data,
and that's what the three articles that they released are talking about. Each article relates
to a different study by Francesca Geno, and in this video I'm going to be taking you through
each one. The results of their investigation are shocking, damning for Francesca Geno,
but I think they speak even louder volumes about the state of academia in general,
and that's what I'm going to be concluding on at the end of this video. So without further ado,
let's jump into the first study. So this first article is called clusterfake, and it's referring
to a paper written by Geno in 2012, along with their collaborators Shu, Nina Mazar, Dan Ariely,
and Max Bazeman. Given the fact that I know the first names of all of those researchers with the
exception of Shu, I should tell you that all of these researchers are very well-known people in
the field of behavioral science. So in this study, they were trying to get participants to be more
honest, and their hypothesis was that if you put an honesty pledge at the top of a form,
that'll make people more honest when they then fill out the rest of the form. So all of the studies
in this paper by these authors were looking at this idea, that if you put an honesty pledge at the
top of a form, people will be more honest than if you put the honesty pledge at the bottom of a form.
Now the first study in this paper was led by Francesca Geno, our protagonist. So in this study,
students were brought into a lab to complete 20 math puzzles in five minutes. The students were
told that they would be paid one dollar for each math puzzle they solved correctly, and the way that
this worked was that when students walked into the room, there were two pieces of paper. They had
their work paper and their report paper. So on the work paper, they'd write down their workings for
the math questions and of course their answers, and then on the report paper, they would then have
to report how many answers they got correctly and therefore how much they should get paid. The students
were then told that before handing in their report paper to the researchers and getting paid, that
they should shred their original work paper. The idea behind this is that by shredding their work
paper, there's then a stronger incentive for them to cheat on the report paper and lie about
how many answers they got correct, since the researchers in theory should never know how
many answers they got right on the work paper. But what the students didn't know was that the
shredder at the back of the room was not a normal shredder. What the people in the experiment don't
know is that the shredder has been fixed. So the shredder only shreds the sides of the page,
but the main body of the page remains intact. Now in order to test the hypothesis of the researchers,
on the reporting paper, the participants were split into two groups. Half of them had an honesty
pledge at the top of the paper, and half of them had an honesty pledge at the bottom of the paper,
with the idea being of course that those who signed the honesty pledge at the top would
then cheat less going forward. So what was the result? Well the result showed a massive effect
from this simple intervention. According to what was published in the study originally,
for the students who signed the honesty pledge at the top of the form, only 37% of them lied,
but when students signed at the bottom of the form, 79% of students lied. This is a massive
effect size that the researchers are reporting, and as a result of that, this study gained a lot
of public attention, and I have talked about it with many people in the past before because it is
so surprising. But that's why these vigilantes were suspicious. The results just seem a bit too good.
Can it really be the case that simply moving an honesty pledge from the bottom to the top of a
form can have such a dramatic effect on the amount of cheating that happens? It seems pretty
unlikely. So our vigilantes managed to source the original data set that was published by the
authors of the study, and when they looked into the data it just seemed a little bit fishy. If you
look at this table and specifically look at the left hand column, the P hash column, this is referring
to participant ID. This is the unique ID given to each participant in a study, and as it's highlighted
in yellow, there are some weird anomalies in the way that this data has been sorted. Because
when you look at this data, it seems obvious that this has been sorted by first the condition, so
all of condition one are together, and all of condition two are together, and then in ascending
order of the participant ID, which means that the numbers should consistently get bigger as you go
down the line, and there should be no duplicates. Remember, each participant has a unique ID. So
when you look at this data, it's a bit weird. We've got two 49s here, that's a duplicate,
that should never happen, and then at the end of the condition one set of participants,
you have participant 51 coming after 95, then 12, then 101, like that sequence doesn't make any
sense. And similarly, when you get to condition two, we start with seven, then 91, then 52,
then all the way back down to five again. These entries in the data set look suspicious. They
look like they're out of sequence, which suggests that somebody maybe has tampered with them. So
our vigilantes are suspicious of these rows. So then you have to ask the question, why would the
researchers want to tamper with the data? Well, it's because they would want to show a bigger
effect than those actually seen in the real data. The more dramatic the effect of the intervention
is, the more surprising the result of the study is, and therefore the more likely it is to get
published in the top journal, the more likely it is that this will make a lot of press headlines,
that they will get lots of interviews and work off the back of it. And so there's a strong incentive
for the researchers to fudge the data a little bit, make the effect seem larger than it really is.
And so that's what our vigilantes were looking for. They wanted to see if these suspicious rows
in the data set showed a bigger effect than the normal data that wasn't suspicious. And sure
enough, that's exactly what they found. If you look at this graph, the red circles with the cross
show the suspicious data and the blue dots show the unsuspicious data. And as you can see, the
circles with the red crosses are the most extreme ones, meaning that these few data points are
inflating the effect size. Now the article goes on to show how our vigilantes did some very clever
work to unpack the Excel file that this data was stored in, and they were able to show quite clearly
that these suspicious rows were manually resorted in the data set. I won't go into it on this video
because it's quite technical, but I'll have a link to all of these articles in the description if
you want to read them in full. But as you'll soon see, this theme of suspicious data and then those
data showing extremely strong effect sizes will be a recurring pattern. So let's move on to study
two. Now this second article is called My Class Year is Harvard and you'll see why in a second.
They're looking at a study from 2015 written by Francesca Geno as well as Kuchaki and Galinsky,
again two fairly well known researchers in the field. Now the hypothesis for this study, in my
opinion, is pretty stupid. The hypothesis is that if you argue against something that you really
believe in, that makes you feel dirty, which then increases your desire for cleansing products,
which is kind of silly in my opinion. But nevertheless, this is what they were researching.
So this study was done at Harvard University with almost 500 students and what they asked the
participants to do was the following. So students of Harvard University were brought into the lab
and then asked how they felt about this thing called the Q Guide. I don't really know what the Q
Guide is, but apparently it's a hot topic at Harvard and it's very controversial. Some people are for
it, some people are against it. So when they were brought into the lab, they were asked how do you
feel about the Q Guide and they either said they were for or against it and then the participants
were split into two groups. Half the participants were asked to write an essay supporting the
view that they just gave. So if they said I'm for the Q Guide, they had to then write an essay
explaining why they were for the Q Guide. But then half the participants were asked to write an essay
arguing opposite to the point that they just gave. So if they said I'm for the Q Guide, they would
then have to write an essay explaining why they should be against the Q Guide. Again, the idea
being that those who are writing an essay against what they actually believe in would make them feel
dirty. Because after they'd written this essay, they were then shown five different cleansing
products. And the participants in the study had to rate how desirable they felt these cleansing
products were on a scale of one to seven, with one being completely undesirable and seven being
completely desirable. And again, the authors found a strong effect. You can see here that the p value
is less than 0.0001. And for those of you who haven't had any academic training in statistics,
basically when you're doing a study like this, you're looking for a p value that's less than
0.05. That's the industry standard. If it's less than 0.05, you say, yes, I'm confident that the
effect that I'm seeing is caused by the manipulation that I just did. So less than 0.0001 is an
extremely strong effect. You're basically 100% confident that what you're seeing in the data
is caused by the manipulation that you did. So once again, our vigilantes are suspicious of this
very strong effect sites. So they managed to source the data online and do a little bit of
investigating. And what they find are some weird anomalies in the kind of demographic data that
the participants have to give when they enter the study. And this is very common in psychological
studies that participants have to give a little bit of demographic data about themselves, which
gives the researchers a little bit more flexibility about how they cut up the data later on. So in
this particular study, the participants were asked a number of demographic questions, including their
age, their gender, and then number six was what year in school they were. Now the way this question
is structured isn't very good, in my opinion, in terms of research design. But nevertheless,
there are a number of acceptable answers that you can give to year in school. Because Harvard is an
American school, you might say, I'm a senior, right, which is a common thing, or a sophomore,
you might write the year that you're supposed to graduate, 2015, 2016, etc. Or you might indicate a
one, a two, a three, a four, or a five to indicate how many years of school that you've been in there.
These are all different answers, but they're all acceptable and make sense in the context of being
asked what year in school you. And so when our vigilantes go into the data, that's exactly what
they saw in this column, a range of different answers that were all acceptable, except for
one, there were 20 entries in this data set, where the answer to the question what year in school
are you was Harvard. That doesn't make any sense. What year in school are you? Harvard. What? Right,
that doesn't make any sense. And the other thing that was suspicious about these Harvard entries
is that they were all grouped together within 35 rows. Again, this was a data set of nearly 500
different participants, and yet all of these weird Harvard answers were within 35 rows. So once again,
our vigilantes treat these Harvard answers as suspicious data entries. They mark them in red
circles with crosses. And as you can see, the ones that are suspicious are again, the most
extreme answers supporting the hypothesis of the researchers, with the exception of this one. But
come on, it's most suspicious when you look at the ones on argued other side. So these are the
people who wrote an essay arguing against what they didn't believe in, and therefore was supposed
to feel more dirty and find cleansing products more appealing. All of these suspicious entries on
that side of the manipulation went for seven, that they found all of the cleaning products
completely desirable. And so what our vigilantes go on to say is that these were just the 20 entries
in the data set that looked suspicious because of this Harvard answer to the demographic question.
But who's to say that the other data in the data set was not also tampered with, but just they were
more careful when they filled in this column and didn't put Harvard. Since it seems pretty clear
that at least these 20 entries were manipulated and tampered with some way, it probably means that
there are other entries within this data set that were also tampered with. Are you shocked yet? I
hope you are, but it's about to get worse because there's a third article to do with Francesca
Geno. So this third article was released literally yesterday, the day before I'm filming this video,
and it's called the cheaters are out of order. This is written by Francesca Geno and a guy called
Wilta Muth. I don't know Wilta Muth, but again, I find it incredibly ironic that all of this
cheating and fake data is being conducted by researchers who are studying
the science of honesty. It is incredibly ironic. So in this third study, Geno and her co-author
are investigating the idea that people who cheat, people that lie, who are dishonest,
are actually more creative. And they call the paper evil genius, how dishonesty can lead to
greater creativity. So let's quickly go through how the study worked. Participants were brought
into a lab where they were sat at a machine with a virtual coin flipping mechanism. What the
participants are asked to do is to predict whether the coin will flip heads or tails, and then they
would push a button to actually flip the coin. And if they had predicted correctly about whether
it would go heads or tails, then they would get a dollar. So again, there's a strong incentive to
cheat. So the participants would write down on a piece of paper how many predictions they got
correct, and then they would hand that to the researcher in order to get paid. Then of course,
the researcher would then go back and look at the machine that they were flipping the coin on
to see how many they actually got correct. And then they were able to tell how many times that
participant had cheated. So after they completed the coin flipping task, they were then given a
creativity task. And the creativity task was how many different uses can you think of for a
piece of newspaper? So in psychology, this is a pretty common technique for testing creativity.
You give somebody an inanimate object, and then you say how many uses can you think of
for this inanimate object. And again, with this study, we see a very strong effect size. Remember,
the magic number that academics look for is P less than 0.05. And here we have P less than 0.001.
So basically what that means is that there's an extremely high likelihood that the effect that
the academics are seeing is caused by the manipulation that they did. So again, our vigilantes
are suspicious. But this one is interesting because our vigilantes were able to actually
get the data set from Gino several years ago. So they got this data set directly from Gino.
So again, when our vigilantes look into the data, they find some weird things going on.
As you can see, it seems to be sorted by two things. Firstly, by the number of times the
participant cheated. So all of the people who didn't cheat at all are zeros. And then the
number of responses is the number of different uses for a newspaper that that participant could
come up with. And those are clearly ranked in ascending order. But as you can see from this
next screenshot, some of the cheaters are out of order. So these are the people who cheated once,
who basically over reported one time, and the number of uses that they could come up with for
the newspaper are out of sequence. Here we have three, four, 13, then nine, and then back down to
five again, then back up to nine, then five, then nine, then eight, then nine is just a total mess,
right? So these ones that are highlighted in yellow are the suspicious ones. They're the ones
that are out of order, according to how the data appears to have been sorted. So what our
vigilantes did was they basically took this data set and then made a new column and they called
it imputed low or imputed high. What that basically means is that rather than taking the number of
responses that are written down in this original data set, they're going to say, well, where does
this entry sit in the ranking order? And so we're going to replace the value that is given here
with what the value should really be. So if it's between four and five, then that number should
be either four or five, whether it's imputed low or imputed high. Does that make sense? So once
again, our researchers plotted the data, suspicious entries are marked with a circle and a cross.
And as you can see, the suspicious entries are the ones that deviate from the pattern that you see
in the non cheaters, the blue line. So in other words, the ones that are out of order,
the suspicious entries, they're the ones showing the effect. But when you use the imputed position,
so that's the number that is implied by the row that the entry was in, then suddenly the entire
effect disappears. And the group of cheaters seem to show a very similar pattern to the group of
non cheaters. And the result of this statistically speaking is significant. Remember the original
p value for this study was p less than 0.0001. But once you use the data that's implied by the
row, suddenly the significance completely disappears. It then goes to p equals 0.292 or p equals 0.180,
depending on whether you're imputing low or high. Remember, in order for an academic study to be
significant, the standard is p less than 0.05. And here the p is clearly more than 0.05. Again,
this article goes on. The vigilantes do a little bit more research to really back up the point and
really drive home the fact that this data is very suspicious. I won't go into the details now. Again,
all of these articles are linked in the description. Go check them out. And you'll notice that these
were all called part one, part two, part three. And that's because this is actually a four part
series. So I'm expecting a fourth article to come out after this video is published looking at yet
another study from Francesca Geno. But I hope by this point, you get the picture, there's a number
of studies conducted by Francesca Geno with very suspicious looking data. So at this point,
you're probably wondering how did Harvard allow this? And the short answer is, well,
they don't really seem to have done. If you go on Francesca Geno's page on the Harvard website,
it shows that she's on administrative leave. I think we all know what that means. And Harvard,
who have even more access to Francesca Geno's data than our vigilantes do, have since asked for
several of Francesca Geno's papers to be retracted from the journals that they were originally
published in. Now, this is a bad look for Francesca Geno, right? And we can't be sure that it was
Francesca Geno who was doing this manipulation. It could be one of her co-authors. But given that
she's the common thread between all of these different papers, it seems pretty likely that
it was her in the world of psychology and writing good quality academic papers. This is really bad.
It's not only bad for Francesca Geno, but it's bad for the field as a whole. It casts doubt over
the entire field of behavioral science, because we don't know the extent of the damage that bad
actors like Geno have been causing in the field and for how long. Like I said, Francesca Geno has
been a prominent name in the field for years, gaining a position at one of the top universities,
Harvard. So who's to say that this isn't a problem that is rife amongst many other researchers
in the field? We certainly hope not. But you can't really know when somebody so high profile like
this has been engaging in this kind of behavior for years and getting away with it. It also looks
bad for people like me who work in the industry, who trust these academics to publish good quality
research that we then use to try and influence real world change in businesses, in government,
and so on and so forth. Like I said, I've used Geno's work before to make recommendations to my
clients. And I've recommended to you guys to read Dan Ariely's book, The Honest Truth About
Dishonesty in the Past, a book which I no longer recommend since the paper that was talked about
in the first article here is used heavily as a reference for a lot of the claims that Ariely
is making in that book. And while it's tempting here to just completely lay into Francesca Geno
and just, you know, really have a go at her for this kind of bad behavior, I actually kind of
understand why she did it, right? If you're an academic at a top institution like Harvard,
you are under an enormous amount of pressure to publish surprising results and consistently.
Surprising results with big effect sizes are more likely to get published in top journals when you
more press interviews and basically cement your position there at a top university like Harvard.
So there is a strong incentive for academics to fudge data like this and come up with more
surprising results in order to try and maintain their position. I'm not condoning the behavior in
the slightest. It's completely unacceptable that an academic would do this, but I can somewhat
empathize that she's under a lot of pressure and can see how the incentives are working against
the practice of following good science. But what do you guys think of Francesca Geno and all of
this nonsense? Let me know in the comments below. Please go read the articles that are in the
description. Thank you to Yuri, Joe, and Leigh for publishing this research. You guys are absolute
legends. And Francesca Geno, if you're watching this video, I know you must be going through a
really rough time right now to have your sort of entire career ripped away from you so publicly
like this. While I think that what you did is completely unacceptable, please don't do anything
stupid with your own life. You're still a valuable human being. But thank you guys so much for watching
and I'll see you next time. Bye bye.