Hi there, so this is a quite interesting video and I think it's very
topical. At the moment of course we get all these results from vaccine trials
and when you read these trials you'll see a lot of them expresses the
efficacy of the vaccine. Now in order for us to determine efficacy we look at the
relative risk. So this video I'm going to show you a notebook, two notebooks in
actual fact. I'm going to use R just to explain the language for
statistical computing just what relative risk is and how we then use it to
calculate efficacy and we're also going to look at a specific trial. In South
Africa there was a small trial as far as the AstraZeneca vaccine was concerned
and it showed very poor efficacy and because of that the vaccine was
withdrawn from South Africa which of course is a very big decision was the
first vaccine it was supposed to go to healthcare workers such as myself and
the vaccine was withdrawn because of the poor showing. So I'm going to show you
how they got to this very bad efficacy level of only 21% and of course
it's not only about that it's about this the confidence intervals around that
efficacy and that's what I want to explain. Now of course with drawing that
was a very difficult decision and it wasn't only the clinical data there was
some data as well and I'll talk a little bit about it about the neutralizing
antibodies etc a lot more went into the decision not to use the AstraZeneca
vaccine in South Africa. So it's all about relative risk and then this video
I'll show you just how a relative risk works how you can calculate it and how
from that we get the efficacy. So here we are on my art pub's website you can
view all the documents that I upload you can view them here and of course the
original the RMD files are available on GitHub and the links to all of these
things will be in the description down below. So we're just going to look at
uncertainty in relative risk. First what is risk what is relative risk and how do
we express uncertainty in that and of course it's very topical with the
vaccines these days in the pandemic and we express the efficacy of these
vaccines. I want to show you just just how to do that. So in this first notebook
we're just going to talk about what risk is and what relative risk is and then
what efficacy is and then how can we express uncertainty just due to
randomness. We do one trial but there is a lot of other trials that if if we could
do it we could do it over and over and over again and this one trial that we
have is just one of the possible outcomes and we need to look at where the
actual efficacy lies and it'll be in some range that we can simulate around
this one this one study that we've done. So let's first have a look at what risk
is and you see there in equation one it's just a number of positive outcomes
divided by the total in the group. Now we've got to talk about what a positive
outcome is and we say positive outcome but it doesn't sentimentally have to be
positive. The outcome can be quite negative and in this instance it might
be well develop the disease and certainly that's not positive but we just
use this term that's the positive outcome that the outcome that we are
interested in and investigating. So if we have a bunch of participants in a
study a certain number of them will develop this positive outcome the
outcome that we're interested in as a set which might be quite a negative thing
but if we just take that ratio that fraction the number of positive outcomes
divided by the total number in the group that is the risk. Now if we've got two
groups one group for instance received a placebo intervention and one group
received a treatment intervention we can just look at this difference in the
risk between the two. So we'll calculate risk as per equation one for both of
them and we just take the difference so the risk in the control minus the risk
in the treatment and what we're assuming here is that the risk in the treatment
will be lower because the other name for risk difference is absolute risk
reduction ARR absolute risk reduction that's just the difference in the risk
and that's a very good way to express a difference in risk between a control
group receiving the placebo and the treatment group getting this active
intervention. So just that difference you've just got to just watch out if the
risk in the treatment ends up being higher than the risk in the control of
course then we cannot talk about absolute risk reduction or we still can't talk
about absolute risk reduction we just got to say that being in the placebo
group gives us a reduction in risk for this positive outcome that we're
talking about. You see there the number needed to treat that is just an equation
three there we're not going to discuss it I've just put that in for you so what
we really want to do is talk about relative risk. You'll see ARR risk ratio
relative risk that is the fraction of the risk of the intervention over the
risk of the control so we worked out the risk in both groups very simple
calculations the positive divided by the total the positive divided by the total
and for these two we'll just we'll just take the ratio. Now what we're hoping
for you of course is that the risk the positive outcomes that fraction will be
lower in the intervention or the treatment group than in the control group
and if that is so this fraction of course will be less than one and if it's
less than one it means the risk is lowered by being in the intervention or
treatment group. So that's when we express this idea of efficacy so let's
imagine here in this piecewise defined function on the top row here for
efficacy that the risk in the treatment group is lower than the risk in the
control group that it was good to develop this because fewer people
fraction wise for the individual groups was lower if you were in the treatment
group than in the control group. That means this relative risk will be less
than one it'll be a fraction of one and what we do is we subtract that relative
risk from one so one minus the relative risk and that gives us the efficacy. Now
I've put the second part in here but we really don't use the second part I just
want it's just to keep your mind or to to simulate your stimulate your mind a
little bit. Imagine that the risk in the treatment was higher then we can't really
talk about efficacy anymore and as much as if this positive outcome was a
negative thing and we want this treatment to lower that risk but now it's
going to increase that risk so we just say relative risk minus one but I warn
you there then we can't really talk about efficacy anymore the efficacy is
really just for that first line one minus the relative risk. So let's look at
some coding examples so we're going to simulate a study we're taking 41,100
people in our study which is when these vaccine trials were developed what is
the power we need to see how many people need to be in there so that we
reach a sufficient power to find the significant difference between the two.
So we say here in our control group there were 20,500 people and in our
treatment group there were 20,600 people and we're saying in this trial
350 people in the control group develop the positive outcome so this is just
thumbs up numbers not from a specific trial and 115 in the treatment group
develop the positive outcome so in the case of a vaccine we have 350 people in
the control group they just received a placebo they developed the disease and
only 115 in the treatment group who got the active vaccine developed the positive
outcome which is developing the disease so we're just saving that also as some
computer variables so we've got a underscore control and a underscore
treatment and if we just divide those 350 divided by 115 that's not something
that we would express but just for interstate then there are three times
more positive cases in the control group than the treatment group now there is no
denominator in here so if I had lots more people in the placebo group then
in the treatment group that value was going to change so that's not a valid
expression really of what is happening here it's just expressing in this nearly
equal groups that we had there were three times more positive cases in the
control group what we're interested though is is the risk so let's see what
the risk in the control group is which I'm going to call risk underscore control
here so that's a that's the control how many got the disease divided by how many
was in the control group so that's going to be the 350 divided by 20,500 and we
see a value of 0.017 now what you would commonly see is this multiplied by a
thousand so you can say that the risk of developing the disease would be if we
multiply that by a thousand the one two three that'll be 17 people per thousand
people so you'll always see that per thousand per ten thousand per hundred
thousand depending on what makes sense now let's do the same for the treatment
group so that's the a underscore treatment that's how many got the disease in
the treatment group and divided by how many there were that's just the risk and
we see a much lower risk here of 0.005 so there'll be five and a half people per
thousand people develop the disease was it the risk then of developing the
disease and now we're just going to do the relative risk so it's the risk of
the treatment of the risk of the control and now we see it's 0.32 multiplied by
100 that's about that's 32.7% so we want to express efficacy though so we're
going to subtract it from one so one minus that one minus the relative risk
and we get the efficacy 67% so we can say the efficacy of this of this vaccine
was 67% and that is how much it lowered the risk really that is what we're
expressing but as I said before that is just one study we did and if we started
a week later we would have had other people in our study if we could do this
over and over again we would get different results every time so this one
result this one efficacy that we found this is one of many possible ones and
what we are interested in is not only this 41,000 100 people in our study we
want to infer these results because it's just a sample on the larger
population so what is the true efficacy in the population as a whole because
eventually we want to inoculate everyone so we need to express a confidence
interval around this efficacy and how do we go about that you know so in
different papers you'll see different methods of doing this there are different
equations for doing this cloper Pearson there's some other ways of doing this as
well but what we're going to do here is something that I like to do and that is
just to do resampling from the results that we found and in that way we're going
to build up simulate a bunch we're going to do a thousand as if we're doing our
study a thousand times over that gives us a distribution of poor possible
efficacies and we can then calculate a 95% confidence interval now remember
what confidence interval means maybe I should keep quiet now when we get to
confidence intervals when we've calculated the confidence intervals I'll
just remind you exactly what that means so here in R we've created a little
function I'm going to call it simulate underscore group it is a function it
takes two parameters n and p now what we're going to do is create this local
variable inside of the function it doesn't exist in the global space so it's
just internal to our function I'm using the our unit function random uniform so
we're going to draw a random number from a uniform distribution a uniform
distribution remember is that every element in the sample space of of this
distribution has an equal likelihood of being chosen at every time we run the
experiment so the random uniform is going to draw from zero to one in that
interval on that interval zero to one it just draws a random value so it will
then throw that value back in the bin so that the next time around we do it that
number is as possible to draw that number again but every value from zero to
one has an equal likelihood of being chosen a uniform distribution it's not
bell shape that certain values are more likely to be chosen at random it's
uniform and now what we're going to do is we're going to look at this number that
is chosen and we're just going to sum them up if that value is less than p the
probability now that p that we're talking about here is actually the
risk remember there were a certain number of people who got the disease
inside of that sample of people and if you think about that that the risk that
is if we do that division the number got positive divided by how many there were
that's in essence a probability of this p that we're talking about here in our
function the parameter that we've called p so we're saying we're going to
simulate this and we're going to say that random person we're just
simulating this random person they get this random value and if that value is
less than this p p value now I'm not talking about a statistical p value not
the famous p value I'm just saying this risk if that was smaller than that when
then we're going to start summing them up and that's a simulation because anyone
can get from from 0 to 1 and this value that was chosen there and we only sum
them up we only sum it up when it is less than the numbers that are come out
less than this p value the risk in action in actual fact and what we're going
to return is this k divided by n the n that we supplied to the function the
sample size so let's let's look at that so I'm storing p now as in this instance
we're going to take the risk in the treatment group so the number got
positive and divided by the total number they were that's our p and now we're
going to run a single simulation so we're just going to say n treatment p and
we just run that and now we have not seeded the seed of random number generator
here so every time you run this code you're going to get a different value but
in this instance I got 0.0055 now we're going to use less comprehension and
you'll see early on this notebook I just I just loaded this comprehend R package
because it contains this function to VEC and it's going to allow us to do less
comprehension on this instance vector comprehension so I'm just going to
simulate this thousand values all in one go so that I just have this vector of a
thousand possible instances I'm going to store that as t so we're just going to
simulate this risk in actual fact over and over and over and over again so
sometimes the value is going to be more than p and it won't be summed and
sometimes it's less than p and it will be summed from what we've done way up
there so if we do that we get these thousand values and we can draw the
sconal density estimate plot and it shows us this distribution of risks
simulated risks there we go for these thousand times as if we could do the
study a thousand times over and there you see the distribution of risk a lot of
them here by 0.05 just over that open of 0.053 there abouts 4 and that was
just simulating that over and over again now one way that we can express this
sort of range of values the measures of dispersion would be standard error and
what we've done here is just to take the standard error that's the standard
deviation of t in this instance and we can see it there and because we've got
this distribution now we can we can calculate the from all these values
these t values we can calculate these cutoff values so for that I'm going to
use the quantile function and I'm just passing that 1000 values to it and I'm
saying calculate for us these intervals that will be 5% cutoff at the bottom
95% cutoff at the top so if you look at this basically it's going to cut
off the bottom 5% and cut off the top 5% and that gives us a 90% confidence
interval then and the values within this thousand values of ours that gave us
that was 0.00475 to 0.0064 so then we're saying a 90% confidence interval
around this around this risk of ours the mean risk was going to be these values
so you're not necessarily interested in this single one we want the relative
risk so we're going to create another little equation here another function I
should say and it's just going to do what we've done before twice for the
control group and for the treatment group this time so that we can have this
efficacy as 1 minus the relative risk risk 2 that's going to be the treatment
divided by risk 1 which is going to be the control so we've got to pass four
parameters there so the p-value that we are going to ask for it to count below
as the p1 will be the controls risk and the p2 will be the treatment arms risk
and then we just simulate that once and it'll give us back one possible
efficacy 65.9% now again using this two-vec function I'm going to create
this vector of a thousand efficacies all in one go calling this function of our
simulate trial and the simulate trial remember it calls the simulate underscore
group function twice one for each of these two groups of ours and if we plot
the kernel density estimate there we see that we have this range of values
possible values we just simulated so we've resampled based on this finding
that we had for this specific study and then we see the mean efficacy of the
1000 simulator trials was 0.67 our actual one was also 0.67 that's where it's
going to work out so if we want a 90% confidence interval for that we just
pass those thousand values to the quantile function and we set a probability
cut off the bottom 5% the top 5% what were the values within T2 which is where
we saved a thousand values would be 60.8 to 72.7 so we can say the
efficacy of this study for this drug or this vaccine was 67% 90 or 90%
confidence intervals 60 to 72 or about 61% to about 73% so that's 90% confidence
intervals and now let me just remind you what confidence intervals is we're not
saying that we are 90% confident that in the globe as a whole if we gave it to
everyone and that we are 90 it's not to say that we're 90% sure that the true
efficacy in the world population as a whole will be this no that's not what
it means it means if we ran the study 100 times over just imagine what that
would cost now long that would take but if we ran it a hundred times over every
time we're going to get slightly different confidence intervals in 90% of
those the true population will be true population efficacy will be within the
confidence intervals that we set so we're not saying that's true for the
specific one is if we could do it hundred times over in 90 of them 90 of
them will capture within its bounds the true population efficacy now that we've
done that let's go and see this trial that was done in South Africa with
AstraZeneca trial and now this trial I'm going to warn you I mean from the time
of this recording it's just on as a available the pre-printed was not not
accepted by a journal yet not peer reviewed yet and on the space on the
evidence of this very small study the the vaccine was withdrawn from South
Africa so there was about a million doses available this was the first
doses of any vaccine to land in South Africa it was ready to be distributed
amongst health care workers and it got pulled on the strength of the study now
the study has more than one component so what we're going to look at is just a
clinical side of it looking at the relative risk and the efficacy but it
was also about it was about more than that there was part of the analysis was
also on the neutralizing antibodies and whether they could were effective against
the variant that's prevalent within South Africa so it's not just based on
this but I want to show you what the what relative risk does in efficacy what
it would look like at least the uncertainty in the value when we're
dealing with a small trial and how difficult it becomes in a small trial
where the risk is relatively low so let's look at that so you can click on
the link there to find the pre-print of this article and there were some
important points so the primary endpoint and I've just listed them here the
primary endpoint was this efficacy of confirmed symptomatic COVID-19 more than
14 days after the second dose so waited 14 days after the second dose then start
looking at whether people develop confirmed symptomatic COVID so the
primary for the primary efficacy analysis only per perperatical seronegative
participants were included and the vex vaccine efficacy VE was calculated as 1
minus the relative risk and 95% confidence intervals were calculated
using the clopper Pearson exact method as reported so that's not what we're doing
we are using resampling which is what I like to do there's a bunch of these
tests and they have their strengths and weaknesses and debate about you know
whether they work or not and when they should be used and when not my feeling
on the matter use use resampling so whether a thousand and ten participants
received vaccine and a thousand and eleven received placebo and in the end
there was a lot of exclusions you can read the papers to why in the end though
remember our simulated study before had over 40,000 people in them 20,000 more
than 20,000 each arm yeah there was only 715 in the vaccine group there was
analyzed and 750 vaccine and 717 in the placebo group so very small now and
other problems with the trial and I don't say that's problems the trial does
correctly done is this we want to infer that to a larger population the
population out there and of course the participants in the study were not
representative of the population as a whole it was only representative of
certain people in the population because the median age was very young was only
31 years 56 and a half percent were male and then there was a racial
distribution as well all 42 endpoint cases were graded as either mild or
moderate so there were no severe cases following this trial so even in the
placebo group there was no severe cases and we can see in the vaccine group
15 mild and 4 moderate and then 17 mild and 6 moderate so there are no cases of
severe disease or hospitalization in either arm so that makes it very
difficult because half of these people receive placebo to infer the results to
the larger population so let's just see how they you know if we do the relative
risk and we look specifically at the uncertainty around the relative risk
that's what this is all about so there was 717 in the control group 750 in the
treatment group 17 plus 6 that's the mild plus moderate got the disease in the
control group and 15 plus 4 that's in the treatment group so we're gonna work
out the risk in the control group which is just that very simple ratio and the
risk in the treatment group so that we can express the relative risk and the
relative risk as you can see there that was lower than one so we subtracted
from one and we get the efficacy and that was the headline it was only 21%
effective only 21% effective and of course mostly you'll see that we're
looking for at least 50% efficacy in these but here comes the problem we need
to express our uncertainty in this 21% efficacy and so again we're going to
create our two functions the one that just simulates again from a random
uniform distribution just as we did before only counting those that was
lower than this risk value and then we're going to simulate it at the two
risks and we express the efficacy again as one minus the risk two over risk one
so risk of the treatment divided by risk of the control group and our P values
again remember that just taken from the outcome of this actual study the two
risks and then we're going to simulate it and I've run a simulation just this
once and we get a negative value we get a negative value and now this becomes
very difficult to interpret and let me show you why because now we're going to
simulate it a thousand times using this two-vec function so we can do list or
vector comprehension so in one go we get our thousand values and here I've used
plotly and not the inbuilt r plotting so we can see here this distribution around
the around the efficacy and you can see how it tails off below zero now how do
we interpret that so I leave that for you in the comments to interpret that
because if you think about it we're actually back in the real or realm of
the vaccine actually increasing the risk okay and that's the way that their
values are going to come out and you can see this bump here right at the top it
is at about about 21, 22, 23 percent the efficacy and what we
interested now is the 95% confidence intervals so we said the efficacy of
this study of the AstraZeneca vaccine was only 21 percent and now you see the
95% confidence intervals around that from negative 50% to about 59% so it's
quite possible that the efficacy of this efficacy out in the population just
based on the study that the efficacy of AstraZeneca vaccine out in the
population is somewhere between there so this is bizarre on this side of course
and as I say leave your thoughts in the comment what this negative values would
really be but this is we're still within the 95% confidence intervals almost 60%
efficacy of the AstraZeneca so very difficult to make decisions based on a
small study like this where our risk is very low the risk was very low for
someone to develop the disease both in the placebo arm and in the treatment arm
and the efficacy they've the two risks were very close to each other meaning
the efficacy was only 21% because these values are so small and we simulate a
thousand of these when we express our uncertainty in this 21% you see that
this uncertainty is quite big and as I say this the idea behind the study was
not only looking at this to make the decision to withdraw the use of the
vaccine that's AstraZeneca vaccine in South Africa because a part of the study
was also about neutralizing antibodies etc there's a whole other parts to that
but see how difficult it is or how difficult it can be if you've got
relatively small sample sizes and the risk is also small then you are going to
struggle to make a decision because your uncertainty in your efficacy is not
going to be very good there's going to be a wide confidence interval in the
efficacy so I hope this was interesting for you leave some comments down below
remember to like the video you can read this these notebooks here on our pubs
or follow the link down below to download the RMD files the our markdown files if
you've got our studio you can just import that and you can play around with
these values maybe simulate some more draw some pretty graphs etc and I hope
this really helped you to understand the idea a very relevant example of
understanding relative risk and efficacy
you