So what I'm going to do now is show you something beautiful, some beautiful mathematics.
We can't do much in physics or we can't start this discussion properly
as far as the gradients and Hamiltonians are concerned
if we don't understand the concept of the minimum.
Something is at a minimum and that is how nature decides what to do.
Nature decides that the shortest distance between two points
in a clean space is going to be a straight line.
How does it decide that?
There must be something underlying this decision in nature.
It's the concept of the minimum and you've got to understand it
through the concept of the calculus of variations.
So how do we do that?
There's going to be many boards and I'll have to wipe the board in between.
Let's just have a look at this.
I have the XY plane and I have two points which is a starting point
and a final point and there's various paths I can take through this.
So you could in space, there's my X and there's my Y.
I'm going to go from one point to the other point on some path.
You can imagine I can go to Andromeda Galaxy and back
and there will still be one path if Andromeda is there
at least if I could just go in a two dimensional plane.
There is many lines I can take between this
but I want the shortest possible distance between those two.
The shortest possible distance.
Now one way I can measure this, any of the paths
that I can possibly choose is just to divide it into tiny little segments
of say a specific length delta S.
So let's blow that up a little bit.
If I were to blow that up it's almost going to be a straight line.
Most lecturers would skip this but then go straight to the integral
but this is good so this is going to be this arc length.
It has a length but it will have from that point to that point
a delta Y and a delta X.
So the length of delta S is very nearly going to be what?
Well the square root of that per se, this is Pythagorean theorem.
So that will be delta X squared plus delta Y squared.
Very beautiful and we know if I can let delta X approach
the limit take the limit as this approaches zero,
this is going to become smaller, this line segment will become shorter
and right in the end I'm going to have this differential tiny little distance dS
which is going to be the square root of dx squared plus dy squared.
We can all see that and I can rewrite this.
Just want to show you how nice you can rewrite it of course.
You're going to say dS is going to equal the square root of,
I can take a dx squared out which will leave me one plus dy squared over dx squared.
It's beautiful.
I've just taken this out as a common factor.
If I were to multiply this back in there of course I'm going to line it back up there.
In other words dS I can write as the square root of one plus,
let's just call it Y prime, Y with respect to x squared
and that's very ugly, I should do that.
You can see as the whole it's dy squared and dx squared.
So that and I'm just calling it Y prime dx.
That's what I'm doing.
So that will be the length of an infinitesimally small little line segment there.
I've zoomed in so much that it actually is a straight line so I go from approximate to absolutely equal to
and that is in the limit as delta X goes to zero.
And what can I do?
How do we do integration if I have to just sum all of these together?
I take the integral of that.
So if I were to take the integral of both sides, what am I left with?
S, the total distance of this arc, so this is just a line integral,
is going to be this definite integral and going from x1 to x1 to x2
of the square root of 1 plus Y prime squared dx.
So there's my line integral.
And this is setting up distance, but this needn't be distance.
I can set up many things in physics.
I might want to know what the shortest time is.
So there's going to be some path chosen that represents the shortest time.
I can have many things in here.
I can have not just distance but shape what would be the minimum surface area of something.
And I can do that by just setting up an equation for surface area.
So what we do in calculation of various calculations of variations is
we're just going to call this I, that is this group for not only length
but surface area, time, anything.
It's going to be something that I can now plot on a,
so there's needn't be distance and distance.
We can have something else.
But it's going to go from some initial point which I'll call x sub 1
and some final point which I'll call x sub 2.
Just to refer to the fact that there's something on one of the axes
of some function and if I look at this function very carefully
it's actually a function of x, y and y prime with respect to that axis.
So it's from one point to another point on that axis.
So it's the f of x, y and y prime.
Now there's no x in there but that one might as well have been x to the power 0.
So there is and there's no y, just a normal y in there
but that might also have been y to the power 0.
In effect this is a distance one so there was no x and y in there
but there could be.
So there's a function of x, y and y prime.
So at any time we can set this up.
It's called a functional.
This is called a functional that I'm going to do something
and it's going to give me some scale of value.
And I'll clean the board and we're going to use this concept
to prove to you that in the Euclidean space,
and it's not some funny space, it's flat space,
that the shortest distance between that point and that point
is going to be a straight line, we're going to develop this
to prove that that is indeed so and through doing that
hopefully I'll show you that that is what nature does
and that's what we can do.
We're going to use the calculus of variation
to show that there is something in here that is a minimum distance
or a minimum time or a minimum surface area
and that is what nature chooses.
I'm going to clean the board and we'll carry on.
The board is clean, let's have a look.
So there we go.
Now imagine, I'm going to construct something.
So imagine I knew the answer.
The equation for that curve between the two points
which is the minimum.
Imagine I knew that and that solution was the y of x,
small y of x.
Now let's construct another function,
we'll call it capital y of x,
and that's going to include this small y of x
plus some constant multiple of a second function
called eta of x,
as most textbooks will do it this way.
And I'm going to pause the video here
and just insert another video I made
which is a screencast of how this is actually the absolute truth.
Before I do that I just want to make two things abundantly clear
and we're going to set this up.
This is like a magician setting up something specifically
so that it works out for him or her.
And we're going to set this situation up
so that it does work for us.
So this is my one point and my other point
and we all know intuitively this is going to end up being a straight line
but what if it isn't?
So I have this curve there
and right at this x sub 1
and right at this x sub 2
I'm going to choose another curve
and that's my curve,
eta of x
such that at these points x1 and x2
it has a y value of 0
and I can choose many of these
just by changing this constant multiple eta.
If eta is 1 this would be one curve
if eta is 1.5 it will be another curve
if eta is negative 3 this would be another curve
and this was my two answer which is a secret up till now
but imagine I knew what it was
and if I just add this at every point I just add these two
then I was going to have something like this
but you can imagine this capital Y of x
is just these two additives
but you imagine they are multiple
for every eta of x
I can choose any constant
which will give me an infinite number of these little curves
which means added to the real answer
I can get many others
and remember single variable
just normal variable calculus
if I just had a curve
if I had a curve
and I wanted to know the minimum of the maximum
well all these extreme points
extreme would be at spots where the derivative
the first derivative was going to be 0
that is a minimum or maximum
and I knew it was a minimum
if I took the second derivative
and if that answer was at that point was larger than 0
I knew that to be a minimum
and that's the same thing we're going to do to this
we want a minimum
the derivative of this
and set it equal to 0
remember this is how I set up my distance
I had s equals
a different integral from x1 to x2
of the square root of 1 plus y prime squared dx
that was my distance
I want to take the derivative of that
and I want to set it equal to 0
and if I do that
I'm going to get to the minimum point
and that's what we want
something that this line falls exactly on top of that line
because if I do that
there will be some minimum
and that will be the two result that I get there
I'm ahead of myself
so this is what we set up
I'm going to pause the video here
and insert that a little bit
just to show you that this is an actual fact
you can set this up
in many ways you can set this up
this is not some trickery here that is mathematically unsound
it's very sound
you can set this up and I'll show you in the video
so here we go
let me show you
I want to construct this capital Y of x
in terms of small y of x
plus some other function eta of x
and at eta of x I want to be able to multiply by some constant
so I've set some things up here
let's have a look at them
let's just take some of these away
and let's just bring them back
one by one
just that this is my y of x
I've made it a straight line
it needn't be a straight line
and here's my eta of x
and I'm just drawing in these two straight lines
just to note that I've constructed eta x
in this instance it is something here
there we go
there's my epsilon
which I've called in here
and it's this
minus x minus 4 squared plus 1
I'll show you now why I put the n in there
so what I'm saying is
one thing
I've got to construct this so that
at x1 and x2
which is this spot here
and that spot there
I want that to correspond
here to the same values
that's why I've got the two straight lines
and the fact that
the y value for eta of x
down here has got to be 0
and 0 at both points
that's the way I want to set this up
so what I have now
is the capital Y of x
and the capital Y of x
between x1 and x2
has got to be the addition of these two
and this is what we have right up here
this is this green
note though
that because eta of x is 0
at this point I'm not adding anything to
small y of x
and at that point I'm not adding anything to
at these two curves
at every point on the x axis
between x1 and x2
if I added this value to that value
I was going to get that top value
that's what I'm saying
but look at this if I put eta in front of it
which here I've called n
it doesn't matter what size I make
eta
it's just some constant multiple
what epsilon I mean
my n here is epsilon
sorry for that
this value I make epsilon
it's a constant multiple
it is a constant multiple
of eta of x
and these points still
correspond to
my little y of x
and my little y of x there
so it doesn't matter
I now have this
almost well I can say
indefinite number of capital Y of x
every time that I change
epsilon
I'm going to have a different capital Y of x
look at the green curve
there are so many of them
look how many of them
there are
that means to get from
1.1
to .2
there are many many
paths that I can take
and I've got to find the
shortest one basically
that's why I'm setting up this problem
I want some minimum value
and the problem I'm going to deal with
obviously minimum arc length
between these two points
but just to show you
that I can construct
this capital Y of x
in the manner that I've done on the board
and it makes absolute sense
and you can just see it
beautifully in this illustration
good I hope you enjoyed that
now this is beautiful mathematics
stay with me you'll see where this is going
so what we're suggesting
and remember that was
my equation and I'm going to take the derivative
of that and set it equal to 0
that will give me the minimum value
that's all we're going to do
but I don't have this anymore
I've changed it
that refers to what I had in me
the real answer was going to come from that
was going to come from that
the real distance was going to have
some equation to it
some value to it
that in the actual fact that now
is a new function
in x capital Y
in capital Y prime
that is what I have now
so by constructing this addition
I've changed it from
x small y small y prime
to x large y y prime
so
some suggestion of this
will be remember that was
the square root of 1 plus y square
y prime squared
but if I do this to it
I'm going to have
this as my f of x
I have this
and I'm going to just do
some preliminary work
and you'll see shortly why I'm doing this preliminary work
if I
if I had this
function
imagine let me just write it out
y of x
equals the y of x
plus
epsilon eta of x
what if I
were to take the derivative
of this with respect to this constant
can you take a derivative with respect
of constant of course you can because
what is 4
other than 4x to the power
if I were to take the derivative with respect
to x
I can still take the derivative here
with respect to x
that's probably not the best way
to explain it
let me rather do this
can I say
d y
capital Y of x
d epsilon
can I say that
now I don't necessarily want to do that
it's going to be a bit difficult
let's do the partial derivative
partial derivative with respect
to that constant
appear there
so that's going to equal 0
and
as I said I could have written this
with an x to the power 0
and what you can see this as
basically I suppose
is just the product of two functions
so I can take the derivative of this
times that
and this times the derivative of that
so I can actually have the
d epsilon
eta x
plus eta times
d
del
whichever way you want to pronounce it
of
eta x
so what are we going to have here
we're going to have the fact that
that's 0
that is 1
so we will
definitely have that
so that will be the eta of x
and there's no eta in there
so the partial derivative
of that with respect to epsilon
sorry is 0 0
times epsilon is 0
so the derivative of capital Y of x
with respect to epsilon is just
eta of x
let's take y prime
of x
well it's just going to be that
prime
and you can put the examples in here
and just show it to yourself
and what is going to happen here
well it's with respect to
x that I'm taking
that I'm taking this derivative
that is a function of x
so this is very easy this is going to be
epsilon eta prime
of x
in what way to happen if I took the
partial derivative of y prime
with respect to
epsilon
there's definitely a partial derivative
there's nothing in there that's going to be a 0
exactly the same thing has happened there
it's going to happen here
so we're just going to have eta prime of x
so that's all we're going to have
so these are the two equations
some preliminary work
I probably shouldn't have bought it in here
because you wonder why is he doing this
why is he doing this
let's clean the board and we'll carry on
let's carry on
now remember this thing
back I had my equation
which was this 1 plus y prime
square root of that
what were to happen if I
took the derivative of this
of this function
well I would have had to use the chain rule
so when I had the f of
x, y and y prime
I was going to have to use the chain rule
nothing changes if I have
this
if I have that function I'm also going to
have the chain rule
but because I have changed this
into that
I have a new
function i
which I now want to make a function
of epsilon
that is now going to be
x of 1 to x of 2
of the f of x
capital Y
capital Y prime dx
I have now changed
when I went from
my previous solution to this solution
I have now made this
a function of
eta because I could get
many y of x's
by simply just
changing this constant
so this now becomes a constant
of this function
and if I wanted to take the derivative
of this
if I wanted to take the derivative
of this with respect to
epsilon
why did I say eta all the time
you know what I mean when I write this
when I write this with respect to
with respect to epsilon
what is going to happen
now that is why I chose things
very carefully I also want to
do it at a point
where epsilon equals
0 and that's why I set things up
so remember when I showed you
on the screencast
that's why I chose things one of the reasons
and there's another reason there's sales
I wanted to because of that equals
0 then
my large y of x
this one will be exactly equal
to this one they'll fall on top of each other
and I'll have my solution
and another thing is
remember when I took the derivative
when f hat is 0
I have a minimum
so this is the secret
to this whole thing I'm going to take the derivative
so I've changed it to a function of eta
I'm going to take the derivative
with respect to eta exactly where eta
is 0
and if I set it equal to 0
that is the calculation
the calculus of variations
now just as we had
here I would have had to use the chain rule
let's use the chain rule
of this because if I
take the derivative of this
it's actually this
if I take the derivative of
I with respect to eta
it's the same as doing my integral
and taking the derivative of this inside
remember your first year calculus
so what we're saying here
they're just going to equal
the different integral going from this to that
and I'll have to apply the chain rule
so I'm actually going to have
d i f
d i small
let's do that
d i f d i capital Y times
del Y
del
epsilon plus
we must not make a mistake here
and I'm going to have f with respect to
y prime times
y prime
over epsilon
all of that
dx
so don't get confused here this is just the chain rule
of a function
of any function
remember if you were to take the chain rule
of something if you would take the first derivative
of something as simple as this
it would be very easy to do
this was going to be to the power half
you bring the half forward
and that becomes negative of half
the derivative of the inside function as well
which is going to be 2y prime
so it's easy to do
for any function f of x y
and y prime
I was going to use the chain rule
so yeah I'm also going to use the chain rule
nothing different and that's exactly
what I have there
and remember just the board before
I did this
and I did this so I know
what this is this was
remember what this was
or that was this
eta of x
remember that
rewind and you'll see and what was this
it was
eta prime of x
okay
so that works for me
and this has got to equal 0
because if I set it equal to 0
then I have a minimum
okay we know where it was
it's going to be an extreme
but let's call it a minimum for now
because that is exactly what it is
okay so we are there
what I want you to realize is one thing
I can do this
as integration by parts
remember the integration by parts
I just have to decide which one is u
and which one is v prime
and that's very easy to do
let's choose my v prime
equal to this
eta prime of x
that makes my v equal
to the prime eta of x
and if this was that
then that must mean
this one is u
by if
by capital Y prime
and that makes my u prime the d dx
of
by if
by y prime
now I can just simply do
integration by parts
remember that would be this times that
minus
the integral
of this one times that one
remember integration by parts
but I want to show you something
very specific here as well
and that's why I set things up
I was a magician and I set things up that they were
out specifically for me
I said I want to do this
around a point where eta equals 0
and what's going to happen
when eta equals 0
capital Y of x
and small y of x are going to be
exactly the same thing
they're going to be exactly the same thing
so what we're going to have
is the following so remember when I have
the integral
of the sum of two functions
I can just do them separately
so here I'm going to have
x sub 1 to x sub 2
of del f
del y
I'm making it a small y now because I'm setting
things up way epsilon equals
0 so then I will have
capital and lowercase
y of x is being exactly
the same times the eta
of x
del x
now for this side
I'm going to do this integration by parts
so it's u times v so it's d
these two so it's del f
del y prime times
eta
of x
from x sub 1 to x sub 2
minus
the integral of
going from x sub 1 to x sub 2
of these two
so it's
d dx of
del f
del y prime
eta
what was that
eta of x
dx and that's going to equal 0
I hope you can still see that
now remember also when I did here
I let these two
points be exactly the same
so if I were to plug
those into there
I was going to get 0
so this whole turn disappears
this whole turn disappears
and what am I left with
this integral
minus this integral
is going to equal 0 I can put them all together
in the same integral because this is
the difference between two functions
and I can take
these two out
is a common factor
and what am I going to be left with
going from x sub 1 to x sub 2
of what
well we're going to have
del f del y
minus
the dx of
del f
del y prime
all of that times
the eta of x
all of that dx is going to equal
and that low and behold
is the way we were trying to get this
is a thing of beauty
now I want to set this up
for any
eta of x
any eta of x
because for a different integral
to equal 0 that means this
inner part
this integrand has got to be 0
but I want it to be for any
function of 0 so
arbitrary function of eta
and so if that can't be 0
it's being multiplied by this
this has got to equal 0
and that
is the Euler
Lagrange function
and it states the following
that del f
del y
minus
the dx
of del f
del y prime
equals 0
there we are
that is the thing of beauty
and remember when my f was this
this was my f of xy and y prime
if I were to take the derivative
of this with respect to y
and I took the derivative
of this with respect to y prime
and then the derivative
of that
equal to 0 I was going to get
the answer
for the shortest distance between those two points
but I generalised it as I
so it might be the shortest time
it might be the shortest surface area
I can use the Euler Lagrange equation
to set up many physical
problems
if I can just through my physical problem
develop this
and we'll look at examples
in the next video I might just show you
how this distance between two points is a straight line
by solving
this Euler Lagrange
but this Euler Lagrange equation
right here is absolutely a
thing of beauty
and we set it up right from here
right from the start
we use the simple fact that the first derivative
if you set it to 0 you are going to get an extreme point
and that extreme point
is going to be a minimum
value for you
it's going to work out in this instance to be a minimum
instead of an extreme point
and you're going to land up
with this
this is a real
true a thing of mathematical
beauty
now
let me prove to you that the
shortest distance between two points on the Euclidean surface
is just a straight line
nature will always choose
a straight line
so you'll remember my equation for
using integration a line integral
for the length of
any arc
is that
this is my Euler Lagrange equation
so let's just do that
this is my F
this is my function F
function of x, y and y prime
let's get
iF times y
what is that going to equal
of this this bit well
there's no y in there so this is going to be 0
that was a simple one
y prime
well there's a y prime in there
so I better do this properly and I've got to do it
we said it before
I've got to do it
by
the following method
so what is that going to be
I'm going to bring the half forward so that was going to be a half
times
again we
we're still going to have this
squared to the power negative
for half and then I still have to multiply
by the inner
which is going to be 2 times y prime
that's really firstly a calculus
except that this is a partial derivative
but there is y prime in there
so these two are going to go
so what am I left with
I'm left with y prime over
the square root of 1 plus y prime
squared
that's what I'm left with
and so
they are left with 0 so I have
minus
dvx of
that which is now
just this
y prime over the
square root of 1 plus y prime
squared is going to equal
which I can multiply both sides
by negative 1 so this will disappear
simply
when is the derivative of
any function equal to 0
when that function is a constant
isn't it so all of this
is some constant
in other words
y prime equals
some constant times the square root of
1 plus y prime
squared
I can square both sides
if I square both sides
I get rid of this
and I square my constant
which leaves me with another constant
I can multiply this constant in there
so I'm going to see
some constant plus some constant
I can bring this over to one side
which means y prime
I can get on its own
which is then going to leave me
with 1 minus this
squared
remember I squared this now
to get rid of that
and that is going to
still equal some constant
I'm going to divide this into that side
which is giving me another constant
and in the end I'm going to
take the square root of that so y prime
is going to be some constant
just run through that
I'll be fishing
but just do it for yourself
you'll notice very quickly
that y prime
is equal to some constant
when is the derivative, how can a function of x
y prime of x
how can that be a constant
well the only way that that can be
is if the y of x
equals ax
plus b
if you take the derivative of that
that would come forward
so that's just my constant a
there's no x in there so that falls away
and what is that in the equation of
a straight line
proof that the shortest distance
between any two points in euclidean
two dimensional euclidean plane
is a straight line
how did I solve that
I set up my
differential
here
which is my
differential there
and I used the calculation of
the calculus of variations
to set up the Lagrange-Waley equation
I used the Lagrange-Waley equation
and I proved that the shortest distance is there
so if I set something else
of the any physical system
I'll have to set up this function f
and if I can set that function
of f with its time
with its surface area
I can use the Lagrange-Waley equation
to always give me the minimum
that is why I can set up a physical system
where I can look at time
what will be the shortest time
I can set up the surface area
and the most famous one of those
is if you have two rings
one smaller, one larger
and you put them in some of this
bubbly soapy water
and you bring them out and you'll separate them
and that will form a very specific
pattern between those two
soapy bubble circles
and there's a reason why you choose that
because that will give you the minimum surface area
that whole surface area
of the soapy fluid material
between these two
you've got to make that a minimum
and minimum and you can do it for volume as well
why is this one a volume
a sphere
in nature it does that because
it is a minimum
and some minimum is chosen
and lastly from that
who will come in this fact
a plane
that has to roll down
what is going to be the shortest time
for the ball to roll down
is it going to be a path that goes straight down
or is it going to be one of these
one of these paths
that is called the brachistochrome
problem
brachy which means short chrome
referring to time, shortest time
there's a reason why this ball
will roll down
will get from there to there faster
on the ball rolling down that path
there's a reason for that because nature
can choose the minimum time
that's what nature does, it wants to choose the minimum time
to get from there to there
and that is why it will choose a specific path
that will be the shortest path
to get down there
you just have to work out
an f of x
for this problem
you