So I'm going to be talking about this interesting little system,
Erbit, that I and some friends have built.
Erbit is a clean slate full stack system.
So let me explain sort of briefly the problem that we're
solving here first, because this is a little different
from the problem that a usual language is solving.
So we have basically a coupling of kind of two interesting
problems here.
We have a very different kind of technical problem that we're
solving, and we also have a different human market need
that we're solving.
So let me go through both of those super quickly.
So the technical problem we're trying to solve here is
something I call a high level deterministic computer.
So that would be basically a computer whose entire life
cycle is defined by a single frozen function.
So it's really very functional.
Of course, a hardware VM, a CPU, is defined by a single
frozen function, which is the CPU function, which is very
frozen because it's on the chip.
But we'd actually like to define that at a layer at the same
level at which the programmer conceives the system.
So if we look at some kind of approximations to this that
exist in reality today, JavaScript and the Java VM, of
course, are high level definitions, but they're
defined only sort of for a transient system.
So here we're defining the whole life cycle of the
computer.
This is not just a memory image.
This is the whole machine, which is a single level store.
Lisp and small talk have these image-based systems that
come a little closer to this kind of approach.
I don't think people in practice usually use Lisp and
small talk actually as databases.
And they're not defined functionally in the same way.
But it's definitely in the image-based system tradition.
When you're using this thing, it basically feels like an
integrated interpreter OS and database, which is a very
kind of unusual feeling for a programming environment.
You might also ask what happens when a determinist to
computer hits an undecidable problem.
We'll get into that in a little bit.
One way of sort of defining this problem that I like to use
is an unusual versioning system that we use, which I
call Kelvin versioning.
So Kelvin versioning, you count down to absolute zero and
you count by integers.
So if you run out of numbers, you've made a mistake,
basically.
So absolute zero is absolutely frozen.
So Erbit, or at least the sort of the formal definition of
Erbit, which does fit on a t-shirt, is at five Kelvin,
which is like liquid helium, basically at the moment.
And we'll see that spec in a little bit.
Let's switch gears totally and talk about the human need that
this system is supposed to be solving.
We have this little problem in the computer world, which is
that the internet actually failed.
It succeeded very well as a digital modem.
It's a great digital modem.
It's entirely a client-server environment.
It is not a peer-to-peer network.
It's never going to be a peer-to-peer network.
And if you look at sort of the dream of the internet from
the 80s and 90s, it was a dream in which everyone on this
network would have their own server.
And things like what we do on Facebook today would be done
by protocols like SMTP.
Well, you can't introduce a new wide area protocol on the
internet today.
You can barely keep SMTP alive.
These systems were designed in the 70s.
The same thing for basically Linux, which is, in a sense,
I would say, layer seven of the internet.
It's the application layer.
If you're on the internet, you're either a Unix box or
you're pretending to be a Unix box.
You can't really say to my mother, hey, you should go out
and get an AWS box and put all your data on that and app
get installed, something.
That's just never basically going to fly.
And so we've kind of reconciled ourselves to those
sort of loss of this dream where people actually control
their own individual computing.
And instead, we've basically gone back and recreated the
Hayes modem protocol with HTTP.
And we've recreated AOL with Facebook.
And we're kind of stuck in this space.
So we have a big problem here.
And these systems aren't basically not fixable.
Well, there's a way to get out of a problem that isn't
fixable, which is to layer over it.
So the browser already did this on the client side.
Basically, you had these OS APIs.
And they're like, OK, we're going to build a new
application layer.
I guess browser people didn't realize that this is what
they were doing.
But it's certainly what they were doing.
We're going to build a new programming layer that is
isolated from the substrate under it that cannot call out
in any way, shape, or form.
And we're just going to program to that layer and not care
about the underlying OS.
And that actually kind of worked great.
So on the server side, basically, this
hasn't been done yet.
And I would say, basically, we don't know that people don't
want personal servers.
People ask them, you tell them what a personal server is.
And they say, yes, I want that.
We do know that they don't want Linux and internet
personal servers.
We do know that my mother is never going to run an open
Linux server on the internet.
So there's basically a real case to be made for saying, OK,
we need a new layer here.
If we sort of drill down a little bit and define the need,
the need is basically caused by the, essentially, the
obstacle to the universal personal server is just
administrative cost.
My mother is not a Linux is that thing.
So when you're looking at a problem and your problem is
administrative cost, it makes sense that a solution to this
problem is going to be technical simplicity.
Because basically, the difficulty of administering
the system tends to be roughly proportional to the number of
lines of code in it.
And if you haven't noticed, there's a lot of lines of
code in Ubuntu.
And so basically, the idea of building the browser for the
server side is sort of a problem that kind of makes sense
next to this problem of let's build a high-level
deterministic computer.
So OK, let's build it.
How do you define a one-function computer?
Well, you need, remember, we're defining both the network
and the OS here.
We're really defining a computing environment as if we
just stumbled on a planet that had chips and wires and no
software whatsoever, which is kind of fun.
And if you're going to define the way this works, you're
defining networking from scratch.
I find the simplest way to think about networking is to
imagine just basically a global party line.
So a packet is just a big integer blob that people put
out.
Everybody hears everyone else's packets.
And if you have the keys to decrypt those packets and make
them make sense, then you use them.
Then you can basically say to this global party line, hey,
we would like to actually optimize this.
And you get back to routing.
But routing is basically an optimization in Van Jacobsen
has this great term, a content-centric network, where
you're basically ignoring who sent you the packet doesn't
matter.
What matters is what's in the packet.
So that's sort of the network perspective on this.
From the sort of functional perspective, there's basically
two ways to define a one-function computer.
You can define it as a life cycle function, which is
where the state is a pure function of input history.
And remember, this is a frozen function.
This never changes.
You cannot upgrade this function.
Or you can define it as a transition function, where
basically you have an input event in an old state,
outcomes, a bunch of output actions in a new state.
These are really, in practice, basically turned into the
same thing.
In practice, essentially any life cycle function is going
to wind up spending most of its time as a transition
function, because you're certainly not going to
recompute the whole log every time you get a packet.
And one of the advantages of doing it the life cycle
function way is when you're basically building a system
where you have one frozen function which defines the
semantics of every computer in the world, you need to
basically break symmetry.
And you need to basically, when you're starting that up, you
need some startup packets.
You need some startup.
You need the load and operating system into your
function, essentially.
And so a life cycle function makes slightly more sense as a
way to define this.
Let me skip down for a second and talk about how you
implement these things.
Actually, implementing a sort of one function computer like
this is kind of very easy with the kind of substrates that
you have at the moment.
Event sourcing is basically this pattern.
It's usually not used for a general purpose computer, but
it's the same pattern.
You have low latency reliable logs are uniformly available.
Kafka isn't the greatest thing in the world, but it works fine.
Normal databases are defined in terms of the pend only
transaction log and an image snapshot.
So you're basically building this the same way a normal
database is built.
You're saying every packet is a transaction.
And it basically works great.
You can also do non-packet I.O. I mean, I like to think of an
abstract computer as just packets in, packets out.
But as you'll see, we want to serve web pages and so forth.
So basically, you can model even ordinary HDDB requests
as here's an event that's like you got a request.
Here's my action respond to this request.
So there's a great library LibUV, which is used by Node.js
that implements these patterns very nicely.
So it's super easy to do.
I mentioned decidability earlier.
That's kind of an interesting problem for a deterministic
computer or any kind of non-preemptive OS.
When you're building a non-preemptive system, basically
the decision of when to terminate a computation is
essentially a heuristic choice.
If that event is caused by a console, that heuristic choice
is very easy.
Just go until they hit Control C.
If it's a packet, that's a little harder.
You need to decide when to time that out.
There's a kind of nice duality between unreliable packet
networking and turn completeness.
And when you drop a packet because it's
spending too long, you're essentially detecting congestion
in the CPU.
And so that kind of makes a certain amount of sense.
Node.js has shown that you can actually do very useful
things with non-preemptive systems.
One of the most interesting problems in building a system
like this is you're going to have certain kinds of
non-determinism that you can't avoid.
Let's say I write an infinite loop.
I made a mistake.
I wrote an infinite loop.
I pressed Control C. One thing I really want there is a
stack trace.
So that stack trace is completely
non-deterministic information.
You can't get that into a deterministic way.
But all is not lost because basically the underlying C
code that actually implements this system sees that stack
trace, has that stack trace.
All it needs to do is basically inject that back in as a
deterministic event.
And so basically, you get an event that says, hey, I was
trying to do this packet, but it crashed.
And here's where it crashed.
And then you can write that to the user in the appropriate
way, and that actually works.
So if you replay that log, we've replayed 30 gigabyte logs
and wound up for the same bit for bit state.
If you replay that log, it will replay the error.
Essentially, it won't even bother with their
original transaction.
So this is not pieing the sky.
This is a working system.
This is clearly doable.
So probably a lot of Lisp fans in the audience, let's try
doing this in Lisp.
So it's actually easy to define a life cycle function in
Lisp.
You simply say, OK, the first event in the log is my
operating system.
And all the rest of the log, the cutter of the log, is the
rest of the event.
So run the operating system on the rest of the events.
You still have to write the function.
But OK, you've made progress.
And now, all we need is the one true Lisp.
So I think all Lisp needs is the one true Lisp.
There have been a lot of attempts to create the one
true Lisp.
I haven't really worked out.
In my view, that's basically a problem that goes back to
really the root of how we came up with this idea of
computing.
Because the Lambda Calculus is OK.
We're at LambdaConf.
I can't say bad things about Lambda Calculus.
But it was originally designed not as a means of
programming.
It was originally designed as basically a
metamathematical tool.
And people picked this up, and they found, hey, wow, this
thing that Church came up with actually works really well
for programming.
So you take that in one direction, and it becomes Lisp.
You take that in another direction, much more
mathematical, and it becomes Haskell.
And it's not like Lisp and Haskell are compatible in
any ways.
You're always basically taking Lambda, and you're growing
hair on it to make it a practical system.
And I would say that that comes from basically a very
deep conflict in the heart of Lambda, which is that it has
these features that are like symbols and variables and
scope that are features of a higher level language.
But if you want to use that as an axiomatic system, and we
just saw a talk on Shen which compiles to Lisp, if you want
to use that as an axiomatic system, basically, and put
the higher level language as something that is actually
loaded onto that axiomatic interpreter, then those things
are in the wrong place.
They're in the wrong layer.
And if you're going to build an axiomatic system like this,
you have just the demands on the precision of your
interpreter are just extremely high.
You want that to be just tiny and diamond perfect.
And you can't grow hair on it.
So in a way, basically, you sort of have no choice but to
invent a kind of different computational model at the
bottom end.
So this gives me a motivation to actually invent all this
crap.
We know that you should never invent anything, but
sometimes you have no choice.
So the bottom of the stack is this thing called knock.
It's a typeless, frozen, accommodator, interpreter,
non-LAMDA.
It's defined in 200 words.
It fits on a t-shirt.
Not wearing a t-shirt today, but I'll wear it tomorrow.
And I know, I know, it's bad choice.
On top of that is a hoon, which is a pure, strict type
functional language.
It compiles itself to knock.
This is type functional programming without category
theory.
We've heard from some people that they hate category
I've heard that somewhere, not sure.
Probably not in this room.
So you can see how if you have a compiler that compiles
itself to knock, then you can kind of bootstrap off of
this basic, essentially, bootloader.
On top of that, we have ARVO, which is a non-preemptive OS.
And yeah, we'll see.
So basically, what I've got to do here is just a really
lightning tour through these three systems.
Don't worry if there's, there might be a little bit of
stuff you don't understand, but just kind of sit back and
get an impression of the system.
All right, let's go into knock for a second.
So I sometimes call knock a functional assembly language.
You can program in knock, but there are no symbols or
anything, so you're typing numbers and doing tree
geometry by hand.
Very much like writing assembly language.
You could, but you wouldn't want to.
It's basically, it is a list, in a sense.
It's a list without any of these high level tools.
How do you get symbols out of a lisp?
Well, maybe it's not a lisp.
A key point, no cyclic data structures, no laziness, so
no infinite data structures.
You cannot knock as an interpreter, which cannot
create cycles.
I think that is basically very much the right choice in the
modern world.
No tracing garbage collectors.
Kind of nice.
Also, remember, this is a persistent system.
And if you look at persistent systems, any kind of
database, whether it's no SQL or a SQL, basically you'll see
acyclic data structures everywhere there.
You will not see very many successful databases that
use cyclic data structures.
And it's also, if you're sending data over the network, how
do you send a lazy list over the network?
How do you send a cycle over the network?
I mean, you can.
It's a little bit harder.
And so this is definitely very much designed for the
network edge, obviously.
It should be extremely efficient.
We'll get to how that works in a bit.
It should fit on a t-shirt.
It should be obviously perfect.
I believe that actually I've hit these points.
So concepts of knock.
Quick.
So a value in knock is a noun.
A noun is basically our version of S expressions.
It's S expressions without the S, because basically all that
stuff has been stripped off.
List, essentially, I would say has almost kind of a dynamic
type system for atoms, which you need if you don't have
another type system on top of it, because how do you print
an atom?
Well, if you have a type system, the type system will
tell you how to print the atom.
But if you don't have it, so basically an atom is just an
unsigned integer of any size.
We use this.
An atom will be a number.
It could be a string.
It could be a network packet.
It could be a giant file.
It's a blob.
But a blob as a number, not as a blob as a number.
And this is how long the number is.
A cell is an ordered pair of any two nouns.
We don't do pointer comparison.
This abstraction is completely semantically opaque.
Knock itself is a function from two nouns, or a cell of
nouns, a subject and a formula to a product.
Subject is the data.
Formula is the function.
A product is the result.
And the way we define knock, we define errors as
non-termination.
So errors are basically anything that produces bottom.
Obviously, we don't do that in practice.
But that's how we define the function.
So let's go over the spec.
We'll see the knock spec in two slides.
These are reduction rules.
You see four basic operators here.
The first one is question mark, or as I would say, what?
This is a deep operator.
So is this a cell, or is it an atom?
If it's a cell, it's zero, meaning true.
And if it's an atom, it's one, meaning false.
Zero for true, one for false.
Probably a decision I might do differently next time.
But it's morally right, and it works.
We can also increment an atom.
That's our only arithmetic operator is increment.
If you try to increment a cell, it reduces to itself,
which means an infinite loop, which means an error.
You can test for equality, same thing.
You can't test for an atom for equality.
And the only interesting operator here is this slash,
which is a slot, which is a tree addressing scheme.
So in this tree addressing scheme, basically, one
is the root of the tree, two n is the left child of any node,
two n plus one is the right child.
So basically, having this kind of simple tree addressing
built into the fundamental interpreter
is what lets us not have to deal with scopes and environments
and basically all that jazz that we know and love from Wisp.
So that's all higher level stuff.
All right, so this is the rest of the knock spec.
This is a complete spec here.
So the first reduction rule here is kind of interesting.
This is something I call autocons.
So basically, if you have a knock formula,
either the head of that formula, the formula is always a cell.
It's always a pair.
The head of that formula is either a cell or an atom.
If it's a cell, then what we have here
is a pair of two formulas.
And the semantics of that is cons in those formulas.
So basically, you can build up, you
know, cons is essentially an implicit operator in a way here.
You can build up and just glom formulas together
and you get this kind of automatically cons thing.
Otherwise, so if you see A here is always the subject
and then we're pattern matching in the formula.
This, by the way, is not the syntax or anything.
It's just pseudocode.
Obviously, if you're writing axioms at a certain level,
they're written in English.
So if the head of a formula is a number, then if it's well
formed, otherwise, you see down at the bottom,
anything that's not well formed resolves to itself.
Again, an error.
If it's well formed, we have instruction 0,
which is just the slot operator.
So that lets us basically pick out
a subtree of the subject.
And then, you know, one, constant.
Two is eval.
So basically, B and C here are formulas
against the current subject for a new subject in formula
that we're going to evaluate.
Again, pretty straightforward.
3, 4, and 5 are the deep bump in same operators
that we've seen before.
Depth test, increment, and equals.
Those are actually all the operators
that we need for not to be as expressive as it wants to be.
So we could actually throw away 6 through 10 completely
and have a much shorter, cleaner spec.
There are simpler Turing-complete interpreters
in this, certainly.
So this is intended to be a practical Turing-complete
interpreter.
And it is actually practical, believe it or not.
And you probably don't believe it.
But so 6 is, I'll leave you with an exercise to the reader
if you can figure out how these macros work,
but 6 through 10 are all macros.
6 is if and else.
7 composes two formulas.
8 composes a formula with the cell
of the product of a formula.
It's basically declaring a variable, essentially.
You're putting a new value onto that subject
and then using it for the next formula.
9 is essentially implementing what
whom we use as a function call to simplify it enormously.
And 10 is a hint.
So you see two 10s there because you
can have a dynamic hint or a static hint.
What a hint is in this environment
is an instruction that throws away data.
So if you discard data, basically,
you're saying to the interpreter,
do whatever you want with this data.
Do something with it.
So hints or anything like a debugging printf is a hint.
You're like, yeah, I don't know that a debugging printf happened.
But if you want to make it happen, make it happen.
Memoization.
There's a memoization hint.
That's another good example.
So the hint basically doesn't change
the formal result of the computation,
but it helps the interpreter do something interesting with it.
So that's all of NOC.
And now let's see.
Here's a little example.
So NOC, of course, the only integer operation is increment.
So if you want to decrement, well,
that's a little bit of a problem.
You actually have to write some code.
You're going to actually have to count up to n minus 1
to decrement.
Not a big deal.
Very simple algorithm.
So here, we're jumping ahead.
And on the right side of your screen, basically,
you're seeing some poon.
Those are two, basically, kind of alternate syntaxes for poon.
One of them is a keyword syntax, which you can probably read
just by looking at it.
The other one is a rune syntax, which you probably can't read,
but that's what we actually use in practice.
It's kind of training wheels, no training wheels.
And on the left is the actual NOC formula
that we generate from this.
If I had a couple more hours, I would actually
go through this formula.
But as it is, it'll just have to serve as an example.
All we're doing is we're basically saying, OK,
we're going to call the subject a, because that's the number
we're decrementing.
We're going to add a counter, which is 0.
We're going to loop.
And we're going to count up until the increment of b is a.
If that is true, our product is b.
Otherwise, we're going to loop again
with b changed to the increment of b.
Pretty straightforward decrement, not super hard.
But that kind of brings up a problem
that you might think of, which is g, o of n decrement.
Well, if you actually run, if you try to boot
urbit with a completely naive interpreter,
it will immediately start decrementing
and keep decrementing until pretty much the end of time.
So that's clearly basically a non-starter.
There's a well-known solution to optimization problems
of this kind.
It's called a sufficiently smart interpreter.
All your interpreter has to do is simply
recognize that it needs to analyze the algorithm that
it's interpreting, recognize that it's decrement algorithm,
and implement it efficiently accordingly.
We also need to recognize add, multiply,
and all of their interesting functions.
So if you know anything about compiler theory,
you know that this is a very hard problem.
Fortunately, there's a much easier problem
which is related to it.
We don't have to recognize every decrement.
We just have to recognize the one that we actually call,
which is the one in the standard library.
And so basically, the way we optimize in the system,
and this should be sort of compared to,
let's say you're building, you're using Java or using Python.
What you do is you say, OK, I wrote some pure code.
It's beautiful.
Oh, it's not fast enough.
And I guess I need a native method.
So then you call it to C. You rewrite your interloop
or whatever in C. You throw away their original pure code.
There's another great advantage, which
is that your interloop in C can make system calls.
So it can modify the file system or something.
And that is not necessarily a very functional way
of proceeding.
The way we optimize knock and hoon is a little different.
So we basically say, when you write, say, decrement,
you say, OK, I'm going to declare this in a namespace.
I'm going to say to the interpreter,
I believe this to be decrement.
It's just a conventional name.
This is decrement.
The interpreter is like, oh, he says this is decrement.
Is this true?
Well, gee, I'm built to recognize, literally,
with the hash of the formula, I'm
built to run this specific formula efficiently.
So I'm going to match this, which is a slightly hard problem,
but I don't know how to super hard problem.
I'm going to match this at runtime,
and then I'm going to do the efficient decrement.
So the advantage of this approach,
and there's a number of advantages of this approach.
First of all, you have both those routines,
the fast decrement in C, which is totally
an implementation detail.
And you're separating mechanism and policy there,
essentially.
So you have your fast decrement in C,
and then you're essentially executable specification
of decrement.
And you're basically binding the two together.
So obviously, you can test these against each other
at runtime, if you choose.
There's certainly, you can sandbox your jet,
so it has no reason to make system calls.
You can also extend this up the stack quite a ways.
So for example, we have one of the,
we serve our own website using Herbit.
And one of the, we serve it from Markdown.
So we have a Markdown parser written in Hoon.
Well, it's a decent Markdown parser.
Maybe not the world's fastest.
Fortunately, Markdown is a standard for some values
of the word standard.
And we basically jet that Markdown parser
with an efficient common mark implementation in C.
Our, for another example is, Google
has this lovely library called TensorFlow.
They recently announced that basically they built an ASIC
for TensorFlow.
I don't know how exactly the programmer talks to that ASIC,
but I'm sure it's a mess.
What you actually want to do is basically
say, OK, I as a programmer, I'm using TensorFlow of this version.
I run TensorFlow, I declare that this is TensorFlow
of a certain version.
And then my interpreter is like, aha,
I have a chip that can speed up TensorFlow of this version.
I'll just use that.
And so that scales kind of in more interesting ways
than the, let's call it, to see model scale.
So we also use it, by the way, to virtualize knock.
So there's actually a virtual knock written in knock
if you thought knock was slow.
But basically, you can get unlimited levels of virtualization
pyramid by basically just recognizing
that you're running your own virtualizer and just saying,
hey, we're at six levels deep.
So that's an improvement as well.
All right, we're done with knock.
That's knock.
Pretty cool.
Let's build Hoon.
Hoon obviously needs to compile itself to knock.
It needs to be a pure strict higher order type functional
language, because that's the hotness.
It needs to have a, I believe it needs
to have a simple transformation to knock.
So I'm really a Unix and Seaguy.
I'm not a functional programming guy at all,
and actually don't know any of their functional languages.
And so that sort of simplicity, that feeling
that basically the compiler is doing something
very simple for you, is really like a wonderful feeling
when you're working inside C. You're
seeing the system basically at two levels.
We definitely want a system that doesn't require
people to have a math degree.
And that's a subject to complaint.
I think more generally, one of the things
that languages like Haskell do is they encourage
their functional programming languages,
and they encourage you to use these powerful tools
as much as possible.
Hoon is kind of opposite.
It encourages you to not use these tools.
It's basically like, OK, the power is there if you need it.
But bear in mind, when you're using this kind of functional
power, you're imposing cognitive overhead
on the ordinary programmer.
Because we really want this to be something
that a Python programmer can pick up and program in.
And I think the ability to basically teach people
these higher order constructs is really debatable.
I don't think it's proven at all.
There's another thing that often happens, both with macros
and with kind of advanced functional languages,
where you get into this kind of DSL pattern,
where basically you're so higher order, you're so meta,
that every file is written in its own language, which
basically gets you to write only code.
And that's like a kind of serious downside
of functional programming.
And the thing is Hoon is still basically almost as
expressive as Haskell.
It has the equivalent of type classes.
It has generosity.
It's like, it's not Haskell.
Haskell people will be a little disappointed in it,
but it's definitely not a lisp.
OK, so let's go a little more into detail on Hoon.
So basically, the back end of Hoon is extremely simple.
So type inference and code generation together,
1,500 lines of code.
Shouldn't be super hard to learn.
So where basically Nock is doing subject and formula
to product, of course, in Hoon, we have an actual expression
that is written in, for some values of the word,
user level code, user level code.
The experience of programming without an environment,
or without a scope, or without a heap,
or without the sort of extra piece of state,
where you just have, the subject is just one noun,
and everything that you need is in the subject,
is sort of somewhat unique and different.
You keep sort of reaching for that,
oh, there must be something that has my variables,
but no, there's really just one noun
that you're defining a function against.
So when we basically take a type system
and layer it on top of Nock,
we're basically computing a mapping from a type in an
expression to a type in a formula.
So we have input type, or subject type,
and expression turns into product type,
and the Nock formula that computes that expression.
So again, a very, very simple straightforward kind of
relationship to Nock here.
The inference algorithm is extremely stupid.
It infers only forward, it does not use unification at all.
It can infer tail recursion, but not head recursion.
So a general pattern is you need a few more sort of casts
to help the type system out.
It's still a strict type system,
but you need to help it a little bit.
My view is that basically having a stupider inference
algorithm is, again, a UI win for a language,
because basically when you program in a language,
you kinda need to follow what the compiler is doing.
The more powerful the algorithm you're following,
basically the harder it's gonna be for people to follow.
And so when I look at Haskell, I see basically two kinds
of Haskell users in a way.
I see people who treat Haskell as a black box,
and they're like, it's sort of a learn you a Haskell
kind of way, and they're like, oh, I made it work, cool.
And then there are the people that actually understand
the math, and both of those situations don't scale in a way.
And so having a simpler system is definitely,
I think a win.
So a little more about Hoon.
So this is brought us in for some criticism,
but Hoon basically, since it sort of has its own way
of doing things, we invent a lot of terms,
because basically the ordinary terms tend to be confusing.
So, and we also have a four letter name
kind of convention going on.
So an expression, or an AST, is a twig.
A type is, well, there's actually three things
that are basically correspond to a type.
So a type, as in sort of a set of nouns
and a semantics ascribed to them, is called a span.
A type in terms of a constructor is called a mold.
And then we also have basically, at the kind of OS level,
I don't think I'll get into that today,
basically the equivalent of mind types,
which is something else also entirely.
Looking at molds, basically,
Hoon is a pure prototype language.
There's no syntax for defining a span.
The only thing you can define are twigs.
So when you want to define basically a span,
a range, a type in the usual sense,
a set of nouns that you're interested in,
what you define is actually a normalizing function
that takes an arbitrary noun and produces a noun
of that type that you're interested in.
What's kind of nice about that is that basically,
if this is the way you define types,
anytime you define a type,
you've defined a validator for untrusted network data.
So we do a fair bit of validating untrusted network data
in today's environment, so that's kind of a win.
Basic concepts of the type system.
This is almost a complete definition
of the Hoon type system.
It's missing a little bit of stuff.
I'll see if I can fill that in,
but we've got to move pretty fast here.
So, and I'm not going to talk about twigs at all,
because once you understand basically a data representation,
it's pretty straightforward.
So a span defines a set of nouns.
What can the set be?
It can be noun, which means it could be any noun,
any remember S expression, basically.
It could be void, which is an empty set.
I'm going to skip over Adam and Core,
because I have separate slides for those.
A cell, obviously a cell.
Here's a span of the head, span of the tail.
A face, basically we're going to label this span.
And so remember that there's no symbol table,
there's no anything in here.
So the labels actually live inside the type.
So when you're searching for a label,
you're actually doing a depth-first search
of basically the type of the subject.
Fortunately, computers have gotten a lot faster.
You can cache this, we do cache it,
but I mean, fine, it's a depth-first search.
How big is your subject, right?
You can have a fork, which is a union of spans.
Pretty obvious.
And the only really interesting one in this page is hold.
So basically one thing we never do in the systems,
we never calculate type signatures.
So this is a strict system, we can't do laziness.
What hold means is basically the span here
is the result of if you take subject P
and run expression Q against it.
So this is very much manual laziness.
Manual laziness has some nice benefits.
Namely, you can use this as a,
you can use a manually lazy span as a key
in a key value data structure,
which is pretty difficult with infinite data structures.
So that's basically, those are the simple ones.
Let me get to the non-boring spans, Adam and Core.
So Adam is just an Adam, slightly non-boring
in that you can say this could be any Adam
or you could say this could be a constant.
So the unit there is who's equivalent of maybe.
And so if that's set, then we have,
this is just a constant Adam.
Then we have P there is something interesting.
The term is a symbol essentially.
And we have what I call an aura.
This is a soft type.
This is a basically non-enforced type
or enforced gently type.
And if you remember, Lisp of course has this dynamic type
and it's Adams, which is just really awful
in my personal opinion.
And if you have a type system, basically the type system
when it has an Adam needs to be able to describe
how do you print this Adam?
Gee, what happens if I try to use a furlong
as if it was a Fortnite?
What happens if I try to use an IP address
as if it was a string?
All those are Adams.
And so you basically need to label those
and describe them kind of informally.
And there's a basically system of specialization
simply by the length of the name.
So you can basically text, ASCII text,
ASCII text with a symbol constraint.
None of the, all these are informal conventions.
None of them are, there's no dependent types in the system.
Sorry, get another no dependent types.
And they're not enforced at all,
except that basically if you wanna turn an IP address
into a string basically and be so foolish,
you have to manually tell it,
you have to cast up to just a raw Adam
and then down back to your string.
So you have to work to basically screw up that way.
That's an interesting design.
You don't usually see a soft type in a functional language.
I think it's worked pretty well.
It's not perfect.
I think the most interesting span,
and remember a span is describing a set of nouns.
The most interesting one is core,
which is essentially an object.
Or it's an object that's sort of
in a very broad in general sense.
It's actually the general case of objects and functions
and a lot of other things,
which you don't really have a name for.
A core is a cell.
The head of the cell is a battery,
which is either one formula or a tree of formulas.
Remembering a formula is just a knock function.
The tail is a payload, which is basically any noun.
And when we run the arms, which are the,
basically they're not methods,
they're computed attributes in the battery.
We run that with the whole core as the subject.
So we basically have this thing
that has a bunch of code in it.
It's like, you can think of,
if you know C++ implementation,
you can think of it as like a V-table, right?
And so it's, here's a V-table with a bunch of formulas in it.
And you say, I wanna run,
I wanna get foo out of this core.
It's like, oh, great, I have a foo.
I'm gonna basically calculate,
that's gonna resolve to this calculation.
So there's no separate namespace
for basically data and for code.
So if you're looking for foo on a core,
and the core doesn't have foo,
there's no foo in the battery.
Then it goes in and says,
oh, well, let's look in the payload.
Let's descend down the tree.
Notice also again,
that there is no attempt to create a type signature here.
So this is just a map of a term to the twig.
Twig is a source.
That's a source expression.
So basically, and that's in the type.
So when I call foo on this core,
I basically go in and I say,
well, okay, that's gonna generate one of these whole things.
So it says, okay, the result,
the type of the span of the result of this foo
is basically the core type and the twig.
And so when we actually evaluate that,
we have to basically manually work through the laziness
and say, oh, well, what's in that type?
Gee, I don't know, let me calculate it and find out.
That actually, that works rather well.
Let me, okay, here's some advanced theory.
I'm gonna go over this super quickly.
So hold again is manual laziness.
One of the nice things about it is that basically,
you can build a conservative work list algorithm.
Let's say you're building a linked list.
Let's say you wanna do a type comparison on two linked lists.
Okay, now this is a basically,
this is a structural comparison.
So you're saying, these could be totally different definitions
of linked list.
Do they match?
So if you basically traverse this span,
what you're gonna see is that that traverse repeats itself.
And because it repeats itself, you can say,
oh, gee, I already checked that there were no violations
on this arm, on this branch, so I'm gonna call that fine.
And that's basically how you can do sort of type logic
in this manually evaluated space.
Again, very, very stupid if you ask,
any smart undergraduate could come up with this scheme.
A little more, at a little more depth,
I'm gonna go over this super quickly.
You may not understand it.
Basically, in polymorphism, you have two,
a lot of different kinds of languages.
And I'm thinking of like Eiffel
and like the Bertrand Meyer kind of world of languages
have basically two kinds of polymorphism.
You have variance and you have generosity.
So basically, any polymorphism in any system like this
is about basically, if I change a core,
let's say, okay, I built this core,
I stuck this battery on this payload.
But now I changed the payload.
Maybe I changed the payload
to something of a different type.
Can I run this core?
So basically, can I run this arm
or will it just be a total disaster?
And that question is actually answered
when you try to run the arm.
So there's sort of simple question of variance, basically.
Can I use this one payload as another payload?
The way we do generosity is,
I can sort of explain this intuitively
at a very high level.
When you're doing generosity,
you're basically saying,
when you're doing variance,
you're basically saying, okay,
does my mutated payload work like the original payload?
When you're doing generosity,
what you're saying is you're saying,
okay, I've changed the type of this payload.
I've changed something totally different.
Now I'm gonna run this arm on it.
I'm not gonna recompile this arm.
I'm gonna run the original knock formula
that was calculated
for something of a totally different type.
And the question you have to answer is,
is that gonna work?
And what span is it gonna produce?
And you're basically treating the twig,
you're treating the arm as a macro,
and essentially working through it.
So it's like the classic example,
can you build a function
to swap two things of an arbitrary type?
So yeah, you basically do that with generosity in Hoon.
So that works, that's how we do containers,
all the usual jazz.
And it's essentially kind of this ghetto,
low rent way of doing type classes.
Syntax design, let's go into the syntax.
Hoon has a very unusual syntax you've seen already.
A lot of people think it looks pretty gnarly.
There is a reason for doing this gnarly thing.
The reason is that basically there are kind of three problems
that you see in a lot of functional languages
that are syntactic problems.
One problem is that basically expression
is sloped downward into the right,
and so they keep attacking your right margin
if they get too complicated.
In a procedural language,
you've got this nice division between statements
and expressions, and statements flow down,
and expressions flow across,
and it gives you this kind of nice tree-shaped structure
which lets you work within an 80-column margin.
In a functional language, you often don't have that,
so you get this slanty thing,
which is uncomfortable to work with.
Another problem in syntax that a lot of these languages have
is they have this unpleasant choice between,
am I gonna have 17 parentheses in a row,
or am I gonna do significant white space?
Both of those have, they work, they work,
they just have, they're just not super pretty.
Another problem that I don't know if everyone has
this problem, I certainly have this problem
when I look at LISPs and a lot of similar things,
is basically I can't distinguish special forms from symbols.
I can't distinguish, is this part of the language,
or is this something that somebody included
from the library, or is it a macro?
And basically making that, again,
getting away from this sort of pervasive DSLization
is definitely a goal of the system.
Speeding up a little, so let me,
before showing the syntax, basically a twig structure.
Once again, the twig is a hoon AST.
You can do, hoon has the same kind of auto cons feature
that knock does, so basically cons is assumed.
If you basically make a cell of two hoon twigs,
that's a cons.
In general, as opposed to LISP,
hoon is kind of more pair-oriented and more tuple-oriented.
We don't throw in terminators everywhere willy-nilly.
That's kind of more appropriate for a typed system, I think.
Most twigs are tagged unions, so they have a head,
which is a stem, which is a symbol, and a bulb,
which is the tail, which is totally dependent on the stem.
It's usually a tuple or a list of twigs,
and let's see how that works in practice.
Basically, there's a regular form.
Again, most bulbs are tuples.
Some are in-area, and there we do need a terminator.
But what we do is we separate,
we basically have two regular forms of syntax.
One, which sort of looks like an expression,
and one which looks like a statement.
Those two ifs there are the same code,
but they look a little different.
What you do is you basically build a structure
whose backbone is basically tall twigs,
and then a tall twig can contain a flat one,
but not vice versa.
Basically, you're mimicking the kind of structure
of imperative code that has this kind of statement
expression duality, but it's all an expression.
There's no imperative anything.
Another thing that you're doing basically
to control the right margin here,
what you really want, you'll notice that C
is at the same indentation as the if there.
So basically, you want to lose no space,
basically for your largest,
hopefully C is the biggest branch,
C is not the biggest branch,
you want unless instead of if.
But basically, you really, as a programmer,
there's sort of an art of arranging these things,
and you arrange them so that they flow down and not across.
And it becomes very easy to read once you know it,
like any language.
And here's the funnest and most fancy part
of our crazy syntax.
So first of all, you've got regular forms
and irregular forms.
So in a regular form, arbitrary syntax,
at least it's always flat,
but that's just something you have to learn.
One of the things I feel, if you look at the implementation
of the Hoon compiler, what you'll see is that basically,
the front end is actually as big as the back end,
which is really quite unusual.
And that's because basically, as a human being,
you've got this great hardware for basically parsing.
You don't have hardware for type inference.
And so what we've done is basically the keyword form
that you saw, I remember you saw those two forms
of Hoon, one using keywords and one using runes.
I'm gonna step forward and show you.
Here are two forms of fizzbuzz.
On the right you see runes.
On the left you see keywords.
Stepping back for a second,
to make these basically pronounceable,
what we've done is taken every ASCII character
and given it a single syllable name.
So where, if you see like if here,
so if is the colon prefixed f there.
That's also the symbol that's actually
in the physical twig.
You can also, as a syntax, you can say question colon.
I wouldn't say question colon though, I would say what?
Which is a lot faster than the same question colon,
not to mention ampersand.
So basically everyone who's learned this is like,
why doesn't everyone know this
and why do I have to say till like my normal friends
when I could say sick?
So hopefully it'll catch on,
if it doesn't catch on at least it's useful in Hoon.
So if we go back to this and we look at the right,
you would say gate infest atom or you would say
park his infest atom for the start of that.
Let me give you 20 seconds to just observe
the fizz buzzes here.
I think that the one on the left
should be at least pretty readable.
Okay, so that's Hoon.
Let's move up on up to Arvo.
Now we're at the operating system level.
The kernel of Arvo is a Hoon core
and this is basically where we get back
to our transition function.
So this core basically has a very fixed battery structure.
You can think of it as basically like a V table
with a fixed structure.
And the Unix interpreter talks to this core
basically at the knock level.
In the life cycle function it's defined at the knock level.
So you basically just hard code those formula offsets.
You can just fix that
because you have only a few functions there.
So basically this is how you have a system
that can completely upgrade itself
because again the whole life cycle function
is defined entirely in knock.
And basically let's say you get an event
and that event is actually a source code update
in the revision control system
that gives you new source code
for Hoon the language itself.
As long as your new language can build a core
that is shaped like the ones that your old language built,
you can turn Hoon into anything.
So ARBO is actually a very, very simple system.
It's only a few hundred lines of code.
It probably should be less than 600 actually.
What it does is it does sort of an internal event cascade.
So you're all familiar with you know,
like you get an event from the outside
and then you're like this happened internally.
Events systems that are very complicated
and deep like this one very quickly
turn into spaghetti event logic.
There's a duality between events and procedure calls
in which basically an event is a transfer of control
essentially and if you take that duality simply,
the dual of a simple event system is go to.
So basically when you have, you're like,
oh through these events and then it's like
the system will go here and it will go there
and it was like why are you doing this?
So essentially we have what you might call
the equivalent of a go sub for anyone
no basic in this room, anyone?
Wow, that's awesome.
I don't feel so old now.
So you have essentially the equivalent of subroutines
in an event kind of model and you have basically
this kind of causal model which I don't wanna get super into
but definitely if you're building
JavaScript event frameworks I think
you could use something like this.
It also has a global type referentially
transparent namespace so basically use any data
in the world as if it was a type constant.
That's kind of nice.
Most of the work of ARVO is done by what are called
veins which are essentially kernel modules
and they have essentially the same kind of core-like
structure as the ARVO core itself.
So these are loaded from source obviously at runtime.
Let me just run through a few of the things we do.
So encrypted packing networking,
we'll talk about that in a sec.
Timer is obviously clay which is like a typed git.
Console obviously air.
We'll see that hopefully driving a demo in a second.
A function build system and I don't really know
how to describe that and an application engine.
And the applications again are cores within Gaul.
So you have sort of these kind of multiple levels
of virtualization.
When you're running user level code
you're actually running it in a virtual knock.
And that virtual knock has an extra instruction.
It has an instruction 11 that de-references
the basically global namespace.
So you're really like de-referencing the whole world
as if it was a constant.
Again that due to the way knock works
you can basically virtualize at any depth
of virtual interpreters without any real cost.
Cause you're actually in implementation
just setting a flag.
All right that's a very, very broad overview of ARVO.
Let's go back to the top and basically look
at what Erbit is doing at the top level.
So we're sort of back to the user level here.
There's fortunately nothing else in the stack
besides NACUN and ARVO and at the top level
what users really see the most in Erbit
is the public key infrastructure
of kind of the identity model.
Basically one Erbit is one event history.
It's one state, it's one instance
and it has one identity.
And you know we basically establish that identity
when we're booting the Erbit.
What exactly is this identity?
What does it mean?
So basically again the kind of the great thing
about doing things from a clean slate
is you really get to think from scratch
which is kind of neat.
And one thing about networking
that is done kind of in a conventional
in the internet certainly is you have these two levels
of well that could spit our audio.
You have these two levels of addressing.
So you have IP addressings and you have DNS.
And the DNS is human meaningful
and IP addresses are routable addresses.
So in Erbit this is compressed into one layer.
So you actually have one layer
which is both a human memorable layer
and it's both a routing address and a name.
And it's actually your personal identity as well.
It's also the base of a path
in the global immutable namespace.
So there's a problem called Zikos Triangle.
Does anyone in the room know Zikos Triangle?
We're definitely not in network land here.
That's fine.
Zikos Triangle basically says there are three things
that you want out of an identity system.
You want the names to be human meaningful.
You want them to be secure
and you want them to be decentralized.
And you can get only two of those three things.
So Facebook, Secure, I hope,
human meaningful names definitely decentralized,
not at all.
BitTorrent, decentralized, yes, human meaningful names, no.
And so there's basically a problem there
that as an OS guy, what they teach us to do
is find the trade off and almost solve the problem.
So the trade off that we make here is basically,
the trivial solution for an identity system of this scale
is basically to say your identity
is the hash of your initial public key.
Very easy, IPFS uses this, very easy to do.
How do you remember a 128-bit hash?
You don't.
And so what we're looking for is basically a way
to make these names that are memorable,
but not meaningful.
So first trick we do is we basically come up
with a new way of representing numbers.
Many things like this have been done before,
not super original, but we do a phonemic base 256.
So if you look at my three numbers there,
there's a hexadecimal number in urban syntax,
there's an in-hune syntax, there's an IP address.
We also have a syntax for that.
And then there's 128, 42, 19, 109,
versus patent of tarlott.
Patent of tarlott is a lot easier to remember.
It's kind of like a human name in a foreign language.
People actually bond with these names
very easily and very quickly.
I'm a task-fine part of it, I think of myself.
People say task-fine, I turn around.
And so of course that's a 32-bit number,
which is a lot shorter than a 128-bit number.
So how you get from 128 bits to 32
is tricky.
So you can actually do the 128-bit hash
of a public key thing, that's called a comment.
Anyone can create their own urban identity.
That is a completely non-scarce resource.
And it's also, there's just no way
of making a 128-bit number memorable.
So what you notice is that basically
the most valuable real estate in this
is down at the bottom of this whole 128-bit space.
And in fact, you can overlay a 128-bit hash
will never be a 64-bit number.
So you can overlay a completely different
64-bit identity scheme on the bottom of this.
So your 64-bit scheme is distributed hierarchically.
It's basically, it's cryptographic property
a little bit like Bitcoin, but it doesn't use a blockchain.
So the way it works is that a 64-bit chip
is the initial key is signed by its 32-bit parent,
basically the half width prefix.
The 32-bit chip is signed by a 16-bit parent.
The 16-bit chip, which is a star,
is signed by its 8-bit parent.
And the fingerprints of 8-bit galaxies
are hard-coded in the kernel source.
This is what we call a pre-mind in the Bitcoin world.
So basically again, this is a PKI
in which revocation and renewal are the same thing.
So basically when you wanna change a key,
whether that's because you wanna give someone else
this identity or you just feel like your key
might be a little bit compromised,
you basically sign the new key with the old key.
Unless you're a moon,
moon should not be floating around unaccompanied.
You sign your own updates.
So basically your parent signs the first key,
but you sign the second.
So you're genuinely independent here.
The main sort of question in that is basically
how these updates get distributed.
Fortunately, there's a lot fewer of them
than sort of the equivalent, which is like a Bitcoin spend.
So there's a lot more room for basically
just sort of handling it in a kind of less aggressive way
than Bitcoin does.
But it's the same basic principle.
Your identity is definitely cryptographic property.
You own it, you can sell it, et cetera.
And there's the 32-bit point
is clearly kind of the right point for human beings.
One of the things about having these 32-bit names
as your names is basically like in any situation
in which people are actually using this system,
some people are using it,
but hopefully everyone will be using it.
You have a scarcity there.
You only have four billion.
And so the price of the scarce resource cannot fault a zero.
So one of the things about that situation
is that the basic problem,
one of the reasons why my mother
can't run her own internet server
is that the internet is basically, you know,
a digital mazizly.
I mean, it's just all kinds of scum and villainy are out there.
And when you get a packet from someone,
you have no way of ascertaining the reputation
of this IP address.
Yes, there are IP address reputation systems in practice.
They basically turn off all residential things
and don't let them send email.
But the ownership of an IP address is not clear.
And so you can't really use, an IP address is not property.
You can't really use it as a mechanism in this way.
When you basically have an address
that's a scarce resource,
let's say you paid 10 bucks for your planet.
Okay, I paid 10 bucks so I wanna be able to compute.
Then you're gonna send messages
directly from that planet.
You're definitely not gonna send them through
like Google or some MTU, like, you know.
And if you spam, like someone's like,
hey, I got a spam from Taskline Partive.
And you go on a blacklist like this.
And basically your 10 bucks is now worthless
because no one will accept anything
from that planet anymore.
So essentially in order, like your spam better
have made you 10 bucks or like, you know,
and that's a pretty high bar for spam.
And so basically just by having this sort of limited
supply of real estate that's treated as digital property,
you basically have the basis for building
a reputation system that works
because the real killer of reputation systems
is an infinite supply of identities.
Because you have this problem where you're like,
I've never seen this identity before.
Maybe it's a new user.
I really wanna say hi.
Maybe it's that spammer I just banned.
I really don't wanna say hi.
That's kind of an unsolvable problem.
And so basically I think this is one of the things like,
you know, nobody, a tiny young network like Erbit,
nobody abuses.
But, you know, in the future, as you grow,
basically you become a target.
And so having a system like this
helps you not be a target.
Let's fall back on the point of all this.
Inventing new system software is always a bad idea.
It's a terrible, terrible thing to do.
Never, never, never do this.
So let's go back to basically the goal of this project,
which is to build a personal server.
So a personal server is gonna be a social server.
So if you have a real personal server
that's a real social server,
when I socialize with you,
in the one nearer case,
barring like weird identity games,
I shouldn't be sending packets directly to you.
I shouldn't be sending packets to some Facebook thing
over there that then sends them to you.
I should be able to basically actually socialize
in a distributed way using distributed protocols.
And one of the things about the way we compute today,
and the reason basically we don't do this,
is that if you look at the difficulty
of distributed programming,
let's say you're building like a tic-tac-toe app,
compare the difficulty of building distributed tic-tac-toe
with the difficulty of building centralized tic-tac-toe.
Centralized tic-tac-toe, my score,
your score, they're variables.
They're in the same data structure.
It's easy.
Then suddenly you're building distributed tic-tac-toe
and you're like have to apply to the ITF for an RFC
for your TTTTP, right?
And it's just like six orders of magnitude different
in difficulty.
And if you wanna ask why we don't have
a decentralized internet,
basically the reason we don't have a decentralized internet
is that decentralized programming is too damn hard.
So basically you need to solve this problem
if you're gonna build anything like a true personal server.
So let me talk a little bit about
the kind of programming or experience
of where we're aiming to get with this.
This is actually my next last slide.
So let's see, first of all,
you're programming in the system.
You can dereference a global immutable namespace.
So basically use any data in the world
as if it was a typed constant.
That's kinda nice.
Your application state is permanent.
You don't need a database to basically flush stuff out too
when for your data actually exist.
When you do an update,
your updates basically come through reactively
through the, you have basically a revision control system
that's clay or I didn't talk much about that,
but it's basically a revision control system with hooks.
And so you're like, oh, I got a source code update
for this thing I'm running.
And then I'm like, oh, I need to change out the code.
Oh, gee, the type of my data change.
So I need to have a type adapter in there
to make that work.
That all works great.
A very different experience from kind of updates
or upgrades in a lot of systems.
When you get to messaging patterns, basically,
you've got a poke, which is a forward, basically,
essentially an RTC without a return.
And you've got a subscription model.
Let's look at basically what we get with pokes
for a moment.
Number one, you get exactly once delivery.
You've probably heard that exactly once delivery is impossible.
It was a great blog post about that a few months ago.
Exactly once delivery and message semantics
actually is possible if all of your entities
are single level stores.
And if they can basically run permanent sessions.
So you have a permanent session and you're like,
oh, I expect message seven from you.
Well, you're only gonna get message seven once.
Where that breaks down in this kind of system
where you have transient and permanent state
is you reboot the computer and then you're like,
do I expect message seven or message six?
Or you have these idempotence problems.
So every message is a transaction
in this kind of distributed programming environment.
If the transaction succeeds, there's no return data.
So it's a one way transaction.
Your messages are automatically type checked
and validated on the receiving side.
You can even do basically protocol type updates
on the live network and not propagate errors to the user.
The data that you get over the wire is passed to you typed.
You basically just get it as an argument
and it's a typed value.
We do end-to-end acknowledgments,
which basically means there's kind of a single error mode.
So when you're doing acknowledgments,
like think about you're doing a normal RPC or HTTP.
Something goes wrong.
Well, what could go wrong?
Your socket could break.
You could get an HTTP error.
You could get an error at the RPC layer.
What do you even do with half of these things?
Like there are different kinds of error.
And that basically is just very, very difficult to handle.
So if you're basically doing acknowledgments
at an end-to-end level,
that means the packet level act that you send back
is actually the transaction acknowledgement
that you succeeded or failed.
Messages are queued by the sender.
Obviously, this is a P2P network.
It traverses NAT and of course it's authenticated
and encrypted.
Your subscriptions are sending diffs.
Those again are typed.
So this is a very different distributed programming experience
than your sort of normal, I'm writing this in node experience.
And our experience is basically it's,
you just do things and they pretty much just work.
What is the status of this system?
It's about 30,000 lines of Coon, including basic apps.
It's totally open source.
You can go to urban.org.
And which is served by Arbit, although we cash it.
And yeah, I mean, it essentially works.
We were on occasional global flag days,
so you might not want to move your business onto this system.
But yeah, I mean, when creating a system like this,
involves a lot of rewriting stuff over and over again
until it actually works right.
And we're basically getting to the end of that process
and we're kind of close to being ready to sell
some address space to the public.
Let me do a quick demo of this system
to see if it's actually working.
I'm actually doing this over my,
so here is, you're in Arbit.
Live, yes, we're live.
That bounced off the server and came back.
So that's basically a simple console talk app.
Hello from, a little bit slow on the typing there.
Our console path is pretty complicated
and we could use some serious optimization.
Let me see if I can bring up the web UI of talk.
Ah, yes, here is a web app.
Let me get it fully up.
Looks like it needs a reload,
which it actually should not.
Hate it when that happens.
But here, basically, you're seeing a web UI.
Do you want to say something?
Anyone want to say something?
I'll just be, hello from William the Comfort Inn.
Boulder is beautiful.
So, beautiful with an extra K.
And this has to bounce off the server to get back.
Actually, the Colorado's router
seems to be blocking my transition directly.
But, you know, I'm doing it via Verizon, so it works fine.
TaskFind Partive is actually running on this laptop here.
Yeah, so that was a very simple demo
and now, any questions?
Yes.
So, does Richard Stallman know about this?
I don't think so.
Because I don't think this would really get
to what Richard Stallman would like to see.
Yeah, I think there's a lot of people
who are tired of this sort of Facebook-ization
of the internet.
And this is definitely also, I mean, yeah,
is this a list?
Is this basically E-Max?
At a certain level, it's basically E-Max.
So, yeah, you know, all right,
we're at a one-minute warning here.
Time for maybe one or two more questions.
Be over?
Yes?
So, I feel like maybe you're trying to
talk to me confusing, like, do you use the word twig,
but like, I'll be referred to as a nasty?
Mm-hmm.
Is there a particular reason for, like,
these more or less travel elements?
Yeah, I mean, the reason is basically you're,
you want to use the word that the actual source code uses.
Is the reason for that being the convention
and the source code, is that a good reason?
Maybe not necessarily.
It certainly makes things kind of tire
and more readable in a way.
There's an aesthetic, which kind of,
there's an aesthetic of short names,
which works fairly well in kind of a functional environment,
which wouldn't work in an imperative environment.
But, yeah, I mean, you know, the criticism
that this is a little more obfuscated
than it has to be, is certainly one
that I think holds a little bit of water.
So, when you chat with the one message
and so there's a browser,
how do you go through the centralized events?
So, that is basically, that, if you saw,
if I turn on debugging, here,
turn on debugging, and you'll see a lot of...
Okay, so what's actually happening is that packet,
so I'm logged into, I could log in via
taskfinepartive.erb.org, here,
let me turn this off, this is horrible.
And I could log in via taskfinepartive.erb.org
and be proxied by basically the star
that is, taskfinepartive is a planet of.
But, basically, I'm in a channel,
that channel is hosted on DOSNEC,
which is the star that I'm responsible to.
And so, basically, that packet is going up to DOSNEC,
coming back to me, and then it's going
over localhost8080 to the browser.
All right, any more questions?
I think we're time.
Thank you.