Testing.
Yep.
Ah, yes.
So,
do me the favor
of
saying your name
so that I don't mispronounce it.
Yep.
Balapile.
Yes, and I am Darren Stevenson,
so we are here in a conversation together
that I wanted to record.
Because it was becoming,
as I expected,
it too very interesting.
Balah had been discussing
something
in
ideas
from a specific
person
whose name you can say.
Actually, maybe you can just go over
briefly.
Yeah.
Okay, I'll do that.
What I was talking about is
the notion of
network state.
As in any T, W, R, K
second word state, S, T, A,
T, E, network state.
Um,
chat called Balaji Srimivasan,
quite a
personality, known personality online.
Um, used to be CTO
of Coinbase.
But,
you know, it's not just a crypto guy,
it's no crypto, very well read,
you know, history, background,
people.
You could summarize him as a pro-anarchy guy,
right, who doesn't take
limits of, um,
government and all that as limits.
So,
his,
what the network state means is,
right,
you can form
enough of the ethos,
and the common
wealth
of a group of people
online,
and then later,
right, enough of the cohorts
can, you know,
could have agreed
to where they want to stay,
and live in a place where they,
uh,
where they get along.
Where they're physically approximate
so that they can collaborate
in each other's
life development.
Yep.
Right, so that,
um, this is much more,
it's not impossible to do at a distance.
Yep.
But it's much more difficult.
Absolutely.
Well, there are more challenges.
Um, yeah, it's just,
it's a different space of
challenge for
those who are not proximal.
Um,
but you said something
that I thought was hilarious.
You were like,
I'm brilliant.
Go ahead, you were talking about somebody
buying a house.
Okay, the background word is this, right?
I've gone through all those states.
What do I mean by all those states?
You know,
living,
grew up in a semi-rural village,
you know, where everybody
knew everybody and,
you know, it's a tropical place
so that you're never worried about
money because it seemed like,
why do you, you know,
food was available all over the place
and you could go and sleep in anybody's house.
So what's your problem?
You know, right?
That was, um, and then,
but my parents
have moved from India
to Malaysia,
right?
My father had gone through the struggles
in India and in some,
in Malaysia, he was continuing
in Malaysia
and he was driven
to have,
to have lots more money under the pillow,
right?
And on that, later,
he was just full on into like,
being a stingy guy
who saves and saves and saves
and for good reason because of his
background, right?
Right, his history, yeah.
After that, and the British rule
in India, right?
His tough times, right?
Uh, there were tough times. So in Malaysia
it's easier but he didn't realize it
that easier. So he,
he went on a spree of, um,
ah, so what he would do
is buy one property upon property
upon property and including
our house itself,
what we call,
the house, the family house,
his only concern was
to replace, you know, if you buy this house,
ah, what's the replacement value?
If I were to sell it, how much money would I get,
you know? Um,
he didn't care about much
anything else and then
me, right,
ah, has to pay for that
because it has completely broken up
the family.
As compared to,
you know, now my adopted village,
Darren, is a village
in Indonesia, in Java.
It's a zero crime village
similar to the kind of village
my father was born in, right?
Uh, they didn't live there
on age 18
and there,
the values
fit with the village, the people
despite the rest of the world not
wanting to have anything to do with zero crime
villagers because it's got
consequences, right?
It's got consequences.
For example, people won't
be fronting wealth because they won't
be much wealth, it'll be culturally
communist, right?
Yes, yes.
But you will not worry about old age
and children being taken care of because
the people love to take care
of other people.
Yes, they are living in a
traditional
a traditional context
where
everyone takes care, not
not every single person,
most of the people take care
of each other
and they understand
so this changes their role
as a human being,
right? Transforms
their role as a human being
from I am here for me
and mine
or just I am here for me
to we are here together
for each other.
Yeah.
If you don't have that,
I will argue, if you don't have
we are here together for each other
you don't have humans yet.
You have something
weird. It's not human.
That's it.
And I want to
stamp it even further.
Yeah, by all means.
I mean
I've grown up in like
fighting a lot of people,
probably
post
you know, post university
even in university it didn't
occur to me.
Maybe particularly from the 90s onwards
okay, basically
I'm into unconditional love
that
I'm with again and again.
Bala, why are you being...
The thing that I find hilarious about what you said
is that
linguistically it's backwards.
It's not that you're into unconditional love,
it's that you didn't
defect from it.
Right?
That's the natural position
for human beings.
You simply didn't defect
in my view, but please continue.
I'm with you.
Yeah, so exactly
because my mother
grew up
in such a place.
So she didn't know anything
else and she went to great lengths.
Oh my god.
Consequences.
But leave all of those
cause, you know,
talking to you, one of the greatest things about
talking to you Darren is, you can talk
about things that are, you might
have a long life
taught its age, unconventional, so kind of like
censor that a bit, you know.
No, you can do whatever you want
so I love it, you know, okay.
So I
loved, you know,
my mother was the epitome of unconditional
love and I love that.
Beautiful.
You know, it didn't occur
full on to me at that time, right?
It occurred enough, but because
occurred enough as in, you know,
when the world became
difficult, there's one person
that you could go to who has got time, patients
for you. She listened
and she won't, you know, abruptly
stop you halfway or say that
that's a silly idea.
She will take it that it's possible
that her child may know something that she doesn't,
you know, right?
And that was
special, right, in this
kind of like cruel world, right?
Extremely beautiful, yes.
So I want
to continue that and I was not going to
stop, agree
with anybody who said it's impossible.
You know, you can't.
And later in life,
of late, I realized, no,
they,
many who say it's impossible
are only saying it because
our narrative has so much
become zero or
100 binary.
It's like, if something is not
exact, you know, it's like, can you guarantee
me that 100%
you know, that person who is
in your village, you can have unconditional love?
Well, the real answer is
why do you even, why can't it be
fuzzy at the edges?
Say again.
Even when we do math
or graphs, you know, we cut off the
extremes and that's good enough
if you can manage it 90% but, you know,
there are outliers but you don't need
to like spend your whole lifetime
passing the last 2%
you know.
Okay, you've touched on something, wait,
you've touched on something I want to highlight.
Please
nurture your
line of thought and where you are going
so that you can hold on to it for a second.
But I
want to say something, the zero 100
thing. So
as children
eventually
we attempt things
that are at least
initially, they are
impossible. Okay?
It is initially
impossible for you to
stand up.
It is initially impossible for you to take
a step.
It is initially impossible
for you to jump
or run
or walk or speak
or swim
or hold your breath underwater
or ride a bicycle
or write language.
All of these things start out
initially impossible
and if we
evaluate them on the basis
that is usually used in our cultures
pretty much nothing is possible
because you can't, the only things that are
possible are things where you go from
zero to 100 in one move.
Right?
In a single move.
Never happened.
Right?
So we do have this mindset
and I was reading
I just want to share something from
a book called the dawn of everything that I was
reading last night.
We're talking about
our views of history being wrong
and we basically have two views. It was
wonderful. We all took care of
each other and then we fell from that
now it's every man for himself
and there's no way to change it.
The best you can hope for
is slight adjustments
to the tyrannical nonsense
of human society.
And I say this
as long ago as 1936
the prehistorian V. Gordon Child
wrote a book called man makes himself
apart from the sexist language
this is the spirit we wish to invoke.
We are projects
of collective self-creation.
We approach human history that way.
What if we treat people
from the beginning
as imaginative intelligent playful
creatures who deserve to be understood
as such? What if
instead of telling a story about how
our species fell from some idyllic
state of equality
we ask
how we came to be trapped
in such tight conceptual
shackles
that we no longer even imagine
the ability of reinventing our societies.
They say ourselves
but what they mean is
our societies.
We can't imagine it because it seems
like it's like a task like eating
the moon
or drinking the ocean.
So no one imagines
that it's only possible
it's necessary
to be intelligent.
The entire history
and future of life on this planet
may depend on the single
on this single pivot
can humans form
intelligent
aware collectives
with and for each other
and with and for the history
and future of life on this planet.
Now of course we can
on the small scale.
We can do it immediately
we can do it. You and I are not going to
have any problem doing that
right here, right now. We'll be doing that
together, right?
So it's immediately
if you just shrink the scale from
everything to something
you can do it right now
with any few people
who are motivated and sincere
you know, yeah.
Please continue.
Right on, right on. Excellent.
So, so good to hear.
So good to hear.
And you know
much of it is
self
it's like self fulfilling prophecy
or self created meaning
one of my biggest answer backs
has worked right against this notion is
against this notion of
it can't be done you know it's impossible
it's
this whole
hopelessness is
you know guys
if we were living
you know
before the first village
right and
the first village would never have happened
you know like
often I'll see in
online forums
like
the ones that you quite a lot
in this one the p2p foundation
right quite a lot of people from
around the world
and often
the people are so good at
nitpicking right
right and I'm like by the way these are
people who probably never accomplish anything
other than nitpicking
but go ahead.
Yeah.
They're professional nitpickers
right what do you do for a living I sit around
on a computer screen and pick
nits
so
I'm like saying hey look
right
you
just imagine you know
if our ancestors
very little they made the first village
happen if they could not get along
right
if they were egotistical
the first village would not have happened
in all likelihood it would have taken many attempts
for the first village to
to happen
you know to stay and be
maintained continue as first village
but we know that it
happened and then it went on to become
a small town and
those language and
so if those people
can kind of hold their negativity
their pessimism down a bit
right to let
the blossoming as the blossoming
see in nature right despite
all the earthquakes and whatever
negative you know there may be
there still is you know
flowering and blooming and you know
joy and aesthetics
in nature
right
why can't we
look at the good
and ignore the bad
right unless the bad totally
you know cannot be
right if the house
catches on fire we'll get some water
yeah
right yeah
you know
but it's not
a matter of okay it's not a matter
of this it's a matter
I think and by all
means correct me if you see it differently
yeah it's a matter of
the
okay look
we got two different
kinds of options right
you can put humans together
you can get them to agree
to come together as a group let's say
a small group seven people
okay
and you can
say again
I said entirely
I mean nobody would argue
same person can argue against that
if you said seven people you know like
okay
right you can get seven people together
and
tell them either one of two things
okay
you're just going to learn how to
get along and help each other
yeah
and be for each other
and be together as one unit as well
as being individuals
you're either going to learn how to do that
or we're going to give you some principles
but the fundamental problem is that
there has to be a catalyst
right
there has to be a profound catalyst
that makes the people want
to be together
and to grow together
and to learn together so either
the catalyst
for most people
the catalyst is either the fear
of really bad experiences
of being human
or
it's the
it's FOMO
it's a version of FOMO
I know that being human can mean
so much more than living in this box
and watching television but I don't know
how to get to that
the fear of missing out
right those are two highly
motivated highly motivating
things but the third highly
motivating thing is a fire
right like the village is on fire
get up let's go
right or
or you know
in a city
you will see humans
form highly effective
cooperative pods
little groups right pods
spontaneously
if there is a car accident
if there is an earthquake
right
what will happen if there is an earthquake
is you will see three things
people who are sort of neutral
they don't know what the fuck to do
so they're kind of milling about
the people who are
acquisitive
these people are looking for opportunities
to profit off the situation
and then people who are
you know they convert to altruists
right we're going to help each other
get through this right now
Hey, follow up to you
you remind me of something
critical I want to ask
I wanted to ask you
let me ask you
of course
keep your thought along but I want to ask you this
you know
I've gone through a tough life
situation the last few years
and one thing you say
for me
has been a dog named Benji
right
this is not surprising even slightly
I'm listening
yeah no surprise there
I want to ask you
this one thing
it goes into the granular
of
unity
is diversity
it's not
once people don't have to riddle themselves with
finding
we can find unity within diversity
or allow for diversity
within unity
what you will find
is something like your hand
right
where you have a bunch of unique
members
and there's
no problem with the index finger
being its own finger
no problem
but they always
work together for each other
and the synergy that the palm
right where they come together
the synergy where the palm of the hand is
that stuff is powerful
in fact that's the stuff that makes most
of the trouble
for humans
is we're making the bad form of synergy
right
we're like oh with synergy
you can go faster you can get more
you can
you can mutate
and propagate wildly if you have synergy
but I'm listening
I didn't hear
your question
you were talking about diversity and unity
good good good
the small subset
within that
with my dog
the dog loves
to come
and lick
the inside of my mouth
right
and
you know
it's a mix between
a golden retriever and a food dog
right
very
humanly
very into humans
I have no idea what people listening to
our conversation will think when you say that
but keep going because I'm going to go somewhere
that I think you're actually going to go to
but let's see
anyway
I have this overall view that
all creatures and plants have been
made
maybe we don't know like a bed bug
we don't know why
but it's got a logical reason
but it's got a reason
so when my dog
when this dog comes and licks me
wants to you know out of his instinct
and he's so determined to like what to do
I let him
so as time goes on
it's fine
because
but now let me go to the
the gist I want to get to you
he
you know we have I think
adopted a practice of giving
it's different
from
gating
and giving can never be as good
as
satisfying as
gating
oh that is
such bullshit but I understand
that that's the tradition
yes go ahead
okay but you know
for the dog
I'll cut to them
yeah you're right
it's very happy
number one
and it's happy more time
much of its happiness comes from
giving
it's like instinctively
I mean I would argue that the dog
doesn't even make that distinction
yeah
that's it
it never makes that distinction
it understands receiving
so to speak
perhaps it differentiates that
I'm not sure
but its body understands the difference between
he's holding a chunk of meat
and he isn't
body understands that
but the thing about the dog
okay look it's doing something crazy
and you know
this isn't to suggest that everyone should
French kiss their dogs
for those of you for whom it's natural
by all means
let them you know let them lick your mouth
I think many in the west
would consider that disgusting
or dangerous or unhealthy
because the dog has a lot of germs
so to speak
but here's the actual thing that's crazy
I will argue
something really bizarre here
and I'll take responsibility for my argument
I will argue that your dog
is already
your dog has senses
that sense your mind
yeah
the same way you can smell the dog
the dog can smell your mind
right yeah
senses that can sense your mind
it has senses that can participate
with your mind
it has senses that are telepathic
it has senses with which it can
bond its intelligence to yours
and give something
truly astonishingly miraculous
to you
humans all the time and the humans don't recognize
it at all they don't even notice it
they just feel better when the dog's around
they can't see what the dog's actually doing
and I'm going to argue
that what most of the dogs are actually doing
is they're trying to
they're trying to do something like
the Vulcan mind meld
in Star Trek
where Spock becomes
the two minds become one mind
it's trying to do something like that
and it's trying to do that for
a way of heroic purposes
one of the best things it could possibly
do if that were its goal
would be to get its microbiota
into your gut microbiome
and your microbiota
into its
once you start sharing
the digestive
microbiota especially
the first
sort of landing zone
for microbiota and humans one of them
anyways the mouth
so
when dogs are sniffing poop
and doing whatever they're doing
presuming they do such things
they're
connoisseurs of bacteria
it's obvious to me from observing them
so I would argue that
the dog is actually trying to become
one fit more
one organism
with you
so that its microbiota get into your mouth
and your microbiota get into
its mouth and some on both sides
survive
and they reproduce and they become families
of trillions of organisms
trillions
there's 43 trillion
bacteria inside a human body
and once again right you have the same thing
you have unity and diversity
the diversity supports
the health of the unity
yep
and especially
on this part right
especially if you say look
what is the reality when people talk about unity
and
diversity
in today's governance world
when they talk about unity
they're talking about conformity
isn't it
conformity does absolutely
cannot be that the basis for unity
no
this is why
if you're putting a cohort together
you don't
want to have to give them rules
you want them
to discover the process together
so that it's organic
I think
but in a dire situation
where there's something interfering with them
discovering it together
the catalyst should
should declare the
principles
yes
the catalyst should
communicate the principles to us
and what I was going to say is that
a long time ago
let me just say something really simple and stupid
by the time a human collective
needs rules
70%
of that collective has gone missing
in action for one reason or another
and it's offline
yep yep
by the time you have to tell people what to do
the intimacy is
not there
there's no intimacy between them
they can't sense each other
they're not sensing each other
and doing predictive analysis for each other's needs
and vulnerabilities
and things like that
which humans in a tightly knit group do that
all day long every day
they just naturally do that
they're vigilant
in a way
they're vigilant of everything
as if they were the unity
as if the concerns of the unity
I don't know it's really hard to say it in language
because it sounds like a rule and it's a game
it's not a rule
hmm
but once you make it a rule
you're going to have a tough time
like by the time God had to write stuff in stone
on top of some mountain
and send Moses down to his people
with what
10 rules
you gotta imagine like
things must have been really bad
for something that
severe to have to happen
you gotta tell people
don't kill each other
you gotta tell them
not to steal
right
you gotta tell them to wear a loincloth
all right
or you know what don't rub your butt on your food
and
time you have to
tell them these things
something's gone horribly
haywire like not
in a little way
in like an apocalyptically
bad way
it can only go from here to disaster
kind of way
and
text
I mean writing it down
overall
I mean in a large
in a large way
it's taking us backwards
especially
I mean
as with any technology
good and bad
and also
unfortunately for humans
pretty much unavoidable
given the situations
unavoidable
okay look
the problem with text is you have
okay if I am speaking with you
or you are speaking with me
right yep
we both have an idea of to whom we are speaking
and also to whom we are
listening
once you have text
you have the possibility which is
very dangerous for human cognition
the way human cognition
psychologically
it's anatomy very very dangerous
if you have a thing which is this
speech without someone speaking
it to you
now you can't
tell whether that's an actual
person
whether it's a machine
whether it's God
or
whether it's a problem in your consciousness
and since you can't tell
which one of these it is
things go badly
once you have
disembodied speakers
things go badly
for humans
generally it's also a sign
that things have already gotten
weird
I mean when I think about getting
humans together for each other
and this is perhaps the most exciting thought I am capable of having
I have to admit
it seems
almost impossible or wildly
unlikely to my
pragmatic
mind
my pragmatic thoughts
how do you tell them
what do you want them to do
what's so exciting that
we are going to get together
and actually go on a mission
I have various answers to those
questions but it sure seems
just as we were talking
as we were speaking about earlier
in the conversation it seems to be
a 0-100 problem
it isn't
it isn't a 0-100 problem
but it seems that way
until
you get a few experiences of
making it work
and you can make it work
for an hour
you don't have to make it work for the future
or the world
you can make it work for two hours for five people
now
they will get a taste
oh shit we can do this
we can actually do this together
because
I would argue
and I know this is a very dangerous thing to say
but I am quite certain of the truth of it
I would argue that a team of
five people could transform
a nation
in 90 days
any nation
probably almost any five people
and if this was ever true in human history
it's more true now than it's ever been
because
the history and future of life on earth
depends on
the humans becoming intelligent
yeah
the humans must become intelligent
or either that
or you have to kill off 97% of them
or something
right
if you want to keep the world alive
because they will just keep making machines
not arguing to kill anybody
to be clear
I am saying if you want to preserve life on earth
we either have to
the entire history
the meaning of the history of life on this world
and the future
of those histories
we have got to get the humans playing a game
that isn't lethal
together
right
it's the fundamental priority
it's more important than any other thing I can think of
if we care about
will there be a world for our grandchildren
if we don't care about that
it's still really important
but
so
so then you have the problem of
in this case
in the little toy
universe that I'm creating here during our discussion
in this case what you do
is you get five people together
and you teach them how to solve an intractable problem
locally to where they live
right
so that they have the experience of
taking on a problem that just can't be fucking solved
synergizing
you know
solving the problem
now they have experience
this was
this topic was related to
our agreement
to come to listen to talk together
today
because we were talking about teams
I was talking about teams and that's when you sent me
a message on Facebook right
yep
yes correct
so there's something about collaboration
collaboration
how can we
make what you are
trusting and which is what I'm trusting to
in your messages
I love that word
saying
okay
that's an alternative
and you put it in such a way that
again
a lot of the usual suspects
cannot even object to it
because it's beyond
also look
I don't care
I want to be really clear
yes I don't care about the usual suspects
objecting because here's what's going to happen
once you get humans being
actually human together
and
the public
is able to observe that happening
and
see the results
and see what it's like to be
to have the scope of our humanity
some portion of that return to us
relationally
behaviorally
in terms of our role and our felt sense of
role if you can give him some of that back
those objectors
are going to last about six days
and then they're going to be on
forming their own teams
and be left out
no idiot is dumb enough
that when they see the humans making that
nectar of being human together
they're going to be like yeah I don't want to be part of that
that's the original
money
that's what money is a representation
of is that nectar
yeah
that's right that's right
it's the synergistic nectar
yeah
and then the humans can learn things like this
you can teach children this and you're like
look your parents are doing this thing
with money
and what they're really trying to get
is this other stuff that you and your friends
make naturally when you play together
they're not getting any of that
so they're trying really hard to get money
you don't have to do that
the thing that you and your friends are doing
can develop
can grow
and can be maintained
like you can get five people together
and then five of them split apart
two of those form
new ones
the other three
join existing ones
so that there's sort of cross-pollination
between
team and pod groups
and this is something that works really really well
the game that I'm talking about is the game that every organism
in nature is playing
and the humans are
made to play this game but they're playing
sort of the opposite of it
which is kill the unity
and make representations of the dead things
and then sell them
to each other
so
if you give them a game that's authentic to play
and they like it
it's going to become really
contagious
if you give actual humans something
to do that's amazing and the other people see
you'll have
objectors at first
but it's not going to last long
don't say that again
I want to process that
say the last two sentences again
the goal is to do something
so momentous and beautiful
that nobody can stand
to be left out
nobody
everybody wants in
that's full on I can
sense that because
and that's an achievable thing
in a way
just you and I speaking
of such matters is the beginning
of that
can you see why I say that
Bala?
and I know 100%
and I have happened in my background
these people who are labeled
poor and whatever in the zero crime villages
but these kids are so rich
I mean
they are alive
to be human
if you get excited
with the cockroach being upside down
I mean whatever
toys can come from
what the rest of the world
might call nothing but
they're excited
because like you were saying
walking is impossible
running is impossible
jumping is impossible
but
they're not overwhelmed
by all of the
text around the world
I suppose
yes and also
I'm guessing
do the children have phones?
no
they don't
by the way
this is like an alien
comes to earth
and finds your village
and looks and says this is a very unusual village
here
where are your children's phones
and you say
they don't have any and the alien says
oh I'd like to raise my children here
do you think it would be okay?
can I
can we do this together?
wow
it's almost like asking
do your children
wear a mechanical parasite
that destroys their attention
motivation
awareness
it's not the only thing the phones do
but
it's a lot of what they do
Darren you remind me
I'll be going back
again in a couple of months
back to the village
and
the permanently based there
very soon I'm just
organizing to do that
tying some of those
with the
urban world
what was beautiful
every time I'm there
the kids
automatically want to help the mother
I mean
it was very common
it was very common me growing up
my sisters would help the mother
and I would help the father
and stuff like that
I mean they didn't have to do too much
but
now I've played
my kids
to some extent but just generally
I noticed
people are finding it very hard
to get their kids to do chores
yeah
but when I go to the village
the kids
seem to like wow
I'm given a chance to be an adult
yes
amusement
and like wow they're treating me like an adult now
they're not completely saying
I can't do this and I can't do that
and so
because
my brother-in-law
my
sorry my
my brother-in-law's children
essentially
my nephews like
Anises
bring breakfast I'm upstairs and they're downstairs
and they're bringing coffee and this
and this is like 8 years old
she does a good job
I'm so happy
with that
and a mother or my wife
doesn't have to
push up she looks forward to
doing this
it's like
what you'll find is like
in our culture
the children are competing
to get things
they want to get things
in the village culture
the children are competing to
it's not merely
give
they are competing
to participate
meaningfully
with the family
the village the planet
and the adults
and the children
participate meaningfully
and so the chance to bring coffee
is better than just sitting there looking at my thumb
and
they don't have a smart phone to defect into
so they're not going to defect
that way so you know
they wouldn't be doing any other thing
but the chance to bring coffee is meaningful
I'm serving my ancestors
they are still alive today with me
in the same room
this is magic
we are still alive together
and then maybe
if it's just this
a rite of passage as in
one of the things all want to be
they don't want to be
treated like kids
like we know nothing
too often
some of that works in their favor
because some of the children
respond to that by becoming
monumentally
intelligent
because they're like
that dumb kid
my dad called me dumb
so I learned quantum physics
I'm just giving
a ridiculous example
some of it does sort of help
the children
but that shouldn't be
the cultural
you know
that shouldn't be the cultural tradition
I'm listening
so wait Darren
I want to imprint this into my head
which is
number one there's an issue
there's a big problem of getting kids
to like do the
sensible things
and one of the reasons why
they don't want to do this
they want to get things
they want to either get things
or they want to defect
and they're addicted to electronic stimuli
and things like that
so they're used to
constantly referring to an object
with their attention
the children there don't have to do that
if they have a phone
even if they have a computer
if they have a video game
if they have a television
if they have even a radio
it starts to be
the same kind of thing
and also because
we've totally
you know
okay I have to say
I'm sorry
I have to say
the thing all those things are replacing
is meaningful relation
in the village with the others
all those things
they are replacing that
they are the money version
of the nectar that's produced naturally
when the people are there
for each other
this great sweetness
combination of silence
laying hopscotch
in front of the hall
seeing the kids
from the neighbor's house coming
not wearing something different
all of that
is little sparkles
you know
talking
learning how to speak a bit better
it is because you and the children are there together
for each other
even the children who aren't yours
and you know
the children
they like
I don't know how to put it
the children are carrying
assets
that the adults don't
recognize
and dispose of
and punish the children for carrying
everywhere around here
mostly a little bit of you know
there are a few intelligent parents that know better
but
the children are bringing something
to the table
and the adults pretend
to be rude
you are dependent on us
and since we have to protect you
and this creates a kind of slavery
children in the west
are sort of conceived of as slaves
this is why we send them to school
which is basically a slave making process
this is why they go to university
get degrees and so forth
in the representational layer
of human culture and society
which is
mostly pretty bad
mostly different kinds of slavery
children are meant for something else
and they can tell the adults are suffering
and they have assets
that will ease the suffering of the adults
if they don't eradicate it
the children are carrying
something like medicine
children are living medicine
the adults are living medicine
especially when they are together
for each other
then they naturally make the medicine
together
does that make sense
yes yes
in this case medicine isn't like a pharmaceutical
medicine is
the food and drink of our soul
or our heart
medicine is what
we open
we learn
being ready to learn
as opposed to taking for granted
that
the
representationally
sends
the wrong signals
it does
it completely messes up our thought
don't want to make a mistake
go on sorry Darren
no please I'm sorry
please continue
often I'm not able to
it's kind of like
often I'm not able to articulate it
but I understand
the moderns are captured
by a layer of
processes that they enact
as behaviors like drive the car
to the grocery store
get the groceries
get the job get the pay
take the kid to the doctor
pay the attorney do the taxes
watch the television show
mind the smart phone
clean the house
chores
what we would call chores
but really those are like
those are all
all those processes are mostly vampiric
they are extractive
they take something from us
and they give us a representation
now we can
negotiate that layer very carefully
if we're smart so that we get
actually nourishing food
when we go to the grocery store
and we don't get poison for example
candy bars and whatever
yep
but the representational layer is powerful
it's well established
it affects everything on earth
it's lethal
it steals life
it's
an actual vampire would be
terrified if it saw the representational
layers
relationship with humans because
it would realize that that must be
it's god
that must be the god of the vamp
that's what spawns vampires
vampires come from that
if there are such things
right
but yes the medicine
the village makes together
this medicine
is very powerful and it has
a unique protective effect
vampires bounce off of it
it makes like a shield
right
and so vampirism doesn't get established
in the children or the adults
and they're busy playing every other beautiful
game
everybody will be happy even when
things are difficult they're still
going to be way happier
yeah
everyone will be taking care of
each other
I'm listening
they're in one way of like maybe
peeling away
the representational layer
just expose it to people
I've tried that and it works
because I
I'll tell you this right
even the people there in the village
and stuff
in Central Java
it was very famous you know
spice trade Asia, immersion
people were discovering things
and all that stuff
from nothing
the village just became better
and better as humanity went on
but all of that is kind of like
blocked off by modern writing
and books and even anthropology
because
but okay this thing I want to tell you
once I'm in the village
I realize you know what
these people are the richest
people on planet earth
even though they are very little
currency
sorry there's a lot of currency
but very little money
yeah
why
yeah because money
money eats
the spirit of relation between humans
it does
it destroys that shit
it's like pouring acid there
to get rid of it
because now there's a single standard
to rule all things
like
the terror in the fantasy
story of the lord of the rings
one ring to rule them all is that
the ring that rules
the seven elvish magic rings
that keep the world alive
rules them is malignant
and that's money
the one ring that rules
them all in Tolkien's language
cash is the
best metaphor for it around here
it's hard to say
it's hard to say that it isn't
objectively
evil
because it's effect on the humans
okay look I could show you so many
features of this
god alright
I used to feed some blue jays
I met these blue jays
I'd bring them peanuts
I took great joy in feeding them
yeah
and the male would come to my hand
he'd land on my hand
take a peanut female wouldn't
okay
for important reasons
one day
the female got angry with me
and I didn't really understand why
what I had noticed was this
the blue jay couple
forms a vigilance pair
the girl stays up high
the boy can go down an adventure
only when the boy is up high
does the girl come down
oh shit I just realized that
fuck
so
I was interfering in that
and it would have been okay if I interfered
in it once or twice
a day
but it's not okay if I interfere
with it for two hours
and the reason it's not okay
is that they live in the terrain of a pair of
cooper's hawks and those hawks hunt blue jays
oh
alright so here's what I'm doing
I'm giving them the effect
I'm telling the story
yeah
if you put something in front of people
or animals
hmm
that's so compelling
that it not only changes their behavior
it changes what they
can be
right it drags what they
can be down
to fewer
much more explicit things
hmm
so
identity becomes binary
when I was throwing those peanuts on the ground
for the girl bird
because she wouldn't come to my hand
she was having
to go to the ground
without
radar above her
because the male
was off stashing the peanut I'd just given him
I wasn't
paying attention to their
vigilance necessities and I was providing them
the stimulus that was so compelling
that they would break
their culture
of mutual support
right it would break
that culture
yeah
it's so compelling that their bodies
it's like putting meat in front of a dog
right the body
is going to respond
you know if you
if you watch you know just put like a stack
$100 bills tie it up
with a rubber band
and put it on a street
and watch the humans
like it will drag their behavior down to
you know
the most likely
yeah
it captures the nervous system
can you see that it's
a representation
that's powerful enough to completely capture
the nervous system of an animal
and for the blue jays that's peanuts
and for the humans that's cash
or these days crypto
and overall
it's because I mean
if they were enough
of what I'm saying like zero crime
villages right
meaning there's
okay I have to ask you
sorry go ahead if there were enough of the zero crime villages
okay if there was enough
of that
and people go and live inside there
like say my wife comes from Indonesia
despite all the amount
of money
quite a lot of immigrants who come here
work here want to stay in Malaysia
you know they come from around the region
with much poorer places maybe like
Nepal or
used to be Thailand
Sri Lanka
countries that have got constant
political problems and stuff
so
people
really have a tough time finding a job
and stuff like that
when they come here many of them they want to stay here
because life is better
for them here right
but this Indonesia
Java when they come here they want
to go back
why do they want to go back
they see their village
as the safety
the security of the village
the nest
is too cozy for them
want to trust
anything else they want to go back
go to the nest
so
what I'm saying is
oh I see wait
their way of life is so familiar
that the new way of life
even though it's amazing
they go back to the old one anyways
is this what you mean
yes or do you mean
not just old
it's not just old at least one thing
is add to the old
all plus I won't be sent into an old folks home
oh
right
they just
whatever comfort you may give
to them in an old folks home
they don't want it
they want to be
poor with their kids
their grandkids
they want to care
and be cared for
by family members
who know their idiosyncrasies
not some institution
okay that was brilliant
yes that's very very true
I would almost go so far
as to say that for most of us
that is
a implicit
feature of our human
experience is that
as we get older
most of us soften
and we become vulnerable
and
it's
loneliness is much more difficult to bear
than it was
when we were younger
and we may be infirm and have illnesses
and we may need help with certain things
so that
if I'm in a house where there's children around
I feel relatively safe
if there's something I can't handle
they can take care of it
you know
or my
brothers and sisters
there's family
and if there's not family there's the neighbors
and they are family
humans naturally
do this they family up
unless
something gets in between them first
and one of the main things that gets in between them
at least where I live
is money
the fact that you guys don't have that
see
in the village
the lack of the importance of money
is almost like saying
we get water that isn't
we get relational water
that hasn't been pre-poisoned
you see
it's the same thing you said earlier
you said I
what did you say
I'm in
I'm inclined to
unconditional love
or something like this
and I said no you just never defected
the villagers don't defect
there's nothing that would motivate them to defect
a big stack of money
they might just laugh at it
and say like no
hmm
you know
I mean
to add to what you're saying
the helicopter
they kind of bail out
of their village for a while
to get some money
to build a house
once they get that
minimum amount they're back
and they don't want to be
in the town anymore
they want to be back in the village
familiar people
that's hilarious
do you see how much more intelligent that is
than what we do
in a situation like that
where everybody has a shot at surviving
and so do the relationships
that most matter
in your heart
in the other place
where they just go to the village
and they stay there
I mean they go to the town
to get the money
and then they just stay there
they continue to stay there
because they bought extra houses
they're dying inside
they're dying
they're going to live
after they die
I mean they're not going to die
they must
leave so much wealth to the next generation
things will be better
no they create
everybody is doing it
crime culture
you know despite
disparity what we have
yeah it's funny because
I think it's really important when I hear you speak
you say
and
I'm not sure
that a lot of people even know
that such things exist
at all
in the world
obviously
yeah no most people would be like
what does that even mean
although the statement
makes it real you know the language makes it
relatively clear what it means there's no crime in here
but
and by the way if there's no crime
like you probably don't
you don't really need cops
you might need a fire department
but you don't need cops
and you don't need weapons
you don't need lawyers
you don't need guns
yeah you don't need an anti-corruption body
yeah
right right right
you don't need courts
you don't need prisons
all of the people correctness
the most ugliest things
is like
cosmeticized dirt
it's really dirty
but you put lots of makeup
and you stop anybody saying the truth about it
yes
yes all these things are
I mean
I usually don't think in religious
terms but when I see
the festering malignance
of the prisons and the courts
and the cops and the armies
and the military and so forth
it's hard for me not to think
that they're demons
they do
what actual demons would actually do
so it doesn't really matter
whether their origin is metaphysical
or not they're the same damn thing
now look
here where we live
in the west in America
the institutions
that
that underlie
our
social agreements
our governments
which is
a big mess of a million little
branches
our police
the military
the fire department
the hospitals
the schools
those things
yeah
some of them are decent
we couldn't get along
without cops because shit would just turn
into the wild wild west we think
so we have to have
cops
and sometimes the cops are
an absolute nightmare
and sometimes they save your life
they sort of have both
both valences
the fire department almost always
just does good
you know is put out fires
okay
of all the single jobs
you could pick that one seems pretty
virtuous the hospitals kind of similar
the schools
the schools start to get sketchy because
it's about slave making and stuff
but
do you think universities are worse than the schools?
the intensity
of the
light
the intensity of the disease
in the university is
similar
to grade schools
in high school
it's just more sophisticated
and highly complex
let's just call this
the malware in the education
system
it's in every
step
it's in every step of the system
so the malware is in the whole
staircase but the way
the malware works up near the top of the staircase
and the universities is different
and there's you know 15 new kinds
as of last year
that stuff is mutating
right as fast
as you could try to eradicate it
it's
emerging in new forms as you
watch it
it's very
it's highly
resistant to
technical intervention
it's primary vulnerability
is relational
intervention change the relationships
the malware can't
function
hey Darren
would the US
have less of a problem
less of a
problem
if it wasn't
if it was
five separate countries
not messy
it's interesting
okay the honest answer is of course
we don't know
the simple
wait let me finish
the simple correct answer is
any attempt
at responding would obviously just be my opinion
whereas some of the things
that I'm talking about are not merely
my opinion these are
in a sense
obvious features of our situation
but
I think
that solution
or that transformation
would change a lot of things
we've never really experienced anything
much resembling it
I don't have any data
and it's not like we're just asking
in a vacuum we're asking
in the time and context in which we live
so we're asking like
if the US split into five bodies in 2024
you know
what effect do you think
that would have on malware and education
one
feature of the setup that I like
is
if you've got five petri dishes
in which to attempt to
spawn
something
more intelligent than our educational system
you'd have five shots at it
instead of one
but you can actually have
as many shots as you want
because the fact that
you know
I mean anybody who wants to is free
to start some kind of new educational system
most people aren't that bold
and there have been attempts
in the states we have Waldorf schools
for example
which are wildly different
from standard educational system
you don't hear much
talked about
what happens to Waldorf students
for example as
they go hard
are they
better citizens than the others
because
I don't know what the data is on that
what is that Rudolf Steiner's game
I think it was
yeah Rudolf Steiner as well
one of my girlfriends
had been raised in a Waldorf school
and I'd known a couple of other people
who were
and even when I was young
some of the same
ideas were used to
build
a school that had one classroom
for all the ages
so like a central eye
like you know unity
we'll keep all the ages together
they can learn together
help each other
instead of segmenting them
didn't go very well
for who knows 10 reasons to Sunday
but
but yeah I don't know
it will go well because
the malignancy
spread across so many aspects
yes look
look
you know I can imagine
a science fiction story where we go
to
we pick
70 billionaires
and we go to them
and we tell them
we will educate your children
we will give your children an educational
experience that they will
always be excited about
and they will outperform anything you can buy
from anyone else
and so you build the system
experimentally that way
you learn how to do that
right that way
and then you just attack
the whole fucking school system from there
with the same
with whatever you can produce from that breeder reactor
right
how do we actually get children
meaningful
human experience
and at the same time deep
representational intelligence
and one of the best ways to do that is just to
teach them the
structure of representational cognition
once they see that
they will never bow to it
they will manipulate it from above
just like humans should always do
it's okay if we have representations
we have to manipulate them from above
we have to not be manipulated
we have to not be puppeted by our own
representations does that make sense
yep
and you can teach this
this is teachable stuff
right this is stuff we could discover
those features of language
and modern thought
those features simple
semantic and linguistic and philosophic features
that you could teach to children and adults
that would mostly
free them
at least in their minds
from I don't know
68% of the traps
they're going to face in consciousness throughout
their lifetime
like
we're walking around wearing like
iron cages in our minds
us humans
so far most of us
I am myself included to the degree
that I live in a city I'm
subject to the same
problem
I'm a prisoner dreaming of a jailbreak
where it sounds like for you
you know where outside the jail is
and you intend to get there right quick
yep
yeah
is Benji with you
wow
say that again
is Benji with you where you are
yeah I mean
I thought I heard him
barking oh not right now
no not right now
earlier he was
he was just staying here
before I started talking to him
yeah cause I heard him
okay okay
yeah
it's quite a character once
but
it's saved my sanity
now so
it has me
to really much better understand
the village scene
cause you get lost one of the things
is
me too
I wanted to achieve
you know you've got this right
so
all kinds of people like not just
everybody like 10 out of 10
100 out of 100
1000 out of 1000 people
only know achievement by hey
how much wealth do you have
that's what I said
yeah it's a sick standard
that
turns everything to one thing
so when you ask them you know
determine your value
as a person
they want to know what property you own
who you're married to
you know are you
are you well bred
do you come from power
do you come from money
like for example
you know I got suspended by
LinkedIn you know
of being forthright
because fellas were
doing con job in Singapore
so I was like stop
I mean just generally it pisses me off
like nobody
speaks up against a
blatant con
yeah okay I agree
but let's agree
together that we will try to
discover how to do things that are effective
yep
right so that even
if we take on some kind of small
mission together even the mission of this
conversation cause this you know this works
then let's just have
the some simple agreements
I'm not trying to write these in stone
but we will try to help each other see better
and if action is required
we will try to find very effective ways
to act
because LinkedIn
is like putting a
firecracker in the fire department
like they're just waiting
for someone to go sideways
it's the same with Facebook
those are battlegrounds
that's enemy
own terrain
this is part of why I am
careful
mostly careful on Facebook
it's funny you know
a few days ago I did something I
never ever do
I posted
some comments from a news
source on a political
issue
and it wasn't any
rowdy it wasn't any specifically radical
statement
over the next two weeks
that post got zero views
none
no one saw it
wow shadow ban
yeah not an accident
so devious isn't it
such a devious thing to do
well I'll tell you
Valala
there's we could
we could take that model
and flip it over
that model
okay
that thing gives us a model of what not
to do
if you have a really good model of what not
you can flip it over
and no one will not want to be there
like
I have a model of how to build a system
on the internet
that
puts this back together
keeps all our data and communications
private
okay helps us get smarter
every time we make a move
with a machine of any kind
okay yep
and produces a social
adventuring system
so that people form teams to
accomplish you know
instead of putting a ball through a hoop
right
we accomplish something in the actual world
of humans
you've been developing it
I have a model
I can show you a model of how we could do it
and also
here's the thing that's actually
a little more compelling
okay the way
that system works is a model of how we can play
together
without machines
we don't need machines to do it
we naturally do it together
hmm
if most of the malware isn't running
we naturally do this together
I'm just trying to
demonstrate that there's a way that we can take
the electronic infrastructure of the internet
and do something completely
the opposite of what we're doing with it
and it would be
everything that currently exists
and it would I mean
there's so many abilities you could have
with it
that we don't have
and look I'm not a big fan
of link the humans to machines
that's not
my favorite game plan by a long shot
the problem I have
is that the humans are linked to
machines
hmm
we might want to capture some humans
and give them a shot at liberty
or at least discovering
what that might mean
we might need to capture their machines
yes
we might need those
machines doing something different
then what they're doing
like something non vampiric with the humans
yep
these are just thoughts but
I do
I think very deeply about these matters
because I want
I want the experience
of being with other humans
doing meaningful things
that's what I actually want
yep
really
say that much
because
I
like
I just
I kind of like
when I said enough of these machines
I just run away
yes
both go
I don't want to explain
and be politically correct
and use the language to
just go
hey
but I hear you
100% on
I tend to do things
more effectively than I
have
meaning
in the transition
you have to get into the machines
that they are attached to
to get them off the machines
for example
if all the kids are going to have phones
we have to give those kids
something on their phones
that it doesn't eat them alive
and
to even
get them to instruct them
to get them to work together
on an offline activity
and
what I have in mind
as I talk to you here
is confederating and intense
making a bit more intense
village life
in a village and small town life
in Indonesia
a country of 20 million people
one of the
last bastions of reality
you know
the funny thing is
it's ironic
if you
one of the questions that I had
in our conversation
for you that I haven't asked you yet
is do you want your village to have a voice
yes
with which it speaks to the world
okay so I thought
perhaps this might be so
and what I'm trying to tell you is
that's not
impossible
but to protect the village
that voice might have to be anonymous
sure all of that's good
if okay but if something
if the world realizes
there's a zero crime village
that's not gonna go well dude
that will not go well
because they'll come over
then they'll think
they'll get past it is it
there's 15 things
that can go wrong with that
but I did have the same idea
early in our conversation I thought to myself
wait
there's a zero crime village
holy cow like we need to get these people on the radio
to the other villages
we need to link the zero crime villages
around the world
these people need to have a voice
and then I thought wait a minute
that sounds like
setting up a
sky beacon to 15
different kinds of vampires
just like I can't wait
to extract whatever nectar they're managing
to produce over there
and commodify that and bank the
bank the profit
you know
I've said that you know what it is
a whole bunch of things
has it like it's not that easy
I'll give you a few examples
if you go to India
if you go to even Malaysia
pretty much
all good sources of natural water
from the mountains
has been taken over by a Nestle
or a company like that
this is what I mean by vampires
they're straight up vampires
they go after the water
I'm with you
they know how to do the TV
advertising and the search engine
all that stuff
we'll give you candy bars
you know
but
in Indonesia
the politics
is such
that it's very hard to
it seems like
many layers
and it's not
it's not mainstream
it's not organized so that you can say
this is one layer
this is exactly
it's just kind of like a bit all over the place
so it's like
meaning for example to get the mountain water
right by a Nestle
they have to get 18 different approvals
and those
they're not in 4 or 5 camps
they're like all over the place
so you can't
people don't try
seems like they try and give up
and it doesn't go anywhere
so they go after a few things
like national telephone
they can get somewhere
but not anything that has got
too much of a regional
local footing
like water from a river from a mountain
whoever
the people
in the villages nearby
the people affected by that river
have enough of a sea
and sometimes have enough of a
stop it
doesn't get there
so yeah
I can't
explain exactly all why
but one big difference
between Indonesia
and quite a lot of
the rest of the world
I mean this just makes me think
I'm sorry to say this but it just makes me think
Nestle is right now talking
to Bard about how to break that trap
right Nestle is going to
straight up use AI and go like
okay this trap has 19 parts
for this
here's three solutions with a 70% chance
of success and here's 19
with a 58
that will not last
that safety won't last
I mean who knows what's going to happen
the world is wildly unpredictable
we could be living in a
from now on it might just be like a storm
of black swans
events that we never predicted
but
there's certainly much
more of those now than there
ever were
in our lives
but go ahead
somehow
you know
the alternative
to me like life in Malaysia
has gone downhill and when I sense
the US has gone downhill
at a very fundamental
give the individual
in a
soul
you know
I mean
like
why must there be like
virtually no choice except to be
to go into an old folks home
why can't the family unit be together
I mean what's
yes because
it's the difference between a modern culture
and a traditional culture
and look
some
in some nations
there is still
traditional culture there's even some of it
here in the United States where the children
just naturally care for their parents and grandparents
and so forth
but mostly it comes from other countries
because
for some reason
during the origin of this nation
that value
was not
emphasized
it was much more about
the privilege entitlement
defection
and addiction of the individual
you know like I said is basically
just malware
it's relational malware
or you know perhaps that's one useful way
to think about it it's not the only way
but yeah that tradition wasn't preserved
if you go to Japan it's there
I don't know how much in
various places in China it is
Russia is a bit more like
the United States
France and England
more like
the United States but some other countries
the tradition is alive
and in most
countries that didn't suffer
eradicative colonization
that tradition
you know
lives
it's naturally I think it's naturally
human it's not the only game
in town but I think it's naturally
human
I mean the problem
in modern countries is we want convenience
and grandma and grandpa are wildly
inconvenient
I'd rather defect by watching some
comedy channel on TV
than deal with you know
whatever's going on with my ancestors
it's a defection based culture
sorry go ahead
there is other ramifications too
like all folks right
yeah
no the all folks who like the children
sorry go ahead
no like the whole
90%
for example 90% of
medical expenses
of that sort right
it's incurred in the last year
of a proper person's life and stuff
and like that's not why not die
a year earlier
yeah
well the main reason
you don't want to die a year earlier
is because there's nothing has been fulfilling
in your life you've been living a life
of just defecting from
whatever you might have otherwise
participated in
it's very safe
but it's extremely lonely and boring
I mean like
you die in your village
together with the other people
and so you're not drug
onto
onto a really hopeless
medical system
and you know
supposedly wants to
keep you alive but
it is actually vampiric
yeah
literally it just sucks
the life out of you and then it sucks the money
out of your family for sucking the life out of you
it's like a double vampire
I mean if someone said hey would you want
it on this game we're gonna suck the life out of this person
you're gonna get that life and we're gonna suck the money out of their family
you're gonna get the money you want some
a lot of people would sure say yes
so
and come on
with all the challenges
and don't you think
don't you think
AI would be used to like
make this explicit and
this is not really
this is a forced in bargain
that's not a bargain
yeah I mean
although the problem is that the AIs
are curated and it would be
just as much of a problem if they weren't
like the humans have really invented
something very
very dangerous here
and it's not without
promise
but as we know
from looking historically at humans and
technology
that shit goes
sideways right
after the idealism
is overcome
by piracy
today
despite all
the negatives
of the US
medical insurance system
and how it's based
and all that stuff
enough
let's say at the
public intellectual level
enough of us know that
also in Canada
seems to be doing it a bit better
in other European countries
Australia seems to be doing it better
than the US
exactly there are examples of countries
that do it pretty well we might imagine
okay but
that doesn't seem to be portable
into the US
we can't look at a guy who gives an excuse
oh we are the US
okay look
what you don't okay look the problem
here is that
and this is an
ironic problem
we actually call this country
the US
that is the word us
and that
along with many
unfortunate features
of our history
incline
the citizens of the United States
to think
in a way that is fundamentally
black and white
fundamentalistic
you know it's fundamental in its
fundamentalist
in its understanding of us
and them
who are we and who are they
and most of the us's
are fake
right the same way most of them
are
but if you identify with one of those fake us's
you inherit a bunch of them
and this is a kind of an us and them
economy
that the US is amazing
at
it's like being amazing at
filling your own organs with cancer
or something relationally
it will never work intelligently
but this is
a fundamental problem with us
yeah it's bad
despite the fact that
I mean your states
and municipalities have enough
independence for example
I do
but Miami goes up
yep
they can
but they generally don't because
the malware
the influence
of the malware is powerful
right
politics in the United States
is a lot about
what
various kinds of theft
counterfeiting value
more effectively than your opponent
get the money
and then
a sort of
complex back room favor
exchange among politicians
so
it's like
the structure of the system might be
sound we've never implemented
that system does that make sense
it's just a layer of
it's like a multi-layer
cake of seven kinds of piracy
floating on top of the structure
as it stands as a legal
or
you know sociological
agreement system
mostly the structure
doesn't get implemented
what gets implemented is piracy
and vampirism
Ramaswamy
was running
for a while and
articulates that you can sense that
for example
he talks about
getting rid of the
FBI
Trump
because Trump was
caught by the civil servants
that you can't
there are too many laws
that stop you from firing
civil servants
but
Ramaswamy was saying that
that is the case when you're
firing individual civil servants
but if you're having a mass
restructuring
the law allows you to do that
and with
the Supreme Court as it's stated
as it's constituted
because it's got
enough of a majority of Trump appointing
a conservative
who are ready for
who see the sense
of
the president has the right
to restructure the FBI
by executive order
I mean this guy is
possibly even the constitution
I mean
Trump is basically
okay
Trump
is really dangerous
in my view for two reasons
the first is that he is
successfully circumvented
regulation in the past
and
the second is that
he has not only
he has no respect for regulation
he's a scoff law
right and a scoff law
will
earn the vote of
every male scoff law
in the United States just for that one
reason
and okay the third thing that's dangerous
about him is he has shown
much smarter people
what is possible
and what he has shown is possible
is as follows
the United States as a nation
can be captured
by a single male human being
he's shown them that
he's basically shined a flashlight
on a part of the game
that nobody really believed
was possible he's doing the impossible
he's going from
he's gonna go from 0 to 100
he's gonna have a go at the impossible
and he's old enough that he probably doesn't
give much of a shit if he fails
he's got nothing to lose
right it's all
anything he gets done is gravy
right
like he can do anything
that works
so yeah this is
this is dangerous shit
he's shown others
who are much more intelligent than him
that the prize can be had
you can take the virgin home with you
for sure
you can have a whole family
you know
that whole thing you can just grab that whole
damn thing in one fell swoop
right and here's how you do it
you start with these moves over
here you place some judges on the Supreme Court
Bing bang boom
casino payoff
right that's really
dangerous he's shown others that it
can be done
he's relatively stupid in my view
or at least he plays that face really well
but
damn what a fucking dangerous
idiot oh my god
but
hey Darren
when you had Hillary
you know running against
Hillary Clinton running against
didn't it occur to you
that my god the US has failed
if these people
are running for president
that's brilliantly said but yeah
no that occurred to me
some
okay I'm pretty sure
that occurred to me when I was six
and I watched
John F. Kennedy being executed
in Texas over and over again on TV
and you know
juxtaposed with some of his speeches
no that dream died
in me a long
time ago my friend
I mean I was born
the month after Kennedy
was executed and I've seen
that guy speak
I've never seen anything
in politics resembling
the appearance
of true human
virtue
that I saw in him
I note that it's the appearance
I'm not saying the guy was a saint
I'm saying
in a room full of demons
he stood out brightly
and that happened only a couple
times during my lifetime
you know
Carter might not have been a great president
but he wasn't evil
so to me like
if you can allow
a contest like that
you fail and what else
can you expect of a failed
system apparently
I think most Americans expect
that the failure of the United States
has to end
with a bunch of bloodshed and violence
preferably as much as possible
maybe even apocalypse level
right if we're going to go out
we're not going to switch
to a new system
we're going to take the planet with us
just like any insane psychopath
we're not going to try a new way
of doing this
we're going to blow shit up
because
there's a feature
in private cognition
that can be inflamed enough
and the human societies resemble
the shadow
of this problem
so
the kid who
alright
I could probably tell you
a lot about what happens
when some
kid picks up an automatic weapon
and goes to a public place
and just opens up on the people there
because what's happening in that kid's mind
is
a reflection
of a feature
of our society
and that feature is
I will win
whether I
deserve to or not
and if I don't win
everybody dies
there's a feature of private cognition
in that way
there's a feature of our own minds
that works that way and it gets reflected
in the social cognition
of modern humans
and that's the thing that produces
stuff like
I don't know
Hitler, Putin invading Ukraine
maybe there's stuff
I don't know about that move
but that looks insane to me
from outside
Israel pounding Gaza into dust
not dissimilar except in that case
somebody punched them first
so it seems
yep
I think the people there
I remember when 9-11 happened in the United States
I had two thoughts
the first was
15 people just changed the course
of the nation in 12 hours
wow I thought it could be done
and then the second was
oh my god are we in trouble now
we're gonna go chasing the wrong
we're gonna go killing
the wrong
scapegoat
for
yeah we're gonna kill the wrong scapegoat
and that's gonna create
a future
of enmity and hatred
and blood oaths of vengeance
and things like this
both thoughts
now I'm not an advocate
of changing the course of nations with violence
I want to be very clear about that
but I did notice that a very small
group of humans in this
was like the course of I don't know 48 hours
they
radically altered the course of an entire
nation that made me realize
that the principle was real
small number of people
I just imagine the
I'm trying to figure out what's the opposite
of a bomb and how do we make one
what's the opposite of a bomb
yeah what's the human relational
opposite of a bomb
and how do we make one
I want to make the opposite of a bomb
I want something that
heals things back together
explosively and contagiously
it just starts crystallizing
the whole network toward
intelligent unity
I can imagine it
I can see it in my mind
it's possible
yes yes yes
it's positive
it doesn't occur to me right now
but what occurs
to me is I come across
such
what appears to be
opposites but they may just be complementary
at a level that
I'm not
familiar with because
it's not discussed enough
you and me
what you're writing is so rare
but it's so appealing
and it would be even better
if there were a few more people
who could engage at your level
so that there can be interaction on it
not just pedantic
interaction as to what do you mean
and what do you mean
people doing their own
homework right
and then reflecting and then
passing
and weaving
or actually
initiating projects
even better
doing stuff together
that's what I want to do
I'm good at
cuddling people together
you know
a lot of people
because of low confidence
I like to say
oh I don't understand
come come come
look we can take them
to nursery school
if that's the case
we can do very simple
exploratory
stuff together
so that they get a taste for the water
they don't have them in the water
they don't have to become
mercenaries or something
right
we just introduce them to the water
a little bit at a time and say
hey are you comfortable here
okay let's go to the next step
beautiful
we can learn
together how to do this
in the same way your mother
attended
the mind of your childhood
we can start out
with the presumption that we're all
intelligent, playful, creative
human beings together
and then we can just make simple
moves
like a kid learning how to stand up
we can do it
it's not hard to do
humans naturally are good at this
you can get them doing this kind of thing
I think
I do have a small group
I experiment with
we try some actual stuff
I'm not just talking
and I'm not
I guess I'm afraid
of being pedantic
I want to be active
not pedantic
okay
you want to be substantial
I mean you want to
do
yeah let's fail
as long as we're doing something no problem
yep
that's it
and as you were mentioning
I was thinking of the school
in my village and the kids
I wonder about that
that must be amazing
what's that like have you been in there
have you been in a classroom do you know
how they relate with the children
the
the school is not good
the school is not great
it doesn't open them
but they're not bad compared to
other schools as well
they're not too kind of like a nannish
or monitor
they're not that either
on the other hand they don't
they don't allow for any creativity
they want them to follow the rules
yeah it sounds typically western
or worse
yeah regimented
regimented so
but
when the kids come out of school
back to their villages
back and all that
to me they're learning a lot
when they're playing
with their families
they're imitating their dance
they're preparing
because parents are preparing
for somebody's wedding or feast
they're helping out and they're watching
watching over people
and parents are also going to
to the plot of land
and planting rice
they're helping the parents
with planting the rice
and tending to the garden and stuff like that
overall
they're apprenticing
the bigger role for them is not
what I go to school and then after school
I was going to get a job no
in the case of the girls
I'll be
my mother
they become good mothers
and they become good healers
taking care of people
they seem to learn
because it is traditional
to take care of each other
yeah
so we just need to expand
that to because
expand that to hey
whether you choose to do it at home
or you choose to do a bigger thing
between villages
medical things or even computers
all the other things
that you need to do in today's world
it's not you'll get bullied
by countries that do
with weapons
you've got to act together
to a level that
you're able to defend yourself too
you're productive enough
making enough returns
so that's enough of your people can be soldiers
like they were like societies were
I know but now
will come the malware
I'm afraid
once
it's like it comes with
the police and the soldiers to have soldiers
you have money problems
you need money
now what will happen to the village
I am afraid I hear you though
will you continue with your thought
I see so good
I like your candidness
because you know what
when you mention that
one thing I agree
pay attention to that
what do we do about it
how do we anticipate it
the other thing that comes to me is
when the
societies were very strong
the villagers
didn't have police
they didn't need
any arms
to have the strongest villages
because
they were able to anticipate
somewhat like in nature
how is it that
there is quite a lot of law and order
in a tropical forest
I mean we think of
actually there's
not law and order
I'm not sure that there's a lot of
well maybe I'm not understanding you
properly yet
I'm not sure there's a lot of law and order
there's a lot of non
not defecting
but go ahead
do you mean law and order between
the insects and the plants and the animals
do you mean that kind of law
or between tribes
no I mean
between the 10,000 species
okay yeah
I mean there's something there
I don't think it's law and order
it's intimacy
right it's one animal
in a billion bodies
so they don't defect from intimacy
therefore no laws
are required and there are no orders
so you see like
they can share the same I mean like
you have birds and you have insects
and lizards and ants
and they can have
like
kind of like unawaresly share the space
yes
yep
but if the lizard get hungry
the insect better move
if the bird gets hungry
yeah
all of that but you know like
when you're walking through a forest
whatever that seems like a minority
the exception is
share the food
but that is not the
versus
in the case of human beings
we've made it like the capital issue
and it's not just
we've made it it really is
a big deal that
we
we've gone downhill
yes
no we're collapsing toward
the worst potentials
of our species
rapidly
we're
we're all contributing to this collapse
actively
instead of doing any other thing
and mostly I think it's because
A we don't know what to do
and B it doesn't pay as well
thankfully
now I'm old enough I don't care
I want to do something
meaningful
if I have to pay to do something meaningful
fine
let's go
okay
yeah I want to
I want to run the experiments
Darren this model that you
have right
would you
do you think it has to be done in the US
or it can be done in another country
or it can be done it would be very
be very radical
it could be done somewhere else
but yeah it could be done anywhere
okay in fact
I argue I would argue that it's
basically what nature usually
is up to
she's just observe nature
she's doing
this set of things that
humans could do really well together
and they naturally do it really well
together wherever that isn't captured
or interfered with
okay
but yeah the system
as a system it could be done
anywhere
it can be done with existing technology
it would change
I honestly I don't believe
if we could actually produce what I have in mind
I don't think governments
would last another four years
we can do something so much better
than governments that I'm really shocked
nobody's had the idea
to do that
okay great great
so
what
basically you can envisage
the model that you have in mind
and I can imagine
the model you have in mind
and within it
teams of five for example
doing problem solving
and add it together
yeah they can
synergize with other teams easily
in fact they're highly motivated to synergize
with other teams
okay
essentially there's a kind of money
which is something more like fulfillment
that we can pay the humans
and they can also make money
with the analytics they produce
without those analytics being traced
to them personally
so that they can have privacy
fantastic
because that's what I mean
in like in Indonesia
they like that
they pretty much want that
because they're not
totally free from their
military phobia
yes for good reason
eventually the soldiers will come
they may not be here today
but someday they are coming
you know
right everyone knows this
all the old people know it
yes yes yes yes
so they I mean like on Facebook and stuff
all of them don't use their own names
right why would you use your own name
it doesn't make any sense
for most purposes it's dangerous
please
Darren were you
were you in the internet
when there wasn't any
any web and stuff
that was just mailing lists
I'm a computer technician
I've been working with computers
since 1981
I've done
some programming I watched
the birth of the internet
long ago
in the beginning we used to have
what were called bulletin board systems
yeah
you know you would dial
yeah bbs is you'd dial up with it
you'd have a 1200 or 2400
modem
you'd dial up with a modem
you'd have some sort of a
validation
exchange with the server
and then
you were a user on a bbs
most of those were used for
sharing cultural
objects
art
porn
computer programs
games
particularly
media
yeah
why I asked Darren
the early days of the internet
pretty much there wasn't any
pseudonyms
the mailing lists
maybe the
soft culture
wait are you sure
in what
bbs was it not
pseudonymous
because you had user names
yeah bbs
in the beginning of the internet
yeah
oh yes
mostly true
campus background
maybe because of the
economic background
because I worked
at that time I was working
for a complete ip shop
in Toronto
oh yeah
and I saw
the value of us being able to
recognize this guy
and see
you know
in a trustworthy situation
well you'd still probably want
the option of pseudonyms
but in a trustworthy situation
you'd use your
your primary name
yep
I imagine
although you know with indigenous
cultures
they didn't have names like
Bob or Tony
I mean
and their names would change
under certain conditions
it seems
to me
yep
like if you marry into a new
yeah there's lots of conditions
that would change your name
why do you mention it
so okay let me make sure I'm hearing you
so you're saying something like
I remember conditions
under which it was very useful to know
precisely who I'm speaking to
no
masquerading
were you saying
something like that
going
going to the heart of the matter
just like you said
don't
the speaker should not be
should not be split
from the speech
the stage value
right yeah
yeah I mean on the other hand
there's 10 different people inside
me and it's not because I'm schizophrenic
I'm human
ah yes yes yes
so now what
must all of them bear the responsibility
for the voice of any of them
yes yes
no no no
well I don't know I'm not saying yes or no
I'm just saying
I hear you
it's a complicated question right
like I want to actually entertain the question
hmm
yeah yeah I think
what is this for enough for some
for enough things
maybe all you know
maybe the ethical things
we want to
the issue is
where do we want accountability
and where do we want this
and I would say that
um
most of the time when we want
accountability
something has gone
really badly wrong already
right like
yeah by the time
we need accountability
relational intimacy is broken down
dramatically
why don't you want the exploratory
and why do you want them to wait till they
are sure before they open their mouth
why don't you want them to come in
with the explanations
why don't you have language
that explicitly allows
enables that
the worst thing
it's not the only truth
but a fundamental principle is like
once
human cognition becomes oriented
toward indicting someone
or something
it breaks down
it's no longer very intelligent
it's making a mess
the
vulnerability of the space
the spacemen allow for lots of vulnerability
yes
yes yes I mean
that's more brilliant than what I would say
um that's really brilliant
what you're saying there
you're saying um
it's crucial that we allow
um
the play
the natural play
of explorative learning
and discovery and making mistakes
and getting it wrong
you know
um and all kinds of other things
that disappear once
go ahead
it should be children ready you know
yeah
I mean
what a brilliant thing
you with your expansion
made it for me
yeah but you
you were the one who said this first
I only tried to see
what you were saying I was like no he's saying something
even more radical than what you're saying Darren
what I was saying was
um
by the time you're interested in indictment
you've lost most of your intelligence
and I find this to be true of myself
but you said something crazier
you were like
uh in an actually trusted
relational
in context
the free play
of mistake
doesn't lead and you know
experiment and discovery and learning
doesn't lead to judgment it leads to mutual
benefit or something like this
yeah yeah yeah
yeah that's crazy
all of this
you can't say that
who told you you could say things like that
you
mustn't go around saying things like that
the humans will get ideas
so that's it
you know like
what are you doing
basically
hey there
essentially allow the kids to teach you
yes
hey this is how we do it
this is how we dig a hole
or how we catch a tadpole
come you know
teachers have been stopping us
and we go inside
and say you can't
laugh or whatever the teacher
can you give us a break
you make the club something
distract her
when you go back to learning from the kids
and then
what do you think some outcomes
make the old school teacher happy too
yes
exactly right
you can please the old guard
and innovate at the same time
right
doesn't have to be pure rebellion
you can please
you can please tradition and still innovate
yeah
so long as you're becoming patient
you're persistent
it should yield a better
the better result
the better outcome for everybody
absolutely many yes
patience
this doesn't have to be done in the next 10 seconds
that would work
right because the kids are smart too
you know
and
they're kind of like forced
to
accept the status quo
and the teachers too
finding maybe too difficult
because they're all busy
too much of an accent to it
how they have to do this
kind of a modern world
with too many details
too many chores
in a way
do you sense that
that is part of the reason why
the change is slow
and all doesn't happen
no the problem is worse
is that
the new teachers
should be free
to grow along
with the children
instead of to dictate
the direction of growth
to the children
and they know nothing but to dictate
that's it you know
to dictate
in english
I make a joke about this
it's like a person holding a hard penis
and they keep pointing it at you
they're dictating
I know it's a very crude joke
but
in english
that's a reasonable pun
and it makes sense
it's like they're hitting you over the head
with the hardened
member of authority
it's a shitty job
like no teacher would want
no teacher
would ever act that way
or want that if they were having the experience
of learning and growing with the children
and nobody's
going to tell me that we can't produce that
we got the teacher on site
we got the kids on site
you got them together
you should be able to pull off miracles
it might take you a little while to figure out
how but don't tell me you can't
I've seen it done
I've participated
in it in schools
where I had a teacher who was like
we're going to take the one kid
in this class who can't write
at all
and we're going to get that kid writing essays
that are powerful
and blow people away
I mean here's a secret
that will blow your mind
in 1990
or something
no way to
probably
I took an English class
I hadn't been in school since I was 12
I never went to high school
I'm a self educated person
I took an English class
because I'm a writer
and the teacher asked me to teach the class
for the next semester so I did
and what I discovered was pretty
amazing
so there were about 90 kids
they ranged in age from
16 to 26
we had three classes
of about 30 kids a piece
they were mostly upper middle class
white kids
most of them were like
B, B plus
average
coming into junior college from high school
of those 90 American kids
in a wealthy
suburb
suburban town
four of them could reasonably
produce a written sentence
in their only language
and two of them could
compose a paragraph
wow
those kids
sucked at understanding
or speaking or writing
the only language they
speak
they were abysmal at it
and I was blown away
because I'm hyperlexic
I have a natural
affine relationship
with language and particularly
English
I've been that way since I was very little
so for me
this was staggering and shocking
I was like
I wanted them to have more education than I had
and they had
catastrophically less education
than I had
though they had been
in school an additional
six years compared to me
and
kind of like
somewhat role model parents too
I suppose
I don't know
but
my parents weren't
particularly intelligent
but they did read
books
and they did read books to me
and I think my parents were frightened
a little bit I know my mom was
I don't think my dad was but my mom was scared
because
I remember
I was reading science fiction novels
when I was five
maybe earlier
who brought them
to you?
my parents I told them what I wanted
oh how did you know what
so like I had seen
advertisements for
2001 Space Odyssey
when I was watching Star Trek
and I knew what the book was about
and I read science fiction stories
already
myself I could read them by myself
so I asked my mom to get me that
book and she's like that's a grown up
book and I was like I want that book
that's the book I want to read
so then I got it and I read it
and my parents ended up reading it
and in a way
I was kind of educating them
because I had a lot of books
eventually I became a book thief
that's a story for another time
I only
stole books to read them
though I didn't steal like valuable books
and sell them
I stole books to read them
when I was a runaway
so I didn't have any access
yeah when I was a runaway
I used to steal books to read them
you said earlier that
you know
you thought yourself from 12 years old
like um
that would have been like
almost unheard of isn't it
no there are
there are um
okay especially these days
it's different now
there are a lot of children
who are
there's a cohort of young people
who naturally become self-educating
to varying degrees
some of them become prodigies
some of them become
nobody's right some of them just disappear
some of them go mad
because they're lonely
but yeah there's like
I know a couple other
every once in a while someone will sniff me out
and they'll approach me
and they'll go like
when did you
you know what were you reading when you were a child
and I'll say science fiction
and they're like how about when you were little
and I'll say science fiction and they'll go like
yeah that's what I thought
you know
um
because
recently somebody sniffed me out
and they were like you're one of you're just like me
you're a feral
you're a feral kid who lived
in the wilderness
and you're someone who's read
a few thousand books and not two
right
um
and they recognize the fingerprint
of my mind right and I recognize
there is when we have conversations
like I'm talking to my twin or something
it's ridiculous
yeah there are kids that are like that
I imagine all over the world
but like say if you were
like if you were
not going to school
were you still at home
I ran away from home
wow
I lived in the forest
in the Russian river
yeah
in California
wow
I mean
you just
find it hard to believe that people would do that
in a first world country
because
that's what
number two
I would have thought that the comfort
you want to mix of the two
not just be in the process
home that bad that you had
that you didn't miss it
I would have been killed if I stayed in that town
wow
I became
by most like the home
other young troublemakers
like myself
hoodlums
I went from being like a straight
A student
to being a little bit of a hoodlum
and where I was living
in Stockton
things were pretty bad there
even though we lived in the good part of town
and I eventually
ended up
in various kinds of trouble with
young criminals
now it's not as serious as like gang life
is that shit's really serious
this is pretty very minor
compared to that
but yeah I basically
I realized that
if I stay there
I realized if I stay here
I will either end up in prison
or dead
so
given that belief
anything's better
than either of those outcomes
pretty much anything
so even just like
like living outside
is better
so eventually I made it out
it took a few attempts
wow
and then you were able to
be out for years
on stretch
yeah I came home in like the last
half of 17 so I was
out for three and a half
something like that
okay
okay wow
your parents
your parents would have been
like
I mean both
so sad and mad no?
especially I don't know
this is very personal but
but my mom
was relatively indifferent
and I ran away to near where she was
living
because it was by visiting her
that I realized that there was this
enclave in the forest
where
it was a bunch of
basically old hippies
wow
so there was like this enclave
and it was very
richly cultural
unlike where I was living
which was like
zero culture like dead culture
so yeah I wanted
the culture I couldn't access
the culture because I wasn't an adult
but I didn't want to be
in Stockton anymore
trying to figure out how to steal cars
with my buddy so we could get some weed
or whatever the fucking
agenda was
yeah I just
I didn't want to be
in that place
anymore and I did not get along with my dad
who I was living with so
I went to the forest and
some adults helped me
I made it through okay nothing horrible
happened to me while I was on the street
I hitchhiked around
you know
didn't eat much food
a lot of fasting
oh
yeah
but
I hitchhiked through the US
really
hmm
wow that's crazy
yeah it was fun
yeah that's
really intense
in what year were you hitchhiking
I mean I'm hitchhiking in like
the late 70s early 80s
mine
was 1980
from
January say
oh wow yeah not at a similar time
let's see how old was I in 80s
hmm
but you know it's quite
I mean it was a different experience
I mean it was a rich experience
I stood out
like a sore thumb
yeah well
in the south
right it was like impossible
together
right yeah
and we learned some chords
and stuff so I said hmm how do I
overcome this
I've got to find a white guy
right
to
hitchhike with
brilliant yeah you have to hitchhike
by first hitch you have to
racially hitchhike before you
vehiculatively hitchhike
right
yeah that's hilarious
oh my god yeah
I came across the really
solid guy you know my house long
right and there was this guy
I was on my way first
just to go to a New Orleans for Mardi Gras
hey talk about that you know
we're talking in a very opportune
pertinent time because Mardi Gras
is going to be happening soon
in now to about this time
of the year right 1980
yeah
so I want to go to New Orleans
you know
so
with my buddy I'd reached up to Atlanta
right from college
hitchhiking with him to Atlanta
so I went to Atlanta
to New Orleans
three days day in day out
when I go to the exit you know which is a bit of a
it's not that easy to go
from downtown Atlanta
like Salvation Army or something like that
sure
to the exit
so anyway three days
and I couldn't get it right nobody was stopping
I knew it okay
so I said okay I'll take a greyhound
to New Orleans
I go to New Orleans and that was
heaven for me there was like
the hobos and the hippies from everywhere
for Mardi Gras
and that guy
looked like Jesus Christ in the hair
yeah
the oldest and self-blown hair
brilliant yeah
he didn't guru for him
so
because we got along
really quite well like
house and fire
so
yeah he had been
hitchhiking for like 10 years
so with him
the world was a different world
you know because
people would stop for him
I would be like back
back a bit in the back and when the class
stopped I would run
and people would see
they're safe enough so it's good
right
I went all around quite a bit of time
in Boulder, Colorado
and Kansas City where it's home was
and then
I wanted to
following the Grateful Dead
I was wanting to follow
to Mount McKinley
in Canada
but got stopped at the border
the Canadians wouldn't let me in
so I spent some time in Seattle
yeah no
I had a passport
it was best in all that
so it was always good
I went to University of Virginia
Charlottesville
but the student visa
runs out
after you are a student
you know the visa
has got a termination date
so when I
my plan was
to go to
to the concert
the last
Grateful Dead concert
happens in like
the equinox or something of that sort
you know
one of those dates
the day when there's
the largest amount of flight
in Alaska anyway
and I would come back because
the flight was out of Seattle
but the Canadians said no
your visa
your American visa
is
over
so they won't let you back into America
so since they won't let you back into America
we can't let you into Canada
I see
I did not need a visa to Canada
Canada being in the Commonwealth
Malaysia is in the
there was no need for a Malaysian
to have a visa to enter Canada
I see yeah
you know
but it was on the grounds that
I wouldn't be allowed to
leave
if my basis was
I was flying out of Seattle
I wouldn't be allowed to enter
I would not have enough money
and whatever
Canada can stop me from entering Canada
not on the grounds that
I don't have a visa
but on the grounds that do you have enough money
to sustain yourself when you're in Canada
yeah
that's reasonable in pretty much all the world
countries all over the world
have environment
exactly
I didn't prepare for that
because on the thing that
I'm just going to come
for the concert come back
get on my plane now I'm home
I don't want to be here
I mean
you have a short term goal
you know
I'm sorry go ahead
yeah me not
realizing immigration
things in a black and white
very strict way
that's pretty much the half tool
but
it didn't
fully occur to me
because in my head
I'm still in America because I'm going to Alaska
man
but
it didn't
register in my head
that hey
doesn't matter what you think
it's so funny you say that
it's really funny that you say that
because I was just thinking about
when I was a runaway and when I was hitchhiking
I was so naive
that it literally didn't
occur to me even
slightly
that I might
want to be careful
because what sort of an adult
picks up a 13 year old boy
on the side of the road
yes
never even occurred
to me
that I was filtering the adults
right
and I'm filtering them
in a specific direction
right which is has
some interest
in a 13 year old kid
now thankfully
only
I don't know how many times I was near
trouble
but only twice did I
actually get close to trouble
and both times
I was able to
to kind of like avoid them
yes both times I was able
to resolve the situation by
acting tough
yeah yeah
it drives past my stop
and I'm like hey my sauce
back there and he's
not speaking to me
and it's late at night
and we're out in the middle of nowhere
and I just basically said
I will
cut your fucking head
off with my pocket knife
I will stab you right now in the neck
if you don't pull this car over
and he was like boop
I got out
oh wow
oh so
did you actually have a knife then
yes I did
oh good
I used to carry a dagger
little dagger
you're not that naive then
I was
it's just that in this case
I realized
like
yeah
I can still be
I can still be very naive
I'm not cunning
the way some people are cunning
and I honestly
it never once
occurred to me
that most of the people that would like
that most of the people that would stop for a kid
that looked like me
would probably
have ulterior motives
or at least
a goodly you know some
portion of the people
never occurred to me one time
not once
is it
because okay
Darren
when I was in the US too
like
I mean
the country was a different country
in the sense that
I would have thought
it's
nowhere as dangerous as it is now maybe
me I would agree
yeah
also I was in a strange
I was
in a strange sub context
right I was in the Russian
river
so there's a lot of basically the three primary
okay this is going to be really bad
say here but
the three primary populations
there were rednecks, homosexuals
and hippies
and the hippies and the homosexuals
got along fine
the rednecks hated
both the other camps pretty much though
got along better with the hippies than
the gay people
so
that was the context there
and obviously
you know
yeah I could have gotten a lot of trouble
but I never did
I never did
no one ever hurt me
so growing up after the age of
leaving home
you hadn't been exposed to
the dangers of
such dangers as much
I was
you have no idea how naive I was
in your wildest estimations
you will underestimate my naivety
I was
yeah I was
I was very intelligent
and skillful
in certain ways
but my god was I naive
it's just one of the
feelings I've always had yeah
it never even
okay look let me be really clear
about this so you can understand the depth
not only did it never occur
to me that I was attracting the people
who would have some interest
in a 13 year old boy ever
it never occurred to me
not only that
that it didn't occur to me
until just now
40 something years later
50 years later
it never occurred to me
that it didn't occur to me until this conversation
today
that's how naive I am
wow
I never realized
that I didn't realize
until just now
yeah
it's that bad
you know
to me in my
when I got rights there
when I started getting rights and stuff
the people who were picking us up were so generous
that made a big difference
and innocent
usually it would be like a small town
you know the tour in some way
and then
at the back
yeah some of that too
and
all beautiful it was
right beautiful it was
I mean nowhere else in the world
I think I mean
would you get that
yeah it's true because the
counterculture in the United States
at that time was still
kind of blossoming
a little bit
and how old were you
were you like 18
20 or something
yeah I would have been
perfect
so
you know you present
to
the drivers
obviously
something they might
find fascinating
and
adventurous
to some of them
yep
so that works in your
favor but yeah it was pretty good like
most people were very kind
some people gave me
money or brought me food
some people asked me
you know like how do you survive
they were curious
occasionally
like if it was raining
or something somebody would be like hey
you can just crash at our place if you want
you know
and obviously that could be very dangerous
but never turned out to be
not once
because I mean I was 22
so it didn't occur to me
you know
anything would happen to me
I was least
concerned about it
to me it's like how do I get it right
I don't know the money
yeah that's all I was concerned with
too I was just like how do I get
to where I'm going I wasn't thinking about
why someone would
or wouldn't stop to pick me up
in other words
there was no
there was no meta reflection
right
there was no
there was no meta cognition
yeah
no meta cognition about my circumstance
whereas you
must have had some by your age
yeah
I mean
more
but you know violence wasn't
like you didn't have the school shootings
you didn't
yeah
the malware wasn't
concentrated yet
yeah
and
say for example
people may say okay
blacks are dangerous
but
right
I'm almost black
right exactly
so
you know
I'm more likely to see you as an ally
than as
an enemy or prey
yeah
and I wanted to try it
I had to
because part of
that was the American equivalent
of you being a sadu
of you being like
you know
that's funny yeah I got you
right yeah
that's a hilarious way of saying it
like you're
yeah it's the American version of you're a holy man
or something
oh no you have faith in nature
oh you have faith I see
I see that
come on don't be
yeah that's what I had actually
that is what I had back then
in a way
I had faith
that it was
possible to be myself
without a house
without a roof
without money
without food
with nothing
I
knew that
money would be an issue so I had to
watch out and you know
in our places we stopped
anyway we made it
because we could get jobs in some
places and
little short term jobs
especially
in Boulder Colorado
I remember
in 4th of July
around about 4th of July
I was there and it was snowing
right
in Boulder California then
it was a bit of a surprise but
that was good climate I mean they had
you know like a
job placement
for tramps and hobos
you know
but because I was with this guy called
Bernie
Bernie McGraw
yeah
he knew the ins and outs
where you go and get food stamps
and where you get
day jobs
and stuff like that so
rather quickly
after 4 days I got a job as a
dishwasher
in
Boulder
right and
you know that was fun and
the pay you get
compared to what you need is like
great because it was staying in like
in Boulder
after a while was staying in like
an abandoned
house in the edge of a river kind of
like in a forest right
so
we had sleeping bags and stuff like
rather
winter proof sleeping bags so
managed that was good you know
there were other people later
we met some people
and we lived in the house for a while
very liberal
I mean very truly liberal place
Boulder was when I was there you know
very
very generous
you know
the first day I remember too
I remember too
I tell you this
I
already I had rather little money
like 25 dollars or something
like that and I had a camera and stuff
and my buddy was hitchhiking with me
he said let me borrow your camera
and then he goes and fawns in
fucking
and so
because of that
I remember that day I had no more money
I had no more money and I didn't
have a camera and I was like
how am I going to solve this well
this is this I've got to
learn this and I've got to learn how to
be without any money so
I walk along
the street pearl street in
Boulder you know so downtown
one street
that is
walk only no cars
right so I think I walk
and I signboard right
on the side of a building and he said
Naropa
this is this
institute
me
wow this is like
next to bumfuck
U.S.
I mean
I'm not even Kansas City
Salina, Kansas by the highway
this is like
for me it's like nowhere
and how come it's got a Buddhist institute
this is my thing
this is my
culture yeah
in the middle of America
so I said I have to go upstairs
so I go up and I see you know there's
two guys and stuff and it's like a
conversation and they're so wonderful
they offered you know one of the guys
offered his place for me to stay in
because his buddy was
had gone off somewhere so there was
they can see
so come and stay with me and stay at my
place and it was great
you know beautiful
always the whole thing was beautiful
and Seattle
my last stop was fantastic
you know after by the time I reached
to like Seattle and stuff I'm on my own
but
I was walking you know I get
I was walking and this guy in a pickup
truck you know comes past me
stops
winds his window down looks at me and says
are you going somewhere
can I take you I was like wow
because
you know they were
they could see me
and I'm like wow it was
great it was because
I
to me
the folks then in Seattle
were like a great above the rest of the world
they were like really
friendly to
it is actually okay there is
something weird about
it
how to put this
so I have
not traveled much
I've mostly only been
in central and northern California
throughout my entire life I've been
basically nowhere
but a couple times I traveled
a couple times I traveled a little bit
and I went
for example to Oregon
or Washington State
and
I don't know
I think
that because I'm not well traveled
I probably have a
a distorted sense
but the people in
Oregon were very different
the people in Washington were
very different it may be that
it does actually seem
to me that places
have
something that
resembles a personality
and that the humans in those
places
reflect that does that make any
sense?
yeah yeah yeah
something like that
that's a yep
I'm an echo yeah
because the man made me think much
and I always say this
I know this quite well
because I go to India often
I've gone to India quite a lot
and they're forever complaining about
the outside and places dirty
and this and this
it's a manifestation of
the sum of the minds
in
in Hindu culture there are
words for these things
in English there are not
in Sanskrit there are words for
words
you have a culture that's like
8,000 years older than ours
and the white people
think they're intelligent
what?
you guys are playing with Play-Doh
or something works
you know
my son
he studies Advaita Vedanta
I know there are words
for all of these in Sanskrit
and in
Indian philosophy
there's very complex
sophisticated language about
all the different features
of anything
you might want to
refer to in consciousness at all
it's very interesting
compared to
how it is in English
it's so much richer
and more intelligent in some ways
you remind me of one thing
I was talking to another
buddy who might join us
who's a good candidate
to join our team
I must ask you to hold
I'm getting an important call
okay
oh it's too late
I missed it
it's alright, I'm here
oh I see
okay
maybe I'll talk about that
and we'll
we can continue another day
of course
there's a word
Darren
the word we are looking for is like
sensibility
meaning
what is it that we are looking
what is it that we are trying to get
artificial intelligence to do?
what is intelligence?
acumen
but they seem
the western world seems
to not want to talk about
the word
which is even more clear
in the Indian language in Tamil
and some of our local languages
it's called Bhutti
Buddha's name comes from that
Buddha is not his name
no
but they call it
like miss the sensible
what I
see I want to talk to you
I mean one word in English is equanimity
equanimity is it?
yeah it means not biased
you don't
you don't collapse into extremity
you're balanced
hmm
ah yes
that says that
your balance
what
I guess what to me
why the western world my trip over
it is when we talk about
sensibility
in the context
they are thinking of cognition
the western world
when it talks about AI
it's like forever going into cognition
and we are saying no the body
and the mind
must be both taken into account
in realizing what is the right
sensible thing to see sensible
or the right thing to do which is
which we will say is a sensible thing
to do the sensible thing to do
includes what your body
which means instinct
what your instinctive reactions are
because you're dealing with for example
indigenous people
and pretty much they're running on instinct
you know we don't know about
what cognition they have or they don't have
it doesn't matter
they're functional people on instinct
so sensibility
the word sense immediately implies
you know the five senses
for example right
more cognition
why had it occurred to you
or does it occur to you why does the western world
not talk about sensibility
the question is very
broad
meaning
like say when
in the AI circles and stuff
right when you're talking about
ethics and whatever
why not say
hey
which of these LLMs
is more sensible
takes into account
sensibility
which is different from intelligence
and I think enough people would know
that yeah
because intelligence immediately in a big way
kind of like
in the slides
or the leans towards
academia
leans towards
it does
but the common humans have no
all
they're missing
what you have
they're missing the experience
of
coherent
daily life
that
most of whose
rules don't need
to be written or declared
so what they have is something really
weird they have a thing where
all the rules are written
and declared
and you have to either obey
the ignorant of
or reject them
and one of the reasons why
Trump is about to get elected in this country
is because the rejection crowd
is really pissy at this point
in history
everybody all the males
all the ignorant poorly educated males
who have no fucking
no clue about
what it means to be human and yet are
anyway
they want somebody who gets away with breaking the rules
and they will elect that guy
if we don't you know
if something doesn't stop them
and
the guy
so he's the opposite of sensibility
but he masquerades as sensible
right
I saw some advertising with him
between masquerading
as sensible
and having to be sensible
to get elected and stay there
in a way from the other
prejudice
you're not going to get elected if you're sensible
there's no chance
of that happening
yeah that's
no
that's not going to happen
you get elected not okay
in America you get elected not because you're sensible
you get elected because you're sensational
it's a society of spectacles
right
the better your spectacle the better the brand
of spectacle that you produce
the more likely you are to be elected
that's sick
that's sad I mean
it's screwed that up so bad
I mean like
here let me ask you this
Kamala Harris should not be there
should not be up there
should she
I don't know
how would I tell
I mean supposing I really cared
right
how would I make the determination
do I want
a pissed off para-feminist
having a voice in the government
yeah I probably do
her particularly I'm not sure
I mean like
like a fly on the wall
you know
I don't know Kamala Harris's
talk very much
maybe I'm actually thinking of AOC
when you said her name
at least AOC is
I mean like she's
she's smart
yeah I mean
yeah smart
she
I mean she knows how to get attention
and it's not just
she used to be good
but I think she's going downhill
by the way
I've spent about 27 minutes
of my life listening to politicians
in 2020
acts
that's something I mostly
just ignore to be clear
and also to be clear for posterity
if anyone listens to this
I'm not well educated
okay
so and you're able to
I guess
for whatever you do
it doesn't affect you too much
or you find spots where
you're not affected by
you operate
I have a simple principle
at this accelerated age
that I'm at almost 60
not a kid anymore
the simple principle is
try not to actively import suffering
outside
so
the news is basically all about
importing suffering
so I mostly buffer that off
I may glance at it but I don't take it seriously
and I rarely reflect on it
it's mostly just me taking
the temperature of modernity
is the apocalypse likely to happen today
or next week
yeah
it's mostly that
do you pay much attention to news
what's your relationship with it like
not much
I mean I pay attention
to the news
in the last 5-10 years
some areas I'm a bit interested
more like world issues
well I mean like say India
Russia
is hitting
China to some extent
of course
I want to get
for orientation
then
being a bit more attentive
I'm still more
I would read news
that touches on our area
like what I'm talking to you about
getting funding
or if it's not funding
how do I go to the next step
from where I am
and the next step in
your village
becoming a voice
and making connections
and me
finding a way to
self sustain it
to fund it
when I sent you
the link
to
we move
we found this or whatever
basically
align with people
who would
invest in us or finances
or help us out
because we've got
enough
if we have a team
enough of us have to be paid
right
such as the world
so
where can you get funding and who funds them
and what are the requirements
and who has been successful
that kind of news
that I keep up
and then over and above that
when you see me
writing
most of my writing is under
the under
the substrate of it is
how do we
why can't we be
the same state
develop
why can't we be the same state
high state we were
500 or 600 years ago
right in my neck of the woods
and in particular
like
saying the villages
why
all of the things
zero crime
embodied currency
embodied learning
why can't we have that
it's like
why can't we have what I had from
zero to seven with an unconditional love
mother
I can go and sleep
and I want kids
and I want my
I want the work
of hundreds of generations of
my forefathers to continue
instead of it going
so downhill in one generation
it has gone downhill too
everybody
is doing it meaning
you go around with solicit doing crime
and whatever just casually
and you ask me what the hell are you doing
and they say hey everybody you can't
you don't do it everybody is doing it
and I said no
not everybody is doing it
I'm not doing it come on
for example a lawyer who is
stealing and cheating and screwing his customer
hey don't have faith in your intellect
that you can do something else
for example we stopped
you know emerging we stopped creating
anything new for 600 years
why didn't we do part of that
that needs law too
I mean the young kids
the younger people are a bit ready to
listen to that the folks
who are the lawyers and stuff
big names no they're not interested
in that they want to screw the system
bloody hell I'm so
but I guess they're not born in the
kind of village and conditional love
environment that I was
look whenever you take
a cohort like lawyers
or doctors or dentists or
teachers
you're gonna find a large prevalence
of what I'll call the worst common
denominator
which is the people who
you know
but what you're actually looking at
is a topology
and as you come to understand
the structure of the topology
you'll be able to find the people in
the cohort who aren't defecting
and those people will be excited to discover
you as well
this is a moment of mutual
appreciation
that's long been coming
many of us would like the dreams of our
ancestors
not to be flushed down the toilet
in a single generation
and some of us would like those dreams
to be actually fulfilled
so that's
those purposes live
in the hearts of humans
and if we can
awaken them it will be very
powerful
and it doesn't have to be a cult
it doesn't even have to be
political it can just be human
and you often you know in your writing
you know you say
this is an everyday
thing
this is normal
yes
I think that's what those guys in the
book I quoted from earlier were saying
too they're like we have this narrative
that it's impossible to change this
and that humans are fundamentally broken
it's not true
they're just trapped in why are they
trapped in thinking they're broken
so yeah these are things that I
want to keep
exploring and understanding better and get
people doing something around
right experimenting
play grow learn discover
remember
remember how we can be
yeah
I'm trying to
you know in my own way
yeah yeah okay good good
so you know
between Indonesia
and San Francisco
you know I'll
on this you know formulate
some more what's next steps
we can take
making this happen
yes
we let us
let us bookmark that
for our next conversation but there are
some for sure
and I'm absolutely
willing to explore them together
I just need to get some food in me
okay good on you
okay sorry
no no it's fine
this is wonderful I'm very
I'm very grateful and excited this has been
profoundly
educational for me
alright all blessings my friend we will talk
again soon yes
yes yes
okay bye bye for now