Hello everybody. Welcome. I appreciate all of you who listen to my recordings and it
would help me a lot if you subscribe or like them or make a comment or ask a
question. My engagement is embarrassingly minute. So to reach more people, whatever
help you care to lend would be greatly appreciated. But I'm glad you're just
here and that I'm here. We're both still alive. Apparently we're breathing. I'm
crossing urban streets on foot, which is vastly more dangerous than we like to
think. It turns out that although there are many explanations for the complexity
of our human brains, I strongly suspect many of them are either completely
wrong or put the precedents on the wrong thing. Obviously social cognition is one
of them and it would be amazing if we developed complex brains to handle
social cognition. Only to discover that that would cause us to simulate, this is
one of the explanations for human brain complexity, that would cause us to simulate
another which would become the self a fiction. Because similar to one of my
fingers deciding that it is real and the rest of the hand is well whatever that
is, we would become catastrophically misguided thereafter, continue to produce
simulations, as well as representational culture, right, where we with each thing we
lose direct participation and relation with. We form a token and then thereafter
relate with the token instead of resurrecting the relationship and the
participation. And so we end up in an endless thirst trap where the more
representations we make, the more we are suffocating for participation and
meaningful roles and relationships, and this leads to a descending nightmare of
self-amplifying, what is the word, poverty, impoverishment. And this seems to
match up pretty damn good with what I see going on. But the social cognition
argument is powerful, the problem is it leads to an endless cascade of disasters
as we stop relating with and in pod groups in which our identity and purpose
of motivations are useful, celebrated, effective, alive, vital, creative, playful,
joyful, fulfilling, rewarding. You know get together with a team of three people
and do anything meaningful, right. The rewards at the end of the day are off the
scale compared to any possible representation you could form. Yes, this
is all the change I have. The large coin is a dollar. You're welcome. That poor old
woman, my goodness, she must be 70 and she's living on the street. You see what
ends up happening, right, like without meaningful cohorts that are real, our
elderly end up dying alone in boxes or we're still on the street. And what do I
mean by our elderly? Okay, I get the problem with the language. I do. We could just say
the elderly, which we will all become. So that's us in the future. Okay, what else?
Where am I here? Social cognition, meaningful groups, pods. So in our situation,
what's the what's the antidote here? So the first is to teach each other to
understand the representational gambit's foundations, right, which involve the
simulation of a separate self and then the inaction of a separable self that
becomes an isolated self. Ask yourself this question. I'll ask myself the same
question. How many times per month do I directly physically engage meat space
with other humans for meaningful purposes that I trust and are beautiful
and noble? So first of all, how often do I engage with meat space others for
anything? Myself, with a couple of trenchant exceptions, one being somebody I
live with, the number of times per month that happens for me is zero. And that's
part of why I make these videos, because this is a way for me to participate, to
work my vocabulary, which is important because my vocabulary is one of my
as a writer and someone who values articulate intelligent speech. My
vocabulary is crucially important. I've worked hard to develop it over my life,
although it was natural for me to do that because of my interests. And also to
create a context where I'm doing something meaningful in the day to me that
may provide benefit for distance others, some of whom I know, some of whom I love,
many of whom are unknown to me. There's just sort of people who manage to find my
channel. But this is not particularly crucially important to my point. I'm
merely trying to say that ask yourself the question. How often over some
interval, say 90 days, are you able to get together with other humans and enact
your humanity intelligently, creatively, meaningfully for a purpose you believe
in? And even if today in our time, right, circa 2024, that's a virtual get
together. Let's count those. We'll open the aperture from meat space only to
virtual context. But you can see the radical difference, right? Suppose that
I'm just going to pick something incredibly trivial. Three neighbors once a
month get together, wander around their neighborhood together and pick up trash.
Not particularly heroic, but powerful because they're doing something they
believe in and they will communicate and act as a single member, right? Act like a
hand. In fact, they'll literally be picking things up. It's very handlike. And
of course, it turns out that the hand is one of the best metaphors for human
togetherness and unity that you can possibly come up with. It might be the
best because there's there's just there's nothing. It's a part of your
physical body, right? So hello.
It was developed by evolution. So the model is not a human intellectual model.
It's an evolutionary model. It's older than old.
It's a really good model for the actual nature of human existence being
interiority. I noticed that the first thing that happens when you destroy
human social groups is that you get individual fingers attempting to do
things to enact their humanity in ways that require a hand. I'd love to see
any one attempt to use any of our tools. Though, you know, they might succeed with
a few. Try and use pliers with a single finger. I mean, try to do anything with a
single finger. You might be able to sort of play some kind of musical
instrument as long as it didn't require your breath. You could plunk your way
along something with a single finger, presuming that you had a hand that the
finger was on the end of. The way that our systems work is as if they amputate
the fingers and then scream at them for not being able to do all the things that
a hand could do. So obviously what I'm trying to say here is that the
embodiment and fulfillment of our potentials as human beings naturally
requires communion. Potting up. You will see very few intelligent animals
there are exceptions that don't pot up. One exception would be octopuses. The
other polarity are the organisms that form supergroups. These would be creatures
that form hives. Ants, bees, wasps, certain species of spider form
massive web communities. Unclear. It may be that the fundamental problem with our
species is just that we form misguided supergroups. So what was I thinking
originally here? Oh yes. All right.
So we've actually I've actually covered much more ground than I was imagining
when I began my talk and what was inspiring me. Okay so I'm going to circle
way back here. I sometimes form relationships with animals by offering
them food and there are certain animals with which it is less dangerous for
both of us than it would be with others. So for example I am currently in the
San Francisco Botanical Gardens. The coyotes here are reasonably well known
to me. I see them commonly. I could easily form relationships with them by
bringing them some meat. Any transaction between humans and wild things,
especially city humans, will produce a lot of danger for both participants.
Primarily because the human is dumb about what is important for the animals.
Don't know if you heard that. That was a coyote.
Let's see if it, yeah it's yipping.
All right let's examine this problem here.
Okay this is a really good, really good instance of synchronicity.
It's crucial for all animals to avoid danger and one of the ways they avoid
danger is by avoiding calling attention to themselves. There are some situations
under which it is relatively more safe to call attention to oneself and others
under which it's extremely dangerous. There's only one animal here around here
that is a threat to the coyote and that's homo sapiens. If I were to begin
feeding a coyote and I could delude myself into thinking this is a good way
to establish a relationship with them and to nourish that relationship
literally, physically. Okay the reason that coyote is calling out at full
volume in broad daylight. Very dangerous thing for it to do is that there are
sirens. So the humans make a machine that mimics a signal that essentially
causes, nearly forces the coyote to reveal its location. I mean if you wanted
to hunt coyotes you could just bring a device with you that produced sirens and
they would light up their location with calls because they're physically, to some
degree, they are physically unable to resist that stimuli.
Hi. Now if I were to begin feeding coyotes around here what would naturally
happen is that I would interfere with their natural tendency, one might call
it, at least around here, to avoid contact with humans. Now if I live, if I were not
a city dweller and I lived in the wilderness and I wanted to have a
relationship with the coyotes, there are a number of different ways I might go
about forming that relationship. Perhaps the most important but least blatant is
to imagine that the coyotes form an emissary to the humans and I form an
emissary from the humans and in my imagination and perhaps in my dreaming
me and the emissary meet and we exchange protections and potencies and
medicine and so forth. Humans are unlikely, modern particularly, unlikely to pursue
that kind of connection. Many of them would not believe that it's real but
that would be a good way and then perhaps I could ask the coyote emissary
questions and it could ask me questions and it might even have things to say
to my people, things that wished to be communicated to my people about their
people and our ancient union because some animals, synanthropes particularly,
have had more than a million years of relationship with Homo sapiens and you
could say well our species really isn't that old, are you sure? Yes, our species
isn't that single age old or it probably is. I don't know what the current model
is of our estimated age of Homo sapiens. Probably measured in flat years though
which there never were so our age is actually the time since the appearance
of Homo sapiens in the in the records so to speak times the number of humans
who have lived one year right and for each year we'd have to add age so our
actual age and the age of our relationships with synanthropes is
absurdly enormous. Bees, ants, wasps, mice, rats, porcupines, possums, skunks,
moles, gophers, house cats, house dogs, coyotes, wolves,
blue jays, magpies, sparrows, hawks, eagles, raptors, owls, crows and ravens, spiders,
all of these are synanthropes, these are creatures that prosper and are used to
the proximity of human symbionts, companions. Extended body is the concept
here not Darren has crow friends, extended body, I am crow, I am blue jay, I am
sparrow, I am spider, these organisms as they interact with me extend my
intelligence, they extend my senses dramatically, I will learn things from
observing them that are formally impossible for me to discover on my
own quote unquote. So in a sense what I'm advocating here is the formulation not
merely of a human relational hand-like situation but a very complex hand-like
situation involving many non-humans including the non-synanthropes presuming
that there is any such thing because synanthropy is a matter of degree, not
necessarily, you know, binary polarization either is a synanthrop or isn't.
On if you take the planet as a whole and you realize that like your comparator is
what we know of time-space
so if you take sorry I'm having an actual exchange with synanthropes right now
again ironic or synchronous or both
if you take as your time-space as your comparator then the earth is basically
like a little droplet of water in a vast desert and that droplet there's nothing
that isn't synanthropic there because essentially from this perspective from
the perspective of time-space toward the earth rather than the earth out you
know the human out to nature nature out to time-space which is the perspective
we are trained to take by our language and its categorical gambits it's absurd
and stupidifying categorical gambit. The whole package of lies that comes along
with English courtroom mind war mind anthropocentricity terracentricity all of
these things so from from time-space toward earth what you obviously have
here and if you're not capable of thinking this way I will argue you're
barely capable of thinking at all is what you have here is a single organism
that takes many forms now it may turn out to be absolutely a physical fact that
that's what you've got here one imagines for example a space faring organism
that I'll call starfish it naturally swims between the stars in a proto form
that proto form could be incredibly profusely transcendent not merely
intelligent and it may only be a cellular form and still be transcendent
there's no reason to believe bacteria are probably not
representationally intelligent but it's unlikely that we could get the forms of
intelligence we're familiar with in human beings without them and so which is
superior right is the origin superior or is the results superior well once you
decide that one of them has to be superior you're already having courtroom
my point is just that it may well be that a single organism was primordial
here and that everything that you see that lives on this planet is actually
starfish's morphs right morphs of starfish one thing one one organism it
may also be that that organ that there were multiple forms of starfish that
lived that came here dwelt here there might have been some competition stuff
that looks like war but isn't but yeah you got one organism here so you should
definitely be able to think that way and you should probably think that way in
precedence to thinking oh these are all separate Darwinian Lee competitive
morphs that last thing can't be true primarily it's the problem with the
idea of competition there's no such thing as competition without symbiosis if
you don't have cooperation you don't get forms complex enough to compete so
the emphasis on competition is almost certainly a bad move all right if I
feed the coyotes in the botanical gardens it will reduce their suspicion
and avoidance of humans in general what that will mean in very short order here
is that the coyotes I feed will eventually realize ah humans are a source
of food food is difficult and dangerous to get here I'm gonna occasionally
approach humans some of those humans will have children some of them may have
dogs and coyotes will generally see small dogs small coyotes smaller
coyotes will see small dogs actually all coyotes will most coyotes will see
small dogs as prey that's a that's a good meal that's fairly easy to obtain so
they may go after those small dogs and that will result almost certainly in
the humans killing them particularly here in the botanical gardens
similarly if I feed the blue jays peanuts which they love
that signal
resembles playing a siren in the territory of coyotes
an analogy would be dropping hundred dollar bills along a busy freeway why a
busy freeway well for the blue jays many of them live in the hunting territory
of hawks and so when I come with my peanuts it doesn't shut off their
vigilance their vigilance but it radically reduces it it's funny I have
learned to recognize the shadow of the birds that I know so that sometimes I
can detect them behind me so if I put peanuts out and if I'm not careful
about it and I'm not attentive and I had to learn this by error by making bad
mistakes costly mistakes then I'm interfering with their vigilance
who's responsibility is it it's not a courtroom this is a communal animal me
plus the birds right so I also love the hawks and I have some relationship with
them as well but I don't want them to eat my blue jay friends obviously I want
them to get fed now all of this is very complex the problem is that I am not
aware ordinarily of the environmental relational historical biological
necessities of blue jay life or hawk life or coyote life and so if I wander
into that stumbling around like a magical thinking human an indictment that I
certainly deserve but I'm now beginning to understand in a in a richer way I
like to think I'm learning I will cause harm where my goal is to have beneficial
relations usually beneficial relations and that will be emotionally painful for
me because my desires are not utilitarian I am aware that the animal
intelligences including the insects will in a sense make offerings of
intelligence dreaming communal identity they will benefit me they will try to
figure out what what will benefit the one who is our friend and many of those
offerings will not be ordinary it's not like they're gonna bring me cash money
though in the case of a representational animal like say a particularly precocious
raven such a thing could take place it could bring me objects so if I want to
actually honor the relationship I have to to some degree protect the living
beings from the rapacious and omnicidal stupidity of my species and also my own
ignorance it will be difficult for me to form physical relationships with the
coyotes in this garden without feeding them if I feed them it is very likely
that will lead to them being shot by parts in Iraq or whoever does animal
control whatever parts in Iraq will call animal control will come out and
quote-unquote basically need to obliterate them you know more stories of
during stupidity so one night I was sitting in my room and out one of my
windows I noticed a family of coyotes excuse me a family of raccoons boy
here's a if you want to talk about courage motivation intelligence difficulty
heroism one pride one standout exemplar of this would be raccoon mothers in
urban settings there's no one to babysit the children the children like
any children are precocious playful curious very difficult to orient meanwhile
this mother has to bring them through places with dogs and cars and broken
bottles and poison and every kind of dogs every kind of threat cats you can
imagine coyotes every night every night that mother is going to bring their
children through a battlefield of things that will kill them and her so one night
I'm in my room it's late quiet and I hear the chortling of the of the
children naturally stupid as I am and also you know at that point prone to
magical thinking I emulate the sound back to them what happens the family of
raccoon stops dead in the middle of the street trying to determine the source of
that sound meanwhile a car doing 40 miles an hour comes up the street and
somehow I think that even though they were in the car's path when it passed I
think they all managed to survive unscathed I am not sure one of them
might have been struck by the undercarriage of the car however if that
were true there should have been a dead raccoon nearby in the morning probably
baby in any case if you want to imagine me cringing to the core of my being for
a moment you know I thought I was being playful and human and intelligent and
recognizing them and relating with them what I did not realize is they are on a
street there is traffic in the street this is why I made the metaphor of dropping
$100 bills on the freeway when I put out peanuts for the blue jays I had best be
complicit in their survival concerns vigilance protocols I had best
understand something deep about these because if I don't I am I am giving
them an irresistible stimulus in a terrain where there are hawks not only
that there are most likely nearly all of these would be males by the way case you
think gender doesn't matter there are most likely people who would kill the
blue jays for fun so once they learned for example that you could bring a blue
jay to your hand with a peanut they would do so for nefarious purposes the
other day I was in a part of the garden where there's a scrub jay that knows me
by the way that jay remembered me I fed it one time like five years ago and that
jay remembered me every time it saw me thereafter the animals have their
memories are unencumbered by representation so they have a lot of
memory resource to enact it's funny what a long road it's taking me to get back
to my original motivational thought here that started this this topic so for some
birds the appearance of a peanut is so compelling that they become like their
nervous system actually divides against itself and their ordinary instincts
for self and companion protection at least briefly collapse into must get
that peanut before something else does and so this messes up their vigilance
activities now a brief you know a brief
divergence from protocol probably won't get you killed at least not the first time
oh yeah see I was just feeding them and a hawk has come one of the coopers has
come to see oh it was turned away from you know it's hunting I respect that hawk
and have felt its talons because again ignorance got in trouble with the hawks
so there are some kinds of stimulus and you know the humans have the same problem this
is why social media has become a terrifying this manipulative disease you can see that
the goal is to capture attention which has for some time been the new form of cash
and this is natural for an organism that's collapsing away from participatory relation
meaningful roles and relationships into representations money porn social media
shows video games etc the coyote can't help it it's not powerless but it's nearly powerless
when the siren is near it directly captures its nervous system and this is what happens to us
with our technologies we undergo nervous system capture
now there's a blue jay in a part of the garden that remembers me from a long time ago a couple
weeks ago I was I gave it a peanut and because it's a male and it knows me it will come to my hand
now by the way that's a particularly interesting situation let me explain why
if I put the peanut on the ground or on a branch the jay must do if it wants to live
it's going to check maybe between eight and 30 vectors before it moves and then when it lands
it will recheck those vectors ordinarily the jay will have a companion up high
they can directly check with to see if it can't if there's something it can't see yet
and this complex participated relationship of mutual positive vigilance keeps both jays safe
relatively well
now if instead I am aware that there's a male and the male knows me I hold out a peanut in my hand
the male can be relatively certain that it can cross the interval between its perch and my palm
safely because it's a very short interval and it's fast
and grabbing the peanut from my outstretched hand it doesn't have to do a bunch of vector checking
because a hawk is very unlikely to attempt to take a jay from a human palm
unless the hawk has previously succeeded at such an endeavor so in a way the male's
willingness to come to my hand
is a bit more safe
than coming to ground
huh what's she shooting oh I see sparrows are eating seeds in a bush
interesting that we call photography shooting
leads to a whole other conversation wherein
human vision is understood to be a complex series of rays
that travel out from the eye bouncing back from the things these rays touch
so in a sense the male that comes to my hand is fairly safe
and as long as such interactions between me and the birds are infrequent
it's unlikely to produce their death unless there's something wrong with the peanuts
or conceivably but awfully unlikely
they acquire some microbe from my skin surface or something
so I was feeding this this male and there were a couple of men approaching and they saw the
bird come to my hand and they said uh do you speak with birds and I playfully said doesn't everyone
laugh and made some comment like well I don't I don't see the birds coming to the hands of people
here's a male scrub jay that knows me so now I will do the thing that I was just talking about
where the bird comes to hand and he lands briefly on my hand when he grabs the peanut now if there's
a female around I can put I'll usually put a peanut out for her
so that she can also have the benefit of
what a birder I know called bird heroine which he meant peanuts so yeah the guys said said this to me
and I said well
peanut is a language understood by many birds
and they laughed
so
you know the humans do some degree of monkey see monkey do
so additionally if I'm out in public and I'm witnessed relating with animals by giving them food
creates problems very unlikely that other humans are even
even similarly sensitive to the well-being of the creatures that I am and I've made terrible mistakes
not on purpose so yeah I put some in danger
and what I was thinking when I began this walk and talk was
there's some crows that know me and
when I'm near them when I'm near their their terrain
they group up and follow me
and people might see this
and I wonder what they would think if they noticed I mean I often wonder if people think actually at
all but I wonder what they would think if they saw you know five crows following me up
up or down some street in the city and I thought that they might think I'm a witch
human's naturally
surveil each other and they do so sometimes in obvious ways and sometimes surreptitiously
I was just being surveyed surveilled by a male in the garden
so yeah I wonder what the humans might think but the thing that I find interesting is that
there's a very clear pecking order in the group of approximately five crows
that know me well and I give them peanuts sometimes
so they know that I am
I'm gonna bring them something good to eat and it's winter harder to get food colder need more
need more fuel it's very it's relatively easy to discern the genders
in the corvids behaviorally
I have almost never seen if ever
a female who's relatively adventurous and aggressive
whereas the males the males will come right down and grab a peanut and
they won't merely grab a peanut they'll check the other peanuts they'll like do a weight test
they'll try to figure out which peanut is best so they might pick up with their beaks three or four
peanuts before the females even get near the food and
so that creates a problem where it's difficult to get a peanut to the females at all
um the male crows have a craw so that they can
store one probably one peanut maybe two if we're talking raven
um
and
so they can grab up you know most of the peanuts
and and the females are so timid in in this particular group
that although they may land near where the males are grabbing peanuts
and they may make some tentative passes toward peanuts um what you will notice
with crows and ravens is they have a complex neurological behavior where
they all make a pass at something they intend to grab and then bounce
right like leap backward leap away they'll make a pass towards something and leap away from it
and when they grab something they'll leap away from from it even though they've got it
and this seems to be a what humans call an instinctual behavior most corvids share it
I imagine I haven't seen all the different kinds of corvids I've rarely been able to
observe magpies um I think I've seen one in my life for a few minutes in real life
though I have sometimes observed them in video by the way there's a bunch of
so convocation of crows
and they seem stirred up
yes I am speaking of your people please do not poop right on my head
so interesting the foreground background feature of vision because
in the foreground I see the crows and in the background there's these
like
visually challenging puffs of cloud
that what I mean by visually challenging is that they
if you look at one area of the cloud forms
the others seem
the others
could almost be in motion the kind of motion that one sees in anything in the foveal vision
under the influence of psychedelics this kind of internal efflorescing outward
like transformational non-motion
that envision probably due to forms of neural feedback still things appear to be moving
the whole context may appear to be breathing so forth so the clouds are kind of
um relevant with this
interior spirit or energy although I am not under the influence of any drugs at the moment
unless you consider peanuts a drug I did eat a couple
so it's hard to get peanuts to the crow girls and I have a natural
um
tropism
for the underdog for the little one for the rejected one for the outsider so forth
so
I remember one beautiful afternoon fairly safe this this I think where I walked to the ocean
after not having seen it in many many years and I brought some peanuts with me and it turned out
that when I got there I encountered an enclave of ravens and so first thing I think I did
I'm not really sure actually which thing came first let me be
we speak with integrity about this I'm not sure I may have given them peanuts first
I may have sang to them first
but both things were offerings of respect and uh honoring them
honoring their people and their spirit honoring our communal
relationship
and I remember that there was one raven
it's funny how emotionally effective
a affect effective this is for me affect
when I remember this I'm starting to choke up
there was one raven
there might have been a few ravens that I could visibly detect ticks around their eyes
but there was one raven who its eyes were surrounded with ticks
and if you've ever watched young young crows and ravens
you will commonly see brother and sister pairs preening each other
and maybe brother and brother pairs maybe sister and sister pairs
I don't know how common it is that a clutch produces one male and one female
but you will see them preening each other
right they will come very close together on a telephone wire or something
and they will preen each other or one of them will preen the other and they will
request you can see them request preening
and I knew as I was looking at the raven with all of the ticks
that it was not treated well by the rest of the
they can be very mean in their in their social pods
corvids well the crows and the ravens at least
if the jays form extended communities I've not seen them
I know that magpies seem to but what I realized when looking at the the raven was
first of all obviously this bird is not being preened
and it cannot remove the ticks but any other creature could
any of those jays any any of those ravens excuse me could have preened it
and they would have received a tasty nutritious insect meal by so new me
at least you know in my thinking confused as it may be
so I worked extra hard to make sure that raven got some peanuts
and having fed them and sung to them I walked up the
I walked up the shoreline where was I walking north I guess I can't remember probably
I walked up the shoreline and I acquired an entourage of ravens
so either you know if someone were watching me they would either think this is a magically potent
person very few people would think that or they would wonder why they wouldn't have a conjecture
they just wonder what the hell is going on here or they would intelligently infer that I had given
them food it's pretty hard to get a peanut to the girls in the little crow enclave
but what I noticed the other day that I thought was great
was that it appeared to me that one of the males cashed a peanut in his
his claw
and then when the other crows weren't on the ground
exuded the peanut for the bird that I imagined to be his sister
or could be his mate to consume and I thought that was really cool
you know I life is very challenging and difficult and much more so in a world filled with machines
and perhaps somewhat naively I believe I'm an extreme altruist an exalt
um in Andrea Kuzhevsky's nomenclature
I generally will travel in the direction of mutual benefit naturally
in any way that I can understand how to do so my heart is more intelligent than my brain at this
time much more intelligent and so I get confused by my thoughts
often I make mistakes
there's an explanation for the complexity of the human brain that I prefer
which is that we might not be the alpha symbiont
and what I mean by that is something really weird I don't mean the symbiont that dominates
overall others or is the most important I mean the symbiont
that naturally becomes the summation lens of all of the other intelligences around it
all the forms of intelligence produced by starfish fungal microbial
vegetal animal land creatures water creatures air creatures living place being skybeam
all these intelligences and
you know I think the humans have this role
there's a bunch of very intense child signaling going on there
so
pause for a moment here while a loud noise doesn't get recorded
it seems to me that I've said this before in a very real sense the human species is the
the arbiter
of the well-being or destruction of everything that isn't too small for us to see and much of what is
so whether or not
some creator god divinely mandated that we were the shepherds for life on earth
it turns out to be the case by fiat or by uh by function anyway
now I think there are other similar alpha symbionts like us on earth
and some of the microbial ones might be far more profound in the scope of their
relationships than we tend to be
clearly in the waters the whales and dolphins represent living summation lenses of the aquatic
intelligences
how ironic the humans would slaughter them thereby denying themselves access to those organs of
intelligence perception and relation for what for the commodities their dead bodies produce
those are so worth pennies on the trillions of dollars of what is being disposed of as
usual for humans trapped in representational cognition
but yes our form has incredible unique
monumentally profound faculties and abilities that are disposed of almost entirely by our
representational behavior cognition
our great forgetting our our amnesia
our actively self-generating amnesia
so I like to think that
the complexity of the physical organ that we refer to as our brains pretending it's
distinct again pretending that
obvious it should be blatantly obvious that again one organism first the singularity of
the organism has precedence to any organ by many orders of magnitude so that
if you say the word brain you're actually referring to the entire body and the extended
environmental relationships and the entire history of life on earth and the
potential and future of life on this planet
because there is no brain without a heart you don't have a brain without kidneys
no skin no brain no mouth no brain
there are certain organs you can do away with and still have a brain
but not most of them
and the humans are doing the same damn thing to the earth right they are they are ripping the
organs of the earth out selling them on the black market for cars and guns and bombs and
shit and terror and torture and cages and awfulness the species
can't tell if this guy's yelling at himself or if he's yelling at his phone
so yeah I mean if the earth is a single animal and the humans are an organ of that animal
they are an organ destroying organ of that animal
most of us have no desire to be anything resembling that
and ordinarily we would have a fairly minimal and perhaps relatively net positive effect
on the biosphere and the environment particularly if our population were limited
but also if the object population that we produce were dramatically limited
this is interesting
many people complain about the human population certainly it's a problem
but the actual problem seems to me not to be the number of human bodies but rather what the masses
of them tend to do and one of those things is madly proliferate objects
and thus create from living beings and places effectively garbage and machines
so I think there's another explanation for the complexity of our brains
which is that the meta organism that earth is naturally produces in her organs
complex meta symbionts capable of astonishing feats of symbiotic sensing relation cognition
participation so forth and the more of those the earth has the the more alive her own
this creates webs of jewels in the net of her transcendentions
expanding it dramatically to whatever degree those meta metacognitives and meta symbionts
uh remain true to the beautiful and noble and heroic missions of living beings
on a delicate world in time space
there's a my foot there's a little plastic elephant
or maybe it's a pig
I wonder how many billions of those we've produced while the elephants and pigs were slaughtered
you know at the species level we are deadly poisoned to living worlds presently in our in
our current whatever is orienting our groups is malignant fundamentally malignant and life
despising intelligence despising because any intelligence that tears itself to shreds must
fail to qualify and similarly any intelligence that attacks its own foundations in relation
and organism must fail to qualify it's not clear at all individual humans are can be relatively
intelligent small groups of bonded humans can be preternaturally intelligent but large disoriented
cohorts of humans tend to be omnicidal in our time and that's a game with a short future
so one thing that I want to encourage you to do and I'm going to try and take my
own advice here is get together with a small group of other intelligent humans
and come up with a mission that you all believe in and go on have that adventure together in the
living world very hard to emulate that sound
it's funny there's there's ravens right above me
and one has to wonder if right if this is accidental
so
it's a pair
now I can't tell what their signals mean so I can't really tell
if they're upset
right I can't really tell
if they're upset at my behavior I've been circling a tree if they're curious
or something else
if we want to experience the potentials of our intelligence our dreaming aspects
our transcendence as human beings
there are paths where this can be pursued in isolation
but if you want an accelerant
go with trusted others into adventure meaningful relation meaningful roles nick names private lexicons
explore the palm that unites the fingers and you will never be disappointed
you might have misadventures things may go wrong but even from those you will learn
very profoundly and quickly and you will develop new senses new abilities new perspectives
so it turns out the guy that was yelling nearby is yelling into his phone
I wish you beautiful lives and ways companions adventures love and play and creativity
and I look forward to learning together again very soon thank you for joining me bye bye for now
you