Hello everybody. Welcome. I have just
reattached my wind buffer to my wired
Apple headset, microphones, or
microphone. It's not particularly windy,
but I'm sort of pleased with the simple
solution of wrapping a cotton ball
around the mic and securing it with a
... there's probably a formal name for
these objects, but a bread wire. Right?
Those little wires that sometimes close
the bread package. Hmm. A lot of contrails
in the sky today. I suppose there are
people who suspect that every time they
see a contrail, they're seeing what
chemtrails. Pretty sure most of those
contrails are just vapor caused by vapor.
The engines heat the air, makes a vapor
trail. There might be occasionally, and
some places, some things that aren't
contrails, but I strongly suspect that
people who spent their lives watching
aircraft and contrails would alert us.
I know this is a very controversial
topic that borders on the conspiratorial
but there are other strange problems
like, I guess, maybe my objection isn't as
strong as I once thought. This often
turns out to be the case, but one of my
simple objections was if somebody's
spreading some kind of chemistry in the
atmosphere itself and they're doing that
on purpose, it's going to affect them
and their children and their children's
children and so forth. I suppose it could
be that they don't have any children and
they don't care. This is strange. This is
the second bit of a carcass that I've
seen today and it's interesting because
I almost never see bits of carcass and I
walk here every day. Is it just that
today I'm noticing what I don't notice?
Or is today a bit of carcass day? I just
don't know. They're rather disgusting.
Little chunks of fleshy, bloody, gristle
and fur and things. Certainly
unappetizing. I don't necessarily have
a plan for this talk today. We'll see
where it goes. I was thinking about
some things. Various kinds of magical
intent. The transactional kind where you
trade something often or sometimes this
is apparently whatever is referred to
by one's soul for some boon or benefit
in the short term. It seems like a
wildly stupid idea to me. Hopefully I
haven't accidentally done that myself.
And the kind where you employ. Wow, what is that sound?
Oh, it's a bird. Oh, it's a baby bird. It's a
feed me sound. Oh, okay. There are two
fundamental principles of something
resembling our idea of magic, which
let's face it. It's get or accomplish
something without physically having to
do the thing or, you know, chase the
thing or something. Something like this.
So in traditional Blackfoot knowledge,
the language is problematical because
what magic means in English is a broad
array of things. Or actually, magic doesn't
mean anything in any language. It's just
a word. What actually happens with words
is that we use them to mean things to
each other in actual conversations,
unless we're not having conversations
and we're just saying things. And this
becomes very confusing very quickly
because then the presumption that words
have meanings begins to pervade. We have
to interpret the gap. What gap? The gap of
no relationship, no no pre-existing
context, random context, and so forth.
There are ways in which that situation
can become useful for us, but only if we
deal with it very insightfully,
intelligently.
And what do I mean? I mean,
the randomization of language is a kind
of a paramagical substrate.
What am I trying to mean by magic? Well,
I'm not trying to mean illusionist's
tricks. Fascinating though they are.
And I'm not trying to mean the mere
manipulation of the vulnerabilities
in human thought and consciousness.
I'm trying to mean something more like
perhaps what people usually very naively
mean with the word manifesting.
An idea that I fundamentally mistrust,
or maybe it's just the language that I mistrust,
or maybe I'm ill-informed, which isn't
as rare as I might like to be.
Yes, I'm not, as my listeners know,
a big fan of the secret, or the various cults
that derive their central premises
from such ideas.
At the same time, there is something to
a kind of envisioning or dreaming of the future
that is very powerful.
The question is, is it as trivially silly?
Like what happens when you make that idea
explicit is one of the questions. Because
there's a fundamental difference
between peripheral vision and foveal vision.
Between explicit identity
and potential identities.
And in that blur, there's something transcendentally
momentous and powerful.
But if we make the blur explicit,
irony often results.
Meaning direct contradiction with
stated purposes, goals, hopes, desires, intentions,
cautions, and so forth.
And so perhaps what actually bothers me about
the manifesting cults is that they're taking something
that I suspect properly belongs to the peripheral
and making it foveal.
Your foveal vision is the center vision.
It's what you use when you look at something.
It's your peripherals what you use when you spread your gaze
and take in the whole.
And as some of you know, that if you gaze at the night sky
when you look at stars you can see the stars visible to your foveal vision.
When you look toward them,
I'm getting a little wet there.
If you spread your gaze you will see stars
that will literally disappear if you look at them.
And this is kind of what my concern is
as well as a sort of ideological trivialization
of destiny, dreaming, visioneering.
Yes, yes, yes.
Ascent of the herbs. Beautiful.
So yeah I'm getting somewhere near
what sticks in my craw.
And the weird thing about this problem for me
is that by explicitly pointing
at what sticks in my craw,
this is part of the problem with thinking and part of the problem with language.
Once I think I have a sense of what might be going on
I tend to become kind of clingy about that.
And in that clinginess,
well, you know, it's not always
conflicted but it's often produces
significant conflict.
Sage flower, scent, yum.
In Blackfoot the two principles are
similitude and contagion.
And they mix together, they mate, they bond,
they form very powerful abilities
you might call them, as well as faculties.
I'm not going to lecture about that today.
These two principles are also
found in other magical traditions
such as
voodoo, hoodoo,
various
witching ways.
And perhaps also
shamanism. Resemblance
is a way to understand similitude.
And similitude is a very sophisticated word
that my friend Ryan First Diver uses.
Contagion is fairly obvious.
In a way,
to refer to something
directly in consciousness
can often be a bit of a trap for us.
Whereas to suggest it
is much more powerful and in a sense magical
by which I mean transcendentally potent
historically
women, females,
are masters of
indirect communication.
Suggestion,
entranced
which places consciousness into a sort of
a flow state that can then be
directed
or shaped, or both, redirected
so forth.
Yesterday at this spot there was a young woman
sitting on a log up above me
and she was practicing
playing a particular kind of flute
that appeared to be made of wood or possibly bamboo.
I sat down, you know,
without gazing directly at her because once again
suggestion produces problems.
Or, you know, it's occasionally appropriate.
But usually if we're paying direct attention to something
it's often that we have the desire to capture, possess, or manipulate it.
And nobody really wants to be captured, possessed, or manipulated.
There's that explicitness in
language again, of course sometimes we do.
Sometimes we partly want that.
Or an aspect of us desires this while other aspects of us flee from it.
This is the stormy cloud
of what it's like to be human.
I've made it
to the high view.
And there's that thing that looks a bit like Warden Cliff Tower
but is actually
the emergency public broadcasting
speakers.
The peripheral and the foveal.
You know, dreaming consciousness largely corresponds
to the former, waking consciousness to the latter.
Without being
explicit, allow me to suggest that in the daytime
in bright sunlight
the sunlight declares the color and identity
of objects and situations. What they are doing is obvious.
It's explicit, relatively explicit.
Whereas the moonlight, if it's there, or even the total darkness
in total darkness it's pure
suggestivity.
If you don't know where anything is, you can tap your way along the path with a stick
if you're lucky, or skillful, or have practiced that.
If you're very witchy, you can run
in the darkness.
I've never known someone who can do that. I can usually
perambulate. I've heard of people who can run in pitch darkness.
Having practiced a kind of a
way that is natural to humans and animals, but
rarely
siren.
Terrible noise.
Dominates the entire oral sphere.
Thankfully most situations
are highly temporary.
The moonlight suggests
rather than declares identities, and thus
pareidolia.
I need to look up exactly how to pronounce that word.
But the imaginative
experience of shapes and faces
in, for example, the whorling
bark of trees, or the
texture of the surface of the trail,
or the clump of bushes that just happens to be
in a shape that looks like a raccoon, and you can't
at first tell it isn't.
This dichotomy between suggestion and declaration
is very profound.
And similarly in dreaming, because in dreaming
things, beings, and situations
we may later decide, oh, that was my brother,
that was our house, that was this, that was that. But in the actual
dreaming experience, it's not really like that.
It's just a house that's quite different from mine
can be my house. My sister can be a man.
All kinds of strange
amalgams
of possible and actual
form, identity, function, behavior,
ensue.
Usually when
I don't know, when those jays are making that noise, there's often
a raptor in your mind, but maybe not.
It doesn't sound as chiding. It sounds more like
here I am, here I am, I'm over here.
Well though, that looks like a raptor tree to me.
That's a stellar's jay.
Making the calls. See, there's that thing
right of explicit categorical identity.
See, there's that thing right of explicit
categorical identity.
See, there's that thing right of explicit categorical identity.
So there are kinds of magic
that don't really require
trades.
They're not transactional.
And by magic, in this case, I mean
the curation
of time, space, and relationships
in the hope of producing
the resemblance of desired
situations, transformations,
relationships.
Without manipulating them directly physically,
although some kinds of physical activities, such as
ceremony and or ritual, whether they are formal or informal
may be involved.
You know, one can envision
very formally by deciding I'm going to sit
in this place which is powerful
and envision.
But then, you know, think about, okay,
so when you go to sleep,
dreaming tends, for many of us,
some of the time, to resemble breathing.
It just happens. It happens, it's as if it happens
to us and also within us.
Now one can then form intentions
around dreaming, for example, the intention to dream about a specific thing
or the intention to the request
that the dreaming aspect helps us better understand
the situation or experience the transformation
of some kind or gain what we think of as information
about something that's otherwise difficult to know about
as if the dreaming mind has powers that are
irracular and transcendentally seeing and I think it does.
The dreaming mind is an array of faculties
but also some things we might think of as functions
meaning it does stuff,
important stuff, regenerating the organs,
cleansing the metabolism, transforming the energetic
situation in the body,
what we might think of as spiritual energies or soul energies
or life energies or electromagnetic,
subtle electromagnetic stuff.
All of these things the dreaming mind is naturally skillful with
and it does its job much like our heart and lungs do
without much instruction but it can also be
instructed or skillfully developed much like our breathing
perhaps like our heart rate, certainly like our habits of thought.
So we can
have the formal intention
to vision-ear futures.
And there's what I remember when I was younger
the informally vision-earing futures
and they many of them came to fruition
but there was a mix, right? Like I formally wanted to play the guitar
I formally wanted to be a graphic designer
I formally wanted to publish texts
I formally wanted to be a good
fisherman even though I don't really eat fish
I formally wanted
to have a nest like Robert Wagner's
that one sort of came true which I think is
ridiculous although now I'm old and it doesn't matter
much.
I formally wanted to be a secret agent
I also informally wanted
I'm not sure why I have such a
antipathy toward the formalization
of certain kinds of things perhaps I'm not really concerned
about their formalization I'm concerned about the way that
cults utilize formalizations
of principles and
wisdom
to capture
and
abuse people
to disempower and blind them
by giving them the wrapping paper
instead of the gift
hmm
yeah I don't like that
although sometimes it can be very helpful
and this is hard to understand at first glance
we'd like to have societies and situations that are so fundamentally enlightened
that we just climb the ladder together beautifully and successfully
toward self development, mutual development, insight
skillfulness, awareness, wonder, awe, play, joy
humor, eros, all these things
we just climb the ladder together and
are constantly lifting each other above positions previous
or at least into harmonious balance
where health and vitality and rejuvenation
and resurrection
are natural
features of the situation right of course we all hope for this but
in our actual situation sometimes we may
it may be useful to fail
talked about this before
imagine a situation where
everything you do succeeds the first time
and so it requires very little effort and there's
it's going to be extremely difficult to improve
to experience a gain in skillfulness or ability
or function
in order for that to happen there has to be the possibility of
making mistakes
and perhaps of pain and suffering
confusion, ignorance, all these things
so it can be very useful at least in theory
to
to become
enamored
of a cult
I have
before
and you know
we join the cult, we are enchanted by it
it's very compelling because suddenly we have
belonging, we have an experience of belonging that can be otherwise quite difficult
to
in our modern
common modern situations worst common denominator
talk here but in our common modern situations it can be very difficult
to find a coherent groups that are doing something amazing
and beautiful to belong with and so
this is part of why even though education
is kind of a disaster it's also very
wouldn't necessarily just want to get rid of schools
clearly one might want to
what
mediate you know
positively mediate and transform
the existing institutions
but the schools are very important because they give young people
and the teachers and others
the experience
of belonging together
and so to the cults and so to
the various
pedals on the strange flower of fandom
musical groups
films, sports teams
also the
usually lethally in more ways than one motivated
military
cohorts and such
belonging
and obviously we get all kinds of pandering around this
social media
panders to this desire
to belong and delivers
largely
counterfeit representations
we steal the
the real thing is stolen, ground up
compromised
essentially destroyed
and
we are sold a broad array
of ever less rich
and powerful counterfeits
this is the common thing
that happens a lot in our
society
now when we come together with and for each other
and we forge intentional social
contexts and cohorts
pods if you will like a dolphin pod
or a primate pod or a whale pod
then we have both a kind of natural
to these gambits and the capacity to lift each other out of them
or even to manipulate them from within
this is the rather covert
version of
the possibilities
of our human
sociality
and this can be done
in various different kinds of ways
it can be done
in rather serious ways
and it can also be done in more or less playful
or game like ways
and these two can actually merge so that you can have
playful games
that actually transform
or ameliorate the
humanity and ear sats community
spirituality
that is so pervasive in our modern
experience it's not the only thing going on
alone when we're isolated it may seem like
the entire context is just violations
and this is what leads people to
terror, agony, self harm, suicide
what we think of as madness
madness is a fairly natural result of the constant exposure
to the kinds of double triple quadruple
you know myriad sorts of binds
right where
that emerge in our experience
of the broad
array of competing anti-cultures
anti-nations, anti-societies
corporations that dominate
our modern experience
and concern
and they are terrible but they're not the only thing going on
and in order to you know it's not just that we discover what's going on
when we begin to form intentional communal groups
even if it's only for a short period of time see this is the key
we can get escape velocity immediately
in a small group with a shared intention to do so
and we can sustain that over time
and give it a heartbeat and that can even reproduce
other little groups that bubble
and prosper even in
the counterfeit
nightmares
from and perhaps against
and out of the
desire to
transcend
these troubling situations
so there are forms of
magic that don't require
or soul-selling and so forth
but are very powerful and some of them are profoundly virtuous
they are not
composed for the sake of vengeance
this is very dangerous motivation generally speaking leads to
a lot of trouble in almost every case
they are not war machines
primarily for personal gain
they may not be entirely selfless
though they can be composed under such circumstances
but they are resistant to capture
yeah
by selfish manipulative
or war-like motivations
and they can also be profoundly
protective
healing
calming
nurturing nourishing
and these forms arise
from an ache that I suspect we all come
to human incarnation with
the
it's an ache for the positive
version of justice which is the dissolution
of injustices and their replacements with virtues
now again if once either of these ideas become highly explicit
there's going to be a lot of trouble
most of the time
if you're explicitly concerned with virtue
this tends to produce irony
if you're explicitly concerned with harm or vengeance
or war you're going to have irony
cleansing
bathing
smudging
um
nurturing grounding
getting your feet, your bare feet
out of the ground
surrounding you know
going into nature, going into the living waters of the river or the ocean
the lake, the stream
these are potent and powerful precursors
to the formation of the kinds of intentions
that naturally become
that naturally influence
without dictating futures
and transformations of situations
I was speaking with someone
maybe about a week and a half ago
and I asked him if he had ever prayed
and I don't think I ever really got
the impression that something was listening
and that's a very rational
response, sensible
why should we engage in
activities whose effectiveness we have no way to determine
well you know that's one
effective but I wonder if it ever occurred to him
that whether or not someone was listening
or something was listening
the transformational effects
could be profound either way
they could be profound neither way
they could be profound both ways
they could be profound even if there was no way to understand
how or why they were in fact profound
because
somehow
our behavior
transforms our potential
and the fact or fiction
in many cases
either doesn't matter or
can be very limiting
so yeah
these are things to consider
I heard once that some president
perhaps it was Bush
a prayer
it's like attempting to study
I don't know
something that cannot be
cannot be detected
by the methods we would ordinarily
presume I heard this morning of an experiment
to establish what's called the Weisman barrier
in biology
a feature of biology that is certainly wrong
and yet has been canon for a very long time
in modern, in terms of modern science
and the experiment was absurdly stupid
and yet everyone supposed that it was one of the greatest biological
experiments that had ever been done
well perhaps not everyone
it was very common to suppose this
yeah so had people pray
for sick people and so on people who knew them and people who didn't
and apparently the study produced
the result that the people who were prayed for were actually
less likely, slightly less likely to recover
than those who were not prayed for
experiments
and rational thought
and science are very powerful tools
their scope though is quite limited
compared to that which is
you could say that which is the case
but not that which is
their scope is different from reality
the scope of rational thought
is similar
in its limitations to the scope
of the physical manipulation of objects
I can move hammers all I want
much of my experience
cannot be reasonably
affected, cannot be
properly transformed or successfully
transformed by my manipulation of hammers
and if I should fall under the
delusion
that my capacity to manipulate hammers
is the only way for me
to achieve
true and valid belief
conceptual or procedural
insight
understanding
then I'm going to be in a really bad situation
one imagines
someone that
is a boatwright but specializes
in the formation of the
skeletal precursors to the hull
and they think
this is the only important thing the skeletal precursors
can't have a hull without these
they only build skeletal
they only build the frame and the frame doesn't
float and they think
that they are an expert and that they know everything about boats
because they do the most important thing which is produce the frame
my presentation of the metaphor was a little
sketchy there but I think you get the idea
this is similar to the
overvaluing of rational frameworks, models, explanations
theory, experiment
and so on
when one does, when we do experiments
we
try very desperately to evict most of what's going
on from the context so that we can control
the resulting context
and its variables well enough
to acquire deterministic knowledge
of cause, effect,
future transformations
and this is a very compelling method
but it can also be blinding
in tests to determine
whether things like telepathy exist
they do, I assure you
I am as sure of telepathy as I am of breathing
very few if any of the experiments
took a fundamental feature of telepathy into
the experimental context, what is this feature
intimacy
deep
mutual concern and awareness
which is naturally
productive
of various forms of non-ordinary awareness
and sensing of the state needs, thought, concern, desires
of the other, natural between
mothers who adore their
young and newborn children
though it's not merely a matter of the young and the newborns
natural
between dogs and cats and their human companions
probably other pets, natural between
certain insects and humans
birds, reptiles even
but you know we hear
well there's no evidence, nobody's written a paper about that
there's nothing in the literature, I remember one day I was here at this lake
talking with an ornithologist and I explained that by careful observation
I had determined how to sex
how to determine the physical gender of geese
the snow geese, white cheeks, the Canadian geese
Canada geese I think they're called
which by the way I'm pretty sure isn't named after the country
I think it's named after a man whose last name was Canada
I think I heard someone saying this, they might have been
having their friend on
yeah I explained by careful observation over time because this is a quest I undertook
I realized the geese can tell for sure
each other's gender by sight
and if they can tell we can tell but in the literature
it is claimed that it cannot be determined, it can be determined by behavior
but not by appearance
and I didn't believe that
so I went on a quest, it took me a few years, it wasn't until I met
an old goose couple, an older couple
which is very uncommon in nature because old geese don't survive in nature
but in cities they can
and then in them the distinctions were
highlighted, exaggerated
and so I said to this guy, I was like you know
there are ways to visually determine the gender of these birds and he got very upset
and literally said there's nothing in the literature about that
and I was like how about we just look at some birds together
and let's see if we can do it, nope, there's no evidence
we hear this all the time, there's no evidence of faith
healing, no evidence of God, no evidence of angels, demons
I would argue that Facebook and Google are pretty strong evidence of demons
not to mention
many other bizarre features of our modern world
so
if you decide to not look for evidence or if you decide that
previous experiments not done by you
explain for all eternity what exists
what doesn't, what it doesn't, doesn't do, what it can and cannot do
then you have become
theory-blinded
because in point of fact
we speak and think
as if
that which has previously been established
is continuous and permanent
when there's no evidence of any permanent thing
and continuity is relative
it's not concrete, it's relative
and the nature of time itself can change, the nature of light can change
and the behaviors can change, does change
if you're dreaming you're still perceiving
so
it's very important to be able to distinguish
between
there might be stuff that's nonsensical in a dangerous way
that we should avoid
acting it, acting as if it's true
on the other hand
life and thought, our bodies, our relationships
as human beings are fundamentally experimental
the fact that there are concrete realities
that
doesn't mean
that all previously known
exemplars of fact
are the concrete foundation of our existence
or our reliable guides to futurity
you know what
Nassim Nikolas Taleb calls black swans
which are previously unknown phenomena
happen all the time, the current models of time space and such
all come from black swans
no one expected that Einstein was going to come along and go like
I think this distinction between space and time
while it seems very obvious
intuitive is wrong
and then Arkhani Hamed and others of his ilk came along and said
this perspective that
time space isn't must be
fundamental to all that's going on
not only is unlikely but can't be the case
black swans
come
into our awareness
and obliterate previously
dominant biases
and when they do so they are usually liberating
we gain new degrees of freedom
insight, wonder, play, ability, function
so on
the findings of science theory and experiment are provisional
they will be overturned
it's not they might be overturned, they will be overturned
and so we should recognize that the terrain ahead
isn't the ignorant
you know
I'm not sure what to say, there's a word I'm looking for
the crippling suppositional
certitude that oh we've already determined
what a goose is
and now we know, well I doubt it
the fact is we don't know what anything is
we have highly provisional toys
and when we exchange those for wonder and curiosity
passion and insight
something inside us begins to die
you know what we have mostly
as moderns
is not knowledge, it's representation
and representation in language and concept
is
deceptively powerful
and it is this deception
see here is magic
here is transcendental influence
by which we can be captured and manipulated
what we have is something
that replaces intimacy with tokens
words
maps, models, hypotheses
because actual knowledge
is intimate like kissing
and if you experience
the inflowing and indwelling of this knowledge
it will not be like thinking, it will be like orgasm
it will be like kissing
it will be like death
it will be like birth
some of you may notice a radical transformation
in the vector of my
my illocution
but yes, science
is powerful
but it is not the arbiter
of meaning, identity, purpose, value
fact
truth
and we see this kind of
refraction away from
science in many domains of our
modern social experience
the problem with that particular refraction is that some of that
is a weaponized sigh up
nations
are experimenting with how to kill each other's populations
with information
and so we have the mixture of the truth
of the danger for example of the covid vaccines
with
the intent
to deceptively harm populations
right, the
this is very common unfortunately in our modern
situation
but yes
all my father's life he thought he
knew what a tree was and then one day at the mirror
pool here in this garden where I'm standing
I accidentally enchanted him and we sat on this bench
where a woman is sitting now and he
began to have what might be described as an
emergence event and he turned to me
and he said we have to leave, I am dying
I'm going to become this tree and he was quite
he was simultaneously
hello
nice to see you today
he was simultaneously alarmed and ecstatic
he had never had an experience like this
drugs were not involved he felt he was becoming
the tree and I tried to calm
him I told him it'll be okay we can leave if we must
he said we have to go we have to leave and then a squirrel climbed up his
leg and up onto his shoulder and he said see see even the squirrel
knows I am a tree this is intimacy
and trance can produce
the potential for modes of intimacy that
I thought must extinguish
speech is very similar
I was talking with someone the other day about their dreaming experience
and gosh who was it
whoever it was
he said I don't think
I remember speaking in a dream and I was wildly
surprised I was partially surprised because most of us think
it's the keyword we think that we
have the experience of having many of us have these
memory of an experience resembling conversation in
dreaming and that part is true it resembles conversation
but as it moves more and more
explicitly toward the semblance of speaking
the manifold that supports the dreaming is collapsing
the intimacy is disappearing
one way to end an experience is to speak about it think of
two people passionately kissing
and one of them then
for whatever bizarre
reason of dissociative confusion decides that the most
important thing in this moment is to say something
the speech ends the experience
language is deceptively weird in that
we think it gives us the power to communicate
it does but primarily in the layer of representations
which is not the same layer as experience
and certainly not the same layer as intimacy
where in this mess is science
science is
in our time at least demonic
and when I was a child I wanted to become a scientist because it seemed that these were the people
who best knew
complete knowledge of things being
circumstances, origins, futures and so forth and machines
were very fascinating to me because it was as if in my previous
incarnations these things didn't exist and now they do
and they seemed quite impossible
not even the thing like a zipper this is impossible
how much more impossible is a thing like a mouse
you know humans can compose
a zipper they cannot compose a mouse
so you see this kind of representational
knowledge is extremely dangerous because it evicts us
from
what I would call transcendent participation
and that's where our actual
spirit
our capacity
to forge purposes beautiful, noble and true
and to embody and enact them together arises
not from knowledge
from participatory intimacy
you know we
because we are embodied humans
eventually one way or another
most of us
the last majority of us have an experience that we call orgasm
and for some of us this happens in childhood
and for others it's in our teens and for some
it might not be even until our adulthood
and there are more life phases than those ones
as well
but there are
experiences of intimacy that make what we think of as
orgasm seem trivial in comparison
and these are four modes of intimacy
that's not true
no it's true
there's a broad array of experiences that are normally
well they are very successfully inhibited in us
moderns and there's a broad array of
modes of cognition the use
the reformation or the formation
of modes of awareness, consciousness
things that resemble thought and so forth
that are so different from everything we've ever imagined
and yet are natural to our kind of being
our form, our humanity, our animality
our values, our organismality, our beingness
there are
modes of intimacy
so ecstatic that you would never trade them for an orgasm
and this is part of why we hear
some mystics singing the praises
of
what the
ascetic path
the path of not
of non-indulgence
the path of chastity or temperance
and you know dreaming
really is very very profound
and in dreaming there can be modes
of adoration and eros that are vastly
beyond what we are inclined to usually experience while awake or
beyond what seems accessible to
to us while awake
in our life phase, in our development
but what I'm trying to get at here is that this thing we call
orgasm
it is in a sense
a
there's different ways to say this
it's a repercussion
of participatory intimacy
that can be physically produced
and since our first experiences with it
are usually catalyzed by physical sensations
rhythms
rhythmic pulsing, rubbing, so forth
we should understand that that is a
interstasis, a lesser exemplar of something for which there is
a forest of superpositions above that
and when I was a child and I was fascinated with science what I didn't realize
is that I had no way to understand this
although some people tried to say something maybe this is why
the problem ensued
there didn't seem to be anyone whose knowledge was deeper than
the knowledge of scientists
but the knowledge of the poets, of the mystics, of the philosophers
of the adoring ones
this knowledge makes
the powers of science
shrivel
they are still mechanically powerful and may in fact snuff our planet
and our people
yes they are physically very powerful
but where is the intimacy
it is that participatory intimacy that we
hunger for and when we hope
not for justice
but for
the diminution
the
transformative composting
of injustices
it is this participatory
intimacy
that we know
we sense would thereafter
obtain
and become
the water
the many forms of waters
in which our hearts
and histories and futures could then
swim
we
we poor moderns
have named nearly everything and thus evicted
all the named
features and beings and relationships and situations
from much of our experience
yeah
hmm
we have representational
knowledge
miles deep
how tragic for us
that is the
the alexandrian library of the skeletal remains of what
might have been understanding and insight
medicinal awareness
transformative ecstatic participation
magic wonder play
all
virtue
walking in the botanical gardens here
even though
this is a place curated by
my extremely confused at the group level species
the living beings here
they form a
a manifold over
the strange
dead inside evictions that otherwise prevail
as cities and roads
shops and buildings and so forth
and they are ecstatic
and in our way of being in time
this ecstasy would flow into and through
and around and between
all the aspects of our being in such a way as to draw us
into transcendent visionary awareness
and I don't say this
because I know it this isn't knowledge
I'm on the verge of experience
I'm on the verge of the experience of what I hear
suggest
we are not distinct
in the ways our common thought
suppose
or create
and there are games afoot there are missions here so beautiful
that the entire history of language and knowledge
has nothing to do with them
there's no thing you can formally know
that's more interesting
than the kiss of your beloved
of that food grown by your grandmother in her garden
on endless afternoons
to make the foods
the families would consume
together
mostly in distracted confusion
especially once
the
the invention of televisions began to become dominant
and think for a moment of what the television is replacing
there's a reason that thing is so compelling
was so compelling it's a reason why we have these screens
they are counterfeiting something
and if you think just a little bit you will see what they are counterfeiting
and what it is is something resembling group dreaming, group telepathy
group organized, group missioneering
organized group anemnesis
and this is what we must reach for together if we are to retrieve
the faculties
the ecstasies
the beauty of our origins and natures and potentials
and that's a mission I adore
and do believe in
and if my humble
speaking
can contribute
then I will have lived this day
in a way worthy of
my ancestors and their dreams
my progeny and their dreams
which dreams must not
be euthanized
my thought, language, machine
modernity, war, prison-eering, commerce
tokenization, representation
and conviction
there are many ferns here
I've always loved the forms of the plants
the insects are impossible
the organisms on this world are fundamentally
impossible
the staggering burdens of representational
cognition ecstasy would naturally arise
because we ourselves are
and are surrounded by
infinite manifolds of impossibly beautiful wonder
organism
origin
spirit
purpose
the superposition from which the concept of beauty is derived
the living bubble
of being, history and future and purpose
that naturally
in beauties up from the soil
I die like trees
rain ecstatic
originary true vital
oh how I adore these organisms
how confused I mostly am
when deprived
of that fundamental participatory intimacy
which is true recognition
and explosive anemesis
thank you for joining me
I'm so grateful to have this time
take a moment to like
or comment or ask a question
or share something personal
in this way you will
help
help my humble efforts
reach more people
may your ways be beautiful
your hearts be light and your relationships
exquisite
thank you for joining me
I look forward to learning
together again very soon
bye bye for now