hello everybody if I had realized that I might be motivated to make a
recording while I was out walking today I would have brought something to screen
the wind and usually a cotton ball or even some facial tissue wrapped around
the mic with a rubber band something like this it's enough it works it works
fine for my recording setup
yeah I'm not going to talk about that all right so what is on my mind first of
all I am where am I I am at a lake it is very windy and no shame for any of you
who decide this is too much wind noise for you but those of you who are bold
can accompany me in this strange adventure where I am risking my life
primarily from widowmaker tree falls to get a little exercise on Sunday in the
midst of some really interestingly stormy weather lots of wind gusts
occasional bouts of serious rain but not the long slow calm kind of rain that is
often well less threatening when the minute when the wind picks up the
primary threat seems to be trees falling and where I live there's a lot of sand
actually that's ridiculous let me be more clear as I understand it most of
Golden Gate Park is a giant sand dune with some complex aquifers underneath it
so I guess long ago the humans imported a bunch of topsoil so to speak and spread
it all around and one of my friends well actually no longer my friend what ex
communicated me for let's see I had a tiny bit of a sniffle and I was outside in
the gardens without a mask on or no I had a mask on actually but as I wasn't
severely quarantining I guess my friend decided I was a bad man turned out that
it was less than tiny allergies that I was experiencing not even a cold and I
certainly wasn't getting in anyone's face so yes she once remarked you know
there's so many non-native trees here and they just don't form deep roots and I
thought I mean especially now it's very obvious to me that she having the status that we would
associate with a person of color particularly whose ancestry comes from India might have
been making a psychological right right a displacement or a projection in metaphor
without knowing it because what I saw we see a lot of trees fall here in fact I'm
looking at five or six that fell recently right now yeah there's a bunch of them wow
I mean it's you know it's literally dangerous to be out in weather this windy the secondary
danger for pedestrians is stuff going in your eye or being impaled on your umbrella but anyway
back to the tree things so my friend who excommunicated me is a docent at the botanical
gardens I think still and I would be surprised if she did not understand that you're talking
about a maximum of two or three feet in most places of topsoil sometimes less and then just
saying right so when trees fall over I don't think it's because they're non-native right they fall
over they don't form complex root systems not because they're not native but because it's pretty
hard to do in sand right so yeah part of the it's funny part of the the trail here has been
cordoned off
yeah I guess there's also being hit in the head by things that fall that aren't branches for
example pine cones and stuff or little pieces of branches that could wipe you out as a human
it doesn't take a lot of weight coming from the sky you know 20 30 feet above your head
to hurt you or even kill you especially if you're not wearing a hard hat so yeah lots of risk
what's the f side well a couple of things one who as one gets older you start to have to pick
more or less explicitly between something resembling
more adventure or something resembling more safety and the more safety line
is devastating in a bunch of ways because although you could handle maybe you could handle
box life um without too much trouble a while ago when you start getting older
the comfort of box life begins to become rattle into the comfort of the grave so to speak
metaphorically and so
so
one necessarily chooses and it's a choice that you make each day now it's similar with
our minds do we adventure or do we stay in familiar terrain
um and why and what what turns out to happen is it's a bit like exercise
if you don't if you don't keep it up
it tends to oh wow there's a little yeah see I just saw a branch fall that
could have definitely hurt someone thankfully it was um
slowish oh wow I just heard another one yeah it's like I'm out here and it's it's like I'm
hearing gunshots right except they're not gunshots they're tree breaks
so it's probably good that trail was cordoned off because I might have been stupid enough to go
up there and I can tell from here basically it's a bunch of cypress trees and these things naturally
produce um I think it's mostly cypress and they naturally produce these long slender branches
that are prone especially when water soaked to just snap off right it might be some kind of
you know evolutionary benefit or something maybe maybe those branches both fertilize the ground as
they as they fall apart or um bring other organisms or root possibly or maybe there's no
you know obvious benefit if we're doing what we might imagine is Darwinian accounting
which brings me to a variety of topics I've long held to switch to the topic of house cats
that house cats are basically they can be understood from a variety of interesting perspectives
including that they are effectively ambient psychedelic organisms meaning that if you begin
to bond your mind with the mind of a provocatively intelligent house cat rather than a really lazy
one but even the lazy ones or it's like they're smoking opium or something all the time um
or rather they don't need to smoke anything uh the Cheshire cat in Alice in Wonderland is sort of an
example of someone who has noticed the strangeness of the cats but I have long held that um
in terms of intelligence and non-human intelligence and alien like not alien is in bad alien is in
family member from another origin right more like that um yeah the house cats those are
like the square root of an octopus is a house cat you know
and maybe if you you know house cat to the second or third power equals praying mantis or
something like this and you know you can flip it around um the the the intelligence of the
ambush predators is very unique and profound um and the intelligence of a house cat which is a
really peculiar an animal with a very peculiar history um developmental history very peculiar
and trippy because it goes from being a wild alpha predator to being a half domesticated
beta like you know delta predator or something that effectively causes its primary symbiont
right um captures a food source in humans trippy right very strange very unexpected um from some
perspectives now of course the natural contrast to a house cat is the dog um similar similar
developmental history uh and look um cats aren't not pack animals they just uh you
know lions at least um have what we call prides in english groups and are there other
examples i don't know there are probably examples of couplings and friendships but not
primary necessary groups i just don't know enough about the feeling animals to know
but there's at least one example of uh where they form you know cohorts and pods
and i imagine young lions and perhaps mountain lions and so forth may certainly when they're young
right they um travel and hunt and play with their siblings who knows if there's inter
interfamily activity of that kind i was talking to my friend uh jay the other night
actually was last night and we were talking about this this topic and i love to wax uh
enthusiastic about the intelligences of the ambush predators because they are in a sense
like if you want security and um familiarity dogs work beautifully right those are the solar
animal essentially of the pair and look there are solar cats and there are lunar dogs but
fundamentally um the dog is the solar animal uh daytime predator right um although not entirely
you got coyotes and wolves that are nocturnal um maybe i had that wrong actually uh nighttime
predator nocturnal and similarly cats also nocturnal but perhaps more so than dogs
um tend to sleep all day stay up all night left to their own devices probably
i don't know what they would do in their natural situations because i don't see those
animals in those situations but i do think of dogs as solar
not explicitly and not only and cats as
though now there's going to be some serious wind
so we were talking about this the other night and okay what was the topic all right the topic
was actually pretty deep it was
a topic that i've spoken of some recently but even since then the insight has been enriched
it's the topic of what happens when something captures the nervous system of an animal
and there's lots of stuff that capture our nervous system
um a simple example of this is that you know it's the pavlovian thing right if we smell
something delicious in fact i'm just i'm merely thinking of something delicious and my mouth is
starting to water but if i smell something delicious much more so so that's an example where
where you can see that i have no control i have no mental control over
so
gale force winds just short of hurricane speed
i have no control over whether my mouth waters or not that i know of
of might be able to influence it with nlp or hypnosis or something but i have no
my salvation and similarly if i hear one of those gunshot branch cracks and it's loud
enough and near enough probably y'all jump
when you see corvids at least around here
approaching food on the ground
they will often sort of hop toward it and leap backwards
i was thinking a lot about that particular behavior the other day after observing it because
trying to understand
one thing i can imagine now which it didn't occur to me before
i mean it's not crazy it's natural it's just different from the very safe norm
that usually applies and the difference is profound enough that i am well aware i could
be killed it's not very likely but it's probably 50 times more likely than it was yesterday
all right so
the thing that occurs to me now and i couldn't figure it out before but now it seems relatively
obvious snakes eat birds and one of the best ways to catch bird
would be to hang out near the corpse of an animal right
you're an ambush predator you have that that feline intelligence that praying mantis intelligence
that octopus intelligence the jumping spider intelligence right you have this
trap setting capable capable of setting a trap intelligence praying mantis is straight
upset traps on flowers right just no doubt about it you see them do it all the time
so i wouldn't ambush predators
and since corvids eat meat
they eat other stuff too they eat seeds and bugs and worms and stuff it depends on the birds and where they are
since they eat meat
what might happen is a snake might or other ambush predator possibly not sure what a bobcat maybe
what else would eat birds i don't think i mean coyotes eat birds but they also eat dead things
snakes don't usually i don't know of any snakes that eat corpses
now you can teach cage snakes to eat dead mice i don't know if they eat dead mice in the wild
not clear to me it seems pragmatically effective that they should i just don't know
but yeah i can imagine snake hangs out near bird food of any kind right dead things seed piles you
name it and just waits for birds and waits close enough that when the bird gets to the food item
it's within striking distance of the snake so that would explain
evolutionarily how the peck jumped back like it's literally like that that
that song that has the lyrics jump back jack in it the bird like goes forward and then leaves
backward it may do that a few times and after like two or three times it'll it may just fly
off and leave the food alone that does happen i've seen it but what's going on there isn't that the
bird is thinking i'm scared i think what's going on is that the bird's nervous system has been
captured by something like an evolutionarily developed and look the thing may not be genetic
there's got to be nine other ways of influencing organisms that aren't merely genes and most of
those ways might we would argue would would necessarily have some effect on genomes because
they they become selection variables in that theory and we're going to get some weird stuff
about that in a minute um so they might have they might have selective
functions so to speak or effect
but yeah what i think is going on is that the organism's nervous system has been captured
and like a goose that sees a ball rolled a few feet from its nest during a certain season
and it will go the goose will crane its neck at least this is what i've heard
crane its neck from research crane its neck go toward the ball and roll the ball back into
the nest whether or not there's a ball there anymore at all and you know whether or not it
much resembles an egg so you can see that
there are these protocols you know in the age of computers we would be likely to call them programs
because we're just reaching around for some metaphor but it's a
historically physically structured vulnerability to capture
when an organism detects high heat suddenly it recoils
it may recoil from other things water food that may not be safe or smells wrong
um you know one kid on the bus uh disgorges his breakfast on the floor
now you pretty soon have what a oh this could be good just siren
we might get a demonstration of this effect let's see
uh yeah pretty soon you've got you know
sudden unexpected public vomitorium on the bus right because once two more kids
follow suit and they're certainly not doing that on purpose right they're not trying to do that
they don't want to do that they can't help it
so uh
we didn't get the example i wanted so um
you can see that there's a structured response
um that's probably ordinarily rather than being activated
we can think of it both ways and we probably should
rather than being activated by stimuli it could also just be ordinarily inhibited
and under some circumstances that inhibition collapses and the coyote howls
in concert with the approach of a siren not because it wants to
not because i mean possibly it's in pain it is possible we don't know and it's reasonable to
imagine it might be um when you present uh wildly exaggerated stimuli to an extremely sensitive
organisms
to a hypersensitive organism right if a wasp can detect one molecule of a substance within
a two-mile range within a two-mile circle as i understand it some wasps are capable of that
degree of sensitivity if you subject them to for example
some kind of human perfume laundry soap for example laundry soap stench
could be physically painful to them so we don't know whether the siren is physically painful
but we do know that it resembles other coyotes calling
and so when the dogs howl in the coyotes um howl at the siren there's a good chance that
they're just being triggered right their body is howling not their mind and
um you know we hear people talk about sensory experiences like the hair stood up on the back
of my neck um i got goosebumps and obviously goosebumps are a thing that happens when we're
cold too but uh there are certain physiological transformations uh heart palpitates right we
like i don't know if we like it i think we like it because we're our most of our experience is
kind of deadened but we like horror movies sometimes or we may like um scary rides because they
deprive us of the control we might ordinarily have over our body's sensations
or the selection of sensations right actively selecting sensations
um and subject us to extraordinary forces and sensations
so we too can be triggered
um it would be interesting to see the library of programs so to speak they're not actually
programs i don't think but to see like the library of a single creature now obviously if you
observe a single creature very closely over time and you observe many of them many of their kind
quote unquote you will begin to understand something of the library uh so praying mantises for example
will they have a complex striking uh behavior it's a pray capture behavior but they can use
it like a punch as well and they have a complex uh threat display where their body transforms
you know into a creature oriented to both fight and shock uh a possibly predatory animal creature
so we were talking about the peculiarities obviously right like social media is weaponizing
this against us it one could say it is studying in a sense human activity and then producing
hopeful monsters that capture it amplify it um and make it contagious that's one of the dumbest
uses of technology that anyone could imagine i mean it's almost as dumb as just throwing bricks
at people's heads the problem here is that they can't see the brick right it has the same effect
in that they get dumber every time they're subjected to it most of them some of them
have a good buffer some of the humans um but yeah they get dumber every time like
every iteration makes them dumber and
the problem there is really dangerous because anything that reduces your awareness or sensitivity
over time is prone to create a situation where you can't you won't be able to perceive what you've
lost and this is part of the problem with ordinary human aging one might argue that social media
ages certain aspects of us um precipitously and invisibly
since our bodies don't age in response though i think actually internally they do we don't notice
anything that affects the thing you notice with right creates a really good
a really effective process that hides its own it hides its own progress and it hides the damage it
does it naturally does this so we want to have awareness when we approach technologies or media
we want to have awareness of what's getting compromised how quickly how deeply
and how can we if it if it becomes necessary for some reason that we interact with the technology
anyway or if we want to we want to have the intelligence necessary to make determinations
about what that curve of harm looks like to whatever degree we are able and then adjust
our behavior accordingly so as to preserve the assets that would otherwise be lost
now you can see that the pros for example when they approach a food source on the ground
start to go at it and then jump back they're testing to see if anything moves nearby the food
during that process and if it does they will become aware that the food is a trap
now obviously also once humans became tool makers of some kind they probably made bird traps too
of various kinds and so the bird is trying to check whether you know probably a
whether there's a organismal trap and b whether there's a physical trap even though it may not
its body probably isn't a complexly differentiating between those two things
all right so triggering
I think even likely for an organism to take advantage of programs that are normally
let's not call them programs let's call them abilities
for or what do I want to call them
abilities
each organism seems to uniquely develop
of
yeah this is this starts to run into problems between the difference between language and
description and what animals and organisms actually are and are doing are being
so imagine a broad spectrum of unique forms of sensitivity and or intelligence
that naturally result in super effective like meta effective
relational or physical
skills one can imagine that it might be possible for an organism to
especially for humans for example because we have a lot we have a great deal of luxury
compared to most animals in consciously determining our developmental spectrum spectra
so the humans we probably have access to
to at least probably thousands of potentially developable
abilities that result when enacted in something resembling either relational or physical
super function or both and one tends to lead to the other right because for example
brilliant athletes who become known for their athleticism
acquire relational benefits what we call fame which radically increases both there
the opportunity space for reproduction but also for just enjoyment
unfortunately at the same time because of how strange the humans are in modernity and maybe forever
that will also attract enemies opponents undesirable possibly obsessive attention from other humans
and maybe under some circumstances from the sky itself
so my friend and I were talking about cats and she said something resembling you know
well i was talking about how cats can be triggered right if they and that sometimes house cats
dogs you can see dogs doing behaviors displaying behaviors that and i guess i'm anthropomorphizing
bit that may be natural for humans or at least some humans
you know when a dog makes a silly mistake a silly physical mistake or like
it misses the bite or it slides chasing the ball it crashes into the wall or
and by the way that's you can see triggering right there because the dog ordinarily does
not crash into things but under circumstances where it becomes hyper focused on the ball
it will crash in many dogs will just crash into walls or other nearby objects
so
i have seen okay we're in gale force winskin dogs appear to exhibit emotions that resemble shame
and or embarrassment i'm granting that that's my interpretation
after cert after being witnessed
they seem to be aware of observation in a way not dissimilar to how we are
if i suddenly step on the side of my foot for example and begin to stumble because i missed
step the first problem is the pain in my ankle but the second problem is did anybody see me
you know i will quickly glance around to see if i have been seen to have failed at something
as simple as taking a step right so i was i was explaining that it was my experience when i began
to learn more about cats because my girlfriend had a pair and certainly i encountered them many
times before but i think this pair of cats was the pair i was most intimate with him
throughout my life to memorialize them mexicat and panther which who was her son
mexicat was a very hyper intelligent sensitive loving soft mother cat very fluffy furry white
found in the desert with a piece of her tail missing as a kitten i think if i remember right
and panther was one of her children big black fluffy
cat and panther would when we were playing occasionally and i've seen other cats do this
very few of them won't be triggered if you accept the gambit so this is this is a gambit in animal
chess called cat belly when dogs give you their belly it may or may not be submissive but it's
they're they're showing their vulnerability because their primary powers as an animal
are
the primary powers are like a spear in a dog they lunge and penetrate
the cat is different it can lunge but it normally attacks with paws because those are razor sharp
and grippy and once it gets a grip then it can penetrate usually the neck of a creature often
the neck with jaws both animals have bone breaking jaw power the cats is less because it's smaller
the house cat anyway um but what what she was saying i was saying that basically sometimes
i would pet panther and he would you know roll over on his back and this seemed to be an invitation
for you know some gentle aware belly petting um gentle and aware both because you know this is
an animal's vulnerable underside and previous experience had taught me that under certain conditions
cats become triggered and when they are triggered they may bite unintentionally
and usually they can manage the force so that it's not really bad it's still painful
and they also can there's some word for this it's not worry that's what a dog does it's
some kind of shredding thing they basically um grasp with their front paws and may claw with them
and then shred or gash with their rear paws and so what would happen is i'd be petting panther
we'd be having like a love session and you know he really he really enjoys that but then sometimes
he would get triggered and capture my hand bite it and try to rip at it with his back claws and then
he would he would sort of snap out of it and display signs of that i interpreted as sadness
shame embarrassment i didn't mean to do that this kind of thing and uh it took me a long time to
understand what was going on i certainly didn't understand to the degree that i you know in any
thing that resembles what i'm saying now i was unconsciously aware but not cognitively and
conceptually aware of what was going on i didn't have a model but i did learn very quickly that
when cats show you their belly it's either one of two things usually going on either they really
will enjoy the intimacy and danger of allowing it effectively a god right an animal that is
unimaginably powerful full compared to you um you can kill a cat probably just by crushing
its rib cage in your single in the grip of one hand right you can kill it if you wanted to kill
a cat hopefully you don't um it would take very little effort on your part to destroy the animal
physically and there's very little the cat could do about it so and the cat may not know your
physical strength but it probably suspects it from examining you so when the cat rolls over either
um it has learned to inhibit the triggering that is likely to happen when you approach
its belly with your hand and begin stroking it um and so it just enjoys the ecstatic feeling
of being vulnerable like being loved where one is most vulnerable so to speak
in human language um but other cats and again look the cat rolls over and displays its belly
so something's going on there but it's not necessarily my friend was saying a display of
submission or you know because when the cat is on its back all 20 of its face knife footraisers
are accessible and the bite and so now
it can grip with its fore paws bite
and shred with its hind legs
and this is a for for many animals I suspect this is a disemboweling move right it opens up
first of all just opens up gashes on the animal if you're a large cat
if you're a small cat it still messes them up
so yeah we had a big laugh because she was like the cat rolls over and people think it's a submission
move because they've been watching dogs or something it may or may not be partly submissive
but basically the cat now has full access to all of its weapons
it's almost like the cat is saying like the cat is daring you
right do you want to put your hand in the chainsaw
it's like a Tasmanian devil in loony tunes I just rips things apart
so I thought that was hilarious hilarious take on
cats but if you want non-ordinary experience
if you're someone who seeks that the best place to seek it is in
devoted contact with the living place with specific animals and birds
you know it doesn't matter whether plants have spirits or plants have minds
they are organisms and we are organisms and we are organisms from the same world
so in one set of categories that makes us the same thing the same being
we are that that tree is me outside my body I am the tree outside its trunk
and I'm not saying this is a fact but it is categorically true before even we are organisms
we are beings so it goes like the concentric circles go like mystery universe then beings
and organisms and earth organisms and then you know on down the line to animals human animals
and that's just what if what if our category tree is missing three important elements and I would
argue it is so that we can't even see them in language there's no way to detect them in concepts
because we have no placeholder for them in our categorical libraries
and I think actually this is a huge problem for all humans
but particularly for we who speak English because our category tree
is it's almost like it was hit by a shotgun or something it's missing big chunks of crucially
important placeholders shelves containers so forth that would draw our attention to
modes of existence that we no longer have a placeholder for and so since we don't most of those modes
get they get exported to the supernatural the psychic the superstitious the religious but
they shouldn't they don't need to be the actual situation is so weird that it's weirder than all
of supernatural speculation it's weirder than all religious speculation it's weirder than all of science
so none of those should become the authorities of identity those are conceptual frameworks
right you might argue one might reasonably argue that humans are particularly vulnerable
to structured reactions that are not necessarily physical but are similarly involuntary and our
conceptual right what would be an example well weirdly I was listening to the most enlightening
podcast last night on I think a philosopher called Dugan that it is in thought that it is
thought or Durgan that it is thought influenced influences Putin's policy dramatically
and for the first time I heard
powerful criticisms of the concept of liberal being liberal
so yes where was I going all right
examples of such cognitive traps are the Christian belief that everybody who doesn't accept Jesus
is going to hell and that there's a Satan now similarly the doctrinal liberal belief
once it becomes doctrine once you have to either be liberal or fascist the liberal belief that
you get to invent your identity you get to invent your gender you are free to completely dispose
of all conventions and anyone who doesn't dispose of these conventions is evil
particularly if they do not dispose of them in the way that you dispose of them
now you have sectarian liberality right and this can become extremely dangerous virulent
and compelling for humans we
adopt programs from not tradition but traditional language and the traditional
presuppositions about identity meaning and value also which games are played
that are imported when we learn a modern language particularly in my case I can speak
only telling me about English okay
hmm so
wow that's interesting
I've walked around the lake I think I'm on my third circuit
I'm sure you heard that sound that sound was the sound of a spear
falling from a cypress into the ground a foot from me it was pointed straight down
it was pointy on the end it stuck into the ground and it had a cone on it it was small but
had I been struck by that likely I'd have been injured possibly seriously
so it's probably time to stop the adventure but I'm not going to just yet
because the sun has come back out and there's a break in the rain and it's a good time to
stretch my legs I think of course I could walk in safer places
um
that startled me so I branched in thought
yes so the humans are vulnerable okay when we learn a language like English a bunch of
games are imported like courtroom mind or war mine or mine and yours or us and them
now us and them exist in most languages and conceptual frameworks
uh but the way the particular character of the English the modern the colonial
the neocolonial the pericolonial
you know what that is it's probably crashing crashing trees it's tree branches snapping yeah
scary yeah be careful uh there I've seen branches fall on the path it's very very windy
they can kill you I'm not saying don't walk I'm out here walking too but just be aware because
it is yeah yeah but I almost got hit a moment ago by like a spear that's stuck in the ground
and it was like a foot from me so be you know be aware those those cypresses they naturally
drop large branches so on that side you're at risk around this side not so much yeah okay my pleasure
yeah there were some gunshot branch cracks
all right I keep getting distracted but thanks for bearing with me those of you who have hopefully
I'll give you some uh some juicy morsels here um all right so
so
complex array of what I would call malware comes packaged with English and it's not
actually it's not in the language
per se the malware isn't necessarily in the language
the malware is packaged in metaphors models of identity meaning value relation function
um
efficacy and basically good and evil that come from the cultural or anti-cultural right the malware
traditions that
influenced how we tend to utilize the language together particularly today and over say the
past two three hundred years um the malware package that's attached to languages evolves
over time along with the language it's not clear that the languages contain malware rather it's
the suppositions underlying their deployment and particularly their deployment um beyond
the personal like the person-to-person environment in the larger social and
and disease riddled you know um cultural
dumpster fire that is you know modernity
back into the gusty winds but not too dangerous here
so there's no trees likely to drop a branch on me near me
all right so
recently I've been listening to people like David Berlinsky and actually there's a primary
author whose name I can't remember but also
um a man whose name I'm going to mispronounce David Gilertner and if you want to find one of the
things I listen to um just search on mathematics and Darwin and okay so Darwin's book was called
The Origin of Species it is by it is you know he was the Einstein in a sense of biology
in that he gave us a map that appeared to be valid and explanatory for a broad range of
uh observable phenomena um and doctrinally
it is canon to oppose it in any way is to earn broad denigration attack insult
and this is unfortunate because science should never be about doctrine
science should be about discovery and logical rational thought
it should not cater to biases or presuppositions in fact it shouldn't cater to anything
but the facts and an ever-improving description of the relationships between them that we observe
obviously this involves explanatory manifolds
so intuition and suppositions about identity function
distinction and and you know the scientific method is fundamentally dissective
so it tends to break things down into parts and then examine relationships
that by itself can be an error but um
nearly every biologist believes well maybe that's not true many many modern biologists believe that
that the book entitled the origin of species
does in fact tell us how species arose
and so is generally accepted as an origin of life argument tells us how we got species from
the origin you know organisms now it doesn't make any I don't I don't actually know the
book well my doubt explains about origin of life because that's still quite mysterious
even though the mechanical physicalist
eliminative materialist version is either soup you got a complex soup on earth that
eventually produced cells or you know RNA and then there's some you know leap from RNA
to cells and DNA and bacteria and protists and archaea and so forth
but nobody knows how you get from chemistry to life
there are precisely zero successful models of this
uh lots of people have speculations some of those speculation the belief is generally
and what is taught is that life is the mechanical result of the combination of chemicals
and forces on earth
um
and a number of scientists who are not trying to import god into biology
are making the claim for intelligent design by falsifying something resembling
Darwin's blind watchmaker claim
i.e okay so the one of the old proofs of the existence of god was the unimaginable complexity
of organisms now our human experience of that complexity and our cognition about it has changed
quite a bit over many years
particularly since Darwin and has been influenced by a bunch of doctrinal garbage
that really has nothing to do with it but a long time ago someone possibly bacon
argued maybe it was Francis Bacon i don't i can't remember
argued that the existence of organisms proves the existence of god because
if you were walking along a if you were walking along a path in the forest
and you look down and you saw for example
i'm going to use a sort of weird example um a colander
right
uh or a knife
i'm using a very simple physical object a knife you would not presume
be very unlikely for you to presume that the knife had been produced by the accidental combination
of substance and forces
there are certain kinds of objects
that naturally to our intuition imply a mind was involved in creating them
and fundamentally these objects can be said and in some cases blatantly obviously do
they can be said to encode information
so for example
dna is a digital data storage and propagation machine if we think in those terms i don't
but i'll use the language common to biologists of my day they tend to think as the they think
they think of cells and organisms as machines which i think is hilarious i get what they mean
um they don't mean diesel engine they mean
a structured process that causes the transformation combination and distinction
of various substances and structures over time
i mean something resembling that
i don't think of them as machines but we'll use the language so where was i the machines
there are precise precisely zero
instances we know of
of where complex ordered information was produced without a mind
the biologists are presuming
unjustifiably that the cell is such an arrangement there is no evidence for that in fact
if we do the math these scientists argue
um i think one of the guys wrote a book that might be called darwin's delusion
and by the way what they're saying is effectively this
darwin got the theory right for downstream transformations of genomes mutations
changing parts of an animal from you know a bat wing to a bird wing or something
right um mutations that don't wipe out the organism and we'll get to an interesting feature
of that in a minute so the the scientists that are questioning this and look we don't have any
good arguments for origin of life panspermia is a change of arena right that's a rhetorical fallacy
you just move the you move the question elsewhere without supplying any useful further information
about it right um because you have the same problem with panspermia that you have with
origin of life on earth if life traveled here from elsewhere it had to begin somehow
and so it either began on a planet like ours or it began in an interstellar space or
it began somewhere maybe something we don't even understand you know again
the origin of life could be so profound that the concepts we presently rely on
uh
are insufficient
all right um though the scientists rarely argue this
so what they're saying so first of all we have no good explanation for the origin of life
many biologists believe that it's essentially a mechanical accident there's no evidence for
the involvement of an intelligence uh the east scientists believe that there's no evidence for
the accident in fact they cite mathematical analyses of for example the probability of
accidentally producing what
a useful protein i think is the example they gave
i can't recall if they were examining for you know an amino acid or what specific
um biochemical element they were they were speaking of but i think what they said
is that the chances of producing a useful protein by accident okay the search space is
something like one in ten to the seventy and that's just one protein we're not talking about
you accidentally produced an organism um that resembles the probability of being able to locate
a single point particle say uh proton single proton in a search space nine like as large as
nine of our universe as we presently understand it the chances of you might as well call it
imp or linsky says if you want to say it's impossible i'm on your side if you want to say
it's improbable i'm on your side but let's be clear it's monumentally probable
and you know something i've argued for probably almost 20 years is that the complexity of the cell
radically defies anything any explanation that the humans can come up with at all
and this has turned out to be prophetic in that every 10 years or so
the complex as the complexity as the apparent complexity of the cell expands
for our science perhaps sometimes geometrically the possibility of explaining it recedes with every
expansion um and it recedes at a similar pace right it's like you thought you knew what was
going on you now found out there were 10 trillion variables you weren't including your chance of
explaining that mostly just disappears into infinity you know in my perspective uh i think our
physical theories are insufficient to explain biological phenomena and their origins and their
meanings and almost certainly their purposes which of which reproduction is not you know in the
physicalist lexicon that's the crucial thing to do but there's probably 900 other things they're
doing and there's certainly 15 of those that are nothing like what we suppose if you actually observe
organisms with an open mind you're going to discover something that generally defies description
it's not there for description for the purpose of humans describing it there's nothing to do
okay what the heck is this it's an artificial rock i don't understand oh i see it's a rat trap
wow it's a rat trap that looks like a rock wow humans are crazy
hmm i think i should visit my friend the tree
so
the scientists are in question here are very upset that textbook biology and the
the broad scale supposition of mechanical accident his origin for life a proposition for which not
only is there no evidence or nearly none um if we run some of the analytic math so that we come to
understand what the actual probabilities we we should be looking at are at this phase in our
understanding the math points in the direction that unless unless something really strange here
happened unless you hit the lottery you know unless you won the lottery 9 000 times in a row
like you you won almost every time you played there's no chance of producing not not never mind
organisms just RNA DNA the complex protein synthesis apparatus of cells all of these things
or not no chance but an unimaginably almost infinitely unimaginably small chance literally
you know zero with a bit you know i don't know 5 000 decimal points after it and then a one
so uh i looked up the author um
although perhaps burlinski has collaborated with him stefan mire they have some essays and books
the deniable darwin darwin's doubt and i suspect they also make arguments that darwin himself doubted
that his theory was any explanation for the emergence of organisms on earth or
for the poorly defined idea of species
so it turns out that the origin of life arguments that are doctrinal are mostly nonsense
uh it's not that they're that it's entirely impossible that the emergence of life on earth
was a purely mechanical accident it's we have the actual problem you know minus uh the supposition
of god in the original argument that if you find something finely articulated and what could be
more finely articulated than a blue j it makes i mean just at at the level of its cells
its 900 magnitudes of complexity beyond any machine we've ever built a single cell
so
staggers the the computational complexity of the entire history of humans doing math
and it does that over the temporal space of like 10 seconds or maybe even one and we're talking
a single cell so you have a cell either hyper structure like a blue j or a raccoon
you're looking at something that
is pure science fiction there's no chance of something that sophisticated and agentive
was produced by accident at least not in any way that we can presently propose
is when we find in nature extremely complex objects invariably they are the produce of
minds with zero known exceptions so it's it's sort of the opposite of the problem we have
with um sorry i'm getting battered by the weather um it's the opposite of the problem we have
with the technical probability of there being life on other planets technically
due to how statistics and probability function if you have only a single
example of something you have no chance of determining the probability therefore the
probability is stated as zero so until probabilistically according to how we use statistics and probability
um there is zero probability of life on other worlds because it's unknown you have no data
with no data you can't produce a probabilistic estimate there are other ways to estimate the
probability intuitively we are very unlikely to believe that in a universe as vast as ours
this is the only planet with life that life we would have to believe that life
cannot spread from solar system to solar system or that there are no mechanisms for that transfer
to take place because if there were especially if there were fast methods
um something possibly sheldrake's morphogenic fields might represent
a sort of layer in in the universe or in time space in which once you manage to get an organism
on one world somewhere in time it's now vastly easier to get it on another one
um i doubt any of these scientists are fans of sheldrake meaning burlinski,
alertner and mire
but what i'm what i'm getting at is it could be that there are features of the everything
and i prefer that term or really the every one thing way all nests there are features of the
grand unity that we don't know anything about and could easily i think could reasonably possibly
set up a network between planets where information is transferred either at incredible speed or
instantaneously there might be forms of fields capable of doing this but this is my argument not
there's um what is their argument so their argument is that if you take the entire biospace
of organisms that we believe have ever existed on earth this includes you know bacteria viruses
the whole thing everything that number is something like 10 to the 40
if you then
divide the search space 10 to the 70 by the number of chances you have to produce say one useful protein
you're left with i don't know 10 to the 30 or something
um which is effectively no chance it means that over the history of life on earth there wasn't
time to accidentally assemble a useful protein uh unless something was going on that we don't
understand right and this inclines them to believe that that the explanation of intentional
terraforming or biospace was vastly vastly more probable than this was a mechanical accident
you got some chemistry together you got some forces together
out pops organisms that make unimaginably complex proteins and you know rna dna mrna
all of these things right uh that stuff just pops up you know on a roulette wheel right you
just keep spinning the wheel long enough out comes archaea so yeah wildly unlikely
whatever darwin showed us it wasn't how species originated a really good grasp on
certain features of of biology
mutation selection all this but nothing for how species arise right how do you get a different
animal from a prototype we don't know and it's very unlikely to be accidental so it turns out
there's another problem which is something like the incredible amount of wind and rain pounding
into my face at the moment no i'm kidding there's another problem with where the kinds of mutations
that would give you a different animal from a prototype animal have to happen early in
blastogenesis i might have that wrong but they have to happen fairly early
in the process of producing an organism from oocytes right from from egg and sperm and so forth
um although uh the language is more complex than what i'm when i'm presenting here i'm not
sure a sperm is a i think there's a different word for the sperm uh so you have to produce
a mutation early in the process to get a different animal and if you produce mutations early in the
process what you get is a dead animal like if you make any mistake early in the process
it's invariably fatal so if you get an early mutation
they said like someone said it was probably um an alert I think he said you know you have like
19 tails or way too many organs that don't fit inside the animal or you leave out like it doesn't
make blood right something fundamental goes sideways and the only way to get different animals
that we know of that we can imagine is mutations early in the in the process of generating the animal
um again those mutations tend to be fatal so you can't use mutations early in the process
and late in the process later in the process doesn't produce different animals it produces
different traits so effectively if i understood their argument there's no space
in the developmental arc of an organism that we can understand
that would allow a mutation to produce a new animal so how do you get stuff like the Cambrian
explosion it looks like on earth we have something rather than um gradual meticulous evolution of
animals which i think was long held to be the likely case we have sudden like pulses
of unexpected diversification blossoming of myriad species myriad different organisms
and that certainly isn't explained by anything we have no idea how you get i mean i have some
propositions about this i would argue that um it's probably it could be helpful very helpful
to look at the organisms of earth as a single organism an organism that naturally diverges from
its origins or naturally enacts its original
uh what naturally enacts its original endowments and propensities by diversifying
that leaves me challenged to the same problem that any biologist be challenged with which is
explain the the mechanism that produces the diversification
we have no explanation so we go back to the problem of you find a wristwatch
all right you find something as complex as a wristwatch and by the way let's be very clear
a cell is i don't know 10 to the 900 times more complex than a wristwatch so you find one of those
you know imagine i don't know imagine you're walking around on a
on a new planet
and you find what i don't even know a hyper computer the size of a pinhead
you discover that there's these little pinhead like crystals on the ground when you examine them
you determine that they're hyper computers they can warp time you can do all kinds of impossible things
and you decide oh the universe must just have accidentally produced these
that like the possibility of accidental production of an organism is so much more remote
than the accidental production over wristwatch
there's no chance there's no way we could understand
how such complexity could be accidentally produced in the time frame we suppose now
if you know it's not even clear that the universe has been around long enough to do that not not
clear enough to me um given our estimates of its age and presuming that what we're thinking about
is time is even relevant at the scale of the universe which it may not be could be totally
some other property that governs that and possibly most likely one we have no concept for
all right so what else what other problems so many problems
um
there are still people who believe and do science around the supposition
that it's a mechanical accident and it's reproducible we can figure out how to produce the
mechanical accident in the lab and thus produce life forms from forces and substances
the hubris implicit in the
um suppositions
of the materialists
and those who
unjustifiably
presume that no intelligences were involved in the production of the intelligence with
which they examine the question all right it's an accidental you know it's an epiphenomenon right
of the nature of time space planets and stars all right they just accidentally produce these
minds there's nothing mind like in them there's nothing metamind like there's nothing transcendent
in them and it's an entirely mechanical process unguided by anything all right it's just not
the only thing that guides it are in some way the forces uh which would be you know chemical
bonding properties chemical transformation properties gravity electromagnetism strong
force the league force etc etc seems unlikely to me so that's been a fascinating i never really
believed that to be honest um i never supposed i didn't trust the doctrines
i can sense dark doctrines and sort of smell the stink of them in various branches of science
and philosophy and i tend to be uh i let's just say i have great antipathy for them
in my own view there are a variety of intelligences
i don't merely suppose that intelligences were involved in the composition of organisms i take
the claim much further it seems very likely to me that something beyond intelligence was involved
probably in the construction of time space because you have a similar problem there
right which is the fine-tuning problem and it's a huge problem now there is one way to
sort of what's the right word there's one way to account for the fine-tuning problem
that's a little strange but interesting to mention it is that you have a sort of a popcorn machine
right but instead of producing popped kernels of corn it produces universes and most of those
universes are not viable the forces don't interact quote unquote properly or in such a way as to
what what is meant by viable is achieves extent in time
so
you keep bubbling these universes up from some universe progenitor field okay
and the non viable universes mostly quickly dissolve and only the viable universes persist
so you will naturally if you find yourself anywhere if you find yourself at all you will find yourself
in a persistent universe otherwise you won't have a self to find or find with
and this is sometimes offered as an explanatory
uh
unexplanatory prosthesis
for
for the strangely perfect you know the goldilocks universe
and the goldilocks solar system both right because you have to have both you can't have a
goldilocks universe i mean you can't have a goldilocks solar system in a non goldilocks universe so
in this model something just keeps producing nascent universes and some of those turn out
to be viable and you will only have minds and bodies and organisms in those that do
therefore that you know sort of explains the uh the existence of the fine tuning problem
what was myers objection to that it was kind of brilliant i know he was using someone else's
objection i wonder if i can recall it i don't think i can but yeah i find this fascinating and
brilliant because these are serious scientists they are not theists um even though one of them
might be religious maybe a couple of them are i'm not sure um but they're not attempting to
import god right they're not trying to sneak god past your scientific nose they're saying look
the complexity we're discovering here cannot have been produced there's not enough time to have
produced even some of its more basic features in terms of the age of the earth now i could see
that someone could say produce the features off world somewhere import them to the earth and
then things go along fine i can imagine that line of argument but you you you may have the
same problem elsewhere what's the actual lifespan of a planet presuming that that's that life only
occurs on planets which is something i don't presume since i don't know where life originates
i i tend to be open minded and speculative about that but yeah we've got a huge problem with the
origin of life on earth in modern science the problem is steeped in doctrine the doctrine
makes no sense never made sense similar to the move to evacuate the universe of meaningful
intelligences right because we were we were science was so busy trying to get rid of god
that it threw everything away and just decided no it's all it's all just mechanics dude there's no
there's no evidence of any kind of um there's no evidence of any kind of intelligence version
of what we used to call the ether which probably got replaced by the the the
the propensity of time space to curve around mass to become curved at at at complex structure
and now more than like there may be forces that we don't know about too right i mean i'm
quite sure there must be constants and forces that we haven't discovered that might naturally
mechanically produce life but we can't argue for the existence of those until we have some
evidence of them and we can't make arguments that this the complexity we're seeing just plopped out of
a roulette wheel there's no real chance of that being true as far as i can see
so i am now home and safe and alive i am grateful for all of you who have
braved this long journey with me the terrifying noise of the wind in the mic
i'm grateful for all of you who support my work and please do if you enjoy it at least
you know log into youtube and give me a like or a shared link or something and if you
if you'd like to support my work more directly i'd be very grateful for that
a dollar a month matters if you want to make a one-time donation just let me know in the
comments and i'll i'll get you a way to do that i'm so grateful to those who do support my work
thank you all of you you help me keep making this content and i'm really really appreciate it so
i look forward to learning together again very soon may your ways and world be blessed
amazing and joyful my life for now