Hello, everybody. Welcome.
I've been listening to
Danny Jones
interviewing Neil from
Nossom Performance. I can't recall his last name at the moment.
It's like, Sendiac. Sendlak.
Something like this. Fairly interesting.
And this is obviously one of the things
that's going on with Danny's podcast at the moment, Concrete,
is that clearly he's exploring the
world around Amen
Hillman.
And
Neil has a lot of interesting historical
perspective and information. Neil is an
autodidact. He was not educated like me.
He's a self-educating person. He follows his passions
and his interests. And he became interested in these
topics through what he called
studying his way out of Christianity, which is a very interesting
thing to say.
There's a lot of good information.
Neil is very supportive of Amen's
classicism,
his Greek scholarship.
One of the things that Neil says is that most of the people that are attacking
Amen's
perspectives, I will call them.
Just basically attack it from the place of, we'll know
the agreed upon knowledge,
right? The, let's call it,
consensus.
By the way, that's basically just like saying with
the numbers, with the census.
And this is the adpopulus,
historical fallacy. Well, most people think, who gives a flying
poop storm what most people think?
Let's be really clear. If we go with generalities
and generalizations, we're only going to miss
everything important.
Because what will be overlooked is everything that
opposes popular consensus.
And in our situation with the moderns,
the educational level of the common people,
if we,
how would I put this? If we adulterate
the pool with
the entire scope
of the numbers, we're going to find
and we got to include people who are so old their memory doesn't
work yet. We also have to include children and stuff who have
no formal education speak of or not much
yet. So if we
dilute the numbers with the common
people, what you get is basically just stupidity.
Like bald
inveterate ignorance.
Which you can see very commonly in the United States
in our political situation. You have two species
of catastrophic stupidity, you know,
assembling golems in public to war against each other
for the sake of what? Who has nothing to do with running a country,
I'll put it that way. It has a lot to do with lining pockets
and
sustaining lineages of socio-political
economic war, prison,
you know, power, back room power
exchanges.
The currying of favor and favor trading
and so on, which is the opposite of what a democracy
should be about.
In any case, one of the things that was bothering me is that
both Neil and Danny
with all due respect, Danny is
catastrophically naive about anything relating
to spirituality. I'm pretty sure
he's an atheist and
it's, you know, Danny asks
Neil if he's religious and he just says anything but.
So Neil is also
hopefully my wind buffer is going to work here. I did test it a bit.
what? I'm not going to say he's an atheist.
As far as I can tell, he's anti-metaphysical.
He doesn't believe there's anything like souls or spirits or gods
or diamonds or angels or anything.
And, you know, I'm reminded
of experts on fishing
who've never held a rod.
And this analogy turns out to be really important here in all kinds of ways.
They've never seen a fish. They live in the
desert. They don't believe in fishes. Fishes are a
story that crazy people tell.
And the crazy people are so insane
that these desert dwellers, and these aren't like the
Bedouins who actually have wisdom and stuff. These are idiots.
These are people who live in a world of their own suppositions.
No experience of the things that they speak of. This is what I was talking about in my
recording about knowledge and writing and the problem that
that produces. It also produces amazing
possibilities of learning and the exchange of
the transfer of knowledge on a broader scope than person to person
by song and oral tradition and transfer. That's true.
It does do that, but it comes with very lethal dangers.
Historically the humans tend to ignore the dangers of their new technologies
and then what happens is
the structures of power,
the under structure,
the sort of malignant under structures
of power and wealth
and rape and torture and lying and
not the good kind of lying, not the aurea.
No, no, the kind
of lying that leads to the immiseration of
thousands or millions of people over epochs of time, that kind
of lying. This all gets supported by this process.
What we have here are people, I can't really speak much about
Danny Jones, and it's not my intent to insult him
or to be disrespectful
but it's clear just from listening to him
he sounds like an 11 year old kid
knowing absolutely nothing about the topic
and look, he's interviewed a good, I don't know what his numbers are
but a good probably 500 or 1000 people
very deep minds, very rich
in intelligence. Strangely
his own intellect appears
largely immune to these intelligences
and I find it tragic
this is the problem with the claim
of knowledge, these people are talking
I don't care what they believe and they're welcome to believe
whatever they like or disbelieve whatever they like
they're talking about things they have no experience of
just like people in the desert who make up stories and say
there's these people in the west
and they say that you can go to the end of the world and if you go there you will see the great water
that fills the whole horizon, those people are insane
it's not possible for there to be great waters like that
there's no chance of it being true
water as far as you can see to the horizon
all the way around you, those people are doing, those are drunkards
and silly people, they're just making shit up
which is effectively what they're saying
they're saying Neil studies
the origins of religion
and he's an interesting cat
and he has a lot of name based
date based, place based, he's got this sort of
like you see on those detective shows where you, there's a wall
where all of the sort of major players and situations
and the timeline is there and there's a web of red threads
between all the stuff, Neil's mind is a bit like this
which is super cool, I mean for all it's worth
in terms of trying to understand
classicism
what happened in the ancient world, how did, where did we get
did the Masoretic text come before the Greek
Septuagint or vice versa and why and so forth
and
Neil's defending Amin primarily by saying that
his detractors cite
consensus, well the consensus is obviously that
Masoretic text precedes the Greek, but when you look at the actual numbers
at least
from some of the people that Neil has been interviewing, some of whom are
lifelong scholars of these matters, so not trivial
idiots, you know, who, these aren't political theorists
who, I think, you know, nope, it's nothing like that
these are people who have spent their entire lifetime studying
in the archives and in universities and all around the world
some of them are probably even in the Vatican libraries
which must be catastrophically astonishing
um
many of these people think
that we should ask questions
about the texts
and their origins, so he's defending some of what
Amin is saying and also by saying
that the people who are trying, you know, by saying that the people who are trying to
refute Amin are not citing much
they're really just saying well the consensus has long been
particularly if you see on YouTube some ridiculously
titled video, Amin Hillman debunked
well what a load of bullshit that is, there's no debunking of Amin
first of all you can't debunk a human being, let's just be really clear, Amin Hillman exists
so, you know, the text is already
stupidifyingly
pitifully titled, just insane
you can't debunk a human being, Amin Hillman debunked
what are you debunking, you're debunking your own intelligence in language
so what you can debunk is a claim
not a human being, let's be really clear about that
that little 10 minute video, can't recall
don't even care to recall, the name of the guy who
obviously a friend of Dan McClellands who
has his panties in a bunch about Hillman
and I would argue doesn't even understand, has no chance of understanding
what Hillman is doing because what Hillman is doing
isn't history of religion
it's related, it's related
and it has an influence in that domain
but what Hillman is doing is
magical, it's not scholarly
there's features of it that are academic and scholarly, he's drawing on his
education as a classicist and his fascinations
particularly with ancient Greek
Galen, known as others
everywhere there's these machines
even in the park, the gardens
driving machines around, in any case
what Hillman is doing
is initiatory
he's time traveling, it's like he's opening up
a window to a lost world
inside himself, he's opening up this window, this portal
if you will, and he's transporting us back
he's giving us a
there must be a word for this where
where you are in time is flipped around
in exchange for another place in time
that's what Hillman is up to
in his
paramaniacal
dissertations
and the actual origins
of what's in the Bible, particularly the New Testament
but not merely that
and
you know
Hillman's been accused of various kinds of nefarious activities
I don't know
what the verity of those activities might be
basically
he was specifically accused apparently by some
feature of the Catholic church
of summoning demons
opening portals
he's definitely opening portals
he's trying to understand
what the origins of the often absurdly
ridiculous things we believe in modernity
he's trying to understand
the history of these situations
and when he uses the word history
he doesn't mean a record of what happened
he means to inquire of those with actual knowledge
intimate knowledge
the kind of knowledge you have of your lover's mouth when you kiss them
that kind of knowledge
the kind of knowledge you have of a fruit when you eat it
direct, somatic, visceral
spiritual, originary experience
not thinking, not opinions
not ideas
and he doesn't give a flying fuck about consensus
nothing does not care
in fact he will blatantly declare
that this consensus thing
is completely delusional
nothing there at all
he often yells, he will yell out
everything you think
all those thoughts you have, all those ideas, all those stuff you've been taught
all of that nonsense
and then he'll go off camera and you'll hear spanking sounds
at least
now look
nobody has to authorize
Hillman, right? you don't have to bow to him
he's not running around saying worship me, I am the truth and the light
what he's saying is if you want a taste
of the ancient world that's much more like
what was almost certainly going on than what you've been told
we will go together
using the ancient greek as a vehicle of travel
travel in what? travel
in pneumaticon
in the freens
in the strands
the threads, the tributaries
of our own origins, our minds, our consciousness
our awareness, our souls
the spectral body, the soma pneumaticon of the greeks
he will spin that up
and take us far beyond
anything we've ever been exposed to
for those who want to go
it's an opt-in thing
he's not telling the world what to believe or the scholars
but he will openly laugh at them
and, you know, piss in their faces
happily, joyfully, playfully
what they've been trained to think
they're doing the same
kind of thing that they like to accuse him of
they're very selectively picking certain senses
of certain words that match up not with history
not with the consensus of primary sources
which consensus Hillman may well
theorize. No, they are doing the same thing
they're excluding what they don't want to hear
why did Hillman have to exclude all references to recreational drugs from his dissertation
when the use of drugs by the Romans
was probably the primary focus of his PhD dissertation
why was he told to exclude these
because it was said by the gatekeepers
of the institution the Romans would not do this
what? What? The Romans were doing this
of course they were doing this, we do this, every people who have ever lived
have done this
and what is this? We use intoxicants
and sometimes psychedelics and other sedatives
and other things
but if you experience anesthesia in the surgery
this is what he's talking about
so
his detractors are doing the same thing
they're promoting specific
senses of words in Greek
and or Hebrew
and they are ignoring
the senses that don't agree with their pre-existing narratives and biases
many of which are ridiculously
it's the right word, McDonaldized
right? Jack in the Bible
eyesed
so
frankly I think it's weird
when people like Danny
opine on religious topics
or metaphysical topics
I don't know his whole history, I don't pay a lot of attention to him
but if he has any direct experience of metaphysical
the world outside what you are thinking with your representational cognition
which let's face it is 99% of the universe
point 999
basically everything isn't what you like to think
is the truth of reality
that which is, we might call it, all that is
and Danny's over there trying to think his way through that
good luck Dan, you're using the fingernail
of your pinky for something that needs to become
the palm of your hand and replace your representational
cognition for you to understand it
they're literally arguing about people being possessed
and laughing about it, him and Neil, neither of whom apparently believe
in possession which I think is hilarious because
clearly, Amen
it seems very clear to me and I'd love to ask him questions
about this but if Amen himself has not experienced
various kinds of possession particularly by his muse
the
dead girl he talks about when he says he has a cheat
in the sacred
the podcast by quote
speaks, unquote, when he talks about
this dead girl who resurrects the ancients before
him one by one so that he may inquire directly of
them, if he's not experiencing something resembling
possession I'd love to know what it is that he is
experiencing and these two
young men who know nothing of what they're talking about
apparently and by the way, you know, you can disbelieve
something to such a degree that it either kills
you or blinds you, right, in the same way that you can believe something
to such a degree that it kills you or blinds you, you can disbelieve that food is nourishing
and die of intonation, right, you can disbelieve that you need
water, you don't need water, dead, you know
34 days later, if not sooner
you can say, there's no objective evidence for love, that's just something
people made up to amuse themselves, okay, you won't
have any experience of love, there are certain features of being
human and I would argue that many if not most of the features
of being human are like this, where if you
decide that they don't exist, you become incapable
of participating in them, right, and
unless something comes and overwhelms
your
your blatant ignorance
your, it's a word I'm looking for that I can't quite find
unless something comes and just overwhelms
you, right, and takes you over, which by the way is pretty much
and I'm not recommending the use of psychedelic drugs here, but that's what happens when one does
psychedelic drugs, you don't either nothing happens
which is what happened to me the first eight or nine times
I smoked weed, nothing, nothing happened, similarly
my friend Alan Steinfeld when we were talking the other day, he was like, you know the first
time I looked at a television it was just incoherent, I couldn't tell what the hell
that was or what was going on there, and he's right
it's because the form of our cognition
this idea that
the crazy people have
that what your mind reveals to you is what exists
and what it doesn't reveal doesn't exist
that is impossible, there's no chance of that being true, because what
actually happens is that the mind reforges its own
anatomy
in order to reveal or occlude
features of potential, relation, history, future, possibility
and if the mind has never taken on a particular form
before, it doesn't know what to do
with the information, and so it may generate
literally it may just knock you out
I've had direct experience of this with things that other people
think are completely ordinary and happen all the time
your first experience of eating food with your mouth
that wasn't just milk was probably like this
your first experience of standing up was like this
my first experiences of relation
erotic relation with women in my teens
I go like this, that it was like going to another universe
so this idea that you're the arbiter of identity
function, situation, circumstance, and you just declare
what's happening and what's isn't
you can go ahead and play the game of
consciousness that way, Neil, Danny, go ahead, be my guest
you're going to miss out on most of what it means to be human
and from your weird little isolated
castle, or your dungeon of naivete
you're going to make ex-cathedra declarations that you think
other people are just either having us on
or they're good actors, I mean this is what the left hemisphere would say about everything
that it doesn't originate, grip, control
and also anything that would threaten
its supremacy and consciousness, and by the left hemisphere what do I really mean? I don't mean
the left cerebral
hemisphere, what I mean is certain
features that we know
have an intimate relation with that hemisphere from having done experiments
with stroke victims and from having done the water test
where we anesthetize one of the
hemispheres and we ask the person questions and we can talk to them later about their
experiences and so forth, we know that
there are faculties
from which, okay, there are faculties
that representational cognition relies fundamentally upon
and these faculties are tyrannical, you can see them
in actual tyrants, you can see them all spun up in people like
Mr. Trump and other
tyrannical nightmarish folks from history
who probably need not be named here
so there's this aspect
again it's like the fingernail on your pinky or the
tip of your pinky screaming at the rest of the hand
you don't exist, I have never seen a ghost
who such thing as possession, I mean that's the hilarious irony
is these people who say there's no such thing as possession, okay really?
because you are possessed by an array of faculties
that are declaring that and you are unaware of your possession
and think that what you have is
the antithesis or opposite of possession
when there's no chance that's true, no chance
when there's 10 miles thick
you're possessed by a tiny little array of your cognitive faculties
a little tiny island, an archipelago in consciousness
and that archipelago is saying many things that's not from around here
doesn't exist, those other islands have ocean, stuff like that
it's not there, there is no boatman
boats are a fantasy dreaming thing
something very close to me last night was arguing fiercely
that romantic love was just an invention made up by poets
that everyone decided was a good idea afterwards, he's not entirely wrong
but neither is he correct
because the mind can reforge
its anatomy and under some circumstances
that can be
not exactly forced
but very forcefully catalyzed
and so this is really important to understand
if you are a person like Danny or Neil who thinks they know things
about what it means to be human, what's real and what's not real
you don't, you're wrong
you're using the point
of using one book in a library or one
angle of a sphere
to determine what is true real good, veritable, trustworthy
and so forth, you know Alan Steinfeld who I recently did
a beginning interview with
spoke about his first experience with a trans channel
and he said in the interview
you know I met this man
and I thought
okay either A, he is psychotic
B, he's a really really
good actor
or C, and this is the voice of the left hemisphere
incredible doubt and skepticism
maybe, maybe, maybe, maybe, maybe, maybe
he said maybe like 12 times
there's something going on here that I don't understand
and then later Alan was, Alan is a very intelligent
well educated person
and then so
a performance where this
actually I can't remember if it's, I think it's a woman who is the channel
and she channels an ancient warrior
his name is something like
something like this, I can't, it was very, this channel is very famous
one of the first trans channels
he was at a performance
the channel picked him out of the audience, pointed him
very reluctantly, so I said you mean me?
you talking to me? and then the channel said yes, in very elaborate
ancient pre-shakesperean
English, I said yes my beloved you
and Alan had a full
on suddenly, very rapidly, the whole tabloid changed
he said that the theater filled with a kind of
paraphrasing here, like a glowing mist and he rose
kind of out of his body and they embraced and he had this experience
unlike anything he'd ever had before and you know you can argue
whatever you like, ah, hypnosis, blah, blah, blah, I wasn't there, I didn't see
that, ah, it's just hearsay, go ahead, be my guest
you can argue the same thing about the flavor of food
you're not seeing red, that's just blah, blah, blah
make up any noises you like, you can make all the face noises you want
and you can have all of the critical left hemispheric
refutations, be my guest, you're welcome to have them
you're wrong, you're just dead wrong, you're missing
the thing you're using to determine what is real
is only useful in a very, very tiny
scope of human
experience, nature, being
thought, awareness, consciousness, all these
things, very tiny scope, it's very useful if you want to tell
is that pot hot or cold, very useful there
you know, how many coins are in my pocket, very useful there
beyond
this applicable scope, those faculties
are lethal to understanding
they crucify it, they basically just rip out its organs
and spray them on the wall, so if you think
that you know what's going on based on your rationality, you not only
don't know what's going on, you're like a bird that thinks
only this one feather on my wing
or in this case my right wing
because birds are similarly lateralized to us
only this one feather can I trust, which guess what that means
that means that you will never fly
and you're a bird, you're born to be sky born
you're born for the wind to just
lift you up into the atmosphere
into the sunlight, into dance with the clouds
this is what you're born for and you're really focused on this
one feather, you're like, well I've never seen anything incline me to believe
blah, blah, blah, blah, okay
good luck and everybody's, you know, lots of us start out there
the problem is some of us finish there
and I have my own biases and perspectives
I too can, I've experienced delusion
I've also experienced manic insight
mantic insight
paranoia, grandiose, yes, yes, I've had these experiences
and of course we want to be protected
from them, we don't want to
we don't want our buffers so permeable
that anything gets in and that's part of why
rationality reigns
supreme is because we're really afraid of the
contagion of madness, okay, I get it, but there's other approaches
that allow us to explore
our nature, our origin, our intelligences
our creativity, our participatory
transcendence
and this is very crucial that we have these experiences
so we need a buffer
against, you know, having the membrane
completely ruined
by nonsense, which is conceivable
but we still need a
trustworthy and worthy array of incitements
maps, teachers
mentors, and perhaps daimons
to lead us
out of the prison-eering cage
of mere rationality
that's it for now, more soon, thank you for joining me
may your paths be beautiful and your relationships
loving and your dreams amazing
bye bye for now