I'm going to say hello and a warm welcome to the free monthly online holistic science
talks.
Again, they're organised by Schumacher College in collaboration with the Field Centre.
I'm Simon Rieks, having asked you where you're from, I'm in Nalsworth at the Ruskinmore Trust.
I'm the publishing manager for Ruskinmore Trust and a researcher at the Field Centre.
This month we are delighted to be welcoming Matt Sagal, and Matt will be presenting on
Alfred North Whitehead's Philosophy of the Organism, sorry, Philosophy of Organism.
I'm going to give a brief introduction to Matt, who is a process philosopher and he
teaches on process relational thought and German idealism for the Philosophy, Cosmology
and Consciousness programme at the California Institute of Integral Studies in San Francisco.
Matt's going to present on Whitehead, who's best known for his process philosophy, as
a broad number of applications, and you can find this, for example, in ecology, theology,
education, physics, economics and other such areas.
So before I hand over to Matt, there is a Q&A box that you'll find on the bottom of
your screen, and then if you put your questions or your comments, I will then shape those
into a discussion with Matt for you at the end of his presentation.
Please try not to put them in the chat box, try and put them in the Q&A.
Okay, Matt, a very, very warm welcome to you, we're delighted to have you with us.
Thanks so much, Simon.
Great to be here on planet Earth somewhere, you all are, and I'm here in California.
It's a delight to be able to join Schumacher College, to meet Simon this morning, to see
Troy and Judith here, and I've been really enjoying the opportunity to teach a bit for
Schumacher.
I've talked twice now in the past, once in person at Dardington Hall, back in 2018, of
course on Whitehead, and then earlier this year online in Pandemic Mode, of course on
Whitehead and Gerta, and I'm doing that again later this summer.
And it's a real delight, both to work with master students at Schumacher College and
also short course participants.
I've found in teaching Whitehead that there's such a diversity of people with a diversity
of backgrounds that are interested in his work.
As Simon was mentioning, he's sort of touched on a whole variety of different disciplines.
He's not just a philosopher, or at least his philosophy is not just relevant to other
philosophers, it's also meant to be an aid to our everyday lives and part of an effort
to allow us to reconnect to a universe that, you know, in the last few hundred years has
really grown in size, in magnitude, compared to what pre-modern people were used to.
And so we're in quite a novel situation, and Whitehead's philosophy of organism is
an attempt to make us or allow us to feel more at home here.
So I'm going to try to go into, go until the top of the hour here and run through first
a brief sort of biographical introduction to Whitehead, who he was, the trajectory of
his career.
I think that helps make sense, it helps us make sense of how it is he managed to touch
on so many aspects of, you know, contemporary human life here on planet Earth.
And then I want to just step back and ask the question, you know, why would we even care?
Why do we do philosophy?
Why do we do metaphysics?
Why is it relevant to our lives?
And then I want to spend the remaining time going into detail, introducing you to some
of Whitehead's philosophical concepts and to try to paint the picture of a world in
process.
He's a process philosopher, right?
And so I'll introduce you to some of his categories, his concepts, his new words, neologisms.
And after that, you'll probably be full of questions.
So all right, let me share my screen here and thumbs up, Troy or Simon, if that's good.
Okay, great.
So there he is.
Whitehead was born in Ramsgate, England in 1861.
And by the time he, in his late teens, you know, he's already showing a lot of promise
in mathematics and he makes his way to Cambridge University, King's College, and Trinity, excuse
me, not King's College, and studies math there.
He studies with James Clerk Maxwell's student.
So Maxwell, of course, invented the or discovered the electromagnetic theory and developed the
maths to understand the propagation of light waves.
And Whitehead wrote his dissertation on the electromagnetic theory.
And so from, you know, his very first academic work and research, he is bridging mathematics
and physics and this connection between the abstract domain of geometry and the concrete
physical world remains of deep interest to him throughout his career, as we'll see.
So in, I think, 1884 or so, 1885, he begins teaching mathematics at Cambridge.
Around 1906, he and Bertrand Russell begin to collaborate.
Actually Russell starts as Whitehead's student, and they, you know, very quickly realized
that, you know, they were peers, to some extent, and that they should be working together
on a project that climaxed in the Principia Mathematica, which was a supposed to be four
volumes and ended up being three volumes, which was an attempt to prove logically that
one plus one, in fact, equals two.
And we might take for granted that this is a simple formula that even, you know, elementary
school children can can solve.
But in fact, as they discovered in the course of writing this book together, there are some
logical paradoxes embedded in this simple formula.
We don't really have a clear definition of what a number is, much less what two numbers
are.
And so Russell and Whitehead did really, you could say, inaugurate the whole discipline
of analytic philosophy by developing a quite impenetrable symbolic language that costs quite
a bit of money for Cambridge to print.
I think they even asked to just to do this, the type setting.
I think they even asked Russell and Whitehead to chip in a little bit of their own funds
to print the first 500 copies.
The book didn't sell very well, but it was nonetheless very influential.
So that was, I think, 1911 through 1914, that these three volumes came out.
There were supposed to be a fourth volume on geometry, which was going to be mostly
Whitehead's contribution.
But the war started and Whitehead and Russell began to have some tension around that.
Russell, of course, would be himself dismissed from Trinity College, Cambridge for his pacifism
and anti-war activism.
Whitehead, I don't know that he was cheering on the war, but his son, Eric, was drafted
and was in the Royal Air Force, and a few years later actually would be shot down over
France, I believe, and died.
And so given that just the difficulty around the loss, not just for Whitehead personally,
but for many of the European nations during the war and Russell's, you know, you could
say brave pacifist stance at that point.
Whitehead and Russell, who were good friends, sort of had a bit of a falling out.
And at that point, there was something else brewing in the international scene of physics
and cosmology.
Albert Einstein, of course, beginning in 1905 and then in 1916, had published his special
and general theories of relativity.
And Whitehead, independently of Einstein, had already been exploring, again, this relationship
between math and the physical world.
Actually also in 1905, Whitehead had published this article that was called Mathematical Conceptions
of the Material World.
And in there, he's exploring different approaches to modeling the physical world mathematically
and he looks at four or five different models and the fourth and fifth models begin to gesture
towards something like a relativistic understanding of bringing space and time into a more intimate
relationship than had either or two been done.
But Einstein was the real genius here in bringing together some work that had already been underway
with physicists like Lorenz and Minkowski and Reiman and others, building on the development
of non-Euclidean geometry to totally shift and transform our understanding of space and
time and gravity and matter and energy.
And so Whitehead was really swept up by this Einsteinian revolution in physics in the first
two decades of the 20th century.
It brought him more and more out of just mathematics and physics and into metaphysics.
So to set the scene here, in 1916, Einstein had made some predictions about how light
would bend around the sun and suggested that during an eclipse, we would be able to take
photographs of the moon blocking the light of the sun and see the stars around the sun
and we could actually measure the parallax, the degree to which the light from the stars
around the sun shifted due to the warping effect of the sun's gravitation.
Newton had also made a prediction that this would occur, but Einstein's prediction was
about, I think, twice as much as Newton's.
And so they could determine whether Einstein's theory of gravity was correct or not by observing
an eclipse.
Actually Einstein's first prediction was off.
He got the math wrong.
And lucky for him, the attempt to prove his theory in 1916, it must have been, was thwarted
because, well actually it was 1914, so he had developed a theory a little bit earlier.
And someone went off to Russia to try to observe an eclipse that was happening then,
but the war started and this scientist was arrested and his equipment was impounded and
he couldn't run the test.
If he had, he would have found that Einstein's prediction was off.
So luckily that didn't occur or Einstein might have been dismissed and wouldn't be the greatest
genius of the 20th century.
Einstein has another chance to redo his math, makes a new prediction.
Sir Arthur Eddington and a team of astronomers from the Royal Society decide in 1919 that
they're going to travel to the West Coast of Africa and to Brazil to have two teams to
observe the eclipse in 1919.
They're able to take some photographic plates.
They barely got enough plates.
It was hot and the mirrors were warping and Eddington was off the coast of Africa on this
island where monkeys were stealing his equipment and so it was not easy to get these photographic
plates of the eclipse, but they managed it and Eddington makes the announcement later
that year in London at the Royal Society, Whitehead is in the audience.
Eddington says, we have confirmed Einstein's predictions, light indeed is warped by the
presence of mass because according to Einstein, space bends, space time is warped, it bends.
That's what many of the newspaper headlines read the next day, there were headlines like
space caught bending and Whitehead reports the theatrical environment in the hall at the Royal
Society when these men and women of science are taking in this new discovery, the universe has
unveiled another aspect of itself, but Whitehead has some issues with this notion of space bending
and over the next several years you would have several occasions to speak with Einstein
at the statesman and philosopher Lord Haldane's home in London.
There was a party that Haldane through invited Einstein.
Einstein gave a couple lectures as well at Cambridge and elsewhere and Whitehead tried to
talk Einstein out of his implicit metaphysics.
He was fine with the physics and with the new geometrical tools that Einstein had developed
with help from other mathematicians, but he was worried about this notion of space bending
because the thing about measurement is that you need a rigid ruler in order for measurement to
be accurate and Whitehead thought that if space was allowed to bend due to the presence of mass
which is sort of contingently spread around the universe we're in a situation where before we
can measure anything accurately we first have to know where all the mass is, but to know where
all the mass is we'd first have to measure it and so you can see how as Whitehead put it we'd
first have to know everything before we can know anything and you know Einstein had a response to
this that because over the the spread of the entire universe masses distributed more or less
evenly we don't have to worry about the warping of space over long distances,
Whitehead was not convinced, he thought that we needed to distinguish between space which was a
matter for geometers, geometry to figure out and physics, you know the mass which was what we're
trying to measure and if we conflate the two we end up with some logical and indeed metaphysical
paradoxes and so this set Whitehead off into metaphysics himself and he developed a whole
philosophy of nature and a cosmology which integrated relativity theory and also the
early some early aspects of quantum theory that were being developed in the 1920s and just as
Whitehead was beginning this work he was invited to when he was 64 I believe he was invited to come
to the United States to the other Cambridge, Cambridge, Massachusetts where he began lecturing
in the philosophy department for Harvard University. Whitehead says in his first course
as a professor at Harvard that it was also it has to count as his first philosophy course
himself, he'd never actually taken a philosophy course and here he was taking up the chair that
William James, a great American philosopher had held until like 1910 and Whitehead continues at
Harvard from 1924 until 1937 when he retires and during this time he publishes a number of books
on process philosophy or his so-called philosophy of organism. Process in reality
was published in 1929, it was actually a series of lectures he gave at the University of Edinburgh
so he went back across the pond to Scotland and gave the Gifford lectures and process in
reality is one of the most difficult books in the history of western philosophy. I don't recommend
that you try to read it by yourself, you may get lost and will never be seen or heard from again
in the thicket of new words and difficult arguments that Whitehead makes in that text, however
if you can find a group of other people who are weird enough to be interested in metaphysics,
studying it together is helpful, you can keep track of each other, you can speak with each other in
this new language that Whitehead develops and I don't mean to scare you off from studying Whitehead's
work, I just think it's important to recognize that he's really developing a new language in this
book and his subsequent texts which are a little bit easier to read, adventures of ideas, modes of
thought, some titles of his later books which take the dense technical and formal language of
process and reality and make it a little bit more digestible, but Whitehead's really trying to
develop a new language that once we learn it, it in fact alters our perception I would say
and we begin to inhabit a world that is no longer sort of the mechanistic common sense that
for the last few hundred years we've been raised to accept where we're in a sort of spatial container
with other solid objects in this container and that time is simply a measure of the change of
the location of these objects in this spatial container and that these objects including
we ourselves, we have no intrinsic relationship to each other, we're all what Whitehead would say,
we're all just externally related in this container of space bumping into each other,
that's the sort of more or less Newtonian picture that Whitehead thinks 20th century physics
completely demolishes and so let's shift them to this question of why philosophy is is even
important and you know why Whitehead was drawn into metaphysics, you know I spoke to this a bit,
it was he was really inspired by the Einsteinian and quantum revolutions in physics to move in
the philosophy but why, well because he felt that these revolutions in physics had demolished the
old mechanistic worldview, the old mechanistic metaphysics that had undergirded science since
its foundation in the 17th century, Whitehead refers to this as scientific materialism and it
was based on the idea, two main ideas which he refers to as the idea of simple location,
that a thing has simple location in space and that its location can be determined independently
of the location of everything else in space and the other idea would be this notion of
nature being fully present at an instant or say a bit of matter being fully present
at an instant so that there's sort of this notion of of matter as just this enduring lump of stuff
or substance would be the technical metaphysical term that just mutely endures indoors in its
motions through space or its endurance through time, it's just there right fully present at an
instant and with simple location. Now after relativity and quantum theories
demolished both of these notions of simple location and nature at an instant,
Whitehead realized that science was now advancing its theoretical understanding
almost floating in free air, floating without a metaphysical foundation and if you try to
understand quantum theory and all the the weirdness that ends up seeming
like a consequence of some of the findings of quantum theory you'll note that there's such a
disconnect between our common sense experience and what quantum theory is telling us like
Schrodinger's cat right in this chamber with a radioactive isotope apparently we can't know
whether the cat is dead or alive but it's worse than that we have to say that the cat is both dead
and alive at the same moment right this totally conflicts with our common sense understanding
and from Whitehead's point of view this is because we don't have we don't have the metaphysical
substructure to undergird our scientific understanding such that what we discover
in the special sciences whether it's in physics and the different aspects of physics or in biology
or in chemistry unless all of these special sciences have a metaphysical substructure
we don't know first of all how they all relate to each other just within science
but we also don't know how science itself relates to our everyday experience to our common sense
experience of being conscious agents in a world of other conscious agents who we think have some
responsibility for their actions who perceive beauty who you know have have purposes and
life goals how do we integrate the findings of contemporary science with the hardcore
presuppositions of our everyday lives Whitehead thought that the 20th century revolutions in
physics and even before that the metaphysics of scientific materialism and mechanism had
sort of left us in a bit of a muddle in a fragmented state because I mean before the
revolutions of the 20th century if you looked at mechanistic science and tried to integrate that
even though mechanistic science was Whitehead admitted a clear set it had a clear set of
principles everything was more or less understood the universe was a clockwork right that doesn't
integrate with our understanding of human life at all this is why you know Descartes an early
modern scientist had his dualism where the mechanistic world could be understood with
perfect precision mathematically but it was set apart from the inner realm of the human soul
right and this was a sort of a compromised position but as science advanced it began
to encroach more and more upon the inner life of the human soul but then in the early 20th century
as as this mechanistic metaphysics is called into question Whitehead seized the opportunity
to develop a more coherent understanding that was not dualistic that didn't separate
human consciousness from the rest of nature but that understood nature not as a collection of
objects blindly colliding with one another in empty space but rather came to understand nature
as a network of events you might say and this network of events is for Whitehead in in a process
of becoming that is inherently tilted towards complexity tilted toward beauty he would say
and when we think of nature as a a network of events
Whitehead thought that an event or an occasion a happening something like you know the the
agitation of energy described in electromagnetic theory that this was easier to bridge you know
the agitations of energy as a as a as a happening as an event is easier to bridge with our understanding
of experience because experience too is a happening it's not just an object in space right it is a
subject to which events are transpiring or for which events are transpiring and so in Whitehead's
universe subjectivity is understood to be pervasive not conscious self-reflective
you know rational consciousness such as human beings some of the time possess
um but a more basic form of experience which is uh simply the the feeling of inheriting a past and
anticipating a future right so every event in the universe for Whitehead is inheriting a past
and anticipating a future even if you think of the wavelength of light you know it's even if it's
highly repetitive in its inheritance of the past just repeating the same energetic pattern over
and over again Whitehead says well why is it repeating that pattern because it's enjoyable
right and so this is a point where many people who are perhaps more wed to the materialist worldview
and want to see human consciousness is something totally different Whitehead's going to give them
pause here and they're going to find this perhaps incredulous incredible but Whitehead found reasons
looking at and we'll go into this looking at the post Einsteinian post quantum study of physics
and looking at biology and evolutionary theory he found that he was justified in moving to
what's called a panpsychist or a pan experiential metaphysics because again his goal was not only
to integrate all of the sciences but to understand how science and human life can be integrated such
that the universe that we actually experience as conscious human beings would have some relationship
to the you know the the particles and the waves and and the galaxies and stars distant stars studied
by by science and so we do philosophy and metaphysics Whitehead would say
in an effort to to understand our place in the universe right and one of the best images
that I could find for describing Whitehead's universe was was this spider web with some
dew drops on it so rather than again a universe imagined as a spatial container with objects
within it I described Whitehead's universe as a network of events and Whitehead refers to events
also as actual occasions and these are actual occasions of experience right and each of these
dew drops you can imagine as an actual occasion of experience and that they exist in this network
or mesh work with one another is to say that just as each of these dew drops reflects all the other
dew drops each actual occasion is mirroring the rest of the universe and so there's a holographic
sense in which within each actual occasion at whatever location it happens to be in the universe
it is in fact containing within itself the entirety of its cosmic environment right and so if you
were to zoom in on any of these dew drops you'd see each of the other do do drops reflected there
and then if you were to zoom in on those dew drops you'd see again the repetition in a fractal
like way of the entire web and so there's this infinite nesting occurring in each of these
actual occasions of experience and in Whitehead's universe we're not just externally related to one
another from moment to moment we are including one another one another's pasts within ourselves
right and so the only problem with this web is that it it presents a sort of static picture
of interconnection Whitehead's understanding of the relationship among these actual occasions
of experience is in process right and so we'd have to imagine a more dynamic image whereby
these dew drops are constantly growing together into one another and then dispersing out again
if we think about this in human terms it's a profoundly Whitehead's is a profoundly relational
understanding of existence whereby you know as you're taking in my image and my words right now
yes it has to be translated into you know electronic pulses in a in a series of
transistors and and microchips and then sent across the planets wherever you are but then
it's produced through your speakers on your computer back into sound and my image is conveyed to you
and Whitehead is saying that the energy that I am expressing is absorbed by you and it actually
becomes part of you and when I get to hear your questions later you will become part of me and
that we're in this constant give and take with one another whereby we are literally making each
other from moment to moment and so it's quite a profound mesh work that challenges not only this
old idea of mechanistic physics that things exist independently of other things but it challenges
our modern sort of political and social sense of individuality at least if we take that to an
extreme if we were to imagine individuals existing on their own private island without
being constituted by their relations to others I mean it becomes quite obvious when we think about
developmental psychology and the maturation of of an infant in relationship to the mother
we can see I think in that dynamic the sense in which we really do belong to one another we really
do require our relationships with one another to be who we are as individuals and that's very
much in the spirit of Whitehead's philosophy so before even the 20th century revolutions in
science there was the first scientific revolution which was shocking enough right it begins with
Copernicus who rediscovered some ancient Pythagorean speculations about the design of the solar system
and you know Copernicus puts forward this hypothesis that actually it's not the earth
that's at the center it's the sun that's at the center and the earth like the other planets
is wandering in space so you know Copernicus throws the earth into motion this was profoundly
unsettling for you know the the medieval world to to take in and in many ways hundreds of years
later we're we're still grappling with the fact that we live on a planet that is in motion through
space and following Copernicus Kepler and Galileo and Newton developed laws of physics that allowed
allowed them to overcome this ancient sense of a division between the earthly and the heavenly
realms right the terrestrial and the celestial domains for Aristotle very different laws applied
in these two domains there was perfect motion above the sphere of the moon perfect circular motion
but below the sphere of the moon from the terrestrial sphere there was only imperfect
motion but Newton with his universal law of gravitation says note the same laws apply
in heaven as as as apply on earth and so modern science
inaugurates this new sense of the unity of the universe in fact and one way of looking at this
is to say that now post scientific revolution the earth is itself brought into heaven
I mean the materialistic way of saying it would be that the heavens were brought down to earth
but I think we can look at it either way and so you know from a contemporary cosmological point
of view Whitehead felt the urgency of providing us with a newfound sense of of where we are
right situating us in these vast expanses of space and time but just to think about our situation
in space this is a map as it were of our local galactic neighborhood with the Milky Way at the
center Andromeda off to the right and down a bit Andromeda is actually hurtling towards us
and we will collide with Andromeda at some point in the next I think
billion or two years it it might not be as catastrophic a collision as as you might
first assume two galaxies colliding there's a lot of space within each galaxy and while
the gravitational effects might distort the perfect spirals of these two galaxies
it's likely that we will survive or the earth will survive and that in fact this
the gravitational effects of this collision will seed new stars right so this whole understanding
of of our situation as a galaxy among other galaxies billions hundreds of billions of other
galaxies in our visible universe it's you know we're talking about a century here where this
has been understood and it's profoundly disorienting right there's been plenty of documentaries that
you know Carl Sagan maybe the first to do it and more recently people like Neil deGrasse Tyson
and others who just depict this this new story of of where we are and it's almost maybe we think
it's normal now we know the words you know to use to describe our situation but have we really taken
it in the magnitudes here are I think actually impossible for us to grasp we don't have the
the biological capacity given the proportion that our senses have evolved you know to allow us to
perceive I don't even I don't really think we have the imagination that is powerful enough
to really make sense of our scientific knowledge and for whitehead this was a problem
because if we don't have uh if we if we're not adequate if our imagination is not adequate to
our knowledge uh he he was worried that the very foundations of civilization would be unstable
because a civilization needs to have some sense of confidence in its purpose and to know our purpose
we have to know our place in the wider universe and so whitehead was very worried right about as
much as he was excited by the advances in science he was worried that there wasn't enough effort
being made to connect his uh this new cosmological story to our everyday human existence and this
is an attempt to depict our situation in time if that galactic map was our situation in space this
is a simulation of what happened hundreds of millions of years after the big bang as the first
clouds of gas condensed and gravitational forces brought them together to form stars
which form the first spiral galaxies
and so from whitehead's point of view right remember as I was describing this in the
with the spider web and the dew drops all of that space all of that time despite the the vast
magnitudes we're talking you know roughly 14 billion years back to the origin of of the visible
universe according to you know inflationary cosmology or big bang cosmology and the you know
hundreds of millions billions hundreds of billions of galaxies that we can observe
whitehead thinks that all of this is unfolded within each moment of our experience that it took
the entire history of the universe to produce each one of us right and you know we know we're
all stardust right and that even it took a second generation star to produce heavy elements through
the process of you know going supernova so that complex chemistry and the emergence of life
would be possible here on planet earth and perhaps on other planets and so whitehead really wants us
to feel the the energies and the magnitudes of this wider cosmic environment as as something
that is present within us as a potential and that is in fact giving us the strength and the power
to to move forward in the world as human beings in a creative way we are an expression of all of
that cosmic organization but how do we bring it down to earth how do we inhabit this planet
how do we make sense of of our situation here you know with grass and trees and clouds and the sky
let's hear from whitehead for the first time he says philosophy has to rescue the facts
as they are from the facts as they appear we view the sky at noon on a fine day it is blue
flooded by the light of the sun the direct fact of observation is the sun as the sole origin of
light and the bare heavens
conceive the myth of adam and eve
in the garden on the first day of human life
they watch the sunset the stars appear and low creation widens to man's view
the excess of light discloses facts and also conceals them
right and so whitehead is here pointing out the way that
there's more to the universe than what at first meets the eye which is why the scientific
process of discovery is so exciting and so with lauren we think we have understood something and
we continue to study it and then there's a deeper layer which reveals itself
from whitehead's point of view this process of discovery is unending
because the universe isn't just a finished object it's not a the big bang is not something
which occurred 14 billion years ago and then finished right it's still banging the universe
is still in the process of creating itself and we as scientific observers are a part of that
creative process and so in a universe of creative process we will never be done
knowing right knowing itself must remain an open-ended process
and whitehead wants to invite us into a new understanding of knowledge right and
this is where his understanding of science and philosophy relates to
education he was an educational reformer who while he was always teaching mathematics and
philosophy he was also involved in administration trying to shape the modern research university
to provide a holistic education for for its students so that students who majored in science
would also also take courses in literature and humanities and vice versa he thought that if
someone were to graduate from university only having studied engineering without any sense of
you know Shakespeare or without any exposure to to to Kant and the history of philosophy that
it really diminishes our outlook on the nature of reality and so for whitehead knowledge is really
important but it's a side issue the important thing is learning right and the process of learning
we do learn in order to come to possess knowledge but in whitehead's view we have to be willing
to not be possessive over our knowledge because it's going to constantly need to be updated
and expanded and so you know we could think of his view of of of science and the scientific
investigation into nature is not an effort to produce knowledge as though the universe were
just some fixed already completed collection of objects out there but science is really about
this ongoing process of learning and that in in many ways it is an end in itself right it's not
that we investigate as a means to arrive at some end where we will then possess the complete
and and final understanding of everything science is the process of learning the process of
discovery is itself the end right and we need to whitehead would say be content to remain in wonder
at this universe and ourselves are placed within this universe to pursue science
as an infinite task right rather than something that could finally be completed
you know whitehead says i often start my talks on whitehead with this quote but i'll give it to
you now that echoing Aristotle he says philosophy begins in wonder but whitehead adds at the end
when philosophic thought has done its best the wonder remains right and so the goal of the
philosopher is not to replace wonder with explanation to explain away wonder right by reference to
whatever mechanism might be favored in a particular era rather the goal of the philosopher and the
scientist is to elucidate and and bring some understanding to our experience of wonder but
that experience will always remain it cannot be explained away right and if science begins to
explain away the wonder for whitehead that's a pretty good indication that it has become dogmatic
and needs to be it needs the critic the critique of a philosopher to remind
to remind it that in fact we inhabit a creative universe
it's one more powerful line from whitehead and then we'll get into some of the details of his
metaphysics you know what i only have like five minutes left so we'll have to i'll give you the
quicker version of whiteheads entire metaphysical scheme so whitehead says in our experience there
is always the dim background from which we derive and to which we return we are not enjoying a limited
doll's house of clear and distinct things secluded from all ambiguity in the darkness beyond
there ever looms the vague mass which is the universe begetting us right and so for whitehead
this vague mass is what he calls creativity right it is this ultimate metaphysical category for him
and everything that we see around us everything that we experience in ourselves is an expression
of this creativity it's this creativity taking the form of temporary products right so creativity
is infinite productivity and then our bodies planets stars these are temporary sort of
achievements of creativity which enjoy themselves as they arise but then perish back into this
creative process but they perish back into the creative process gifting their experience back
to the whole such that the process of the universe is unfolding for whitehead is i would call it
cumulative right there's a memory bank and everything that happens in the universe gets added
to that memory bank so that the next moment to arise has this storehouse of experience to
draw upon to advance the universe one step further right so this is going to be quick
and do not expect to have by the end of this five minutes mastered whitehead's technical jargon here
but i want to use this illustration to introduce you to some of his concepts here this is
these are some daffodils and i'm going to explain the process of concrescence to you
concrescence is whitehead's term for how creativity or infinite productivity becomes
a finite product concrescence is that process whereby the infinite becomes finite but only
for a moment because the finite entity which has concrest immediately perishes back into
this you know dim background from out of which we arise and perish
so if we turn these daffodils on their side we can use them to illustrate illustrate
concrescence which whitehead defines as in terms of this i think almost magical formula
um concrescence is the process whereby the many become one and are increased by one
what does that mean well the many are perished objects in the past environment so the daffodils
here are let's say an actual occasion of experience right and each actual occasion of experience
begins by inheriting perished objects in its past environment
now in addition to the past environment whitehead also had this realm of what he called eternal
objects these are like platonic forms but unlike Plato's forms whitehead didn't privilege this realm
of eternal objects as the preeminent actualities right for Plato the forms were the most real
things that there were and the actual world was a pale imitation whitehead totally inverts that
picture these eternal objects for whitehead become deficient in actuality he says they're
pure potentials but they long for actualization and they're pure potentials so that they provide
the different forms of definiteness that become actual in an actual occasion of experience so
colors shapes sounds they're they're sort of like the adjectives that characterize our experience
so every actual occasion has these two poles to it a physical pole
and a mental pole right and so everything down to um subatomic particles and the most
trivial puff of existence and far off empty space up to um each moment of our conscious human
experience is an actual occasion which has a physical pole and a mental pole though for
very simple occasions like those associated you know with photons or protons or subatomic particles
these occasions are mostly dominated by their physical pole right which is to say that
they're repeating what has occurred in their past without much innovation now an occasion inherits
its past via what whitehead calls a prehension and a prehension is a feeling right prehensions are
the process whereby the past is allowed the objectified past right the perished past is allowed
entry again into the into the present to be felt by this concussing occasion of experience
now eternal objects are not you could say they're prehended they're conceptual prehensions but
whitehead also has a term for this called ingression so these pure potentials ingress into the mental
pole of an occasion to allow this occasion to again characterize what is it what it has inherited
from its past environment now without the ingression of eternal objects to provide
an actual occasion uh with some novelty some alternative ways of characterizing what it
is inheriting from its past then there would only be repetition right in each of these
occasions of experience and so the ingression of eternal objects provides some source of novelty
in the mental pole of an occasion so that it can innovate upon what it is inheriting from
its past but again simpler forms of experience say in the inorganic world they don't ingress much
novelty they mostly repeat the past right it's only more complex living organisms and multicellular
animals like like you know mammals and primates and humans who can ingress um these pure potentials
so as to you know really radically shift um from from what we inherit from the past and
do something totally new almost free we might say um freedom something like freedom seems to become
possible uh in in human beings we don't just have to repeat the past anymore but again the
inorganic world does mostly repeat the prehensions of its past which is why um physics can develop
such reliable um lawful descriptions of what happens in the inorganic world whereas it's very
difficult to um predicts how a human being will behave in a new situation but even us we still
have some degree of habituality right in our behavior but nonetheless we ingress we ingress
these pure potentials and are capable of quite a bit of novelty now this term subjective form is
whitehead's way of talking about the emotional quality that of occasion experiences as it begins
to inherit its past how does it feel about that past right that's the subjective form
and then the subjective aim is how in the process of uh concresing the various prehensions of the
past are led to grow together and and any conflict between them between the feelings of the past
is brought into contrast whitehead says and harmonized like notes in a chord that is struck
and so the subjective aim allows the the many of the past to grow together into a new one
right and achieve satisfaction as this new subject which for whitehead as soon as that
new subjective point of view is achieved it perishes right and becomes a superject
and this superject uh is a subject's way of um of persisting into the future of gifting itself
and the value that it has realized in its process of concrescence to the future so that it becoming
a part of the universe again can be taken up by the next moment of concrescence right so
the last thing I want to say about this is if we think about it um at the level of our own
psychology as human beings this this process of concrescence is meant to apply at multiple levels
right it's the it applies at the simplest level of of a wavelength of light and electromagnetic
propagation uh as it does to our stream of consciousness you know for for we psychologically
psychologically um complex human beings and what it what whitehead is suggesting in in our case is
the reverse of of the Cartesian understanding where Descartes said I think therefore I am right
which implies that there's an already existing subject me who has experiences right and or has
thoughts and these thoughts sort of um they qualify um my substantial self but my substantial
self the subject that I am pre-exists my experiences of objects in the environment
and um sort of persists as the same entity throughout my life whitehead is saying
that actually in each moment of my experience a new subject is emerging and rather than a
pre-existing subject having experience of objects in whitehead's universe the perished objects of
the past are growing together and being concrest into a new subject so a new subject grows out of
the perished objects of the past allowing the past which is finished and perished right to
to move again into the future um through the present and so each present moment of our subjective
experience is the result of the growing together of these objects and so whitehead says he says no
thinker thinks twice right and if if you're familiar with the first process philosopher
Heraclitus he says uh you can't step into the same river twice well whitehead is extending this
principle of process philosophy into our own conscious experience no thinker thinks twice
or we could say no subject experiences twice right because each moment the subject of perspective
that we are is arising out of our environment experiencing and itself as a new perspective
enjoying that perspective and then that perspective perishes and becomes an object for the next
moment to inherit and so in whitehead's view my identity my personality my sense of a flow of
consciousness is actually a whole series of these actual occasions a historical root he says of
these occasions which are in the case of my own consciousness intimately related to one another
in a way that you know my historical root is not as intimately woven together as
with your historical root and so we each have our own sort of flow of consciousness because we each
are composed of a of a distinct chain of actual occasions which are inheriting from one another
and so a human soul in whitehead's view becomes something that needs to be understood as a sort
of pulsing process of coming right rather than a substantial ego as it was as it was in Descartes
view we're more of a process right and we are a process that is constantly enfolding the environment
into us right and so we're not separate from the environment we are the environment
coming to take a subjective perspective upon itself it's a radically different view of who
and what we are from the typical Cartesian perspective so I will I will stop with that
I'm sure you are I'm sure your heads are spinning that's a good thing this is a very novel perspective
on reality and so if you're not confused then you probably didn't hear me but I'm happy to
discuss this with you and answer some of your questions so thanks for your attention
I'll stop sharing my screen here too there we go
so Matt I want to thank you very much for the first of all for the invitation into the confusion
but also for the clarity that you brought I really appreciate your introducing of white heads
biography and then deepening into the philosophy I get a sense of somebody who
wants to develop a language to enable a new seeing of the world but one that is corroborated by
science at the same time and it also gives the human being this this creative knowing
it has creative knowing and the process of becoming back to the human being
yes good so
the next session we're going to come we're going to give over to a discussion
and I've got some questions that have come in from the participants
and this is Jason and he's saying concerning whitehead and Einstein developing mathematical
physics this is to say that math wasn't really meaningfully applied to physics
or to the study of the material world before this point what does it mean more broadly to
have begun to conceive the world abstractly at this time yeah very good question
um no it's not to say that math isn't meaningfully applied to physics
there would be no modern physics if we couldn't meaningfully apply math
and you know whitehead was in in being critical of Einstein wasn't trying to say
that we cannot use mathematics to model the physical world he was simply
trying to suggest that we must be careful not to mistake the model the mathematical model
for the reality and so in the case of Einstein whitehead did not deny the practical utility
of a four-dimensional geometric manifold for making predictions about how bodies masses
move in space. Einstein's equations are very accurate in the predictions that they make
about large masses in space and in fact in space time even his his understanding of the
relativity of space and time has been tested by synchronizing clocks very accurate clocks putting
one of them in an airplane flying around for a while and coming back to look at the to compare
the two clocks the clock that moves in the airplane is slower relative to the clock that
remained on earth we've tested this so the the faster that an object moves apparently the slower
that time passes for it relative to a stationary observer so the consequences of some of Einstein's
equations while they may be difficult for us to grasp and imagine are nonetheless many of them
experimentally proven now but the question still remains given the physical accuracy of
Einstein's mathematical models what's going on metaphysically what is the relationship between
the model and the reality now one of the issues that whitehead has with Einstein is in he would
describe it in terms of what he called the fallacy of misplaced concreteness many people who have
not read whitehead directly have probably seen him cited in other works with with regard to this
fallacy of misplaced concreteness and this is just precisely to mistake the model for the reality
if Einstein's model of spacetime is correct in other words not just correct but if it is in fact
if there is no difference between the model and the reality then that says something about our
our human conscious experience of a flow of time it says that it's an illusion basically
and Einstein repeated this notion you know he famously wrote in a in a letter to one of his
best friends widows that upon the death of his best friend that you know for us believing physicists
the difference between the past the present and the future is nothing but a stubbornly persistent
illusion now for whitehead this is no basis for a purposeful human life to take that point of
view seriously and so whitehead like some other 20th century philosophers disagreed with Einstein
not about the accuracy of of his new model for making predictions but about the metaphysical
interpretation that Einstein was giving it Birxon Henri Birxon the the French philosopher had a
debate with Einstein in 1922 about the nature of time and and Birxon wanted to say hey we can only
do science because we are conscious beings and all the dials and meters and and doing the math it
all presupposes conscious human beings right um a clock can't get itself read without a conscious
human being to to look at it and for Birxon as for whitehead there's a a time a process of unfolding
that is um anterior to or prior to the time that is measured on clocks by physicists
and Einstein did not like this idea he didn't want to cede any territory to the metaphysicians
claiming this um concrete time of becoming as somehow primary but if we don't recognize this
time as primary as concrete then we lose ourselves in the abstractions of the model and we we begin
to denigrate the deliverances of our concrete experience by reference to the model which we
are told is what's real and so whitehead is just saying to Einstein and he's not saying we can't
use the tools of math to understand the physical world he's saying do not forget that we're dealing
with models and that um there's more to the concrete becoming of the universe than any model can capture
so hopefully that helps with that question. Matt thank you that also there was also another
question on Birxon but we've touched on Birxon a little bit um I want to go from the west to the
east we've got two questions around and this is normally this is quite a popular question
around western philosophers this um this this genre of question so and this comes from Jurgen
and also from Dennis what would you say about the connection between whitehead and eastern thought
say Taoism to me it seems almost as if whitehead is dressing Taoism in western language there's
a friendly smiley face after that one I should explain um and then also yeah does whiteheads
philosophy relate to the I'm sorry how does whiteheads philosophy relate to the Hindu-Vedic
cosmological concept of Indra's net or web if that is something you are familiar with.
Yeah um great questions Indra's net is precisely what I was attempting to illustrate
with my spider web with dew drops on it that is certainly an apt metaphor for whitehead's
cosmology with the caveat that we have to throw it into motion and make it more dynamic.
Whitehead's universe is not simply not that it's simple it's not simply though a holographic
universe wherein each part reflects the whole um it's also a creative advance whereby again
remember the definition of concrescence the many become one and are increased by one so the universe
is this um cumulative process that is continually growing the universe is never the same twice
and so when we think about the universe as a whole as all of these occasions of experience
reflecting or mirroring or containing one another there's also new occasions of experience
constantly being birthed which contain the entire past but carry it forward into the next moment
so it's much like Indra's net though with this dynamic tilt toward toward the future toward
toward the as yet unrealized future and you know in terms of the broader connections to
eastern thought uh eastern religion and philosophy whitehead says himself in
process and reality that his metaphysics resembles more um Vedic and and Buddhist forms
of thought than it does um anything in western philosophy uh or in the Judeo-Christian religious
traditions um and so he was quite aware of this he didn't study Taoism or Buddhism in any depth
so far as I know um he did write a book called religion in the making which was published shortly
after process in reality where it's clear he had done some reading in Buddhism he was impressed
enough by the Buddhist tradition to say that it qualifies as what he called one of the rational
religions and he certainly his his notion of of flux and impermanence right has quite a a
similarity to the the Buddhist notion of you know impermanence or emptiness
um the relationship of these dew drops on the web is also something you can describe as a relationship
of dependent co-origination uh which is an important concept uh for certain um Mahayana
Buddhist traditions and in the contemporary worlds um actually whitehead's work is being taken up
um by China uh there are something like 35 graduate programs in China devoted to process
philosophy and and whitehead's thought um two billion people 35 graduate programs so it's you
know a lot of people but still that's a lot of whitehead in China and I think there are several
reasons that the Chinese are so interested in whitehead's thought one is that yeah it fits naturally
with um the the Taoist and Confucian Buddhist traditions there but
my understanding is that uh you know the communist party is a little bit hesitant to
allow in those more ancient traditions and to they want to be modern and whitehead affords them
the opportunity to to be modern with his understanding of science and you know he's coming from the west
um but while still tapping into these these deeper um traditional understandings of
of the the nature of the universe as as Lao Tzu and Shuang Tzu and Confucius um
not that Taoism and Confucianism are the same but there are some similarities there
whitehead's thought allows uh China to in a way get in touch with its own history while also
moving more into the modern world and so his thought is exploding there I think precisely
because of the resonances that that are being remarked upon in these in these questions
Matt thank you uh I want to go in a different direction now and this is what to do with with
panpsychism and possibly consciousness studies and this is from Dennis who's saying Matt in your view
what does it mean to experience and the sub question from that is can particles experience
yeah good question this is a major stumbling block uh for many people who are new to whitehead's
thought though um what's sometimes called panpsychism is actually undergoing a bit of a renaissance
right now um even in analytic philosophy more philosophers of mind are taking this
idea seriously um even in the last five or ten years than ever before um whitehead's not the
first panpsychist obviously um Leibniz uh was a was a panpsychist um Giordano Bruno one of the
early modern scientists was a panpsychist um and so there's a there's a sort of venerable tradition
here it's a sort of um marginalized yes but still um readily uh visible stream in the history of
western thought even Heraclitus processed philosophy yes right um everything is flux
but Heraclitus also referred to everything as he says the universe is an ever-living fire
and so in other words life goes all the way down right life isn't something that just emerges
atop a physical substrate um and so for whitehead he protested against what he called the notion of
vacuous actuality a vacuous actuality would be um some sort of an entity which is imagined to exist
independently of experience whether its own experience or being experienced by someone else
he thinks it's a meaningless notion and the reason panpsychism is becoming
is coming more into the mainstream academic uh philosophical uh arena is because of the
difficulty of this hard problem of consciousness right which is if we do inhabit a physical world
that is not experiential at what point does something like conscious experience
arise or emerge um and and how does it emerge right if if in the physical world you have parts
that just rearrange their relative location to one another um and just mutely persist right as
these substantial bits um how is it that surely through a rearrangement of those inert parts
you could ever get something like an interior experience right or or uh experience of what
it's like to be somebody um it seems like not only a hard problem but an impossible problem
and so panpsychism is an attempt not so much to solve the problem but to to dissolve it and not
to have ever imagined in the first place that there would be a dualism between matter on one hand
and mind on the other and so you know whitehead's taking this track uh in an attempt to understand
how there could be conscious animals like us in this universe what must the universe be like
such that we are possible um is the question that whitehead asks and so he wants to push
experience down all the way to the simplest happenings in nature but remember he's a process
thinker so it's not that atomic bits of matter are or have experience um we don't want to think of
particles as little substances as as um little inert um you know globules of stuff
um remember in whitehead's metaphysics the universe is made not of stuff but of happenings
and so um a particle for whitehead let's say a hydrogen atom it's an enduring entity we can
actually see groups of atoms now under microscope and for whitehead that enduring entity is itself
he would call it a society of happenings it's a or a historical root of happenings that are repeating
the same pattern inheriting the same pattern from moment to moment as this helium or this hydrogen
atom right and so you could say the experience of the hydrogen atom is this rather repetitive
experience of just saying ah I am I am helium I am helium I am helium just over and over and over
again and there is indeed a vibration to these to these particles right and for whitehead the
vibratory signature is itself um an expression of this this process of um arising and perishing
arising inheriting the past and perishing and so we get the sort of um the vibrate the
vibratory pattern of this atom persisting uh through time and so what is experience in this
context well at the simplest level it's just the feeling of inheritance of a past and the
the contrast of the contrast between that feeling of inheritance and an openness to the future
and so if you can just just imagine the the um various form of like tension that might exist in
this present moment that is not closed off from the past and the future but it's held intention
between past and future between inheritance and anticipation and you know for these simpler
forms of of existence it's just a flash right and that that moment the present moment as you move
up the scale of nature and into more complex organisms the present moment can expand a bit
we can in our conscious imaginations as human beings we can we can hold the present moment
keep the tension stretched and taught and consider different possibilities before we
actualize one of them right for hydrogen atom there's no time for considering possibilities
it's just repeat the past repeat the past but always with some little bit of creativity
otherwise hydrogen wouldn't have formed stars stars were something new in the universe
you know 500 000 years after the big bang or thereabouts
hadn't been any stars and then all of a sudden there were stars where did they come from well
it's because these simpler forms of energetic activity aren't just repeating the past they're
also lured by certain possibilities to take on greater complexity and order and deepen their
experience so you know it's it's a difficult imaginative exercise to think of experience in a
way that's generic enough and general enough that it's not conscious reflective human experience
anymore but something yeah vaguer and just more basic but why did things you know if we give it
a try we can't imagine something um simple enough that it could reasonably be applied across every
scale of the universe thank you um we've still got a number of questions to get through but i'm just
gonna i'm gonna um because of the time i just want to balance the scales a little bit um and
take it in a different direction and bring it back to the human being this is um so i think
you talked about the transformation of the subject into this is it the super jacked
great okay um and this is a question from paul and it's rauti and other american pragmatists have
suggested that the contemplation of metaphysics has been a philosophical distraction for 2000 years
partly because we can't know what we know rather the goal of philosophy should be making life better
for all please discuss yeah so richard rauti called himself a pragmatist and i think you know
he he is a version of pragmatist um you know inheriting the thought of
william james and charles sander's purse and john dewey whitehead is also a pragmatist you know as
i mentioned he took up william james's chair of philosophy at harvard um a little more than a decade
after james had died and you know for for whitehead william james was he called james the american
plato um and thought that james put um philosophy and metaphysics on a new basis and what whitehead
found so important about james's philosophy uh was its pragmatic emphasis and so whitehead is
a pragmatist he is a radical empiricist in james's sense of the term um and so given that you might
wonder well why was he doing this abstract metaphysical stuff well you could say that
what whitehead did was take james's psychology um and if if you've read james's 1890 book uh
principles of psychology maybe you haven't read the whole thing it's it's quite thick but any
part of it um you'll see what a brilliant writer james is it's so accessible um and still very
relevant i mean you know neuroscience was just beginning to take baby steps back then but
so much of what james had described is is you know with a few tweaks here and there are still
accurate and whitehead's taking james's psychology and actually this this phrase um drops of experience
whitehead borrows from james's psychology and applies it to cosmology um james had some of
his own speculations and i think we could say he was a panpsychist of sorts but what whitehead
does is take james's psychology and systematizes it into a cosmology and so you know whitehead has
to do some system building um he has to develop all of these categories as part of his new
cosmological scheme because he wanted to make sense of science um and james might have been
somewhat unhappy with the this the systematic element of whitehead's philosophy james was suspicious
of system um he worried that it it would it would grow too abstract and disconnected from everyday
life and you know perhaps one could criticize whitehead on these grounds but whitehead himself
at least his intention uh was to elucidate our everyday experience he even goes so far as to say
right at the beginning of process in reality he says the sole justification for any thought
the sole justification for any theory is the elucidation of experience
and so what's driving whitehead to erect this whole cosmological scheme is he wants to make sense of
the universe that science is describing to us so that it can be understood as congruent with
and consistent with our everyday conscious experience and he thought that um already with
the first scientific revolution in the mechanistic world view that there was an incoherence because
the human soul was put off to one side the rest of nature was described as a machine
and then in the 20th century we couldn't even fit um the disciplines the sub-disciplines of physics
together as part of the same universe right because you know I didn't mention relativity theory
describes um the macroscopic universe as this you know continuous field whereas quantum theory
describes the microscopic universe as discontinuous they don't fit together these two theories they're
describing two very different universes and so that's the first problem whitehead wanted to
solve with his cosmology how can these two theories relativity and quantum theory describe the same
universe but also how can our physical understanding of the universe be related to our human conscious
experience right and how can we preserve um a sense of importance and purpose and value
and freedom and beauty all the things that are part of the human realm of conscious existence
right how can we take all of that seriously as real factors in the universe not just as
nice things that humans can believe in despite the fact that physically we know they're not real
for whitehead if if that's the metaphysics or the cosmology that's guiding our civilization
we're in deep trouble because that's a very fragmented worldview where we're asking people
to find purpose in their lives that they know or they're told to believe is actually
ultimately illusory whitehead didn't think that that was a stable foundation upon which to build
a civilization he thought that uh the scientific picture or scientific understanding of the universe
must in some way support the values that we presuppose as civilized human beings
and so his pragmatism comes through in his effort to justify
human human values in light of our cosmological understanding so how can we fit our scientific
understanding into a cosmological picture that would provide a source of inspiration for us
in our social and cultural and political endeavors rather than being at best irrelevant or at worst
a profound challenge to any sense of purpose that we might attempt to realize so yeah ultimately
I think whitehead is a pragmatist we already didn't like whiteheads metaphysics I think we're already
was especially influenced by Ludwig Wittgenstein in this view where you know whitehead was engaging in
this form of metaphysics that you know is predicated upon the idea that language can
provide us some insight into the nature of reality of the world beyond words
and you know there are some readings of Wittgenstein that suggest that that's
just a a faulty understanding of what language is and what the task of the philosopher is which
is simply to to clarify our sentences and to make sure we know what can and cannot be said
whitehead wasn't satisfied with any sense of boundary um he didn't want to remain silent
about the apparently ineffable he wanted to be able to expand the dictionary as he said
and invent new words to describe realities that we hadn't even conceived of yet or hadn't yet perceived
and in this way he's you know he engages philosophy like a poet and that with new
turns of phrase we can actually enhance our perception so that the world we thought we knew
with the prior language is expanded as we begin to speak about it in a new way.
Matt thank you so much I want to thank you on behalf of all the participants for being
for being so generous with your insights with your erudition and also for fielding such
a broader broad array in the discussion from the questions there and just jumping in.
We've got three invitations and one of them is going to come from you because you're doing an
online course at Schumacher which is Science and the Soul of the World and that is 24th of July
to Saturday 28th of August. Can you say a few words to tempt people in?
Yes so um this is my second go at this course it's Science and the Soul of the World um it's
not just on whitehead it's also on a German um poet and scientist and statesman Gerritter
and what I'm trying to do here in this course is
reveal the ways in which Gerritter as a poet scientist and whitehead as a
mathematician and philosopher though they may seem like quite different
like they have quite different approaches to to understanding the natural world
they are in fact sort of ideal opposites that in brought into polar relationship with one
another can intensify our understanding of the universe and indeed a universe that is
ensouled a universe that has a soul um and that they these figures both whitehead and Gerritter
allow us to engage in science um not as a a method which would disenchant the world but in fact
there's another approach to science which they exemplify uh which allows us to um
to study it in a way that enhances its enchantment that in that allows us to deepen into
the life of the whole of which we are apart and so um I think we have six sessions together
and you know we'll go deeper into whitehead we'll go deeper in Gerritter we'll bring them into
dialogue and um I think it's going to be a lot of fun
Matt thank you and I think Troy has put the the link to the Datington website
into the chat so you guys can get it there if not if you just go to the Datington website
then you can find out all about that okay so two more invitations to join us um the next one
is for the Healistic Science Online um lecture series we'll be back on Thursday the 1st of July
again at 4 p.m. with Stephen Harding um and Stephen is sorry Stefan is one of the founding
members of Schumacher College and he will be presenting on Deep Ecology and the Healing of
the Earth and then there's an invitation to join us in person actually live live human beings
and that's at Schumacher College later in the year October the 1st of the 3rd that is for the
Healistic Science in Dialogue Conference um that's a collaboration between the Field Centre
Schumacher College and the Healistic Science Journal and that conference revisits and builds on
the contributions to Healistic Science made by Henry Bortoft, Margaret Colhoon and Brian Goodwin
so we'll have presentations, research panels and also discussions booking for for the live
for that live conference will happen as of next week so we have confirmed speakers Emma Kidd,
Dr Judith Sassoon, Claudio Stern and also a confirmed keynote is Isis Brook
so um once again thank you very very much to Max Segal um I'm going to say thank you and
depending on where you are where you've been tuning in from around the world all of you lovely
participants on behalf of the team I'd like to wish you a very good day evening or night
wherever you may be and hope to see you soon thanks Simon thanks everyone