So good afternoon everybody. If I can have the first slide. Thank you. So this
session is entitled Insects and Other Organisms and I will be telling
you about viruses. So we've seen this slide before so we know there's an
extraordinary diversity of insects and with all sorts of shapes they
evolved in a long periods of time and we are particularly interested in the
laboratory in the study of the interaction of these insects with
infectious agents and having colonized all terrestrial biotopes of course
insects are exposed to a lot of microbes often the same as we so parasites,
viruses, bacteria and fungi. And the reasons to study their the defense of
insects again infections is mainly free fall so the first reason is that they
are they produce anti bacterial or anti fungal molecules and by studying them we
can maybe use them as a therapeutic agents or at least by studying their
mode of action we can have ideas about new strategies to counter microbial
infections. Of course we share common ancestors and so we've heard this in the
the talks yesterday on the use of insects and Josephila as a model so a
number of genes are conserved and by identifying important genes in Josephila
we can learn things about human genes and the last reason is that a number of
hematophagus insects are vectors for infectious diseases and these insects
are not passive carrier they are themselves infected and so they fight
these infections with their immune system. So in the laboratory we are mainly
interested in viruses and this is another extremely interesting things about
insects is that they are host of a large number of viruses and this is a study
that was published a few years ago by the group of young Zeng Zeng at the
Institute of Disease Control in Beijing where they have sequenced 220 animal
species belonging to nine phila and they have identified 1400 viruses and what
you can see on the slide here is that a lot of these viruses are found in the
atropods and in particular in insects you have a very large number of insects
and if we look at another study that is this time focused on a particular
family of viruses the negative strand are only viruses what you can see is
that you have here it was 70 atropod species that were sequenced and they
identified 112 viruses and you have these viruses here and what you can see
is that insects are actually a reservoir for an extraordinary diversity of
viruses because you see that these viruses are extremely diverse and what
is interesting is that these viruses are at the root of many of the viruses that
infect other organisms including humans so you can see for example here the flu
virus and you can see that it shares a root with insect viruses you have philo
virus here the same or RNA viruses here as well so it is very relevant to
investigate the interaction of insects with these these viruses and now of
course some of these viruses can be transmitted to mammalian hosts and this
is an old slide that from an article that's related the history of the
identification of new viruses and you can see that a number of these viruses
are atropod born viruses transmitted by by insects and as we have seen since
2013 this was pre Zika for example there are certainly a number of other
viruses to to come hence the importance to understand why mosquitoes
transmit viruses and why there are these epidemics some years and then the year
after it's gone and we don't really understand why and so what happens is
that we have the urban cycle here where people get infected and these viruses
sometimes may spill over from a silvetic circle where they are transmitted to
wild animals and so one of the parameters you we've all heard about the
importance of the microbiome in a number of biological functions and one
component of the microbiome is also that the varum the viruses and a lot of
insects actually are both viruses that we've seen in the previous slides so
hence the question could viruses present persistent viruses present in
mosquitoes be involved in the rate of transmission of insects and so with my
colleague and friend Joe Marx we started to look into that a few years ago and so
briefly to isolate viruses so the traditional technique is to filtrate
sample tissue to grow viruses on tissue culture to use electron microscopy and
each of these techniques are not very sensitive prone to bias you may contaminate
the sample when you you work it and so there is a direct method now which is
just to use high throughput sequencing to identify new sequences and this is what
our Chinese colleagues have done in the papers I mentioned in my introduction
and in this case you isolate RNA you make cDNA synthesis and you do high
throughput sequences and then you compare the sequences you have to data
basis to find if you have a vowel sequences so now I just want to make one
introduction to the immune system of insects again vowel infections and this
is a slide that summarizes the defining that we have made in our lab in
Strasbourg but also a lot of other lab in Europe and the US and elsewhere and so
basically there is a major response to our infections is RNA interference in
insect and basically whatever the virus you can find that they can be targeted
by RNA interference and then there are other genes encoding either restriction
factors or signaling pathways receptors that trigger inducible responses and so
first I will tell you about in connection to this viral analysis about
this first response which is an anti-vial RNA so the principle here is that
when you have so here it's the case of a positive strand RNA virus that answers
the cells the genome of the virus is like a messenger RNA it will be
translated and this will produce the vowel polymerase which is an RNA
polymerase RNA dependent and this enzyme will copy will use the plus strand as a
template to make the anti genome the minus strand and then in turn the minus
strand will become the template for the polymerase to make the plus trend and in
this intermediate step of replication you have double-stranded RNA that is
generated and this is recognized by the enzyme Dysotoo which is an RNAs free
enzyme and so Dysotoo will bind to the vowel double-stranded RNA and this RNAs
free will cut it and it will generate 21 nucleotide long small interfering
RNAs or SI RNAs and this duplex will then be loaded on another enzyme named
agotoo with the help of this RNA binding protein called R2D2 and in agotoo one of
the two strands will be cleaved and discarded and the remaining strand will
remain and act as a guide so it will provide the information that will allow
agotoo to recognize the vowel sequences by base pairing so it's an extremely
adaptive system the recognition of foreign double-stranded RNA will generate a
small RNA that will program the nucleus to degrade the vowel RNAs so and to show
you how robust this is you have here the small RNAs that are generated in two
insects so this is a virus that is called vesicular stomatitis virus it's an
arbovirus transmitted to vertebrates mainly cattle by insects and here this
is what we obtained in laboratory in the fly this was work that was done a while
ago in collaboration with Carla Salé at the Pasteur Institute and basically what
you have on the first graph here on the top it's the size of the small RNAs so
basically we sequence the small RNAs and you will see that we have a sharp peak
precisely at 21 which is the size produced by the isotope and the second
graph here you have the abscise here is the vowel genome and in blue and red you
have the number of small RNAs that were sequenced in blue when they matched the
plus strand and in red when they matched the minus strand and so basically what
you can see is that the whole genome is covered and you have the same density on
the plus strand and on the minus strand which is exactly what you expect if this
small RNAs were produced from double-stranded RNA and last year we published
with Joe we repeated the same analysis but this time in one of the vectors the
natural vectors of VSV which is Lutsomia longipalpis and what you can see is
that the picture is very similar with the sharp peak at 21 and then the
homogenous coverage on the two strands of the genome and so the connection
of this to the varum analysis is that this leaves us with a choice if we want
to identify viruses by RNA sequencing we have the choice between looking at
traditional RNA sequencing where you just take long RNAs and you sequence them
or we can make the choose choice to just sequence these small RNAs in other words
what is produced by the immune system at the advantage of doing this is that then
we look really at viruses that are replicating and that were recognized
as replicating and potentially dangerous by the immune system and so with
Joe Marcus we compared with this group in Belo Horizonte in Brazil we compared for
the same samples long RNA sequencing to small RNA sequencing and for most RNAs
as we might expect we get more information by long RNA sequencing than
small RNA sequencing but when it comes to viruses the picture is different and
here you have the size of the vowel contigs that we could assemble from this
sequencing and what you can see is that in these three samples the contigs are
much longer when we do short RNA sequencing compared to long RNA sequencing
and as a result when we try to identify the virus we have a much better
results with the short RNA sequencing so here we have three viruses that were
identified in these samples and here you have the coverage with the long RNA
sec and you can see there are lots of holes it's very incomplete but with the
short RNA sec we basically reconstituted the whole genome showing the promise of
this technique and now I'll show you briefly one application of that and this
is again work conducted against under the directorship of Joe so where we
investigated a small city in Minas Gerais Kachinga and where mosquitoes were
collected and so a total of more than 700 mosquitoes were collected and
32 or 31 of them were sequenced and so basically we identified viruses in these
samples so one of them is a physico and physico and like virus a Bunya virus
that was identified some years ago in Southeast Asia so it is present in
Brazil as well the other one had been identified discovered by Joe and his
team a few years before in the neighborhood of Rio de Janeiro and the
third one was a new virus mosquito Kachinga virus and using this technique
of small RNA sec now this city of Kachinga was not taken by just by chance
it's in a region that is endemic for for dengue and so now we can ask the
question whether the presence of these virus might have an effect on the
transmission of dengue and so far the data that we have is that when you look
at the present the first that the blood of patients that are available so you
find dengue in percentage of the of the patients but we don't find the other
viruses indicating that they are present in the mosquitoes but they are not
transmitted or they do not replicate in humans which fits with the fact that we
cannot replicate them and grow them on mammalian cell lines and when you look
at IDES Egypti so you can see first that the prevalence of these viruses is
quite high and by contrast the presence of dengue is quite low it's the
expected what people report in a few percent of the mosquitoes are infected
by by dengue but what is interesting is that if we look at the association of
dengue with HTV or PCLV we see a correlation and we see a higher
prevalence of dengue in the mosquitoes that contain HTV this is highly
significant or PCLV even though in this case it's less significant suggesting
of course this is only correlation so now we have to prove this in the
laboratory but suggesting that the presence of these virus persistent
viruses is not neutral and can have an impact on the transmission of dengue
and maybe other viruses to humans and so in summary for this first part the
information that we can get about biodiversity through these high
throughput sequencing techniques can help us to understand the dynamics of
vector competence possibly it can help to prevent the outbreaks of novel
viruses because maybe some of the viruses that we identify can become new
threats infecting humans and also when you look at the prevalence of these two
viruses PCLV and HTV this could be one day turned into great vectors for
manipulation of mosquitoes so I will now switch to the second part of the the
talk so I've talked to you now mainly on viruses and how they may affect the
immune system of the host and I want now to say a few words about the
immune defense of mosquitoes against and of insect against viruses and again I
go back to this same slide and so there is the RNA interference and then there
are a number of genes that are induced by infection this is something that we
observed and others observed and a few years ago we decided to investigate one
gene that we call the DDL it doesn't look like anything known and the reason
we were interested in this gene is that as you can see here what you have here is
the expression of this gene in flies infected by different viruses and that
belong to different families and you can see that this gene is induced by four
of the five viruses that are tested here and in particular it's very strongly
induced by SymbiS and VSV here so this is now Josephina and so this was one
reason to be interested in this gene and the other reason was that when we looked
at it it's sequence it didn't look like anything that was clearly not
conserved in humans so for a lot of our grant agencies it's not something that
would be dubbed interesting but when we looked at the sequence we first we were
able to crystallize it and get the structure in collaboration with Anna
Houssel in Marseille so it's a new fall it's a secreted protein circulating
protein and but when we looked in the database so here's the
Drosophila protein we found that it was conserved in the genome of several
viruses and not only that it was conserved in granular viruses so like
Bacutovirus in Ascoviruses and even an entomopox virus so this means that this
did not occur once it's known that gene cell genes can be hijacked by viruses
and here this gene was hijacked but only once at multiple times and not only
that we also identified a related protein in the venoms of some parasitic
wasps which instillate venom together with immunosuppressive substances
substances in the larvae in which they inject their eggs so this told us that
this gene there was probably something interesting induced by virus hijacked by
other viruses and so we decided to study infarction in Drosophila and to cut a
long story short I'll just show you the phenotype of the mutant flies so we
generated null mutant flies for a needle and what we found is that these flies
are short-lived and especially when we infect them by one virus in this they
they die rapidly compared to the to the well type interestingly the next thing
we do in these cases is that we look at the valve titer to be usually we expect
that the flies die because they cannot control the virus and there's a lot of
virus replicating and there was not more virus replicating here than here so
the reason the flies die it's not because they do not control the virus and so
then we looked at the transcriptome of these flies we looked at the genes they
expressed and here we had a very striking picture we had a very strong I will
call it here for sake of simplicity inflammatory response so we had a very
strong induction of antimicrobial genes as if these flies were infected by
bacteria and it's known that these antimicrobial peptides many of them are
cationic at high doses they can be they can have toxic effect and all the more
so here because it's persistent it's not a transient response as you would
have in a normal antimicrobial response but these flies mutants for diddle they
make all the time a huge amount of antimicrobial peptides and so we suspected
that this was the reason why they died and so it was easy to prove it because
there are two signaling pathways that regulate expression of these antimicrobial
peptides and one of them the the signature of the genes that we have was
really coming from one of the pathway which is a pathway discovered by Jules
Hoffmann and Bruno LeMette when it was in the lab that is called the immune
deficiency pathway and so we combined the the mutation of diddle with IKK gamma
which is a one gene of the pathway but we had the same results with IMD and what
you can see is that when we combine the the little mutation with a mutation of
the IMD pathway we have a spectacular recovery of the flies confirming that
indeed there's nothing wrong with diddle not being there diddle is just there to
control the IMD pathway and if you block the IMD pathway the flies recover so the
bottom line is that this told us that diddle was a suppressor of the IMD
pathway and you can learn a lot of things about immunology by looking at
viruses because viruses when a pathway is bothering them very often they find
a way to neutralize it and in particular by acquiring some genes and so
for example it's known that a lot of gene viruses have suppressors of RNAi others
have suppressors of apoptosis, baculovirus in particular inhibition of
translation and so now we describe that several insect viruses have suppressors
of the IMD pathway so the corollary of this is that the IMD pathway must do
something to to viruses and Akira Goto a scientist from the lab looked into that
in detail and he identified a function not for the whole IMD pathway but for
two important genes of the pathway the kinase IKK beta and the NFK-PA-B
transcription factor relish so you can see that when you silence these two
genes there is a strong increase of replication of these speak-on-alike
virus here and so to cut a long story short we identified one gene regulated
by IKK beta which is a molecule called sting and that we could prove that sting
acts upstream of IKK beta in this pathway and this is very interesting because
sting is a very important gene in innate immunity in mammals sting means
stimulator of interferon genes and there are no interference in insects but
yet sting is present and we show that it regulates an induced response and so if
there are no interference what are the antiviral genes that are controlled by
by distinct pathway and Akira and Kyoshi Yogedo who was a postdoc just looked
the undertook a small functional screen for genes regulated by IKK beta and to
find genes that are antiviral and here you have a loss of function screen and
what you can see that we have two genes here at the end when you silence them
there is an increase of our replication just as when you silence the kinase
IKK beta and here it's the opposite it's a gain of function screen so they
overexpress this gene alone and they look if it does something to the virus and
you can see that these two genes also they reduce the virus so one of these two
genes is the factor sting and now I'll finish by mentioning the other genes
this was an unknown gene and so we call it naso which in the Japanese means
enigma and so what is naso this is a protein with a single transmorbent
domain and I call it a Josephila innovation what is the reason this gene
is present in all animals in humans it's called C19 of 12 it has no known
function for the for the moment and the innovation is that in Josephila the gene
has been duplicated and so there are two copies and so one of them we call naso
and the other one that is more closely related to the gene in the other animals
so it's probably the ancestral copy we call father of naso and what is
interesting is that there are a number of species of Josephila for which the
genome has been sequenced and so we can exactly tell when the duplication occurred
and you can see that for example the subgenus Josephila doesn't have the
naso they have the father of naso but they don't have naso whereas the so for
us subgenus have both naso and the father of naso and what is interesting is
that when we over express naso so here it's in stable cell lines so we induce
expression of naso here and here you have the effect on the virus and you can see
that in each of these cell lines each time we induce naso we have a very strong
effect on the the virus we completely nearly completely block the virus but
if we do the same experiments with the father of naso so here we induce the
expression and you can see that we have absolutely no effect so it was a
duplication and a newly acquired function and so I believe that this is
something that the insect field can bring it's a very fundamental question
how do you build an immune system and with this gene now naso now we have a
very good system to ask how a gene became an immune gene using these
fantastic tools of all the Josephila species for which the genome has been
sequenced and what is really interesting so you have here in bold the ones that
we have now in the laboratory and you can see what is interesting so they all
have sting and the father of naso but then some of them have naso but not
others and what is really interesting is that they here you have their
sensitivity to Josephila sea virus these pecanavars that this pass with targets
you can see that the sensitivity varies and you can see that even though some of
them are very closely related but they differ in their sensitivity and what's
also very interesting is that they differ in their ecology and so we can see
how the environment maybe helped to shape the repertoire of immune gene in
these functions and so I will start by this last slide so we have on one hand
this tremendous variety of insect viruses with common roots to the
plague humans and then we have on the other hand this fantastic variety of
insects that is not exploited to the moment and genes like naso which is in
the one two percent of gene that are specific to one insect they can have as
I demonstrated some very strong antiviral effect and so basically the
message is that there is a very important diversity of antiviral genes and
maybe also antiviral probably antibacterial antifinal genes in all these
insects and this would could be a very interesting challenge for future study
to pinpoint what these genes are and how they work and with this I'll stop and I
thank my co-workers who are listed here and as I mentioned this is collaboration
with the group of Joe who now also has a team in Strasbourg thank you for your
attention. Thank you Jean-Luc so we have a couple of minutes for
questions. Hi Jean-Luc very nice talk I wonder if you only found the counterpart
of naso in mosquitoes. So there is a there is a counterpart of naso in mosquito
there is no but there's no sting which is intriguing and so this is one thing
that we would like to know so first in the Jocophila we will focus on the
Jocophila is for that so there are species which have sting but don't have
naso so then the question is is sting antiviral my suspicion is that sting
will be antiviral and then we want to look at what other genes are regulated by
sting and mediate the antiviral effect but in the case of mosquitoes it will be
also interesting to see if naso is regulated by infection or not but this
we don't know. Please use your microphone. Yes I have a question on the
first part of the talk on the HTV it belongs to little virility it does not
replicate in mammalian cells and it has been well it's not infected in human but
it's a group of plant viruses also so I don't know I'm not virologist if they
infect other hosts the the the HTV or the little if there are other little
heredity that do not infect non-plant hosts and my question relates to the
ecology of mosquitoes that are linked to plants because they are nectar feeders
and and eventually they can also feed on other plants etc so they are dealing
with plants. So this is a very good question so what the what the slide was
showing is the the heats you have in the gene bank so one big limitation when
you do metagenomics like that is that in the end you have your sequences and you
blast them against the database and it comes back with homology with the
polymerase and so the fact that the polymers comes from or the envelope or
the capsic protein comes from one virus does not mean that the virus is from
this this family so this is the the first element. The second element is that
you're perfectly right and this is a big limitation also of metagenomics is that
when you find a sequence does it come from maybe some integrated sequence in
the genome does it come from indeed the food that was taken and and so this is
what's interesting with this small RNA sequencing is that we focus on the 21
nucleotide reads which is produced by the immune system so if we detect it it
means that the virus replicates and so indeed there's no doubt that HTV is a
mosquito virus and is replicating and persistent in the mosquito populations
even when they are taken to the lab. Thank you very much Jean-Luc and we have to
move to the next talk and thank you Jean-Luc again.