The
connection between philosophy and the mathematical sciences has always been
very close. Plato had written over the door of his academy the words, let no
one enter here who is ignorant of geometry. It was Aristotle who codified
the basic sciences into the categories and gave them the names that we use to
this day. Some of the greatest philosophers have been themselves great
mathematicians who invented new branches of mathematics. Descartes is an obvious
example and so is Leibniz and Pascal. In fact most of the great philosophers, not
all but most, came to philosophy from mathematics or the sciences and this
tendency has continued into our present century. Bertrand Russell was trained
first as a mathematician. Wittgenstein was trained first as an engineer. The
reason for this persisting connection is I think obvious and that is that the
basic urge which has driven most of the greatest philosophers has been the urge
to deepen our understanding of the world and of its structure and this is also
what creative scientists are doing. For most of the past, too, people thought
that mathematics was the most indubitable knowledge as well as being
utterly precise and clear that human beings possessed. So there have always
been plenty of philosophers examining mathematics to try and find out what was
so special about it and whether this was something that could be applied to the
acquisition of other sorts of knowledge. Ditto with the sciences which were also
thought to yield a very specially safe and certain kind of knowledge. What was
it about science that made its results so reliable? People asked themselves and
could its methods, whatever these were, be used in other fields? These
investigations into the concepts and methods and procedures and models that
are involved in mathematics and in science have come to be known as the
philosophy of mathematics and the philosophy of science and it's with
these that we're going to be concerned in this program. Chiefly with the
philosophy of science, though in fact we have someone taking part who is
expert in both, Professor Hilary Putnam of Harvard University. Professor Putnam,
I'd like to start our discussion from a standpoint which I think a very large
number of our viewers occupy anyway and it's really this. Since the 17th century
I suppose there's been a spectacular decline in religious belief especially
in the West and especially among educated people and for millions the role
that used to be taken in life by a world view based on religion has been
increasingly supplanted by a world view based on science or at least purporting
to be derived from science anyway and this is still enormously powerful in the
whole that it has on people's minds throughout the West. Probably it affects
all of us. So I think I'd like to start this discussion by getting you to pin
down that scientific world outlook which is so influential in the modern world
which will be underlying a lot of what we're going to have to talk about.
Let me dodge the question a little bit by talking not about what scientists
think now but what many scientists thought a hundred years ago or 75 years
ago. Think of doing a crossword puzzle. You might have to change a few things as
you go along but towards the end everything fits and things get added on
one step at a time. That's the way the progress of science looked for 300 years
in 1900 a famous mathematician David Hilbert gave a list of 50 mathematical
problems to a world congress of mathematicians which are still very famous.
It's very interesting that he included one problem which we would not call a
mathematical problem very early in the list I think problem three which was to
put the foundations of physics on a satisfactory basis. Just a small task
and that was for mathematicians. Not for physicists, right. The idea is to tidy it
up. That's right. The idea is Newton, Maxwell, Dalton and so on had all put in
all the parts of the story and now it was just for mathematicians to basically
clean up the logic as it were. I think in a conversation we had a couple of days
ago you described this as a treasure chest view and I like that picture but
here's this big chest that we're just filling up. It's an accumulation and you
don't have to subtract, you don't have to take out. Occasionally you make a little
mistake but basically the idea is or to shift the metaphor like building a
pyramid. You put down the ground floor then the next floor then the next floor
and it just goes up. That's part of it. This view of knowledge is growing by
accumulation. The other part of it is the idea that the special success of the
sciences and obviously what we're impressed by is success. This culture
value of success and science is a successful institution but there's the
idea that science owes its success to using a special method and that comes
partly from the history of science from the fact that Newton for example lived
after bacon and was influenced by bacon and the idea that empirical science has
grown up together with something called inductive logic and this idea that is a
method, the inductive method and that the sciences can be characterized by the
fact that they use this method and use it explicitly and consciously as it were,
not unconsciously as maybe someone who's learning cooking might be using it but
pretty deliberately and explicitly. So I think that these two things, the idea of knowledge
is growing by accumulation and growing by the use of a special method, the
inductive method, are the key elements of the old view. Yes and if I were going to
put the same thing, I suppose slightly differently, I think I'd say this that
for two or three hundred years educated Western man thought of the universe and
everything in it as consisting of matter in motion and that was all there was
whether from the outermost galaxies of the stars into ourselves and our bodies
and the cells of which we're made up and so on and that science was finding out
more and more about this matter and its structure and its motion by a method
which you just characterized as scientific method and the idea was that if we
went on long enough we'd simply, as you said with your crossword puzzle metaphor,
we'd find out everything there was to find out. We could eventually by
scientific methods completely explain and understand the world. Now that has
been abandoned by scientists, hasn't it? Though in fact this hasn't got
through yet to the non-scientists. There are still large numbers of
non-scientists who go on thinking that that's how scientists think but of
course they no longer do that. I mean this has started a breakdown. I think it
started to break down. I think it started to break down with Einstein. If I can
drag in a bit of history of philosophy, screaming by the hair, Kant did
something in philosophy which I think has begun to happen now in science. He
challenged a certain view of truth. Before Kant, no philosopher really doubted
that truth was simply correspondence to reality. I mean they're different words
some philosophers spoke of agreement but the idea is a mirror theory of
knowledge. Today I think, well Kant said it isn't so simple. There's a
contribution of the thinking mind. Sure it isn't made up by the mind. Kant was
no idealist. It is not a fiction. It isn't something we make up but it isn't
just a copy either. What we call truth depends both on what there is on the way
things are and on the contribution of the thinker, the mind. I think that today
scientists have come to a somewhat similar view that since the beginning of
the 20th century the idea that there's a human contribution, a mental
contribution to what we call truth. The theories aren't simply dictated to us by
the facts as it were. I'd like to ask you to unpack that a little because I think
that some of our viewers will find this idea a little puzzling. How can it be?
Some people will ask themselves that what is and is not true can depend not
only on what the facts are but on the human mind. How can that be? Well let me
use an analogy with vision. We tend to think that what we see just depends on
what's out there but the more one studies vision either as a scientist or as a
painter. One discovers that what's called vision involves an enormous amount of
interpretation. The color we see as red is not the same color in terms of
wavelengths at different times of the day. So even in what we think of as our
simplest transaction with the world just looking at it, we are interpreting, you
know. In other words we bring a whole number of things to the world that we're
not directly conscious of usually unless we turn inwards and start examining
them. That's right. I think the world must have looked different in the Middle
Ages to someone who looked up and thought of the stars as up and us at the
bottom for example. Today when we look out into space I think we have a
different experience than somebody with the medieval worldview. And what you're
saying is that the very categories in which we see the world and interpret
our experience and the the ideas within which we organize our observations and
the facts around us and so on are provided by us so that the world as
conceived by science is partly contributed by external facts but also
partly contributed by categories and ways of seeing things which come from
the human observer. That's right. And an example of that in science I'll
oversimplify but it's not basically falsified is this wave particle business.
It's not that there's something an electron which is some half a wave and
half a particle that would be meaningless but that there are many
experiments which can be described two ways. You can either think of the electron
as a wave or you can think of it as a particle and both descriptions are in
some crazy way true and adequate. Alternative ways of describing the same
facts and both descriptions are accurate. That's right. Philosophies have
started talking of equivalent descriptions. There's a term used in
philosophy of science. Now for a couple of hundred years after Newton educated
Western man thought that what Newton had produced was objective fact that he had
discovered laws which governed the workings of the world and the workings
of the universe and this was just objectively true independently of us
that Newton and other scientists had read these facts off of nature by
observing it and looking at it and so on and these statements which made up
science was simply true. Now there came didn't there a period in the development
of science and beginning in the late 19th century when people began to
realise that these statements were not entirely true that this wasn't just a
body of objective fact which had been read off from the world in other words
that science was courageable scientific theories could be wrong and that raises
some very profound questions. I mean if science isn't just an objectively true
description of the way things are what is it and if we don't get it from
observing the world where do we get it from? Well I don't want to say we don't
get it from observing the world at all obviously part of this Kantian image is
that there is a contribution which is not us there's something out there but
that also there's a contribution from us and even Kant by the way thought that
Newtonian science was indubitable that he thought we contributed its
indubitability. The step beyond Kant is the idea that not only is reality
partly mind-dependent but that there are alternatives and that the concepts we
impose on the world may not be the right ones and we may have to change them
that there's an interaction between what we contribute and what we find out.
Now what was it that made people begin to realise that this basic
conception of science as objective truth was wrong that science was
courageable, that science was fammable? I think it's that the older science turned
out to be wrong where no one expected it to be wrong not in detail but in the big
picture. It's not that we find out that say the Sun isn't 93 million miles from
the earth but only 20 million miles from the earth that's not going to happen.
I mean sometimes it makes blunders even about things like that but that's like
making a blunder about whether there's a chair in the room, wholesale
skepticism about whether numerical values are right in science would be as
unjustified as wholesale skepticism about anything but where the newer theories
don't agree with Newton it's not over the approximate truths of the
mathematical expressions in Newton's theory those are still perfectly good
for calculation. It's over the big picture we've replaced the picture of an
absolute space and an absolute time by the picture of a four-dimensional space
time we replaced the picture of a Euclidean world by a picture of a
world which obeys a geometry Euclid never dreamed of we've replaced we've
swung back to the picture of the world as having a beginning in time which is
really a shocker it's not even the things once refuted stay refuted forever.
Yes so it means really that a whole conception of science has been superseded
instead of thinking of science as a body of knowledge which is being added to all
the time by further scientific work that whole conception of science has been
dispensed with really hasn't it and we now think of it as a set of theories
which are themselves constantly being replaced by better theories by more
accurate theories by richer more explanatory theories and even the
theories we now have like those of Einstein and his successors will
probably be replaced in the course of time by other better theories by
scientists yet unknown isn't that so? That's exactly right in fact scientists
themselves make this prediction that is that the the main theories of the 20th
century relativity and quantum mechanics will give way to some other theory
which will interpret both of them and so on forever. Now this raises a very
fundamental question namely the question what is truth I mean when we say that
this or that scientific statement is true or this or that scientific theory is
true what in these newly understood circumstances of ours can we mean by
truth? There are still two views as there have been since Kant one is this
old correspondence view still has its adherence but I think the view that's
coming in more and more is that one cannot make it a total separation between
what's true and what our standards of assertibility are that the way in which
the what I called using the Kantian picture the mind dependence of truth
comes in is the fact that what's true and what's false is in part a function of
what our standards of truth and falsity are and that depends on our interests
and which again change over time of course. That's right. I'd like you to
say a little more about this question of truth because this again I think is
puzzling to the layman I think that people who are not trained in science
or philosophy are apt to think that there are a certain set of facts and a true
statement is a statement that accurately describes those facts I'd like you to
talk a little about some of the difficulties that are actually involved
in this. I think the the biggest difficulty in science itself comes from
the fact that even within one scientific theory you often find different
accounts can be given of so-called facts this came in with the special theory
of relativity when it turned in turned out that facts about simultaneity
when the two things happen at the same time could be described differently by
different observers one could say Boy Scout A fired a starter's pistol before
Boy Scout B the other could say no Boy Scout B fired a starter's pistol before
Boy Scout A and if the distance is sufficiently large so that a light
signal can't travel from one to the other without exceeding the speed of light
then it may be both descriptions are correct both are admissible. Of course
this leads to I mean profound conceptual difficulties in understanding some
modern scientific theories and this prompts the thought that a scientific
theory can be useful and meaningful and can work even if nobody really quite
understands what it means this is the case with quantum mechanics isn't it
I mean nobody is really sure what quantum mechanics actually means and yet it
works. That's right and again there I want to say one shouldn't push that too
far because I think we don't want to give up our standards of intelligibility
altogether we want to say quantum mechanics works and the very fact that
it works means that there's something fundamentally right about it and with
respect to its intelligibility we're willing to say in part that may be that
we have the wrong standards of intelligibility that we have to change
our intuitions but in part there are real paradoxes in the theory and I think
that more work has to be done to really get a satisfactory resolution of these
paradoxes. Things are very ticklish now. Yes I think somebody hearing our
discussion and to whom perhaps some of these ideas are new might find himself
thinking well if all this is so how is it that science works if traditional
scientific theories are breaking down if science is turning out not to be a body
of reliable permanent firm objective knowledge if a significant proportion of
every scientific theory is subjective anyway in the sense that it's
contributed by the human mind by the observer by the scientist how is it in
these circumstances that we can actually build bridges fly airplanes make rockets
go to the moon and actually make all this soft fuzzy changing partly
subjective body of theory work for us it must fit the world in some very basic
way in spite of everything that we've been saying. That's true but I think the
contrast between being subjective and fitting the world isn't altogether
right. I'm not saying that scientific knowledge is subjective or that anything
goes and say when the difficult position that we often are in in life of
thinking there is a difference we good and bad reasoning but we don't have a
mechanical rule. In everyday life we use interest loaded terms we wouldn't say
that there's a policeman on the corner if we didn't have a whole network of
social institutions somebody coming from a primitive tribe which didn't have
policemen might say there's a man in blue on the corner but the fact that the
notion of a policeman is shaped by our interest doesn't mean that it can't be
objectively true that there's a policeman on the corner. Also I think
science works precisely because of this corrigibility in large part as Professor
Poppers pointed out the difference between science and previous ways of
trying to find out truth is in large part that scientists are willing to test
their ideas because they don't regard them as infallible in a way that was
known at the beginning and then in the success of Newtonian science somewhat
forgotten and we've had to be reminded again of what Bacon knew that you have
to put questions to nature and be willing to change your ideas if they
don't work. In some respects the traditional opposition between science
and religion has the two parties of cross places haven't they I mean many
religious people now believe they have certain knowledge about the world that
it was created by a god that he made us in his own image gave us immortal souls
which will survive our death and so on certain very fundamental propositions
which they hold with absolute certainty and it's the scientist who believes
that everything is fallible that the world is a mysterious place that we'll
never get to the end of the mystery of and so on and so forth isn't there
something in that? It may be. You say it may be. I'm not sure. Well let's not pursue
that but one point I do want to take up with you leaving even religion aside is
that now that science is seen in this entirely different way that you've been
describing by virtually all scientists doesn't it mean that the difference
between science and non-science isn't what it was always thought of as being in
other words since science is so subjective indefinite changing and so on
it's no longer a clearly cut and different kind of human activity or
kind of human knowledge from other sorts of human knowledge and other sorts of
human activity. I think that's both true and culturally very important. I think
the harm that the old picture of science does is that if there is this realm of
absolute fact that scientists are gradually accumulating then everything
else appears somehow as non-knowledge something to which even words like true
and false can't properly apply. I think that the so-called fact value dichotomy
is a very good example of this. It's hard to have a discussion on politics for
example without someone very quickly saying at least in my country is that a
fact or a value judgment as though it can't be a fact that Hitler was a bad
man for example or a fact that Farrah Fawcett Major is a beautiful woman. And do
you think that it is a fact that Hitler was a bad man? Oh yes I do. I do too. But then if
this is so if we are abandoning so many of these comfortable clear-cut
distinctions of the past what's the point of continuing to use the category or
the notion or the term science anyway? I mean does it any longer clearly demarcate
something differentiable from everything else? I don't think it does. I think that
you know if you're going to distinguish science from non-science that makes a
lot of sense if you still have this old view that there's this inductive method
what makes something science is that it uses it and uses it pretty consciously and
pretty deliberately and that what makes something known science is either it
uses it entirely unconsciously as in learning how to cook you're not
consciously thinking about inductive logic or perhaps does use it at all as
metaphysics was alleged not to use it at all I think unfairly. But once you say
but both say that there's a sharp line between say practical knowledge and
science and to say that the method which is supposed to draw this line is rather
fuzzy something that we can't state exactly and attempts to state it by the
way have been very much a failure still inductive logic cannot be say programmed
on a computer the way deductive logic can be programmed on a computer. I think
the development of deductive logic in the last hundred years and the development
of the computer have really brought home very dramatically just what a different
state we are in with respect to proof in the mathematical sciences which we can
state rigorous canons for and proof in what used to be called the inductive sciences
where we can state general maxims but you really have to use intuition general know how
and so on in applying them. One of the two categories that you described the old
fashioned we're looking at science in terms of was that there was a particular
scientific method if you observed the facts and on the basis of these observed instances
you generalized to form scientific theories which you then verified by experiment and so
that was the old view wasn't it now that that has been abandoned is there any longer any single
method which is thought of as being scientific method. I don't think there should be people
talk of scientific method as a sort of fiction but I think that even in physics where you do get
experiments and tests which pretty much fit the textbooks there's a great deal that does and
then a great deal that shouldn't and I think in fact in the culture I don't really believe
there's an agreement on what's a science so what is it any university will tell you in its catalog
that there are things called social sciences not sociology of the science so that economics is
a science I bet if you ask anyone in the physics department whether sociology is a science you'll
say no and why will he say no that's interesting I think the real reason is not that the sociologists
don't use the inductive method they probably use it more conscientiously poor things than the
physicists do I think it's because they're not as successful so in other words science has become
almost a name for successful pursuit of knowledge that's right yeah yeah well now I think you've
given a very very good description of the way in which this age-old view of what science was has
broken down in our century and been replaced by something much more fluid and perhaps much more
difficult to get hold of but you have I think described it very clearly can we now come against
this background to what philosophers of science are actually doing you are a philosopher of science
what do you and your colleagues do well part of what we do which I won't try to describe on this
broadcast is fairly technical investigation of specific scientific theories we look at quantum
mechanics very closely we look at both to learn what lessons we can for it from it for philosophy
and to see what contributions we can make as philosophers to clarifying its foundations we
look at relativity theory very closely we look at Darwinian evolution very closely and so on
this is the part of philosophy of science that provides the data for the rest but much philosophy
of science is leads shades over into general philosophy and I think it's the best way to
describe it is in terms of what we've been talking about that is each of the issues we've been talking
about divides philosophers of science the issue there are philosophers of science who have a
correspondence view of truth and try to show this can be made precise the answers can the objections
can be overcome you can still view science somehow in the old way and there are others who try to
sketch what another view of truth would come to there are philosophers who still think there is
an inductive method that can be rigorously stated and who work on inductive logic and by the way
I think it's important that there should be because we won't make progress to trying to state the
inductive method if there aren't and that there are others who view the development of science
more culturally more historically and that people like myself who have a sort of in-between
position that there's something to the notion of a scientific method there are clear examples
but that it's more or less a continuum that you you mustn't think of it as a kind of
mechanical rule an algorithm that you can apply to get scientific knowledge so that I'd say each
of these issues the nature of truth the nature of the scientific method whether there's any
necessary truth in science anything conceptual contribution which is permanent and can't be
subject to revision is a big question and who are you plural doing all this work for
I asked that I don't ask that in an irreverent way but what I have in mind is this I've myself
taken part in attempts to bring scientists and philosophers together for discussions of precisely
the issues that you've raised and these attempts have usually failed and failed for the same reason
namely that the scientists lose interest they go back to their laboratories and get on with doing
more science and the great bulk of working scientists it seems to me don't in fact take very
much of an interest in the issues that you've been talking about I think it's conspicuous that
the greatest of all scientists are exceptions I mean they they're really blockbusting the path
breaking scientists who've actually made the revolution in this century that you've been
talking about people like Einstein, Max Planck, Niels Bohr, Max Bohr, Schrödinger, De Broglie,
these people were enormously interested in the conceptual questions that you've raised but these
were the the pioneering geniuses and the great mass of thousands of scientists who follow on
behind them and put their work to its practical application they don't seem to care so who is
listening to you who is reading the stuff that you publish well I'd say first of all I think we
are basically writing for the philosophically interested layman for the reader of philosophy
I don't view philosophy of science as giving direct advice to scientists just as I think
moral philosophers are ill advised to think that they're giving at least immediately
current contemporary advice on how to live your life or what bills to pass in parliament on the
other hand I do think that scientists tend to know the philosophy of science of 50 years ago
and perhaps this is the bad thing that it's perhaps this time lag this culture lag has some
value in weeding out what they shouldn't pay attention to I mean it's a novel philosopher
to encounter a scientist who's both sure that he didn't listen to any philosophy of science
and then who produces verbatim ideas which you can recognize is coming from what was popular in 1928
and is there a direct parallel here between what you're saying about scientists and
Cain the the economist Cain's is famous remark that nearly all businessmen who thought that they
were indifferent to airy-fairy economic theory were in fact the slaves of the economic theorists of
yesterday of a previous generation that's exactly true I suppose another parallel one could make
would be to say that the account that ordinary language users give of language and their use
of language would be extremely unsophisticated simply because they take it for granted and
have never thought about it that too would probably apply to the account that most scientists would
give of what they were doing when they were doing their science that's right that is it's a mistake
to think that merely because when practices an activity one can give a theory of it one criticism
that's often been made about philosophers of science is that although they talk of science in
this general way what they're nearly always referring to in fact is is one science namely physics
now it's true isn't it that the science in which the most exciting developments have probably taken
place in the last 20 years anyway has been not physics but biology our philosophers of science
open genuinely to the criticism of being too physics-based in their view of science and having
ignored biology too much I think I would defend us against that on the grounds that I don't although
the theories in biology are of great scientific importance Darwin's theory of evolution Crick
Watson on DNA and so on they don't by and large pose big methodological problems of a kind that
don't arise in physical science I'm not sure that you're going to agree with that well I mean
you mentioned the word evolution just now and it seems to me that here is a concept
which originated in one of the sciences namely biology and which over a comparatively short
period of time has spread throughout the whole of our culture so that the way almost everybody
thinks is influenced by the notion of evolution not only about the origins of man but about
institutions or the arts all kinds of other things I mean evolution has become a dimension
of western man's thinking about almost anything is that not so that's right and perhaps there has
not been enough attention to this theory though what strikes me as interesting is that the possibility
of explanations of what we think of as the biological kind explanations in terms of function
rather than in terms of the building physics and chemistry what you're made of have come under
more attention recently as a result of computer science now this this is very this does raise
something I'm particularly interested in when you talk of computer science and that is the
interaction between our technology in the case of computers and philosophy not just science and
philosophy but technology and philosophy I mean computers were originally constructed on the
basis of a self-conscious analogy with the human mind weren't they but as they became more and more
sophisticated we began to learn things from them about the human mind so our construction of computers
and what they then tell us about ourselves seems to actually proceed by interactive growth isn't
that so that's right and today the this is one area by the way in which philosophers are in close
contact with scientists that is the fields of linguistics cognitive psychology computer science
philosophy of language today interact constantly people send papers to one another not because
someone tells them to there are conferences at which specialists in these field meet together again
not because someone decided there should be some cross fertilization the interesting thing about
the computer case if I can stick with it for a moment is one might have thought that the computer
the rise of the computer would encourage a certain kind of vulgar materialism the idea so after all
we are machines so after all everything about us can be explained in terms of physics and chemistry
paradoxically the real effect of the computer on psychology and on philosophy of mind has been a
decrease in that kind of reductionism see the thing about the computer is that when you work
with computers you very rarely have to think about their physics and chemistry there's a
distinction that people draw between their software meaning their program their instructions
their rules the way they do things and their hardware and generally you ignore their hardware
you talk about computers at the software level and you wouldn't really be able to explain
what they do in a way that would be of any use to anyone in terms of the hardware level you
there is a kind of emergence here although it's not a mystical kind of emergence it's not that
they're violating the laws of physics it's just that the the level of work at higher level facts
about organization have a kind of autonomy you'd say this the fact that's following this program
explains why it does this and I don't need to know how it's built I only need to know it can be built
in such a way that it will follow this program this is a return to a view and if you apply this to
the mind it suggests a return to a view of the mind that I associate with Aristotle there's the
view that we are not ghosts in a machine not spirits which only temporarily embodies but that
the relation between the mind and the body is a relation of function to what has that function
Aristotle said if you use the word soul in connection with an ax and of course he said you
don't you'd say the soul of an ax is cutting and he said the soul of the eye is seeing and he thought
of man as a thing that thinks you're talking now of the alternative to materialism and
say a religious view that this gives us puts me in mind instantly of the most significant of all
the materialist philosophers in the modern world namely Marxism which after all is the
official state philosophy of about a third of mankind as we sit here discussing this
it Marxism claims to be scientific and this is a very important thing about it
is there a significant Marxist contribution to the philosophy of science I don't think there's
a significant Marxist contribution but I don't think that the Marxists were all wrong either
I think Engels was one of the most scientifically learned men of his century he had a he got a
number of things wrong but he had an immense general scientific knowledge and anti-during his
big book on philosophy of science although it contains some rather strange ideas some of which
he gets from Hegel by the way is on the whole a sensible book on philosophy of science among
other things on the other hand it's not specifically Marxist I'd say that Engels views in philosophy
of science are in large part influenced by the standard philosophy of science of the time they're
fairly sophisticated inductive account and what about subsequent Marxist thinkers who also had
some pretension to be philosophers like Lenin for example well I think they're uneven Lenin I think
is on the whole one of the worst he says for example the theories are copies of motion I mean
there you have the copy theory of science just copying off the reality in its crudest view
Mao is more sophisticated and Mao is very influenced by John Dewey who was widely read in
China in the 1920s do you think it's actually made a contribution to the subject as it is today or
not really I think that it anticipated it perhaps might have made a contribution if
people had been less ideologically divided because I think non-Marxists could have learned the Marxists
were among the first people to try to somehow combine a realist view with the with a stress on
practice with a stress on corrigibility and they were very hostile to the notion of a priori truth
and today many mainline philosophers of science are very hostile to a priori truth as it is they
play somewhat the role in philosophy of science I think that Cain said they play in economics he
described Marx as one of his sort of underground predecessors yes yes when I was introducing
this program I mentioned not only the philosophy of science but also the philosophy of mathematics
and before we close I would like like us to say something about that anyway I suppose one can
really say that the central problem in the philosophy of mathematics is a direct parallel
to the central problem in the philosophy of science namely how does it fit the world with science it's
how does science fit the world in mathematics it's how does mathematics fit the world is that right
that's right and it's even worse because if you're trying to defend a copy view a correspondence
view of truth and empirical science you can answer the question well how do we build up this picture
in such a way that corresponds by saying we have sense organs as I mentioned before that's not a
total answer because there's a tremendous amount of interpretation involved in simple seeing and
simple hearing but if you are talking about numbers and sets and somebody says okay if
mathematical knowledge is simply some kind of a copy of the way numbers are and the way sets are
and the way other abstract objects that mathematician study are the question then what sense enables us
to see how they are because what is a number what yes yes a deeply problematic question but
still an important one that's right and on the other hand I don't want to say that the anti
correspondence view has it very easy either it seems to me that mathematical knowledge is a real
puzzle and I think that philosophers should concentrate more on philosophy of mathematics
than they do now because it seems to be an area where no theory works very well isn't there another
very important parallel between mathematics and science I mean throughout the history of science
one of the conflicts has been between one camp who thought that it was all about objects in the
world which existed independent of human experience and another camp which thought no it's human beings
and observers who actually contribute most of this and as you pointed out much earlier our discussion
the truth is almost certainly a combination of both there is a long-standing dispute in mathematics
isn't there between one body of people who think that mathematical knowledge is something that so
to speak inherent in the structure of the world and we derive it from the world by experience
and observation and another body of mathematical thought that says no no no mathematics is a
creation of the human mind which we then tries to try to impose on reality like a grid as it were
on a landscape isn't that so that's right the latter story is attractive because of the sense
organ problem but it doesn't seem to work either because it it seems that we're not free to impose
any mathematics or any logic we want almost anyone would admit that at least you have to be
consistent and what's consistent what isn't isn't somehow something we can just make up or decide
as when we try to stress conventionalist accounts subjective accounts we come up against the
objectivity of mathematics we try to stress the objectivity of mathematics we come up against
another set of problems I think we can learn a lot more than we now know about human knowledge
and about scientific knowledge by going further into this area talking of of where we're going from
where we are so to speak I think the most interesting way in which you could end this
discussion Professor Putnam would be by talking about what you regard as the most interesting
problem areas of the moment and therefore I take it the most likely growth areas for the
immediate future in both of the subjects we've been discussing philosophy of science and philosophy
of mathematics okay I think that if I'm allowed to confine my prediction of the immediate future
because we know that long-run predictions are always false but in the immediate future I would
expect philosophy of mathematics to be a growth area and philosophy of logic I would expect
philosophy of physics I think to decline somewhat from its central place in philosophy of science
although I think they're part of it touches philosophy of logic the question the astounding
suggestion has actually come forward in connection with quantum mechanics that we may have to change
our logic our view of what the true logical laws are in order to really understand how the world
can be quantum mechanical I think this side of philosophy of quantum mechanics that touches
philosophy of logic will be a hot discussion area but more generally I think areas which we almost
don't think of as philosophy of science that become philosophy of language and philosophy of mind
like these questions about computer models of the mind computer models of language
and these more general questions about theories of truth the nature of truth the nature of
verification how science can be objective even though there's not a rigorous scientific method
that I think these questions will continue to be the staples of the field one thing that worries me
about this whole area is its relationship to the educated layman I mean which in a sense is the
person our discussion has been for after all it's now over 70 years since the 25 year old
Einstein published the theorem of relativity and I'm sure you'll agree with me that it's true
to say now that the great majority of educated people with higher educations university degrees
and so on still have scarcely any idea of what this is all about and it's done very little to
actually influence their view of the world isn't there a danger that now science and mathematics
are simply racing ahead and the whole new range and world of insight that that is giving us into
the universe in which we live simply isn't filtering through to the non-specialist or not
filtering through anything like fast enough that is a danger but it's one that something can be done
about there's now for example a text of special relativity called spacetime physics which is
designed for the first month of the first freshman college physics course and the authors say at the
beginning that they look forward to the time when it will be taught in high schools and do you think
that time will in fact come and quite soon I'm sure of it as well I I think you're right and
indeed I hope you are thank you very much Professor Putnam thank you