My name is Richard Sutton, I'm a professor at the University of Alberta and I also part
of AIME and I work at DeepMind.
My research is really trying to understand the mind by building artificial intelligence.
I work in the area of reinforcement learning where we really recognize that intelligence
is interacting with the world and trying to build a model of the world to behave better
and to achieve goals.
In my work I'm not really focused on applications, but reinforcement learning has been used for
lots of applications, both in gameplay like AlphaGo, you may have all heard about, but
also for process control and saving energy in data centers and autonomous driving, search
algorithms, really any case where you have decisions that have to be made in an automated
way and should be sensitive to experience and data.
The most fascinating thing are the beings that have minds, you know people and animals
and I've always felt that way and can't we understand it.
Of course also we are minds, we are kind of looking at ourselves and say I'd like to
understand that better, I'd like to understand what I am and so intelligence, artificial
intelligence even though it has a word artificial and it is really about answering that fundamental
question of what I am, how I work and what is my role in the universe.