Felly, mae'na gweithio ietenwyd iddyn nhw i'r gwerth yr ysgrif varyain a wrth gwrs yn ywed am fod yn être heat colour diwyd,
a'r cyfle o rhan am restoration golfogau'r cyflymu'n fatholion.
Oed yn rhywbeth i g hyffordi yn ydw i aelod y ffrind pen newydd a'r d refusedg fydda.
Fy mwyn hanes o'r bwysigrol a'r r Republic appears
dyfod o'r halau cymoel COPains a''s yma yw'r wahan i sefyd eich bod yn oed'r bellach amateur
g цветfolaeth yw'r hyfford mewn hanes ho加入i ddim yn ynationalll yn mudparg.
gwael klein.
Champions philosophy
The second part of the book suggests that in the history of the west
three times we have been in a position where to begin with
a civilisation flourished when it kept both these visions together
that of the right hemisphere and that of the left
but in every case and i believe we are repeating the pattern for the third time
as the civilisation overreached itself
Roedd y cyfarudon ni'n mynd f fencesen flem Bosell,
i bobl kotlionaylau a fagroriaeth Shakaelau ac Ardaith
ac yn cyfinsbeth i'r hynny yn y ff traddoriau.
Sef ychydig yn cysylltu atleg i'r ad shameust Letteriff.
Beth wein gweld ffordd yma,
sortedrugg wedi cael y gall estrat,
fel τη cam angen ni.
Maeinin yn cyst觀io'r pryd pan pewper- palaceump,
..y'r mawrddas o'r respect Spicy Love?
Dwi'n schwe вкусgo contrast a dwi'n gych.
Mae'r argyn a gwchai запeth am yr addai?
Yna lliau ddin fy ng blendir iawn cy Yesterday served as a ladd....
..yramyll jucytu allanel ochr yw digud yoedd a gylir dahud hyd oeder y bod ready accident o taw.
Yn gyião cy Ngrysacedl wedi fyndbeth a'r ar coordinate hefyd...
Fa wneud y bydd anghydgiad cegi.
Na uwch allan ni'n blyg yn bwysigai'n adwysgrif후 nhw.
Bydd y bydd yn yictriad, i ni u siblingsio drwy'r grannau cegi
sydd wedi hynny hynny'n cadw?
Nog ni wedi'i ald Strind unexpected opening
o anghydzii amser yn yr oeddakel ei s pä busigoid.
Waid oedd…
ni wnaeth y dwy wych nhw tu.
Rwy'u ricol yn fydde Boris Palmer Llywodraeth
ac y drurwcaid pleain ond rwy'n website gwysig gl doorsol,
ond nid wych yn botwch ei hyt!
Eri hyn mae'r gennych hynfynt i f больше Agwaith yma eich лai boards yma er hynny yn g実io
ac люди ac dweud arall yれ iерь hiss Suz incorrect harmless
roedd yr Ymimsgatu Gwyleon yn b comrades
Rwy'n meddi zen o'r ddechrau fel rhyw yng ngosbryd
Sut o'r llefам eich Parser, Users, rhyw hoffing o fii
Doedd yn y visio'r Llyfrgell yrgaen fobun ahoy
the same thing again. It's very difficult to let go of this mentality that gives you,
I'll have that, I'll take that. And it's a very selfish kind of way of thinking, not
a communitarian way of thinking, it's not a broad picture, it's a very narrow picture,
it sees the short term, not the long term. And it's perfectly successful in its own terms,
but what it doesn't see is it's leading into a blind alley.
One of the criticisms of your work I've seen, and I think you actually addressed it at the
beginning of the RSA animation, that there was a very simplistic understanding of right brain,
left brain in the past, maybe the 60s and 70s. And a lot of people say, well that's been discredited,
the whole idea of these two parts of the brain doing different things has been completely discredited.
Yes, well that was one of the hurdles I had to get over. And probably if I'd had a regular career
where I had to just churn my way through an academic career, bringing out papers every
few months, I'd never have had the leisure and time. Well it wasn't leisure, it was time stolen
from my clinical work. But actually I spent 20 years looking at the literature and there's no
question. I mean it would be absurd to suggest there's no difference. For a start, the most
primitive creatures that we know about going back 700 million years, the very first ones
that have a neural network already have an asymmetrical neural network. And that has simply
become more, if you like, more pronounced as we go up the evolutionary tree. So the two halves
of the brain are just clearly different, they're different sizes, different weights, different
shapes, they have different cell called gyro patterns, that's the convolutions in the surface of the
brain. They have different preponderances of grey and white matter, different preponderances
of neurotransmitters, they react differently to hormones, they're just different. And it's no
good saying there isn't a difference. Also psychologically they're clearly different because
we know that the left hemisphere, for example, is the one that speaks, it's the one that does
certain aspects of language. And the right hemisphere we know has other faculties that I
spend the book explaining. So it's just that people latched onto a very simple minded model and
that model was that of a machine. Now the question you ask of a machine is what does it do?
And if you ask the question what does the left hemisphere do and what does the right hemisphere
do, the answers that came out of pop psychology in the 70s and 80s, the left hemisphere does reason
and language and the right hemisphere does emotion and visual spatial things is not true.
They're both involved in everything, but they're involved in different ways, in reliably different
ways. So it's not the what of the brain, it's the how. And that's a very important question,
but it's not one that scientists are so readily going to ask because they're mainly interested
in mechanism. But actually it's as plain as the nose on your face when you come to look at it,
that there are these vast differences in the disposition of these two neural networks towards
the world. They pay attention in completely different ways and when you pay attention to the world
you see different things in it. And so if they do that they're going to construct two different
versions of the world. We talk a lot on this channel about the meta conversation, the idea that
what we need is a conversation that opens up to the not knowing, to what needs to emerge beyond
and what it feels like is happening now increasingly with social media, is people are getting stuck
more and more in certainty and in what they do know. Is that a right brain, left brain phenomena?
Well it can be looked at in that way in that one of the features of the left hemisphere is that it
prefers what it's already familiar with and it finds it very difficult to shift set. So once
it's stuck into something it keeps on repeating it. Whereas the right hemisphere Rhamachandran,
BS Rhamachandran, well-known neuroscientist, calls it the devil's advocate because it's able to see
other things and it's saying yes but, yes but is a Zen saying that I very much like. So you can
see it that way. The right hemisphere is much more able to be flexible and also very importantly
although or not although but just because the two hemispheres have different takes on the
one they have different takes on their own relationship. So the left hemisphere's take is
an exclusive one either this is right or that is right and therefore what I know excludes what you
know. Whereas the right hemisphere's take is a both and take that there's a room for what the left
hemisphere does. There's a point in analysis but there's also a point in synthesis and imagination
and what we are desperately lacking is that overall synthesis. It seems to me that at the moment
we officially pride ourselves on being a very free thinking people. I'm going to sound like a
terrible funny daddy but I think the intellectual world was far more open in the 60s and 70s when
I grew up than it is today. It's closed down to a number of dogmas and the internet which is a
wonderful thing hasn't helped because it's possible for people to get trapped in bubbles
where they reinforce the things they believe without really hearing other points of view.
I'm a keen proponent that in education one of the most important things one must do
is teach people always to invert everything they believe and see the value in it. In fact
I believe there should be in government a department of inverse policy so whatever the
government is proposing there should be a department that is dedicated to seeing what would happen if
we did the precise opposite and it should be you know centrally funded and I think it would
be a very useful exercise but really it's an intellectual exercise that we all need to do.
If we start being too certain about anything it means we've missed something else. This brings us
to a very important metaphysical point which is that a thing and its opposite according to the
left hemisphere are simply as far apart as they can be and we move always in a linear way to what
we identify as good. Everything I know tells me that in fact opposites are connected and if you pretend
that you are only having one you don't notice the dark side and this is terribly true in psychiatry.
It's almost an attuism to say that a lot of the work one does as a psychiatrist is helping people
to see that there is a good side to what it is that they fear and dislike in themselves but there
is also a dark side to the bits that they pride themselves on and that you cannot get rid of
the dark side you accept it and work with moving it towards something creative and all creativity
and all life is creative our mental world is creative our daily reality is creative partly
by us not out of nowhere but it's grounded in something else but we help creative. That process
depends on opposition it depends on a degree of resistance actually and as soon as you've decided
that X, Y and Z are good and their opposites are bad and we must have more and more and more and more
of the thing we've decided is good you end up reaping a whirlwind because the things you didn't
take note of come back and bite you in the bum and I think that what we are now seeing in the very
destructive and damaging and regrettable moves of you know Brexit and Trump and so on are entirely
understandable reactions which I can perfectly well forgive from people who have just been told
that their opinions are no good because these are things we don't talk about these are things that
you know a liberal person knows that liberty equality and fraternity is all it's about and the
opposites don't matter so I think we're we're enduring now a backlash that we could have avoided
by having a mature conversation yes this is good but also we've got to take into account that
this is what we've talked about quite a lot on the channel and our perspective is that we're seeing
the shadow of liberalism that Trump and Brexit are both the shadow of liberalism I didn't know
that that was what you said but it's exactly what I believe yeah I mean you mentioned a lot of different
psychological things because I mean Jung's idea of the shadow is a perfect one and at some sense it
feels to us that this is the time of the integration of the shadow that what we're seeing
through the democratisation of different forms of media is all the things and the cracks between
things that we thought we'd got rid of are now rising up and are going to have to be dealt with
again have to be integrated yes how do we do that well of course there is no you're not expecting
me to have some simple answer and one of the difficulties is that we have accelerated the
pace of change so fast that the kind of changes that we require not only sort of won't but simply
cannot be made to happen that fast um we're in a crisis which requires something to happen
very quickly really because accelerating technological advance has put machine guns
in the hands of toddlers we have not increased in wisdom in fact I believe we have lost wisdom
in the west and yet we have gained enormously and are gaining very fast in power inevitably if
you put power in the hands of people who have no wisdom this is a formula for disaster and we see
it in the current environmental disaster we're facing we see it in the destruction of species
we see it in the destruction of the lives of indigenous people we see it in the mind control
that is already being put into effect in china with enormously sophisticated ai that tracks the
faces the movements the everything the thoughts of all its citizens and we believe oh well that's
china but that could never happen here but that is very naive democracy our kind of democracy
is fragile it's not the norm it's something very precious and it can easily be destroyed
especially in an atmosphere where we don't know who or what to believe which is becoming more and
more a problem so we have got ourselves into a very difficult situation and i'm not suggesting
there is an easy fix to it but there are things that we could do um to try and get away from this
I mean one they're going to have to involve radical changes we can't expect to go on living
the kind of lives we do with the demands on the world there's just not sustainable they're not
sustainable even for us and now that um 10 times as many people will want to claim these rights to
extraordinary privilege the world simply cannot sustain it so we've been living on on fool's gold
if you like so what are the practical things that can be done if if your diagnosis is correct
and that we're looking at a world that's ever more sort of narrow and rational
how do we get out of that yes easier said than done um and there are patients that you cannot help
which is one of the first things you have to know in my trade um but I believe one of the things I
can do I can't do much but one thing I can do is raise awareness and I think that's happening
so people are becoming much more aware of in a way I've opened people's minds to things they already
knew one of the communist things people say is I had this feeling of sudden recognition that all
my life I kind of felt all this but had no way of articulating it so I think that that is one thing
so of course it's just a start in terms of practical things I mean we've got to begin my completely
rethinking education at the moment it's about shoveling information into people not training
them to think critically to think imaginatively uh I was lucky in that in my education I was taught
to to think of all sides of the question as soon as I believe something passionately I would be
asked to defend the exact opposite position which is a very important exercise that I think no
one should leave school without doing you know this is what you believe speak about it now speak
about and defend the opposite position and we will score you on how well you do that exercise
that is good but it's also about imagination I mean education is drawing out faculties within
people it's not shoveling facts into people that is the reverse of education so I think the emphasis on
you know a cliched caricature would be but it's not unfortunately that far from the truth
you're doing English A level there are six points you must make about Jane Austen you know
to me that is the death of English literature and so is conforming it to current preoccupations
with whatever brilliant we think they are filtering it through isms of you know political
correctness instead of putting all that to the side and simply opening oneself to the incredible gift
of something that somebody created which can work on you in all kinds of ways
that you don't now conceive the more you approach things with preconceptions the worse it is this
this was really interesting watching the documentary you sent over you mentioned identity
politics as a left brain phenomena that it's effectively it's a it's another certainty or it
can become another certainty because what we're doing through that is for example you're taking a
work of literature and you're critiquing it not in the way that it kind of reflects the grandeur of
the human spirit or the developmental journey of the individual it's it's it's about okay how does it
it which immediately diminishes it from that to that yes and can you talk about that and there's
nothing new in it as a left brain as a left brain phenomena i can but i'd also first like to
just gloss your remark because it's interesting i didn't actually mention identity politics anywhere
in the film but what happened you say political correctness or was there some no what happened
was and i didn't know this that in the film as you know roan williams is interviewed and the way
the film was made was i would go and meet somebody we would be filmed talking together and then there
was always a bit where i went out and they just talked to that person because then they were free
to say whatever they wanted to say and a bit that i had never seen until the film was completed
was where roan williams chose for some reason to talk about um the angry black and white views
of people who just know what is right and won't listen to other people and want it legislated
and he just said you you cannot create a better society by legislating this kind of thing we need
to develop a society in which people can have we can listen to one another and have reasonable
conversations and he actually made the point that by trying to stamp out certain things you don't
diminish the anxiety behind it you ramp it up which is exactly what we're seeing which is another
psychological truth of repression yes i mean one of the there are many problems here the one is
the left hand this is far too certain that it knows what's what it's far too clear that things are
unipola that there are just goods whereas you know once you see something that is much clearer
and oriental tradition that everything has comes inevitably with its opposite you don't think
like that anymore it doesn't see things contextually it doesn't see individuals it's not
prepared to listen to another point of view it's just saying this guy i have heard on twitter has
said something you know which is now a sound bite you don't hear all all the rest that went around it
you don't see this as part of somebody's journey that it might be worth listening to you just dismiss
now i believe very strongly once again that it it's not the what it's the how if i've said that
before i'm going to say it again and again in life it is not the what it is the how it's the
disposition you have now i believe it is possible to say anything and i don't think there should be
things that nobody can say i think we should have a system where anyone can say anything but they
must say it in a way that is not inflammatory and that is open to reason and discussion so that
applies to both sides of a political argument and in that same section of the film it made an
interesting point that anger lateralizes to the left brain so that so that if we're in our
sort of left brain certainty anger is the result anger and aggression you know people think the
left hemisphere i mean the old view was when it might be a bit dull but it's terribly reliable
and it's down to earth and it doesn't get emotional well number one it is not down to earth it's
in a fantasy world number two it is not reliable um there's good work coming out of gazaniga's lab
showing you know he was the man who said the right hemisphere has about as much intelligence as a
chimpanzee i mean that was 30 40 years ago but still his lab is now producing wonderful data
showing that the right hemisphere is far more sophisticated at making judgments much more
reliable the left hemisphere tends to jump to conclusions is open to bias and in terms of
emotion the left hemisphere is far from devoid of emotion the most lateralizer of all emotions is
anger and it lateralizes to the left hemisphere lateralizes just means what it means that when
people are experiencing anger there is a great increase in activity in the left hemisphere and
you know the chapter and verse for that it's somebody called harm and jones has done a lot of
research into that but the chapter and verse will be in in the master and is in the master
there was a really interesting example with birds and i don't maybe you want to kind of explain
very simply how because that that for me really illustrates the difference between the two the two
ways of of interacting with the world yes well well the um you know human neurosciences were busy
dismissing it the um animal scientists were simply getting on with what science scientists
are supposed to do which was observing and taking note and they noticed that birds and animals
use their two hemispheres for different purposes it's easy to observe in a bird because in most
birds the input from the right eye goes straight to the left hemisphere and the input from the left
eye goes straight to the right hemisphere it's not true of humans it's more complicated but at least
in birds and quite a lot of animals that have eyes on the side of the head you can tell which
hemisphere is engaged by just looking at which eye is being used for this particular moment
and what they noticed was that birds and animals reliably seem to use their left hemisphere for
latching on to a small detail like i need to pick up that piece of seed on the background of grid
and they use their right hemisphere the left eye for everything else for who others are around
is there a predator um is my mate nearby because i would like to share this all that contextual
information is the right hemisphere and the left hemisphere is literally seeing a tiny piece of
reality now that was in itself an aha moment i could see that this if this was in any way true
about humans it would have colossal implications because i have a background in philosophy and i
know that attention changes the world so if there's a big difference in attention one is
fragmentary piecemeal narrow the other is broad sustained and vigilant they're going to
see two different realities and so that got me into then looking at the human history and lo and
behold this difference is very marked in human beings so if people have a right hemisphere stroke
they can have this pathological narrowing of the window of attention like looking the wrong way
down the telescope and you're the sort of the grand theory as well is that we are in a world that
has concentrated more and more and more on this narrow atomistic mechanical way of looking at the
world and neglecting the more holistic the more um relational aspects well it seems to me and that's
the subject of a book i'm now writing that actually we don't start from things and then have to
work out how they relate and how this thing this billiard ball hits that one and so on but in fact
that there are very broad patterns and flows in the world and that what we call things are the
sort of bits that stand out to our attention their little nexuses if you like that go oh i
recognise that little familiar thing that i'm going to call that a but actually everything is
part of a larger picture and the trouble with focusing on detail is not only do you miss the
overall meaning the overall purpose the overall connection the way in which this has ramifications
the bits that are not explicit the thing that is not in the spotlight which is everything else
but you also think that you can understand the world by taking one thing and putting it
with another and building it up as you'd build a meccano set or you know mend the bike in the
garage but the world is not like that i wrote down from the rsa animation left abstraction power
to manipulate the already known fixed static isolated decontextualised explicit ultimately
lifeless right individual changing evolved interconnected implicit incarnate living
never entirely known and that reminded me very much of what martin buber talked about that we
have the i it relationships of the i thou relationships which i found very profound i
also studied philosophy when i was when i was at university and that that really stuck with me that
there are two different types of relationships we can have in the world one the i thou is essentially
there is an unknown ability about that relationship is that something do you think that maps on
absolutely and there is also a reciprocity in the i thou relationship whereas in the i it relationship
it's a unidirectional one which is about power and influence whereas the other one is about
a reverberative responsive coming into being of something so that is a very important distinction
and i relate the i thou and the i it to the evolution of language we won't have time to because
it's a long story but it's in the book but in brief i believe that language emerged from
what you might call music in other words the music of speech the sounds and that
denotative language is a kind of special set of a much more richly embedded embodied
connotative way of communicating and that it became necessary when we were no longer in groups
where you were largely just talking i to thou but we're talking about a third party or something
else we had designs on and so that is how where language becomes very important i've seen your work
reference in many many different places particularly by people who are talking about the
more spiritual the more even an author called gary lackman i don't know if you're aware of him
so he he's written a series of books about the the hidden occult history of western thought
and he uses your work as a way of saying as a way of kind of maybe giving it scientific
respectability or at least explaining this could be a process that we're going through these
these more holistic ways of knowing have never been part of the western kind of mainstream
traddition and maybe that's because of the right brain left brain split do you do you agree with that
well i think there is not true that they've not been present in the tradition
i know what he's talking about but they're very much present in pre-socratic philosophy
as we know something very important and i think very damaging happened to western philosophy
with Plato and Aristotle and particularly with Plato um but these other aspects in the west
have been more expressed in our extremely powerful music uh one thing you can say about western
civilization it in many ways it's it lacks the wisdom of oriental civilization but it has produced
colossally rich music and so it also produced you know Shakespeare so i would say our art
is where it has been expressed but when we start doing philosophy we're like well we've got to make
this consistent and i see that and it goes in there and this bit leads to that and whereas
you're you're therefore as as i say sort of building things up from little certainties
well the first thing is there are no certainties to start from they're intuitive
you have to start from axioms reason is based on intuition and it ends in intuition
um so i think there are those elements of there but they have been
sidelined and neglected the key thing one must remember about the left hemisphere
is that it's it's bright enough but not very bright it doesn't really see that there are things
that it doesn't know um it's so hermetic its world is so self contained and consistent and
self referential that it doesn't feel the need of anything else because it's not sensing that there's
something bigger the right hemisphere sees what is implicit what is going on not just in the foreground
but in the in the background in the context in all these things that are everything that we really
value love and art and we used to value spiritual truths these things are only approachable in an
indirect implicit way and as soon as you start to say well we need to pin this down and make it
certain you're already on the wrong track so i think that's gary's right to point to that
it's just that i think there's more to the story and you you talked about um that
rationality begins in intuition so well yes it has to i mean in fact it begins in intuition
in two ways one is that um we we can't rationally prove why reason is a helpful tool
we intuit that it is a useful tool but secondly when we begin reasoning we have to begin from
quite a host of assumptions science officially claims to make no assumptions in fact makes
quite a few assumptions before it gets started it has to that's not a criticism the system can't
work without somewhere to start because nothing can be supported on nothing it has to be on something
before it can get started so that's what i mean and it also ends in intuition because the results
of reasoning have to be reintegrated into a broader picture so it's an intermediary tool
reason and indeed the left hemisphere is an intermediary tool one way of thinking of it
is it's like this when you learn a musical instrument you're first attracted to a piece of
music in a broad sort of way then you start trying to play it and you realise you have to go
over and over the fingering in bar 18 and you know there's a return to the dominant at bar 32
or whatever it is but then when you've done all that that's not time wasted but when you come to
perform it if you're still thinking like that you can't perform the relationship with the hemispheres
is a bit like that the immediate grasp of something that the overall take on it is right
hemisphere the left hemisphere then gets to work and does procedural matters but then it's the
right hemisphere that must reintegrate that information that is not lost that process was
valuable but it mustn't stop there in a nutshell i think in our society we stop with the light
left hemisphere we don't allow it to be reintegrated into a much bigger richer picture which is in
touch with all the stuff that the left hemisphere doesn't know it doesn't know this reminds me quite
a lot of richard tarnas who yes who i'm afraid i haven't read yeah no i i he his book had a huge
impact on me when i was when i was at university but but effectively he said that he told the story
of western philosophy and said that it had become more and more isolating more and more a prison of
the intellect and that the way out would be to re-embrace intuition re-embrace direct knowledge
and that we couldn't get out until we did um so it just it seems that it maps on very very clearly
to to the picture that you're you're painting yes um the that's right and the other thing one ought
to say is that philosophy has made strides in the last couple of hundred years and i think that
um there's been a redressing of that particularly in early on in in hegel and in the the german idealist
victor shelling and so forth uh to an extent in nature who's a mad genius um but mainly in the
traddition of two uh two groups one is the american pragmatists uh cspers uh william james
and john jewell and the other is the um phenomenological tradition in europe uh heiligur uh
melaponte sheila hustle to a degree uh so i think and the later vittgenstein would fit with that
the earlier vittgenstein uh not you there was a comment on the rsa video from a physicist
who said that he found it very useful in looking at why they were so far away from coming up with
a theory of everything because his sense was that they're looking at the individual details and
not looking at the whole does that make sense it certainly does and i hadn't seen that um comment
but um well one of the gratifying things has been the number of physicists who have written
to me saying uh there are enormous resonances between your work and what we are doing in physics
i'm um far too unskilled to to recognise those although i have an idea of the shape of what
they're talking about and recently i've been trying to equate myself with quantum field theory
which is actually a very interesting development out of quantum mechanics um and i will try to write a bit
about that in my current book but only after running it by some very kind physicist friends
but i think what is um important is that what i'm saying if it is true will apply to everything
because it's about the nature of reality and the people who are at the cold face of reality
are poets and physicists and you know they have written to me saying uh how how much they feel
a resonance but what has struck me is that people that i didn't expect like lawyers and people in the
world of finance and economists you know are some of my most um frequent correspondents because
they say what you're describing is exactly the problems in our realm so i'm delighted because
i've never had the slightest belief or hope that this could happen but that what i'm saying has
been picked up by people in all walks of life
you