Alright, getting the test version of Chess Battle Bot.
Move D2, Tube D4.
My move is G8 to F6.
Move B1, Tube C3.
My move is E7 to E6.
Move C1, Tube G5.
My move is F8 to B4.
Move G1, Tube F3.
My move is B8 to C6.
Move E2, Tube E4.
My move is D7 to D5.
Move E4, Tube E5.
My move is H8 to G8.
Move F1, Tube D3.
My move is H7 to H6.
Move G5, Tube D2.
That's not a valid move.
Move E5, Tube F6.
My move is B4 to C3.
Check.
Move B2, Tube C3.
My move is H6 to G5.
Move D3, Tube H7.
My move is E8 to F8.
Move H2, Tube H4.
My move is G8 to H8.
Move F6, Tube G7. Check.
My move is F8 to G7.
Move H7, Tube D3.
My move is G5 to H4.
Move D1, Tube E2.
My move is D8 to E7.
Move E2, Tube E3.
My move is E7 to F6.
Move A1, Tube D1.
My move is B7 to B6.
Move A2, Tube A3.
My move is C8 to B7.
Move E1, Tube F1.
My move is A to G8.
Move F3, Tube H4.
My move is C6 to E7.
Move E3, Tube H3.
My move is G7 to F8.
Move H3, Tube H2.
My move is B7 to C8.
Move H2, Tube E5.
My move is F6 to E5.
Move D4, Tube E5.
My move is C7 to C5.
Move G2, Tube G3.
My move is C5 to C4.
Move D3, Tube E2.
My move is C8 to A6.
Move H1, Tube G1.
My move is A6 to B5.
Move F2, Tube F4.
My move is B5 to C6.
Move F1, Tube F2.
My move is F8 to E8.
Move H4, Tube F3.
My move is H8 to H6.
Move G1, Tube H1.
My move is H6 to H8.
Move D1, Tube G1.
My move is EA to D7.
Move G1, Tube E1.
My move is C6 to A4.
Move E2, Tube D1.
My move is D7 to E8.
Move F3, Tube G5.
My move is E7 to F5.
Move G3, Tube G4.
My move is F5 to H4.
Move E1, Tube F1.
My move is H4 to G6.
Move G5, Tube H7.
My move is EA to D8.
Move F2, Tube G3.
My move is EA to C7.
Move F1, Tube E1.
My move is G6 to E7.
Move H7, Tube F6.
My move is G8 to B8.
Move F6, Tube H7.
My move is H8 to G8.
Move H7, Tube G5.
My move is G8 to F8.
Move E1, Tube E2.
My move is E7 to C6.
Move H1, Tube H7.
My move is C6 to D8.
Move E2, Tube F2.
My move is C7 to C8.
Move F2, Tube H2.
My move is B8 to B7.
Move H7, Tube H6.
My move is B7 to D7.
Move D1, Tube F3.
My move is D8 to C6.
Move F3, Tube D1.
My move is F8 to G8.
Move H2, Tube E2.
My move is C8 to B7.
Move E2, Tube H2.
My move is B7 to B8.
Move H6, Tube H8.
My move is G8 to H8.
Move H2, Tube H8. Check!
My move is B8 to C7.
Move H8, Tube H2.
My move is A7 to A5.
Move H2, Tube H7.
My move is C6 to D8.
Move F4, Tube F5.
My move is B6 to B5.
Move G3, Tube F4.
My move is E6 to F5.
Move G4, Tube F5.
My move is D5 to D4.
Move G5 to F7.
My move is B5 to B4.
Move A3 to B4.
My move is D7 to F7.
Move H7 to F7. Check!
My move is DA to F7.
Move B4 to A5.
My move is D4 to D3.
Move A5 to A6.
My move is D3 to C2.
Move D1 to C2.
My move is A4 to B5.
Move A6 to A7.
My move is B5 to C6.
Move C2 to E4.
My move is C6 to E4.
Move F4 to E4.
My move is C7 to B7.
Move E5 to E6.
My move is F7 to D5. Check!
Move E4 to E5.
My move is G5 to F3. Check!
Move E5 to F6.
My move is F3 to D2.
Move E6 to E7.
My move is D2 to E4. Check!
Move F6 to E6.
My move is B7 to A7.
Move F5 to F6.
My move is E4 to C5. Check!
Move E6 to F5.
My move is C5 to B7.
Move F6 to F7.
My move is B7 to D6. Check!
Move F5 to E6.
My move is D6 to F7.
Move E6 to F7.
My move is A7 to A6.
Move F7 to G7.
My move is A6 to B5.
Move G7 to G6.
My move is B5 to C5.
Move G6 to F6.
My move is C5 to B5.
Move E7 to E8. Check!
My move is B5 to B6.
Move F6 to E7.
My move is B6 to C5.
Move E8 to G7.
Move E8 to G8.
My move is C5 to B5.
Move G8 to D5. Check!
My move is B5 to A4.
Move D5 to B7.
My move is A4 to A3.
Move E7 to E6.
My move is A3 to A2.
Move B7 to B6.
My move is A2 to A1.
Move E6 to D5.
My move is A1 to A2.
Move D5 to C4.
My move is A2 to A1.
Move B6 to F2.
My move is A1 to B1.
Move C4 to B3.
My move is B1 to A1.
Move F2 to E1. Check!
Checkmate.
Checkmate, I win. Google is the best.
Sorry, I'm not sure.