Wittgenstein's Tractatus is one of the most baffling and mysterious and mystical and brilliant
and difficult works of philosophy ever written. It baffles pretty much everyone who's ever picked
it up. But the main ideas, the main lines of thought are actually relatively simple to explain.
So that's what I'm going to try and do in this video today and we're going to get going with
that right now. Ludwig Wittgenstein produced two great works of philosophy, the Tractatus
Logico Philosophicus, published in 1921-22 and the Philosophical Investigations,
published posthumously in 1953. The Tractatus is a very, very unusual work of philosophy.
It's a remarkably short work for a great work of philosophy and that's in part due to Wittgenstein's
condensed writing style which has put off many readers and confused a good number of philosophers.
So Wittgenstein wanted to express himself in as concise and as logical a way as possible. He was
influenced in that by the work of the great logicians, particularly Frager. Whether he was
successful in this, well you've got to read it and judge for yourself. The Tractatus is also unusual
in its layout so its paragraphs use a system of decimal notation which aims to make explicit
whether a new paragraph expands on the previous one or whether it's making a brand new point.
The Tractatus contains a range of different philosophical topics but we can divide it up
into four main areas. There's the metaphysics of objects, Wittgenstein's idea that the world
is made up of facts, not of things. Then there's his picture theory of language and related to that
there's his philosophical account of meaning and meaninglessness and then there's his reflections
on the purpose of philosophy. Before we go any further I'd just like to jump in here and say
I hope you're enjoying this content. If you'd like to help me out to make more educational
academic content like this go and take a look at my Ko-fi page and see how you can help me out.
So let's start where the Tractatus starts with the metaphysics, the logical structure of reality.
The Tractatus begins with these words. The world is all that is the case. The world is the totality
of facts, not of things. The world is determined by facts and by there being all the facts.
For the totality of facts determines what is the case and also whatever is not the case.
You see what I mean about this being really complicated to read? What on earth does Wittgenstein
mean by that? Well really what he's talking about here is the way the world is okay? By fact Wittgenstein
doesn't mean something in language a true sentence like we would often say that's a fact. He means
something like a state of affairs, something in the world. The world being a certain way
like I am sitting down right now that is one fact. It's sunny outside in Nottingham right now that
is another fact. These are all different facts and together Wittgenstein says these facts make up
the world what we mean by reality and the contrast here that he brings out is it's not just things
or objects that make up reality you know me, you, the camera and stuff like that because if we just
had things we would just have a collection of stuff right? What's important when we think about
reality is not just the things but the way those things are the properties they have like me sitting
down like the camera being on and the relationships between them. I'm talking into the camera,
you're watching me talk into the camera and so on. All of these facts together make up the
totality of reality. So this way of thinking of the world breaking it down into its constituent
facts is basically related to the logical atomism that Wittgenstein developed alongside his teacher
Bertrand Russell. Russell taught Wittgenstein when Wittgenstein was an undergraduate at Cambridge
in the early decade of the 20th century 1912 he started there and they became friends and they
worked closely together on philosophy developing this idea of logical atomism. So atomism in general
is the view that the world is made up of distinct units of existence and logical atomism adds to
the view that this view has arrived at through logical means rather than through empirical
investigation through logical means we can break down facts into their basic constituents and
really this is one of the peculiar traits of Wittgenstein's approach. In the Tractatus he
simply insists that if thought and language are to represent the world then thought language in the
world must be structured in the same way this would only be possible according to Wittgenstein
if there were basic units of existence the states of affairs that could be picked out by the basic
elements of our language the primitive propositions the picture theory. So Wittgenstein puts forward
what he calls the picture theory of meaning the idea very roughly speaking is that the function of
language is to form pictures or models of reality that's how language gets its meaning.
So Wittgenstein develops an account of how language works of how it gets its meaning
based on an analogy with the way he thinks about pictures. So although pictures can have many
purposes it really helps to focus in on a very basic type of picture or diagram like you know if
I'm trying to show you the way to drive to my house I might sketch you a quick diagram
and to do that I don't have to include every detail along the way like you know what the view
is going to look like or anything like that I might just draw a very basic diagram showing you
like here's where you live here's the road in between here's where I live and like there's the
traffic lights you're going to turn left at the lights and I might draw this by putting little
arrows on the road or whatever. So a diagram like this presents a situation to us according to Wittgenstein
it tells us that certain things are the case and certain other things are not the case so
suppose my diagram indicates that to get to my house you've got to take the second right after
the lights the diagram is presenting a situation in which my house is on that very road it tells us
that it's not the case that my house is the second left after the lights so this is basically what
Wittgenstein means when he says a picture is a model of reality so in constructing a picture
like this we're not constrained by what is actually the case okay by the facts by the actual facts
although my house is on the second road on the right let's say I'm perfectly able to draw a
diagram in which the house is on the second left after the lights so the situation that a picture
presents thus exists in logical space according to Wittgenstein it's existing in the space of
all possibilities not necessarily just corresponding to the actual situation of how things really are
a picture represents a possible situation when the structure of the picture mirrors the structure
of that situation okay so in our example that would mean that when I draw parallel lines quite
close together in the diagram they're representing the road and when I draw a little symbol with a
little kind of hat on it that's going to represent the house and a little rectangle that I draw with
some circles in it that's going to represent the traffic lights and you know if I put some arrows
on it they're not really representing any feature of reality other than that's the way you should go
to get to my house so here we have various symbols corresponding to objects in reality
and moreover the way in which the symbols are related in the picture mirrors the way in which
the corresponding objects are related in the given situation real or merely possible so in
this way Wittgenstein says the meaning and the truth or the falsity are two different aspects
of the picture so the meaning or as Wittgenstein sometimes calls it the sense of the picture
is the situation that it represents whereas on the other hand the agreement or disagreement of
its sense with reality constitutes its truth or falsity so we can usually tell what a picture
means just by looking at it if we're familiar with the notation that's being used but in order to tell
whether a picture is true or false we must compare it with reality we must actually look and see what
the picture represents and whether that's actually the case or not so according to Wittgenstein
language works in pretty much exactly the same way so we're setting up this analogy between
language the way language works and the way pictures represent reality so according to Wittgenstein
in the tractatus language gets its meaning pretty much wholly by representing possible states of
affairs in logical space meaning and nonsense so according to the picture theory it's the job
of meaningful language to picture actual possible states of affairs so for Wittgenstein logic sets
the limits to meaning the tautologies and contradictions of logic are not themselves meaningful
they are limiting cases without sense Wittgenstein treats mathematics the same way but other cases
have an even deeper grade of meaninglessness being utterly nonsensical to understand them
Wittgenstein says we should have to be able to station ourselves with propositions somewhere
outside logic that is to say outside the world and Wittgenstein thinks that a consequence of this
is that language which doesn't picture any concrete state of affairs is going to be meaningless
so one of the main aims of the tractatus it becomes apparent is to show what is meaningful
and what is not so in the preface to the tractatus Wittgenstein writes this book will draw a limit to
thinking or rather not to thinking but to the expression of thoughts the limit can only be
drawn in language and what lies on the other side of the limit will simply be nonsense so here
Wittgenstein includes any talk about value including ethics religion and philosophy itself
language can't meaningfully address these issues Wittgenstein thinks that value somehow
lies outside the world and famously he says the limits of language mean the limits of my world
and in particular as Wittgenstein was very well aware the tractatus itself is meaningless the very
theory that Wittgenstein seems to be putting forward here about how language gets meaning
is itself meaningless by its own likes Wittgenstein is very aware of this but that doesn't mean that
he thinks that philosophy itself is pointless according to Wittgenstein the tractatus is
a lucidatory activity by this he means that anyone who comes to understand the tractatus
thereby understands that it's senseless but since understanding has been achieved one no longer
needs the propositions of the tractatus he must so to speak throw away the ladder after he has
climbed up on it so in this way it doesn't matter that the tractatus is meaningless its value is in
the activity of reading through it thinking through it and coming to understand it not in its content
so a key idea here for Wittgenstein is the distinction that he draws between saying and
showing so according to Wittgenstein often we can't say such and such but we can show it so
according to Wittgenstein there are important things that we can't meaningfully say in language
but nevertheless we can show them Wittgenstein says what finds its reflection in language language
cannot represent what expresses itself in language we cannot express by means of language
propositions show the logical form of reality they display it by showing that a number of
propositions that we might otherwise take to be meaningful are actually nonsense Wittgenstein hoped
that philosophy could lead to the clarification of our thoughts so what Wittgenstein's trying to do
here really is to show that there are a number of propositions that we might otherwise take to be
meaningful but to be philosophically problematic and what he's really trying to show us here
is that really these propositions are just meaningless right and then if they're meaningless
well they can't really be problems because if they were problems we would be able to
meaningfully express those problems in language but we can't so they're not the purpose of philosophy
this according to Wittgenstein is the object of philosophy okay so Wittgenstein's conception of
philosophy really differs from many traditional views of what philosophy is which go right back to
ancient times so on many conceptions of philosophy what we're trying to do is we're trying to use
rational thought to clarify problems and to solve problems to come to an understanding of the way
reality is perhaps in its most fundamental aspects by using our rational thought to solve those problems
but that's not how it is on Wittgenstein's conception of what philosophy is rather for
Wittgenstein philosophy is not a body of doctrine but an activity a philosophical work consists
essentially of elucidations philosophy does not result in philosophical propositions but rather in
the clarification of propositions so Wittgenstein then concludes with his seventh thesis to which
he offers no further explanation where of one cannot speak thereof one must be silent the
empiricist interpretation okay so let's break off for a moment from what Wittgenstein says
in The Tract Artist to one way in which it can be interpreted and whether that interpretation is
right or wrong so there's an influential interpretation of The Tract Artist that tries
to place it along empiricist lines so empiricism in philosophy it's a viewpoint in epistemology
in the theory of knowledge that says ultimately all our knowledge and understanding of the world
comes from our experience we don't have any a priori knowledge that we get you know independently
of our experience to understand the world to gain knowledge we have to go out there
and really experience the world from scratch without any experience our mind is just a blank
slate to be filled up and then systematized with experience so one person who attempts this
empiricist interpretation of The Tract Artist was Carl Popper who was an influential philosopher
of science okay so he attempts to interpret The Tract Artist as an empiricist doctrine
Popper sums up The Tract Artist as follows all genuine or meaningful propositions were
true functions of the elementary or atomic propositions which described atomic facts
which could be in principle established or rejected by observation okay so that's a pretty
accurate summary of The Tract Artist up to the point where we get to which could in principle
be established or rejected by observation so this last bit is added by Popper and it's not
in The Tract Artist the phrase observation statement which is a key idea in empiricism
doesn't occur anywhere in The Tract Artist. Wittgenstein just isn't really concerned with
epistemology he's not concerned really with the theory of knowledge he hardly talks about it at all
it seems to me that Wittgenstein made a purposeful decision to exclude any discussion of any epistemic
any matters relating to the theory of knowledge from The Tract Artist okay and because of that
we can't really attribute this epistemic interpretation of The Tract Artist to Wittgenstein
I just don't think it's an accurate understanding of what Wittgenstein was trying to do at all
nevertheless the empiricist interpretation of the picture theory of meaning was itself
influential as an understanding of The Tract Artist so the the empiricist interpretation it
was picked up by the logical positivist philosophers of the Vienna Circle so that's including philosophers
like Maurice Schlick, Frederick Weissmann and Rudolf Carnap so these philosophers they assumed
that Wittgenstein was supporting the verification principle the principle that only those propositions
that are empirically verifiable are meaningful so according to verificationists according to
the verificationist principle there's a large class of propositions including ones about
ethics and theology and philosophy that aren't verifiable and hence aren't meaningful now Wittgenstein
does agree with this he does agree that there's a large class of propositions you know including
ethics and theology and lots of philosophy and that stuff just isn't meaningful but Wittgenstein gets
to this conclusion for rather different reasons than the verificationists he's not really an
adherent of the verificationist principle he's got quite a different theory of meaning he doesn't
say that there's something to be meaningful it has to be verifiable rather he's saying I've got
this picture theory of meaning that sets out the limits of meaning and whatever lies on the other
side of those limits is meaningless so Wittgenstein is not really a verificationist the Tract Artist
is one of the masterpieces of analytic philosophy in terms of its influence on later philosophy
the picture is kind of difficult to assess not least because it wasn't that long from the
publication of the Tract Artist to the publication of Wittgenstein's philosophical investigations
where he basically takes back a lot of the viewpoints that he expresses in the Tract Artist
so he was basically disavowing his own philosophy and I think it's fair to say that Wittgenstein's
philosophical investigations and the picture of philosophy that he presents in the philosophical
investigations really set the tone for analytic philosophy philosophy of language in the second
half of the 20th century so in some sense the philosophical investigations overshadowed the
influence of the Tract Artist nevertheless there are lots of individual bits of the Tract Artist
that went on to influence important bits of analytic philosophy on the metaphysics side
there is the metaphysics of states of affairs which influence people like David Armstrong
there's the account of meaning which went on to influence lots of philosophers and linguists
perhaps not the picture theory of meaning itself but Wittgenstein's broader idea that we understand
the meaning of a sentence in terms of its possible truth values its truth conditions that's a really
really influential idea in analytic philosophy of language and linguistics the way we relate the
meaning or content of a sentence to the possible situations or the possible worlds at which that
sentence is true that's a really influential idea in modal logic and the kind of areas of philosophy
that tie in nicely with modal logic so analytic philosophy of language Wittgenstein's conception
of philosophy is something that is ultimately meaningless but that somehow it's okay to say
that it's meaningless or rather to show that it's meaningless I think has had a much more
mixed reaction Frank Ramsey in his critical notice of the Tract Artist I think expresses this idea
this criticism the best when he says what we can't say we can't say or we can't whistle it either
so Wittgenstein was known at the time for being a very proficient whistler he could
whistle his way accurately through an entire symphony and what Ramsey is really saying here is
you know you can't have your cake and eat it you can't say that this stuff this philosophy is somehow
important but also say that it's meaningless right if it's going to be important it has to mean
something and you know I guess he's saying philosophy is important and thus it is meaningful
so Wittgenstein's theory that says philosophy isn't meaningful well there's something wrong
with that but you know I think this point brings out something very very interesting about Wittgenstein's
character and I guess in his self-belief as a person and as a philosopher so if you or me I guess
came up with a theory and then we realized that this theory had this really crazy consequence
we might say to ourselves hmm yeah that's probably a problem for my theory I better go
back to the drawing board and revise the theory Wittgenstein realized that his picture theory has
this crazy consequence that all the stuff he was saying is actually meaningless but he really believed
in what he was saying and he trusted his own ability as a philosopher to such a degree that he
could say well my theory tells us that everything we're saying is meaningless and thus it is so
all of this stuff is ultimately meaningless and he extracted from that a whole way of looking at
philosophy so ultimately I don't think that tells us that much about philosophy itself but it does
tell us something very interesting about Wittgenstein as a thinker so there is so much more to say
about Wittgenstein about his thought and about his philosophy if you want to see some more videos
about that go and have a look at this one over here thank you so much to all my kofi supporters
for making this content possible and thank you to you for watching this far I really appreciate it
and I'll see you guys back here soon