Hey everybody, let's build a Dyson Sphere. We know we want to, humanity yearns for the
cosmic climb, so where do we start? Welcome to science technology in the future. Today
we have Canadian futurist, science writer and ethicist George Svorsky with us. He wrote
an interesting piece on how to build a Dyson Sphere in five easy steps. So we are here to
discuss the hows, what's, wins and where's of doing so. George Svorsky has appeared many
times in our show since 2012 discussing journalism, human enhancement, singularity,
the Turing test and the AlphaGo phenomenon. He is a contributing editor at Gizmodo and IO9,
the chairman of the board at the Institute for Ethics and Emerging Technologies and it's one
of the directors for the rights of non-human persons program. Hey thank you so much. It's sad
that we're here to discuss the passing of an iconic figure but it certainly gives us a good
opportunity to delve into some of the issues that he raised over the course of his illustrious
career and at times a controversial career and we'll dive in and explore some of these pretty
exciting concepts. So the way that I was really introduced to the idea of Freeman Dyson was
actually through Dyson Spheres, my interest in large galactic mega-scale structures. First of all,
I mean what is a Dyson sphere and why would we want to build one? Yeah I mean the whole,
I mean the whole thing got started for Dyson back in the late the late 50s. I think you penned
this two, just a two-page essay where you just kind of got thinking that you know eventually
you know like a super sophisticated, super powerful technological civilization
they're going to need a lot more energy than what's you know what could possibly be provided on
their home planet. So he conjectured about these hypothetical megastructures which are basically
these under a massive array of solar panels that will completely envelop the sun and extract
virtually all the energy that's output from the from the star. And yeah I think he had originally
envisioned it as a whole fleet of satellites like a spacecraft in orbit around the sun
but out of tremendous like like I would think like hundreds of kilometers of density so they
would not you know they would not intersect in this fashion to each other but effectively
it would kind of from a distant observer there'd be so many and so many working in concert that
would effectively like be this swarm of spacecraft or really what are solar panels in orbit like I
said around the sun extracting that energy and that energy could therefore be used to to power that
civilization and they could continue to advance and you know develop as an advanced civilization.
And he also got thinking well if this is a possibility for extraterrestrials well two
things come from that one he said well it therefore represents a way for us to potentially detect
the signs of extraterrestrial civilization so that thus becomes a kind of techno signature
and indeed this this obviously this this giant shield that kind of you know envelops the sun
is going to be absorbing a tremendous amount of heat it will then be giving off a certain amount
of heat radiation so he said that and others have since speculated that we should be able to
detect this infrared signature at specific bands from Earth but that'll that'll depend on the
materials that are used and the amount of heat that still is able to be dissipated from the structure
and yeah I mean and then the other the other the second issue that this raises is that well hey
that means that's something that we might do in the future as well so this is not something exclusive
for extraterrestrials it's something that future humans might want to build as well
and yeah I mean it's pretty exciting as an idea I think it's a no-brainer I'm not
that's funny because I'm such a huge advocate of solar power as a renewable like I yeah I like
wind of course and I make some renewables but oh my god like for me like a solar is a no-brainer
I have this envision like from transformers like Cybertron but instead of kind of creating
Cybertron why don't we just convert Earth into this gigantic solar you know like basically a
gigantic orb that's plastered in solar arrays right yeah I exaggerate but but the point is that we
are absolutely squandering so much real estate on this planet that should be extracting solar
you know solar energy that's otherwise going to waste of course you know we don't want to
destroy it for us and things like that obviously plant life and other life need this well there's
a lot of death it's isn't there yeah there's a lot of rooftops unit I mean those two things right
there I mean we could just exploit those resources in terms of real estate we go a long way I think
to providing some of the much needed power so but what Dyson was thinking about back in 1959
again he was thinking that eventually though you know this will be unsatisfactory even if we
can't harness as much as much energy as we can on the planet and what would be what would what
was since we would be referred to as like a Kardashian one civilization but perhaps I'm jumping
ahead of ourselves as we will get to Kardashian stuff in just a minute but it's nice that these
ideas intersect with each other that a Kardashian one scale civilization would harness the entire
energy available to it on this host planet where it would therefore need to graduate to a Kardashian
two scale civilization where it can actually harness all of the available output from its host
star and that's where Dyson Spirit provided the Dyson provided a mechanism a potential mega
structure with which this could conceivably actually happen so it's kind of obviously
futurists get excited by this idea because it really does present a plausible solution for our
energy needs moving forward whatever those energy for whatever we want to you know convert that
energy into in future whether we're running supercomputers or you know the like so so yeah
that's that's that's kind of maybe that's the answer your question yeah that's kind of like
what this what we haven't even got into all the different kinds of Dyson structures that
can exist but that basically is you know how I'd answer your question as to why and how
we're not how and why we want to build such a thing indeed yes um yeah so uh so two luminaries
two amazing minds recently passed away Freeman Dyson and Nikolai Kardashev no I'm not talking
about the Kardashians folks in case you haven't heard of like the Nikolai Kardashev here's a guy
who came up with civilizations the scales of civilization and and what sort of resources
they'd be using and how large they'd be and so yeah there's a there's three Kardashev scales do you
want to give us a brief yeah yeah sure and again very much a contemporary not the Kardashev scale
yeah the Kardashian scale is coming completely different we'll save that for another podcast
yeah so Freeman Dyson and Nikolai Kardashev obviously contemporaries so whereas Freeman Dyson
was running with Dyson Spears in 1959 I believe it was Kardashev in 1966 conceived of the Kardashev
scale and again it was a very simple scale uh one to three and you know he was to him like this
this way he was a soviet astrophysicist and to him you know energy availability was a
massive metric like it meant everything in terms of how you would you know really define a stage of
civilization and he got this idea well eventually you know a civilization should be able to harness
all the you know all the energy that it can possibly extract just on its home planet and that can be
you know obviously just we're just talking about solar so that can be incoming solar but can be
anything else it can be wind it can be currents and all that but eventually that's there's only so
much you can extract once you've kind of hit that cap you're what he would call a Kardashev one scale
civilization and the next was a civilization that can then harness the entire energy output of its
sun that's a Kardashev two scale and perhaps more radically I don't want to say more speculative
because all of this is speculative but more radically he also conjectured about a type three
Kardashev scale civilization which can harness the entire energy output of the host galaxy
which when you think about how many millions billions of stars are in the Milky Way that's a
lot of energy that's a you know mix of wonder you know at that point you know that that that
point is beyond human comprehension to understand what that civilization would be like and what
they could possibly use that much energy for it gets in it is kind of maybe like godlike
the state of being that again it's difficult to to imagine so oh man I looked at some of these
numbers and look it's hard to make intuitive sense oh I know they're just so ridiculously yeah the
exponentials are massive and yeah like the orders of magnitude beyond orders of magnitude beyond
orders of magnitude it's because the point where it doesn't the numbers that you suggest that
of them they just don't mean and it just doesn't make any more sense to us I think even like to
think about a Kardashev one scale civilization is still enough to kind of make my to make me real
in terms of what that would actually represent let alone you know a Dyson sphere capable civilization
and I mean since I mean that's a great scale and it got a lot of conversation going on the
late great Carl Sagan uh loved the idea and he thought hey why don't we actually kind of dive
into this a little bit break it down a little bit kind of came up with a schema for you know
creating incremental versions of Kardashev scale so according to his measure so for example today
earth and earth today human civilization would be about a 0.7 like a 0.75 on the scale so we're
gonna like we're like three quarters of the way there to be a full k1 civilization and similarly
they get out like 1.2 1.5 or whatever you know obviously if you're working from a Kardashev
two to three you could be a Kardashev you know 2.0000006 you probably that's a ridiculous you
know because you may be at that point in part is let's say 10% of the uh the Milky Way so these
kind of make sense and but even others are taking inspiration from uh Kardashev and come up with
other ideas you know for example the amount of space let's say that a civilization has uh as occupied
so let's say if it's now kind of dominates its entire solar its entire star system well that's
could be a certain level or the amount of infer this is not one that I'm particularly partial to
and I believe Carl Sagan also promoted this idea was that it was the amount of information available
to a civilization and I believe you kind of did this across the scale of A to Z so you could have
whereas A is like hardly any you know level of information and set as like I forget the way
what it was the the actual metric that he used but it was that that was like the end of the scale
so I believe he said that we were like at an H level so we were like we're like a Kardashev
so we were like we're like at a 0.75 H type civilization right now in terms of like not the
energy that we have available to ourselves and the amount of information processing that we're
capable of uh of engaging in and I think that those two things there are I think a very potent
measures you know where you're at there's of course it doesn't measure things like you know
gross domestic product that doesn't measure things like you know social well-being and
health factors um and I mean there's so many different ways I think you could still drill
down and come up with different ways of describing like the technological or social or political or
whatever aspect is important too in terms of the development of a civilization whether it be
ourselves whether it be an extraterrestrial level civilization and I think we'll always be biased
but what we think is a good metric of progress um you know so you know who knows maybe in a
hundred years from now we'll have a completely different sense as to what the direction and
the developmental trajectory that we would be desirable for uh an advancing uh civilization
such as our own and you know you can't speak to what that what that might actually be and maybe
if you look at for example maybe it could be the amount of um you know renewable uh energy
available to a civilization outside of uh non-renewables that'd be a good one I'd be
fascinated to see that you know that scale put you know put aside to that or if you were partial
to things like you know the hedonistic imperative uh or you know shadow engineering you know maybe
how far are we to toward that goal like and how many and how many individuals both human
and non-human animal on the planet are in a kind of uh entering into a state of uh of
hedonism as opposed to the kind of uh modality that we find ourselves in uh today so different
there's different ways on all this then you know that's Kardashian but that kind of got us thinking
about you know um the ways in which we can um you know conceive about uh you know how we describe
the state of a civilization yeah indeed yeah I should uh preface that I am partial to the hedonistic
imperative I've done a lot of interviews with David um although I don't think to me I just
I'm not quite ready to commit to pleasure being the only metric that's important I think uh
sensitivity to novelty is also very important and uh yeah um and the ability to to make progress
intelligence and um yeah so yeah wow it's it's it's amazing how large theoretically civilizations
could get um but it's been conjectured and I'm also a little bit worried that we can't see any
evidence of other civilizations doing this yeah and hence this this ties into the Fermi Paradox
right no Drake equation absolutely I mean first and foremost um we can almost write off Kardashian
three as a possibility because you know our our astronomical observations uh seem to be in violation
of that that idea you know we look up into the sky and uh we see no evidence of uh of you know
galaxies that have been completely uh re-engineered or in or away somehow obscured
um by um you know this massive use of uh of like Dysonian type megastructures and there have been
actually this is actually not something I just you know I'm not just idly saying this to you
there have actually been specific um astronomical observations looking for um these sorts of signatures
coming from other galaxies and obviously these studies aren't to be all an end all you know maybe
other ways of searching for these cloaked galaxies that are out there but we have yet to kind of see
such a thing so right off the bat it's like oh I don't know I mean I also think just I mean
it's kind of like you suggested it does bring the Fermi Paradox to mind because maybe we should
be seeing these like even if we are looking potentially you know hundreds of millions
or billions of light years away because obviously we're looking deep deep deep back into time
you know like we have for example special lens that could show us the universe or the cosmos
outside of the Hubble bubble that we're in maybe it would be a dark universe and maybe
that we're at a special a special time in our universe's development where galaxies are you know
starting to become subsumed by the intelligences which they've given birth to but more locally
to the Milky Way again the searches have only begun like we've only been talking about Dysonian
SETI for I'd say but the last 10 or 15 years and again the term Dysonian SETI again we can
that's a tip of the hat to Freeman Dyson so again thank you for for that and
with that the idea behind Dysonian SETI is in addition to looking for traces of Dyson spheres
or shovels or swarms or whatever we should be looking for any kind of techno artifact and in
particular mega-scale engineering because there could be many different kinds of things that advanced
extraterrestrial civilizations would do that would leave some kind of a signature for us to
be able to detect it could be everything from pollution and heat waste you know and back to
pollution like for example even planets that are of an unnaturally high level of carbon dioxide or
have been other kind of chemical compounds that are not consistent with what we know about the
known laws of physics in terms of what can autonomously be generated through natural processes
it could be traces of s you know engines or the rearranging of stars or again or even just very
straightforwardly a you know a Dyson shell itself as we were alluding to earlier and even
what's also fascinating is that there's constantly you know new thinking in terms of where we should
be looking so recent papers said hey you know what like never mind like plain old stars like
we should be looking at pulsars for Dyson instructors that what they will do is that
that makes more sense to create what's like a Dyson like a Dyson ring is really what it would be
so just you can imagine a ring around a pulsar and I'm sure your viewers and listeners can imagine
that as the pulsars spewing those concentrated streams of energy it would be they would be
orientated along the ring the interior of the ring and it would be such power you know that
in such efficiency that you don't need you don't need to build such a massive structure
you know right now like for example we wanted to build a Dyson shell that completely enveloped
our sun here in our own solar system I think Andrew Sandberg is probably the leading guy that's
done this math among others and it's like yeah like you got to take apart Mercury probably
take a huge chunk out of Venus and let's go dive into the cores of the gas giants and next
you know like we're kind of starting to run out of actual material in the in our own solar system
to build such a thing so there is kind of like a prohibitive nature to to that as well so if you
if you can be more economical in terms of the material that you need to to build then why not
you know exploit perhaps better sources of that energy such as pulsars and there's even talk of
like for example creating similar structures around a black hole so what you do is let's say you know
black holes what they do is when they're uh when they're pulling in material they also spew a stream
of high energetic jet of photons so what you can do is I'll likewise set up a massive you know a raise
energy extracting a raise at the at the exit point there where the jet is streaming out
and you know that's your turbo your energy turbine for lack of a better word that that works there
or we can like deliberately shove a star or several several stars into a black hole to
even create facilitate this process and create even more output for us so um maybe it's not so
much a passive thing in terms of just some and capturing our star as it is going out there and
finding better places to exploit but now at this point really what we're talking about is we're now
escalating down that Kardashian scale we're now definitely I would say you gotta start at a k
two and then you know I don't think you go from k one to having you know a pulsar capable
Dyson shell I think you gotta you graduate towards you know to those you know means of
k ability and as you're working your way toward that k uh that uh I guess toward that k three status
so um so yeah um I forgot even what the initial question was Adam you have to remind me what
well you know what um I'm I'm just wondering like I guess we spoke about like a um what it means to
to not see any evidence of galactic structures or expansion of civilizations out there and we
we started to speak about the Fermi paradox and and Drake equation I brought up and
Robin Hansen brought up the great filter argument and he described the that we should be concerned
if there aren't any galactic spanning civilizations out there because it decreases the likelihood
that we will be able to reach that sort of status ourselves that will likely go extinct
yeah uh it's a very potent uh an upsetting idea and uh yeah I mean the the search for
Dyson instructors has only really just begun um so that was just to be fair but there have been
searches and nothing has come up yet but more more practically I suppose uh considering the
contributions of Enrico Fermi um it shouldn't even matter uh whether or not we see these spheres
or not what matters is that we we just seem to be uh completely um out of touch with other
extraterrestrial civilizations we see no no signs of anything they never they don't appear to travel
through the solar system um and what that means is is that and that for the casual listener that
might be the world I you know maybe you know maybe there've been tons of you know aliens that
sit through our solar system and and certainly while there's a I suppose a chance of that
there is a general feeling in the futurist community and those who are engaged in this
kind of deep deep kind of speculation that look when a and when when we're when we're talking
about these advanced civilizations they're not just going out on field trips you know
at holidays to visit star systems what we're talking about are is are expanding bubbles of
the civilization itself and that when it reaches another star system uh it doesn't just you know
pass through it actually will make it its own it'll actually adopt it build its own probably
you know extract all the resources it possibly can to continue to fuel its civilizations uh spread
including building a distance here around uh the star of that system completely transforming it
even more speculative everything and everything we're saying is so super specular but why not
let's just keep going if then you get some objectives like oh Star Trek Prime Directive
they come here and they'd be like oh there's intelligent civilization on earth we have to
leave them alone because it's Prime Directive like no no no no no like that what the the
very least what they would do is uh well destroy us but i doubt that that's the case i think more
plausibly than uplift us so within a snap of the finger they would basically uh integrate us within
their own civilization by whatever means is available to them so that's become part of the
organism become part of the board collective we'd be subsumed into their civilization hopefully it
would be a benign and uh enlightened uplift and not a like the board is obviously as a dystopian
scenario as it gets uh you would hope that that's not the kind of uh assimilation that would
happen and instead what i mean uplift i mean in the truest kind of like you know sense where we
would be uh you know bioengineer uh reconfigurated to be this kind of post biological uh entity that
they themselves are most assuredly uh that they most assuredly have become i'm not imagining
green aliens visiting us i'm imagining you know um uh machine minds digital beings passing through
here uh transforming you know the galaxy uh as they expand out through the milky way so yes so i
just stand step back a bit so yes it does not appear that we have been visited by extraterrestrial
civilizations why because everything looks pretty peaceful natural uh you know in a as that currently
you know that we've nothing but we're not touched we're not touched solar system so
um and as far as we can tell you know as we look out into the galaxy it looks like all of the other
star systems in our galaxy are the same of the same way although it's we still we have yet to see
any sign of something that's you know undeniably uh inalienably uh artificial in nature everything
this does appear to be out there we look out in space it's very these are all natural processes
everything fits in nice and cosily you know within the laws of physics as we know it so there's no
reason for us to believe that that we're looking into uh you know a highly technified uh galaxy so
that's that's kind of essentially i mean that's probably taking what Fermi said a little too far
all his observation was like oh my god like we you know we we should have definitely seen somebody
by now like uh what he what's what's what's potent about the Fermi paradox is he basically
eliminated time as a factor because that what would you a common argument is like oh there
hasn't been enough time uh for civilizations to occupy the entire galaxy um and that's fundamentally
wrong uh there has been more than enough time our galaxy is really really old and has been able to
host a biological life for a very long time uh long enough such that uh you know this galaxy
should have been colonized you know not just once but multiple times yet it's not it hasn't happened
and that's kind of alarming and that's what you know Robin Hansen has said well maybe it's because
it doesn't happen that there is this kind of great filter in effect where that you know no civilization
can and there's a certain developmental stage that nobody can get past and it could it might be
self-destruction of some sort it i mean it could be let's say a technological a complete you know
technological hurdle um even if you even go for example it could even go back in time to the uh the
the the rise of uh you know uh from you know single sub-life to multi-cellular life and that
that's the case that's actually amazing new that's the best news i could possibly share with anybody
today because it means we've actually passed the great filter and that we're freaks we shouldn't
actually even be here and we might even be the only civilization in the entire universe for
certainly in the galaxy that somehow we leaked through this filter where you know no other
planet that was even possible so that that's we don't in other words we don't know if the filters
behind us or if it's still ahead of us personally i'm inclined to think that it's it's ahead of us
that we're heading toward our daily our inevitable doom and that there's something that will prevent
us from building dyson spheres and becoming a kardash of you know you know 2.4 civilizations
and so on which is a kind of depressing thought but unfortunately that's potentially where the
evidence is leading us in terms of trying to understand you know our future there were other
possibilities of course i mean this is quite alarming but it's also um a great motivation
to be extra careful and to do whatever we can to increase the likelihood of um becoming aware
of potential filter should be stepping right into one and mitigate the likelihood that that'll
wipe us out like all filters you know something gets through like a great filter is considered
like to be many like like robert hanson described it as a whole like range of things but um like
steps going up a staircase now some some life doesn't make it beyond the first step some life
makes it beyond the second and third and fourth maybe we're on the 16th and there's a 17 18 19
20th before we reach a technological mature civilization um so hopefully they don't like
squash us out of existence before we do that right yes it's an interesting thought and uh
i mean we there's no shortage of threats in our future i mean we could we could go on and on about
artificial superintelligence we could talk about molecular nanotechnology we can talk about you
know deliberately engineered viruses and on and on and on not to mention the nuclear threat which
remains an apocalyptic uh risk um so there's still that and like i said things that we could probably
invent that we don't even know are possible but there's also nothing to consider is that
maybe there are modalities of existence that advanced life you know um kind of escapes into
that doesn't involve you know uh you know this kind of you know colonization way that we've been
talking about um yet you know at the same time these these solutions have to do two things that
has to satisfy the energy requirements needed to enter into that desirable modality of existence
and it has to be a solution that applies to every other single uh advanced extraterrestrial
civilization out there not just the subset because when it didn't apply to every uh advanced sieve
then at least some would decide to embark upon colonization campaigns and again the solution
has to take that into consideration has to come up with a like i said like a solution that's like
well what what's to prevent everybody from venturing out and reworking the uh Milky Way
in their own image so that's that to consider well there's yeah exactly there's a prism
prisoner's dilemma right where um if you're ever aware that you have galactic neighbors
or that you are suspicious that one you have galactic neighbors you're going to try um and get
all the resources that you can to preemptively protect yourself or even use to attack this
potential neighbor so that they don't do exactly the same thing everybody like would be thinking
of the same thing um let's reduce let's let's grab the resources so that we can defend and attack
and perhaps even preemptively strike because our neighbors might be also thinking of
preemptively striking whether they're aggressive or not they may decide that that's just the most
rational self-interested thing to do yeah that's a very depressing thought i mean uh it's uh and
i love that you invoke the prisoner's dilemma there and it does seem that that's kind of the
situation like you know what do you do with partial information you know what do you do you
know when you're not entirely sure what um you know a cohort is what kind of decisions a cohort
is going to make and yeah just the whole maxian concept you therefore unleash a whole fleet of
berserker probes and sterilize the uh the Milky Way before you know a berserker uh you know swarm
you know uh wipes you up uh again that's another i find also find it fascinating maybe more
optimistically that we also have no evidence of berserker probes again a berserker probe is um
this idea that uh instead of like happy von Neumann probes that are self-replicating probes that go
out there and do exploratory work or even colonization work um and then again like I said they
self-replicate and they continue to spread and spread and spread in a very happy way um uh berserker
probes just simply go out and uh just destroy uh basically they're sterilization waves and
then it would be it would be well it could be one of several reasons as to why this can happen
well one is just pure like malevolence just to like create this kind of scorched earth policy or
scorched galaxy scorched galaxy he has scorched galaxy policy to bring just as a protective
measure so a defensive measure um it could be uh like a rogue ai has gone completely you know
mad and it's just you know uh you know or just as or just again I don't want to speculate on
the reasons but I mean it's it's the fact is that we've not actually seen such a way make our
and make us way through our galaxy uh simply because we're here uh we're talking about berserker
probes so if you're talking about berserker probes they're probably things that they don't
actually exist uh so that's how like I said it'd be more optimistic way of looking at it
yeah that's true um now you've done like you've recorded like a whole taxonomy of different
types of like possible von Neumann probes right um yeah and you you you're in discussions with
aliezer and what was it nick buster maybe and is sandberg um trying to sort of lay out at least
some of these different yeah one of the ones um this came out of a discussion at uh chicago in
two 2008 i think transvision and uh it's kind of like aliezer the greatest term for you call it
the whack-a-mole hypothesis which is this idea that you that yeah that you have kind of like
berserker probes do exist but they're they're they're they're they're they're discriminant as
opposed to indiscriminate so like similar to like uh the the monolith on the moon uh in 2001
it's just hanging out kind of waiting for us to reach a certain developmental stage
and then it's kind of like kicks into action and it does what it does uh again what what a
wonderful idea by Arthur C Clarke but anyways uh so the idea of the of the whack-a-mole uh
discriminant probe is that it's waiting simply to see what becomes of us uh after the as a result
of our own technological singularity that one of the big things that Yadkowski talks about is that
there isn't necessarily just one kind of artificial super intelligence that can emerge that there's a
whole family of different types that can come out of the technological singularity we just don't know
what kind we're going to produce and nor do the aliens know what kind we're going to produce
whether it's a happy version or a sad version so let's say it's hanging out there and we can't
detect it it it's it sees it oh we've passed the technological singularity and it's a oh it's a good
good ai we're going to let them live and we're going to just let them be or integrate us or whatever
or if it's a potentially dangerous artificial super intelligence when they even threatens
the aliens is uh ongoing survival then it will extinguish us and that's the end of that so that's
just that's one idea and um uh and even as another idea for these uh self-replicating or not even
self-replicating but just this idea of probe technology Andrew Sandberg has also speculated
about uh kind of like policing probes which is kind of like maybe a more enlightened idea what
you were suggesting earlier about uh you know going out just you know terminating uh potential
threats is just basically exactly that just kind of like policing and uh kind of just assessing and
just uh making sure that any any threats that or anything that's coming in is what was desirable
rather than uh than you know than potential threat so in other words we may not have to
be a prisoner's dilemma sort of situation we can maybe have this kind of intermediary situation
where we can kind of just get a sense as to the intentions of that extraterrestrial civilization
but um yeah there's uh there's different you know ways of thinking about this problem
oh absolutely and that's a whole whack-a-mole or whack-a-civilization idea brings up some absurd
visuals in my head yes um yeah so well I guess you've also been given us a very uh interesting
step-by-step description of how we could bootstrap a um a galactic civilization starting with a
Dyson sphere or a Dyson swarm usually people um mean Dyson swarms when they say Dyson spheres
and not a thing that sort of shell with gravity problems um yeah so do you want to just step us
through sure and to be clear and to be clear this idea is uh is not my own it's uh it was
Stuart Armstrong from Oxford University who first articulated this particular model for
or like you suggested bootstrapping the Dyson sphere and what I did was I kind of distilled
his ideas and popularized it and I've been happy to talk about talk about it ever since but definitely
he deserves full credit for this idea so what it is is what he was saying is that really that
within short order we will um be able to start working on this it is not something that we should
think of as you know being so far away in the future and uh or something that only you know you
know the civilization is far and away in the future we'll be able to uh to mark up on this he said
that you know we should probably start thinking about you know building uh this structure relatively
soon and and well yes it's going to require some new tech and new ingenuity and new capabilities
but um we can get going because ultimately he said if we kind of get started on it that the
kind of like this very first uh uh stage of the sphere or swarm will become operational you know
you don't need like the whole thing you don't build the whole thing and then turn it on uh we've
kind of silly um be like actually you know what I'm imagining like the scene when you're you know
you you put the lights on a Christmas tree and you hit the start button and uh it doesn't turn
on it was one of the lights is this is actually out but that's kind of like old I guess it's
old school technology I'm just imagining what you're seeing with it okay let's start up the
Dyson Swarm and the sound from the blade and that's not starting correctly so no what to do is you
create a huge chunk that is going to be uh drawing power from the sun transforming it into useful
energy and what Stuart Armstrong was arguing is that you there you then use this to now
newfound energy source to continue to fuel the construction of the Dyson Swarm and this becomes
this kind of like it becomes this exponentially improving process and no manpower will be required
because the way he envisioned it is you're going to have probes robotic uh sorry robotic devices
working in space to actually construct um these these these panels these receivers
and they would also this have to work in tandem with mining expeditions to the inner planets and
perhaps even the asteroid belt and the outer planets uh unfortunately we'd have to say goodbye to
Mercury um and possibly parts of Venus and like I said the asteroid belt and uh other places in
the uh the solar system and that clearly will create a lot of upset I mean already just when I
write about it people write get I get very angry angry letters like how dare you talk about the
dismantling of the solar system and I okay well I mean my only concern about it is that it uh it
could disrupt the kind of orbital equilibrium that we do see in the solar system that there is this
kind of like um there is this prospect where if you suddenly remove a planet from its orbital plane
it can have this rippling gravitational effects down the line we perturb the trajectories of
planets and what that does is over the course of many millions of years we can actually result in
collisions between planets uh which is not good last night check so that's that's one one possibility
but like let's let's be let's be honest like Mercury is useless right there's it's it's it's just
baked in radiation and there's nothing of value there I mean aside from just for the sake of it
being there Venus I'm not even going to speak speak to me it's interesting only from a scientific
perspective in the sense that we they could maybe help us understand our climate models a bit better
and what you know the potential risks are uh and what some like severe case situations are like for
what an atmosphere can actually do like that's pretty scary when you look at you know what because
Venus is a sister planet to our own like it's so close to us it's basically the same size as ours
yet it's a complete shell and uh what's it what happened like what's the difference between us and
that so yeah before we dismantle Venus I would like us to know how it came to be and actually
what excitingly NASA is actually considering a couple of missions finally I think one of the most
even those that are closest celestial neighbors one of the most neglected planets in the solar system
yet it should be I think a high priority that we understand it a little better obviously all the
focus is on Mars because it has this this this this historical potential for habitability certainly
doesn't have that anymore um so that's why there's all this excitement about Mars but we also think
of it as you know there's potentially you know planet B for us which again is a as I don't know
if you you were you caught this one Adam but um last year I wrote a piece called why will never
colonize Mars generated a lot of excitement and a lot of upset and I basically argued that Mars
is not what you think it is and the whole these all these ideas of like how great it's going to be
to live on Mars and colonize it and terraform and all that is a bit of a pipe dream and it's complete
um uh you know um completely neglects you know the hardships and realities of doing so
so so yeah um well yeah I agree this can be really hard in our current biological form
but by the stage we you know um build a maybe a type two Kardashev civilization we can have the
ability to sort of adapt ourselves to sort of operate in a variety of environments probably
a lot more hardship than Mars for sure and I was at the long term I was a bit cheeky in my
headline there when I said humans will never colonize Mars because it was my excuse to say
yeah post-humans can colonize Mars so that that was kind of like where I was coming at uh on that one
so uh definitely I definitely made at that point that yeah we had modified humans and that's a
different story altogether so um yeah so back to the building of the Dyson sphere uh basically
once you've created this core um uh panel then it becomes a sex financial thing and uh I mean
Armstrong's predictions were that you could do this in maybe four stages I think five stages and it
would only take you know a few decades once you went to the ball once the ball was really rolling
and I mean uh I mean this idea has been attacked uh for not just because you require the dismantling
of planets but also the time obviously the time scale I I agree um maybe when I wrote this article
about 10 or 12 years ago I maybe overstated um our ability to get into space and work into space
we're finding it to be much more difficult than we could have ever imagined and uh you know that's
just the sheer cost alone of you know rockets uh delivering rockets and we're seeing this the
private sector finally getting a bit of a handle on this but it's still the lot the launch requirements
the technological requirements the ability to actually have machines working on mercury for
example that would not you know succumb to the elements like to be fair we're still quite a ways
off from being able to do this but like I like I said one thing I will stand by is that it's not
too early to think about it you know let's let's let's let's talk about it let's make up some
plans let's maybe make some timelines like let's maybe say hey what's the tech that we need to do
this what's the material that we need to do this you know what what kind of what how would a robot
actually work on mercury to kind of dig down deep into that we need to actually access them
usable materials and what do we do with all the waste and all this stuff these are questions we
can ask right now and get some very smart people working on even if even if it's just let's say
from uh like a crowdsourced perspective obviously I think academics should be talking about this but
maybe you know just as an active community so I mean obviously you've got the Mars Society and
people talking about that um people it's just so devoted to colonizing Mars so why don't we have
you know a group of people devoted to getting the ball rolling on the creation of a dexon
swarm so uh timelines okay maybe not maybe what we what we thought but certainly I don't discount
what Armstrong suggested though that once the ball is rolling though and it does become this
awesome feedback process where now you can really in earnest build this thing rather quickly next thing
you know you've got this you've got a dexon swarm so um one of the the way again one of the real
points here in the article what and uh what Armstrong was even arguing was that again this
is something that is plausible you know this is not what Dyson was conjecturing about was
fascinatingly intriguingly um you know doable and you know it was it was it was just kind of blew
my mind to see a guy actually put pen to paper and say here's how we can do it at least at a
conceptual level that it made sense to me and I continue to think it's just a fascinating possibility
oh indeed yeah so I mean in terms of the timeline to actually bootstrap to get started in this
process seriously and start at least using some of the energy that we can harvest from the sun
with a few uh I guess um panels in place as the beginning of a Dyson swarm how long do you think
that would take? Armstrong said 40 years which is crazy but that that's what that's what that's what
he said so um 40 years to get started no oh sorry I think you know the complete completion of the
swarm you're asking me like when we can actually get started on the project to start building the
first one yeah what's your opinion on that? Oh boy um not for a few decades I mean we're still at
the stage where kind of crazy because like we're talking about like NASA's now and Congress is
earnestly talking about a mission to Mars by 20 in the 2030s for example and uh the fact is that
we're embarking on a really small step still like we're still not working on the moon we don't even
have a moon a moon an orbital moon base we haven't even been to Mars yet um you know it and we don't
know some of the uh not only do we not know the technical hurdles that await we don't know the
socio-economic hurdles that await as well um our situation here on earth can start to get so dire
in terms of the environment that uh deep space exploration and uh and work out there will have
to take a backseat to the problems that need to be addressed here at home and it's going to be
increasingly difficult for governments to justify the spending taxpayer money you know for what could
be deemed as these rather uplandish uh science fictiony uh prospect I'm not saying I agree with
that perspective I'm saying that will be a prevailing perspective so it's because of these
kind of realities that you have to temper these kinds of expectations so to answer your question
maybe not sadly maybe not for a to 100 years uh and yeah of course like I said a lot of there are a
lot of wild cards and blacks wants to consider between them both ones that can continue to
satisfy but even like blacks ones that could perhaps uh be good like let's say an artificial
that's we kind of have this kind of like uh an artificial super intelligence that that we can
kind of understand and control uh very dubious that we could do that but um let's say that we
kind of like start to offload some of these design and engineering tasks to artificial intelligence
uh and we find ways of let's say you know becoming more economically uh stable and having the means
the resources with which to launch the source of expeditions so those things kind of came together
then all that's our offer terms of when we could start to mark upon this project so that's the case
I would say you know after the 2050s uh 2060s recently I will I will add though I'm turning 50
this year this is just a an aside almost any irrelevant aside but turning 50 this year and
you start to do the mat like when I was a kid like you'd see the oh yeah you know NASA's
launching probes to this planet or this moon and it's going to take 15 years to get there or
whatever it's going to be 25 year long project and you you kind of it's easy for you to digest that
it's you know think a lot it's still far away in the future which you can digest it now like for
example there uh that NASA's going to be sending a probe to uh to tighten it's fascinating it's
going to be actually uh a drone it'll be able to fly through the atmosphere because it actually has
an atmosphere and uh yeah it's going to be it'll be landing in the mid 2030s assuming they can get
it going and yeah I'm going to be like I'll be like 64 65 years old when it happens and uh radical
life extension Adam notwithstanding I'm hoping in terms of what you know what you know what you
know what how our health can be prolonged in the future I tend to be a status cool type of a type
of a person I don't tend to assume that that's going to happen um I take I assume that I'll be
aging normally and I'll die you know at a depth you know as per the situation today it'd be wonderful
you know I could prolong my life but it does seem that I'm starting to get to a point now in in my
life where perhaps some of these longer scale uh prospects are something I'll never live to see
and uh you eventually there's going to be some kind of a project where yeah if I do the math I'll be
115 but it actually gets rolling in other words I probably won't be alive to see it
so I'm not sure why I'm bringing this up just aside from the fact that um starting to it does
affect perhaps the way you look at the future and understand that yeah you know life will absolutely
go on without you being there and of course without you being there to observe it and appreciate it
but of course that doesn't mean you should think it's still gonna not gonna happen most certainly
you should never let that prevent you know this kind of multi-generational thinking I for example
I'm a firm staunch believer that we should start to not not just talk about uh Dyson swarms
in construction let's start talking about interstellar uh expeditions you know we've got Voyager
the Voyager 2 probes you know they they're incredible but why don't we scale up something
like that you get a massive you know I think uh they're already been like Stephen Hawking talked
about this for example creating these ships with solar sails that my god like these things once they
get cooking and moving in space powered only by like uh the the particles emanating out from the sun
but then a short matter of time it'll be moving at 10 the speed of light you know that suddenly
these relativistic speeds the the nearby star systems aren't so far away anymore and now you're
talking about missions that are like what 10 40 years you know instead of like prohibitively long
like like wait like Voyager's not going to reach the first possible star system for like tens of
thousands like hundreds of thousands of years obviously that's super discouraging but anyways
point being is I would love us to start taking the long new bold ideas yeah we may not live to
see it in our own lifetime but maybe you know generations four five 10 20 from now will absolutely
yield the benefits of this it could even be potentially existentially worthwhile the sense
that it could actually get detect you know habitable systems uh to learn from the science of these
expeditions and uh so I think we should also start thinking along those lines as well yeah the idea of
astronomical waste comes to mind and population axiology or population ethics where um we should
be considering the moral relevance of people who are not yet around or like slots for life that are
not yet available can we say um and if we were to go extinct or to um I guess be damned to live
only on this sort of film on top of this rock called earth in this tiny portion of our own
galaxy let alone all the others then that would be a shame um because there's a whole lot of
matter out there that doesn't isn't being sort of used to support lives worth living um and so
yeah it there's a paper out there called um something along the lines of astronomical waste
yeah but it's quite interesting when you start thinking about the huge sheer amount of possible
lives worth living that could be cut short or just never actually be realized if we go extinct or if
we just never get off earth yeah and you know bringing it back full circle to freeman dyson
if he were here talking to us right now he'd be absolutely on board with what we're talking about
he was actually a big thinker in terms of uh the future human trajectory and uh he you know he
what did he say fair his book very famously said infinite in all directions now it's in such a
beautiful beautiful term and but he believed it you know like even thought that you know eventually
we could find ways of uh you know um prolonging the existence of a civilization um you know by
slowing i i have to forgive me if i get this a little bit wrong but basically what he was suggesting
is that uh we we dramatically slow down like the clock speed of civilization to the to the point
where it's so excruciatingly slow that the time ticks relative to the actual how time is elapsing
around it that it might as well be you know quasi infinite in terms of how long the civilization
could actually last given the constraints of of course of cosmology uh i think he came up with
these ideas back in the 70s when we saw a different view of uh cosmological evolution and development
we now know for example that the universe will eventually start to expand and expand quicker
and quicker and quicker which will preclude i think some of these uh ideas of you know finding
almost like infinite ways of prolonging human existence or post-human existence whatever will be
like 22 30 billion years from now but um yeah he was definitely online with this thinking like
like think big think bigger like that's i think that's one of the more fascinating aspects about
Freeman Dyson was how he would kind of like just take things to a level that perhaps you know
no one uh no one had before you know when we were talking about a guy who penned this thing in 1959
okay it's it's hard for us perhaps to understand how radical an idea that would be okay this is
in 1959 say hey extra trust you we're gonna build what he didn't call him Dyson's spheres and people
called it after that like they named it after him yes he actually didn't like the term that that
was named after him but i will say he got the idea from Olaf Stapleton and that very good point
actually um and thank you for bringing that up he it's not was not his idea yeah you got it from
science fiction Olaf Stapleton and perhaps even others were already talking about ideas such as this
again he just looked at it as a potential solution for you know the insatiable energy demands of a
civilization but i thought it was pretty great like when i heard that he had died a couple of days
ago i thought you know i mean i really hope that we build a Dyson swarm if not for the simple reason
that we can call it a Dyson swarm or a Dyson sphere that it would what a legacy that would be as a
thinker to have a megastructure you know of such magnitude be actually named after him and i think
i just i would just love for that to actually happen even if he didn't like the term too bad
freeman you came up with an awesome idea or at least populated popularized and more fully
articulated the idea again with all due respect to Olaf Stapleton maybe i take back what i said
make sure you call them stapleton swarms i don't know but but still i think we're pretty damn cool
we actually do call it that we we build something like that but anyways point being that how radical
must have been for him to not only just talk about megastructures but to talk about it in
the context of the search for extraterrestrial intelligence which i'm not sure that was even
determined existed in 1959 it wasn't until uh drake in the like what 1964 or so and project osma and
the first efforts at radio set he got underway so this could predates for even radio like actual
efforts for radio set city so today we can talk about amazingly we can talk about megastructures
and dyson sphere uh you know without blinking an eye and batting an eye like for example um a couple
years ago there was that uh variable star which is called boy a boy on star is this tabby star the
same thing tabby star it's the same star it's the same thing and that had this unexplainable
irregular dimming episodes and a number of you know theories were posited to explain it uh
of uh in the from a natural perspective but inevitably it got people thinking well maybe
this is actually evidence of uh and the first data point we have of an alien megastructure
and what delighted me as a journalist covering this stuff well was that i could actually just you
know matter of fact we say yeah could this could actually this is actually being entertaining as
possible and i didn't have to like like really beat people over the head to understand it and i
and appreciate it like people like oh i know i've heard of that i don't have a nice enchilas you
know or whether it'd be through the science fiction or whether just through casual conversations
becoming whereas we had to fight for dysonian city you know just tended to 15 years ago it's now
almost taken for granted that that's how we should look for extra trust with civilizations that and
now almost the the radio study almost seems anachronistic i still believe we should we should
do it don't get me wrong i still think we should listen to radio signals but now yeah let's let's
look for uh like i said other techno signatures even laser settings becoming a thing and all that so
um again but again um i just find it interesting that uh freeman dyson being the free thinker
that he was you know just had it you know just thought this is what needs to be said and thought
through and you know and not like i say is what it is i've often thought about like what others
like strong attractors could um i guess motivate a civilization to uh expand in a way which is
indetectable um and you know at least molin came out with the idea that like maybe black holes
born universes and and there's other sort of permutations and an idea and and perhaps
uh galactic civilizations engineer or optimize black holes to spew forth the types of idealized
universes for computation and and and life right um and they think that you know they sort of ascend
or transcend in some way to to a better reality or a reality more conducive towards flourishing
i kind of hope that that's possible and that's a good reason why we can't see
other civilizations out there but what are your thoughts on um i guess strategies for
civilizations to continue without being detected so again i have to work under the um the data
that we have right now which does suggest that advanced civilizations should they exist they
don't become interstellar colonists that just that's that's the assumption that i'm working under
so i'm a bit i guess i can call me like a contact pessimist or even like a you know
just you just doubt that's kind of like within our within our future uh future means so i keep
asking the question well how the why then what is this kind of modality that a civilization
would enter into that's that's that's still uh deemed of value and uh it just it mean it just
keeps coming back to this idea of uh of you know this internal existence that living within ourselves
like locally and not branching out like just finding uh you know means to uh you know perpetually have
access to resources that might mean star hopping or parking near a perpetual energy source of some
sort um but living more modestly in that sense and yeah just running you know ancestor civilizations
or hedonistic civilizations and living out you know the the the remaining duration of the cosmos
in in that manner that's kind of like the best solution that i can come up at this point that's
still that that in my opinion uh does not violate the uh the non-exclusivity issue and at the same
time um answers the question as to why we've not made contact with anybody else that maybe we're
all just inherently xenophobic and we just keep to ourselves we enter into this uh happy heaven
like modality and that's that's and then in that post-unit of happily ever after the end so
i'm not suggesting for a second that that's what will happen or that's the greatest solution to
this but it's certainly one that uh occupies some of my thought uh in terms of um what's the solution
here what's the what's actually going to happen what's a non-exclusivity issue it means that um
it has to be a solution that every single extraterrestrial civilization will independently
uh enter into and that there can't be any outliers because if there were outliers and we would have
made contact with them by now they would have made their presence known that's again
working under those kinds of uh constraints i suppose in terms of uh when used to kind of
make these sorts of uh extrapolations i guess freeman dyson did have some controversial opinions
and views um and one of them was uh that he was sort of critical of climate change models or that
whether climate change would have a serious impact on global health and viability yeah he
kind of alienated a lot of people toward the end of his life and um yeah he was not kind of on board
the whole um you know climate justice span wagon and quite the opposite and uh you know
he he said himself that you know to be a good scientist kind of like means you have to be
subversive i don't think you ever liked i think the more popular an idea you know became i think
the less inclined it was to latch on to it kind of i was looking for ways to kind of chip away at it
and climate change was certainly um one of those targets and uh yeah he kind of thought that
scientists were i think it was a bit of a climate change skeptic first of all um but even if you did
buy into the models he kind of thought well it's not so bad you know which from today's perspective
like i don't have to tell you as a someone who lives in australia like well it is kind of bad
i think it's kind of like it's a show you know it's just awful and uh like because he was saying
oh it's great that carbon dioxide is great for plants and you know create these lush environments
and um all these kinds of like this i think the hand way these sort of um you know proclamations
that it got me thinking well he's a he's a big thinker but he was also maybe sometimes spoke
outside of his immediate area of expertise and maybe didn't think through some of the repercussions
of this yeah i will say at the same time he's like the only climate skeptic or whatever you
want to call it actually i kind of he'll ring in my ear every once in a while you know like
you for example you'll study like Jurassic environments and you understand that you know
there was no polar caps at that time and the dinosaurs lived at a very unique time in our
interplanets history and understand that yeah we're the climate change is an indelible part of
this planet's history like the planet in fact the history of this planet is simply the history of
climate change and in this constant study of how the planet has changed and how animals have reacted
to this to climate change over time and that includes all kinds of different things um hominins
and uh of course dinosaurs and animals and all sorts of things so um you know you do have to
look at climate change that that lens yeah what's i don't have to remind you or your listeners
obviously this is characteristically different because we're the ones that are now responsible
for it and we're kind of uh causing this change on timescales that are unprecedented in the planet's
history like it's uh these spikes are just unreal in terms of how quickly uh we're able to now impact
upon uh the environment you know it also gets me i'm thinking even about kardashev's scale because
kardashev says talks about k-1 civilizations and you know harnessing of the entire uh energy
output of the planet one thing kardashev would not have been concerned about well at what cost
to the environment what does that mean in terms of the heat expenditure uh you know uh if a whole
planet you know is working in that way like what is what is that doing environmentally what is it
doing to sustainability is it viable sustainable is this you know is it actually creating a planet
that's actually going to be able to continue to move forward in time and uh uh and and still sustain
you know what what we would value in terms of wildlife and uh and plant life and all that sort of
stuff so um it's one thing to conjecture about is one of the things sometimes one of the most
difficult things is to project outcomes and consequences and i think maybe that's where
freeman dyson was maybe a little lacking and and i could do cavalier perhaps about what he thought
were the ill effects of climate change and and not to accuse him of this but maybe simply because
it was at the sake of being contrary and being that that that guy who was that um you know to be
that kind of deviant when it came to scientific uh to scientific thinking so that sadly will
probably be one one area in which he will not be fondly uh remembered as uh i think
we can pretty much agree that uh climate change is something that needs to be
mitigated rather than celebrated right but um yes so a lot of people have controversial opinions
and it shouldn't really detract from the value they contribute in other areas um and i think
some people like to demonize thinkers because they come up with one controversial opinion
and that can kind of be like throwing the baby out with the bathwater which is i think silly
yeah yeah no no for sure i mean uh i you know i have you know so many quote unquote heroes that
that i admire but i don't think there's a i would never say like the reason why i had to put heroes
in scare quotes is because you know whether it be carl saying it or freeman dyson or anyone of
these people that i hugely admire they're not perfect and there's always something about their
personality or something they might have done or something that they believe in that there's
absolutely not you know conform to my own beliefs or values so i i would never say that i would i
will unabashedly feel and irreservedly follow someone and declare them you know to be the
perfect hero for me that that does not exist for for me personally so i could admire the
hell out of somebody that doesn't mean i have to buy an absolutely everything that they have to say
so i kind of yeah totally agree with you yeah yeah is there any other points which you'd like to
bring up at this stage which we haven't yet covered um uh you know we we boy we we covered a lot there
i just want to just uh maybe back to tabby star just to say that it's not it i don't know we've
kind of came full circle on that it's not a megastructure um right now they're pretty sure it's
still uh uh some kind of naturalistic phenomenon and it was a fascinating paper a few months ago
suggested that what it might actually be is a disintegrating moon so what what happens in some
star systems is that uh a planet uh will at the end of its life get subsumed by its host star
and it'll bring along its moon or moons with it in this case they're saying that that did not
happen that the moon got ejected and it's slowly disintegrating um as it is also being a subsumed
by the star it's kind of creating this anomalous debris field that uh is uh uh that is infrequent in
terms of uh how it's happening and that's the explanation and i actually talked to dr boyan
about this and she thought it was an intriguing possibility so um i decided to mention that
because i didn't want your listeners to think that it was still people are still very much thinking
that it's a megastructure it's we're pretty sure it's not but i think it's pretty exciting um that
we can talk about this possibility yet at the same time you never want to you know whenever we
see something that you don't understand is put your hands and say oh my god we don't understand it
it's gotta be aliens like i think that's i'm not suggesting we should do that by no means in fact
we're talking about pulsars earlier the first pulsars that were discovered were so odd to
astronomers they had no explanation for them because these things are blinking with such
extreme rapidity and regularity like that was their first thought too and i think they're actually
in the notes they're like was like lg uh lg m's they called them or something like that which meant
like little green man or something like that basically hinting that oh my god we're maybe
discovered you know some kind of alien signature here it turned out not to be the case but there
always is this tendency that when we do see something that's super weird and it defies our
expectations there is this tendency to invoke extraterrestrial life i'm not saying that's
the healthiest thing to do it should be this kind of last resort if you will kind of like that
like the anecdote at the end of an anecdote to say after we've exhausted all these possibilities
you know a through f let's just maybe keep an open mind that it kind of maybe is consistent with what
we think is technosignature could look like it's that's all i want to say about tabby star um at
this point awesome well um i guess if you'd like to conclude what if you were to meet somebody
who was thinking about donating their large fortune towards some form of exploratory research
what would it be and how would you convince them to do something that you value
that maybe relates to our discussion today wow that's that's a heck of a question i never
really given not really giving so much thought to that like i will say that it might be an answer
that um it's kind of like unsexy uh relative to discussion or even irrelevant to the
discussions we just had but i admire for example the bill and blend the gates foundation for what
they've done in terms of being smart about where they spend their money and in particular as to
what they deem to be areas that are most in need and for example a big thing for them is
neglect the tropical diseases and uh obviously you know with the COVID-19 being what it is right
now that's not a neglect the tropical disease obviously but it just shows that we are still
victimized by microorganisms like in a way like that's just unreal you know we we like to think
that we have a handle on on nature that we don't we're not preyed upon by lions anymore you know
or wolves um but we're most certainly preyed upon by other kinds of animals and they're
microscopic in size whether it be malaria you know zika virus um you know the common flu
and the cold and now the COVID-19 uh disease it's uh i think that we need we need to continue to
spend our money and our resources on those kinds of threats because at the end of the day and at
the end of the year when you look at the uh you know the actuarial tables those are the things that
are killing us uh you know at a horrific scale you know that's what's killing us on mass and we
need to get a handle on that and similarly the back out include bacteria and bacterial infections in
that in that uh the body of thinking and we're heading toward the so-called you know antibiotic
apocalypse where there are antibiotics looks like they're not they're increasingly becoming
ineffective and we're starting to talk about you know super viruses that are even super immune to
um standard uh cocktails of antibiotics so these are the kinds of things that scare the crap out of
me and me too and it should scare your listeners as well and so yeah that's if i'm okay you know
i think that people with horrendous amounts of money should probably spend it to alleviate those
kinds of uh blights so that's how i will answer that well george it's been an amazing mind blowing
discussion i i love talking about these topics and i really appreciate the time here that was fun
to talk to the review so yeah thanks heaps and i look forward to chatting with you again in the
future absolutely me too
you