I forget now whether you do have a discussant or not. Yeah, Virginia.
Oh, it's Virginia's gonna. Okay, great. So
She's here. Yeah, she's there. Hi, Jenny. I've been Virginia. I mean
Have you
Josh, you haven't seen any sessions at all yet, right? Um, I've seen I haven't been able to join live, but I watched video from the first two days
Did you watch belkin?
I did. Yeah. Okay, great. Okay. I was even gonna refer to it briefly. Yeah. Okay. That's why I don't want this to explain. Yeah
Um
I'm I'm also trying to see if there's some time
I know you said that there might I might be able to join I can't join the discuss or there is no discussion today, but um
I'm trying to see if there's any one of the other panels that my schedule would be great. I can add
Yeah, I'll I'll uh
I'll I'll be in touch about that. Okay. Let me just
Solid duty here
Welcome everybody to the afternoon session everybody out in in the
Distributed land and everybody here. I'd like to um
Introduce Josh Stendenbaum who's professor of computational cognitive science in the department of brain and cognitive science
at mit
He's a principal investigator at the computer science and artificial intelligence lab called sea sail. Is that former sail?
No, uh sail is a stem from sail
But it's formerly the AI lab and the lcs laboratory for computer science
Great. Yeah, and a thrust leader in the center for brains minds and machines cbn
And his papers are on perception learning common sensory reasoning in humans and machines with the twin goals of better
Understanding human intelligence in computational terms and building more human like intelligence in machines
In other words, he's cut out perfectly for this
Summer school. I hand it over now to Josh Stendenbaum
Okay, great. Thank you so much, Steven for organizing for inviting me
You know, I I got to watch much of the first two days and it was really interesting to see a back and forth between people who are
Extremely impressed with large language models
Both on their language abilities and maybe some of their general thinking abilities and other people who are much more skeptical
That they have really anything to do with intelligence at least of the human form
The work I'm going to talk about here is a is an interesting I think mix of those two perspectives
And I hope that will
Be useful stimulating
Engage in some interesting discussion both now and going forward over the next two weeks
The the heart of the talk, which will really be more like the second half is based on this paper
Which you can find on archive from word models to world models
Understanding natural language by translating into a probabilistic language of thought
But I'm going to spend the first half setting some context on just how we think about thinking and then it's built on that for the relationship between language and thought
This is you know, I would say this is both an AI talk and a cognitive science talk
Although most fundamentally to me. I'm really interested in the computational structure
of the human mind
So just in that
hear it in that lens
But I think also just sort of very generally
You know, nobody can fail to be surprised and impressed
At what has happened with the most recent machine learning models
And at the same time they're they're very puzzling and confounding in certain ways
So I hope to try to be able to resolve some of that or at least
Point the way towards some of that
This paper the work i'm going to talk about is joint with a number of people
I want to single out two people Lionel long and Gabe grand who are the joint first authors of that paper
I'm putting Lionel a little bit bigger
In part because a lot more of my slides are taken from lines
So I would say all of the credit for the good stuff both on the research and in the slides to Lionel and Gabe
And you know anything that doesn't quite work or make sense is probably just me garbling things
Okay
But a lot of other people contribute to the work that i'm going to talk about here
So again, you know, we can't who cannot be impressed with the advances of AI
Whether it's in perception and and you know robots deployed in the real world
Like the self-driving car systems of tesla and wemo or most recently conversational AI systems like chat gpt
Clearly there's something really interesting and important happening
But at the same time something quite puzzling now
There's a number of puzzles that people here have talked about just one
I'll point to is what you might call the puzzle of confabulation
Which points to what ways I think that the kinds of
What intelligence or unquote intelligence that we see in these systems is different in nature and origins from that in our own minds
So think about for example in the context of driving. This is a video from tesla
A self-driving system where it's it's faced with something a little bit out of its training set a horse drawn carriage and and
Buggy and it interprets it as a truck first facing one way the other then it's
SUV then it's a truck with the person behind it
Now the person's gone away
Shortly the person will come back
You know, they can't figure out which way the truck is facing
If a person were having this experience on the road, you would think they should stop driving and get off the road as soon as possible
Right. There's something fundamentally
Detached about their mind from reality here
And when this happens in systems where lives are at stake, it can be deadly. So this is a serious worry
technologically and
Sightly now when it comes to computer vision and tesla self-driving a lot of progress has been made
What I showed you what i'm showing you here is from a few years ago
Um, but you still see similar kinds of things and also on the language side
I'm just going to show one example of analogous kinds of things that really make you scratch your head
On the you you could find these in language models, but i'm going to talk about multimodal language and vision models because this is where
You know, there's a lot of really interesting stuff going on
Where machine learning and especially like grounded language
Potentially might meet up with what goes on in cognition
um, so this is a i'm just going to show you a couple of little demos from
Google's large language model multimodal language model. Um, gemini both earlier versions and then the most recent version
This is the figure i'm showing here, which i'm giving to gemini and I should say you can see similar things with chat gpt
But it's a little bit funnier with the google ones. I'm going to focus on that
Um, this is an image from my colleague vikash mansinga whose work will also figure in the talk
Um, vikash is one of the world's experts in probabilistic programming
He and I are very interested in how our minds and our machines could model uncertainty
So here's an image that that I think all of us when we look at this
It's it's it's pretty clear that though. It's a little hard to read kind of messy
It's really clear that there's a word here and that the word is uncertainty
Um, but what is uh an lm a multimodal lmc from this?
Well, it might see this the image you sent me shows a black and white image of a text box
The text book has a dark gray border rounded corners. Good inside is the word dream written in a bold sans serif font
Is there anything else I can help you with? I ask how many letters are shown in the text box?
There are five letters shown in the text box the letters are d r e a and m
What is going on with this?
Now we could say all right. Well, at least it's pretty good
I mean at least it's recognizing that there's text and it's you know, it could be worse
But it seems to be strangely self-confident strangely confident about an incorrect answer
But you could say at least it's not like seeing a person or person walking down the street
But consider this small change to the input image now our lm says this shows a black and white pixelated image of a person
The person is facing forward and appears to be standing still. Here are some details about the person
They have short hair. They're wearing a shirt with a collar. Their legs are slightly wider than their torso
Since the image is pixelated
It's difficult to discern other details such as facial features or specific articles of clothing
Now again, the thing that I think should make us puzzle here is
Is not just that the system gets this wrong, but that it seems to confidently assert things that are so
detached from our sense of of the reality of what we're seeing
And where just a small change can make such a huge difference
Just to update things this was this was from the first version of google's gemini the most recent version of gemini 1.5 pro
Has gotten better in some sense
Now given uncertainty. It doesn't say dream. It says optical illusion
But it's still wrong and it's still over confident. Um, it rates itself as fairly confident
That it says optical illusion. It's interesting. It makes you think is there some semantic association between dreams optical illusions and
This particular way of presenting the notion of uncertainty. I don't know. Um,
The the very most recent thing this was well, it's not that recent but the last time I gave this talk
Um, I tried this on the the newest updated version of gemini 1.5 pro just to see if perhaps it had been improved
And now it gave a very different answer
It didn't say it didn't read it as optical illusion. It gave this
Extended digit number six one two nine eight one five three two four two and I asked it to judge its confidence and it said
Well 70 to 80 percent
Again, what what happened? Just to check again consistency and coherence of this
Weird interpretation. I asked it just 10 seconds later just in an out of context again
Just gave it the same thing and the next 10 seconds later. It said geocache
Um, again now 75 confident and then one more time
Um, a distorted text appears to read northeast blackout
However, it's difficult to be certain
But it's moderately confident that the text reads northeast blackout because the first and last words are relatively clear
While the middle word is slightly less discernible, but still suggestive of blackout
Okay, so what's going on here?
That's one of the mysteries now
I'm not I'm not I'm going to gesture at what I think some of the mysteries or some of the answers might be
But mostly to point the way towards the difference with human intelligence and what we're trying to understand in in artwork
Okay, I think fundamentally what's going on is whether you're building a computer vision system or
An llm or a multimodal language text system
You're building a system that takes the inputs and outputs that our brains do
perception of the eternal world sense data of some form and it produces actions or something like actions that can be
Grounded back in the external world, but the inside of the system doesn't have any notion of a world
It's a function approximator
It's learning to approximate the input output functions that our minds produce
And it's learning to do that from various data sources including objective data sources as well as human reinforcement
Now how why does this possibly work? Well, again, there there may be some
laws of physics things that are like physics like for example the famous scaling laws of neural language models
Where you can show in some form
Especially when you're trying to predict like you know
And this is very much following some of the information theoretic ideas that richard has been talking about and others in the group here
If i'm just trying to predict the next token from the previous ones
There are certain fundamental power laws of language and distributions in language that these systems seem to incorporate
And build on such that if you increase by an order of magnitude the amount of compute
You can in a predictable way lower the test loss in predicting the next token. That's on the left
In gpt4's technical report
They suggested that you could see similar kinds of scaling laws for problem solving not just text prediction
Although it's a lot if you're there
And I think fundamentally the problem is the power laws are beautiful laws and they're predictable in a certain sense
The thing about a power law is while it approaches asymptote
Or it rather approaches zero error in its asymptote
It in some important sense never gets there compared to like an exponential decay
Where there's a predictable timescale on which it will get to zero a power law keeps slowing down
and if you have any uncertainty in the power laws coefficient or
You know in its applicability to the not just to predicting the data stream, but actually solving a problem
Then it's it's basically impossible to know how much data and compute you're going to need to actually get to the asymptote
Which we want to call, you know full adult human intelligence
In contrast
Humans don't seem to be built this way. We our minds seem to be built as world modelers from the start
And I'll say more about this, but from the very beginning
We have our minds and our brains and this is something that
Inherits shared with other animals and inherits from our evolutionary legacy seem to be built to model the world
And to deal with all kinds of incompleteness and uncertainty
And that means both in how in the the structure of the world
And our uncertainty over what's out there the current state as well as the the fundamental deeper laws
The causal laws of physics or how agents plan and so on
But we're built to engage these kinds of mental representations
As i'll as i'll show in a little bit the way in our group
We've modeled this for a long time is what we call the game engine in the head by analogy to say video game engines
That our brains and minds seem to be built with these kinds of resources for world modeling
You can see that this the the notion of world models that are used
Even not just in human adults, but in young children to coherently understand the world and deal with situations that are
Importantly out of distribution
Right and that's really key
The ways in which we perceive and learn about the world are not nearly as time to the distributions of our experience as
machine learning or function approximation
So here's some examples of different kind of self-driving system. These are
four-year-olds for the most part three four five-year-olds
In a genre of youtube videos, you can see one of them actually the video on the left
It's it's sort of the the video genre on youtube is like, you know
My four-year-old driving for the first time and parents have put their kids behind the wheels of golf carts or tractors or cars or trucks
And just go at it and they video from the side or from next to them
and
You know, you could question the rationality of the adults who are putting their kids in the situation and then putting the videos online
But there's a certain basic rationality that the four-year-old has
Even though they haven't been in the situation before the systems that their mind has built through evolution and the last couple of years
The first few years of their experience
Allow them to handle this totally new kind of perceptual information
The world's going by them at a high speed and they're in control in some way
But they can generalize from their from from their experience because the the nature of their generalization
Is their mind's models of the world and those transfer to these new situations?
Of course, their new things they have to learn about exactly how the steering wheel works
But they can learn those very quickly too because the learning is grounded in their world model
So fundamentally, I think what we have is the is a contrast between the scaling thesis
of deep learning and today's ai
And what you could call the original scaling route that human intelligence follows what we might call
Growing up as opposed to scaling up and I want to contrast
Three points, which I think are really important for understanding
In general our intelligence and the contrast between ai and machine learning and especially the role that language and language models play in
So three points that are that are fundamental to the way today's ai is working based on deep learning one
That intelligence is seen as the end result of learning
We're learning starts with some simple very general and in some ways dumb mechanisms
associative learning prediction, you know in some way
But the idea is if you scale that up enough you have the surprising emergent phenomenon that now we start to call intelligence
um
The the problem is though, I mean either you call it a problem or you can call it just the way things work
But there's some remarkable kind of generalization
But it still is going to depend on similarity to training data
And its ability to go beyond the training distribution is is weak and unpredictable compared to when you're in distribution
Um, this is true whether you're talking about perception or other forms of higher level cognition
But especially thinking things that we recognize as forms of reasoning planning problem solving and so on
The the sort of thing that we've never seen in any computer vision system
But we're starting to see some interesting kind of approximation to in language models
Crucially that in machine learning thinking derives from language
Because it's only the data of language not the data of pixels that conveys information really about human thoughts
Which makes sense again humans have always used language as our main medium to express our thoughts to others
Just like what we're doing right now in giving talks like this, right?
um
But crucially thinking requires language data and even carefully cleaned and curated language data
Our colleagues who are at the big ai companies can tell us a lot more about this or rather
Maybe they can't tell us about this but they can tell us that they can't tell us about
And those of us who've worked with this know the importance of having the right kinds of language data as well as the right reinforcement data
Okay, so contrast this with human minds and especially human children
Our intelligence if for our intelligence
It's not just the thing that is at the end result of all of our learning although we do
You know babies are not in some important way not as intelligent as human adults we would like to say
But human intelligence is is built in in some form from the start. It's the foundation of learning. It's not just the end state
It's what's there and the the learning mechanisms that let you learn so much from so little
Okay, and we saw some of that in virginia's talk and you know
I think the the field of human cognitive development is a testament to this or what I was just showing from the four-year-olds
Is another example but in other work that i'm not going to talk about here
We've done a lot of work trying to model the core knowledge of even you know
12-month-old or 10-month-old babies and there's important ways in which they have a common sense understanding of the world
That is in in in significant ways. It's not all built in but in significant ways
It seems to be present even even in two and three month olds. Okay
um
As a result of our built-in capacity for modeling the world our generalization is based on the fit of our mental models
It's not about the training data. Okay data is important. We improve our models. We grow models
We can make new models from data, but what accounts for generalization and what drives generalization is not similarities to the data
But the fit of our world models and their ability to be flexible and themselves to be generalized
And crucially thinking isn't the thing that comes at the end state as an emergent property of modeling language
But rather thinking is there from the start and it's the basis for language
It's the basis for why human children construct language so robustly and resiliently and again there
I'm referring to
By using that word resilience to some of the ideas that virginia talked about in her talk and susan golden meadow has talked about
I urge everyone to watch her rumelhardt prize talk where she talks about this as well
This idea that as we saw in susan's work and annie sangus's work with nicaraguan sign language
That you know children who grow up who grow up without
Any language input?
It's not just about the poverty the stimulus in the traditional linguistic sense
But you grow up with deaf without sign language input and you create in some form your own personal proto language
Or at least a way of communicating that has hierarchical symbolic structure
And then you bring a few such children together and within the span of a couple of generations
They've created a whole new language from scratch. Okay, so it's very clear from data like that
That humans are built to think and we're built with an
A desire to understand and to under to be understood to express our thoughts
In some form and share them with others in our as our social partners
And that's you know, there's nothing I think more fundamental to
To understand if you want to understand where our intelligence comes from
So what we've been trying to do in our work is to try to capture the human growing up scaling root in computational terms
And it starts with this idea of probabilistic inference and
Expected value decision-making on top of world models, you know informally
I would say and like many others that thinking not just in human brains
But in brains and in many other animals is about making good guesses and bets not about the next
Data thing you're going to see not about the next token or the next pixel or set of pixel values
But about the world what's going to happen in the world and how
It might depend on your actions or the actions of others or how you might be able to change the world to change those
dependencies causal and counterfactual reasoning and then having some sense of what you'd like to see happen
Or and what you'd not like to see happen or what could really cost you your life or
Be hugely valuable and making good bets about how to act and what to think about next
fundamentally this classic idea of
effectively rationality that
You know, you could say our minds and brains are the original sources of this idea through evolution
Being constructed to do this kind of computation
In our work and this is the stuff we've been doing with language models builds on this
We've been using the idea of probabilistic programs, which is a
family of mathematical languages and actual programming languages and platforms
To embody this idea basically take this conceptual idea of rational world modeling inference of decision
And turn it into practical engineering terms that can be models of human minds as well as more human like ai
And I don't have time to give a whole introduction to probabilistic programs
But you know, you can think of it as a kind of catch-all phrase or a complicated suitcase phrase just like neural network
Packages a number of different things together, but probabilistic programs are formalisms
For combining what I think are several of the best ideas about intelligence that have come up through through a number of
You know decades in the field that includes neural networks modern probabilistic programming languages
Like gen from vikash man singha's group who I mentioned before at mit or pyro
That was developed by originally a group at uber ai that noah goodman
Another collaborator of ours helped to start along with a number of others
you know
In many ways build on languages like pie torch
Or tensor flow the languages that support modern deep learning and that allow you to construct really complex but end to end differentiable
Functions for approximation or other purposes
But that's not the most important part the most important part are building on the idea of symbolic languages for expressing abstract knowledge
for modeling the world
that is
You know across many areas of science and engineering
consistently the strongest most powerful toolkit we've had for building coherent models to
To understand the world are various forms of symbols
And then the third idea is the probabilistic one using those symbolic languages to express probabilistic models where you can be uncertain about
Everything and in a in a turing computational sense
You can be uncertain about the state of the world right now or more abstractly how the world works
How the different kinds of data that you're getting perceptual or others are connected to the underlying state of the world
And then to be able to do joint inference about all those different sources of uncertainty as the basis for perception
reasoning planning learning and so on
And probabilistic programs bring those things together
I'll say a little bit about how that toolkit works as well as then how once you learn language
The ability to externalize and internalize thoughts that are produced by these kinds of probabilistic programs basically
That transforms things in fundamental ways and here, you know, less people think that i'm just a
Deep learning or a llm skeptic or something
I you know, again, I find neural language models and the the long tradition of distributional statistical learning
In language that they build on to be really important and in the work that we've been doing we've been using
large language models or in many by today's standards
I might even say small language models to capture this actually
So I think this is a place where the you know, I would not say that you want to think about human minds
It's llms or or transformers all the way down nothing like that
But the kinds of things that are going on in distributional sequence learning
Could be a way to capture some aspects of how language grounds in these tools for mental modeling and and also
enriches and extends it
So, I mean just very briefly for people who aren't familiar with this idea
There, you know, for a couple of decades now I and and many colleagues
Students former students a number of others who are very interested in what you could call the Bayesian approach to cognition
Have been using this general toolkit of probabilistic inference over structured symbolic models
To capture many aspects of mental models and I just this is a plug for a book that's coming
forthcoming edited by tom griffith's nick shader and myself and with many many other contributors
And it'll be coming later this year from mit press
But it's it's part textbook part research monograph and just showing how this toolkit can be used to
Capture to both explain in a principled and you know, actually understandable way
But also to quantitatively predict and model behavioral data across so many different ways in which our minds model the world
Just to illustrate one which i'll come back to in the context of language in a minute
An area that we've done a lot of work on is intuitive physics
As as a kind of probabilistic inference and the particular kinds of intuitive physics
We're thinking about are in these complex seed understanding cases, which again not coincidentally
I think are also really interesting in classic settings for studying grounded language
So for example, if I show you a
Scene of a bunch of blocks think like jenga blocks stacked up in various ways
Some of these images might look very stable others might look unstable and I can ask you a question
How likely do you think this stack of blocks is to fall under gravity?
And we can model that by having a a structured world model which consists of basically 3d object models
And then causal models of how though of how those underlying 3d scenes give rise to images
That's like a graphics program basically the computer graphics is a way of writing programs that generate images
From those underlying 3d world models
But then there's also these physics programs and again here I mentioned game engines
So game engine style physics simulators capture a lot of aspects of effectively real world
But common sense physics in ways that hack hack Newtonian or actual
True scientific physics in all sorts of ways to be efficient
But to a pretty good job of capturing
What we expect to happen in the world which makes sense because we're the ones playing the video games and they're designed for us
So by doing probabilistic inference to infer the input to a graphics program given the output
Which is the image you can do a lot of 3d perception and then by doing probabilistic forward simulation
You can imagine what might happen next. It could also be conditional on your action
So the same toolkit could be applied to a much less familiar sort of judgment
Like imagine I have these scenes of red and yellow blocks on a table
And what if I bump the table hard enough to knock some of the blocks onto the floor?
Will you knock off more red blocks or yellow blocks?
So the first judgment the one about how likely the stack of blocks to fall
I mean anyone who's played jenga or anybody who's ever been a kid probably has built things
If you're a professional builder, you have a lot of other intuitions
But you know, that's very familiar the question on the right is one that unless you've seen me talk about this
You probably never thought about it's not something you have direct experience about you can't learn it from feedback
How to answer that question?
But I can use my language to give you that question as well as the other relevant world knowledge
And then you can reason about it and the models that we build can capture both the familiar judgments of like
How likely the stack is to fall as well as these novel judgments
Relatively equally well
So these scatter plots are examples of the kind of data and modeling that we've done in our lab for a long time
On the y-axis we're plotting the average human judgments of let's say on one to seven scale how stable or unstable the blocks are
and on the x-axis the average
Result of doing a small number of probabilistic simulations where we imagine running forward
Game-style physics a few time steps with uncertainty about exactly where the blocks might be and how the physics works because we don't
There's are all things that our minds don't fully know
The same kind of model can be used to answer these red and yellow questions. So just to illustrate this
If we take one of these
Scenes and we reconstruct it in a game-style physics engine and we simulate a bump of the table
So there's one simulation on the right. I'll show you another simulation with a harder bump
Okay, and you can see watch it again that different things happen
in these two simulations
But it doesn't really matter which one of those you ran to answer the question, right?
I mean you look at the scene also and it's very clear from the beginning that if I bump the table
Relatively hard. It's going to probably be mostly yellow blocks on the floor. How do you do that?
Well in our model you only need to run
One or a small number of these simulations to answer the question at the grain of intuitive physics
And you don't need to run it very long. You could stop it now and you already know the answer
Okay
So a small number of short incomplete simulations is the basis for these pretty
Quantitative models and they've also been used in robotics to actually predict and and be able to get for example a robot to
Learn to play the game genka, but learn from a very small amount of realistic human experience
The same kind of idea has been very
impactful
I think even more impactful in intuitive psychology
Where we and many others this there's work that I've done with a number of students and my colleague at mit rebecca sacks
But especially I would highlight work from chris baker and julia har edinger who did quantitative modeling here
Going back years with us
julian continued chris is now working on self-driving cars and industry julian
is now working on
It's now a professor at Yale where he's he's extended on this kind of approach in many areas of social and communicate with social cognition and communication
in really interesting ways
And many other colleagues here
I and I should mention also though I didn't
I forgot to mention this before the intuitive physics work started in our group
More than 10 years ago with pete patalia and jess hamrick and others
And they are now actually both working at deep mind google deep mind working on various interesting kinds of deep learning approaches
For both intuitive physics and all sorts of real-world physics that matter like climate modeling. That's where pete's current focuses
I won't go into the details on the bayesian theory of mind
But the basic idea is again, there's a program that now describes
Not necessarily how actual minds and brains works, but our mental models of other minds how the actions we see agents take
We interpret them as the effect of planning programs that take as input
The our minds representations of their beliefs and desires
And by seeing how agents act and change the state of the world and modeling also their perception process
Which leads to belief formation and updating we can model many aspects of how people understand
Other minds especially in what you might call these sort of physically grounded and perceptual scenarios the kinds that you can also
Study in young babies like in the experiments. I'm showing here from gargay chibra. Kylie hamlin paul bloom and others
Um the the intuitive psychology case is especially interesting
Because in work that we've done like in this paper with uh, brendan lake tomer olemann sam gershman that helped to set some of the
Current stage of debates between deep learning and more cognitive approaches to ai
Where we put about a challenge back in 2016 and 2017
For the the deep learning ai world about how to think about the kinds of inductive biases mental model
Materials that seem to be built into human minds and the learning mechanisms that build on those
We highlighted both intuitive physics and intuitive psychology in the famous sparks of agi paper showing again some of the most
earliest glimpse into some of the surprising things that gpd4 seemed to be able to do
bubeka and colleagues also highlighted intuitive physics and intuitive psychology and then in a recent paper from eric schultz's group
Which is kind of forms a a three-part story here and it continues as as i know bushoff and and schultz and colleagues
Continue to work on this area and we also do
Is to now in the era of these multimodal language and vision models like i showed you at the beginning
We can go and take on all these tasks like whether it's block tower intuitive physics things or agents moving around in the world and interpreting
As julia harr edinger called it the naive utility calculus of their rewards and costs
And give language models or multimodal models the same kinds of stimuli and questions that we give people
And as schultz and colleagues showed
In some of the intuitive physics settings, they're kind of okay. They're not great
In the intuitive theory of mind ones they fail altogether. That's a quote from their paper
So as an example, this is this is work that julia harr edinger did as part of his phd thesis with myself and laura schultz
Um where we call these the astronaut studies where people would see an agent an astronaut on some planet
Who would start at a certain point and have a home base that they had to get to and they would follow some path along
This the surface of the planet
They could just go straight to their home base or they could take a different a not straight path
Um crucially there were various objects that they could pick up that could either be positively valuable or aversive to them
And we asked people based on the path
How likely do you think that the agent likes or doesn't like one of these objects?
And also there are different terrains and the terrains could be more or less costly
And by showing people different maps different configurations of objects based terrain and different paths
You could get very interesting rich inferences about what about what the agent both wants and
What the rewards assigned to the different objects are as well as the costs for moving around on the terrain
So here's an example of some of the stimuli from one experiment
Just to show you the kind of variation and then in each of these cases
We can ask people to make four judgments or three or four depending on how many kinds of terrain
And that's what's shown here. These are these are the actually the predictions of the model
Z scored for the relative cost for the different kinds of terrain and the relative value for the different kinds of objects
And we're assuming that the agent basically takes in a
of rational efficient plan trying to maximize reward
Minus cost where there's a small cost for each step, but especially costly when you travel over certain kinds of terrain
So seeing the path you can make inferences about how the agent has rewards and costs
And then when you ask people to make the same judgments, they line up almost perfectly
This is just one of many experiments that julian did showing what is really a remarkable quantitative
Match and but but by a model that isn't just fit to data
There's a little bit of fitting but it's mostly based on
Thinking about what are the core concepts of theory of mind that people like I mentioned before like gargay and chibra
Have studied even in very young infants pre-verbal infants infants who can't even walk
And barely just able to reach for things themselves yet
They still have these ideas these intuitions about efficient inference and and use those it seems
I mentioned sherry lou's work who was a
PhD student at harvard a few years ago with this velki who worked with tomer omen also in me
To show those same kinds of things work in babies sherry's now doing amazing stuff extending that in a new lab at johns hopkins
Um, so these these are cases where this kind of probabilistic program model works really well, but just a pure language model
Uh is basically at chance zero correlation with human judgments, although quite good at telling you things like the background color of the scene
Okay, so in the last part of the talk having sort of set the stage for how are our
Human thinking seems to work and how we can model this in ways that are explanatory
Understandable and quite quantitatively predictive using these probabilistic programs. Let's understand where language comes into picture
I don't think that a pure machine learning transformer approach like the ones we've been talking about
Are on track to give a human level or certainly a human like account of how it works
But I do think the ideas of sequence modeling statistical distribution learning that you see having
such great success in llms
Even perhaps on a smaller scale could say something important about how language comes into the picture
So this here is the at the beginning
I talked about this archive paper the word models to world models paper
From line along Gabe grand and colleagues and that's what i'm going to be talking about here is how we've been using bringing these tools together
But a key ingredient is this I would say the modern return of the language of thought hypothesis
You know made famous by jerry fodor, but obviously with a history that goes back hundreds if not thousands of years
But in the number of recent papers
And proposals from various groups the idea that again that there's some kind of
Not necessarily single language, but but abstract symbolic languages, which could be general or also
Created and constructed domain specific languages
Some kind of abstract symbolic language is seems to be a powerful way to think about human thinking abstraction
concept learning and so on
And the particular kind of languages of thought that we've been thinking about are
What noah goodman and toby gersenberg and I called the probabilistic language of thought
So this is the idea of using probabilistic programming languages the technical tool
I talked about before
To to formalize in a cognitive setting a certain kind of hypothesis of a language of thought
But one that is focused on modeling the world
Not just possible worlds, but probable worlds and where the the symbolic language can also express ways of conditioning and query
So that we can ask and answer the kinds of questions that our minds do and that
We might we might want for example any kind of general ai system to do
So if you want to learn more about the probabilistic language of thought check out our chapter in the conceptual mind
This is one of the margiles and laurence
Readers or the web book probabilistic models of cognition, which which has examples of the kinds of models
I'm going to be talking about
Not with language models though the new thing is to take advantage of llms and specifically the fact that
Most llms these days are trained not only on natural language
But on on programming languages and source code
Namely programming languages like all the ones we're probably familiar with that are designed to be read and written by humans
And not just machines and so they're written in a very english like way
Or natural language like way, you know linguists have long pointed out
Sometimes the differences between natural languages and programming languages, but from a certain perspective
They're a lot more similar than they are different
A hierarchical structure syntax and even just much of the lexicon, you know natural languages
They're not just commented or programming languages are not just commented in natural language
But functions variables data structures are named using english for the most part
Okay, so that's a very powerful data source that allows
Some kind of statistical sequence to sequence model for predicting and translating between streams sequential streams to effectively learn to translate
From english or any other natural language into programming languages of thought and that includes probabilistic programming
So the idea of this paper what we call rational meaning construction. That's the name of this
Is is a particular thesis on how language is understood and perhaps also how it might be produced and learned
Although our focus here is on language understanding
And thinking about the relation between language of language and thought in that context
By thinking what we think of as like the core original notion of thinking is what I've been talking about for the for the first part of the talk
Which is the idea of having a
Structured probabilistic model of the world conditioning it on observations and then
And then drawing samples of underlying latent states and future states
Okay, that's thinking from this standpoint
And then understanding language is effectively translating from natural language
Into a probabilistic language of thought that's used to define and condition and query the probabilistic world model
So we're going to exploit the the property of these
LLMs to translate from natural language to code in a way that might be familiar if you've tried using them to code
But it's different in some key ways in particular
We're not going to be just asking our LLM to write a whole bunch of code at least not to start
But we're going to be focusing on the sentence level and what is meaning at the sentence level
It's something like trying to infer a line of code in a mental programming language
that is your best understanding of
The meaning by which we just mean the thought that the person who's uttering that sentence is trying to convey
Okay, and the the LLMs in this case can represent that meaning construction function
Okay in ways that have some very interesting properties
So i'll just illustrate this with a classic example from the probabilistic language of thought literature the so-called Bayesian tug-of-war
So just to ground this imagine that you're reasoning about a situation
Like for example, uh
Various games of tug-of-war various people symbolized by colored shirts here are facing off against each other
And let's just take one person. Let's just say this is a
Guy named jack and you might say well, how strong do you think jack is I haven't shown you any information?
So your best guess might be just average. Okay
Now, uh, suppose I give you some other information
Like um, or I should say here. So here are a few samples, you know, I might say average
Maybe it's a little less than average
If we're talking about MIT students, you may just pick the MIT average
But now I could give more information like suppose, you know that jack beat leo in a game of tug-of-war
So that might move your arrow up from the MIT average because well, you know
People who are who are stronger might be more likely to win than people who are weaker somehow. Okay
I could give you some more information
Like leo had just won 10 previous matches as well. So that means you might think leo's pretty strong and jack must be even stronger
So your arrow goes way up
But suppose I told you well leo sometimes it doesn't pull as hard as they really could
So maybe maybe leo was just getting a little lazy when leo faced jack. So it might go down a little bit
But then leo single-handedly beat a team with jack and tom on it. Okay. So now you think okay
Well leo was probably lazy before jack. Maybe isn't that strong
Since leo when they wanted to could beat both jack and tom. Okay
So the point is in a classic example of non-monotonic reasoning your inference about this one aspect of the world jack strength
It's going up and down as you get various information. So we'd like to understand how that thinking process works how
Updating your beliefs based on linguistic evidence linguistically expressed evidence works. Okay, that's the starting point of this paper
And the idea is to use in this case
We're using the the probabilistic programming language church which is based on a dialect of lisp or scheme
So there's a lot of parentheses and i'm not going to be able to unpack all the language
But hopefully you can get the basic idea that we write we define functions that describe
probabilistic distributions on
Strength laziness and so on all work through this and that's you know, that's been that's well-attested work
That's been very good. You know, it's basically the the general toolkit for doing the kind of probabilistic intuitive
Mental modeling that I showed you with two to physics and intuitive psychology, but here we're doing it for this kind of novel domain
It's not there's no core domain that infants are born with for tug of war
But we can write a model like this to capture what adults in our culture at least might think
And then the key new thing here is to understand how to to ground language in these mental models
So this is where we're going to model the translation of a statement in english like jack one against leo or a question
Like how strong is jack into lines of code that support probabilistic updating and querying in this language
And this these the meaning functions, which will be implemented by the neural network here
other the
Large or even small language model
Um capture various interesting ideas that have been proposed
You know, I don't have time to review this history but proposed in different eras of linguistics and thinking about
How to think about meaning how to think about concepts and you know, I it's it's a it's a very rich literature
That I'd be happy to try to discuss if we have time during the question period
Okay, um, but the hypothesis here is that maybe these distributional language code models can implement some
human like perhaps approximation to this meaning function
Um
And again, crucially, it's it's we're not trying to now capture like to learn patterns in data in the in in the world
We're trying to learn patterns in our thinking and how thought is expressed in language
So it's a more modular problem
It which I think is better suited to the way language actually works in the human brain, right?
It's there's a delimited part of our brain. That is a language processing network
Strokes or other lesions there can really impact your language ability without impacting your general thinking ability
And you know, it's a relatively late evolutionary addition to us to a brain structure
Which shares a lot with other non-human primates, for example
And so it's it's that that modularity. I think is also really important here
So again, just to unpack how this works
You have a probabilistic program that describes these concepts
That I can just I can describe to you in language in this way
But to the model right now, they're just given in code and I'm not and they just describe for example that
You know players strength is drawn from a gaussian distribution players can occasion be lazy
When you when you're lazy it cuts your effective strength in half
And the strength of the team is that some of the total strength that they pull that the members pull with at any one time
And the stronger pulling team wins. That's basically what this is now for now
We'll just assume that that's you have that kind of mental
Model of a tug of war game
And we'll just talk. How do you update your release language?
And the basic way of doing it is that we're using what I would call now a medium language model
We used open ai's codex, which was the first widely used code llm pretty small by today's standards much smaller than gpt4
Kind of like an early version of gpt 3.5
To translate from a sentence in english like this into what in church the probabilistic programming language is called a condition statement
It just expresses the constraint on possible worlds that while the underlying
Define statements define stochastic or probabilistic functions, which give you distributions
Probability distributions on possible worlds. This says we're going to restrict our probability distribution
Which is like our prior to a posterior just those worlds that are consistent with jack beating in one match leo
okay
And then similarly a quest to a query statement like how strong is jack turns into this worry
Which is which the probabilistic programming language then basically
Evaluates it draws samples from possible worlds consistent with the condition and generated from that prior on the left
And and checks what the strength is and then just kind of counts up those distributions
So it's a kind of probabilistic mental simulation the same effectively the same or a generalization of what we were doing
You like those intuitive physics examples and from this one piece of data jack beating leo
You can see the posterior updates from the prior so jack is stronger than average
If I say oh jack also beat alex or proceeded to claim victory from alex that turns into another condition
And that updates the posterior even more so now while jack's a lot stronger than average
Even working as a team leo and alex still could not be jack. Wow now jack's even stronger when you add in that conditioning statement
So each again the where the llm is coming in here
Is it's just it's just adding in the the statements into the language of thought and then we're running inference in our probabilistic programming language to give these answers
It's worth and this is again, especially if we want to understand what I think is
The way forward to thinking about how meaning and language works in humans and where l lm's can come into the mix
What's what's really powerful about?
Neuro language models here
As ways to parameterize a meaning function is the ways that they can pick up on statistics context pragmatics
metaphor
Um semantic associations all the things that in many ways were most appealing in connectionism like distributed content addressable
Uh associate of memory and distributed representations of graded semantic associations
So for example, the llm will translate jack won against leo
Which into this statement which looks like a fairly transparent semantic parse of that natural language
But it'll make basically the same semantic parse of a sentence which on its surface
And and in traditional syntax, you know language structuralities looks rather different, right? The syntax here is more complicated
I'm not actually using the word win, but
In the context the relevant aspect of meaning for thought here is the same namely. This is just another way. It may be more poetic way
Or dramatic way to say that jack won against alex and the model knows that automatically
It doesn't have to be specially prompted or trained for that using its associative memory properties
It's also distributional. These are probabilistic models not on worlds
But on strings and in this case they're probabilistic models on strings in our mental programming language
so they can
Bring into you know bring in classic notions of vagueness if I say jack is strong or very strong
I'm not telling you exactly how strong jack is but you might interpret that as a distribution
On different condition statements saying well jack strength is is greater than some threshold
But I don't know what that threshold is but it's probably pretty big remember this in this case
The mean is 50 and the standard deviation 20 so 80 is you know
One and a half standard deviations above the mean and the idea is this is again like in scalar
Adjectives it's basically saying I'm conditioning on the idea that jack is greater than some threshold
But I but I could be uncertain about what that threshold is and even metaphorical things like if I say jack is pretty strong
And ben is a beast right in this context
It's reasonable to interpret ben is a beast as as saying saying ben is really really strong
You know 80 where jack was maybe 60 or greater in a different context if i'm talking about you know
Whether you should date someone and I say ben is a beast, you know, then i'm probably saying stay away
right
So that that both metaphor sort of context sensitive metaphorical interpretation is the kind of thing that this meaning function is very good at
um, I'll mostly just skip over this but in work with ben lytkin and and
Leo and gape and others we've we've done and this is really all ben's work some very nice quantitative studies
Of showing that these contextual aspects of understanding of strength
In in the kind of tug-of-war context can match very nicely not always but in a lot of cases very nicely with human judgment
so it's suggesting that the distributional aspects of
um meaning that we're capturing here are at least somewhat
Not psychologically real at least consistent with the judgments that people make
Okay, so so but mostly what i've done with this example is just to try to show you how this kind of framework can work
To be a way of implementing what is in some sense a classical idea that language isn't
That directly the medium of thought at least the only one
But it's a way of expressing and communicating thoughts internalizing and externalizing them
Okay, and that statistical distributional mechanisms can be a powerful way of learning that
The mappings from the signs and symbols that we externalize
To the to an internal compositional structured language of our thought
Now a lot of what goes on in this paper and i'll just show you one or two examples
Such as work with sed zhong in an intuitive physics domain or some intuitive psychology work with lan xing and shen or
Tan shi shen
Is showing how we can take the same kinds of things that i showed you in the first part of the talk
And effectively reconstruct them, but now in a world's worlds that are just described by language
So to manage it take that task of the red and yellow thing where before i was showing you the image of a scene
And then i was using language to describe a question
But what if i just use language to describe the whole world, right?
So if i didn't show you an image i just described
What's there, you know in many ways, but but but we're still going to do a a mental simulation a probabilistic mental simulation in a physics engine
There's many cases, you know in our daily life where we use language to describe the physical world as we experience it
It can be extremely expressive very complimentary often to you know images or photos
Um, it has vagueness and uncertainty and that's interesting
So we might describe a scene that like imagine a table and there's some blocks on it
There's some red blocks in the center
There are many tall stacks of yellow blocks on the side of the table if the table is bumped hard enough
So we ask the same question but for scenes that are described in language
And then people make a graded judgment the same one to seven graded judgment of is it more likely to be red or yellow blocks?
And so when we can test this again the same kind of quantitative study with
large number of participants all online all just reading stuff
With different kinds of language expressing exact as well as approximate number
Approximate quantifiers logical quantifiers vagueness like the stacks could be tall or very tall
And and different kinds of spatial relations and across many different stimuli
We we mix up more or less complex sentences using these different kinds of language
And in each case we're using again a relatively small
LLM to translate sentence by sentence into
statements for conditioning and querying in our probabilistic language of thought
Then we run a small number of mental simulations in this case in a 2d physics engine
Compute the outputs and compare those with people and what i'm showing you here is again the same kind of scatterplot
I showed before but on the vertical axis are again our human judgments and on the x-axis now are the model
Or the predictions of this language informed thinking model
So it looks a lot like what I showed you before these are the judgments from the battalion all work on the red and yellow task
We're not we're here the model was given a visual scene people were given visual scenes
And the model did that same kind of probabilistic mental simulation in the physics engine
But in the in the current work on the left
Again, the scene description is constructed from language using the tools that i've shown you by conditioning a prior on scenes
Okay, and the main point is just that the models fit human judgments pretty well in both cases and about equally well
All right, which is which is interesting
We can also compare with just a sort of zero shot or a few shot baseline llm
So these are language models, which don't have an explicit mental model of physics or any doing explicit simulation
And they are are much worse fits to people
Okay, this is this on the what the high up here on the y-axis is
Distance and distribution from human distribution of responses to the various models
The blue one is the rational meeting construction model and you can do a similar thing in the intuitive psychology domain
Like for example in the settings that I showed you with julien harenger's work
This is work that uh lans ying and shen did i won't go into the details, but again
We can describe worlds with various
Goal objects that an agent might have and constraints like you have to go through doors the doors could be locked
You have to use keys that could be a red key that could unlock the red door
And so on people could be told either that you know
You need a key of the right color to open each door of the same color
Or you could be told weird things like
Keys only unlock doors of other colors
Okay, um, you know in these kinds of uh worlds again
The rational meeting construction model does a very good job of capturing people's judgments
For some kinds of judgments easy cases even gpt 3.5 does reasonably well gpt 4 does better
But as the situation gets more complex or unusual things change and break down like especially if
We say well in this world keys only unlock doors of different colors
That's an easy thing to say to somebody and you have to change your mental model
But when you do something like that gpt 3.5 becomes anti correlated with people and gpt 4 just go drops from being highly correlated to just being a chance
So these are examples of the ways in which you know going out of distribution from our training experience
If we're just using a machine learning function approximation approach, which is remarkable as those systems like gpt 4r
That's what they're doing
But ways in which if the function approximation is just approximating a much more modular translation function
And building on our mental model tools. We can just do much better
The last thing i'll just talk about very briefly is you know what is
Any work like this has to raise more interesting questions
If if anything like this is right on the right track, then it's it's not answering
At this point the most interesting questions, but just raising them and perhaps highlighting ways you might get at them
So in all the work i've been doing in in for a couple of decades now in probabilistic inference in mental models
You start by showing how you can do inference with a mental model, but then you have to ask where do you get it from
Now learning from experience is one thing and i've done a lot of work and others in our group and many other
Colleagues a lot of that book i mentioned with tom griffiths and nick shader is about how we can learn using hierarchical bays and probabilistic programs learn abstract
Programs by doing inference over the space of programs to make sense of our data
Maybe even small amounts of data
But much of our learning probably the most powerful form of human learning comes through language more abstract
Generic language as many folks in cognitive science cognitive development
Have shown
So the power of language not only to update your beliefs, but actually to give you new world models is really
Incredible and that's probably the most that that's the real human singularity there right is the ability of language to let us
Learn and think about situations that we haven't directly experienced. I mean think about the tug of war for example
I mean, I don't know if you're like me
I've maybe done one or two tug of war games at my
Most of my knowledge about tug of war or my beliefs at least don't come from my direct experience
They come from things maybe people told me about analogous situations
And and more generally many of our mental models and our intuitive theories come from what people tell us
All right
So the same approach that we talked about for updating beliefs from language can also be used to acquire new mental models
But here what's going on is we're we're modeling how somebody might explain to you
The way this tug of war works and in fact in our experiments with humans and in the in the toby gerstenberg and noah goodman and
colleagues did
This is exactly what we do would tell people
Um about how this work people have various strengths it can vary from person to person
And then now we're using the llm to translate
Those say sentences in english that are generic sentences about the domain describing the world model
We want our participants to use
Into the same kind of probabilistic program code, but now these are defined statements
So these are not these don't condition on a specific a specific world, but they define the general distribution on worlds
But again, they're contextual they're distributional
There could be different ways of understanding the vagueness in language
But the basic idea is that we can describe a world model in english and then the code llm
Can construct that world model. So all the defined statements now are constructed
They're not exactly the ones that we use in the original paper
But they have the same functional role and they can support the same kinds of inferences
So it's just just showing you the way we can I think go towards one of the most interesting ways that language informs our thinking
Not just as a way to convey specific beliefs about situations
But new but new world models and in some recent most recent work that's still in progress with tyler brook wilson
Katie collins and a number of the others I mentioned here tyler is a is a brilliant philosopher who recently graduated from MIT
And he's actually just just accepted a faculty job at Yale. So he'll be at Yale in a in a year or so
But together with with tyler and others
And tyler's thesis goes into some early stages of this
We've talked about we've been exploring the ways that the same approach can support
Constructing new models, even if I don't explicitly tell you in language how the world works
But just by again using your associative memory and marshaling implicit knowledge to construct a model of a new situation
So I could tell you about a relay race and I'm not tell the relay race is like a new domain
I'm not really telling you how races work. I'm just giving you some information
But we're exploring ways in which the LLM can
Can be queried to construct possible background knowledge
And write probabilistic program code that can be suitable for reasoning about this domain
Just on its own the LLM isn't enough
But you have to do some reasoning about the models that it suggests
And then those models when suitably
Reason to put upon can support novel reasoning in this domain and even sensible updating
So we're really getting you know, at least demos of steps towards
Computational models that can capture the richness of how we are able to think about new situations
Even ones that we haven't really thought about very much before or that we haven't been explicitly told how to think about
but using the combination of
Language the associative knowledge that's in it and an underlying ability for constructing probabilistic models of the world and updating
I'm the last thing I just want to leave you with is a set of thoughts about
You know, ridiculously
It is it is the last thing
But I think this will set up some of the discussion with with virginia and others too
Which is many people in cognitive science, whether in linguistics or other areas
Engaged in meaning have been interested in what you could call, you know a unified account of meaning and what we're trying to at least
Point towards steps towards this with the framework. I talked about
just to just to again
Raise controversial points for discussion if you like
um, but the idea that we can capture the meaning of a word in context as well as more generally as
Effectively, it's like you might think of it as a form of dynamic semantics if you're familiar with this
But the meaning being in in context in a discourse the incremental contribution to the probability distribution over
PLOT expressions in the problem that we're thinking about with a problem in discussion
And the meaning of a word or phrase or sentence or other unit of language in general
Is a is a higher order stochastic function that can take as input a discourse context and return as output a meaning in context
And the idea is that if we think about the different approaches
These are just four
You know traditional ways of thinking about meaning and language which all have great value and have often been seen as being competitors
Ways in which we can really bring them together ways in which the PLOT ideas that we've talked about
Can integrate the compositional logical aspects of meaning that formal semantics and other areas in the language of thought tradition have emphasized
As well as in the context of probabilistic language of thought and mental models of the world can give a powerful form of grounding
That's not grounded in sense data
But in our models of the world that's what the PLOT does and the LLM or more generally a statistical distributional
Sequence models can capture both the distributional statistical aspects of meaning. It's the base that the
Both the sort of distributional usage approach, but also more general semantic association needed to make sense of language
So flexibly as well as some of the very flexible pragmatic communicative ways we use language
So I'll just leave it at that. Okay. Okay. Could you turn off your share, please? Yes
First of all, thank you very much
There's not a chance in the world that I'm going to forget Virginia this time and I'll tell you why
Because I'm gobsmacked at how many different areas you're an expert in and so anyway, here's another one
uh
Virginia valium from
CUNY hunter
It's all yours. Thanks
Josh that was such a great talk and so rich
In 10 minutes, which is how much time you and I have will only scratch the surface
So departing from the comments I sent you
with respect to the
Unified theory of meaning
Many years ago
Jerry Katz suggested that
The question what is meaning could be
Separated into questions like what is sameness of meaning? What is contradiction? What is anomaly?
What is entailment and so on?
And it occurs to me that it would be interesting to try this
To try your model to see just how well
It can detect
Synonomy contradiction anomaly and so on
Yeah, I think that's um, that's a great connection. I mean I I know a little bit about that
But I you're inspiring me to go back and reread and learn much more about it
I mean, I think just in the context of the last thing I said
The idea exactly that in a sense in this framework at least
What the statistical language model is doing is capturing the notion of sameness effectively because there the distribution on
Code in the probabilistic language of thought if that distribution is similar
And that can be measured in different ways then you might say well things
Have the same meaning either in context or in general because and that that distribution function can be contextualized or it can be
Made higher order. Okay, so that's really interesting, but it doesn't compute entailment or other
You know a conceptual or inferential relations those come from reasoning in the probabilistic language of thought
um
And yeah, I mean I think that's that would be great to explore that more see if that can account for
Unify it both account for the different set of phenomena and unify in that sense
Yeah, I think that would be really interesting to explore
um, so going back to
Some of the more mundane
Which I guess is upon
Aspects um the way that I'm understanding what you've
Said about how the theories
Intersect that is how llm's intersect with basian models
Is basically you're using the llm as a kind of tool
To translate from one vocabulary to another vocabulary. Is that accurate?
Yeah, I mean and that is at the most practical level. That's what we're doing. Um,
yeah
Okay, more about that, but let's let's go with that for now. Yes. Okay. Um
so
The critical difference that I see in what you're doing and what llm's are doing is the
Well, I guess there are two critical differences, but for me the most important one is the use of symbols
um, the other part is the basian
Mechanism, but let's separate them. So
When you put symbols in
To me you're putting a lot of content into the mechanism. Do you agree with that?
um, I agree that adding symbols adds a lot of content, but I think
And I again, I didn't have time to unpack all of this very well
I think but when you say you putting in symbols the in different different things that I'm talking about here
The you and the putting in are different, but yeah, but whenever you add in symbols that adds a lot of
Content and structure here. Yeah. Yeah content. Right. So I'm thinking about the implications of that for nativism
So it seems to me. This is a nativist theory
Um, I would say it is compatible with some forms of nativism that I find plausible
although none I don't have a horse in that game, but I
Through a lot of interactions with friends and colleagues like lisbelki susan carry many others
Come to find
Certain kinds certain aspects of nativism and conceptual nativism plausible especially in
Certain core domains that are shared with other animals
Like intuitive physics about objects that the world is three dimensional objects have some that there's some kind of
physical interactions
That are you know our bodies engage with and also some forms of intuitive psychology not necessarily higher order belief reasoning
But the idea of efficient action and that agents have goals and they pursue actions in the physical world
Grounded in physics to achieve their goals efficiently. Honestly, there's evidence
Again, sherry lou who did this work in spelki's lab and continue to build on it has really, you know
I mean, I was a striking evidence in three month olds
But it's every experiment with three month olds is very small and you know a lot needs to be built on
But as striking as it gets in three month olds
science
I'm showing that that aspects certain aspects of not only physics, but efficient goal directed action
Understanding seem to be present that doesn't mean they're innate
But at least they're not they're present way before language and probably build on some innate stuff
It's compatible with that notion
I'm not sure who that is but could you mute that was an accident. I think they just
Should have turned off their okay, but so so yeah, there's this idea that certain kinds of symbols
Are used in our framework to describe those some of those core systems
But we are in contrast to like a fedoria nativism which says all concepts are innate
In this in this framework here. I mean it or you could say in contrast, although some of uh,
I don't know what jerry would have actually said about this but people like paul patrowski have suggested
You know, maybe he would love it. I don't know but in in a rather different version of like some forms of radical
Conceptual nativism most of the concepts in this framework are not innate
They're written in a language of thought
That it that could be somehow innate or somehow bootstrapped through natural language
I find some of the ideas that that uh,
Susan carrey and lis spelti in their different ways along with jesse snettaker have developed their ways in which language acquisition
and
Mental languages of thought might bootstrap each other and many things in the kind of glitman tradition also I think are reflect that idea
But I so I I think we we are
We still need to show this this is like the most interesting thing to do
But to show ways in which the things I was showing at the very end could be could be used
To explain how and model how natural language can start off
Being grounded semantically and logically in a limited symbolic vocabulary of probable worlds that reflect core knowledge
But then that can support bootstrapping and introducing new concepts via those mechanisms
I was talking about at the end
Including new concepts, but also new domain theories that we get explicitly or implicitly through our linguistic interaction with
Other people who we think know more than us
Okay, um, that sounds great. Um
It also suggests to me that it is a highly modular
System even though it's also probabilistic
um, so it's probabilistic within each of these different modules
And depending on what you think the symbols are that you start with you can
Iterate what you think the modules of the mind are
Yeah, no, I think that's right
And I think you know, I think it's this framework is not a
On its own a proposal for how our minds start
But it can be used to instantiate and build and test some of them
And so that's I think that's right. It's it does suggest that you could have, you know, different
Sub-languages of thought for different domains
But crucially the picture that you get with adults from this is both in some ways like strikingly
Supermodular and in some other ways completely holistic
So the striking super modularity is that the actual reasoning that you do in is in a discourse when I'm thinking about a situation
And we're talking in a conversation is very modular if it might even be just
Specific to this context this what Tyler Brook Wilson calls bespoke model construction
This idea that we might construct a model on the fly to think about a particular situation
That that we're that's the last thing that we've been working on there
Is in some sense super modular because that model is is relatively small and all the inference. I'm doing is just here
so I so I
Side step or avoid the classic problems of what has made Bayesian inference intractable the idea that if I'm going to actually have
A distribution over all possible worlds. I could think about it update that
You know, that's completely intractable many people in the nativist tradition dan osherson and others have written about that
And this this is a a way around that or as Tyler puts it in his thesis
It's in a sense a kind of way to think about a solution certain kind of solution to the frame problem
So it's super modular, but it's also very holistic in the sense that the world knowledge that's used to construct that
Comes from like all the code you've ever written and all the semantic associations
And it's like a gigantic holistic almost quinian web of language and code
What we've sometimes called the github in the mind view
There's the game engine in the head the github in the mind like github is this
You know thing on the web which was crucial for training
Language code models and you can imagine your own mind has lots of chunks of code
Some of which are maybe innate many of which are not and natural language interweave with it
And and having a content addressable associative memory that can use that and and marshal out from that
relevant
symbolic probabilistic models that can be used to reason about a particular situation in some sense that's extremely holistic
And maybe is necessary to grapple with what is in you know very clearly some of the wholism of human cognition
So going back a few steps
The intuitive physics part
In principle
Animals could do that as well, right? Yes. So a chimp could have intuitive physics
Yeah, and joseph call and others have studied that a number of other
Amanda ced and other brothers had studied other non-human primates and we're actually collaborating
With erica cart mill and some others studying
non-human primates on intuitive physics and I know colleagues
Who are studying analogous kinds of intuitive physics in rats?
And I think even simpler organisms
Okay, so the difference between humans and
Other animals is going to be that language allows you to go further
Language allows you to go beyond intuitive physics
Whereas nothing is going to help these other animals go beyond intuitive physics
Yeah, I I think that's right. I mean again
I wouldn't say that all the all the mental models of other animals is just intuitive physics
They also have models of their social world like you know the chainy and save farce baboon metaphysics is mostly a social theory
But yeah, but I would say
Definitely that the key thing here and it's the real human singularity. I would say
Is that language allows us to construct to both enrich our intuitive physics to think about
Aspects of the physical world that are not initially intuitive to us and maybe still aren't
But also to construct things that just go totally beyond any any core domain that evolution gave us
Right
Okay, so one question that this brought up to me
Because what you're talking about are all the ways that humans are so good at what they do
um
But then there are ways that they're not so good at what they do
And far transfer is one of those examples
um
And there there are some things that are hard for people to learn
Or some places where it's hard to get from
A to z
Even though you think you've learned a
So there's a famous little story about someone going to their logic teacher
asking about
Understanding if a then b and the logic teacher spends a lot of time on that
And the student says
Okay, I think I get it
But we try it with r and s now
um
So that's something that just shouldn't occur, but it does occur
Uh, even with smart people
So like when you try to teach people about experimental design
It's hard for them to see confounds often
um, it's hard for them to
Get at what's wrong with some experimental design
And it's not that they don't have a general intelligence. It's not that they don't have some principles
but it's as if
What they've learned is just
Too far away as far as the the string of examples goes for them to get to to the next one
So I'm wondering how
On your system
those kinds of limitations would be modeled
Yeah, no, that's a that's a great point a great question and a great pointer. I think to work that
We could and should do more of so the the stuff I talked about at the very end, which is again this the work with
Tyler and uh, katie collins and
Lansing and and and very much with leo wang also
um
is
What we're what we're getting out there like is is again how we can
Describe a situation in language, maybe even very implicitly just start talking and then see if
See if this architecture can be used to construct a mental model needed to reason about that situation
And you could also make it better
More robust if I explicitly give you instructions as in the educational context you're talking about if I try to explain to someone
Logic or experimental design actually another collaborator on that project said zhong is actually very interested for his thesis
In how we learn like logic and learn to reason through language
But so we have you know, our framework is providing possibly a way to do that
but
In order for it to work at least in the current system
We do the kind of thing that lm folks are generally doing these days, which is some kind of few shot prompting
We prompt the system with examples of other mental models and language for describing them in
Related domains they could be similar or they could be further and what we already can see right is i mean
The interesting thing is can you generalize to new domains?
So our system is somewhat able to do that
But you know, this is a place where near or far transfer would be relevant at least so far
you know as you might expect you have to have some domain that's at least reasonably close
And for example, we're trying we could transfer from like a tug of war to a relay race or to some other sport setting
Or from a couple of sport settings to yet some new sport
um
Or you might transfer from a sport setting to like a math competition or to some other kind of thing
So if it really interesting ideas about abstraction and metaphor
Analogy some of the kinds of things that the the transfer literature has studied are going to be relevant here
We're just beginning but what you're pointing to is actually some set of phenomena and things we should really
Engage with and I expect you know at least based on our current system
It will definitely struggle sometimes with far transfer
Um, which be which might be because at that level, you know, I I I drew this contrast at the very beginning
between the pattern recognition approach
Data driven learning and the mental models approach
But at that level we are doing a kind of pattern recognition. It's just not patterns in the world
It's patterns and thoughts and thought structures and ways of expressing them
And you know at that point if if if that kind of really interesting
But much more abstract kind of pattern recognition is what's driving your ability to construct new models of new situations
Or at least initially before you've had formal instruction or when you're just at the beginning of formal instruction
Then we should expect that it to have it to have the same kinds of fragility with far transfer that any machine learning approach does
Okay, sorry to be a gilljoy here. We have about 10 minutes left
But we have at least four people that want to ask questions. So what I want to suggest
to alina and julia and
also
Uh leijin and stephan carlson is to raise your hand again, and I'll recognize you in the order that you raise your hand
Okay, julia go ahead
well, um, so I was wondering
I was thinking like maybe you can use the um the LLM translator plus the probabilistic models that system to um
Model how the beliefs of a reader would change over the course of being told a story or like reading a book
And then you could look across
The genres or books or whatever to kind of get a sense of
What the kind of model of those stories being told since the stories are themselves a world model what that would be
and that you could incorporate
Because if you have a guess because something that you didn't like touch on in
You know in your act talk, which I'm sure you didn't have time
But was that like if you have a guess about where you are in the trajectory of the story you expect
Then you have a guess about
About what you think's going to happen next
Wrap it up because we um, so I was just wondering like do you do yeah, that's a great question
Um, let me just try to answer it really quickly yet
Leo wong would love that question because in addition to being a great cognitive scientist
They are also a writer they write stories and even novels
And one of the things that we've been working on is little mini like three act structures and things like that that
Follow either classic narrative structures or other
Things and and you know, maybe not surprisingly those are places where we see a big gap between
human story understanding and
LLMs even the state of the art ones, but exactly we're trying to use these models to capture how that kind of
You know journey of understanding might unfold and also even how
A creator might create it. So another student that we've worked with Karthik Chandra has
Had had some work at last year's cog side conference on storytelling as inverse inverse planning and the idea that like if somebody's
Understanding another character's journey by doing some inverse planning as in those theory of my models
Then a storyteller can try to invert that inverse planner to to convey
the emotional
Or mental journey that the character has and that's a way to use this toolkit for both story creation as well as story understanding
So again, it's those are mostly promissory notes, but great question and future research
I think from Karthik and leo and others will address it. Thank you. Thanks
Hi, I'm gonna ask a question in person josh. This is ever
Hi, I yeah go for it. I I really liked your talk. By the way, I watched it on video. Yeah
Cool, great. Okay. So yeah
I was gonna so following the work that you were showing where you were basically based also on what you were saying and then in the
Question period where you were, you know, few shot prompting these language models to produce probabilistic language
World models, I guess I have my I have sort of a more medic question
Which is do you see that as just a way to sort of help step by step reasoning in these models?
Or do you think this is sort of evidence for
Early sort of possible world modeling being learned in these models
Um
I'm not sure if I see it as either of those. Um, I I mean, uh, uh, so
I don't think of it as either doing step step by step reasoning in language models or
Evidence that they do possible world modeling. It might be relate. I mean, there is you know, I've obviously as you know
You talked about some and others have, you know, there's certainly
Um, a lot of evidence that llms if you try to just use them as end-to-end reasoning systems
They can benefit from step by step by reasoning and there might be some emergent world modeling capacities
But you know, again, I look at that and I see a really interesting and mixed pattern of successes and failures
And depending on who's writing the paper and what their agendas are you can highlight the successes or you can highlight the failures and the gaps
um
The to me that an objective perspective is that it's patchy and fragile although extremely impressive and really interesting
So the way I think of what we're trying to do is to say, yeah, there's there's you know
Various kinds of interesting approximate implicit knowledge that those models have that can be used sometimes to succeed
In reasoning complex sequences of reasoning or world modeling
But I think a more robust way to use it is the way we're using it a more both a more human like and a more robust for ai
way to use it which is to
Which is to condition and construct these bespoke world models
that you know where the
long chains of sequential reasoning or actual
You know coherent world modeling are there
By construction
But you know, there are other limits like again as as I was saying, you know Bayesian inference in really complex models
Is very difficult and I don't think people do it. There's a lot of evidence
They don't do it
But they seem to do it very generally in in just the right small model
At least in cases where they have the relevant world knowledge to construct those models and when they don't they don't
Right, so that's all you know
Our minds have mixed patterns of successes and failures there too
But I think this toolkit is better matched to the mixed patterns of successes and failures, which is
What what i'm trying to get out if that makes sense the the the one that we see in humans as opposed to the the weird head scratching
Like super intelligent cases in some places and then super dumb Jesus and others that you just see in a pure sequence model
I'm told Alina can go next. Thanks for your answer. Yeah, thanks
Good question
Alina pick it up or you lose your turn
Yes, um, hello, uh, thank you for insightful talk. Um, Josh so
You said that um, and correct me if I'm misheard that language allows us to construct meaning that it's totally out of bounds of evolutionary gain
um
Is if uh, if this is what you said, I think this is uh, super profound. So
Yeah, I I'm sure I'm not the only person who said that many people sure. Okay. It's just a reminder. I guess profound truth. Yes
Okay, uh, so the actual question
So, um, you mentioned that the meaning on the world is constructed contextually and incrementally
So could you please elaborate on how this process occurs and how it impacts our understanding of complex concepts?
So so we transition between the um from incremental construction of the meaning to generalizations
Right. So the way it works in our
I can just I can tell you how it works in the models that we've built so far
And again, this is not to say that it's exactly like this in the mind
But I think it might be something like this and a lot more work needs to be done
But the way it works in our models is something kind of like what you're familiar in a chat
Like if you've used a chat gbt or other
conversational ai systems
The way it's working is that basically there
You know, if you're used to using chat gbt you type something it types something back and in the middle
Some wheels turn and then you type something more in it wheels turn in the black box and it types more stuff
Okay, so it's it's basically like that
It in that you at each each sentence is translated into some
Expression in the language of thought roughly at the sentence level. I think sentences are real units of meaning like I I am very
respectful and admiring of many insights from language
Including that words are real and sentences are real and there's real syntactic structure to be understood there
That is only being approximated in some ways by these models
But the key is that yes, there's a process the contextual process is like at the discourse level
You go sentence code sentence code sentence code
And each sentence to code translation is conditioned on the previous
Conversational history or the discourse that that you have been interpreting. Okay
That's just a first approximation
Just another thing you might want to do and surely you'll have to do is go back and edit previous code because if you realize
Oh, I misunderstood something. I can't just add new code. I have to go back and edit the code that I wrote before
Which is also something that code llms can do
I'm not saying they'll do it right
But there's other processes that involve like checking and refining and fixing models
That are written in this way
But maybe that gives you some sense of the contextual dynamics of how language is understood in this model
Last question lay jim
Hi
Joshua, thank you for for the presentation. It's very interesting
Um, I have an engineering background, but I'm not an expert in
artificial intelligence
Uh, I have a few questions
um
From your presentation, I understand that
actually llms
the
The the it's it's kind of a gold mine of human knowledge
And uh, you seem to say that they have a modelized the real world facts and the logics are quite correctly
If you ask the question directly in human language, uh, currently they don't seem to to give the good answer
because some with some lack of
algorithm, but if you first translate the
human questions into
functional code and like
The work you are doing and then they are capable of um
I know we execute the code then we we are capable of having
Result results that are quite close to human behavior. Uh, so is that the correct?
Yeah, that's I mean, that's more or less correct
But I don't want to I mean and that's that's what we've been doing in these examples
And what I've been showing but I don't want to
Claim I don't and I don't think it's true
But certainly I don't have the evidence for it being true or how true it is that
You know llms like always do this, right? There's a lot of
Ways in which language is only an imperfect reflection of the ways that we think
There's certain things that again are partly based on evolutionarily ancient core systems. The language is not very good at expressing
And that includes also spatial reasoning and you can see ways in which
Even the best language models break down here and language multimodal language vision models
Have have had persistent problems always from the beginning there
So I think you know, I don't want to suggest like I think yes language is a treasure trove
Of knowledge explicit and implicit about the world, but it's and for us it's it's such a valuable resource as human beings
Okay, that's why it's no accident that language models when they're trained to capture patterns on all the language that humanity's basically ever produced and put out there on the web
Uh, you know start to have remarkable properties at the same time
It's only some parts of our knowledge about the world is key parts to actually understanding and being in the world
That basically nobody ever talks about
And even if they do talk about it they talk about it very incompletely and imperfectly and yet our brains are designed to understand in those terms
So I I don't want to convey the idea that somehow it's all there in language and it's and that's all you need
by not by any means
Wonderful before we, uh, let people applaud
You know, there's some several panels coming. Are there any of them that you can join? They're not today, unfortunately
Yeah, um, I I need to check my calendar and coordinate on some family things and I will I'll I'll try very hard to join one of them
Okay, now we'll applaud you for
Thank you
Thanks, and and thanks so much for the discussion Virginia and all the all the questions. There were great questions. So I hope to engage more
um
in one of the panels and um in person if if anyone hears