from the campus of stanford university people are worried about data they're
worried about their privacy and their security they should be we need secure
systems this is the future of everything but we can't have a system that
closes that data off it is too rich of a source of inspiration innovation and
discovery for new things in medicine today on the future of everything the
future of using physics to understand biology and to build new devices now
when we think of physics we often think of the study of fundamental forces in
the world gravity the theory of relativity electricity the big bang
black holes dark matter we may think about the big experimental facilities
around the world big telescopes particle beams and linear accelerators the
detection of cosmic events black holes we may not think however about biology
biological systems of course of course must obey the rules of physics but
somehow those rules seem distant and not directly applicable in biological
systems we may not always think of a physicist studying fundamental forces
relevant to biology life on earth and creating devices for measuring these
phenomenon but of course physicists do do this indeed life on earth has had to
evolve in response I'm saying obvious things here to the physical world to
solve some remarkable problems how do we encode the shapes of living organisms
so that with just their DNA with just their genome they can
reproducibly form their expected shape how can living organisms work with water
water is a fascinating substance it has special properties in terms of its
chemical makeup its electrical activity how it interacts with itself and its
ability to host other molecules that are dissolved within it how can we build
physical systems in living systems that perceive signals how do we perceive
visual signals audio signals touch taste these must all be sensed at a
molecular physical level and then integrated into useful signals that
the organism can then integrate to figure out the key things like where's the
light where's the food pretty much that's actually that's pretty much
everything where's the light where's the food where's the mate so these are the
basic functions of living systems now a fascinating branch of biology is the
study of how biological systems take advantage of physics to accomplish
complex tasks tasks that appear to be difficult or even impossible so what am
I talking about well this includes the study of self-assembly where individual
units of a biological system can create a complex structure without any
explicit instructions let me give an example there are viruses spherical
viruses that are particles made up of 180 identical subunits that form these
beautiful perfect spheres that contain these beautiful perfect spheres that
contain the DNA that makes the virus infectious just based on how these
individual proteins they are interact with one another they can spontaneously
form these shells there's no need to build a scaffold there's no need to say
okay now you go there you go there they just kind of because of their intrinsic
physical features they assemble with one another and they form these spheres
similarly the outer membrane of a cell which is lipids that create a boundary
between the inside and the outside of the cell are made of lipid molecules that
self-assemble to form these compartments that support the living machinery
imagine having a bunch of fabric and saying could you please make me a tent
and whoosh the fabric spontaneously forms a tent in the case of the virus
imagine just having pieces Lego pieces lying around which will spontaneously
form a sphere without any effort this is what happens in many times in biology
or how DNA of course forms these beautiful double helices that look a lot
like helical staircases imagine wanting a helical staircase in your mansion not a
problem that I have where you just get all the materials and they self-assemble
into a beautiful double helix without any instruction we do not understand all
the ways in which by lock biological systems have harnessed physics to solve
these problems but we have examples where where it has this is worth
understanding big both because of natural curiosity of how biological systems
work and because it may elucidate principles that allow us to take
advantage of these same are the of these rules to build devices and new
capabilities in in our world that can advance our technology and our
understanding my guest today is professor Manu Prakash from the
department of bioengineering at Stanford University and Manu is an expert
physicist working on biological systems he studies the physics of biological
systems at the molecular cellular and tissue level and he also takes the
insights that he learns from this deep dive into the physics of biological
systems to build cool devices we'll get to the devices but Manu as someone who
trained as a physicist applied physics what drew you to biological systems and
what do you tell your fellow physicists about what's exciting or challenging
about biology you know it's once in a life you get this moment where you take
a backseat and you think you know what do you want your life to be and that
happens a couple of times in our lives and that happened to me right after grad
school and anybody who's peered through a microscope would know that there is a
piece of matter that we do not understand that we cannot write down a
bunch of equations to explain and it's so us you know biology so us so I mean you
know I was studying many different things in the past but that that emotional
connection you have with aha you know not only am I trying to understand this
piece of matter but my act of understanding it is that piece of matter
very meta yeah that was that's the philosophical times that you go in and
then you ask this is what I want to do for my life and I think I find it's a
little bit strange sometimes I mean you're right I have to explain some
times to my physics friends that hey this is the most exciting thing in the
world and sometimes I think that sense of wonder if you just share that sense of
wonder first yes I mean the aesthetic and beauty in biology is incredible and
if you're not working on a beautiful problem then you know find a new problem
now I want to give you credit though because I know many physicists who take
a little they dip their toes into biology they love mathematical equations
that explain the world if you've taken any physics you know f equals ma it's
very famous force equals mass times acceleration based on that very simple
equation you can derive how we got men to the moon how we build devices that
work and that don't break and and sometimes my physics friends that you
know biology is too squishy there's no right angles there's no real underlying
mathematical formalism and I'm out I'm sorry yeah this did not happen to you
yeah or did it not yet not yet I think I'm naive and I am perfectly happy being
naive sometimes and I mean I actually tell most of my students you have to be
naive sometimes to have the guts that we will try to understand this piece of
matter and I think I mean to your point about the complexity it's it is what
makes biology so much more fun that although there are these rules there is
every time an exception to that rule yes and I find that fascinating so so you
have worked on this self-assembly issue I talked about the viruses and some
other things tell us what what is the state of our understanding of self
assembling systems and are we just at at a baby point or are we beginning to
really understand the what's going on when these systems do these amazing
activities of creating complex objects from simple subunits yeah so I mean I
would argue we're really at the beginning and the reason for that is most
of our insights initially in that field have come from just watching biology
the fact that now we have the capability of really ripping apart a virus
particle and really see the sets of components gives us the sense that we
are starting to understand the list of components but how they come together
and build things that are not one even two or three orders of magnitude larger
than the component like your example of truly bringing a grant grand staircase
from a point of view of a molecule a cell is a gigantic staircase we don't
really understand where these lens scales are set up you know where is that
encoded shape and form at higher levels hierarchy has been really fantastic so I
think we we don't exploit that too much in and I think the other aspect of the
field has really grown when we had tried to take small components and then ask
ourselves we are going to build something out of it so for example the
entire world of DNA all algorithmic assembly or even general ideas where you
take and now make components that are literally dead but still demonstrate the
principles that's where the most exciting bits that I see because I start to see
an inkling of things that we would never been able to manufacture before this is
the future everything of everything I'm Russ Altman I'm speaking with Professor
Manu Prakash about physics and its influences these days on biology what
is your favorite current system to look at to understand self-assembly I'm
trying to get this down to a real system that you find fascinating that you think
you might be able to understand yeah so this is kind of it's slightly ironic but
sometimes what ends up happening is the biology inspires an insight and then you
can take that insight and even work on that system in an abiotic manner
non-biological non-biological and so there is a system in the lab that we've
been trying to build now for several years to really demonstrate that we can
do algorithmic self-assembly using droplets droplets yeah there is a two
years ago we demonstrated a type of an active droplet system that demonstrates
are you talking about fluid droplets that's correct fluid droplets but they
can actually be phase droplets they can be protein droplets very fluid like phases
that demonstrate very phenomena that you would not be able to distinguish from
chemotaxis for example they can sense each other they can crawl they can chase
each other but they're not living they're just physical literally small bits
molecules of fluid and they're communicating with each other now
that sounds like magic you got you have to tell us I have to stop you then you
have to give us a sense of how that could possibly happen yeah so you can do
this in your kitchen go right now and find some food coloring in your kitchen
and some water and mix it up on a clean glass slide and put these two drops next
to each other in a few moments you will notice that these two food coloring
droplets will be talking to each other what they do is they send out a water
signal there is a vapor cloud around it vapor cloud yes and that vapor cloud is
interacting and there is more vapor between the two than around the
surroundings and that leads to this incredible phenomena which is not so
far from retrograde flows in cells where cells are these engines with all these
motors moving around but this purely arises in a physical system and so the
reason I brought that example is sometimes we although biology is complex
the phenomena's and the basic principles could actually be very very simple in
components yes yes so what I'm hearing from you and this is this really does
make sense is that whereas we might say that because it's a living cell it has
a complex communication with its neighboring cell you have shown that
these two drops which are obviously not living cells still have communication
challenges and we may not need to invoke complex cellular communication to
explain some of the phenomenon that we see yeah and even to a point where not
only do they sense then based on that signal you act on it and you can move
and you can sense quite literally the same phenomena that white blood cells are
doing trying to chase bacteria during an infection an infection we replicate with
two drops of water this is the future of everything I'm Russ Alvin I'm speaking
with Dr. Manu Prakash from bioengineering at Stanford I know a little
bit about your work and I know that that droplet work has also led to some
intriguing demonstrations of doing computation with droplets can you give
us a sense of what the heck I mean I think of computation as silicon
electrons transistors but you've written papers about how droplets can be used to
simulate some of not simulate to perform some of the functions that we have
traditionally associate with silicon and transistors tell us about that yeah so
you know when we think of a computer we're thinking of processing information
and that information revolution has led us here but there is a bit that got
missed out which is that every bit in a computer is also physical you know every
electron that's running around you can make optical computers photons running
around and I had this notion of thinking about could we use computation to
actually assemble matter if that bit could be a grocery bag that I could put
molecules and another things in run a computation and walla instead of getting
a number out I would get an object out so that's been the mission for the last
12 years have been working on this and at this point we're at a stage where we
have demonstrated universal synchronous computation using these droplets that
interact with each other they form all kinds of logic gates they're completely
modular so the system is scalable but the goal is not wordpress or word
processing but the goal is to actually build using this material so imagine you
write a little two-line code that codes for the Serpentski triangle but I have
no idea what that is so you can think of the Pascal triangle for example or you
could think of a fractal yes it's a fractal like structure with a
hierarchical structure and if I was to place every element of that fractal one
at a time serially which is what 3d printing kind of tries to do it would
take forever forever but if you can teach it to do the computation it
algorithmically builds and local parts interact with each other to build a
local structure that interacts with the rest of it so just to help us just I
just want to go a little bit more for this computation with droplets so is it
the is the right analogy that in the same way that we have wires with electrons
moving on them and we get the electrons to go to the left to the right and by
bringing them together they can do ads or subtracts or other numerical that you
can get the droplets to flow through perhaps like a microfluidic channel split
come together and do very similar things as what electrons are doing in wire is
that the general yeah that's a that's a good basic way of describing this and
the droplets are interacting with each other just like electrons interact with
electromagnetic fields and charges they're interacting with hydrodynamic
fields and in the latest system we demonstrated there actually there are no
wires that it's essentially a flat surface of water that they're moving
around and because they're interacting with each other they provide the
structure they need and we inject energy in the system in a way to control it
from outside unbelievable so we can look forward to these computational fluid
systems that are helping us get solve problems through an analogy with
electronic computer systems yeah sort of my hope is that we're able to build
some of these systems that can make materials that we've never been able to
make for example heterogeneous material you know like my hand right has
thousands of different materials multi-component we don't know we're
close to that in the context of our manufacturing capability so speaking of
manufacturing capabilities I want to move to the part that everybody loves
when they talk to you which is your focus on what we call frugal science and
the creation of devices using the rules of physics but with an extreme emphasis
on affordability and I think the one of the first ones that first of all the
computation with fluids could be that already but let's move to a something
that got a lot of press which was your creation of the fold scope can you tell
us what the fold scope is and why it exists yeah so I think we have one in
front of us that's correct we have something sitting here and you should
think of this as a pencil of microscopy you know many of many of us are
carrying pencils and pens around and it's important you know it's a point of
making about literacy that I can have my thoughts be heard and seen and share
it's a tool and very much what ends up happening in science sometimes with you
know two billion kids on this planet and one billion of them technically living
under poverty it starts realizing this idea that access to science is not a
common thing we're just the lucky ones who sort of made it through somebody you
know helped us along and we're here and billions of other kids can also be here
except at the same time they haven't had the access and they don't have the tools
and they don't have the tools there are a lot of knowledge and actually the
information revolution is really changing that Wikipedia Khan Academy many
of these miracles of knowledge there's incredible knowledge but science
composed of knowledge and experience and we're missing the experience without
the experience there is no aha moment without an aha moment I wouldn't be
sitting here so what we decided to do almost six years ago now is to make a
microscope that was gonna cost a dollar and can do resolutions that are sub
cellular and there was this challenge of let's do something where cost and
performance really try to push the limits yes and this is where comes in a
new manufacturing tools so fold scope is an origami microscope so I for those of
you can't see we are looking at what looks like a bunch of cutout paper and
colorful and it has a bunch of cutouts and this you should think of this as
art and craft essentially that it should feel so natural to you it's a piece of
paper you can drop it bang on it but then once it's folded together there's a
little place I insert a little slide of water that I just collected outside I
clip it on and at this point is now holding up to his eye this little piece
of cardboard and I have transported into a new world for a second I forgot about
your eyes because I was watching single cells of a moss which is a plant like
structure but except that little tiles of little pieces of bricks all assembled
together so let me clarify if I may hold that for a moment yeah I'm gonna
actually give this to you I've lost him he is in the microbiome hold here and
here on the two sides and just bring it close to your eye pointing to the light
so let me just first describe that this is fundamentally made out of a kind of
card subcard board grade paper like a what you might get a greeting card on it's
an elaborate folded piece with there but in the middle there is something that's
not paper and I want you to because I don't this is not magic there's still I
guess a lens so could you tell us about the lens set up what it's made out of and
I is that an expensive component or is that not expensive no so I think one of
the questions we really asked ourselves is given constraints in physics and this
is why I call it frugal science because there's a lot of rigor that went into
manufacturing this lens I am seeing things in this lens and one of the threads
that you start thinking about is given two optical surfaces what is the
theoretical resolution best possible resolution you can achieve so you had to
use pretty deep optical theory so we solve that analytical equation that took
33 pages to solve but then once you have it we have a design tool that suddenly
and so rather than asking that I will keep piling up pieces of glass after
glass we asked a question given minimal number of surfaces what is the best thing
you can do and then we built robots this would not be possible because at this
point in the lab itself we shipped around 80,000 of these instruments around
the world how much do they cost so at so we as a disclosure we spun off last year
as a startup company that I'm a co-founder of and at this point for a
$1.50 you can buy a full scope and is that is that an actual piece of glass
that's correct the last lenses it has magnetic couplers it couples to your
phone so you can share the data with friends now for people who have used a
microscope and they know that there's like 10x 40x 100x what is this this
would be equivalent to 140x objective okay and the thing that you start
thinking about is the data that we collect is I can watch individual bacteria
so if we had more time I would have asked you to give me a little spit sample
and then we would have watched single bacteria swimming around and you know and
then and the magnification is sufficient sufficient enough to actually watch
bacteria was this motivated by a real health need or is this mostly for the
education of the youth no I think it's both and it was this realization that
you cannot provide health surfaces around the world if you don't provide
health education if you don't provide I mean I've been out in the field many
times with the fancy hospital in the middle of nowhere but the patients
don't even believe in medicine they have never experienced the germ theory for
that matter you know so seeing a germ might be a transformational experience
for them so there is a social context to this which is really we should open up
science so people get a chance to really understand the beginnings and at that
same time the same sets of tools that are Peruvian doctors who have used this
for cervical cancer we have demonstrated diagnostics applications for these not
just for humans but for plants and animals there is a sailor right now in
the middle of the Pacific Ocean fold scoping on his you know 15-foot boat
unbelievable now can you give me an example of what kind of diagnosis might
a fold scope be capable of making yeah so any stool samples for example if you
really start thinking about from the very beginning of where we started this
the question of helmet infections eggs and stool you can start with urine
absolutely and I think one of the threads is we've demonstrated we can
even image malaria parasites we can image many blood-borne pathogens one of
the things that we have and I want to stress when he says image when you say
image you're talking about with this one dollar and 50 cent cardboard plus a
piece of glass and a piece of metal yeah and one of the things that's valuable
about diagnostics when we started doing this is we realize diagnostics is about
searching for a needle in a haystack and sometimes if the needle is right in
front of your lens you could to see it but sometimes it's not so we invented a
way to around that to find the needle this is the future of everything I'm
Russ Altman and I'm speaking with Manu Prakash about how physics can turn into
extreme frugal instrumentation so you were just about to talk about a new
device I believe it's called the paper huge what's the paper fuge all about
yeah so it sort of stems from this idea that if you're searching for a needle in
a haystack if you could just pick out the needle then you won't be searching
anymore and that process in the scientific context is called centrifugation so
that's usually I think of a big machine that spins very fast and it separates
the thicker things go to the bottom the thinner things stay at the top and we
are able to separate yes and so by density and it turns out parasites have
different density than our native cells so if there is one blood cell that has
a malaria parasite the density has changed now and we'll be able to pull that
out by separating by separating it but now the question is if I'm in the
middle of nowhere under a tree with no electricity no power no nothing that big
centrifuge that I described is not an option that's correct it's not an option
I'm looking at Manu and he's holding an odd-looking thing which I'm sure he's
about to talk about when I shut up but it looks like two cylindrical cardboard
pieces with string and then something in the middle what are we looking at Manu
you are looking at one of the oldest toy in the history of mankind this is a
5,000 year old toy which in many cultures is called button on a string and we
made this realization that if we study all possible toys that spin could we
mathematically write down equations to beat the world record for fastest
spinning object in human with human power human engineered oh and human
powered so we have this object that I'm now spinning it is spinning very fast
he's doing kind of a back-and-forth motion with the string and the central
disc is spinning I have no idea I'm sure Manu will tell us very fast yeah so
this specific one right now itself was spinning around 20,000 rpm 20,000
rotations per minute and then there are many versions of this we make and our
fastest spinning one is actually 125,000 rpm now does that actually set the
record you were seeking that is correct that sets the world record at this point
for the fastest spinning object and I think the reason I'm stressing this is I
really do want people to break that record right if we were a challenge it is a
challenge and of course it took us again going back to the rigor 20 bits of
equations to really describe the parameters because although people had
played with this toy nobody had asked this question how this toy actually works
and so you know the joy going back to the beauty in science is the joy for us was
really figuring that out and of course there is a phenomenal outcome of that
but I would have been happy just figuring out the toy as well so we set the record
for rotations but I guess it begs the question are we able to use this device to
do the kinds of separations you described to actually make some kind of useful
diagnoses find that heavy malarial cell if you will yeah so I think they're in
here if some of you can see there's a little glass slide a glass capillary that
I had put and if we had more point time and I had my lancet I would have done a
little finger prick take the capillary fill the blood within 90 seconds of
going back and forth going back and forth we have separated all of blood plasma
from the blood cells itself and pure plasma is extremely useful and important
for rdt tests all these rapid diagnostics yes because all the enzymes have to get
rid of the red blood cells and you want kind of the clear fluid that you get this
fantastic sensitivity and specificity using that and then of course if we just
spend for a little bit longer for around between seven to ten minutes you
actually separate out every single malaria parasite malaria is a tough one
because it's a really tiny parasite but that in itself this thing is spinning
around 30 000 g forces 30 000 g that's correct so you are experiencing if you
were that little cell you're experiencing a very high force well this is just
fantastic because we've gone from a very for the lack of a better phrase high
falutin conception of what physics can bring to biology to a series of
inventions that are bringing science and the ability to make uh experiential
observations really globally to everyone in the world who has any interest in
doing that thank you for listening to the future of
everything i'm ross altman if you missed any of this episode listen
anytime on demand with the serious xm app