The fear that comes out of whatever is left of the core community is you guys don't have a right
to go direct to a consumer. You don't have a right to talk about the field. That belongs to a tiny
number of people who do this morning, noon, and night who are all possessed of common beliefs.
There have to be some standards. On the other hand, the core group that's been trying to gate this has failed.
We have graciously been joined with two of the most prominent and two of my real heroes in this
field that are maverick mathematicians who are self-made mathematicians in a way. And I want to
talk about how they view the current spirit of the times as zeitgeist, as we say, in terms of
theories of everything that are percolating around in the atmosphere. And to begin with,
I'll ask my guest, Eric, to introduce yourself and say a little bit about where people can find
you. We'll do that right up front. And then we'll get started with our discussion topics. We're
going to have a nice clean fight. We're going toe to toe. No, there's not going to be any fight.
It's going to be very, very respectful. So thank you both for joining. Eric, can you introduce
yourself? And I'll buy me some time to tweet out this link. Check my feed. Eric Weinstein,
I'm a managing director at Teal Capital. I come from a mathematics background. So I'm not a
physicist. And I have an eclectic podcast called The Portal, which I hope to have. In fact, I've
got agreements from both of these gentlemen to be my guests on The Portal. So I'm really looking
forward to that and happy to help blow up into the impossible. Brian, you're doing a fantastic
job. I love it. And it's all thanks to you guys. You guys were actually my first guest in what I
call the pandemic podcast series, which began back in April, actually late March with Stephen.
It was the first of the two of you to come on the podcast and really kicked off this whole idea
of getting some of the world's most brilliant minds to engage around this topic of understanding
the fundamental nature of the universe. And at that time, because of the pandemic, perhaps,
Stephen's schedule was amenable to coming on my podcast. So we chatted for a mere three hours or
so. And he's, as I said, gracious enough to come back. Stephen, where are you joining us from today?
I'm in Concord, Massachusetts. And do I introduce myself? I'm Stephen Wolfram. I do science and
technology and things I've built. Some technology things lots of people use. I've built some science
lots of people use. And about 30 years ago, well, I used to be a particle physicist long ago.
I did that when I was a kid. And then I got interested in computation and have kind of
alternated between doing basic science and doing technology. And I've now done about five cycles
of that. And I think it's a very interesting process, actually, alternating between basic
science and technology, because they kind of build on each other. And it's sort of a
progressively spiral upwards, so to speak. But the big surprise for me was about a bit more
than a year ago now, a bunch of things that I've been thinking about, about how to make a fundamental
theory of physics. I actually thought, I think I actually have some way forward. And a couple of
young physicists were really enthusiastic about working with me on it. And so we're like, okay,
let's try and really do something. And the huge surprise is that it's worked. And which I didn't
expect. Yeah, I mean, it's, you know, we've been, we're at 100 years, roughly for, you know,
general relativity and quantum mechanics, which are the two sort of big achievements of 20th
century physics. And, you know, they've taken us a great distance. But, you know, I had a bunch
of ideas that have been sort of based on things that came out of the whole computational thinking
that I've done. And anyway, the big surprise that's worked, and not only that it seemed to have worked
when I last talked to you, it's been going absolutely spectacularly since then. And it's,
it's really, it's really, it's kind of like embarrassing, because there are a lot of things
I should have been able to figure out 20, 30 years ago, which are now becoming obvious. And I think
one of the other things to say is that one of the surprises to me is that I had thought we were
building this kind of prong in the direction of kind of computation that would be really different
from the mathematical physics and so on that people had done before. Turns out we basically
built a sort of a low level machine code for how things work. But it turns out an awful lot of the
formalisms that people have worked on in mathematical physics the last 50 years or so, they actually
fit beautifully into the kinds of things that we're doing. And they seem to kind of illuminate
what we've done and hopefully what we've done illuminates what they're doing. And I, I actually,
my favorite analogy in recent times for this is what happened in early days of computation theory
with things like Turing machines, which was that people had come up with, you know, models of
computation, combinators, lambda calculus, general recursive functions, things like this.
But it wasn't clear how they fit together. And they all seemed rather abstract. And people
couldn't kind of tether them. And then Turing machines came along. And, you know, in the usual
way that science history is done, we could say immediately everybody understood. But actually,
it took, let's see how long, 40 years, 50 years. So immediately it was actually 40 or 50 years.
But the people understood from from that kind of more concrete tethering of these ideas about
computation, how all these different things fit together. So that's been, that's been, I mean,
it's both both scientifically interesting to me. And I think also sociologically interesting,
because often, you know, you come in with the big new theory, so to speak. And it's like,
you're kind of gunning down everything else. But that's not what's happening here. I mean,
what's happening here is that we've got something which is sort of orthogonal to what other people
have thought about. It's kind of a low level, you know, low level machine code. And we can kind of,
you know, see how things fit together at a higher level. That's your elevator pitch that goes to
the space elevator stage docking station. Thank you, Steven. And both of you guys are notable,
as people are pointing out in the chat, which I'm monitoring. So behave in there. I am seeing a lot
of, you know, questions from younger people. And I think the two of you in particular,
have an ability that other scientists have not yet really been able to achieve, which is to
engage young people. And Steven, you just talked about engagement by these young physics students
that we and I spoke about in our first conversation back in April. And with Eric, people are,
you know, engaged on Discord, on comments, and people all over the Internet are really engaged
with it. What do you think it does? You know, this podcast, the Intangible Podcast, I like to
fashion myself as, you know, someday I'll be the Joe Rogan of physics. There's already one Joe Rogan.
But I'd like to know, what is it about these theories of everything that really engages young
people? And what I want to do is kind of translate. It's fascinating that you have this sort of bucket,
theories of everything. I don't kind of view it as a bucket like that. For me, you know, I spent my
life basically developing computation. And, you know, the fact that I happen to have discovered
that that relates to kind of fundamental theory of physics is kind of a singular event, as far as
I'm concerned. It's a kind of the bucket of theories of everything is not a bucket I particularly
identify with. Right. If I could agree with Stephen, there can only be one.
That was what I said today. There's a Highlander by Highlander.
One of the surprising things that we've discovered is that really isn't true.
There can be many ways of approaching that theory.
Yes. But the thing that's interesting is that, you know, you could say there's only,
fair enough, I mean, depends what you mean by only one. That's an interesting kind of ontological,
epistemological question. But I mean, it's like, you know, you could say about computation. There
could only be one theory of computation and it's Turing machines or it and its general recursive
functions. The thing that's surprising about physics that has become increasingly clear is that
the this kind of there's this notion of, you know, what are the possible, what are the underlying
rules? And then how do we observe those underlying rules? And it's becoming clear that you can
basically the only thing that is absolutely rigid is the underlying rules are computational
and not hyper computational. That is, once you say that the underlying rules are purely
computational, it then follows, it seems that the things we observe from 20th century physics
are inevitable consequences of that and a few other kind of unspecific assumptions.
It's a hard thing to explain. And actually, we're just, I think, okay, so here's a remarkable
connection that's just been becoming clear. So we have this notion of, you know, you have some
underlying rules, you follow these rules, you, you know, reproduce how the universe works.
But on the other side of that, we are observing how these rules are working and interpreting them
to say this is how the universe works. The thing that is surprising is that one can, I mean, in
the language of our kind of theory, there's this thing called the rural multiway system,
which is this kind of this branching system that's that runs sort of all possible rules.
And this is we're now jumping into the most abstract, most, most complicated. But I just
want to say one thing about it, which is kind of kind of interesting, which is it's turning out
that this incredibly abstract thing that we have this rural multiway system, appears to be the
same as this thing called the infinity groupoid, which was developed by growth and deek. And
when it was at the 70s, I guess, 1970s, which is kind of a pinnacle of abstraction of category
theory in other areas of mathematics. And what is really quite remarkable to me is that it seems
like this thing that's coming out of our theory kind of maps into this incredibly abstract
mathematical thing. And the observations that we have of the universe correspond to a particular,
in mathematical terms, kind of vibration of this infinity groupoid thing. And that basically what
we're our our way of interpreting the universe is kind of a slice of that of that mathematical
object. And so it's the statement, there's only one theory, in a sense, all these theories are
equivalent. But the, you know, the question is how how we are observing them. I was making a
pop culture reference. The intellectual spirit of it is that you can have a summit and there are
many faces that could be used as assaults on that summit. In the end, however we traverse,
you know, Einstein, for example, came up with his divergence free equations after some rumbling
around in differential geometry, Hilbert went, you know, immediately to a Lagrangian description,
they were describing something in common. So I didn't mean to suggest that there was a single
description, but there can really only be one underlying theory. And we all of us who are,
I was trying to agree with you, Steven, that the most probable number for wrong guests on this
live stream is two. But in all probability, if it is not two, then one of us is wrong. It strikes me
that you have gained confidence that what you are doing is actually not only capable
of producing a fundamental final theory. And we can talk about what the right language is,
I'm not wedded to any particular description, if you have an objection. But it sounds to me like
you are increasingly convinced that week by week, this is really the most promising assault
on our foundations. First of all, if I'm wrong, I hope that you or Garrett Leasy or one of these
other crazy people turns out to be right. It would be a pleasure to lose to you, sir.
The thing to understand is the kind of system that we've built, it is very likely that, you know,
I don't understand what you've done, but you know, I know a little bit of the mathematical
background, you know, the whole, for example, understanding local gauge invariance and understanding
how fiber bundles work in our systems, as a student actually at our recent summer school,
mathematical physicist, who managed to make great progress on that. And it's actually very clever
and much simpler than I expected. The way that essentially sort of fiber bundle type structures
and local gauge invariance arise in our theories. Now, what you do with it once it's arisen from
this kind of low level machine code, that's, you know, often running with much more traditional
mathematical physics. And I don't think that there's a, you know, it's not an incompatible thing to
say, oh, there's some complicated structure to do with, you know, high dimensional systems and
fiber bundles and so on. That doesn't, that's not like, there's no, there's no divide yet.
Let's try to state how you and I could both be fit into the discussion that Brian is trying to
conduct. One thing I definitely agree that, you know, conciliance is nice and it's wonderful to
have consonants what the viewers want as argumentation. I'm just kidding. I don't care about that,
but when I do, she gets Sabina back on. Exactly. I think it would be really a great outcome of this
discussion would be kind of the joining of your two different, different approaches. I don't know
about Eric's stuff. So I can't really comment on that. The people out in that are watching that
have, as you just said, fiber bundles, hop vibration, gauge invariance, but way of having
sort of a Rosetta Stone. If there are people out there, I'm not asking or asking you guys,
God forbid, with homework, but people in the respective domain experts in both of your two
categories, I think that would be an interesting kind of project to see. Can these be reconciled?
So maybe I should explain what we're doing. Okay, because there's a fairly large effort at this
point. What's been happening, you talk about engaging young people, you know, what I've been
trying to figure out how to do this, because there's been a lot of enthusiasm for our project,
a lot of people interested, a lot of people say, I want to contribute to this project. Okay.
So right now we have, we're just about to kind of roll out, I think we have 30 research affiliates
and junior research affiliates who are mostly people who came to the summer school that we just
spent a month having. And they're people who are sort of in motion, sort of doing research
along the lines of this project and, you know, producing papers and so on. And, you know, one
of the important objectives there, there's several important objectives, but one of them is
making these bridges to other kind of mathematical physics approaches. Another thing is just being
able to check off the list. There are, you know, these effects known in quantum mechanics, there
are these features of general activity, for example, can we go down the list and say, okay, you know,
we have destructive interference, we have spin statistics connections, we have this, we have
that. The thing that's just absolutely amazing is every time I think one of these is going to be
really hard, it turns out to be much easier than I think. And that's been a big surprise to me. I
mean, I've been, my expectations keep on being kind of exceeded. And I think that the, I mean,
the other question is, for example, for something like general activity, which I know, you know,
you have a lovely cosmic microwave background globe and the back there, it's some right,
it's very cool. Yeah, it's weird that it's kind of the inversion of the sky, so to speak.
Yeah, God's I view, right. Yeah, right. You know, so for example, there's the, you know,
we have a sort of mathematical proof that in some limit, we can reproduce general activity.
But the question is, can you actualize that? And so here's an interesting example of how sort of,
you know, a direction we're going in, which is an interesting sort of way to validate theories,
the following thing. So when people normally study gravitation theory, they say, oh, we've
got Einstein's equations from 1915, they work great. But if we actually want to find out her
two black holes merge, we don't get to kind of work out, you know, with Mathematica or something,
the exact, you know, result for, you know, how this black hole merger will work, we have to
make numerical approximations to the Einstein equations, sort of break them down into something
discreet, solve them on a computer, see what the implications for this process are. But that,
that kind of break down the Einstein equations into something discreet that can be solved on a
computer, there's an alternative way to think about that, which is start from our theory,
which is born as something that you can run on a computer, and then go up from there to get to
something which can reproduce what happens in black holes and so on. And so, you know,
this is the kind of thing I happened to do this years ago with fluid dynamics,
where you can start with these very simple, in that case cellular automaton models of fluid dynamics
and build up from those to actually reproduce fluid phenomena. But anyway, so the thing is
what I might call proof by compilation, so to speak, which is you're going from the kind of
low level structure of the model to actually do computations that can then be compared with
black hole dynamics, even though you sort of know it has to work, because you have a mathematical
proof that the two things are equivalent. But it's very satisfying to see it actually work,
it hasn't, we haven't, you know, done that yet, but we're in the process of doing it.
And more interestingly, actually in quantum field theory, where numerical methods have been much
harder to apply, it looks like we have a pretty good way to do sort of numerical quantum field
theory in a different way than it's been done before. When you say it's easy, by what metric
or what measure function are you defining that? Easy in terms of, you know, just easy for a brilliant,
you know, grandmaster of physics to unravel, or easy in terms of computational efficiency in some
sense? No, I mean, for example, one of the things is, do we have to know how electrons work to be
able to, or do we have to know what photons in detail are before we can reproduce effects in
quantum mechanics? The answer is, a lot of these phenomena seem to be more generic than I expected
and more amenable to being kind of explained without having that whole tower of features built.
So that's the main thing I mean by easier. I think in terms of the technical difficulty
and the mathematical depth of what's going on, we're doing what physicists often do, which is
we're skating over many of the mathematical difficulties. I mean, in some of these derivations,
there are like 12 different limits that have to be taken of, you know, this thing is small
compared to the size of the universe, but large compared to this, but small compared to the curvature
of that, but large compared to this and so on. And, you know, each one of those limits is a
significant amount of mathematical work to validate and so on. And, you know, this is the
typical thing that's been done by physicists through the ages, I'm afraid, that just skate
right over those things. Now, we have a big advantage, which was you can do computer experiments. So
we kind of know it's going to work. I mean, we know we're not going to be too far off because
we can actually check a bunch of these things in actual experiments. Although the experiments we do,
you know, if the universe has 10 to the 400, you know, atoms of space in it,
we certainly don't have that many in our computer. So we're doing very small versions of this.
You know, I want to say that I think it might be interesting for us to talk a little bit about
kind of the more sort of societal and structural aspects rather than getting too deep into the
into the. Sure. Wait a minute. I was looking to get, I wanted to get into the into the damn weeds.
Go for it. We will. We will. But yeah, small, small amount of weed,
weed whacking. And then then we can talk about some the bigger picture of science and the world
and so on, which I think I think we probably both have things to say about. I think that segues
nicely into a question that I brought up with with both of you separately and then earlier
today. And that's kind of the structure of the way that scientific revolutions take place. And
it's become a trope, you know, nowadays to say there's a paradigm shift, which is brought upon
by some new idea, radical, usually some lone genius like you guys working almost in solitude.
I'm just teasing, but just going to get us into trouble with Reddit. That's all you're doing.
You're just bathing Reddit. Well, hopefully Dr. Reddit is not watching yet. I guarantee she is.
What do you think about this notion of paradigm shifts? Do you think it's really the way that
science takes place? Or is it just sort of a retro retrospective, retradiction, historical
narrative of what has taken place that is just convenient as a hack for the human mind to say,
okay, in retrospect, the paradigm shifted with Galileo's observation of the Jovian satellites.
What do you, Eric, think about this notion of CUNY and paradigm shifting? You have to
have lived through stasis and stagnation and through revolution and boom.
And even if the boom isn't the largest boom on record, like, you know, the Gold Rush or something,
in science, I lived through one or two revolutions, one of which was a Rosetta Stone between
differential geometry and quantum field theory, or at least the structure underneath quantum field
theory that was figured out in the mid 1970s. It doesn't have a historical, like you can't go to a
biopic about it, which is weird. But your friend Jim Simons, Brian, and C. N. Yang, arguably,
maybe the greatest of living physicists, figured this out over lunch. And that revolution is going
on to this day called the Wu Yang Dictionary. There was another one having to do with the
discovery that quantum field theory was a mathematically natural structure, not just a
grab bag of techniques, and that it would have been discovered as an enhancement of something
in algebraic topology, since Dr. Wolfram brings up Alexander growth and deke. In algebraic topology,
we have a theory called boredism, which is an extraordinary homology theory, and quantum field
theory would be discovered in enhancing boredism theory, as Ed Whitten, Michael Atiyah, and Graham
Siegel and others taught us in the 1980s. Having seen revolutions, yes, there are things that you
can tell people where they're never the same again. They come to understand, as I've said before,
there should be a tattoo on all of our cecums. If you can read this, you're too close. When you
pull your head out, you can better understand the world after the revolution. And what Dr.
Wolfram is discussing is that we've had a small number of complete revolutions in our thinking,
and many more minor elaborations in our thinking. There was one around scale, which might be called
the first and second renormalization revolutions, originally a Feynman and Schwinger, but then
Ken Wilson really was probably the big name in that area. Having been through a few of these
revolutions, having been close enough to study them, and also in a few different fields like
biology with, you know, CRISPR-Cas9 or optogenetics or something like this, yeah, no, these things
are real. And they change everything. And, you know, my resistance to Stephen's theory will one day
turn into, you know, my saying, oh, my God, I can't believe I didn't understand what you were
saying. It was too new to use Feynman's famous quote from when he tried to introduce his path
integral or path sum over history's approach. He said, my machines came from too far away,
because he was derided. And you see a lot of people, we were talking before about Reddit,
just to close this out. A lot of people are trying to figure out what the hell is going on in these
live streams, and why does one person get to be in them, and who's a crank, and who isn't.
They're trying to use some sort of indicia, which is, does that person sound like their wild eye?
Does that person sound sober? And it's a really odd moment, because on the one hand,
everybody sounds crazy, and some of the crazy people sound among the most sane. And I think Dr.
Wolfern, for example, despite the fact that I think he's wrong, I think that he is one of the
sanest voices out here, one of the most interesting for sure. And part of the problem is the mainstream
of the community sounds mad as a hatter to me, and Dr. Wolfern sounds much more reasonable.
So let's comment on paradigm shifts and so on. I've been fortunate to live through some myself,
even probably responsible for some. The main process that seems to happen is,
a methodological advance is made, that opens up some new area, there's a bunch of low hanging
fruit to be picked in that area. Lots of exciting stuff happens for five years,
10 years, maybe a little bit longer. That area of science gets big, it gets quite institutionalized,
it slows down, there's 50 or 100 years of sort of stasis, and then maybe there's some methodological
advance and it opens up again. And typically, in terms of sort of the conceptualization of
these methodological advances, it's usually a long process for the people involved in them,
and it's usually, you know, you have to sort of think about things in the right way,
and then maybe there's some moment when you realize, yes, I can actually see how this works. Now,
for example, in my current activities in physics, you know, one of the embarrassments of that is
that the fundamental model, which is based on, you can think of it as based on rewritings of
hypergraphs or very minimalist, very sort of abstract thing about transformations for relations
between elements. And that idea you can also think of as transformation rules for symbolic
expressions. Well, the idea of transformation rules for symbolic expressions is what I've been
using technologically in building computational languages for 40 years. And it is super embarrassing,
in a sense, that the core idea, which seems to have unlocked what we're doing now in physics,
is actually something that I've been working on for 40 years. But I didn't see that connection,
I mean, what's happened is that normally, in using symbolic expressions and transformation
rules for symbolic expressions in computational languages, those symbolic expressions actually
immediately mean something. They mean, you know, adding things together, they mean, I don't know,
some other identifiable kind of operation. Whereas in the way we're using them in physics,
it's just the infrastructure, they mean nothing. They get meaning because the things in them turn
into the things like the atoms of space and so on. But to begin with, they mean nothing. So for me,
that's sort of an interesting case, because it's something which has been right under my nose for
40 years. And it took that amount of time for me to have the right sort of conceptual framework
to see how it could be applied in this particular case. And, you know, I think that's, I mean,
this is a question of kind of how people, you know, how these paradigm shifts and so on,
kind of land in the world. I mean, okay, so there's one big one that I've been deeply involved in,
which is the whole idea of using computation and programs as models of the world, instead of using
mathematical equations as models of the world. So you roll the clock back, you know, 300 or so
years, we get to Galileo and Newton and so on. And they had the problem of explaining to people,
no, you can't just reason about how the world works, you can write down a mathematical equation
and solve it and that will tell you how the moon moves or something. And, you know, at that time,
it was a sort of complicated battle to have people realize, yes, you can just, you know,
solve the mathematical equation, it will tell you how the world works. It's not a question of
reasoning about it. Okay, 300 years go by. And then we're at the point where, oh, mathematical
equations are the way the world works. Is there some other way to describe how the world works?
No, no, no, they can't possibly be another way to describe how the world works. You know,
when I started thinking about kind of generalizing sort of rules for how the world works and
thinking about simple programs and what they do and kind of exploring the computational
universe of simple programs, I would say, actually, looking back on it's interesting,
you know, I published this big book called a new kind of science back in 2002. I would say that
many fields were really quite receptive to what I had to say. Fundamental physics was actually one
of the one of the only exceptions. What was interesting there was, you know, some people said,
oh, you know, programs, we don't need programs to describe the world, mathematical equations
do just fine. Okay, now you look just maybe 15 years later. And if you look at new models that
people are inventing of things, they are overwhelmingly based on programs, not based on
mathematical equations. There's a dark story underneath this, which is that as tech has been
really the, and by tech, I really mean computation, because most of the rest of technology seems to
have vanished as computation became the one bright spot in a relatively stagnant world.
And I hate to say it that way. There are caveats, but let's let's keep going.
It came to be that many people started to dress up whatever they were doing in terms of computation,
right, because it was possible to seek, you know, funding from a Yuri Milner or a Mark Zuckerberg,
or, dare I say, a Jeffrey Epstein, you know, all of these sorts of things,
which had exotic funding sources or possible prizes around them in computation. It also
became the case that funders were more eager at the government level to hear a proposal for
something having a computational nature. So the problem that we have is, is that there were all
of these old ideas about, you know, of anointment, of Schrodinger, of Hawking, etc., etc., touring
about the world as a computer. And at the moment, there's a system of selective pressures that
partially has to do with how difficult it is to fund one's research. So I don't want, I'm very
worried about the event horizon of the computational paradigm. It's absolutely true what Stephen is
saying, that this is torn through theoretical physics, but I'm very dubious as I was.
No, it hasn't. No, it hasn't. Not theoretical physics. No, it hasn't.
The people aren't necessarily doing what you're saying, but they are dressing things up in terms
of computation. So I think your interesting points, I think not quite right. Okay, so you're
absolutely right that in theoretical physics, for example, quantum computing has become this
giant, you know, a fundable thing. We can talk about that separately.
Or black hole information paradoxes, or the idea of the universe as a computer, John Wheeler had
old points, but that feel. But that's not what I'm talking about. That's not what I'm talking about.
What I'm talking about is, there is a way of thinking about doing science that says,
you write down an equation, you can solve this equation, and it will tell you how the world
is going to work. Computational scientific material is sort of the old line of reductionism,
which is if we could just solve these equations, we get beautiful, closed-form solutions.
The surprising thing that, you know, I really got serious about in the 1980s was this phenomenon
where if what you think is going on is that it's just following computational rules,
then that doesn't work anymore. There's this phenomenon of computational irreducibility
where the system is doing what it does, and it's doing a computation, and we're trying to figure
out what the system does, and we're also doing a computation, and there's this thing I call the
principle of computational equivalence, which is basically the statement or the claim, which we're
getting more and more evidence for, that our ability to think through what a system does
is of the same level of computational sophistication as what the system itself does.
So we never get to outrun the system. We don't get to do what has been the kind of banner story
of a lot of traditional mathematical science, which is find this reduction, this reducible
computation where we can just say, and the system is going to do this. We're kind of stuck.
There's the issue about whether we can compute it out once we find the rules.
So the idea is that you could imagine a world in which Maxwell's equations are perfect, you know,
all the way down, and you still might not be able to compute the consequences of Maxwell's equations
like the Einstein equations like Navier-Stokes. It happens, but it's very obscure in those
equations, because when you look at the Navier-Stokes equations, the standard equations for fluid
flow, one of the most notable features of fluid flow is fluid turbulence. Fluid flows quickly,
it looks kind of random. You say to people who study the Navier-Stokes equations, can you reproduce
that from the underlying equations? Is that something that's in the underlying equations,
or is it maybe a sign of some, you know, smaller scale molecular processes that are
getting amplified, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera? So they'll typically get, I mean, these days they
have a lot of empirical ways to do it, but if you really push on the fundamental question,
they'll get kind of embarrassed because they just don't know.
It's like quark confinement. If you know the rules of quarks, can you prove that they're
not never going to be found in isolation and only going to be found typically in hadrons?
Yeah, that's a similar thing, which actually has, that particular one actually has a more
direct story of... Let's all agree that we're modern people and we don't have the old reductionist
dream. That's a non-trivial point because in theoretical physics, that point has not yet been
understood. Well, I think it has. I think that the extent to which we talk about what is emergent,
what is not, what is enthropic, what is not, we now have many concepts, including, you know,
galois sorts of, not galois, girdle sorts of concerns that are cropping up in theoretical
physics. Finally, yes. I wrote the paper about undersideability in theoretical physics back
in the early 1980s. I think it needs to be said, you know, again, by somebody who hopes to be your
competitor, that you were very early on a lot of these topics. You weren't doing it as part of a
fad. You were in fact the pioneer coming out of the computational ability of mathematics and all
that you've set up. And you've wrapped some beautiful libraries with many more functions than
anybody ever thought we could have. So, you know, kudos to you. There was a huge resistance inside
of theoretical physics because it was a very closed, arrogant community. It had many reasons to be
arrogant. It has fewer reasons to be arrogant now. And so in part, I think that you were dismissed
unfairly. It's very important that you not be the one to blow your own horn. So I would be happy
to say that I remember when that book came out, I remember the derision, the anger didn't seem to
come from anywhere in particular. And it was not listened to properly, even though I don't think
that it actually is doing what you say it's doing now. But one, happy to be wrong. And it was always
a really important point that you were making within that. I just don't think that it really
hurt. What do you make of that, Steven? Hold on a second. I want to just correct that impression.
Because the fact is, you know, I was looking at this recently, right? Insofar as there was
negativism about that book, where did it actually come from? Because there was tons of positivism.
I mean, the negativism, it turns out, was specifically concentrated in people who did
fundamental physics. And if you look outside of that area, it was not negativism, it was actually
a lot of positivism. But to steal man the critics, which I hate to do, the critics have a feeling
that there's a tiny number of fields where it's very difficult to check people. It's very hard to
say when a theoretical physicist is bullshitting. It's very hard to say when a theoretical, very pure
mathematician is speaking nonsense. So there is this fear. How do we know that what he's saying
in some sense is correct? Correct enough to interrupt, but correct enough to devote
many precious hours to unravel it. There's that, but there's not that much to unravel
at the moment. So I'm not that sympathetic with that. You know, this is sort of Sabine. I don't
have time for this stuff. My feeling is, to hell you don't have time. There's almost nothing happening.
Now, with that said, what I think is, is that there was a fear that quite honestly people like
you and like myself are cheating. And just I want to be open about this. The fear that comes out of
whatever is left of the core community is you guys don't have a right to go direct to a consumer.
You don't have a right to talk about the field that belongs to a tiny, the privilege of a tiny
number of people who do this morning, noon and night, who are all possessed of common beliefs.
And that's something that both you and I have been fighting. Now, I would also suggest that
Stephen and I probably are not eager to open the door to every lunatic with a red crayon who
wants to scribble something on a roll of paper towels and say that they've got a unified theory.
So there have to be some standards. On the other hand, the core group that's been trying to gate
this has failed. It was historically interesting to me. So I was, you know, I did particle physics
during its kind of golden age in the late 1970s when I was a late teenager, so to speak.
And I think I did pretty well. You know, a bunch of I got, you know, got was was sort of pretty
successful in the field. And I wrote a bunch of papers that still get cited because I lived in
the sort of golden age and not a lot came after that. I mean, not because they were necessarily,
you know, there was a question of picking low hanging fruit. And so that meant that I
know a large fraction of the kind of leading people in theoretical physics above some age.
I was quite surprised by the level of kind of angst when new kind of science came out.
But the typical thing that I heard was, oh, my gosh, if this is right, what we've been doing for
the last 50 years, all has to be thrown away. And I kept on saying, I don't think that's what's
going to happen. You know, and people would say to me like, you know, I was I was noticing, I think
I made a you know, wrote a sort of historical piece about this. And I described it as
Nobel Prize winners with pitchforks. And so there was a was a quite a parade. It was quite it's
quite kind of interesting looking back on it. I was going to send one of them an email actually,
just when my new thing came out. And then the person went and died. So they die or they soften.
I think what was interesting to me was at that time, 20 years ago, there was a lot of kind of,
you know, we're going to make it string theory is going to do it. We're almost there. You know,
we don't need anything else. I think that's changed now.
That's about 1984 through 86, when the string mania was at its height.
No, I think that, you know, now, you know, we've got a lot of mostly younger physicists
who are pretty seriously working on this stuff. And I think, you know, it's it's going great.
Of the older crowd, you know, I sort of been in contact with a large fraction of them. And it's
like, Oh, this seems interesting. And it's like, you should actually work on this. I keep on telling
him you should actually work on it. And some of them have, you know, been on live streams,
we've done and things like that. And we certainly talked about things. But I think,
you know, a lot of people, they do something for a living. And this isn't what they do for a living.
And I don't know whether they'll kind of make the effort to kind of turn what the change what
they do for a living. I don't know whether it matters. I think that the the concept that,
you know, it is probably particularly 20 years ago, it was still the case that the kind of
institutional structure of things like physics was very strong. As in, it was like, we have
this institutional structure, and this is how this field is going to work. And we don't do anything
from the outside. My impression is that that's weakened in the intervening years. But maybe
I'm wrong. The perception that I get from comments from people is almost like being
candid with both of you as friends. On one hand, Eric is criticized for a complexity,
a technical, you know, sort of toolkit that is beyond even many theoretical physicists. So,
you know, I disagree that, you know, they'll say, I don't have enough time, but but it is true that
there's, you know, general stock and trade of a theoretical cosmologist is not necessarily
hop vibrations, fiber bundles, etc. It might be perturbation theory, it might be quantum field
theory. And on the other side of the coin, Steven, I think sometimes the perception is it's too
simplistic, not in the sense or it's too elementary. It's too fundamental in the sense that you use
in your in your wonderful new book, which you're kind of enough to send to me. And congratulations
for writing a shorter book than a new kind of science, I think by about 40 pages. Brian gets a
copy. I think Steven will send you one or I'll give you one when we get together. I've got multiple
copies. But Steven, you know, so let me let me just start with with you for a second. Eric knows
his critics, he knows what people say, and I think he brings up a good point. Wait, I have
critics, this is the first I hear of this, Brian. There's two, one's named Pia something and the
other one. But Steven, in your case, I think it's absolutely correct that, you know, people are
blown away by the contributions. I have people, you know, asking me to thank you from the depths
of their heart for for Mathematica for new kind of science that in some ways, it's amazing that
you guys have, I get comments, I'm reading them, you save my life, you touch my life, you change
my life. It's so amazing. But on the other hand, I think that that in in real scientific circles,
oftentimes breeds a class of almost undermining and let me explain something which is which I
think is interesting. So I am that people think what I've done is simplistic is a great compliment
because I've spent a huge amount of effort trying to take the things that I'm thinking about and
make them simple enough that both I can understand them well, and I can explain them well. When I
wrote new kind of science, I even said this in the introduction, I said, the fact that this appears
to be very simple, appears to be very straightforward, will make people who thought, you know, who work
on technical science think that, you know, they must, they must really understand this and this
must be something simple and irrelevant. It isn't true. You know, the fact is, it is, it is much
more difficult, at least for me, maybe it isn't for everybody, but I think it probably is for
almost everybody, to turn things into things that can be described simply than it is to kind of,
you know, maybe there's a certain challenge to sort of building up the tower of being able to
talk about, you know, fiber bundles and self-dual connections and all this kind of thing, but,
but that's a, it's a well-defined tower you have to climb. So, for example, right now, I happen to
be working on kind of a very bizarre thing that, again, I never thought would come out, which is
a kind of a, a general theory of metamathematics. So in mathematics, one, one thinks about, you
know, there's the particular mathematics people do, the three million theorems of mathematics
that have been published in the literature of mathematics and human history, but then there's
the kind of full metamathematics of all possible theorems. And the remarkable thing is that it
looks like we can actually derive kind of the analog of Einstein's equations in metamathematical
space, a very bizarre. We keep coming to this point. I want to just put a pin here just in case
it's of interest. I don't think that it's very difficult to imagine recovering Einstein's equations
given Hilbert's contribution so that we know in a weird sense that Einstein did something very,
very difficult. And I've compared it to Half Dome where there's a sheer face that Einstein went up,
and then there's this gentle face that Hilbert went up after he knew that it could be climbed.
It seems to me that because we know that Einstein's equations results from the simplest
objective function that you could have, which is the scalar curvature in Rouhani and geometry,
that that's not a great target. I mean, it's great that you can produce something that looks like
Einstein's theory out of computational rules. The next one on the list would be Yang-Mills
theory. They're only really four basic equations. Again, the objective function is as simple as
it gets. So to Stephen's point, what we know about the current physical world is that two out of the
four equations, fundamental equations for the fields, the things that dance in our world and we call
particles or waves, both of those come from the simplest possible curvature equations that one
can have in geometry. So if you think of the geometries largely about curvature, then the two
simplest structures that can generate equations called the Yang-Mills Lagrangian or the Yang-Mills
Maxwell Lagrangian, which is just you take the size of the curvature and you square it and that's
it. And the other one is you just take a piece of the curvature without squaring it when you have
a piece to take called the scalar curvature and that's it. The other two equations have a slightly
different character. I want to leave aside the Higgs field and what we would call the Klein-Gordon
equation with the potential. But I would say the next order of business is do you find the Dirac
equation? Because it's very difficult to find spinners arising from computational rules.
So the answer is do we know how we managed to get spinner representations in the rotation group?
We know how to construct these things. There is a mystery about why they are there to construct.
Now there are people who will go to their graves saying there is no mystery, I know how to construct
it, therefore I know what it is, which is never true. I mean we only really understand something
in mathematics when we can walk all around it and see it from many different angles.
I agree that we know how to construct spinners, I know how to construct Dirac operators,
but this is a highly non-trivial question in our world. It comes out of what I call the psychedelic
of mathematics, the square root construction, where you ask a question like what is x squared
equals minus one? It has no solution in the reels. You have to jump into another space
in order to answer the question. So it has this different character which is the answer to the
problem isn't found in the space in which the problem was posed. In the case of Einstein's
equations and in the Yang-Mills equations or the souped up version of Maxwell's equations,
non-linear Maxwell theory if you will, you have something which has a character where I understand
where it comes from. In the case of the Dirac equation, you have got much bigger problems.
I tried to bring this up in the last live stream, it didn't work at all. What do you do in quantum
gravity when you don't have an observation of the metric, for example, and therefore you cannot
construct the ocean in which the electron is a wave? Now, if you think about it very carefully,
in a weird way, electrons are basically functions and photons are basically derivative operators.
That's a bizarre way to think about it. I know the mathematical physics, so I understand what
you're talking about. Then you wouldn't say it's a bizarre way at all, I don't think in any event.
What we're talking about is we're talking about versions of the xy plane and functions and
derivatives. The idea of the xy plane that grows up to become something called fiber bundles which
Stephen mentioned at the beginning. The idea of functions grows up to be something called sections
and the idea of derivatives grows up to be something called connections. These are the basic bread and
butter of what goes on before you get to the quantum. In that picture, there's a big difference
between recovering the easiest bits and recovering the hardest bits. I don't mean to put extra weight
on Stephen's shoulders. If he can do the first bits, that's great, but there's a series of challenges
that are of escalating difficulty in terms of recovery because of the simplicity of some portions
of our model and the Baroque complexity of other portions of the model. For example, the internal
quantum number assignments that give the particles their personality, the number of generations,
the chirality of the situation. It's very interesting. Stephen's rules are going to have to pick a left
or a right, so it's very interesting to how he's going to recover a chiral world.
This is silly. Let me give you my point of view here. We can talk about details of mathematical
physics. It's quite interesting. I know you know a bunch about it. We can go deeply into
how half-interjust spin versus interjusting particles work, etc. What you're doing is you're
making the paradigm shift mistake. You're talking about things in terms of existing mathematical
physics ideas. Yes, you're saying, oh my gosh, you'll never be able to get spinners.
No, I'm just saying let me just make a few points about this. Okay, I mean the fact is
we're actually hot on the trail of understanding how fermions versus bosons work. It's quite
interesting. It has to do, it seems, with cases where in our, and again, it's sort of a somewhat
complicated story, but it's these branch pairs and branch shield space, whether they end up being
things that merge after a small number of steps or not, seems to be what is the distinguishing
feature between bosons and fermions, how that relates to half-interjust spin. We don't completely
know. It seems to be related to various features of homotopy in the multi-way causal graph.
It's quite possible that some of the kinds of mathematical physics that you like a lot are
highly relevant in understanding how that homotopy works in the multi-way causal graph. It looks like
a limit of the multi-way causal graph is quite possibly related to Twister theory,
and that one can understand some of the things that happen there on the basis of Twister theory,
whether we can get, we're now understood, we've understood quite a bit about how rotational
invariance works, how angular momentum works, but it's kind of a weird business because in a
sense, we're trying to build from the machine code up. We can have a detailed mathematical
physics conversation. That's what most people are interested in. Oh, I disagree. I think that
people actually want to see whether or not, you know, both of us are saying outlandish things.
By the way, I don't think what I was saying was silly at all. It started mathematical physics.
I think it's all started mathematical physics. I'm going to invoke my referee. I'm going to
hold on. Hold on one second. I do want to point something out. I think it's very important. I've
heard this from people that I hold in high esteem, Paul Steinhart. One reason that Paul
says he refuses to ever get a Facebook or Twitter account is because he would invariably be tempted
to propose an interesting idea, which by necessity would be new, novel, untested, unproven at some
level. And then immediately it would be attacked, assailed, subjugated to constraints and concerns.
And I think you guys have both seen that for the following reason, that you both are master
explicators of what you do. You both are obviously domain experts in what you know and you understand
the other branches of physics and mathematics that are pertinent to it. However, neither one
really knows the intimacy of the other one's theories. And I think it's important to realize
that just like people assailing your theories from without, I think it's too soon to tell,
at least in the case of Stephen's work, which is, you know, in some sense, 20 years old or
coming up on 20 years old. And in some sense, it's also brand new, because I think when you look
at the successful applications, I feel like we should just check those off, Stephen. I mean,
biological systems, crystallography, you go down the list, finance, economics, where the
Wolfram approach, the new kind of science approach first outlined in 2003 or so, that has already
been proven. It doesn't need to be proven. Where I think it's different is where we lay on this extra
layer of computability as a fundamental nature of the universe, which for my perception, maybe
Stephen, correct me if I'm wrong, has sort of a multiverse component to it. You talk about
different aspects of the universe. Well, you talk in an essay that you wrote in 2017 about,
you know, the space of all universes where these rules... That was before I understood what I now
understand. Yeah. So, but we are barely coming up to where you were in 2017. So, can we take a step
back? We talked about the paradigm issue. I want to talk a little bit more about how these ideas get
into the firmament or get into the zeitgeist. Yeah, before you do that, I want to just clear
something up. Stephen, I'm not trying to scuttle your theory. I believe that your theory, if you
have an approach that works and it's a face up the same mountain, my belief is that you will get
to answer these questions. You may tell us for the first time, spiritually, what a spinner is
from a computational perspective. I'm not saying you've only done the easy stuff and the other
stuff is really hard. The stuff that you're talking about is really hard. What's going to pick out
the Riemann curvature tensor? How are you going to generate this? Great. That one's fairly easy.
Well, I believe that because it's very natural. There's a reason that in some sense it came first
before the Wu Yang dictionary. I think spinners are going to come out as the latest thing,
which is only a week old. So it's still uncooked. So we're tricking him to sharing this on the
live stream. It's exclusive. This is very good here. Well, we probably talked about it on how
working session live streams. But first point is in our models, quantum mechanics is a very natural
thing. When we think about traditional classical mechanics, it's like you throw a ball, it goes
in a definite direction. In quantum mechanics, the idea is that the ball tests out all possible
paths and then we only get to see various probabilities about what happens. In our models,
there are these things called multi-way systems, which basically are enumerating all the possible
paths. And the whole dynamics of how quantum mechanics works comes out of these multi-way
systems. Now, what happens is when you look at one of these multi-way systems at a particular time,
you take a slice through it and you get this thing we call branch shield space.
Branch shield space is the analog in the space of quantum states to physical space in kind of
ordinary position in the universe. By physical space, you mean a space like hyperspace?
These branch shield surfaces are the analog that branch like hypersurfaces, which are the analog
of space like hypersurfaces in standard spacetime. So this branch like hypersurface in branch
shield space, there's an extent in branch shield space, which is where as you move through branch
shield space, you're moving through the space of quantum entanglements. And so states that are
further away in branch shield space are less quantum entangled than states which are close
in branch shield space. What is your notion of a distance? Well, it's based on, if you look at
the multi-way graph, the nearest neighbors in branch shield space are things which have a common
ancestor one step back in the multi-way graph. So those are what we call branch pairs. I mean,
this is, unfortunately, it gets fairly... I appreciate that, but the idea is you have some
ordering by number of steps. Metric, yes. Metric like. It's based on sort of common ancestry in
the multi-way graph. And essentially what happens is, well, that thing on the left is a multi-way
causal graph. The thing on the right is a kind of play version of a kind of mixture of branch
shield space and physical space. Probably not the best visualization, but it's something. But
anyway, so the idea is there's physical space that we're all familiar with. There's this branch
shield space, which is the kind of space of quantum states, just like there's a speed of light
in physical space. In our model, there's a maximum entanglement speed in branch shield
space, which is kind of the maximum speed at which kind of you can... maximum speed of kind
of entanglement in that space. So, okay. Why is any of this relevant? Again, this is... I'm
in the Einstein equations, which have to do with physical space. One is looking at,
in the one way to view the Einstein equations, is to think about what happens to a GDC, what
happens to the path of a particle in spacetime. Essentially, what's happening in the Einstein
equations is that energy momentum causes deflections in GD6 in spacetime. In a branch
shield space, the exact same thing happens. Essentially, energy momentum causes deflections
in GD6 in branch shield space. And it turns out that that deflection process gives one the Feynman
path integral, which is really cool. And it's one of the things that I sort of found the most
elegant in the things that we've done so far in this theory, that what in physical space is
the Einstein equations in branch shield space is the path integral. Okay. Why is this relevant to
fermions and bosons? The reason it's relevant is that... Wait, wait. I just want to take a moment
to think about what you just said. You said that something in general relativity, that is Einstein's
equations, which are maximally resistant of all of our structures to quantization, is analogous,
in some ways, to the Feynman path integral, which I'm going to disagree later with your
characterization, which is Feynman's sort of characterization, the linguistic description
of what we claim is happening when we're taking one of these integrals. But the point is, is that
you're just making a claim on Poisson, which is astounding to begin with, if true. Which is that
the Einstein equations are somehow intimately bound up in the quintessential centerpiece of
quantum field theory, not even quantum mechanics. The Einstein equations... I mean,
this is a remarkable thing, which I certainly did not see coming, that the path integral is the exact
same thing as the Einstein equations, but in a different kind of space. Never heard this. Right.
So that's one of the things that we discovered like, I don't know, six, seven months ago,
that was like, wow. And those two things meet up when you think about black holes and black hole
information and so on. There's sort of this... And in fact, the ADS-CFT correspondence is almost
certainly taking this multi-way causal graph and projecting it into spacetime and projecting it
into branchial space. That it's the same graph projected in two different ways, corresponds
to the kind of general relativity ADS side of ADS-CFT and the quantum field theory CFT side of
it. That's almost certainly what that is. And various people are working on filling in the
details of that. It's pretty neat. So then, okay, you asked about fermions and bosons,
and I was going to tell you this week's kind of way of getting to that. And these are complicated
things. So it takes a few steps. Okay. So the next thing to realize is in quantum mechanics,
one of the things that emerged particularly from von Neumann's work was this idea of, there is an
amplitude. It is a complex number. It operates in Hilbert space, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
One of the things that was implicitly done was something which I think turns out to be a mistake,
which is that the magnitude and the phase of these quantum amplitudes were sort of all packaged
together. You mean the projectivization of a Hilbert space? Yes. Yes. Well, the fact that
the fact that you can think about it as a magnitude and phase is just a complex number.
In our models, what ends up happening is the magnitude and the phase come from completely
different places. And so what happens is the magnitude has to do with accounting of paths
going through this multigraph. The phase has to do with essentially where you land up in
branchial space. And actually, one of the things that we figured out about a week or two ago is
it's just unbelievably easy to get the double slit experiment to work. And we get nice pictures.
Yeah, I don't know what that means. But the first point, if I understand...
Oh, no, it's interference in quantum mechanics.
Right?
I understand that.
You mean you don't understand how it's easy. It comes out naturally in some sense.
No. What he's saying, I mean, we have to go back and unpack what the good doctor is saying.
He is talking about the fact that we claim that we work in a Hilbert space. We don't work in a
Hilbert space. We work in something called the projectivization of a Hilbert space.
And effectively, that destroys a certain amount of structure. So we begin with something like a
vector space. We remove the origin. We pluck it out like the seed out of a cherry. And then we take,
you know, all of the sort of meat and we compress it in this particular way. And what Stephen is
saying is that that is a loss of information that we teach physicists with their mother's milk,
and that this may be, in fact, throwing away information that is actually experimentally
much more important.
Well, I mean, I think that let's not go off into projective Hilbert space for a minute.
You guys never take me anywhere.
Buy me to the Hilbert space.
All right. The thing that ends up being interesting is the when you think about kind of these,
these, again, this is the kind of the sort of quantum gd6. What ends up happening is the phase
of the quantum amplitude is essentially defined by its position in Braunschild space. So you think
about these in general relativity, you'd think about, you know, a gd6 is deflected by the presence
of mass, you know, it's attracted to some massive object, moves around it, it changes the direction
of the gd6 has changed by the presence of mass. Okay. In in Braunschild space, it's the same story.
The the the gd6 is deflected by the presence of energy momentum. That presence of energy
momentum corresponds to Lagrangian and quantum field theory. And what one is doing is deflecting
that gd6, the deflection of the gd6. The interpretation of that is it's changing the
phase of the quantum amplitude. It's changing where that gd6 is going to land in Braunschild
space, which changes the phase of the quantum amplitude. And amusingly enough, what appears in
the Feynman-Path integral is exactly e to the i over h bar times the action integral. The action
integral is the integral in our world of the divergence of causal edges, which corresponds
to Lagrangian. There seem to be multiple things going on here. If I can just I do want to invoke
my my privilege here being being the moderator. We've covered the first of our six or seven topics
in 40 and an hour and 15 minutes. It's clear to me. I just want to finish on bosons for a second.
Okay, please. Yeah, please finish up. Let's move to our next, which will be experimental testability.
The flavor of of this is that what ends up happening with bosons is this kind of collection
in Braunschild space, this this kind of focusing in Braunschild space. And what seems to happen
with fermions is a divergence in Braunschild space. And it's, you know, one of the things that
I've been always been curious about is why are there only fermions and bosons? Why isn't there
lots of, you know, intermediate para statistics and so on. And I think that the answer is that
it's going to end up being the case that basically in Braunschild space, things either diverge or
they don't diverge. And that's going to but you know, there's there's much mathematical physics
packing that has to go around this. And if I could just take 15 seconds to riff off this.
Okay, you have a situation in which the great thing about general relativity, for example,
is that all you need is length and angle. And length and angle turns out to amount to a derivative
operator, which turns out to have mixed partials that don't commute, you can measure their failure,
that's the curvature, you knock it down with linear algebra, and you create grab. It's a miracle.
It's fantastic. On the other hand, it's not that surprising that if you have a situation in which
you have some notion of like size and perpendicularity, that you can create something like that. For
example, you do have something called malinobus distance that you can get out of data, you can
treat a covariance matrix like a Ramanian metric, if you will. So there are all sorts of ways in
which we already know that they're that the discrete that anything that leads to length and
angle becomes geometric. And I think that, you know, that's both very good for Dr. Wolfram,
and it is also just a bit of caution for the rest of us that on the the early part may lead you on
because it's a different way of describing length and angle and the consequences, which
thanks to both Einstein and Grossman and I guess, Hilbert, we know that all we're looking for in some
sense is the most basic consequence of that. It'll be cool to see it come out. And I do
believe that you you may likely get fermions out of a question. You may have to ask the question
about how to take the square root of something. I'll be astounded if you have fermions without
taking a square root. But the key feature, you know, is that you're not that far away from geometry
as soon as you're talking about malinobus distance and covariance matrix and data.
Okay, so, you know, the one cool thing is that the uncertainty principle in our theory is basically
the analog of Riemann curvature in branchial space. So the the non commuting of variables
is just like a non commuting. And in geometric quantization, it is literally the curvature
tensor on in the Hamiltonian picture. Absolutely. So by the way, in terms of the square root thing,
I have the following guess, okay, that what basically happens in branchial spaces, you have
these branch pairs, and they converge. Okay, branch pairs. Next step, they converge. I think
that the boson cases, they diverge and they converge. The fermion cases, they diverge and
they don't converge. And so in some sense, the square root is being taken by the fact that you
are having the the beginning of that diamond, but not the end of the diamond. Sounds like the
difference between commutators and anticommutators. Yeah, yeah, it's the it's the it's my my first
guess about how that works. And it'll it's I mean, the thing that again, I thought we were going to
have to, you know, find actual electrons to be able to distinguish fermions and bosons,
it's seeming increasingly likely that we can basically understand fermions in bulk without
having to know exactly how particles work. What I want to do now is sort of compare and contrast
different approaches, not necessarily only from the two of you. But in the in the context that I
often get, well, first of all, the common thing that I get from all my, you know, friends on Reddit
or wherever else this gets posted is, you know, how come these things aren't being peer reviewed
and what kinds of falsifiable predictions are they making? Let's start with the latter. Steven,
you and I talked back in April, and you made it clear that things such as the fundamental
constants of nature, the speed of light are emergent or embedded encoded encrypted within
within your new findings. I want to know, are there new predictions that could be used instead
of retradictions? Not that they don't have validity, not that they don't have a value.
After all, Einstein, you know, in some sense validated his his theory on a retradiction,
which was known for a million, you know, millions of years. It was known for years,
the perihelion advance of the planet Mercury, and it had to be reconciled with with Einstein's
predictions. And through observations, it was found to be true. I want to know,
Steven, are there new fundamental predictions that you can can point to that have at least,
in principle, a chance of being detected? And then I'll have a similar question for Eric.
Well, let's see, I don't do the the dueling theories theory, but but yeah, falsifiability is a
weird concept that has all kinds of problems. But the fact is, you know, first thing is,
the number one thing that we're building is a framework, like calculus.
Calculus is not something that's falsifiable. Calculus is a framework for doing things.
Second question is, does calculus usefully apply to the universe? That's something we can
validly ask. And that's something that, you know, we can, there are things which are sort of generic
predictions from the framework. So the thing we're trying to do right now is what people
should do when they first introduce some, you know, new set of ideas, which is,
can we actually reproduce? Can we make theoretical predictions? Can we reproduce what
what what has been known before? And can we get out vastly more than we put in? Yes, we put very
little in. And the question is, do we get all these things out? Or do we have to add some special
clues to get fermions? Or do fermions come out naturally, as soon as we understand how to get
there? And the thing which has been remarkable so far is, you know, we've been checking off,
do we get this, do we get that, do we get that? So far, touch wood, no clues. I mean, so far,
it's been hard work. But nothing has been like, Oh, my gosh, the universe, you know,
the theory predicts the universe should be 26 dimensional, we have to explain why it's not
type thing. We haven't had any of those kind of, you know, clues barriers, so to speak.
So that's encouraging. Now, in terms of actually making specific, measurable predictions,
a couple of issues. First issue is going from the raw theory, the low level machine code,
to something where you turn a telescope in that direction, and you see a particular thing.
There's lots of, you know, there's lots of hard work and lots of astrophysics and so on to be done
in going from one place to another. That's first point. The second point is that to actually make
one of the things in our theory is there is one scale. Same happened with Einstein's theory,
actually. Although, for various reasons that, well, we can talk about that, but there's one scale,
which is this maximum entanglement speed. We don't know what the value of that is. We have
some guesses, but we don't know its value. If we knew its value, we would have a whole bunch of
predictions immediately. But we don't know its value. Einstein had the same problem. He had the
cosmological constant. He didn't know its value. It's, you know, a lot of predictions he might
have liked to make. He couldn't make because he didn't know the value of the cosmological constant.
You know, he had one meta prediction was that the universe wasn't expanding, he thought,
which is why he added his cosmological constant in the first place. But that's his scale. So then
he had a few scale independent predictions, in particular, the, you know, the bending of light
around the sun being a factor of two larger than I've been predicting the previous theory,
things like that. So one thing that we've been interested in is what scale independent predictions
can we make? That's question one. And question two, what predictions can we make that are,
as soon as we know this one scale, we immediately have predictions. And then which predictions can
we make that have the shortest distance in terms of the tower of astrophysics or particle physics
or whatever they have to be done. It's a cautionary tale that like Newton, for example, you know,
he goes through his whole, you know, Principia, and he works out lots of things about his law of
gravity. And he has a section about the moon. And the section about the moon ends with the
sentence, I think, but the abs of the moon is twice as great. In other words, he got the wrong
answer. And, you know, one might have said, Oh, my gosh, he got the wrong answer, he better abandon
the whole theory and run away, so to speak. Turns out it was just hard to do those calculations. It
took another 150 years to get them nailed down. So that wasn't, you know, so one has to be a little
bit an Einstein also, you know, the first time he computed the bending of light around the sun,
he got it wrong. And it was, you know, fortunate, the first, you know, experiment that was going
to be done on that didn't end up getting done because of World War One. And so, you know,
by the time an experiment did get done, he'd managed to get the right answer, whether the
experiment was right, it's a different story. But that's, that's another, another thing. But I
think that the so the question of, you know, do we have kind of scale independent predictions?
The answer is quite possibly. I think there's one quite likely one that has to do with
two photon correlations for photons in orbit around rotating black holes,
is a slightly obscure thing, but it's not completely out of the range of what's
experimentally accessible. Other, I mean, it's kind of amusing that that's so bizarrely similar,
it's a kind of a quantum analog of Einstein's, you know, bending of light around the sun type thing.
But, you know, that's one kind of thing. Another thing is a suggestion, at least from the theory,
about the existence of particles much lighter than the electron, maybe 10 to the 20th times
lighter than the electron. That number depends on the scale parameter that we don't know.
The existence of such particles probably has a bunch of implications for dark matter,
which are things that we're planning to work out. There are a bunch of implications for cosmology.
I mean, there's an expectation, not a necessary feature, but a suggestion, at least from the model,
that the universe starts kind of infinite dimensional and only gradually kind of
decay down to the sort of modest three dimensions that we have now. That has a bunch of implications
for inflationary scenarios for the universe and so on. You know, I think the most outlandish
possibility, which I don't think will actually happen, is that still at the time of recombination,
you know, when your cosmic microwave background globe was minted, so to speak, that there would
still be a trace of some of the early discrete processes that happened in the very early stages
of the universe. I really doubt that it would have survived that long. But if it did, the absolutely
outlandish possibility is that the kind of the rule for the universe might be painted in the
microwave background radiation, which would be truly wrong. I don't think that would happen.
I think it's very unlikely. But, you know, early density perturbations, there might be some things
that would be a result of this changing dimensional scenario that's rather different from the traditional
exponential expansion and four dimensional space, space time of inflationary cosmology.
That's on the one side. On the particle physics side, and well, one of the things is that it's
looking very much as if quantum computing at some fundamental level can't work. However,
seeing that and seeing the actual effects of our theory for decoherence and things like that,
it's not at all clear that the can't work point is something experimentally accessible.
And I think that the, you know, it's a question. There's some clever experiment that can be done
in quantum computing that could see this maximum entanglement speed. That's basically the,
and we don't know what the value of that speed is, so we can't really tell. What estimate that we
have of that speed is 10 to the five solar masses per second. If that estimate is correct,
then it is possible that in black hole, well, it's possible that we'll make small
effect in a black hole merger of, you know, one and a half solar mass type size would have a bigger
effect if, you know, two sort of central black holes of two galaxies happen to collide and merge,
then there will be a bigger effect. It's also conceivable that there might be an effect when
black holes initially form. And this is an astrophysics question for you, Brian. How long does
it take a black hole to actually form? Once you have in falling matter, the question is what the
actual weather in 10 to the minus five seconds, something, whether one can tell what's happening
in the last 10 to the minus five seconds of the formation of a black hole. If one can,
and if our estimate of the maximum entanglement speed is right, then there will probably be
differences from the predictions of general relativity for that case.
This is a big question, primordial black hole formation, the end of inflation. These are really
important questions that, you know, it's good to it's good to hear, especially that you're,
you know, providing potential full employment for my graduate students.
Yes, there will be lots of work to do in figuring out the consequences of these things. I mean,
it's a particularly when we get this kind of way of actually doing computations in general
relativity from our model, set up as a piece of practical numerical relativity, and that that
will probably happen fairly quickly. We'll actually be able to see a bunch of these effects
directly in the computations that we do, but there'll be, you know, just layers of astrophysics
to do. And Eric, I want you to sort of opine on this provocative question that I'm being asked
in the chat room. And that is, you know, what of what value is a theory if it is not to be
testable, you know, that which can be claimed without evidence can be dismissed without
evidence as our friend Christopher Hitchens used to say, I believe. So in the context of
geometric unity, I'm not asking you to talk about somebody else's book, but talk, talk your own
book for a second. Are there things that are testable by graduate students in my group or other
brilliant students around the world? Are there predictions? Are there retradictions that are
crisp enough to, to satisfy Popper A? And do you think we should continue to feed Popper as he had
enough Pop Pop Pop Popper corn? The first point would be there's a missing layer between you and
myself. What we do typically Stephen notwithstanding is is that we come up with a classical model
in the form of some sort of geometry. Hopefully it quantizes itself or something like
geometric quantization. And then we try to figure out what the testable consequences are in any
given energy level through a bunch of phenomenologists, experimentalists, and pure quantum field theorists
working hand-in-hand in our harmonious fashion, at least that's the theory.
Given that we have a missing layer, there's tons I can say about what's new, what's different,
and what my theory says, and effectively what would make it wrong.
So I'm happy to get into that because it effectively says that a lot of our standard
verbiage around what we've found is in fact wrong.
So for example, standard thing is the world is chiral, the weak force sees the difference
between our left hand and our right hand, spiritually speaking.
My claim is that the world is not fundamentally chiral, it is emergently chiral, and that
in fact it begins in a non-chiral fashion which solves the problem that Sabina does
not see, which is what chooses whether it's going to be the left half or the right half
effectively that makes up us in some sense.
Can we already know from neutrino masses that we're not seeing a completely chiral situation?
We can get into the issue of how to interpret neutrino masses.
My claim would be that we have entire sectors that we're not seeing.
So for example, unadorned spin one-half bundles that would be tensored with, if you will,
the conjugate of the 16-dimensional representation which imparts the particles, their personalities.
So that is not something that's seen, and I've analogized it, for those of you watching
at home rather than listening, where you have a hand and you see with three fingers in the
middle that you think there's a symmetry in the hand, and then you have this problem about
how do I make my pinky look like my thumb, and you don't realize that there's an entire
other hand and that it's thumb-to-thumb, and pinky-to-pinky, not pinky-to-thumb, it's the
symmetry.
There is a non-chiral world that is emergently chiral, which is fooling us into thinking it's
fundamentally chiral.
There are only two generations, not three generations.
People will immediately say, well, how do you explain the fact that we've seen the tau
particle in the top and bottom works, and the claim is that is not a generation because
it will not unify as you heat the soup up in the same way as the first two generations
will unify.
In fact, it will unify with another collection of particles, also spin one-half, which I
believe, if I recall correctly, the thing that will be misinterpreted as an internal
representation, I think will be like 112 dimensional rather than 16.
There will be no internal representations.
There will be no internal symmetries.
This has been a huge trip up for things like supersymmetry, where we keep looking for these
super partners, which I've analogized a little bit to what happens if you're convinced that
Spiderman should be, in fact, Clark Kent, should be accompanied by Clark Kent, and Peter Parker
should be accompanied by Superman.
We have this wrong.
There is no internal symmetry, nor should you expect internal symmetry, because this comes
out of two fundamental origin stories, one for the spacetime manifold, another for effectively
the y-axis above that as the x-axis.
We decide that somehow we have spacetime and Einstein, and then somehow we get this thing
called SU3 cross SU2 cross U1 that falls out of the sky, which is a second origin story.
There is not two origin stories.
There is one.
Einstein, I believe, one of the problems, Stephen, I'm going to say, is that we have
been in a very difficult position relative to Einstein, because unlike anyone else, because
of the thought experiments, we have a reverence for not only what he gave us in terms of equations,
but also how he thought the beautiful humanity that he imparted to everyone, so we don't
want to harm him in any way.
It's also the fact that he was wrong, and he was wrong in an interesting way, in the
same way I believe that Newton was wrong, and we souped up Newton with Einstein, but
that physics is taking place, in my opinion, on two separate spaces.
You can call x and y, or Brian, I've joked with you, calling it Harris and Hushamai,
the heaven and the earth.
In these two spaces, there is a map between, and that is the map that, in fact, Einstein
started playing with, but he did not think to pull back the information from space two
onto space one, from space x to space y.
I believe that there is a deformation complex, which in the Euclidean signature is elliptic,
which in fact tells us why the self-dual equations and the Tren Simons-Gabe's theory that were
studied in the late 70s, early 80s, are so important.
In fact, it was a special example of a much more general structure, comes out of geometric
unity.
That there is not two kinds of geometry in this situation.
One Riemannian geometry underlying general relativity, an Erismanian geometry of fiber
bundles underlying the standard model.
There is, in fact, one geometry, and that one geometry is why it's called geometric
unity, and it has to do with the difficulty of a lie that we tell in general relativity,
which is that we say that it is a so-called gauge theory, where we try to get the gauge
group to be something called the diffeomorphism group, or general coordinate variance.
We allow it to act on the space of metrics, whereas in the case of the standard model,
we have a space, not of metrics, but of derivative operators from calculus called connections,
and the group we have is the gauge group.
The gauge group is an infinite dimensional beast that acts on the space of connection.
We do not understand, in fact, that telling this lie to make general relativity look like
a gauge theory, in fact, block progress, and that we should treat it as an honest gauge
theory.
We are going to have to recognize that the cosmological constant is not constant.
It is a field which acquires a BEV, or a vacuum expectation value, as it is lured away by topological
mechanisms.
We are going to see that we got the Lorentz group wrong.
We focused on the Lorentz group when we meant to be focusing on the gauge group.
We formed its inhomogeneous extension called the Poincare group.
In fact, you're supposed to extend it by something called ad-valued one-forms to create, effectively,
the inhomogeneous gauge group.
That is the object on which you're supposed to do supersymmetric analysis.
Our concept of supersymmetry is wrong.
In effect, we're acting on the wrong group.
We've chosen Minkowski space as the naturally occurring affine space that is not the right
place to be playing.
The right place to be playing is the space of connection.
There's a huge number of things I can tell you about the missing matter.
What in our sector, its SU3 cross SU2 cross U1 internal quantum numbers will be 16 new
particles that are spin 3 halves with conjugate internal quantum numbers.
The same thing as our usual 16 dimensional representation, but the complex conjugate thereof,
which we have not seen yet, and explaining why the illusion of three generations is generated
by what would be called branching rules with respect to Lie algebra and Lie group representation
decomposition.
Yes, I can tell you a bunch of new particles.
I can tell you about non-kirality, the number of generations, how Einstein is wrong, what
spaces we're supposed to be doing this on, and then there's a question about, okay, well,
what can you tell us about the accelerators?
By the way, this is all subject to, if my theory is correct, but it gets boring to say
if my theory is correct over and over again.
There should just be a general caveat that all of this assumes geometric unity is in fact
correct.
Yes, there's a ton of specificity, and Brian, I'm looking forward to coming down to UCSD
and actually doing it.
Let me just say something.
I've been very pissed off about this claim that what I'm talking about, different from
what Dr. Wolfram is talking about, is so impenetrable and difficult.
It really has to do with the sickness in our field that our field just isn't interested
in some sense because it doesn't believe.
We all know that the problems have gotten so difficult and so hard, and so many smart
people have been over them, that a sense of learned helplessness has invaded the field,
which we have to talk about.
People no longer feel like they're actual physicists that can connect to Schrodinger
or Heisenberg or Dirac or Einstein or Planck.
People don't even feel like Weinberg and Yang were still with us, or in some sense,
nobody's gone to, I see, losing the Nobel Prize at Brian's shoulder.
Nobody's gone to Stockholm for advances in fundamental physical theory, since the theories
put forward since the early 1970s.
I think that's a correct statement.
All the people who've contributed to the fundamental canon are either dead or septigenarians or
higher, I think.
Maybe Frank Wilczek was born in 1951, is at the end of the 60s.
We have to recognize that this sense that it is impossible has caused lots of us to
start faking it and to start calculating what we need to do for our careers rather than
how to actually advance the science, which is one reason that both Stephen and I are
viewed as incredibly brash, effectively too brusque, maybe too arrogant.
The answer, I believe, is that we have to drive this field out of its sense that it's
playing at physics rather than doing physics.
It's talking around physics.
One of the things I want to do on these live streams is I want to actually talk about the
meat of the theories and let people scurry to Wikipedia or help each other out to try
to understand what is said rather than make it an enjoyable product for everybody.
I agree.
But Stephen has said earlier, this is simple.
It's not easy.
It's not trivial.
My nine-year-old, who you'll meet someday, hopefully both of you guys, he can play around
with rule 30.
He can get stimulated.
He can engage with it.
So when you say that it's not difficult, I don't agree that there's a character class
that differentiates, and I'm not pitting it one against another.
For certain, there are more complicated models than even Eric's, in my opinion.
Wait, wait.
How is my model complicated?
I'm just a simple experimentalist.
Fourteen-dimensional dual spaces, and look, if it's too complicated for Sabina to understand,
I think our general...
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
This is just unfair, and I want to be very clear about it.
If you talk about general relativity, which Stephen has been talking about throughout
our live stream, he's talking about the idea that you have a space, call it X, and it has
a metric on it.
And that metric is a map into the space of all possible metrics, call that Y.
That X and that Y are where geometric unity lives.
So with all due respect to Sabina and her, I can't understand anything.
It's also complicated.
You've got to map between the chronospacetime and the space of metrics.
That Romani metric is simply a map between two topological spaces.
It's not that complicated.
I don't...
Brian, it's just not true.
Okay.
Let's move on, actually.
I want to make a few comments about...
Okay, Stephen, go ahead.
So maybe people will find interesting.
I mean, so, you know, maps between topological spaces, diffeomorphisms, these kinds of ideas.
But, you know, I happened to learn these ideas when I was a kid.
Most people don't.
These are fairly...
Most people learn those ideas in, I don't know, mid-math college, if they go to a fancy
college, maybe math, graduate school, those kinds of things.
They happen to be fairly complicated.
There are fields of science where people can contribute without having gone to graduate
school.
There are other fields where they can't contribute very much.
We see that in people.
One of the great things about kind of some of these computational areas of science is
that because it's kind of, you know, because it's very new territory, it's possible for
people to contribute without having kind of gone to graduate school and learned a whole
big stack of concepts.
One of the things, you know, I get pretty much every day, you know, a theory of physics
from somebody.
Eric's version is, you know, he went to Harvard and got a PhD in mathematical physics.
So his version is much better dressed than most of the versions that I see.
Okay?
And most of the versions that I see are, you know, I find it disappointing because it feels
like people are, you know, writing poetry that nobody's going to read and they're doing
it using kind of high school level physics knowledge.
It's mostly cranks.
People who may be well-meaning, but they don't realize that they're way out of their
depth.
Yeah.
Right.
But the main thing is that they don't know what got done in the 20th century in physics.
What got done in the 20th century in physics requires kind of graduate school level knowledge
to understand.
And we can say it isn't true, but it is true.
I mean, it's, you know, general relativity and quantum field theory, you know, Eric
may say they're simple theories.
I think they're kind of simple theories, but that's because I learned about them when
I was, I don't know, 12, 13 years old and by now they seem like simple theories.
And if it's simple to you or if it's even marginally complex to Stephen, what, what
helped?
So just the whole language of talking about things, you know, this is kind of math, graduate
school type language.
And that's, now, is there a way to state these things about fiber bundles and so on without
sort of super fancy language?
Quite possibly.
Maybe some of the things we're trying to do will give away to do that.
And that's part of the hope of just bringing your communities together.
Let me move on just because we don't know much time.
You guys are very gracious with your time.
I want to respect it.
And I have kids to put to bed.
And I do want to ask the following question that my audience is asking when we think about
the power of these different approaches.
Let's take a step away from either one of yours.
There's been a lot made about artificial intelligence and the prospects for as Max Tegmark has put
it, you know, an artificial physicist and artificial Galileo.
What role do you guys see artificial intelligence playing?
And then you know where I'm going next.
I know that you guys know I'm going to the simulation hypothesis.
And I've talked to you guys individually, maybe offline about this, but the audience
is very keen to know your two esteemed gentlemen, what you think about the prospects for AI and
as a benefit to physics.
And then later we'll ask about the simulation hypothesis.
Let me start with Steven, please.
I mean, I've worked on what is now called AI for about 40 something years.
So I know a tiny bit about it.
A lot of, I don't know, I don't know where to start.
I mean, if you're talking about machine learning, if you're talking about, oh, let's sort of
throw everything we know about physics into a machine learning system and see whether it
can figure out the laws of physics.
That's one level.
Yeah, that's one level.
Noam Chomsky, who was on my show and said, you know, he has, he's sanguine about what
you just described, perhaps as his max tag mark, but the true creative stroke, he has
no, you know, the kind of it's a little bit complicated because in, you know, computational
irreducibility tells us that we can know the rules for something, but have no way to kind
of have a large scale narrative for how the thing happens.
So in other words, we might say, yes, we've succeeded.
We found rules that reproduce physics.
You say, well, tell me how they work.
You say, well, here are the rules.
But you say, well, tell me a story about how they work.
Tell me a high level, you know, version of how they work.
That may not be possible.
I mean, for example, in linguistics, picking on, on Noam Chomsky's area, you know, we may
have a description of how brains work and how brains process language at a sort of
microscopic computational level.
And we may still, and it may be completely accurate.
And we may still not have anything we would call a satisfactory science of linguistics.
So in other words, it's a, it's a slightly complicated thing.
And the question of whether, you know, whether we can get a current, you know, machine learning
system to reverse engineer the laws of physics, you know, to some extent, you can do that to
a fantastic extent of, of figuring out everything.
You won't be able to do that.
I don't think and, and, you know, the challenge, again, we keep on coming at things at really
weird angles, but there's a, you know, okay, the way I see it, there's kind of what's possible
in the computational universe, what simple programs can do.
There's this kind of ocean of computational possibility.
There's what we humans understand.
That's another kind of piece.
And there's also what the physical universe does.
And, you know, I've spent a large part of my life trying to bridge between the sort of
ocean of computational possibility and what we humans understand, that's the whole sort
of point of the computational language I've built is to have a way to have humans be able
to think about things computationally and be able to communicate what they want in a
computational fashion.
Now we have the sort of third piece of physics.
And the question is how we describe, you know, how we make this bridge between sort of the
physical universe, doing what it does, our ability to tell a narrative about what's going
on, and this kind of computation in the middle as this kind of mediator of those two things.
But I mean, this is, it's a mess.
I would say that there's a, there's a, I mean, this is a longer discussion.
And I think there's probably the wrong angle to come at it with.
If you say, are we going to have a, a, you know, a magic thing that we can throw stuff
into and get out the theory of physics?
Well, I doubt it.
You know, you talked about the simulation argument, I might, I always find it kind of
charming that people say, you know, I'm an atheist.
I believe in science.
You know, what I believe is that, you know, there's this, we're in this universe and this
universe is actually a simulation operated by operated by the universe.
But I'm an atheist.
Exactly.
Right.
And then all the morality that entails therein.
Yes.
Right.
But, but I think that the, more seriously, I think that that sort of argument is kind
of philosophically doomed because by the time you have definite laws for physics, there
isn't much for the God to do, so to speak.
Now, the only thing you might say is, but the God gets to pick the laws of physics,
except that we now seem to have found that it actually doesn't matter what the laws
of physics are, that in some sense, in this kind of, again, for reasons that again, this
is a slightly longer story.
But what matters is that we are observing physics in a certain way, and that's what
gives us the laws that we believe to be laws of physics.
And there really isn't, in a sense, there's nothing for the, for the God to do other
than to decide that our universe is going to be computational, not hyper computational,
not below computational.
And even if those other sort of kind of conceptual universes exist, we, you know,
again, it's a matter of science to be able to say that we simply can't communicate with them.
They're simply, they're just not things which are in any way connected to what we can perceive.
So I think it's a, it's a, I do like the idea, though, that there's a connection between sort
of AI physics and the simulation argument.
I think that's a, that's a, that's an interesting and bizarre connection, which,
which I think would be fun to unpack some more.
And Eric, you want to opine on this or would you, yeah, go ahead.
I don't really know whether it even requires AI and, or AGI.
There's a particular kind of move that we haven't programmed into computers yet,
so far as I'm aware.
Now, Stephen probably knows this much better than I do, but there's a weird move that comes
up over and over again, which has to do with reaching for something outside of your model
and knowing what to reach for.
So for example, you have a problem with the weak interactions that a new neutron when it decays
into a proton and an electron called beta decay doesn't seem to have enough energy in the final
products to conserve energy from the initial products.
So Pauli had to.
Oh yeah.
Okay.
You're explaining how new tree knows come to be.
Yeah.
Okay.
Fine.
Yes.
Right.
Because it's like one of the most important stories we have.
Not everybody knows it.
You have a problem that you've got three lines coming into a point and there's a failure of
conservation of momentum.
And so you have to hypothesize a fourth line.
You had a different problem when Dirac came out with his theory, which is, is that he only had
the electron and the proton, they were oppositely charged.
So we decided that one was the antiparticle of the other.
Instead, this is the part, you know, similar to the Peter Parker-Clarke-Kent issue,
he should have hypothesized a positron to be the anti-electron, to be the anti-electron
and an antiproton to be the antiparticle of the familiar proton.
That move was too much.
And in fact, Heisenberg chastised it.
There's an issue about understanding how spin comes about.
So effectively, when I've said that the square root is the psychedelic of mathematics,
you have to give your computer program psychedelics effectively so that it can invent new stuff.
That is, I can join something called i or i, j and k to solve a problem that was posed in the
real numbers.
And then I get the quaternions with complex numbers or even the actonians.
I'm going to augment my theory of something called differential forms to something called
the theory of spinners.
Can you discover something called the fofian, which is the square root of the determinant
for a particular class of matrices?
Can you discover that the Euler class is in a certain sense the square root of something
called the Pontriagin class?
All of these things are these non-trivial moves where something that is not present in
the initial formulation is guessable as the thing that would be needed to complete the
stuff that we can see with stuff that we can't to get a consistent system.
If you can teach a computer about primitives and give it the ability to guess outside of
the system that you've taught it so that it can self-adjoin.
And I don't see any impediment to this currently.
You would have a system that would be potent enough to explore not only the theory that
you feed it, but the theories that it can build from that theory.
And in essence, the computer program is being asked to do something similar than what we're
asking theoretical physics to do.
Again, everybody complains about how complicated this is and I'm sick and tired and bored of
hearing it.
Steven's correct.
You do have to learn some level of mathematics.
Typically, this would be somewhat like learning the French language before exploring French
literature.
Yeah, it's expensive.
If you want to learn a foreign language, it costs money.
In time, same thing for learning differential geometry in quantum field theory.
The situation that we're facing is that your computer program has to be capable of building
larger worlds by adjoining things that would make puzzles in the worlds that it knows about
make sense.
And that process of inferential guessing outside of anything that's been taught is a different
problem than the problem of finding, let's say, chess moves or go moves by being able to search
a larger space where the search space is implicit in the rules.
So do I believe that it requires AGI?
Now, one of the stories that I don't think we talk that much about is how much we thought AGI or
artificial general intelligence would be needed to do all sorts of things.
And the great surprise is we don't need anything like artificial general intelligence
to do most of the things that supposedly intelligence systems now do.
We thought that AGI and our consciousness and our intelligence was necessary.
It turns out that much less is usually necessary.
It is entirely possible that we don't need to wait around and we can have the computers guess it.
And to the issue of atheism and the simulators and the simulated, we have two separate stories,
one story in which we are going to build the intelligence, the AGI fear, which it's going
to be smarter than us.
We have another one in which we are the simulated and there's the simulated tour somewhere else.
If you put the two stories together, you see that in a weird way, God should be scared about us
becoming intelligence when we finally learn what our source code is.
This is the moment where Skynet becomes self-aware.
And the thing that nobody sees coming is that we are the AI.
We are the AGI that emerged in somebody else's system.
And whether or not that somebody else was sentient or not is a different question.
But Einstein asked this thing.
He said, I don't care about the spectrum or this or that element.
What really bothers me is whether or not the creator had any choice or what interests me
is whether the creator had any choice in the way the world was made.
This is an interesting concept of not being all powerful, but being all constrained.
And perhaps the creator's sole function, if you will, is to turn on the lights.
And everything else follows from that.
This is sort of a Leibnizian monad construction where the idea is that the rules effectively
tell us what is going to happen and there's very little room for anything else.
But I think that part of the reason we keep asking these questions is to be blunt pessimism.
Rather than working on the actually hard stuff, either in Stephen's case of trying to do it
through computation or my case of trying to remain within the standard mathematical tool kit.
People are so frustrated that we waste our lives talking about the mathematical universe
hypothesis, the simulation hypothesis.
We do all sorts of nonsensical work on theories that have nothing to do with physical reality.
And I just think it would be better if we stopped wasting our time talking around physics
and started talking about physics itself.
Well, guys, I have to go.
You guys have been so generous with your time.
You've answered a lot of questions that the audience had.
And for that, I'm very thankful from both coasts.
Any final words, Stephen?
I did think there was going to be one question you wanted to ask us about peer review
and our attitudes towards it, which I think people are going to want to know.
I think we should wrap it up.
Maybe we'll take that up on a future podcast with you guys individually.
The time has really come to go, or I'll be in a lot of trouble with a multiverse of children
screaming at me.
Stephen, anything you'd like to leave the audience with, any way that they can engage
and perhaps participate in the exciting work of Wolfram Research?
Use Wolfram Language, use Wolfram Alpha.
You can come to live streams we do frequently about the physics project.
You can look at the physics website.
You'll find all of the programs and things there.
It seems like people are finding this stuff, which is great.
And we'll put a link to the YouTube channel where folks can find your many, many live streams
and presentations as well.
Eric, something for closeout, where can people find you and engage with you?
Come find us at the portal.
I think there's also an Eric Weinstein.org.
Look for the Geometric Unity presentation, which was a special presentation within the
Portal series.
I am looking forward to hosting Stephen getting into the thick of his theory and how it works.
I think that one of the things that people should get engaged with is both why people
are so pessimistic and negative about every new emergence.
You should learn about the no-go theorems and all of the things that a theory would have to fit.
I don't think people are particularly negative.
I mean, honestly, we've been playing up the negativism.
But honestly, what I'm seeing is people being very enthusiastic about what we're doing.
So far, I haven't seen anybody.
I'd be interested to hear from somebody credible who says, I mean, you've said,
I don't believe your theory.
Wait a second.
No, I believe that your theory is either going to reproduce a lot of what it is that we already
know and then tell us something new potentially.
I'm not disagreeing with it.
I've said that it might be a face up to some common subject.
It's certainly not the face that I'm taking.
We should hash that out when we do each other's podcasts.
The issue that I wanted to get to, though, is, yeah, there is a lot of negativity.
You can read about it in the Reddit comments.
You can read about it very often left in the YouTube comments.
Some people in the field are very disgruntled.
Very few people have wanted to say, I've waited in.
I've tried to look at it.
I've really kind of to understand it.
And I still think these guys are talking crap.
I think Steven's exactly right that the coincidence of his work and my work being on the same show,
I don't see any need to fit them together.
And I think that if they're both right, then they would have to be fit together.
And most probably, of course, they're both wrong because that we have to say these words.
With that said, get excited about people who are trying to find ways out of the learned
helplessness that comes out of the no-go theorems, the pessimism that came out of the LHC.
I disagree with Steven.
I still think that there is a core community that's angry that people outside are speaking to the world
through this direction.
They may be angry about you.
I don't think they're very angry about me, at least not that.
Yeah, maybe they were.
There is pessimism.
I think Eric's talking specifically.
I guarantee you there are people angry about you too, Steven.
It's not just about me.
It's in general that we're all up against a question where nobody has any precedent.
I think people have one thing that I think is the case is that what I've noticed,
for example, about peer review, which we're not going to talk about here in detail,
but it's the people who say peer review is amazing.
We need peer review on not people inside science.
They're not people who actually know it up close because up close, it's actually people.
In fact, one thing's kind of amusing.
We set up a peer review system for our project and to date,
not a single person has submitted a peer review.
Not a single person.
It's been several months now.
How can people submit reviews of it?
It just says there's just a link that says peer review.
It's next to each one of our documents.
I encourage people to do it.
I mean, honestly, I'm disappointed.
I thought at least a few people would do it, even if they were like,
I didn't really read this, but it's all nonsense anyway.
But what we actually asked for, more specifically, which I think is useful,
is somebody to say, I read section 3.7, and I think it's correct,
or I think there's this mistake in it or whatever else.
We have had people like Sabine Hossenfeldt, an eminent scientist,
and she's written a video, which is the first time you guys appeared together,
where she criticizes these theories.
And she's an eminent fundamental theorist.
We've been an email correspondence with her,
and she asked a bunch of questions, which were very valid questions.
So we gave her answers, and she disappeared.
So if she's still saying she doesn't know what's going on, then there's a problem.
Well, the fact is, is that you've answered her questions.
She had questions that were reasonable, and that's the beginning of the process.
Then if she continues to say, well, he hasn't answered my questions
after he's answered the questions, and she hasn't responded,
then we're in a different situation.
Yeah, then we can actually-
I know Sabine can be kind of gruff and unpleasant,
but I know her to be reasonably fair in most circumstances.
Very good. Thank you guys.
You guys are really spectacular.
It's so generous of you to spend your time,
and we got to see different sides of your ideas
and try to reach some sense of different approaches that are radically different,
and perhaps, but they have the same common goal,
which is to really introduce the world to concepts
take us out of our quotidian existence of politics, sports, and whatever,
the grandest concepts.
I think we should have talked about those here.
That would have been more interesting for me.
Let's do more where we actually treat the people who want to get into the meat of it,
because I think that-
No, no. I was saying less meat, because I don't think this was so useful,
because I think that I felt like we would have done better talking
about kind of the culture of science and so on.
I'm sorry. I take all the blame.
Yes, I know. I'm sorry. It's my fault for not getting to that.
Thank you, Steven. Thank you, Eric. I love your work. Bye, guys.