Hey everyone, my name is Olaf and today I will teach you how to render an animation
in Eevee in Blender 2.8 and as always it's going to be quick and easy, so let's get
started.
Okay, so start off by going to the Blender 2.8 website in the description and make sure
to download one of the test files, so let's download Ember Forrest and then go to download
Blender 2.8 beta and then select Blender 2.8.
Okay, so let's open a file in Blender, so go to file and then click open and then select
the file you have and click open Blender file.
Okay, so now we have the Ember Forrest file with the animation, so let's get into the
settings, let's expand it and to the top right you can see the viewport samples and the render
samples, but let's get into the output settings and here you can choose the resolution, the
quality and at the bottom you can choose the output folder for the animation.
So let's click on the folder icon and then select a folder on your computer and then
give the animation a name, so just give it a name and then click enter to save the name
and then you can choose the file format, so you can choose from PNG to JPEG to video
files like AVR JPEG and MP4.
Now to get to the MP4 type format you need to select FFMPEG and then go into encoding
and select MPEG4 and you should also increase the output quality and if you want you can
also add audio to the renderer if you have a audio clip in the animation.
Now for this animation I'm going to choose the AVR JPEG file format because the MP4s
are usually really compressed, so let's choose the AVR JPEG type and then increase the quality
to 100% and let's turn on Render View as well.
There are two ways to render in Blender EV, you can either use the viewport renderer
or the normal renderer, so let's go to view and make a viewport render test which is basically
just a snapshot of the viewport and as you can see the viewport render is really quick
but let's go back to the 3D view, so if you want you can render out the whole animation
using the viewport renderer or you can go to the top left corner of Blender and select
render and then click render image and as you can see when you do a proper render you
get all of the samples specified in the settings, so let's go back to 3D view and render out
the whole animation, so just go up to render and then click render animation and it will
start rendering the whole animation you have and that's it for this tutorial, I hope you
enjoyed it and I will post more EV tutorials very soon, so thank you guys for watching
and subscribe.