This will be a lecture looking at a whole lot of the themes we've been
considering all quarter in here, how they apply to a topic that is very close to
home. And what I already know from some of the emails today was Friday's
lecture, looking at depression, was already getting close to home. Some of the
themes that came out at the end of the chaos lecture, some of the notions
there that some of the stuff teaching us, perhaps there are no blueprints,
perhaps there need not be blueprints, perhaps there may still be blueprints
despite a theoretical demonstration that you don't need them hitting close to
home also, that is what all of today's lecture is about, looking at some
biological underpinnings of religiosity. And this one is far and away from the
lecture I am most nervous for, simply because this one people wind up having
strong opinions about, and I want to navigate through this one as successfully
as possible. Okay, just to give me a sense of where I'm starting off from here,
how many of you would characterize yourself as religious, as fairly
religious, as highly religious? Okay, good. How many of you would characterize
yourself as very, very comfortably, exceptingly non-religious? Lots of
hands there as well. Okay, lots of potential differences in responding to
this. Where we pick up on is from where we left off with a lecture last
Wednesday, which was the schizophrenia lecture. And where we finished with was
this whole notion that by now we have to have dealt with every single one of
these topics, starting on the far right, what's the behavior look like, and
eventually getting to the far left, what are the evolutionary roots? And what has
always been the rationale for that is the second we're looking at anything with
genes, genetic influences, genetic hints, genetic whatever, we're asking where
these genes come from, where's the evolutionary sense, where's the adaptive
value for anything we're looking at? How would a sociobiologist interpret it
to someone else? Yeah, question?
I should be, and I don't think I understand the subject enough to know. Other
than something about religiosity is done in a social context, and that's going
to become important here. And the difference is one that puzzles me a
great deal, because it clearly transcends issues of just the social
community, but that seems to be a good defining point to start from. Okay, so
where we ended up there with was this puzzle. We finished at the end of
depression looking at evolutionary aspects and looking at there may be some
hidden benefits, that weird argument in one of the readings in your reader
creativity and aspects of manic depression going hand in hand, but we were
left with somewhat of a puzzle at the end of the schizophrenia lecture. Why
might there have been selection for these genes? Because once again, we start
off with a theme from the very beginning. Ooh, genes being selected for. Why
did the giraffe have long necks? Because this is a trait that's adaptive. In our
Darwinian terms, this is a trait that's associated with leaving more copies of
your genes. In future generations, what is the adaptive value for genes for
schizophrenia? Because we looked at the fact that in this contemporary form,
schizophrenia is by definition a maladaptive trait. Schizophrenics leave
fewer copies of their genes than their unaffected siblings. It is a trait which
is formally maladaptive. What might be a hidden advantage lurking there? And
where we left at the very end of that was just a hint that, in fact, as far as
anyone can tell, there are no hidden advantages to schizophrenia. There may
not be any adaptive advantage. What I left you with there was the notion,
however, that there might be another disease lurking around related to
schizophrenia, which does have an adaptive advantage. And to begin here, what we
have to go back to is one of the basic ninth grade biology concepts in science
there, which is the whole notion that, some of the time, a genetic trait, which
is god-awful in one setting, may have some advantages elsewhere. And we all
learned the exact same example back in ninth grade, sickle cell anemia. Sickle
cell anemia, which in one context, when fully expressed, is a hematological
disaster. Absolutely bad news, horrible. And in other settings, can protect you
against malaria and not by chance that versions of sickle cell anemia have
evolved in sub-Saharan Africa, Mediterranean areas, Thalassemia related
diseases, that this has been a frequent solution. Also in passing, showing us one
of the truisms from this class, there's no such thing as a bad gene. There's only
a bad gene environment interaction. Okay, so this theme in medical genetics comes
through a lot of times. Genetic traits, which in one setting are bad news, may
have advantages in another setting. And it's turning out, this is a theme in
lots of different realms of genetics. Other examples, Tay-Sachs disease. Tay-Sachs,
horrible congenital disorder, predominantly found in Ashkenazi Jews. What you
wind up getting there is full-blown version, complete cortical failure to
develop. A child is massively retarded and birth dies shortly afterward. Partial
version of Tay-Sachs disease and you're resistant to tuberculosis. Nobody knows
the mechanism for it yet. People absolutely understand why the sickle cell
trait both sets you up for an anemia and protection from malaria. Nobody
understands it yet with Tay-Sachs, but this explains one of the phenomena back
from the Middle Ages, the European belief that Jews were safe from tuberculosis
because they were poisoning the Christian wells. And that was a cause of a large
number of programs back when there is a genetic explanation, which is the trait
for Tay-Sachs disease in this partially expressed form protects from
tuberculosis. More examples of this. Cystic fibrosis, the most common congenital
disorder these days, and that is massively life-threatening.
A copy finished, so I would need a code to make a...
A code. Anybody know a code?
By Wednesday. Do you have no where the handout is?
They're not Xerox.
Are they sitting there though?
Cystic fibrosis, full-blown version disastrous disease. What you get in
cystic fibrosis is inflammatory disease. Your lungs fill up with fluid. You often
are dead by age 20. Horrible disease. Partial version of cystic fibrosis and you
are protected against cholera. And the exact same mechanism that causes an
imbalance of fluids in the lungs is the same mechanism that keeps you from
losing all your fluids when you have cholera of dehydrating, highly adaptive.
A theme that keeps popping up over and over. Full-blown version, bad news, partial
genetic version, good news. And what you wind up getting is this basic argument,
a numerical argument, very similar to the, I'll lay down my life for two
brothers or eight cousins deal, of if you've got enough people with the
partial protective adaptive version, you can afford the occasional cousin with
the full-blown version. The trait overall will still be passed on. Now what this
sets us up for is thinking about whether something like this is going on with
schizophrenia. And the question to ask of course is, what is a mild genetic version
of schizophrenia? And this one got discovered in the 1970s. Back to that
classic study we've heard about in a couple of different lectures by now,
Kedi, that psychiatrist from Harvard, who with his colleagues went off to Denmark
and spent a decade there looking at every single adoption case and looking at
the patterns of schizophrenia, the schizophrenic, the adoptive parents, the
biological parents. In the course of them doing this, they discovered something
amazing. Because think about what these guys did. This was this team of
psychiatrists who spent a decade in Denmark. What they did was interview every
single family of every adoptee in Denmark. This was like 10,000 people. This
was a massive amount of work looking for schizophrenics, looking in the various
pedigrees, all that sort of thing, interviewing huge numbers of people,
just a handful of these folks, so they would all get the diagnostic criteria
fairly similar. Well-designed study, blah blah. What had they done by the end of a
decade? They had talked to more family members of schizophrenics than any
psychiatrists in history. And think about this. Your average psychiatrist who's
got some schizophrenic patients will, you know, meet once every six months with
the parent. If the schizophrenic is on the young side, maybe occasionally will
also have sessions on a regular basis. These people had just interviewed tens of
thousands of family members of schizophrenics. And they noticed something
interesting. They noticed that on the average, there was something a little bit
strange about family members of schizophrenics. Not all of them, and these
traits are not only found amongst family members of schizophrenics, but at a
higher than expected rate, there is a weird sort of quirky personality that
went with family members of schizophrenics, biological family members. And this
version of a much milder case of schizophrenia is now called schizotypal
personality. This is a standardly recognized disorder in psychiatry,
schizotypalism is a mild genetic version of schizophrenia. What does schizotypal
look like? First off, people have somewhat loose associations, not remotely in the
realm of a schizophrenic, and there are standardized scales that can be given to
show this is someone out of the normal range, but not in the schizophrenic range
in an intermediate range. In addition, you get a social withdrawal. And this is
not the complete dysfunctional, unable to hold down a job locked up in the back
of the village version of schizophrenia. This is someone instead who just
gravitates towards fairly solitary occupations. This is the lighthouse keeper,
this is the fire tower watcher, this is the classic schizotypal occupation,
this is the person sitting alone in the projection room in the movie theater
eight hours a night in the dark there, classic sort of schizotypal jobs,
socially detached, very solitary. The most striking feature of schizotypals
is what is termed metamagical thinking. And this is where things begin to get
interesting. Metamagical thinking, this is not someone who is thought disordered,
psychotic, unable to function, this is someone who just kind of believes in
strange things. This is someone who's really, really into science fiction and fantasy.
This is someone, okay, I see some of the concern popping up here. This is someone
who's into some sort of new age stuff in a really frenzy sort of way. This is
someone who believes in mental telepathy or UFOs. This is a first hint. This is
someone who, if they have a religious structure of belief, has an extremely
concrete level of interpretation. Remembering this seems to be quite similar
to schizophrenia, what apples oranges have in common multi-syllabic words,
that concreteness at the level of abstraction. These are people who tend
towards extremely fundamentalist, concrete interpretations of religious events.
Seven-day creation of the world, this is not a metaphor, this is not a parable,
this could be measured down to the minute. People alive who were once dead,
this is not a metaphor for keeping the spirit going. This is an exact description
of the events we begin to see where we're heading here. What schizotypillism is
about is it's a very mild version of schizophrenia in terms of the loose
associations, in terms of the concreteness of associations, the social
detachment, and most of all the metamagical thinking. This is now a
standard diagnostic category in psychiatry to have a schizotypal personality.
So, what we then ask is, where does this come from? What is this like? And what we
have to ask is of course our usual question when trying to make sense of
a human trait is recognizing 99% of human history was not spent with schizotypills
being able to get jobs in film projection rooms. What does schizotypillism look
like in traditional non-westernized human societies? And the answer to that
turns out to have been floating around for 60, 70 years in the anthropology literature.
And this is back to the 1930s. An anthropologist named Paul Raiden, who was
the first one to point this out, was the first one of a whole tradition
emphasizing what was a pretty strong area of research in the 1940s in
anthropology. He was the first person who pointed out that in
traditional human societies, there is a category of people there who count as,
and these are his exact words, half crazy. Who are the half crazies in
traditional human society? The shamans, the witch doctors, the
medicine men, the medicine women. These are members of
society who make a living being metamagical. And
Raiden was the first one to emphasize this. In traditional human societies,
the shamans are the ones who converse with the dead for ritualistic reasons. The
shamans are the ones who speak in tongues. The shamans are the ones who
at the full moon turn into the hyena to protect the village from predators.
The shamans are the ones who are metamagical for a thing, for a living.
And this has been a theme in anthropology for quite some time.
One anthropologist named Akternek referred to
shamans as being healed madmen. In the 1940s, anthropologists named
Krober, who started the Anthra Department in Berkeley and was one of the
grand old men in the field. This is a quote of his describing what
shamanism is about. The shaman displays his possession by
a spirit by publicly reenacting his specific
personal experience, that of a man suffering from a particular mental
affliction. His projections, his hallucinations,
his journey through space and time thus became a dramatic ritual
and served as the prototype for all future concepts
of the religious road of perfection. And this was the recognition in the 30s and
40s that what shamanism is about is a very controlled,
very socially contextual version of metamagical schizotypillism.
The word did not exist in the field at the time,
but that is what it is. Now what Krober emphasized in his writing was
these are not schizophrenics. And what we heard about in that story in
class four days ago, looking at that schizophrenic
person in that messiah village, is that people in traditional human
societies are no more tolerant to the mentally ill
than we are in the West and just as delighted to find cultural means
to peripheralize them, these are not full-blown schizophrenics.
These are not people who suddenly are speaking in tongues
at the exact silent moment in the hunt. These are people who are speaking in
tongues at the right time. These are people who are hearing voices
at the right time and you remember what the punchline was of that story
about that schizophrenic woman in that messiah village was
she heard voices at the wrong time. Hearing voices at the right time
is not schizophrenia, it is a version of schizotypillism.
And what you see when you look at the human tradition of shamanism,
these are not peripheralized people. These are some of the most powerful
members of society. Many societies have a tradition
of shamans being celibate, but many of them, most of them as it turns out,
do not. And these are people who are anything but
reproductively maladaptive. These are people who have been passing on their
genes just fine throughout history. Shamanism, this mild
version, this contextually appropriate version of
metamagicalism has done wonderfully throughout human history.
And a great example of that, the fact that you need to get it just right,
was Krober sort of emphasizing this, that in the right setting,
what would be an absolutely peripheralizing set of traits
instead makes you a very powerful, very sanctioned,
and that's the word that he used, a very sanctioned member of society,
and it's not for nothing that the word sanction has a whole lot to do with the
word sanctuary. This is a realm in which the exact same
traits would spectacularly fail to work in other cultural settings,
do it right, and it works just fine. And Krober had a wonderful anecdote about
this, this sense of you got to get it just right.
He apparently was at some ritual, a ceremony, he spent most of his time
doing his anthropology with Native American groups,
and this was some ceremony being done by the Winnebago's, and I was actually
found it quite bizarre that there was a group called the Winnebago,
but hanging out with the Winnebago's, and this was one of his
informants there sort of explaining this ritual, and this was apparently some
really fraughty, really quite over-the-top ritual that the Shaman was
pulling off and was speaking in tongues and rolling on the fire, and all of that
and this guy said, that is great, we've got this Shaman here, this guy is
like the best, he's worth every dollar we pay him,
this guy is terrific, we are so lucky to have a Shaman like this in our village,
this guy is, thank god we don't have two of them though,
two way too much, one's just fine, and you have this recognition that
this is not schizophrenia, you wouldn't want a person to be
schizophrenic because they will be as peripheralized as in our own society,
you want to get it just right, you don't want to have too many of them,
you've got to have some people who are some plain meat and potatoes, good hunters,
that sort of thing, and you want the ratio of that to the Shamanistic
metamagical folks to be quite high, but you need a few of them around,
and what the anthropologists have been noting for 60 years is
all human cultures traditionally have some very metamagical folks around,
and these folks are anything but peripheralized with a decreased
reproductive success, they're some of the most honored members of society.
So what you wind up getting here is that classic partially expressed sort of continuum deal going on
which is human societies throughout history have had such a need for shamans
that they can put up with the occasional second cousin who's fully schizophrenic,
as long as you've got the ratio right, and what the numbers suggest,
the 1 to 2 percent rate of schizophrenia throughout human cultures
and the number average population size of human villages
and the number of shamans it works about right. Throughout history there has been more of a
predominance of schizotypal shamans than of schizophrenics you can afford to put up with
the occasional cousin. Now where does this wind up heading? What the main point of this section is
about is this is not just about the people naked in the National Geographics with the bones on their
noses, and this was a critical transition recognizing this. At some point a whole lot of people in
that field were writing about the primitiveness of non-westernized religion, and there was a great
quote who came up with this one, a guy named Devereux referred to primitive religion as being
organized schizophrenia. This was somebody in the 1940s exactly getting this flavor of contextualized
appropriate hearing the voices at the right time, all of that, but this was overwhelmingly literature
about the weird stuff those folks are up to in the night and the time life specials on public
television and what the critical transition is is it's not just about them. At some point this
anthropologist Ackernick who was quite leftist in his orientation wrote a long essay saying how
incredibly culturally chauvinistic it was of the western anthropologists to write all these articles
about how shamans are half healed madmen and how condescending that was to talk about those cultures
as being so irrationally based in contrast to us and what's the obvious punchline is the problem
isn't saying that they're irrational when we're saying that we aren't but it's saying that we're
equally irrational. We are equally irrational in some of the tenets that we have here. A quote
from Ackernick at the time was our culture is unique and outlawing the irrational. Let me give
you some recent statistics from a survey. What's the name of the survey? The main national survey
of people. Who? Yes Gallipole that guy the Gallipole a recent Gallipole survey I don't know about you
guys but these numbers astonished me 25 percent of Americans say they believe in ghosts 36 percent
believe in mental telepathy 47 percent believe in UFOs and more than 50 percent of Americans believe
in the devil and a belief that the devil influences daily activities these are people who can vote
these are people who can serve on juries these are people who can operate motor vehicles these
are people making decisions about medical interventions I for one in this outpost of not
terribly extreme irrationality in this corner of the country I'm astonished we live in a world that
is highly irrational and the punchline of this is this is not simply about non-western traditional
human societies the exact same thread of schizotypillism runs throughout all of the belief systems
of human societies including western ones we are permeated by irrationality now some of the versions
of it that we have in the west are utter nonsense ones ones that have just been like invented out of
thin air in recent years which is kind of like fast food for these sort of Nuvo sort of medieval
peasants in their hot tubs up in Marin this is the world of crystals and channeling and things
of that sort but some of the versions of our westernized irrationally go back millennia
and organize some of our most cherished values the same irrationality and the same valuing
of those who invent the appropriate versions of the irrationality runs throughout the west
okay just to show you that I am not being overly hostile or will try to pull in my own sort of
tradition that I was raised in is not normally considered a sign of robust mental health to
hear voices coming out of burning bushes this is considered a worrisome sign this is considered
diagnostic it is not a good thing to be reporting that you just spent the night wrestling an angel
it is usually a very disturbing sign if you were reporting you've had a conversation with someone
who is dead and has risen from the grave these are diagnosable problems in our secular western realm
these are the backbones of our belief systems we in the west as well as we humans in non-westernized
settings schizotypillism runs through all of human history what you wind up having then
is this obvious question who invented this stuff who came up with the notion that the world was
invented in seven days or snakes with apples are up to something no good or it's possible to give
birth and you're still a virgin these were not designed by committees these were designed by
extremely formative extremely influential schizotypals throughout history yes
yep it's genetic evidence those same studies showed that it runs through the adoption studies
showed it's a biological trait it runs through the biological side of the adoptive pedigrees
it's a it's a genetic trait what the new studies are now being to show is mild tendency towards
increased dopamine tone mild tendency towards most of the biology we heard about what we're
seeing is totally artificial bucket to say schizophrenia up to here past the side non-schizophrenic
we have this in-between zone like everything else we've been thinking about it's on a continuum
and seems to be the same biology in a much milder form question somewhere there
yep same sort of stuff okay so what do you wind up yeah question
yep
no because the the critical thing there is they will very readily tell you much as people will
tell you here in their own schizotypal experiences that you need the right person to lead it they
can't get that going without the right shaman starting it off you need them as a catalyst yeah
okay why do we need this why do we value this okay we'll come to this probably in about two
days but this is tapping into all of the you know why why do we search for some fairly
unlikely answers to the big questions that plague all of us we'll come to this in two days but you
know this is getting at the core of some of the basic questions here okay let me push on here
what you wind up seeing with this is that this is on a continuum and who invented this stuff and
you look throughout the history of religious leaders those who have invented some of the theology
and we will come to different variants of religious leaders shortly as you see those who invented
the theology that there is very often a thread of metamagical thinking that goes through this
and this is metamagical thinking of a type that falls readily into the spectrum of schizotypalism
now one of the themes we've endlessly come back to in this class is appropriate context appropriate
context and this is a perfect realm to see this because what we wind up getting is you got to
get it just right if you hear voices it's got to be during the ceremony if you're speaking in tongues
it can't be in the middle of the silent part of the hunt you don't want to have too many of them
thank god we've got this shaman but not two of them around here you've got to get the context right
and what we've seen throughout human history and western history as well is get it wrong and we
have names for these things get it wrong and these are abortive religious fringe groups these are
cults and you look at some versions of this in our own recent time you look at david koresh and
waco you look at someone like james jinn jones and jones town you look at someone like charles
manson and these are people who were highly metamagical in their thinking highly charismatic
but hit a wall at the point where we still classify them as cults manson is a diagnosed
schizophrenic with the other two there's only post hoc sort of sort of forensic psychiatry
that you can do what you wind up getting is get it wrong and we call it a cult get it right in the
right time in the right place and maybe for the next couple of millennia people won't have to go
to work on your birthday if you get it exactly right in that setting so what i think we see here is
a setting here for making sense the exact same traits in a different context to use krober's
words in a cultural context that is not sanctioned the exact same traits count as psychiatrically
suspect these days what this is about is not only if you get it in the right context is it okay
it is highly honored tapping into the question that came in before that all human societies have a
strong need for a certain degree of these folks around you need to get the ratios right okay
picking up on this theme a transition to a next point in the sense that this is talking about
sort of the structural steel of religious belief what are the basic beliefs you have
there is no god but one he is a la the you know whatever versions of the central formats you have
there is a trinity i am who i am any of these variants these are sort of the building blocks the
structural steel of religion but what religion is often often also about is lots of other things
we have a very modern very westernized view of religion these days what religion is often about
is the social community that it brings you what religion is often about is the motivation for
good works throughout most of history what religion is about in one very orthodox variant is the
carrying out of rituals the daily performance of ritualistic behaviors in the context of religion
and this transitions us to the next subject in here and this whole notion of ritualism as a backbone
of religion wonderful quote to that effect henry ward beecher father of harry and beecher stowe
famous protestant preacher in new england i think the 1830s or so had this quote at the time religion
is daily bread religion is not just cake on sunday the notion that what religion is about
is the small acts god is in the detail religion is in the small acts of the daily rituals now
beginning to look not at the large theological notions our religion believes there are multiple
gods there are virgin births that god can speak through a burning bush but instead religion as
the daily practices of ritual now what is interesting about this what comes through with this is
another theme another subtype of a very mild version of a psychiatric disorder which once
again works spectacularly when you get it just right not now with the metamagical big theology
building blocks of religion but the daily bits and pieces of ritualism and this brings in another
psychiatric disorder one we haven't talked about much in class so far okay i guarantee on a regular
basis all of us in this room getting to some point where it's some anxious period you've got some
major deadline you're applying for some summer something rather that you really want to get
you're totally uptight about it you're sitting down and you're writing the essay and before you
can write the essay you got to get your favorite pen it's got to be right there and you got to
rearrange your desk and you got to get everything sorted out and finally you finish it and you go
mail off the application you know you put in the mailbox and you check again to make sure it went
down and this is really important you don't want to see it check again just to make sure and you're
all set for that and you finally there's no one else around so you go and you look in front of it
and looking back at that and that sort of thing i mean we all do this actually maybe we all do this
and i'm embarrassing myself horribly but my bet is most of us do this sort of thing we fall into
obsessive little rituals during times of anxiety we also have rituals intrusive thoughts that just
invade our heads at times where they are of no obvious purpose they are at the cost of thinking
anything more clearly it's totally maddening and you can't stop the thoughts for example today i'm
working on a paper that's involving all sorts of very deep ruminative thought and figuring out all
sorts of data stuff and i've made no progress on it at all this morning because for some reason
that i don't understand at all all of today i've had the damn theme song from teletubbies going
and i can't stop it especially the part where lala leaps up and says lala the really cute part
there and i can't stop doing this and i don't know what's going on i did not plan to lose today's
productivity because of teletubbies but we get this some stupid jingle that's stuck in your head
you find yourself going up a flight of stairs and you can't stop yourself from counting the steps
we do this we all do this and we tend to do it more often during periods of anxiety and the
interpretation of that is that we impose this totally arbitrary useless destructive structure
at a time when everything else feels like you're walking on quicksand we all do this as some sort
of adaptation to periods of anxiety and what we transition into now is talking about a psychiatric
disorder where people do this all the time and it not only gets in the way of them getting some work
done on a project that requires some concentration this is a disorder that absolutely destroys their
lives this is ocd obsessive compulsive disorder and the full blown version of it bears so little
resemblance to what any of us do when we are having to get the pen right and checking the mailbox
the third time and having the jingle go through your head for a while it is of such a scale larger
it is so much more destructive it is virtually unimaginable from our perspective people with
ocd have their lives completely destroyed by this disorder people with ocd in the full blown version
spent six hours a day washing their hands the characteristic that's always at the top of the
list with ocd is this obsessive focusing on hygiene is worried that you are constantly in some way
soiled six hours a day of washing these are people who cannot hold down jobs their marriages come
apart their relationships are destroyed because they cannot stop washing and you have in the reader
one profile of somebody with ocd from a book entitled the boy who couldn't stop washing this is the
symptom that always pops up at the top of the list and the actual washing process is ritualistic
beyond belief these are people who have bought seven different kinds of antibacterial soap
they go through this whole sequence the water has to be a certain temperature for the first level of
washing then a certain type of towel that they dry themselves off with that towel has to be put out
of the room because it's dirty then then the next layer of washing with the next soap go through two
hours of this they're finally done turn to leave to go to their job go to their whatever and on the
way out brush their elbow against the door and they have to start all over again and you will
stop them at that point and say you will miss this interview you will not get this job and they will
say yes i know but i'm not going to be able to function and i'm just it's dirty i know my elbow
i know i'm going to touch it then and then i'll get in my face and i just have to start over i'm
not going to be able to get anything done today anyway so i need to go wash if i don't wash i'm
not going to be able to and back they go and hours and hours of this people with ocd spend half
their waking hours doing this people with ocd just have constant sequences of numbers going in their
heads constant jingles intrusive thoughts they cannot stop thinking what if i don't stop the car
at the next stop sign what if i run down this person they have the intrusive thoughts of i'm
absolutely sure i struck somebody at that street crossing back there i've got to go back and check
okay they don't see anybody there they drive on five miles down the road
probably the person flew off into the bushes i have to go back and check i have to go back
and check they can never leave their home because they've left the door unlocked they go back they
check the door is locked they have to go back they left the gas on they left the light on this is
absolutely paralyzing intrusive thoughts what if i leaned over and struck the person next to me
what if somebody kills my loved ones you can't stop the thoughts they just keep coming at these
people they cannot enter or leave a place there is a paralysis about entering and leaving built
around this sort of almost magical exclusionary power that you get a transition into a place
they cannot enter a room until they do a prime number of tapings on the wall before entering
they can then not enter the room until if that's prime number and then a different prime number
with their left foot shaking completely arbitrary symptoms of having to enter and leave numerology
these people cannot begin a meal until the utensils are absolutely symmetrical and lined up and
they're never perfectly symmetrical and the entering and leaving ritual is never done right
and they certainly can't enter the classroom unless the number of steps from here to the door
is two times an interval that's with this a very mathematical quality to it and it's never quite
right and you've got to do it all over again and what's been pointed out one of the really
interesting sort of insights as to what ocd is about is that this is an anxiety disorder this
is a pathological attempt to impose structure to impose predictability to impose control
in a world where everything is pathologically provoking of a sense of dis ease and uncertainty
and anxiety and the absolute horrifying version of ocd that i've heard described is this metaphor
where this is straight out of ethology this is a fixed action pattern we all know the fixed action
pattern of a dog is settling down at night on its blanket and what does the dog do it circles a few
times before it settles down but then it circles a couple of more times and just as it's ready to
then it circles a few more and fine and you can see at some point the dog doesn't even want to do
this anymore and it takes a while longer in another 30 seconds before the dog can finally escape from
this fixed action pattern and sit down in ocd the person never ever escapes the person spends forever
circling on the blanket being unable to finally lie down and rest because they are just consumed
with these rituals with these obsessive intrusive thoughts and what you get is this is completely
paralyzing okay here's an example of an obsessive belief that we all have okay can anybody identify this
okay here's what it is this is an aerial view in fact it's a satellite photograph of here
this is a tray of rice crispy treats and you've just walked into the room and it looks like this
and for a huge percentage of us within a minute or so it's going to look like this
because we all feel this compulsive need to take a knife and cut off that edge okay let me just
canvas you on all of that okay how many of you okay how many of you do this for starters i certainly
do okay how many of you have those who do this cut off this bit here because it doesn't really count
on your diet okay a couple of hands how many of you cut it off because what's perfectly obvious is
going from this to this decreases the total perimeter so that it will stay fresher that way
okay problems that how many of you wind up doing it because it's just getting at you that
it's the knife's just there and you just have to cut it off and smooth out the edge yes that's why
we all do it and then what you then decide is that there's this little bump here which requires you
to trim this out and then there's a little bump and off you go with that and we all wind up doing
that but if this is what you did around the clock for your entire life it would destroy it and what
is most striking with people with ocd is you could never go through the sequence i just did
there's no insight the person does not sit there and say help there's something wrong with me i feel
this need to wash my hands six hours a day they say help there's something wrong with me i can never
get clean i'm just so dirty everything i do makes me dirty there's no insight into it okay so where
does this fit in again our modern version of religion our modern very secularly influenced
version of religion so often involves an emphasis on what religion is about is counseling the trouble
what religion is about is holding the hands of the newlyweds and making sure they understand
what they're getting into what religion is about is comforting the distance the bereaved what religion
is about is the good works but this is not what religion has often been about throughout history
often the religious leaders are not necessarily the ones who are most psychotherapeutically
minded or the most galvanizing of people into the good works often religious leaders have been
the ones at the head of a crusade often religious leaders have been the ones with the most vivid
images of what hell and damnation would be like but often what religious leaders have been are the
people who are best at doing the rituals and that has been another thread of religious practice
throughout history of religious leaders as often being among the most fervent the most accomplished
at carrying out of rituals now let me give you a sense of this because as i began to read more
on this this absolutely astonished me because i knew very little about this stuff just the scale
of this and starting off with what will probably be a fairly alien religion for most of you in here
and then moving into examples closer to home looking at orthodox very traditional hinduism
looking at the behaviors of a brahman an individual who devotes their entire life to ritualistic
practice in pursuit of their religion a brahman a highly observant brahman spends six hours a day
in cleansing rituals and there are detailed rules as to which hand you wash in what sequence
how many times you wash each hand separately how many each one together the sequence with which
you wash out one side of your mouth versus the other with water there are set rules for brahmans
as to how you were supposed to lie down at night dictating what your first sight is in the morning
there are set rules as to what direction you must face when defecating in terms of what you
were looking at at the time there are set rules for rituals you have to do when entering a temple
when leaving a temple there are set rules for how many breaths you take through each nostril
you close one nostril during your prayers for a certain number of breaths then you close the other
and all of these are very carefully stipulated the number of mouthfuls of food the number of
times you chew per mouthful the number of prayers you have to say per day sequences of magic numbers
all of this is absolutely spelled out and orthodox brahmans consume their entire days doing this
okay next example orthodox Judaism spectacularly yeah question
great okay hang on for a while we will come to that that's a superb question as to why they seem
to have lots to do with cleansing and food preparation wow thank you okay do you want to
why don't we take a five minute break right now and you can all store in the front here for handouts
lots of opinions here lots of thoughts once again that same thing i mentioned two days ago three days
ago whenever this is very provocative stuff take advantage of the course website put up some of
your opinions get dial-ons going on this because people lots of times have extremely strong opinions
on this and very interesting ones take advantage of this a couple of questions that just came up
how come people with ocd don't come down with learned helplessness why aren't they depressed
because part of the fuel behind ocd is you're always convinced aha one more now i know instead of
doing it 17 times 18 if i do it 18 then it's going to be perfect you've always just figured out
not only do i have to do the six hours of washing but make sure i never step on a crack and then i
won't break my mother's back you're always figuring out the next step then pointing out we're about to
go in a direction where what are the advantages of a mild version of ocd and we're discussing this
in a religious context i should point out in a secular context there's a tremendous advantage
to a mild version of ocd what it does is get you into a place like stanford what it does is work
to a tremendous advantage given how regimented and disciplined a lot of folks are in here get it in
the right context blah blah that theme that we have again and again okay shifting over just seeing
orthodox brahman belief and hinduism absolutely dominated virtually full time with ritualistic
behaviors orthodox jewelry a spectacular number of laws built around food preparation the kosher
laws very detailed rules as to how long of a time interval between eating one type of food and another
type of food if you inadvertently mix up the silverware with different types of food ritualistic
cleansing rituals that you have to go through involving putting the utensils in dirt for months
on end and special prayers that have to be said rules about how you enter and leave a holy place
involving certain prayers involving a certain ritualistic touching that you have to make on the
door jam there all sorts of magic numbers the number 18 has magical powers and orthodox Judaism
and it's built around numbers of times you have to say a prayer multiples of 18 you have these prayer
shawls that have strings on the end which have 18 knots in them and they have to be pulled a certain
number of times here's one of the amazing examples of ritualism okay these numbers have magical powers
and orthodox Judaism and you will note 365 is the number of days in the year 248 is the number of
bones that people believed were in the bodies during the middle ages when this evolved and together
613 according to the holy books there are 613 rules for daily behaviors 365 prohibitions every day
248 things that have to be done every day the preponderance of the prohibitions leading one
clearly fairly depressive rabbi back when to be saying obviously it would have been better if
none of us were born given the fact that there were more things that we could mess up by doing
but what you see here is which is highly ritualistic the number of prohibitions equaling the number of
days of the year the number of ritual constraints equaling the number of bones in the body 613
is the magic number okay where did these numbers come from very often in religious rituals what
you find is a number has symbolic value because it's got a certain appeal for making learning
easier it is not by chance that a base 10 society came up with 10 commandments because 10 commandments
that are much easier to remember than 9 or 11 what are these about you would say okay well there's
some sort of ritualistic content here god the number of things god doesn't want us to do each day
is equal to the number of days of the year the number thing god wants us to do is equal to the
number of bones in the body okay great device for remembering the rules but here's the amazing
thing nobody knows the rules you look through thousands of pages of commentary stretching back
centuries and the rules aren't written down and various rabbis have made a living arguing over
what are the 365 things you aren't supposed to do each day in other words the numbers are more
important than the content the content is less critical than the fact that whatever they are
there's 365 things that god doesn't want you to do and whatever they are there's 248 that god
wants you to do the number that you are attributing to god is more important in that case than the
content okay classic classic obsessive numerology switching over traditional orthodox islam what
you find there is very detailed rules as to what foods you can eat what the first food is you're
supposed to eat each day there are rules as to how you enter and leave a holy place there are rules
for very ornate cleansing after release relieving yourself very very detailed rules when you are
washing out your mouth how many mouthfuls of water which hands you wash in which sequence the exact
same thing exact same rules as with an ocd person after the showering explicitly written down when
a man is washing himself at the ends of the at the end of the cleansing should he happen to touch
his penis he has to do the whole sequence all over again magic numbers thought to have powers there
seven ten seventy and a hundred apparently have magical powers in islam and you have very explicit
concrete instructions about them Muhammad himself wrote down that a man who says a prayer with clean
teeth gets seventy times the brownie points as a man saying his prayers without them multiples of
magic numbers with all of that and probably for most of you by now what will be the most familiar
is looking at orthodox christianity and you have rosaries in the counting of rosaries you have three
is a magic number you have very detailed numbers of times you are supposed to say prayers you have
rules for entering and leaving churches even in christian groups that are viewed as some of the
least ritualistic some of the most cerebral in some ways you look at the Lutherans Lutherans
have set rules for prayers that are only said during even years prayers that are only said during odd
years all of these versions of orthodoxy are absolutely shocked through with rituals built
around cleansing of the body food preparation entering and leaving of significant places
and numerology it's the exact same list as you find with ocd and Freud a hundred years ago
came up with this amazing quote to that regard Freud described obsessive compulsive disorder ocd
quote as an individual religiosity and religion as a universal obsessional compulsion he absolutely
linked the two now just when you're thinking that i'm standing here and i'm started going to start
pathologizing religious belief from sort of a medical psychiatric standpoint the exact same
conclusion has been reached by religious leaders over the centuries as well in the 15th century
there was st. Loyola no st. Ignatius of Loyola and what this guy did was he wrote this long track
describing scrupulosity scrupulosity is not a common word in english anymore but it's opposite
certainly is being unscrupulous being scrupulous having scrupial scrupulosity at the time was
defined as someone who was going through religious ritual for its own sake someone who was not thinking
about the content but was just doing the ritual and he wrote this long track to catholic priest
saying watch out for people like these people who were coming and being super devout but you will
notice they're just doing the rituals without thinking of the content your job is to recognize
them and guide them back into actually focusing on the content they shouldn't be doing the rituals
for their own sake there's a danger of people like that showing up in the Talmud an orthodox
Judaism the exact same thing there is a law in there that when you read the holy book of Judaism
the Torah you were not allowed to do it by heart you have to actually read the words because there
is an injunction to think about the content don't do it in a rote way and Muhammad himself
in Islam wrote down that people who give prayers without thinking about the content the prayers
don't count even religious leaders for centuries for millennia have recognized the pull of religious
ritual for its own sake to have to admonish religious adherents to pay attention to the content
because the ritual takes on a life of its own where the numbers the content the ritual is more
important than the actual thought behind it yeah
exactly and that was that point that transition talking about schizotypillism there's much more
resemblance to the large theological building blocks of religion of spirituality what are our
military's principles what do we believe do we believe you always follow orders you never follow
orders you don't agree with what's more important value sort of stuff this is instead in the realm of
religious practice and this is the realm of very orthodox religious practice absolutely
completely different realm so where am i heading with this obviously emphasizing the similarity
of the traits and that whole business that once again have a six hour compulsion to wash your
hands each day and have it occur in the secular context of ocd it destroys your life you cannot
function in society you are peripheralized you are mentally ill and that exact same theme get it
right in the right context and this is protected this is honored this is rewarded get it in the
right setting now nothing about being able to do rituals and turn them from your own private ocd
into the religious setting this is not a process for making the anxiety go away it's very important
when people are pulling off these rituals in a religious setting it's not to make the anxiety
go away it's to share it it's to share it over time and space with a larger community it's to
take this nameless dread and to give it a name and to have that name come with feeding instructions
and all sorts of rules for how to please the source of the named dread at this point it's not to
make the anxiety go away it's to make the anxiety shared now from this transitioning from this notion
that okay in the right setting the same exact trait that can ruin your life can in fact be
enveloped rewarded welcomed protected in the context of religious belief now taking it one step
further yeah question sure no it definitely doesn't but from that standpoint this is
speaking to one aspect of what it's doing and we still haven't come to the question that was up
there before isn't there an ecological reason why there should be these rituals about cleansing
and food preparation we'll come to that shortly but the other point you brought up maybe this is
to foster a sense of community but this comes back to the question around there before why should
people in a communal sense feel better why should we all feel better when we do rituals and our
rituals of counting the stairs and making sure the application really went down the mailbox
why do we feel even better when we do it in the context of the community you're absolutely right
that these are meant to foster the group shared features of religiosity and spirituality the
question then becomes why does it work why do we respond to it why do we need shamans and
why do we respond to this ability to share these customs why is it the trait of 18 year olds all
over the world to try to invent a whole bunch of generationally shared rituals that lets the world
know i have nothing whatsoever to do with those appalling people who embarrass me my parents
what's that whole separation that goes in why is it that individuation is very often going hand in
hand with i need a community to do this individuation with that in a sense is the question and that
kind of brings us to this next issue looking at sort of a next scale of this application of this
ritualism by far one of the weirdest stories that france kafka ever wrote was the hunger artist
and this is a story about a person who performs starving his performance is he comes into a town
and he's locked up in a cage in the middle of town and he entertains he performs people performs there
by starving himself and people come and watch him starve and initially you read this and this
sounds like one of the more bizarre parables that kafka has come up with until you read that during
the middle ages there were hunger artists there were people who performed in european cities
starving themselves in a ritualistic way for people to come and watch suddenly we now look at a next
level the notion of performing rituals and people who are very good at it once again what are religious
leaders about mostly these days we think of them in terms of people who are empathic people who are
able to use the religious tradition they come from to make people treat each other better to
comfort people during troubled times but back to that issue that some of the time what a religious
leader is about is someone who is excellent at doing rituals and when you look at the history
of religion not only do you have the capacity for somebody to suddenly lose themselves to finally
have the same life destroying rituals being sanctioned and protected you have people who
could make a living performing the rituals you can have people who are aptly rewarded for doing so
some examples starting off with traditional hinduism there is a mantra there called the
gayatri mantra which i'm sure i'm mispronouncing but in traditional brahmanism you are supposed
to say this mantra two million four hundred thousand times in a lifetime to guarantee a good
afterlife and what happens is you have these aging captains of industry who were worried that may
not have quite gotten the right number in there and are feeling the years catching up with them
and what do you do you hire yourself a bunch of brahmins to come and say the prayer two million
four hundred thousand times for you and you say it in appropriate multiples there are set rules
you hire two hundred forty of them so each of them says ten thousand hundred thousand a thousand
ten thousand each of them says a whole lot of them and they all say the same number and there
are rules for what sort of tent city you put up for them in your backyard and what sort of feast
you throw for them you hire people to come and do the rituals for you that get you your afterlife
switching over to judaism these rules of orthodox food preparation there is an entire job you can get
built around ritualistic preparation of food now there is a certain primary level of this
which is people who make a living making sure food is prepared in a kosher way that they slaughter
animals things of that sort but there's a whole second level people who make a living watching
the folks who prepare the food you have rabbis who make a living sitting around and slaughter
houses and making sure the animals are slaughtered in a ritualistically appropriate way these guys
don't do anything with their own hands their entire job is to watch and make sure the rituals
are done right so that you can produce like fat free tofu hot dogs that would bring a smile to the
lips of the patriarchs it's done so ritualistically correctly these guys make a living doing this
and then the version probably we are most familiar with the american experience you have the high
school graduation you have the opening of the new town whatever and what happens the local clergyman
comes out and does a convocation says a prayer is invited to come and do a ritual to mark this
community transition and our response here is well yeah of course that's the guy's job and that's
exactly the point you could make a living doing these rituals and you can do that job these days
complete with health insurance and a retirement package and a 401k and all of that you make a
living doing rituals and when you look at the history of religion suddenly what you see is an
inevitable outcome of that if there's somebody who's spending all his time washing his hands
ritualistically for the good of the community there's some peasant out there who's got to work
by the sweat of his brow to make bread for two people instead of one and there's an amazing novel
a science fiction novel and absolutely caught this which struck me as like one of the truly
horrible novels in terms of writing style almost as bad as asimov but in there was this brilliant
idea a book called zenicide by a writer named orson scott card and had this brilliant idea that
absolutely caught this and this was on as always a multi-planetary empire and the people running
the evil empire figured out the people on some planet were biologically very very prone towards
being extremely smart we could dissect that in lots of ways perhaps the particular prenatal
environment on that planet but they nonetheless worried that this planet had great danger for
producing revolutionaries that were going to leave the overthrow of the empire so what they did
was invent a virus a virus which caused obsessive compulsive disorder and they infected a subset
of people on this planet with the virus and the virus integrated into the dna so it would be passed
on multi-generationally and suddenly you had a subset of people who were paralyzed with ocd with
counting rituals and all of that and what did they manage to foist off on the rest of the population
these were religious experiences they were having and within a few generations this had become a
priestly class who sat around all day carrying out their obsessive rituals and the rest of the
population couldn't begin to think of revolting against the empire because they were spending all
day long having to come up with enough food to feed the priestly class and what you suddenly had
was a paralysis built around an entire class that does nothing other than carry out these rituals
and that planet was no worry to the rest of the empire at that point what you wind up seeing is
that truly involved ritualistic religious belief is often at the cost of doing anything else
there's a spectacular example of this historically and this is a 16th century augustinian monk in
germany named luder and this guy happened to have left a lot of written records and this guy is a
classic example of this he was the son the only son of a very aggressive very violent father there
was some suggestion that the father had in fact killed somebody once and abroad the son was absolutely
terrified of him and was extremely obedient to him very anxious very psychosomatic young man
one day he is out for a walk it's caught in a lightning storm out in an open field has a panic
attack there because the lightning storm makes a devotional agreement at that point if he can
survive this lightning storm he will become a monk he promises god that he survives he becomes a
monk and he is absolutely paralyzed with his ritualistic training he leaves records about
when he had his first mass he fainted beforehand he was so nervous about doing it wrong the mass
went on three times the length that was supposed to because he kept having to stop and start over
again because he was sure he had done something wrong he spent approximately five hours a day
in confession with his priestly mentor there his sort of advisor there confessing to every this is
a guy who lived in a monastery he didn't have a chance to do anything sinful but he'd be in there
five hours a day when i said this prayer i wasn't mindful enough about it i did it by rote when i
did this i wasn't thinking enough about this i pretty sure i didn't wash my hands enough
before doing this prayer i did this wrong god is angry at me for doing this i'm sure god is angry
at me for doing this and records his mentor this elderly priest eventually in exasperation
said one of the most astonishingly modern psychoanalytically insightful things imaginable
he said enough already god isn't angry with you for some reason you are very angry with god
god doesn't care about how many times you're washing your hands and the most definitive thing
about this young man this young priest was something he left in his records he washed
hours and hours a day an exact quote from him the more i wash the dirtier i get
and this is ocd and why do we know so much about this man because we know him 500 years later
not by his latin name of luder we know him by his more westernized name of martin luther
this was martin luther the founder of protestantism and these were the transitional events in his life
and talk about somebody who takes his personal affliction and turns it into perhaps the most
influential event of the last thousand years in western european history this is someone who turned
it into the biggest display of failing to obey his father that anybody has seen in the history of
catholicism and this was a person paralyzed by obsessive compulsive disorder so what we get here
at this point is the obvious question who invented knocking on wood for good luck who's the hindu who
had some sort of obsession with the number 24 or the jew with an obsession with the number 18
who got this belief that god was completely obsessed with the numbers of bones in the body and that's
how many things you should do well we have here is not only the recognition that if you are ocd
religion can provide a sanctuary if you are ocd in the right setting you can in fact make a living
by being religiously ritualistic but the recognition that probably people with strong obsessive compulsive
tendencies had something to do with the invention of many of these rituals i suspect historically
that's where it has come from so that brings up the issue that was brought up before why should
these rituals be so similar you look at the prohibitions for example in judaism more than 200
of these have to do with food preparation and cleansing you see the sequence in any of these
and the top four in ocd are identical to the top four in all of these religions cleansing of the body
food preparation entering and leaving significant religious places and numerology numbers why should
that be basically two types of explanations one is we may be seeing some sort of convergence
it's not by chance that people are highly ritualistically concerned with making sure their
bodies are clean and that their food is correctly prepared and i suspect that has part to do with
it but i suspect what we're also seeing and with records of people like martin luther what we're
also seeing is because some of the people who invented some of these religious rituals had a
background of ocd maybe not fully paralytic versions but nonetheless somebody spending five
hours a day washing his hands and five hours a day confessing about how he didn't wash his hands
enough this does not seem to be a mild version the more i wash the dirtier i get okay what i think
you wind up seeing is that historically all sorts of folks generating rituals ocd is estimated to
have an incidence anywhere from one to ten percent in the population depending on how you define it
the continuum and what you have is i suspect in periods of religious crisis cultural crisis
during a period of persecution during the period where whatever is currently in shape is not working
the right person at the right moment comes forward and in effect says this is how i have
been privately honoring our lord all these years and i am offering it to all of you to see
this is what i have been doing and in the right place and time it catches on and it turns into
the thing that is the ritual for the rest of the community within decades okay so what i've been
suggesting here and what i also emphasize is none of this is original with me except for the notion
that the ocd has something to do with the invention of these rituals these ideas go back decades go
back centuries that there is a parallelism between the symptoms of what we call schizotypillism
and the metamagical backbone of religious theology there is a parallelism between what we call
obsessive compulsive disorder and the ritualism of mainstream orthodox religion and this key point
that the exact same behaviors which in one context destroys your life has you peripheralized do it
right do it in the right context and it is not peripheralizing it makes you very honored and
powerful there are more themes yeah wonderful question would you expect to see different
incidences of ocd type traits in different cultures depending on how secular the society is how
ritualistic the religion is you look at for example catholicism or high episcopalianism
highly ritualistic compared to lutherans or unitarians or quakers at the other end would
you expect to see different different incidences absolutely i don't know if anybody's studying
that that would be exactly a prediction you would expect okay a related one which taps
into the lecture on friday would you expect to see differences in the incidence of depression
depending on religiosity and boring do you see that with a vengeance one of the healthiest things
you could do with your life is to be religious and to be highly religious it is a very strong
protector against major depression religious belief extends your life expectancy and that's
after you control for it changes risk factors you're less likely to drink to excess all of that
what is the big issue in that field is do the health benefits of religiosity merely come from
the social community that you get typically by being religious the question early in the
lecture today religiosity versus spirituality that might be a realm to dissociate them spirituality
if it's a very personal one you wouldn't get the community do you still get the health benefits
nobody knows at this point but those are studies that people are doing but absolutely one of the
greatest things you can do out there to buffer yourself from depression is to be religiously
believing and walk through all the steps at the end of the lecture the other day elements of control
predictability explanation outlet and you will see exactly how religion taps into that okay couple
more threads here in terms of making sense of some of the covariance between biological phenomenon
behavior that we can explain and patterns of religious belief back to something we talked
about earlier in the course take a hungry pigeon and put it in a cage and instead of the behaviorist
circumstance where it has to press a lever umpteen times to get food you randomly reward it and what
we discussed there was a pigeon has a strong psychic need to come up with an attribution
what did i do to cause this food to appear and what we went through was the fact that if a pigeon
is hungry enough and the reward is both big enough and random enough the pigeon has a prepared learning
state to make it think ah whatever i just did is what caused that to occur and then you suddenly
have superstitious conditioning the capacity to get pigeons doing the most outlandishly
ritualistic things over and over and over in the belief that that's the cause of the food appearing
and what we heard was take a room full of hungry pigeons and randomly reward all of them with food
at different points and come back a few days later and every pigeon is going to be having its own
private belief system built around in order to get food i have to do x the enforcement of superstitious
belief and that is the term that is used in psychology and as we often have here is a question
of is this word a metaphor is this word an inappropriate metaphor or what is superstitious
belief and to go back to the question that came up here before why do we have a societal need for
shamans why do we have a societal need for much of this because we are trying to explain the
unexplainable we are trying to look for causal links of things that may or may not be associated
this is basically a way of describing superstition how tight of a link do you need between cause and
effect to believe that there has been cause and effect and this is coming down to statistical
relations and if you allow yourself to believe that this prayer could be answered but it wasn't
this time because i wasn't concentrating enough i need to do it a bit more fervently all of that
you have a system that allows us very readily to see causal links that may not be there now what is
the next interesting neurobiological piece of this is that take animals take rats and damage their
hippocampus and what you get with hippocampal damage then is you have more trouble making causal
sequential links and events what you wind up seeing and this next sentence is meant to be
as provocative as it will sound is when you have rats with hippocampal damage they are more vulnerable
to superstitious conditioning essentially what that is saying is that as you have a damaged
hippocampus you have less of a capacity to tell the difference between accurate cause and effect
linkages and ones that are merely statistically hinting of that or ones that may not be in the
slightest that connected with each other hippocampal damage and rats have a lower threshold for
superstitious conditioning and we can very readily run with that one in terms of what the
implications of that might be going on our usual sequence from in order to appreciate a biological
effect big gross lesion sort of stuff to once again the much more subtle realm we all differ
in our number of hippocampal neurons in the amount of this enzyme in the amount of myelin and all
the biology we know all the individual differences a last disorder that winds up being interesting
there is a type of epilepsy which when you have it something happens to your religious belief system
and this is one of its characteristic features epileptic seizures as I think we've discussed
in here have characteristics as to what part of the brain they originate in and this is
epilepsy that originates in the temporal lobe the temporal lobe containing the hippocampus the
amygdala it's a big limbic area the temporal lobe temporal lobe epilepsy and about 30 years ago
a neurologist named Geshwin who was at Harvard he was probably the most influential neurologist of
the 20th century and Geshwin published a paper first describing what is now called temporal
lobe personality which is a cluster of personality traits that become far more common in people
with temporal lobe epilepsy once again not everybody with this personality profile has
epilepsy lurking there not everybody with temporal lobe epilepsy gets this profile but
statistically at a higher than expected rate what do you see with temporal lobe personality
first off the person becomes extremely serious and humorless okay you might say I would become
extremely serious and humorless if I suddenly came down with epilepsy what's the appropriate control
looking at other types of epilepsies of equivalent severity it's specific to temporal lobe so you
get the seriousness next thing you get is what is termed neophobia you don't like new things you
like to just do very familiar sorts of stuff the same small circle of friends the same very
relatively limited range of experiences okay if I had epilepsy I would suddenly get a lot more
sort of involuted in my lifestyle once again the controls or other types of epilepsies next thing
you see is this bizarre trait called hypergraphia which is people with temporal lobe personality
begin to write obsessively they feel a pressured need to write fourth trait and the most interesting
one of all is people with temporal lobe personality become obsessively interested
in religious and philosophical subjects and these are not people with uncontrolled seizures
happening all the time these are people whose seizures are relatively well controlled with
medication and once again well if I had this horrible neurological disease I'd suddenly
start getting more introspective but once again control for with the other types of epilepsy
and the classic temporal lobe patient that you see is somebody who is meeting a new neurologist
and says oh hi great to meet you you know I very strongly believe that a patient should be more
than just their symptoms so I've prepared this 60 page document here which is my philosophy about
life and meaning and at the next week's appointment comes back with a 40 page addendum this is what
you wind up seeing and there's this fabulous story told showing that it's not that you get religious
you get interested in religious and philosophical subjects this great story showing this and this
was apparently shortly after Geshwin first published this paper and he had some neurology
resident who one day all the residents were in there and the neurology resident was summarizing
some patient this was some 13 year old boy in there with temporal lobe epilepsy and he went through
the meds and all of that and how the kid was doing and at the end said oh by the way I just read your
paper on that personality stuff this kid doesn't fit at all doesn't fit in the slightest clearly doing
some chest thumping kind of territorial stuff with the big man there and Geshwin says oh yeah
really how come and he said because I asked him if he's religious he said no he's not Geshwin says
idiot out of my way he pushes him and goes stormy down the hall and the residents running after him
bursts into this kid's room and says oh hi I'm Dr. Geshwin and puts him through a neurological
exam and all of that and goes through and asked him does he like baseball has the weather all of
that and then offhandedly says well by the way are you religious and the boy says no I'm not and
then Geshwin asks the critical question he says oh how come and this 13 year old kid gives this
hour-long lecture about the internal inconsistencies of Christ's Sermon on the mountain the epic of
Gilgamesh and sort of Ancadi's treatment of this and Bertrand Russell's critique of Christ
and like Geshwin just leaves the residents in their torture to listen to this kid for an hour
and it's not becoming religious it's becoming fascinated with the subject and there's even
been a paper published in a neurology journal doing the sort of paleo forensic neurology
by neurologist speculating someone who in history had temporal lobe epilepsy and this was Saint Paul
Saint Paul who had seizure auras as documented no evidence that the guy was particularly humorous
the guy was hyper graphic as hell and clearly had a very strong interest in religious and
philosophical subjects and you know this is fun but what do you make of the fact that somebody
has an uncontrolled seizure in this part of the brain for 30 seconds once every six months
and they become more interested in religious subjects and at the end of the handout I cite
a novel that was published a couple years ago called lying awake fabulous novel by Mark Salisman
talking about a nun who is in the middle of a rather dispiriting life experience as a nun it
has not been what she was hoping for it has mostly been empty ritual and in the last few years
she's been having religious visions and this is the most exciting thing that has ever happened to her
what she also has to admit is she has kind of become a star of her convent after being this
very peripheral nobody and they're publishing books about her visions and people are coming to see her
and what becomes apparent halfway through the book is that she has a tumor in her temporal lobe which
is causing temporal lobe seizures and suddenly what does it mean that this is what these visions
have been about what does it mean that this is something that somebody in a white coat would call
a disease is this a disease and do I want my disease cured do I want this taken away from me
and it's extraordinary novel absolutely getting these features of temporal lobe personality and
getting at this issue which now is the core of what this whole lecture has been what do we do with
something like this what do we do with the possibility that have an uncontrolled burst of
action potentials in one part of your brain for 30 seconds every six months and in a somewhat
deterministic way that makes you more interested in religious subjects now summarizing here what I
think is really important for me to emphasize is what I'm not saying because that I've kind of
learned the hard way over the years I'm touching on the subject in this class what things I am not
saying I am not saying ooh some snotty you got to be crazy to be religious that's nonsense nor am I
saying even that most people who are are psychiatrically suspect I'm not saying that in the slightest
what I'm saying is it is absolutely fascinating that the same exact traits which in a secular context
are life destroying separate you from the community and in the right setting are at the very core of
what is protected what is sanctioned what is rewarded what is valued in religious settings so often
and that there could be an underlying biology to this and what do we do with this what's most
interesting here is even if this describes one single person I mean to put cards on the table
I was raised in an extremely religious orthodox upbringing and I had a complete break with it
when I was about 14 and that process of completely breaking to the point now where I have no religion
I have no spirituality I'm utterly atheist and in passing it is probably the thing I most regret in
my life but it's something I appear not to be able to change the process of getting to that point
I view in retrospect as one of the most defining things in my life the process of turning into
that person from who I was what are we to make of the possibility that each one of us goes through
some equivalent version in our life deciding how religious or irreligious we are going to be
for a lot of us that are among the most defining features of who we are where we have wound up
with this and how we got there what do we make of the fact that even if there's one case in all
of human history of someone who got to wherever they were instead because of a neurotransmitter
hiccup because of a genetic influence because of something that we would see as deterministic as
your visions are due to a tumor in your temporal lobe what are we to do with this what I am also
saying here is it is just as interesting to ask this question about why some of us lose faith
as to ask this about why some of us gain faith it is just as biological it is simply much less
studied because there are fewer examples of it to study out there but it is just as biological of
the process and it is just as interesting if it has only been one person in all of history
once again coming to this issue what are we to make of who we are if even in one case
somebody has arrived at that point because of just a storm of neurotransmitter abnormalities
rather than the journey that all of us associate with helping to define who we are now this now
is a segue to wednesday's lecture which is going to look at all of these issues in a much more
subtle realm of this biology of what makes our personalities personalities and this is finally
moving outside of the realm of them and their diseases for what makes us us and at the core of
this is what does it mean that biology may have as much to do with it as I will hopefully convince
you of on wednesday so let's pick up them