Hello everybody, this is Serge Rosbondrick and I am going to demonstrate a number of
features of jessesh 7.5.5.
The most powerful new feature is in fact an improvement of an existing feature.
This is an improvement of the search engine in jessesh.
When you use jessesh you can make a search in a folder in which you can define a folder
and you will search in jessesh files which are in this folder so I am going for example
to try a search in the jessesh folder itself.
Ok so I am searching in the jessesh folder and now you can search for instance this was
already possible for a sequence of glyphs say this and it will display all the text
which contains those glyphs.
But something more interesting is that sometimes you want to search for word and you don't
know the exact autography of the word.
So suppose you want text about the visor and so you know there will be the char sign and
normally a t after that but maybe that the t will be separated from the char sign by
another sign so what you can do is add a skip.
A skip represents a number of glyphs an arbitrary number of glyphs between two glyphs so if
I type this and another skip and this a1 then I am going to look at text which contains
the char sign then any number of glyphs then the t sign then any number of glyphs then
the a1 sign.
If I do that I will get way too many results because the signs can be separated by any
number of signs so you can very easily have the char sign at the beginning of a text and
then match later on a t.
So what you can do now and which didn't work very well before is that you can give us set
a value to max skip length which is going to say how many signs this star can represent.
Zero means in fact any number of signs.
If I choose for instance two which is very often a good value then both stars will represent
at most two signs and then I can start my search and you see that I find another number
of texts if I click on them it will open a window and I get a nice v0 here and with
a by the way z1 sign between the t and the a1 and if I click on this one I will get another
spelling from the teaching of tahertep without the z1.
So this is very nice, this is the new stuff in 7.5.5 I am going to say a word or two about
existing features you may not know.
Because you want to look for the particle poo and you know that it might be written
both ways the quail chick or this sign so what you want to do is to do one search for
both of them and of course you could do both search one after the other but you want to
do only one search and what you can use is those brackets.
When you put signs between brackets like this in the search the signs will it will search
for one of those signs so this will search for a p and then one of those two signs.
So if I start the search I've got quite a few answers and if I look at the values then
I've got a poo here and if I look at stillars for instance
if I look at stillars I will get probably something okay okay stillars at stillars if
I look at stillars I will get something with the quail chick here okay that's it there
is a something which might be a powerful system but which will need just as to evolve a lot
about sign description which is the use of viands you can search for viands signs so
if you do this normally you will probably search for both poo with the quail chick and
poo with the rope so for instance here is one example the problem is that it doesn't
always work very well for instance because as a notion of viands I use is very extensive
so for instance if you look at this sign the just sign if you ask for its viands you will
get those viands some of them are actual bona fide viands of the just signs and others are
simply because they look like such a sign they might not be real viands of it and if
you click multiple times on viands you will get viands of viands and for instance this
one is also an oak so you will get the oak sign and if you do this until there are no
more viands you will get for instance basically all get all birds and quite a few signs which
are very removed from the first sign so it's a notion of viands which is not precise enough
for our purpose so this basically is not very useful you can try it but the current results
won't be very good it's supposed to evolve but the data itself in the just sign list
is not currently up to what it should be for having meaningful and useful results there
other new functions of this system the new j sesh system there is a system to add new
lines in a very efficient way so basically you can edit line numbers in j sesh for instance
I'm going to add a line number here and say for instance it's x plus one okay obviously
it should be one but I use x plus one just to demonstrate the new system and once you
have done this and you want to insert a new a new number for a new line you can use insert
next line number and there is a shortcut for it and the advantage is that it will take
the last number in the previous slide you have typed and increase it so here for instance
I can add line numbers as much like my line numbers as I want obviously when you change
your page number for instance you have to type again the whole number but it makes it's
a very very nice system when you want to add line numbers for instance for all your lines
in the j sesh text a new function also which you will like is that at least it's it has
been missing from day one of j sesh so something like 14 years after I've finally taken the
time to add an improper enclosure drawing so I will probably add a related date around
enclosure but now there is square enclosure and I find it might be useful and it covers
the whole manual decodage now so this is it for the for j sesh itself there are a number
of new export functions so suppose you want to use the new unicode system for glyphs in
another software for instance you have a database and you want to use glyphs for j sesh glyphs
unicode glyphs there then you have a copy to unicode copy as simple unicode text and
you paste and there you have unicode glyphs okay you see this is not so j sesh glyphs
it's unicode text you have also normally but it's will probably be more problematic a copy
as unicode 12 which will add between the glyphs a number of formatting characters but it depends
on the font not all fonts will support those characters so ah the last the last new thing
is that you might know there is at last a code in unicode for the egyptological yard
so basically j sesh proposed two systems for the egyptological yard because there were
a number of systems in unicode for this but none of them were was fully usable and now
there is a specific code for egyptological yard so you can check it and if your text font uses
this code you can use it currently the most notable font with the unicode yard is atina
unicode um i hopefully a number of other system will include include this this sign okay that's
all for this demonstration of the new functions features of j sesh thank you for listening and goodbye