Here we have a trading bot that has a buy strategy and a sell strategy.
Each of these are functions, so they use the callable type.
And there are some examples of these functions right here below.
Don't use these for actual trading.
By the way, it's just an example.
And then in the main function, we create a trading bot and we pass a specific buy and sell strategy.
Now, instead of defining these types here in line, you can also use a type alias.
And that makes it a bit easier to understand.
So for example, here we could create a trading strategy function
and give that the type callable that we have right here.
And now instead of using the type directly, we can change this to use a trading strategy function instead.
And same here.
This makes it a bit easier to understand.
And if we ever decide we don't want to use integers anymore to represent prices,
you can change the type here and you don't have to change the types all over the place in your code.